<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Engineering Bio-based Composites for In-Service and Out-of-Service Performance</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>04/01/2009</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>03/31/2013</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>316249.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>335749</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CMMI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Civil, Mechanical, &amp; Manufact Inn</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Yick Hsuan</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Design methods for natural fiber-reinforced biopolymer composites will be developed to produce fully recyclable construction materials.  The polymers used in the composites are produced by bacteria and referred to as PHBs.  When placed in an anaerobic landfill after their useful service life, the composites will degrade to methane.  The methane may be captured and sold as a fuel or be used as a feedstock for bacteria to produce more PHB polymer for new composites.  The objective of this research is to engineer the PHB-natural fiber composites to be durable construction materials in-service yet also rapidly and thoroughly biodegrade anaerobically when no longer needed ("out-of-service").  Novel PHB-based fiber treatments will be developed and evaluated in terms of polymer, fiber and single-ply composite properties.  Results will be used to design and evaluate multi-ply composite performance for construction applications.  A feed-forward and feed-back communication process between the chemical, structural and environmental engineering researchers will be followed.  &lt;br/&gt;The societal benefits of this research include: (1) a construction material that is fully recyclable and producible globally;  (2) strong incentives for methane capture from landfills to provide a biofuel source and/or feedstock for biopolymers; and (3) improved safety for the built and natural environment by reducing ?fugitive? methane emissions from landfills, and reducing the transport of toxic substances worldwide and harm to marine species that is common with petroleum-based polymeric materials.  An exhibit on bio-based construction materials and hands-on activities for science classes will be developed in collaboration with a local children's museum.&lt;br/&gt;</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>03/31/2009</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/24/2010</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>0900325</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Curtis</FirstName>
<LastName>Frank</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>W</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Curtis W Frank</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>curt.frank@stanford.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6507234573</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000382891</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>03/31/2009</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Sarah</FirstName>
<LastName>Billington</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>L</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Sarah L Billington</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>billington@stanford.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6507234125</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000201091</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>03/31/2009</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Stanford University</Name>
<CityName>Stanford</CityName>
<ZipCode>943052004</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6507232300</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>450 Jane Stanford Way</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>18</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CA18</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>009214214</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>LELAND STANFORD JUNIOR UNIVERSITY, THE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>009214214</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Stanford University]]></Name>
<CityName>Stanford</CityName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>943052004</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[450 Jane Stanford Way]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>18</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CA18</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1635</Code>
<Text>STRUCTURAL MATERIALS AND MECH</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7643</Code>
<Text>EnvS-Environmtl Sustainability</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>025E</Code>
<Text>INFRASTRUCTURE MATERIALS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>036E</Code>
<Text>CIVIL INFRASTRUCTURE</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1037</Code>
<Text>DETERIORATION SCIENCE</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1057</Code>
<Text>CIS BASE RESEARCH</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>115E</Code>
<Text>RESEARCH EXP FOR TEACHERS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>116E</Code>
<Text>RESEARCH EXP FOR UNDERGRADS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7218</Code>
<Text>RET SUPP-Res Exp for Tchr Supp</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9102</Code>
<Text>WOMEN, MINORITY, DISABLED, NEC</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9146</Code>
<Text>MANUFACTURING BASE RESEARCH</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9178</Code>
<Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9231</Code>
<Text>SUPPL FOR UNDERGRAD RES ASSIST</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9251</Code>
<Text>REU SUPP-Res Exp for Ugrd Supp</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>CVIS</Code>
<Text>CIVIL INFRASTRUCTURE</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>MANU</Code>
<Text>MANUFACTURING</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0109</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0110</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2009~316249</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2010~19500</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Our research has resulted in new understanding as well as design and analysis methods to facilitate the adoption of a fully-recyclable, closed-loop life-cycle composite material for the construction industry.&nbsp; The composites are made from wood waste (e.g., sawdust) and a polymer that grows in bacteria, which are fed methane (i.e., a carbon sequestration method where the carbon turns into polymer).&nbsp; These bio-based composites may be used in construction and after serving their construction purpose can be taken out of service and biodegraded to methane. In turn, the methane can be captured and sold as a fuel or used to produce more biopolymer. The biopolymer is producible at any wastewater treatment plant or where there are agricultural or industrial fermentations.&nbsp; Thus, any location with wastewater treatment and a local plant fiber industry could be a potential location for manufacturing bio-based composites to be used locally for construction.&nbsp;</p> <p>These bio-based composites can replace petrochemical-based composites, such as for paneling and architectural elements as well as wood and engineered wood for formwork, scaffolding, paneling, flooring, tiles and temporary housing.&nbsp; The eventual population of landfills with more rapidly degrading materials such as the proposed biobased composites will provide strong incentive for methane capture, which in addition to providing both a fuel source and potential feedstock for polymeric materials, will also potentially reduce &ldquo;fugitive&rdquo; methane emissions, a potent greenhouse gas from landfills and digesters, thus improving the safety of our built and natural environments.&nbsp;</p> <p>For widespread application of these biobased composites, they must perform well when in service and also be able rapidly biodegrade in an anaerobic environment when they are no longer needed in service. The intellectual merit of this project was in the technical challenge of balancing the objectives of performing well for a certain amount of time and then biodegrading.&nbsp; Our challenges and outcomes were:</p> <p><strong>1.&nbsp; To engineer PHB-natural fiber composites for adequate in-service performance in potential construction applications through surface modifications.</strong>&nbsp;</p> <p>We developed two novel processing methods to optimize both mechanical performance and moisture resistance for bio-based composites using polymer and fiber surface modification techniques. We have developed and validated three performance prediction models including:&nbsp; (1) a micromechanical model based on cylindrical pressure vessel mechanics was developed to predict moisture-induced cracking in wood polymer compoistes, (2) a numerical model was developed to simulate in-situ performance of wood-plastic composites including transient environmental exposure conditions, and (3) a method of quantifying environmental impact that includes service life has been demonstrated.&nbsp;</p> <p><strong>2.&nbsp; To achieve the goals of 1. while also engineering the composite design </strong><strong>for optimal and rapid biogas production during anaerobic degradation. </strong></p> <p>Towards the goal of engineering composites for rapid biodegradation, we have identified preferential pathways of microorganisms in PHBV and PHBV-wood flour composite samples during anaerobic biodegradation.&nbsp; We have also identified structural changes to polymer morphology during anaerobic biodegradation through synchrotron radiation and small angle scattering, which impacts rates of anaerobic biodegradation.&nbsp; Finally, we have developed a method to link mass and volume loss results with biogas generation measurements from the composite samples where mass loss is measured by mass measurements and volume loss is measured via micro-CT imaging.&nbsp;</p> <p>From this research we have published seven peer-reviewed journal articles and five ...]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Our research has resulted in new understanding as well as design and analysis methods to facilitate the adoption of a fully-recyclable, closed-loop life-cycle composite material for the construction industry.  The composites are made from wood waste (e.g., sawdust) and a polymer that grows in bacteria, which are fed methane (i.e., a carbon sequestration method where the carbon turns into polymer).  These bio-based composites may be used in construction and after serving their construction purpose can be taken out of service and biodegraded to methane. In turn, the methane can be captured and sold as a fuel or used to produce more biopolymer. The biopolymer is producible at any wastewater treatment plant or where there are agricultural or industrial fermentations.  Thus, any location with wastewater treatment and a local plant fiber industry could be a potential location for manufacturing bio-based composites to be used locally for construction.   These bio-based composites can replace petrochemical-based composites, such as for paneling and architectural elements as well as wood and engineered wood for formwork, scaffolding, paneling, flooring, tiles and temporary housing.  The eventual population of landfills with more rapidly degrading materials such as the proposed biobased composites will provide strong incentive for methane capture, which in addition to providing both a fuel source and potential feedstock for polymeric materials, will also potentially reduce "fugitive" methane emissions, a potent greenhouse gas from landfills and digesters, thus improving the safety of our built and natural environments.   For widespread application of these biobased composites, they must perform well when in service and also be able rapidly biodegrade in an anaerobic environment when they are no longer needed in service. The intellectual merit of this project was in the technical challenge of balancing the objectives of performing well for a certain amount of time and then biodegrading.  Our challenges and outcomes were:  1.  To engineer PHB-natural fiber composites for adequate in-service performance in potential construction applications through surface modifications.   We developed two novel processing methods to optimize both mechanical performance and moisture resistance for bio-based composites using polymer and fiber surface modification techniques. We have developed and validated three performance prediction models including:  (1) a micromechanical model based on cylindrical pressure vessel mechanics was developed to predict moisture-induced cracking in wood polymer compoistes, (2) a numerical model was developed to simulate in-situ performance of wood-plastic composites including transient environmental exposure conditions, and (3) a method of quantifying environmental impact that includes service life has been demonstrated.   2.  To achieve the goals of 1. while also engineering the composite design for optimal and rapid biogas production during anaerobic degradation.   Towards the goal of engineering composites for rapid biodegradation, we have identified preferential pathways of microorganisms in PHBV and PHBV-wood flour composite samples during anaerobic biodegradation.  We have also identified structural changes to polymer morphology during anaerobic biodegradation through synchrotron radiation and small angle scattering, which impacts rates of anaerobic biodegradation.  Finally, we have developed a method to link mass and volume loss results with biogas generation measurements from the composite samples where mass loss is measured by mass measurements and volume loss is measured via micro-CT imaging.   From this research we have published seven peer-reviewed journal articles and five conference proceedings and we have given roughly 12 conference presentations on this work.   Four PhD students and one post-doctoral scholar have worked fully or in part on this project.  Three of the PhD students have graduated to date.  Fif...]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
