<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Collaborative Research - Marine Career Tech (MCTech): STEM Careers in Shipbuilding and Marine Industry</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>10/01/2009</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2013</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>818536.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>818536</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>11040100</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>EHR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DUE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Undergraduate Education</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>David B. Campbell</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This collaborative project between Old Dominion University, the University of Louisiana at Lafayette, the Mid-Atlantic Maritime Academy, Marshall Community and Technical College and South Louisiana Community College is modernizing marine technology education in three major shipbuilding and maritime areas of the country.  The project is developing instructional modules in lean six sigma, value stream engineering, green manufacturing and shipyard environmental footprint.    The instructional modules utilize active learning instructional methodologies that have been documented to improve student learning.  Fifteen community college faculty and sixty secondary school teachers are being trained in the use of these modules and subsequently integrating the modules into the curriculum at their respective institutions.  The project has strong participation and support from major shipbuilding entities, including the Virginia Ship Repair Association and the American Society of Naval Engineers, who are providing input on the content and quality of the instructional modules.    The project includes job placement activities for students interested in careers in shipbuilding.   An independent evaluator is implementing formative and summative evaluation plans throughout the life of the project.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/26/2009</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/21/2011</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.076</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>0903255</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Han</FirstName>
<LastName>Bao</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>P</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Han P Bao</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>hbao@odu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>7576834922</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000294224</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/26/2009</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Alok</FirstName>
<LastName>Verma</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>K</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Alok K Verma</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>averma@tamug.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>4097404805</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000240565</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/26/2009</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Sueanne</FirstName>
<LastName>McKinney</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Sueanne McKinney</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>smckinne@odu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>7576834293</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000159539</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/26/2009</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Daniel</FirstName>
<LastName>Dickerson</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>L</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Daniel L Dickerson</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>dickersond15@ecu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2523281741</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000251843</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/26/2009</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Old Dominion University Research Foundation</Name>
<CityName>Norfolk</CityName>
<ZipCode>235082561</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>7576834293</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>4111 Monarch Way</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[Suite 204]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Virginia</StateName>
<StateCode>VA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>VA03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>077945947</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>OLD DOMINION UNIVERSITY RESEARCH FOUNDATION</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Old Dominion University]]></Name>
<CityName>Norfolk</CityName>
<StateCode>VA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>235290001</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[5115 Hampton Blvd]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Virginia</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>VA02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7412</Code>
<Text>Advanced Tech Education Prog</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1032</Code>
<Text>ADVANCED TECHNOLOGY EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9178</Code>
<Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>SMET</Code>
<Text>SCIENCE, MATH, ENG &amp; TECH EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0409</Code>
<Name>NSF Education &amp; Human Resource</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040106</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0410</Code>
<Name>NSF Education &amp; Human Resource</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040106</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0411</Code>
<Name>NSF Education &amp; Human Resource</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040106</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2009~267431</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2010~273734</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2011~277371</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><strong>Outcomes Report</strong></p> <p>MCTech project involved professional development of community college faculty and&nbsp;secondary school teachers, curriculum and education material development, and career pathways development. The project improved and modernized technician education at the community&nbsp;college level by preparing faculty and students with industry relevant instructional modules and by attracting secondary school students to these educational pathways to provide a highly&nbsp;competent well-educated and advanced workforce for the maritime and marine industry. The&nbsp;project also increased career awareness of middle and high school students and teachers about&nbsp;the marine and maritime workforce with active learning kits and career day events.</p> <p><br />The project&rsquo;s primary goal, to increase relevance and modernize technician education in&nbsp;marine technology was achieved through collaborative development of instructional modules&nbsp;and associated activities on industry relevant topics for technician&nbsp;education in the classroom. The second goal, to equip secondary school teachers with resources&nbsp;and professional development to improve mathematics and science instructions through project&nbsp;based activities was achieved through the development&nbsp;of educational materials such as marine kits designed to target specific standards of learning in&nbsp;math, physical sciences and technology. Finally, to attract students towards marine engineering&nbsp;and technology careers, we organized three Career Day events in three major shipbuilding areas&nbsp;in the country. The events increased awareness about career paths and job opportunities among&nbsp;students, school teachers, counselors, and community college faculty.</p> <p><br />The technician education improvement component of the project included development&nbsp;of instructional modules for community college in (1) Lean Six-Sigma (2) Value Stream&nbsp;Engineering (3) Green Manufacturing (4) Shipyard Environmental Footprint. Focus Group&nbsp;Meetings were organized for community college faculty prior to the summer workshops to&nbsp;obtain input from the faculty during the development of these instructional modules. Three-day summer&nbsp;workshops for community college faculty were conducted to train them on Marine Kits and&nbsp;Instructional modules. Surveys were conducted to assess the quality of the presentation and&nbsp;content on each instructional module and Marine kit.</p> <p>During years 2 and 3, 2-day summer workshops for middle and high school teachers were held&nbsp;in Norfolk-Virginia, Lafayette-Louisiana and Huntington-West Virginia. &nbsp;Each participating&nbsp;teacher received a set of four Marine Kits for use in their classroom before the career day event. &nbsp;75% of high school teachers integrated these into at least one course, and&nbsp;47% into two courses. The implementations were not standardized and varied from site to site &nbsp;depending upon various factors. We believe there is a likelihood that McTech materials and&nbsp;elements will continue to be integrated into existing courses at each level. Surveys suggest that&nbsp;instructors find the materials compelling and in many cases usable resources to help support&nbsp;concepts that are integral to existing curriculum. MCTech has provided much needed innovative STEM learning models that are directly&nbsp;tied to regionally relevant economic and career improvement opportunities. Instructor response&nbsp;has underscored the possibility of sustained adoption, which may eventually lead toward&nbsp;increased interest and ultimate participation in the marine-based STEM fields.</p> <p>The MCTech Career Days occurred annually in each project region and included the following&nbsp;three main activities: (1) active learning labs or hands-on booths (2) Industry expo including&nbsp;professional organizat...]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Outcomes Report  MCTech project involved professional development of community college faculty and secondary school teachers, curriculum and education material development, and career pathways development. The project improved and modernized technician education at the community college level by preparing faculty and students with industry relevant instructional modules and by attracting secondary school students to these educational pathways to provide a highly competent well-educated and advanced workforce for the maritime and marine industry. The project also increased career awareness of middle and high school students and teachers about the marine and maritime workforce with active learning kits and career day events.   The projectÆs primary goal, to increase relevance and modernize technician education in marine technology was achieved through collaborative development of instructional modules and associated activities on industry relevant topics for technician education in the classroom. The second goal, to equip secondary school teachers with resources and professional development to improve mathematics and science instructions through project based activities was achieved through the development of educational materials such as marine kits designed to target specific standards of learning in math, physical sciences and technology. Finally, to attract students towards marine engineering and technology careers, we organized three Career Day events in three major shipbuilding areas in the country. The events increased awareness about career paths and job opportunities among students, school teachers, counselors, and community college faculty.   The technician education improvement component of the project included development of instructional modules for community college in (1) Lean Six-Sigma (2) Value Stream Engineering (3) Green Manufacturing (4) Shipyard Environmental Footprint. Focus Group Meetings were organized for community college faculty prior to the summer workshops to obtain input from the faculty during the development of these instructional modules. Three-day summer workshops for community college faculty were conducted to train them on Marine Kits and Instructional modules. Surveys were conducted to assess the quality of the presentation and content on each instructional module and Marine kit.  During years 2 and 3, 2-day summer workshops for middle and high school teachers were held in Norfolk-Virginia, Lafayette-Louisiana and Huntington-West Virginia.  Each participating teacher received a set of four Marine Kits for use in their classroom before the career day event.  75% of high school teachers integrated these into at least one course, and 47% into two courses. The implementations were not standardized and varied from site to site  depending upon various factors. We believe there is a likelihood that McTech materials and elements will continue to be integrated into existing courses at each level. Surveys suggest that instructors find the materials compelling and in many cases usable resources to help support concepts that are integral to existing curriculum. MCTech has provided much needed innovative STEM learning models that are directly tied to regionally relevant economic and career improvement opportunities. Instructor response has underscored the possibility of sustained adoption, which may eventually lead toward increased interest and ultimate participation in the marine-based STEM fields.  The MCTech Career Days occurred annually in each project region and included the following three main activities: (1) active learning labs or hands-on booths (2) Industry expo including professional organizations, government agencies educational institutions and private companies; and (3) Marine industry tours. Surveys suggest that a) students were impressed with the science and mathematics content and the inherent complexity enough to re-evaluate their own confidence in the subject areas b) specific content...]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
