<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>IGERT:  A Graduate Traineeship in Materials for a Sustainable Future</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2009</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2016</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>3200000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>3200000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>11010000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>EHR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DGE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Graduate Education</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Laura Regassa</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The development of the materials necessary for a sustainable future is an area of profound global and scientific importance. This Integrative Graduate Education and Research Traineeship program (IGERT) combines an interdisciplinary research experience with a formal education program designed to apply basic scientific knowledge to real problems in sustainable materials drawn from industrial interactions. Cornell faculty and student participants are united from 7 diverse departments of science and engineering and the Johnson School of Management and will have the opportunity to augment their research efforts with international collaborators. Intellectual merit includes the development of materials from renewable resources, including plant products, exploration of new, high performance materials for energy storage and conversion and the discovery of new methods for the synthesis and processing of materials with reduced environmental impact. Educational efforts feature a module-based course that will introduce students to the principles of sustainable design and the formidable energy challenges facing our society. Students will also gain familiarity with business thinking, industrial practices and business opportunities and challenges related to sustainability.  The broader impacts of this IGERT program include partnerships with two Historically Black Colleges/Universities and an undergraduate summer research program will address the issue of underrepresented groups in the materials field. The IGERT program will also develop a freely available web-based archive of the seminar series on Materials for a Sustainable Future.  IGERT is an NSF-wide program intended to meet the challenges of educating U.S. Ph.D. scientists and engineers with the interdisciplinary background, deep knowledge in a chosen discipline, and the technical, professional, and personal skills needed for the career demands of the future. The program is intended to catalyze a cultural change in graduate education by establishing innovative new models for graduate education and training in a fertile environment for collaborative research that transcends traditional disciplinary boundaries.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>09/01/2009</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>09/07/2012</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.076</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>0903653</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Paul</FirstName>
<LastName>McEuen</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>L</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Paul L McEuen</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>plm23@cornell.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6072555193</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000365626</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/01/2009</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>George</FirstName>
<LastName>Malliaras</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>G</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>George G Malliaras</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>ggm1@cornell.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6072551956</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000486232</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/01/2009</StartDate>
<EndDate>07/16/2010</EndDate>
<RoleCode>Former Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Yong</FirstName>
<LastName>Joo</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>L</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Yong L Joo</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>ylj2@cornell.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6072558591</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000489271</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/01/2009</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Paul</FirstName>
<LastName>Chirik</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>J</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Paul J Chirik</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>pchirik@princeton.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6072584130</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000211902</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/01/2009</StartDate>
<EndDate>03/24/2011</EndDate>
<RoleCode>Former Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Margaret</FirstName>
<LastName>Frey</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>W</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Margaret W Frey</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>mfw24@cornell.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6072555014</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000275270</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/01/2009</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Richard</FirstName>
<LastName>Hennig</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>G</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Richard G Hennig</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>rhennig@ufl.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>3523927327</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000397972</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/07/2012</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Richard</FirstName>
<LastName>Hennig</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>G</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Richard G Hennig</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>rhennig@ufl.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>3523927327</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000397972</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/16/2010</StartDate>
<EndDate>03/24/2011</EndDate>
<RoleCode>Former Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Cornell University</Name>
<CityName>Ithaca</CityName>
<ZipCode>148502820</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6072555014</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>373 Pine Tree Road</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>23</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NY23</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>872612445</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>CORNELL UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>002254837</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Cornell University]]></Name>
<CityName>Ithaca</CityName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<ZipCode>148502820</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[373 Pine Tree Road]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>23</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NY23</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<FoaInformation>
<Code>0000099</Code>
<Name>Other Applications NEC</Name>
</FoaInformation>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1335</Code>
<Text>IGERT FULL PROPOSALS</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>8064</Code>
<Text>IGERT Materials Research</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1335</Code>
<Text>IGERT FULL PROPOSALS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>5936</Code>
<Text>GERMANY (F.R.G.)</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>5942</Code>
<Text>KOREA</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>5948</Code>
<Text>NETHERLANDS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>5952</Code>
<Text>SPAIN</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>5979</Code>
<Text>Europe and Eurasia</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9179</Code>
<Text>GRADUATE INVOLVEMENT</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>SMET</Code>
<Text>SCIENCE, MATH, ENG &amp; TECH EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0109</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0110</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0111</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0112</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0409</Code>
<Name>NSF Education &amp; Human Resource</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040106</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0410</Code>
<Name>NSF Education &amp; Human Resource</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040106</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0411</Code>
<Name>NSF Education &amp; Human Resource</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040106</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0412</Code>
<Name>NSF Education &amp; Human Resource</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040106</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2009~600000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2010~650000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2011~650000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2012~1300000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><strong>Intellectual Merit:</strong> A diverse group of faculty from seven departments of science and engineering at Cornell University established an integrative graduate training program in an area of profound global importance &mdash; the development of materials necessary for a sustainable future. This graduate program directly trained 33 graduate students and impacted many more. The program directly addressed the recommendations of the National Research Council study on <em>Sustainability in the Chemical Industry</em> by combining an interdisciplinary research experience in sustainable materials with a formal educational program that allowed students to apply their basic scientific knowledge to real problems. The major research efforts included the development of high performance materials for energy conversion and storage, the development of materials from renewable resources, and the development of new methods and materials for reduced environmental impact synthesis and processing. The educational efforts were centered around a module-based course that introduced students to the principles of sustainable design and the formidable energy challenges facing our society, while also providing training in important career skills, such as public speaking and scientific ethics. This modular course included a number of key elements that have been shown to increase graduate student retention, such as increased student-faculty interaction and strong academic integration. Although developed for the IGERT Fellows, the course was inclusive; it educated a much larger number of graduate students and motivated them to become broadly educated in fields outside of their current specialty. A student-run and student-hosted seminar series raised awareness of both the technical challenges and the scientific opportunities that are engendered by sustainability, while also integrating Fellows into the professional scientific community through interactions with industrial and academic scientists of national renowned. The team-based research and educational environment emphasized communication skills through both formal and informal interactions. IGERT Fellows were also given the opportunity to present their research at national and international conferences.</p> <p><strong>Broader Impacts: </strong>This program focused on a topic of immense global importance &mdash; the development of new materials to enable a sustainable future. The research performed under this grant developed methods for the production of biodegradable consumer polymers, high performance electrocatalysts for next-generation fuel cells, and new processes that prevent waste and minimize environmental impact. More importantly, this program recruited and trained a total of 33 graduate Fellows in this area of profound national and international need. The program also addressed the issue of underrepresentation of women and minorities in the field of materials research and development. A substantial graduate student recruiting program led by a full-time staff member and with strong participation by faculty made annual visits to minority-serving institutions and hosted events at national meetings that attract significant minority and/or female participants. As a result, over 40% of the graduate Fellows supported by this program were members of groups traditionally underrepresented in science and engineering.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 10/20/2016<br>      Modified by: Richard&nbsp;G&nbsp;Hennig</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Intellectual Merit: A diverse group of faculty from seven departments of science and engineering at Cornell University established an integrative graduate training program in an area of profound global importance &mdash; the development of materials necessary for a sustainable future. This graduate program directly trained 33 graduate students and impacted many more. The program directly addressed the recommendations of the National Research Council study on Sustainability in the Chemical Industry by combining an interdisciplinary research experience in sustainable materials with a formal educational program that allowed students to apply their basic scientific knowledge to real problems. The major research efforts included the development of high performance materials for energy conversion and storage, the development of materials from renewable resources, and the development of new methods and materials for reduced environmental impact synthesis and processing. The educational efforts were centered around a module-based course that introduced students to the principles of sustainable design and the formidable energy challenges facing our society, while also providing training in important career skills, such as public speaking and scientific ethics. This modular course included a number of key elements that have been shown to increase graduate student retention, such as increased student-faculty interaction and strong academic integration. Although developed for the IGERT Fellows, the course was inclusive; it educated a much larger number of graduate students and motivated them to become broadly educated in fields outside of their current specialty. A student-run and student-hosted seminar series raised awareness of both the technical challenges and the scientific opportunities that are engendered by sustainability, while also integrating Fellows into the professional scientific community through interactions with industrial and academic scientists of national renowned. The team-based research and educational environment emphasized communication skills through both formal and informal interactions. IGERT Fellows were also given the opportunity to present their research at national and international conferences.  Broader Impacts: This program focused on a topic of immense global importance &mdash; the development of new materials to enable a sustainable future. The research performed under this grant developed methods for the production of biodegradable consumer polymers, high performance electrocatalysts for next-generation fuel cells, and new processes that prevent waste and minimize environmental impact. More importantly, this program recruited and trained a total of 33 graduate Fellows in this area of profound national and international need. The program also addressed the issue of underrepresentation of women and minorities in the field of materials research and development. A substantial graduate student recruiting program led by a full-time staff member and with strong participation by faculty made annual visits to minority-serving institutions and hosted events at national meetings that attract significant minority and/or female participants. As a result, over 40% of the graduate Fellows supported by this program were members of groups traditionally underrepresented in science and engineering.       Last Modified: 10/20/2016       Submitted by: Richard G Hennig]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
