<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Collaborative Research: Electronic Processes in Disordered and Biomolecular Systems</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/15/2009</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2012</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>225000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>225000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03070005</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DMR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Materials Research</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Daryl Hess</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>dhess@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924942</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>TECHNICAL SUMMARY&lt;br/&gt;This award supports theoretical and computational research and education to model the interaction of light with particular materials. The research will focus on understanding electronic properties and charge-transfer mechanisms in disordered systems which has impact on efforts to develop improved photovoltaic and photocatalytic materials, and better light-sensing devices. Scientific goals are to determine: 1) The structure of ordered and disordered photoactive oxides including vanadium and titanium based oxides, 2) The atomistic origin of light induced effects in these oxide systems as well as in glasses, for example the Staebler-Wronski effect in hydrogenated amorphous silicon and analogous phenomena in chalcogenide glasses, 3) Fundamental understanding of charge and energy transfer processes in acceptor-donor biomolecules with a focus on chlorophyll-carotene systems for potential bio-inspired photovoltaics, 4) Fundamental understanding of charge transfer processes in photoactive metal organic framework materials. Practical new codes will be developed for non-adiabatic molecular-dynamics simulation. The research will be carried out in collaboration with experimental groups with an aim to guide experimental research. Collaborations with other theoretical groups will enable powerful computational techniques to be developed.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The PIs will leverage several student research programs already in place in the State of West Virginia; these programs extend to Drabold through Lewis and thus will impact Ohio University students as well. The PIs will recruit students from these programs and are committed to a mission of broadening participation in their computational materials research. Developing a strong program in nanoscale science and engineering, including developing cyberinfrastructure capabilities, is also a priority for the State of West Virginia. The PIs will further extend and develop a strong program of science outreach to K-12 students and teachers in Appalachia. The PI?s will start a pilot annual joint scientific conference entirely for, and to the maximum degree possible, administered by regional students. The efficacy of this work will be quantitatively gauged and reported. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;NONTECHNICAL SUMMARY&lt;br/&gt;This award supports theoretical and computational research and education to use advanced computational methods to study how light interacts with several classes of technologically important materials, focusing on the motion of electronic charge induced by exposure to light. Technological applications of these materials include generation of energy from sunlight and catalyzing chemical reactions like the transformation of carbon dioxide into methanol induced by light. The research will focus on understanding key quantum mechanical states of electrons that are important when the material is exposed to light and how electronic charge moves from one group of atoms to another.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This is fundamental research that contributes to the intellectual foundations of solar energy generation and photochemistry. The research will be carried out in collaboration with experimental groups with an aim to guide experimental research. Collaborations with other theoretical groups will enable powerful computational techniques to be developed.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The PIs will leverage several student research programs already in place in the State of West Virginia; these programs extend to Drabold through Lewis and thus will impact Ohio University students as well. The PIs will recruit students from these programs and are committed to a mission of broadening participation in their computational materials research. Developing a strong program in nanoscale science and engineering, including developing cyberinfrastructure capabilities, is also a priority for the State of West Virginia. The PIs will further extend and develop a strong program of science outreach to K-12 students and teachers in Appalachia. The PI?s will start a pilot annual joint scientific conference entirely for, and to the maximum degree possible, administered by regional students. The efficacy of this work will be quantitatively gauged and reported.&lt;br/&gt;</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>09/15/2009</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/23/2011</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>0903225</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>James</FirstName>
<LastName>Lewis</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>P</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>James P Lewis</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>JPLewis@mail.wvu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>3042935141</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000485601</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/15/2009</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Jennifer</FirstName>
<LastName>Jackson</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Jennifer Jackson</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>kasi.jackson@mail.wvu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>3042932339</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000066401</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/15/2009</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>West Virginia University Research Corporation</Name>
<CityName>Morgantown</CityName>
<ZipCode>265066845</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>3042933998</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>P.O. Box 6845</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>West Virginia</StateName>
<StateCode>WV</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>WV01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>191510239</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>WEST VIRGINIA UNIVERSITY RESEARCH CORPORATION</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[West Virginia University]]></Name>
<CityName>Morgantown</CityName>
<StateCode>WV</StateCode>
<ZipCode>26506</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>West Virginia</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>WV01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<FoaInformation>
<Code>0106000</Code>
<Name>Materials Research</Name>
</FoaInformation>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1765</Code>
<Text>CONDENSED MATTER &amp; MAT THEORY</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7237</Code>
<Text>NANO NON-SOLIC SCI &amp; ENG AWD</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7569</Code>
<Text>CYBERINFRASTRUCTURE/SCIENCE</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7573</Code>
<Text>BIO-RELATED MATERIALS RESEARCH</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7644</Code>
<Text>ENERGY FOR SUSTAINABILITY</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9161</Code>
<Text>SINGLE DIVISION/UNIVERSITY</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>AMPP</Code>
<Text>ADVANCED MATERIALS &amp; PROCESSING PROGRAM</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0109</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0110</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0111</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2009~75000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2010~75000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2011~75000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>In this award, we explored new materials using novel computational techniques. Among other discoveries, we showed in the first theoretical study of amorphous TiO<sub>2</sub> that the material had an optical gap similar to that of rutile and suggest that it may find application as electronic/optical material. We also investigated doping with nitrogen and noted using a high-throughput method that the nitrogen atoms tend to segregate. In other high-throughput investigation, we also discovered new photovoltaic properties in CuGa<sub>1-x</sub>Fe<sub>x</sub>O<sub>2</sub>. We developed new methods to compute the electrical conductivity of materials, including low temperature effects. This required the development of an entirely new formulation of transport theory, with utilities well beyond standard methods. We also explored the basic physics of the important photovoltaic and thin film transistor material hydrogenated amorphous silicon, and elucidated the means by which light is absorbed. We also explained a long standing puzzle on why the electrical activity of the material is minimal without the addition of large concentrations of dopant impurities. The phase change memory material Ge<sub>2</sub>Sb<sub>2</sub>Te<sub>5</sub> was modeled and the nature of the electronic states was revealed in the liquid phase. We undertook the first calculations on amorphous graphene, and showed that the material to form a rippled or &ldquo;bubble wrap&rdquo; structure. The material has been observed experimentally, and its crystalline counterpart is probably the most studied single material in condensed matter science today. This is helpful in understanding the operation of phase change memory devices, which are starting to be used in cell phone applications.</p> <p>One student received a Ph.D. under this award, and another candidate (M. Underwood) is a very promising female scientist working with Lewis and collaborating with Drabold and his group on TiO<sub>2.</sub> Her exceptional performance was recognized with a prestigious NSF Graduate Research Fellowship scholarship. Drabold and Lewis were key organizers of an international meeting on &ldquo;Large Scale Simulations in Materials Science and Biophysics&rdquo;, held in Tempe, AZ in 2011. The meeting involved about 50 participants from all over the world. A Proceedings volume was edited and published in the German journal Physica Status Solidi B. Both PIs were active in outreach, including a large and popular Open House at Ohio University (which brought in over 800 members from the community, at least half children) and a Summer Institutes for teaching high-performance computing to faculty and students at primarily undergraduate institutions.</p> <p>Both Lewis and Drabold gave their students significant opportunities for international collaboration (Drabold&rsquo;s student Cai visited Cambridge for 6 weeks in a very profitable stay, and Lewis is deeply involved in research in China and his entire group collaborates with researchers there).</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 12/17/2012<br>      Modified by: James&nbsp;P&nbsp;Lewis</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ In this award, we explored new materials using novel computational techniques. Among other discoveries, we showed in the first theoretical study of amorphous TiO2 that the material had an optical gap similar to that of rutile and suggest that it may find application as electronic/optical material. We also investigated doping with nitrogen and noted using a high-throughput method that the nitrogen atoms tend to segregate. In other high-throughput investigation, we also discovered new photovoltaic properties in CuGa1-xFexO2. We developed new methods to compute the electrical conductivity of materials, including low temperature effects. This required the development of an entirely new formulation of transport theory, with utilities well beyond standard methods. We also explored the basic physics of the important photovoltaic and thin film transistor material hydrogenated amorphous silicon, and elucidated the means by which light is absorbed. We also explained a long standing puzzle on why the electrical activity of the material is minimal without the addition of large concentrations of dopant impurities. The phase change memory material Ge2Sb2Te5 was modeled and the nature of the electronic states was revealed in the liquid phase. We undertook the first calculations on amorphous graphene, and showed that the material to form a rippled or "bubble wrap" structure. The material has been observed experimentally, and its crystalline counterpart is probably the most studied single material in condensed matter science today. This is helpful in understanding the operation of phase change memory devices, which are starting to be used in cell phone applications.  One student received a Ph.D. under this award, and another candidate (M. Underwood) is a very promising female scientist working with Lewis and collaborating with Drabold and his group on TiO2. Her exceptional performance was recognized with a prestigious NSF Graduate Research Fellowship scholarship. Drabold and Lewis were key organizers of an international meeting on "Large Scale Simulations in Materials Science and Biophysics", held in Tempe, AZ in 2011. The meeting involved about 50 participants from all over the world. A Proceedings volume was edited and published in the German journal Physica Status Solidi B. Both PIs were active in outreach, including a large and popular Open House at Ohio University (which brought in over 800 members from the community, at least half children) and a Summer Institutes for teaching high-performance computing to faculty and students at primarily undergraduate institutions.  Both Lewis and Drabold gave their students significant opportunities for international collaboration (DraboldÆs student Cai visited Cambridge for 6 weeks in a very profitable stay, and Lewis is deeply involved in research in China and his entire group collaborates with researchers there).       Last Modified: 12/17/2012       Submitted by: James P Lewis]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
