<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>AF: Medium: Center for Quantum Algorithms and Complexity</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/15/2009</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2015</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>1127080.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>1352496</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>05010000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>CSE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CCF</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division of Computing and Communication Foundations</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Tracy Kimbrel</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>tkimbrel@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927924</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Quantum computation has forced a dramatic change in our beliefs about the foundations of computer science, the security of cryptosystems, and the nature of quantum systems. This award focuses on several fundamental algorithmic questions that arise out of this viewpoint. The first is the design of new quantum algorithms. The challenge here is that the major paradigm for the design of quantum algorithms - the hidden subgroup framework - has recently been shown to have severe limitations in its applicability. The center will explore several approaches, including a new framework for the design of quantum algorithms via the quantum approximation of tensor networks, as well as recent work on the use of quantum algorithms for discovering hidden nonlinear structures.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Establishing the limits of quantum algorithms is equally important to the possibility of designing efficient classical cryptosystems that are immune to quantum cryptanalysis. Such "post-quantum" cryptosystems could have an enormous practical impact well before the first working quantum computer is ever built. For this to happen it is necessary to better understand the quantum hardness of concrete classical cryptosystems such as the lattice-based cryptosystems or the McEliese cryptosystem. A different approach would involve designing novel cryptosystems whose security is based on already established quantum hardness results in the hidden subgroup framework.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The center would also study fundamental questions in quantum complexity theory, including the complexity of quantum interactive proof systems. Arguably the most important challenge is proving the quantum analog of the celebrated PCP theorem. This would have wide implications including quantum hardness of inapproximability results, improved fault-tolerance results for adiabatic quantum computing, as well as implications for theoretical condensed matter physics. Another fundamental question is the power of multi-prover quantum interactive proof systems. Resolving whether or not this complexity class is NEXP as in the celebrated classical result MIP = NEXP, is expected to provide important insights into the nature of quantum entanglement.&lt;br/&gt;</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/13/2009</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>09/04/2013</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.070</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>0905626</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Umesh</FirstName>
<LastName>Vazirani</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>V</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Umesh V Vazirani</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>vazirani@cs.berkeley.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5106420572</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000453519</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/13/2009</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of California-Berkeley</Name>
<CityName>BERKELEY</CityName>
<ZipCode>947101749</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5106433891</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>Sponsored Projects Office</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[1608 Fourth Street, Suite 220]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>13</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CA13</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>124726725</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>REGENTS OF THE UNIVERSITY OF CALIFORNIA, THE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>071549000</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of California-Berkeley]]></Name>
<CityName>BERKELEY</CityName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>947101749</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[Sponsored Projects Office]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>13</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CA13</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<FoaInformation>
<Code>0000912</Code>
<Name>Computer Science</Name>
</FoaInformation>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7926</Code>
<Text>ALGORITHMS</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7928</Code>
<Text>Quantum Computing</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7928</Code>
<Text>QUANTUM COMPUTING</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9218</Code>
<Text>BASIC RESEARCH &amp; HUMAN RESORCS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>HPCC</Code>
<Text>HIGH PERFORMANCE COMPUTING &amp; COMM</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0109</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0113</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2009~1127080</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2013~225416</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>In an emerging world of quantum devices, it is becoming increasingly important to test that such devices behave according to specification. However, the testing of quantum devices&nbsp;poses unique new challenges: first, the description of the quantum state of a system scales exponentially in the size of the system, while the law of quantum mechanics severely limit access to this information. Moreover there is an exponential mismatch in the computational power of quantum systems and their classical testers.&nbsp;</p> <p>In a sequence of papers, we demonstrate that other unique features of quantum systems (namely, entanglement) can be exploited to test quantum systems. Our most general and counter-intuitive result shows how a classical experimentalist can issue a sequence of challenges to a pair of completely untrusted quantum devices. If the devices successfully answer the challenges, then they must necessarily work according to specifications, carrying out the quantum computation that they were supposed to.&nbsp;</p> <p>At a more concrete level, the problem of quantum device testing lies at the heart of the two decade old challenge of device independent quantum key distribution (DIQKD). One of the unexpected discoveries&nbsp;with the implementation of practical quantum cryptography (QKD) systems was that&nbsp;they could be successfully attacked despite proofs of unconditional security --- they allowed for new kinds of attacks, for instance where classical information gets leaked via quantum side channels. The DIQD challenge seeks a&nbsp;principled way of ruling out all such vulnerabilities&nbsp;by asking for a protocol that is provably correct even if the devices are untrusted.&nbsp;</p> <p>We resolved the challenge of DIQKD by giving a simple protocol has all the desirable feature of DIQKD: it can be used to generate a shared random key at a rate while tolerating constant noise rate in the devices, and we established its security in the most general setting, against a general quantum eavesdropper.&nbsp;Our proof of security is based on a rare success in establishing a quantitative bound on correlations due to monogamy in multiparty entanglement, a phenomenon that limits two highly entangled quantum systems from sharing much entanglement with any other system. Monogamy of entanglement is a pervasive phenomenon, believed to play a central role in contexts ranging from the area law for quantum many body systems in condensed matter physics to the information paradox for black holes in cosmology. But monogamy is also notoriously hard to quantify. Our quantitative bound on correlations due to monogamy required leveraging techniques originating in many different areas including the theory of pseudo-randomness in computer science.&nbsp;</p> <p>A major theme of this research is the computational lens, which places computational considerations at&nbsp;the center of some of the most fundamental scientific questions.&nbsp;A central challenge in the study of quantum many body systems, such as those involved in high-temperature superconductivity or the fractional quantum Hall effect, is their exponential complexity. The state of a system on n particles is given by a vector in a Hilbert space of exponential dimension, so even giving a succinct classical description (whose size scales as some polynomial in n) of the state is a formidable challenge. Quantum many body systems with nearest neighbor interactions on a line are an excellent test case, since they already exhibit many important phenomena. We gave the first polynomial time algorithm that provably solves such systems (finds the ground state). The algorithm built upon a key innovation from our earlier paper in the form of a class of operators called approximate ground state projection (AGSP). In the algorithm, a suitable AGSP plays the crucial role of keeping the algorithm from getting lost or stuck in a local optimum in t...]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ In an emerging world of quantum devices, it is becoming increasingly important to test that such devices behave according to specification. However, the testing of quantum devices poses unique new challenges: first, the description of the quantum state of a system scales exponentially in the size of the system, while the law of quantum mechanics severely limit access to this information. Moreover there is an exponential mismatch in the computational power of quantum systems and their classical testers.   In a sequence of papers, we demonstrate that other unique features of quantum systems (namely, entanglement) can be exploited to test quantum systems. Our most general and counter-intuitive result shows how a classical experimentalist can issue a sequence of challenges to a pair of completely untrusted quantum devices. If the devices successfully answer the challenges, then they must necessarily work according to specifications, carrying out the quantum computation that they were supposed to.   At a more concrete level, the problem of quantum device testing lies at the heart of the two decade old challenge of device independent quantum key distribution (DIQKD). One of the unexpected discoveries with the implementation of practical quantum cryptography (QKD) systems was that they could be successfully attacked despite proofs of unconditional security --- they allowed for new kinds of attacks, for instance where classical information gets leaked via quantum side channels. The DIQD challenge seeks a principled way of ruling out all such vulnerabilities by asking for a protocol that is provably correct even if the devices are untrusted.   We resolved the challenge of DIQKD by giving a simple protocol has all the desirable feature of DIQKD: it can be used to generate a shared random key at a rate while tolerating constant noise rate in the devices, and we established its security in the most general setting, against a general quantum eavesdropper. Our proof of security is based on a rare success in establishing a quantitative bound on correlations due to monogamy in multiparty entanglement, a phenomenon that limits two highly entangled quantum systems from sharing much entanglement with any other system. Monogamy of entanglement is a pervasive phenomenon, believed to play a central role in contexts ranging from the area law for quantum many body systems in condensed matter physics to the information paradox for black holes in cosmology. But monogamy is also notoriously hard to quantify. Our quantitative bound on correlations due to monogamy required leveraging techniques originating in many different areas including the theory of pseudo-randomness in computer science.   A major theme of this research is the computational lens, which places computational considerations at the center of some of the most fundamental scientific questions. A central challenge in the study of quantum many body systems, such as those involved in high-temperature superconductivity or the fractional quantum Hall effect, is their exponential complexity. The state of a system on n particles is given by a vector in a Hilbert space of exponential dimension, so even giving a succinct classical description (whose size scales as some polynomial in n) of the state is a formidable challenge. Quantum many body systems with nearest neighbor interactions on a line are an excellent test case, since they already exhibit many important phenomena. We gave the first polynomial time algorithm that provably solves such systems (finds the ground state). The algorithm built upon a key innovation from our earlier paper in the form of a class of operators called approximate ground state projection (AGSP). In the algorithm, a suitable AGSP plays the crucial role of keeping the algorithm from getting lost or stuck in a local optimum in the exponentially large Hilbert space, the overwhelming fraction of which consists of quantum states which do not even have a sub-exponential sized...]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
