<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Interactive Microscopy of Graphene Nanostructures</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2009</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2012</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>450000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>457000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03070003</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DMR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Materials Research</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Guebre Tessema</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>gtessema@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924935</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>******TECHNICAL ABSTRACT*******&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Graphene is a remarkable newly isolated two-dimensional material that has novel physical properties and great potential for new nanotechnological advances.  The central goals of this research project are to understand and control atomic-scale behavior in graphene nanostructures via newly developed techniques of "interactive microscopy". These methods allow graphene nanostructures to be not only probed at the atomic scale, but also to be manipulated.  The strategy for this project revolves around the complementary use of scanning tunneling microscopy and transmission electron microscopy to characterize and manipulate graphene in a collaborative effort between the groups of M.F. Crommie and A. Zettl.  Both microscopy techniques will be used in a coordinated, collaborative approach to explore the fundamental electronic and structural properties of graphene nanostructures such as edges, defects, nanoribbons, and nanoplatelets, and to correlate these properties with graphene nanodevice behavior.  This project will provide scientific training to graduate students, undergraduates, and high school students in a strongly interdisciplinary area.  &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;*******NON-TECHNICAL ABSTRACT********&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Graphene is a remarkable new material that consists of a single sheet of carbon atoms chemically bonded in a periodic honeycomb pattern.  This material has great promise for creating new electronic, magnetic, and mechanical devices that can be miniaturized beyond the level of current technology, with great potential advantages.  To realize these advantages, however, the properties of graphene must be understood and controlled down to the atomic-scale (i.e., down to the size of single atoms).  The central goal of this research project is to perform this task via newly developed interactive microscopy techniques.  These techniques allow graphene to not only be imaged at atomic length scales, but also to be manipulated and changed at this same small length scale. Different state-of-the-art microscopy techniques with atomic-scale spatial resolution will be used in a coordinated, collaborative approach to explore the fundamental electrical and structural properties of graphene devices having different shapes and disorder properties at very small length scales.  Critically important shapes include, for example, ribbons of graphene that have a width in the range of 10 nanometers.  This project will provide interdisciplinary scientific training to graduate students, undergraduates, and high school students in the most powerful modern methods of microscopy and device characterization.  &lt;br/&gt;</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/22/2009</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/16/2011</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>0906539</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Alex</FirstName>
<LastName>Zettl</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Alex Zettl</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>azettl@physics.berkekey.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5106424939</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000449330</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/22/2009</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Michael</FirstName>
<LastName>Crommie</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>F</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Michael F Crommie</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>crommie@berkeley.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5106429392</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000449302</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/22/2009</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of California-Berkeley</Name>
<CityName>BERKELEY</CityName>
<ZipCode>947101749</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5106433891</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>Sponsored Projects Office</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[1608 Fourth Street, Suite 220]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>13</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CA13</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>124726725</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>REGENTS OF THE UNIVERSITY OF CALIFORNIA, THE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>071549000</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of California-Berkeley]]></Name>
<CityName>BERKELEY</CityName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>947101749</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[Sponsored Projects Office]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>13</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CA13</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<FoaInformation>
<Code>0106000</Code>
<Name>Materials Research</Name>
</FoaInformation>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1710</Code>
<Text>CONDENSED MATTER PHYSICS</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7237</Code>
<Text>NANO NON-SOLIC SCI &amp; ENG AWD</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9161</Code>
<Text>SINGLE DIVISION/UNIVERSITY</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9178</Code>
<Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9251</Code>
<Text>REU SUPP-Res Exp for Ugrd Supp</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>AMPP</Code>
<Text>ADVANCED MATERIALS &amp; PROCESSING PROGRAM</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>SMET</Code>
<Text>SCIENCE, MATH, ENG &amp; TECH EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0109</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0110</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0111</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2009~150000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2010~157000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2011~150000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><strong>Project Outcomes Report for Interactive Microscopy of Graphene Nanostructures</strong></p> <p>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; This grant enabled investigation into the microscopic properties of graphene nanostructures by exploiting "interactive microscopy", i.e. combined atomic-scale imaging and manipulation via scanning tunneling microscopy (STM) and transmission electron microscopy (TEM) techniques. STM-based methods were highly effective in performing energy-resolved local electronic spectroscopy, while TEM-based methods facilitated exploration of atomic and micro-scale static and dynamical properties.&nbsp; Graphene-based heterostructures for were collaboratively synthesized and explored and many collaborative publications resulted.&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; The <strong>intellectual merit</strong> of these activities lies in the fact that graphene nanostructures were explored in new physical regimes. &nbsp;Precision-fabricated graphene structures were probed in a manner that allowed atomically-resolved electronic and conductance properties to be measured and correlated with atomically-resolved geometrical structure.&nbsp; These measurements allowed new tests of theoretical predictions for novel graphene behavior, as well as the discovery of new material phenomena.</p> <p>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; The <strong>broader impact</strong> of this work lies in our education and outreach<br />activities, as well as the impact that the work has had (and continues to have)<br />on the scientific and engineering communities.&nbsp; This research allowed the development of new graphene material combinations that allowed new explorations into graphene nanoelectronic behavior that were previously not possible, and which should have future impact on technological applications in areas such as computation, communications, spintronics, chemical detection, composite materials, and medicine.&nbsp; This project further provided significant scientific training to graduate students, undergraduates, and high school students in strongly interdisciplinary areas.&nbsp; Outreach and educational efforts by the PI's included the creation of new educational materials on nanoscience and technology; participation in open-house days, nanoscience poster sessions, the Berkeley Nanotechnology Club, nanotechnology workshops, lab tours and lectures; as well as mentorship for under-represented groups, including high school students from the UC Berkeley<br />Summer High School Apprenticeship Research Program (SHARP).</p> <p>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; Specific research accomplishments include <strong>new progress in <em>graphene synthesis</em></strong>:&nbsp; We demonstrated a new process for batch production of large-area patterned freestanding graphene membranes on Cu scaffolds using chemical vapor deposition (CVD) grown graphene.&nbsp; <strong>New progress in<em> graphene transfer</em></strong>:&nbsp; we developed a facile method for direct polymer-free transfer of large-area graphene from metal growth substrates to selected target substrates.&nbsp; <strong>New progress in<em> high resolution TEM characterization of graphene atomic structure</em>:&nbsp; </strong>We invented a method for direct mapping of the grains and grain boundaries (GBs) of large-area monolayer polycrystalline graphene sheets, at large (several micrometer) and single-atom length scales. &nbsp;<strong>New progress in<em> characterization of electronic structure of single atoms on gated graphene</em>:</strong>&nbsp; Using STM-based techniques we performed the first spectroscopic study of individual adatoms placed on a gated graphene surface.&nbsp; <strong>New progress in<em> nanoscale characterization of BN substrates for graphene:</em></strong>&nbsp; We developed a new technique to create CVD grown graphene heteros...]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Project Outcomes Report for Interactive Microscopy of Graphene Nanostructures          This grant enabled investigation into the microscopic properties of graphene nanostructures by exploiting "interactive microscopy", i.e. combined atomic-scale imaging and manipulation via scanning tunneling microscopy (STM) and transmission electron microscopy (TEM) techniques. STM-based methods were highly effective in performing energy-resolved local electronic spectroscopy, while TEM-based methods facilitated exploration of atomic and micro-scale static and dynamical properties.  Graphene-based heterostructures for were collaboratively synthesized and explored and many collaborative publications resulted.              The intellectual merit of these activities lies in the fact that graphene nanostructures were explored in new physical regimes.  Precision-fabricated graphene structures were probed in a manner that allowed atomically-resolved electronic and conductance properties to be measured and correlated with atomically-resolved geometrical structure.  These measurements allowed new tests of theoretical predictions for novel graphene behavior, as well as the discovery of new material phenomena.             The broader impact of this work lies in our education and outreach activities, as well as the impact that the work has had (and continues to have) on the scientific and engineering communities.  This research allowed the development of new graphene material combinations that allowed new explorations into graphene nanoelectronic behavior that were previously not possible, and which should have future impact on technological applications in areas such as computation, communications, spintronics, chemical detection, composite materials, and medicine.  This project further provided significant scientific training to graduate students, undergraduates, and high school students in strongly interdisciplinary areas.  Outreach and educational efforts by the PI's included the creation of new educational materials on nanoscience and technology; participation in open-house days, nanoscience poster sessions, the Berkeley Nanotechnology Club, nanotechnology workshops, lab tours and lectures; as well as mentorship for under-represented groups, including high school students from the UC Berkeley Summer High School Apprenticeship Research Program (SHARP).          Specific research accomplishments include new progress in graphene synthesis:  We demonstrated a new process for batch production of large-area patterned freestanding graphene membranes on Cu scaffolds using chemical vapor deposition (CVD) grown graphene.  New progress in graphene transfer:  we developed a facile method for direct polymer-free transfer of large-area graphene from metal growth substrates to selected target substrates.  New progress in high resolution TEM characterization of graphene atomic structure:  We invented a method for direct mapping of the grains and grain boundaries (GBs) of large-area monolayer polycrystalline graphene sheets, at large (several micrometer) and single-atom length scales.  New progress in characterization of electronic structure of single atoms on gated graphene:  Using STM-based techniques we performed the first spectroscopic study of individual adatoms placed on a gated graphene surface.  New progress in nanoscale characterization of BN substrates for graphene:  We developed a new technique to create CVD grown graphene heterostructures that are supported by a clean BN substrate, and we investigated the nm-scale topography and charge homogeneity of these structures using STM spectroscopy.  New progress in measurement of Dirac fermion screening around tunable charge impurities:  We directly measured long-range screening around tunable point charges in gated graphene.  This allowed us to spatially map out, for the first time, how massless Dirac fermions respond to a Coulomb potential.  New progress in characterization of folded graphene:  By folding g...]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
