<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Collaborative Research:  NanoDomain Structure and Multifunctional Properties of Polymer Derived Ceramics</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/15/2009</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2016</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>530000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>532598</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03070009</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DMR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Materials Research</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Lynnette Madsen</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>lmadsen@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924936</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>0907108&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Raj&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;NON-TECHNICAL DESCRIPTION: &lt;br/&gt;The objective of this proposal is to develop an understanding of the relationship between electronic structure and functional properties of polymer-derived ceramics ? with emphasis on their particular and unprecedented nanodomain structure. The open questions are addressed in a combined theoretical and experimental study, with ab initio computations supporting experimental measurements. This parallelism between theory and experiment is a cornerstone of this proposed research program. Reaching the fundamental goals will make this new class of compounds ?with their outstanding thermodynamic stability above 1500°C ? available to materials applications, including sensors and energy storage in extreme and harsh environments. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;TECHNICAL DETAILS: &lt;br/&gt;A central effort of the proposed computational approach is to model the distinctive and only slowly emerging molecular network structure of this multi-component amorphous polymer-derived ceramics. A two-step approach is designed that first generates an approximate network structure based upon experimental data and chemical intuition. Next, the structures are computed from first-principles including ab initio molecular dynamic simulations. Electronic and optical properties are interpreted and compared with experimental data, yielding information about the atomistic structure and, recursively, giving insight into the atomic arrangements at short and medium length scales.  The doctoral students in the program will work with Ludwig Maxmillian University in Munich and at the University of Trento to achieve a remarkable breadth and depth in their graduate education. Two undergraduates will obtain research experience under this grant. &lt;br/&gt;</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/03/2009</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/01/2015</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>0907108</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Rishi</FirstName>
<LastName>Raj</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Rishi Raj</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>Rishi.Raj@Colorado.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>3034921029</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000102275</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/03/2009</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Colorado at Boulder</Name>
<CityName>Boulder</CityName>
<ZipCode>803031058</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>3034926221</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>3100 Marine Street, Room 481</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[572 UCB]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Colorado</StateName>
<StateCode>CO</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CO02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>007431505</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>REGENTS OF THE UNIVERSITY OF COLORADO, THE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>007431505</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Colorado at Boulder]]></Name>
<CityName>Boulder</CityName>
<StateCode>CO</StateCode>
<ZipCode>803031058</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[3100 Marine Street, Room 481]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Colorado</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CO02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<FoaInformation>
<Code>0106000</Code>
<Name>Materials Research</Name>
</FoaInformation>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1774</Code>
<Text>CERAMICS</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7298</Code>
<Text>International Research Collab</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1774</Code>
<Text>CERAMICS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>5920</Code>
<Text>ITALY</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>5936</Code>
<Text>GERMANY (F.R.G.)</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>5979</Code>
<Text>Europe and Eurasia</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7237</Code>
<Text>NANO NON-SOLIC SCI &amp; ENG AWD</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7504</Code>
<Text>NSF-INTERNAT COOP IN MATERIALS RES-OTHER</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9161</Code>
<Text>SINGLE DIVISION/UNIVERSITY</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>AMPP</Code>
<Text>ADVANCED MATERIALS &amp; PROCESSING PROGRAM</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0109</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0112</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2009~530000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2012~2598</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The outcomes of this project fall into three regimes, (i) basic materials science of an emerging class of new materials, known as polymer derived ceramics, (ii) building a vibrant community of scientists in this special field including mentoring of post-docs, graduate students, undergraduate students and visitors from around the world, and (iii) enabling new technologies with long-term societal impact.</p> <p>The novelty of polymer-derived ceramics or PDCs arises from the method of synthesis whereby <em>organic liquid precursors</em> are converted into an ultrahigh-temperature ceramic material by heating upto temperatures ranging from 800 <sup>o</sup>C to 1000 <sup>o</sup>C. The organic molecules consist of silicon bonded to oxygen, nitrogen and hydrocarbons in myriad combinations. The oxygen, nitrogen and double bonds in the hydrocarbons provide bridges to adjacent molecules and enable cross-linking of the liquid into a rigid polymer. When heated hydrogen is released but carbon atoms, being strongly bonded to silicon remain in the solid state. Various ternary and quaternary ceramics constituted from Si, C, N, and O can be produced. The apparent dichotomy between the strong Si-C bonds and the thermodynamic insolubility of carbon in silica and silicon-nitride, is in fact the source of the unusual nanodomain structure of these ceramics, which, first articulated by the PI, has now become the foundation for the materials science of PDCs. The nanodomain structure consists of a network of graphene sheets that are decorated with mixed bonds of Si-C-O and Si-C-N. The domain size, which varies from 1 &ndash; 5 nm, depends on the carbon content. The high interface to volume ratio of the domains, and the low energy of the graphenaceous interfaces forces the intradomain regions to remain amorphous. Thermal calorimetric measurements have shown the amorphous phase to be thermodynamically stable. The calorimetry measurements have been quantitatively reconciled with predictions from ab-inito modeling. Thus PDCs ceramics constitute a &ldquo;new state of matter&rdquo;; this is a key outcome of this project.&nbsp;</p> <p>The graphenaceous network (embedded in silicon-oxygen-nitrogen) imparts a 2D nature to the PDCs. Large quantities of it can be synthesized in a simple way. It gives rise to unusual multifunctional properties, (i) creep resistance equal to that of carbon at ultrahigh temperatures,&nbsp; (ii) oxidation resistance of pure silicon carbide, (iii) lithium intercalation into the Si-C-O mixed bonds, (iv) piezoresistivity, (v) semiconducting behavior, and (vi) sensor properties. Elucidation of these properties has been a significant outcome of this project.</p> <p>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; The PI has held six one-week-long international workshops in Boulder dedicated to PDCs with the objective of building a community that can work together and grow. Whereas just a few years ago research on PDCs was the purview of a few groups, world-wide, it is now a vibrant field of research with Symposia held at most if not all International Conferences on Ceramics. There is an exponential growth in publications. Applications ranging from porous materials, to anodes for lithium ion batteries, to ultrahigh temperature ceramic matrix composites are appearing on the horizon. The PI is especially proud to have contributed to the field through community-building at a time when it was nascent. He has provided a materials science dimension to this field, which, early on, lay primarily in chemistry.</p> <p>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; In a most significant (recent) outcome the PI and his students have shown that a rapid additive manufacturing concept can be applied to PDCs. Normally, PDCs cannot be formed into objects, thicker than 0.5 mm, since the shrinkage associated with the removal of hydrogen causes cracks, even when cured slowly over several hours. The University of Colorado innovation consists of depositing <em>nanoscale</em> thin films of polymers on a substrate and converting it into the ceramic phase in just a few seconds. Being ultrathin these films pyrolyze quickly without forming cracks. The process is being developed to create ceramic matrix composites (CMCs) by cyclic infiltration of ceramic fiber preforms. The General Electric Company infiltrates the preforms by liquid silicon infiltration with reacts with residual carbon to create a matrix of silicon carbide. Composites made in this way will fly in LEAP gas-turbine engines in 2017. The use of ceramics in engines is opening up a new era of ultrahigh efficiency civilian aircraft. Ceramic matrices made from PDCs using the additive manufacturing method will enable much higher operating temperatures than possible with silicon-melt infiltrated composites whose operating temperature lies well below liquid silicon.</p> <p>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; The CMCs described above have further applications in clean water and gas separation membranes which are currently made from polymers. The CMCs made by the additive method can be tailored to controlled porosity down to nanoscale dimensions. Furthermore they will possess mechanical strength, and even more importantly they can be rejuvenated by heating. Their electrically conductive properties can enable their use as membrane-electrodes in bio-fuel cells.&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 12/18/2016<br>      Modified by: Rishi&nbsp;Raj</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Image         </div> <div class="galControls onePhoto" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation onePhoto" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2016/0907108/0907108_10159962_1482106172105_Fig_2_16CycleCoatingThickness.psdcopy--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2016/0907108/0907108_10159962_1482106172105_Fig_2_16CycleCoatingThickness.psdcopy--rgov-800width.jpg" title="PDC coating on SiC fibers by additive manufacturing."><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2016/0907108/0907108_10159962_1482106172105_Fig_2_16CycleCoatingThickness.psdcopy--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="PDC coating on SiC fibers by additive manufacturing."></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Thin coatings of SiCN(O) polymer-derived ceramic deposited on SiC fibers by the additive manufacturing technique. This result is for 16 cycles. Publication: DOI: 10.1111/jace.14145 (2016).</div> <div class="imageCredit">Azarnoush, Laubscher and Raj</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Rishi&nbsp;Raj</div> <div class="imageTitle">PDC coating on SiC fibers by additive manufacturing.</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The outcomes of this project fall into three regimes, (i) basic materials science of an emerging class of new materials, known as polymer derived ceramics, (ii) building a vibrant community of scientists in this special field including mentoring of post-docs, graduate students, undergraduate students and visitors from around the world, and (iii) enabling new technologies with long-term societal impact.  The novelty of polymer-derived ceramics or PDCs arises from the method of synthesis whereby organic liquid precursors are converted into an ultrahigh-temperature ceramic material by heating upto temperatures ranging from 800 oC to 1000 oC. The organic molecules consist of silicon bonded to oxygen, nitrogen and hydrocarbons in myriad combinations. The oxygen, nitrogen and double bonds in the hydrocarbons provide bridges to adjacent molecules and enable cross-linking of the liquid into a rigid polymer. When heated hydrogen is released but carbon atoms, being strongly bonded to silicon remain in the solid state. Various ternary and quaternary ceramics constituted from Si, C, N, and O can be produced. The apparent dichotomy between the strong Si-C bonds and the thermodynamic insolubility of carbon in silica and silicon-nitride, is in fact the source of the unusual nanodomain structure of these ceramics, which, first articulated by the PI, has now become the foundation for the materials science of PDCs. The nanodomain structure consists of a network of graphene sheets that are decorated with mixed bonds of Si-C-O and Si-C-N. The domain size, which varies from 1 &ndash; 5 nm, depends on the carbon content. The high interface to volume ratio of the domains, and the low energy of the graphenaceous interfaces forces the intradomain regions to remain amorphous. Thermal calorimetric measurements have shown the amorphous phase to be thermodynamically stable. The calorimetry measurements have been quantitatively reconciled with predictions from ab-inito modeling. Thus PDCs ceramics constitute a "new state of matter"; this is a key outcome of this project.   The graphenaceous network (embedded in silicon-oxygen-nitrogen) imparts a 2D nature to the PDCs. Large quantities of it can be synthesized in a simple way. It gives rise to unusual multifunctional properties, (i) creep resistance equal to that of carbon at ultrahigh temperatures,  (ii) oxidation resistance of pure silicon carbide, (iii) lithium intercalation into the Si-C-O mixed bonds, (iv) piezoresistivity, (v) semiconducting behavior, and (vi) sensor properties. Elucidation of these properties has been a significant outcome of this project.              The PI has held six one-week-long international workshops in Boulder dedicated to PDCs with the objective of building a community that can work together and grow. Whereas just a few years ago research on PDCs was the purview of a few groups, world-wide, it is now a vibrant field of research with Symposia held at most if not all International Conferences on Ceramics. There is an exponential growth in publications. Applications ranging from porous materials, to anodes for lithium ion batteries, to ultrahigh temperature ceramic matrix composites are appearing on the horizon. The PI is especially proud to have contributed to the field through community-building at a time when it was nascent. He has provided a materials science dimension to this field, which, early on, lay primarily in chemistry.              In a most significant (recent) outcome the PI and his students have shown that a rapid additive manufacturing concept can be applied to PDCs. Normally, PDCs cannot be formed into objects, thicker than 0.5 mm, since the shrinkage associated with the removal of hydrogen causes cracks, even when cured slowly over several hours. The University of Colorado innovation consists of depositing nanoscale thin films of polymers on a substrate and converting it into the ceramic phase in just a few seconds. Being ultrathin these films pyrolyze quickly without forming cracks. The process is being developed to create ceramic matrix composites (CMCs) by cyclic infiltration of ceramic fiber preforms. The General Electric Company infiltrates the preforms by liquid silicon infiltration with reacts with residual carbon to create a matrix of silicon carbide. Composites made in this way will fly in LEAP gas-turbine engines in 2017. The use of ceramics in engines is opening up a new era of ultrahigh efficiency civilian aircraft. Ceramic matrices made from PDCs using the additive manufacturing method will enable much higher operating temperatures than possible with silicon-melt infiltrated composites whose operating temperature lies well below liquid silicon.              The CMCs described above have further applications in clean water and gas separation membranes which are currently made from polymers. The CMCs made by the additive method can be tailored to controlled porosity down to nanoscale dimensions. Furthermore they will possess mechanical strength, and even more importantly they can be rejuvenated by heating. Their electrically conductive properties can enable their use as membrane-electrodes in bio-fuel cells.        Last Modified: 12/18/2016       Submitted by: Rishi Raj]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
