<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Design of Programmable, Self-Assembling Collagen Biomaterials</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2009</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2013</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>404997.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>404997</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03070013</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DMR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Materials Research</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Joseph A. Akkara</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This award by the Biomaterials program in the Division of Materials Research to Robert Wood Johnson Medical School in NJ is to test the hypothesis that current computational protein design methods are adaptable to the creation of novel biomaterials based on fibrous proteins such as collagen. Natural collagens serve as inspiration for biomaterials design, assuming a multitude of structural forms ranging from thick fibrous bundles to mesh-like networks.  The challenge is approached in two stages:  (1) develop a 'parts list' of peptide modules that assemble into collagen triple-helices with programmable stability and specificity; and (2) link these modules together to form higher-order structures such as fibrils, networks or dendrimers.  The amino acid sequences of three peptides: A, B and C have been computationally designed to specifically assemble into a triple-helix with 1:1:1 stoichiometry.  Initial structural and thermodynamic characterization of peptide mixtures indicates significant progress towards this goal. Assays will be developed to precisely probe the mode of association of peptide mixtures.  Experimental outcomes will be used to revise the computational design protocol.  Connecting modules that orthogonally assemble with flexible linkers may lead to higher-order assemblies such as fibrils, meshes and dendrimers.  A set of designs that combine orthogonal modules will be constructed and tested for types of nanostructures formed.  Insight from these designs will improve the basic understanding of molecular forces in fibrous protein folding and structure.  It will also promote the discovery of new collagen assemblies beyond those found in nature.  A rational design framework will be essential to advance the future development of sophisticated, functional biomaterials for real-world applications.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Computer simulations are being used to design synthetic proteins with applications as biosensors, therapeutics or novel enzymes.  This study targets collagens - long, rope-like proteins that provide most tissues in our body from bones to skin with strength and flexibility.  Using a software platform that incorporates basic physical principles of protein structure and folding, novel collagen-like peptides will be designed that self-assemble into nano-structures.  The challenge is approached in two stages:  (1) develop a ?parts list? of peptide modules that assemble into collagen triple-helices with programmable stability and specificity, and (2) link these modules together to form higher-order structures such as fibrils, networks or dendrimers.  These compounds will be valuable as tissue engineering substrates and biomaterials</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/18/2009</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/23/2011</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>0907273</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Vikas</FirstName>
<LastName>Nanda</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Vikas Nanda</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>nanda@cabm.rutgers.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>7322355328</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000234954</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/18/2009</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Rutgers, The State University of New Jersey-RBHS-Robert Wood</Name>
<CityName>Piscataway</CityName>
<ZipCode>088543925</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>8489320150</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>33 Knightsbridge Road</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[2nd Floor East Wing]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New Jersey</StateName>
<StateCode>NJ</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>06</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NJ06</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>078795875</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>RUTGERS, THE STATE UNIVERSITY OF NEW JERSEY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>001912864</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Rutgers, The State University of New Jersey-RBHS-Robert Wood]]></Name>
<CityName>Piscataway</CityName>
<StateCode>NJ</StateCode>
<ZipCode>088543925</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[33 Knightsbridge Road]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New Jersey</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>06</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NJ06</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<FoaInformation>
<Code>0106000</Code>
<Name>Materials Research</Name>
</FoaInformation>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7623</Code>
<Text>BIOMATERIALS PROGRAM</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7573</Code>
<Text>BIO-RELATED MATERIALS RESEARCH</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9161</Code>
<Text>SINGLE DIVISION/UNIVERSITY</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>AMPP</Code>
<Text>ADVANCED MATERIALS &amp; PROCESSING PROGRAM</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0109</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0110</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0111</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2009~134999</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2010~134999</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2011~134999</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>We applied computational protein design to biomaterials development,&nbsp;establishing a link between sequence, folding and self-assembly. &nbsp;This provided basic insight into the evolution and function of natural collagens and allowed us to design collagenous biomaterials with tunable physiochemical properties.&nbsp; A rational-design framework is essential to advance the future development of sophisticated, functional biomaterials for real-world applications.</p> <p>Computational collagen design has impacted areas outside peptide self-assembly, including the study of natural collagens, engineered chemical derivatives of collagen, photonic protein biomaterials for bioenergy applications, and models for connective tissue and cell-matrix disorders.&nbsp; It also has supported our outreach efforts to introduce molecular modeling and high performance computing (HPC) tools into the classroom.&nbsp; Efforts have focused on at-risk school districts in New Jersey, targeting under-represented minority students.&nbsp; Members of the research group at all levels from undergraduate to postdoc participate in national computing education conferences and lead workshops to expose the larger New Jersey research community to biophysical and biochemical applications of HPC resources.</p> <p>We have made significant progress toward creating a software platform for designing collagen peptides that heterospecifically assemble as an ABC-type heterotrimer.&nbsp; In the design of ABC, we employed a <em>simulated evolution</em> algorithm, used by many protein design groups to determine candidate sequences for a target fold.&nbsp; At each step, a mutation was introduced into one of the three chains and its impact evaluated by an objective scoring function that examined networks of charge-pair interactions (see figure A).&nbsp; Mutations that improve stability were accepted, and unfavorable mutations were rejected.&nbsp;Novel to our work was a second tier to enforce specificity (figure B)&nbsp;where mutations were selected that introduced a <em>gap in stability</em> between ABC and competing states.&nbsp; The final design (figure C) was synthesized and shown to form triple-helical structure only in the presence of all three peptides.&nbsp;</p> <p>This grant has supported in whole or in part the efforts of two postdoctoral researchers, three graduate students and six undergraduate researchers.&nbsp; It has spawned a number of collaborations, several with international labs.&nbsp; Outreach activities were conducted in local high schools, engaging students in protein biochemistry by incorporating interactive molecular modeling directly into the lesson.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 01/02/2014<br>      Modified by: Vikas&nbsp;Nanda</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Image         </div> <div class="galControls onePhoto" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation onePhoto" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2014/0907273/0907273_10028102_1388690616481_design_strategy--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2014/0907273/0907273_10028102_1388690616481_design_strategy--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Collagen Design Strategy"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2014/0907273/0907273_10028102_1388690616481_design_strategy--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Collagen Design Strategy"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">(a) Network of charge pair interactions from the crystal structure of a Type III collagen fragment.  (b) Simulated evolution protocol for sequence optimization of designed collagens.  (c) Sequence of the ABC design highlighting the predicted n...]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ We applied computational protein design to biomaterials development, establishing a link between sequence, folding and self-assembly.  This provided basic insight into the evolution and function of natural collagens and allowed us to design collagenous biomaterials with tunable physiochemical properties.  A rational-design framework is essential to advance the future development of sophisticated, functional biomaterials for real-world applications.  Computational collagen design has impacted areas outside peptide self-assembly, including the study of natural collagens, engineered chemical derivatives of collagen, photonic protein biomaterials for bioenergy applications, and models for connective tissue and cell-matrix disorders.  It also has supported our outreach efforts to introduce molecular modeling and high performance computing (HPC) tools into the classroom.  Efforts have focused on at-risk school districts in New Jersey, targeting under-represented minority students.  Members of the research group at all levels from undergraduate to postdoc participate in national computing education conferences and lead workshops to expose the larger New Jersey research community to biophysical and biochemical applications of HPC resources.  We have made significant progress toward creating a software platform for designing collagen peptides that heterospecifically assemble as an ABC-type heterotrimer.  In the design of ABC, we employed a simulated evolution algorithm, used by many protein design groups to determine candidate sequences for a target fold.  At each step, a mutation was introduced into one of the three chains and its impact evaluated by an objective scoring function that examined networks of charge-pair interactions (see figure A).  Mutations that improve stability were accepted, and unfavorable mutations were rejected. Novel to our work was a second tier to enforce specificity (figure B) where mutations were selected that introduced a gap in stability between ABC and competing states.  The final design (figure C) was synthesized and shown to form triple-helical structure only in the presence of all three peptides.   This grant has supported in whole or in part the efforts of two postdoctoral researchers, three graduate students and six undergraduate researchers.  It has spawned a number of collaborations, several with international labs.  Outreach activities were conducted in local high schools, engaging students in protein biochemistry by incorporating interactive molecular modeling directly into the lesson.          Last Modified: 01/02/2014       Submitted by: Vikas Nanda]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
