<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Materials World Network: The Magnetostructural Response in Heterostructured Systems: A US - UK Collaboration</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2009</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2014</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>420000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>420000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03070010</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DMR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Materials Research</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Gary Shiflet</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This Materials World Network award by the Metallic Materials and Nanostructures program and the Office of Special Program in the Division of Materials Research to Northeastern University is to synthesize and study heterostructured films of equiatomic Iron-Rhodium (FeRh) compound, and to map out its multi-dimensional phase space and identify low-energy pathways to tailor the first-order antiferro- to ferromagnetic phase transition and associated functional responses that are found in this compound.  While first-order magnetic transitions are known to underlie an assortment of extreme functional phenomena with important technological attributes (colossal magnetoresistance, giant magnetocaloric character and giant magnetic shape memory), knowledge concerning key materials factors controlling these responses remains elusive.  In this project, the researchers plan to modify the phase boundaries in model-system FeRh epilayers by: (1) employing additional magnetic layers to amplify or offset the applied magnetic field that drives the transition; (2) applying stress via substrate selection; and (3) exploiting interphase ferromagnetic exchange coupling.  Unique educational features of the project are extended scientific student exchanges between the U.S. and the U.K. teams, as well as providing training to students in the application of advanced probes to the research such as synchrotron x-ray scattering, neutron scattering and transmission electron microscopy.  &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project features fundamental research focused on a member of a very rare class of materials -?magnetostructural materials? - that exhibit intimate interactions between the electrons in the material and the atoms that constitute its crystal lattice.  This unique arrangement lends the material an extraordinary responsiveness to physical perturbations such that very small changes in temperature, magnetic/electric field or strain can drive a very large response in the material.  Thus this class of materials is poised for development and potential application in advanced sensors to monitor environmental conditions and enable, via computer networking, so-called ?smart? networks with relevance to energy management and efficiency.  To facilitate experimental clarity, the simple magnetic compound FeRh will be made in thin film form and studied at the partner laboratories in the U.S. (Northeastern University, Brookhaven National Laboratory) and in the U.K. (University of Leeds, ISIS/Rutherford Appleton Laboratory).  Students from the educational institutions involved will participate in transatlantic research exchanges and will have the opportunity to be trained in fundamental science as well as in the use of advanced probes such as synchrotron x-ray scattering, neutron scattering and transmission electron microscopy.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/27/2009</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/10/2013</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>0908767</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Donald</FirstName>
<LastName>Heiman</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Donald Heiman</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>d.heiman@neu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6173732912</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000441744</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/27/2009</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Laura</FirstName>
<LastName>Lewis</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>H</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Laura H Lewis</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>lhlewis@neu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6173733419</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000460546</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/27/2009</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Northeastern University</Name>
<CityName>BOSTON</CityName>
<ZipCode>021155005</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6173733004</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>360 HUNTINGTON AVE</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[177-500]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
<StateCode>MA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MA07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>001423631</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>NORTHEASTERN UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>001423631</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Northeastern University]]></Name>
<CityName>BOSTON</CityName>
<StateCode>MA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>021155005</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[360 HUNTINGTON AVE]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MA07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<FoaInformation>
<Code>0106000</Code>
<Name>Materials Research</Name>
</FoaInformation>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1771</Code>
<Text>METAL &amp; METALLIC NANOSTRUCTURE</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7222</Code>
<Text>XC-Crosscutting Activities Pro</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7488</Code>
<Text>MATERIALS WORLD NETWORK</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9161</Code>
<Text>SINGLE DIVISION/UNIVERSITY</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>AMPP</Code>
<Text>ADVANCED MATERIALS &amp; PROCESSING PROGRAM</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0109</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0110</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0111</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2009~140000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2010~140000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2011~140000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Magnetostructural materials demonstrate concurrent magnetic and structural phase transformations which may be driven by changes in temperature, pressure (strain), or magnetic field. The ability to alter the phase transformation <em>via </em>a variety of routes makes these systems the interest of fundamental studies of the physics underlying the transformation, as well as potential technological applications. Equiatomic &alpha;&acute;-FeRh, a model magnetostructural material with the chemically-ordered CsCl-type crystal structure, undergoes a first-order phase transition (FOPT) (upon heating) from antiferromagnetic (AF) to ferromagnetic (FM) order with an accompanying 1% (volume) lattice expansion at <em>T</em>~370 K, in bulk. Thin film forms of &alpha;&acute;-FeRh provide an additional degree of complexity to the transformation character as epitaxial film//substrate clamping and reduced-dimensionality promotes anisotropic interface strain, creating a rich arena to explore the FOPT.</p> <p class="Default">&nbsp;</p> <p>In this work, sputter deposited &alpha;&acute;-FeRh thin films have been grown to study the role of intrinsic (chemical modification by thermally driven Au-capping layer diffusion) and extrinsic (strain/film lattice distortion and nanostructuring) factors on the FOPT character. Further, magnetic studies coupled with kinetic analysis have been employed to develop an understanding of the phase transformation kinetics (energy barriers and nucleation and growth mechanism associated with the AF-FM FOPT) in &alpha;'-FeRh thin films. Results have been obtained with laboratory- and synchrotron-based magnetic and structural probes to advance the understanding of the spin-lattice coupling in the &alpha;&acute;-FeRh system with information that allows FOPT tailoring.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>Specifically, results obtained in this dissertation reveal that thermally-driven Au diffusion, out-of-plane lattice distortion, and nanostructuring lead to a stabilized FM phase in the (bulk) AF regime. Further, the results achieved in this dissertation indicate that the degree of undercooling of the FM phase (phase metastability), AF/FM phase coexistence, and the energy barrier associated with the AF-FM transition may be modified with intrinsic and extrinsic properties, thereby creating a variety of pathways to tailor the FOPT.&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>This work was funded under the international Materials World Network scheme with researchers in the United Kingdom.&nbsp; It has resulted in two Ph.D. dissertations, 8 peer-reviewed publications, 6 invited presentations and 14 contributed presentations.&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 08/11/2014<br>      Modified by: Laura&nbsp;H&nbsp;Lewis</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Magnetostructural materials demonstrate concurrent magnetic and structural phase transformations which may be driven by changes in temperature, pressure (strain), or magnetic field. The ability to alter the phase transformation via a variety of routes makes these systems the interest of fundamental studies of the physics underlying the transformation, as well as potential technological applications. Equiatomic &alpha;&acute;-FeRh, a model magnetostructural material with the chemically-ordered CsCl-type crystal structure, undergoes a first-order phase transition (FOPT) (upon heating) from antiferromagnetic (AF) to ferromagnetic (FM) order with an accompanying 1% (volume) lattice expansion at T~370 K, in bulk. Thin film forms of &alpha;&acute;-FeRh provide an additional degree of complexity to the transformation character as epitaxial film//substrate clamping and reduced-dimensionality promotes anisotropic interface strain, creating a rich arena to explore the FOPT.    In this work, sputter deposited &alpha;&acute;-FeRh thin films have been grown to study the role of intrinsic (chemical modification by thermally driven Au-capping layer diffusion) and extrinsic (strain/film lattice distortion and nanostructuring) factors on the FOPT character. Further, magnetic studies coupled with kinetic analysis have been employed to develop an understanding of the phase transformation kinetics (energy barriers and nucleation and growth mechanism associated with the AF-FM FOPT) in &alpha;'-FeRh thin films. Results have been obtained with laboratory- and synchrotron-based magnetic and structural probes to advance the understanding of the spin-lattice coupling in the &alpha;&acute;-FeRh system with information that allows FOPT tailoring.     Specifically, results obtained in this dissertation reveal that thermally-driven Au diffusion, out-of-plane lattice distortion, and nanostructuring lead to a stabilized FM phase in the (bulk) AF regime. Further, the results achieved in this dissertation indicate that the degree of undercooling of the FM phase (phase metastability), AF/FM phase coexistence, and the energy barrier associated with the AF-FM transition may be modified with intrinsic and extrinsic properties, thereby creating a variety of pathways to tailor the FOPT.      This work was funded under the international Materials World Network scheme with researchers in the United Kingdom.  It has resulted in two Ph.D. dissertations, 8 peer-reviewed publications, 6 invited presentations and 14 contributed presentations.           Last Modified: 08/11/2014       Submitted by: Laura H Lewis]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
