<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Collaborative Research: Growth of the Tibetan Plateau and Eastern Asia Climate: Clues to Understanding the Hydrological Cycle</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/15/2009</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2014</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>397169.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>397169</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>06030201</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>GEO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>EAR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Earth Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Leonard E. Johnson</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>For fifty years, the Tibetan Plateau has been recognized as the largest topographic feature that perturbs atmospheric circulation.  It serves as an ideal field laboratory for understanding the geodynamic processes that build high terrain.  Accordingly, the growth of the plateau should have altered atmospheric circulation and therefore written an evolving paleoclimatic signature not only on eastern Asian regional climates, but on global climate as well.  Despite many recent studies, we still do not know precisely when the Tibetan Plateau reached its current dimensions and how it perturbs atmospheric circulation.  This project brings together geodynamicists, atmospheric scientists, and paleoclimatologists in a multidisciplinary study of the when and the how.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;One of the major goals of the project is to quantify the extent to which Tibet has grown by crustal thickening, by thrust faulting and folding, by flow within the crust that redistributes material there, or by replacement of cold mantle lithosphere with hotter material (all in a state of isostatic equilibrium). Such quantification will take big steps toward the understanding of how high plateaus are built and how continental lithosphere deforms, topics at the forefront of geodynamics. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Determining how Tibet has grown will require determining when crustal shortening and thickening occurred, using basic field methods and modern laboratory techniques, and quantifying paleoaltitudes with new isotopic tools. Applying such paleoaltimetric techniques, however, requires an understanding not only of how the atmosphere transports isotopes, but how the evolving high terrain affected surface temperatures at times in the past. Even if the project?s focus were solely on how Tibet has grown, a meteorological component of the study, focused particularly on eastern Asia?s hydrological cycle, would be necessary. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Most continental paleoclimatic indicators are thought to be more sensitive to precipitation than to temperature, and among the unknowns of future climate, the hydrological cycle stands out.  Accordingly, a major focus will be on understanding how high terrain like Tibet affects the hydrological cycle of eastern Asia, and China in particular. These studies will focus on: (1) how the plateau, as both a topographic obstacle and a sink for solar radiation, affects atmospheric circulation; (2) how the atmosphere transports stable isotopes (ä18O and äD); (3) how it affects mid-latitude climate variability, including how, via lee cyclogenesis, it lofts and transports dust, and (4) how vegetation feeds back on atmospheric circulation and the hydrological cycle.  As links from geologic processes occurring at multi-Myr time scales to those on human time scales, the Principal Investigators plan studies that specifically examine paleoprecipitation over the past few hundred thousand years, using both loess deposition and speleothems that quantify paleoclimate. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>09/15/2009</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/06/2011</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.050</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>0909199</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Peter</FirstName>
<LastName>Molnar</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>H</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Peter H Molnar</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>molnar@Colorado.EDU</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>3034924936</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000197137</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/15/2009</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Colorado at Boulder</Name>
<CityName>Boulder</CityName>
<ZipCode>803031058</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>3034926221</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>3100 Marine Street, Room 481</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[572 UCB]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Colorado</StateName>
<StateCode>CO</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CO02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>007431505</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>REGENTS OF THE UNIVERSITY OF COLORADO, THE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>007431505</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Colorado at Boulder]]></Name>
<CityName>Boulder</CityName>
<StateCode>CO</StateCode>
<ZipCode>803031058</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[3100 Marine Street, Room 481]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Colorado</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CO02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<FoaInformation>
<Code>0000099</Code>
<Name>Other Applications NEC</Name>
</FoaInformation>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1581</Code>
<Text>CONTINENTAL DYNAMICS PROGRAM</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>6898</Code>
<Text>EAR-Earth Sciences Research</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>0000</Code>
<Text>UNASSIGNED</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>OTHR</Code>
<Text>OTHER RESEARCH OR EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0109</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0111</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2009~290752</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2011~106417</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Project Outcomes Report for Collaborative Research: Growth of the Tibetan Plateau and Eastern Asia Climate: Clues to Understanding the Hydrological Cycle Award Number: 0909199</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>Out study focused on two questions: (1) how and when the northern part of Tibet grew to its current elevation, and (2) how that growth affected regional climate in Asia, especially the hydrological cycle.&nbsp; Our project included 14 US Investigators and a comparable number of Chinese colleagues.&nbsp; We report here only on the work done by investigators from the University of Colorado.&nbsp; Others among us have focused on when northern Tibet grew.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>Toward the first goal, our most important contribution has been to bring some understanding to how mantle dynamics affects the overlying crust, and in particular contributes to the building of mountains and high plateaus.&nbsp; We find that much written about &ldquo;dynamic topography&rdquo; is ado about very little.&nbsp; Mantle dynamics builds mountains largely by one of two processes.&nbsp; (1) It moves large regions of lithosphere (crust and uppermost mantle) toward one another to thicken crust, which then because of its buoyancy stands high.&nbsp; (2) Flow in the mantle removes cold mantle portion of the lithosphere from beneath a region, and replaces that cold dense material with warmer less dense material.&nbsp; In either case, the mountains stand high because of Archimedes&rsquo; Principle, or isostasy: mass above sea level must be compensated by a deficit of mass at depth.&nbsp; Stresses applied to the base of the lithosphere contribute little; mantle dynamics does nothing comparable to the forces applied to a rapidly spinning baseball that make it curve.&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>Regarding the second aspect of this work, we find that Tibet&rsquo;s role in the South Asian (or India) Monsoon is modest.&nbsp; Its effects are present, but only in the early and late monsoon seasons.&nbsp; In fact, from an examination of how the growth of the Tibetan Plateau might have affected climate and the hydrological cycle of the Indian subcontinent on geologic time scales, we conclude that the eastward, outward growth of the plateau weakened monsoon rainfall over NW India and Pakistan, rather than strengthening it.&nbsp; Although we do recognize that a high Tibetan Plateau affects the strength of monsoon rainfall over India, like others we conclude that Tibet&rsquo;s role has been overrated.&nbsp; (This is not to say that Tibet&rsquo;s role elsewhere, such as over China, is not major.)</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 09/05/2014<br>      Modified by: Peter&nbsp;H&nbsp;Molnar</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Project Outcomes Report for Collaborative Research: Growth of the Tibetan Plateau and Eastern Asia Climate: Clues to Understanding the Hydrological Cycle Award Number: 0909199     Out study focused on two questions: (1) how and when the northern part of Tibet grew to its current elevation, and (2) how that growth affected regional climate in Asia, especially the hydrological cycle.  Our project included 14 US Investigators and a comparable number of Chinese colleagues.  We report here only on the work done by investigators from the University of Colorado.  Others among us have focused on when northern Tibet grew.     Toward the first goal, our most important contribution has been to bring some understanding to how mantle dynamics affects the overlying crust, and in particular contributes to the building of mountains and high plateaus.  We find that much written about "dynamic topography" is ado about very little.  Mantle dynamics builds mountains largely by one of two processes.  (1) It moves large regions of lithosphere (crust and uppermost mantle) toward one another to thicken crust, which then because of its buoyancy stands high.  (2) Flow in the mantle removes cold mantle portion of the lithosphere from beneath a region, and replaces that cold dense material with warmer less dense material.  In either case, the mountains stand high because of ArchimedesÆ Principle, or isostasy: mass above sea level must be compensated by a deficit of mass at depth.  Stresses applied to the base of the lithosphere contribute little; mantle dynamics does nothing comparable to the forces applied to a rapidly spinning baseball that make it curve.      Regarding the second aspect of this work, we find that TibetÆs role in the South Asian (or India) Monsoon is modest.  Its effects are present, but only in the early and late monsoon seasons.  In fact, from an examination of how the growth of the Tibetan Plateau might have affected climate and the hydrological cycle of the Indian subcontinent on geologic time scales, we conclude that the eastward, outward growth of the plateau weakened monsoon rainfall over NW India and Pakistan, rather than strengthening it.  Although we do recognize that a high Tibetan Plateau affects the strength of monsoon rainfall over India, like others we conclude that TibetÆs role has been overrated.  (This is not to say that TibetÆs role elsewhere, such as over China, is not major.)             Last Modified: 09/05/2014       Submitted by: Peter H Molnar]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
