<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Large Empirical Research Project in the Contextual Research Strand: The First Five Years of Mathematics Teaching</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>01/15/2010</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>04/30/2016</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>574955.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>574955</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>11090000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>EHR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DRL</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Research On Learning</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Finbarr Sloane</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>fsloane@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032928465</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The investigators propose to study novice teachers' development of mathematical knowledge for teaching and the influence that previous preparation, school context, and opportunities to learn-on-the-job have on that knowledge.  The project as supported represents a planning and development study that may lead to a larger cross-national study.  The investigators will develop surveys of teachers, a sample framework, unique survey methodologies required, and will enlist country participation.  The contributions of the planning and development phase will include sampling methodology and survey instrumentation that can be used in other contexts. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The larger project as envisioned will survey six representative and independent samples of teachers with zero to five years of teaching experience in the U.S. and in three to five other high achieving countries.  The work builds upon a successful, existing award to the investigators--the Teacher Education Development Study (TEDS-M)--that is examining the math knowledge of undergraduate students who are preparing to teach math.  &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;As a result, the proposed study is the next logical step in this program of research and will tell us more about how U.S. teachers compare with teachers of other countries in terms of their mathematical knowledge and mathematical knowledge for teaching.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>01/05/2010</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>12/18/2015</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.076</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>0910001</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Maria</FirstName>
<LastName>Tatto</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>T</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Maria T Tatto</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>mtatto@asu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5173323524</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000107181</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>01/05/2010</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Michigan State University</Name>
<CityName>East Lansing</CityName>
<ZipCode>488242600</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5173555040</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>Office of Sponsored Programs</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[426 Administration Bldg, Rm2]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Michigan</StateName>
<StateCode>MI</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>08</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MI08</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>193247145</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>MICHIGAN STATE UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>053343976</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Michigan State University]]></Name>
<CityName>East Lansing</CityName>
<StateCode>MI</StateCode>
<ZipCode>488242600</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[Office of Sponsored Programs]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Michigan</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>08</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MI08</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<FoaInformation>
<Code>0000099</Code>
<Name>Other Applications NEC</Name>
</FoaInformation>
<FoaInformation>
<Code>0116000</Code>
<Name>Human Subjects</Name>
</FoaInformation>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7625</Code>
<Text>REAL</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7625</Code>
<Text>REESE</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9177</Code>
<Text>ELEMENTARY/SECONDARY EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>SMET</Code>
<Text>SCIENCE, MATH, ENG &amp; TECH EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0410</Code>
<Name>NSF Education &amp; Human Resource</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040106</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2010~574955</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><strong>Principal Investigator: Maria Teresa Tatto</strong></p> <p>The motivation for the First Five Years of Mathematics Teaching Study (FIRSTMATH) originated from the NSF-funded Teacher Education and Development Study in Mathematics Study (TEDS-M, REC 0514431, Principal Investigator Maria Teresa Tatto, with J. Schwille &amp; S. Senk Co-PIs; http://teds.educ.msu.edu/) where we learned how pre-service teacher education impacts future teachers&rsquo; mathematics knowledge for teaching in 17 countries including the US. In FIRSTMATH we sought to extend our inquiry into the first 5 years of teaching in a selected group of countries including the US. As this kind of study had not been attempted before, the NSF suggested that we undertake a proof-of-concept study before embarking in a large one.&nbsp;</p> <p><strong>Intellectual merit</strong>. FIRSTMATH seeks to develop the scientific basis and methods for a cross-national study of novice teachers&rsquo; development of mathematical knowledge for teaching and the mediating influence of previous preparation, school context and opportunities to learn-on-the-job, on that knowledge. The study also explores the degree to which standards, accountability and other similar mechanisms operate to regulate the support that beginning teachers of mathematics receive during their first years of teaching; and how all this connects with teaching practice and pupils&rsquo; learning. The study design offers the opportunity to test multiple hypotheses at a large scale about how beginning teachers develop proficiency in mathematical knowledge for teaching and in mathematics teaching practice in a range of school and country contexts. Specifically, we have adapted instruments and methods from TEDS-M, and developed new ones for FIRSTMATH. In addition, we have resolved issues related to definitions, sampling, and analysis; we are now ready to launch this empirical comparative research study of beginning mathematics teachers nationally and cross-nationally.</p> <p><strong>Broader Impacts</strong>. The results of this study provide needed empirical evidence about the influence of school context and on-the-job opportunities to learn on mathematics teachers&rsquo; knowledge, and on the nature of the knowledge that is useful in and for mathematics teaching in diverse settings and school contexts. FIRSTMATH speaks to contentious policy issues about the relative cost-effectiveness of school-based training and induction vis-&agrave;-vis pre-service teacher education. Understanding these effects has potential economic impact for thousands of school districts or other agencies concerned with teacher recruitment and retention and with developing quality mentoring, induction, and professional development programs.</p> <p>Among the many significant methodological advances emerging from FIRSTMATH are: the development of a working definition of a novice teacher, the successful implementation of a two-stage sampling design, the introduction of an innovative sequential sampling design as an alternative to the traditional two-stage design, and the development of strategies to access novice teachers and obtain high response rates. In addition, the study developed effective data collection methods and instrumentation. Between 2011 and 2014, FIRSTMATH developed: the FIRSTMATH Novice Teacher Questionnaire (NTQ), the FIRSTMATH Knowledge for Teaching Assessments (primary and secondary levels), the FIRSTMATH Classroom Observation Tools, the FIRSTMATH Pupil Knowledge Assessments (primary and secondary levels), the FIRSTMATH Pupil Background Questionnaire, the FIRSTMATH Curriculum Analysis Protocols, and the FIRSTMATH Policy Document Analysis Protocols.</p> <p>In 2014-2015, we successfully conducted a field trial of these instruments. The countries that participated in the 2014-2015 Field Trial include Bulgaria, Chile, England, Guatemala, Guyana, Honduras, Mexico, Peru, Philippines, Slovakia, Turkey, and the US. The data collected came from 380-Novice Teachers, 870-Primary-Pupils, and 850-Secondary-Pupils.</p> <p>Even as a proof-of-concept, the FIRSTMATH Study is ground-breaking in its initial findings and its capacity to train country researchers, young scholars and graduate students on how to do rigorous research in this area. At the end of this proof-of-concept study, we understand that across nations learning to teach mathematics is a complex life-long process which requires formal preparation and guided learning and reflection. These processes however are highly variable across countries.&nbsp;Through participation in the study and after examination of preliminary findings we have secured several countries' commitment to implement the larger study, and have gained the interest and support of important international institutions, and agencies. We plan to submit a proposal to the NSF for the larger study this fall.</p> <p>The question of how teachers better learn to teach mathematics to diverse populations is of paramount importance to entire nations. While teachers have received preparation through a variety of approaches to date we yet do not know what approaches are best for different contexts and pupils. The implementation of the larger study will help us find out.</p> <p>Participation in an international study as part of a community of learners enables novice teachers to collect information on their practice within a collaborative self-improvement effort. This study is particularly relevant to current policy priorities in the US and globally and it responds to the need to develop valid and reliable methods to evaluate the effectiveness of mathematics teachers in a way that is conducive to future learning.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 07/31/2016<br>      Modified by: Maria&nbsp;T&nbsp;Tatto</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Principal Investigator: Maria Teresa Tatto  The motivation for the First Five Years of Mathematics Teaching Study (FIRSTMATH) originated from the NSF-funded Teacher Education and Development Study in Mathematics Study (TEDS-M, REC 0514431, Principal Investigator Maria Teresa Tatto, with J. Schwille &amp; S. Senk Co-PIs; http://teds.educ.msu.edu/) where we learned how pre-service teacher education impacts future teachers? mathematics knowledge for teaching in 17 countries including the US. In FIRSTMATH we sought to extend our inquiry into the first 5 years of teaching in a selected group of countries including the US. As this kind of study had not been attempted before, the NSF suggested that we undertake a proof-of-concept study before embarking in a large one.   Intellectual merit. FIRSTMATH seeks to develop the scientific basis and methods for a cross-national study of novice teachers? development of mathematical knowledge for teaching and the mediating influence of previous preparation, school context and opportunities to learn-on-the-job, on that knowledge. The study also explores the degree to which standards, accountability and other similar mechanisms operate to regulate the support that beginning teachers of mathematics receive during their first years of teaching; and how all this connects with teaching practice and pupils? learning. The study design offers the opportunity to test multiple hypotheses at a large scale about how beginning teachers develop proficiency in mathematical knowledge for teaching and in mathematics teaching practice in a range of school and country contexts. Specifically, we have adapted instruments and methods from TEDS-M, and developed new ones for FIRSTMATH. In addition, we have resolved issues related to definitions, sampling, and analysis; we are now ready to launch this empirical comparative research study of beginning mathematics teachers nationally and cross-nationally.  Broader Impacts. The results of this study provide needed empirical evidence about the influence of school context and on-the-job opportunities to learn on mathematics teachers? knowledge, and on the nature of the knowledge that is useful in and for mathematics teaching in diverse settings and school contexts. FIRSTMATH speaks to contentious policy issues about the relative cost-effectiveness of school-based training and induction vis-&agrave;-vis pre-service teacher education. Understanding these effects has potential economic impact for thousands of school districts or other agencies concerned with teacher recruitment and retention and with developing quality mentoring, induction, and professional development programs.  Among the many significant methodological advances emerging from FIRSTMATH are: the development of a working definition of a novice teacher, the successful implementation of a two-stage sampling design, the introduction of an innovative sequential sampling design as an alternative to the traditional two-stage design, and the development of strategies to access novice teachers and obtain high response rates. In addition, the study developed effective data collection methods and instrumentation. Between 2011 and 2014, FIRSTMATH developed: the FIRSTMATH Novice Teacher Questionnaire (NTQ), the FIRSTMATH Knowledge for Teaching Assessments (primary and secondary levels), the FIRSTMATH Classroom Observation Tools, the FIRSTMATH Pupil Knowledge Assessments (primary and secondary levels), the FIRSTMATH Pupil Background Questionnaire, the FIRSTMATH Curriculum Analysis Protocols, and the FIRSTMATH Policy Document Analysis Protocols.  In 2014-2015, we successfully conducted a field trial of these instruments. The countries that participated in the 2014-2015 Field Trial include Bulgaria, Chile, England, Guatemala, Guyana, Honduras, Mexico, Peru, Philippines, Slovakia, Turkey, and the US. The data collected came from 380-Novice Teachers, 870-Primary-Pupils, and 850-Secondary-Pupils.  Even as a proof-of-concept, the FIRSTMATH Study is ground-breaking in its initial findings and its capacity to train country researchers, young scholars and graduate students on how to do rigorous research in this area. At the end of this proof-of-concept study, we understand that across nations learning to teach mathematics is a complex life-long process which requires formal preparation and guided learning and reflection. These processes however are highly variable across countries. Through participation in the study and after examination of preliminary findings we have secured several countries' commitment to implement the larger study, and have gained the interest and support of important international institutions, and agencies. We plan to submit a proposal to the NSF for the larger study this fall.  The question of how teachers better learn to teach mathematics to diverse populations is of paramount importance to entire nations. While teachers have received preparation through a variety of approaches to date we yet do not know what approaches are best for different contexts and pupils. The implementation of the larger study will help us find out.  Participation in an international study as part of a community of learners enables novice teachers to collect information on their practice within a collaborative self-improvement effort. This study is particularly relevant to current policy priorities in the US and globally and it responds to the need to develop valid and reliable methods to evaluate the effectiveness of mathematics teachers in a way that is conducive to future learning.          Last Modified: 07/31/2016       Submitted by: Maria T Tatto]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
