<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Heterocyclic Chemistry of Bicyclo[1.1.0]butanes</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/15/2009</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2014</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>390000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>390000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03090000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CHE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Chemistry</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Tingyu Li</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>tli@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924949</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This project will focus on the exploratory chemistry of a strained organic ring system, the bicyclobutane group. Steric strain has always been one of the major driving forces for C-C and C-heteroatom bond formations, but in contrast to cyclopropanes, oxiranes, and aziridines, only minimal progress has been made in the past in the application of the bicyclo[1.1.0]butane building block in organic synthesis. Fundamentally, bicyclobutanes represent 4-carbon alkyne surrogates. Studies to harness their intramolecular pericyclic processes will take advantage of the attachment of suitable alkenes and alkynes to a nitrogen tether and provide access to novel polycyclic pyrrolidines. Additionally, hypothesis driven transition metal catalyzed transformations will be carried out to identify new reactions and construct useful new heterocyclic scaffolds.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;With this award, the Organic and Macromolecular Chemistry Program is supporting the research of Professor Peter Wipf of the Department of Chemistry at the University of Pittsburgh.  Professor Wipf's research efforts revolve around the total synthesis of natural products, organometallic and heterocyclic processes, and combinatorial, medicinal and computational chemistry. The study of chemical reactivity and the use of synthesis to augment the chemical toolbox assists the development of new therapeutic strategies. The discovery of fundamentally new reaction pathways in his laboratory is stimulated by exploratory studies of transition metal complexes.   Successful development of the methodology will have an impact on discovery and process chemistry in the pharmaceutical, agricultural and fine chemical industries.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/19/2009</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/01/2011</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>0910560</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Peter</FirstName>
<LastName>Wipf</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Peter Wipf</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>pwipf+@pitt.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>4126248606</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000245422</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/19/2009</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Pittsburgh</Name>
<CityName>Pittsburgh</CityName>
<ZipCode>152133203</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>4126247400</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>300 Murdoch Building</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[3420 Forbes Avenue]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Pennsylvania</StateName>
<StateCode>PA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>18</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>PA18</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>004514360</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF PITTSBURGH, THE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>004514360</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Pittsburgh]]></Name>
<CityName>Pittsburgh</CityName>
<StateCode>PA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>152133203</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[300 Murdoch Building]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Pennsylvania</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>18</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>PA18</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1950</Code>
<Text>METHODOLOGY</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9146</Code>
<Text>MANUFACTURING BASE RESEARCH</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>MANU</Code>
<Text>MANUFACTURING</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0109</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0110</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0111</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2009~130000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2010~130000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2011~130000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><br /><strong>Report for the General Public for Grant<br />CHE-0910560, "Heterocyclic Chemistry of Bicyclo[1.1.0]butanes</strong></p> <p>The long-term objective of this Grant is to transform the current practice of<br />heterocyclic chemistry by developing innovative metal-catalyzed processes that replace traditional, harsh and wasteful condensation protocols.&nbsp; We designed new strategies taking advantage of the ready availability of the highly strained bicyclo[1.1.0]butanes as precursors for stereoselective <em>carbon-carbon </em>and <em>carbon</em>-<em>heteroatom</em> bond formations.&nbsp;Especially significant was the discovery of novel, one-pot cascade reactions that convert simple starting materials into structurally diverse heterocyclic building blocks. These compunds are significant for the pharmaceutical industry, since they allow medicinal chemists to expand on the diversity of their biologically active agents, as well as for the general field of chemistry, since new materials require tailored building blocks with novel properties. New structural diversity will likely increase the number and utility of small molecule modulators of biological functions, access new intellectual property (IP) space, and stimulate a more creative deployment of the organic chemistry toolset to solve challenges in biology and medicine.&nbsp; While initial hits might be more rapidly identified in traditional assays of libraries rich in privileged chemotypes, as they are routinely performed in pharmaceutical and biotech companies, novel scaffolds showcase the value of an innovative chemistry program, increase the opportunities for the discovery of new biological phenotypes, and bear greater patent value for a platform approach.</p> <p><strong><em>Broad Impact Activities</em></strong><em>:</em><strong> </strong></p> <p>Over the last 4 years, 36 undergraduates (28 women) and 2 high school students (1 woman) participated in research in the Wipf group. During this period, 5 papers with undergraduate coauthors were published. The majority of these students have gone on to graduate school or medical school, while 4 are still in our undergraduate program. The graduate education of 5 students (1 woman) was partly or fully supported by NSF funds. One of these students is currently performing postdoctoral research at Princeton (Filip Petronijevic) and 1 has started a tenure track Assistant Professor position at the University of Colorado at Boulder (Macej Walczak). The postdoctoral work of Michael Yang, was partly supported by funds from the NSF award. He is currently a staff scientist at Evonik Degussa. In summary, the group has an outstanding track record in training high school, undergraduate and graduate students, and postdoctoral fellows.</p> <p><em>Outreach</em>: Over the last 5 years, Wipf has presented ca. 150 invited talks at international and national conferences, departmental colloquiums, and pharmaceutical, biotech and chemical companies. Wipf has been a member of the Organizing Committee of two international conferences and served as a program co-chair of the ACS National Medicinal Chemistry Symposium and the local ACS meeting in Pittsburgh in 2014. He served or is currently serving on &gt;20 advisory or editorial boards, including an Associate Editorship of <em>ACS<br />Med. Chem. Lett</em>. He is also currently on the Board of Directors of <em>Organic Reactions</em> and <em>Organic Syntheses</em>, and he was elected to be the Chair of the Pharmaceutical Sciences Section of the American Association for the Advancement of Science (AAAS) in 2016. Wipf has hosted numerous<br />undergraduate students from abroad in his group for research internships,<br />including 6 students from Uruguay and 2 students from Thailand. He frequently travels to local undergraduate schools to present seminars and meets with groups of students that are not familiar with graduate programs to advis...]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[  Report for the General Public for Grant CHE-0910560, "Heterocyclic Chemistry of Bicyclo[1.1.0]butanes  The long-term objective of this Grant is to transform the current practice of heterocyclic chemistry by developing innovative metal-catalyzed processes that replace traditional, harsh and wasteful condensation protocols.  We designed new strategies taking advantage of the ready availability of the highly strained bicyclo[1.1.0]butanes as precursors for stereoselective carbon-carbon and carbon-heteroatom bond formations. Especially significant was the discovery of novel, one-pot cascade reactions that convert simple starting materials into structurally diverse heterocyclic building blocks. These compunds are significant for the pharmaceutical industry, since they allow medicinal chemists to expand on the diversity of their biologically active agents, as well as for the general field of chemistry, since new materials require tailored building blocks with novel properties. New structural diversity will likely increase the number and utility of small molecule modulators of biological functions, access new intellectual property (IP) space, and stimulate a more creative deployment of the organic chemistry toolset to solve challenges in biology and medicine.  While initial hits might be more rapidly identified in traditional assays of libraries rich in privileged chemotypes, as they are routinely performed in pharmaceutical and biotech companies, novel scaffolds showcase the value of an innovative chemistry program, increase the opportunities for the discovery of new biological phenotypes, and bear greater patent value for a platform approach.  Broad Impact Activities:   Over the last 4 years, 36 undergraduates (28 women) and 2 high school students (1 woman) participated in research in the Wipf group. During this period, 5 papers with undergraduate coauthors were published. The majority of these students have gone on to graduate school or medical school, while 4 are still in our undergraduate program. The graduate education of 5 students (1 woman) was partly or fully supported by NSF funds. One of these students is currently performing postdoctoral research at Princeton (Filip Petronijevic) and 1 has started a tenure track Assistant Professor position at the University of Colorado at Boulder (Macej Walczak). The postdoctoral work of Michael Yang, was partly supported by funds from the NSF award. He is currently a staff scientist at Evonik Degussa. In summary, the group has an outstanding track record in training high school, undergraduate and graduate students, and postdoctoral fellows.  Outreach: Over the last 5 years, Wipf has presented ca. 150 invited talks at international and national conferences, departmental colloquiums, and pharmaceutical, biotech and chemical companies. Wipf has been a member of the Organizing Committee of two international conferences and served as a program co-chair of the ACS National Medicinal Chemistry Symposium and the local ACS meeting in Pittsburgh in 2014. He served or is currently serving on &gt;20 advisory or editorial boards, including an Associate Editorship of ACS Med. Chem. Lett. He is also currently on the Board of Directors of Organic Reactions and Organic Syntheses, and he was elected to be the Chair of the Pharmaceutical Sciences Section of the American Association for the Advancement of Science (AAAS) in 2016. Wipf has hosted numerous undergraduate students from abroad in his group for research internships, including 6 students from Uruguay and 2 students from Thailand. He frequently travels to local undergraduate schools to present seminars and meets with groups of students that are not familiar with graduate programs to advise them on research and professional opportunities (the next upcoming visit to a predominantly undergraduate College is scheduled for 1/23/2015 at St. Vincent College). During the funding period of this NSF project, he presented numerous lecture on bicyclobutanes ...]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
