<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Nitrene Transfer Reactions with Iron Complexes</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2009</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2013</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>430000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>430000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03090005</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CHE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Chemistry</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Timothy Patten</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>tpatten@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927196</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The Inorganic, Bioinorganic, and Organometallic Chemistry Program supports the efforts of Professor Patrick L. Holland of the University of Rochester and Professor Brian Edelbach of Monroe Community College for the investigation of three- and four-coordinate iron-nitrene complexes. Their research shows the influence of the coordination number and geometry of a metal on the rate of hydrogen atom abstraction by the nitrene fragment. Oxidation-resistant supporting ligands are designed to enable spectroscopic and crystallographic studies on the reactive nitrene complexes. These studies lead to new designs for amination and other catalytic reactions of iron. Undergraduate students from Monroe Community College participate in summer research at the University of Rochester. These students contribute to the synthesis of new ligands and gain exposure to cutting-edge inorganic chemistry. The catalytic chemistry of iron provides an inexpensive alternative to toxic, expensive heavy metal catalysts, and thus this research provides a pathway to cheaper, safer routes to useful chemicals. &lt;br/&gt;</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>09/01/2009</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/30/2011</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>0911314</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Patrick L.</FirstName>
<LastName>Holland</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Patrick L. Holland</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>patrick.holland@yale.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2034325162</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000273907</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/01/2009</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Brian</FirstName>
<LastName>Edelbach</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>L</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Brian L Edelbach</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>bedelbach@monroecc.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5852922391</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000383286</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/01/2009</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Rochester</Name>
<CityName>Rochester</CityName>
<ZipCode>146270140</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5852754031</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>518 HYLAN, RC BOX 270140</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>25</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NY25</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>041294109</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF ROCHESTER</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>041294109</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Rochester]]></Name>
<CityName>Rochester</CityName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<ZipCode>146270140</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[518 HYLAN, RC BOX 270140]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>25</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NY25</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1966</Code>
<Text>SYNTHETIC INORGANIC</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>0000</Code>
<Text>UNASSIGNED</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1401</Code>
<Text>CATALYSIS AND BIOCATALYSIS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>OTHR</Code>
<Text>OTHER RESEARCH OR EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0109</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0111</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2009~268000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2011~162000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>This project increased chemists' knowledge about the world around us, and also trained budding scientists. From the knowledge perspective, we developed new chemical compounds (composed of iron and other atoms) that are capable of breaking carbon-hydrogen bonds. Breaking C-H bonds selectively is a major challenge in chemistry, and helps chemists to convert petroleum resources into functional materials. We published ten papers on various aspects of the iron compounds, their reactions, and the details of how they work. This research was primarily done by graduate and undergraduate students, many of whom are using their training to become independent researchers in their own right.</p> <p>Another important part of the project was to involve bright students from a local community college, who otherwise would not have had the opportunity to do research or experience life in a lab doing cutting-edge research. These students from Monroe Community College came to the University of Rochester for ten weeks over the summer, and worked toward new organic and organometallic compounds. One paper was published with these valuable coworkers, and many of them are pursuing scientific careers. This grant also contributed to the intellectual development of several hardworking Ph.D. trainees, who are now involved in scientific careers in the United States.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 09/05/2013<br>      Modified by: Patrick L.&nbsp;Holland</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ This project increased chemists' knowledge about the world around us, and also trained budding scientists. From the knowledge perspective, we developed new chemical compounds (composed of iron and other atoms) that are capable of breaking carbon-hydrogen bonds. Breaking C-H bonds selectively is a major challenge in chemistry, and helps chemists to convert petroleum resources into functional materials. We published ten papers on various aspects of the iron compounds, their reactions, and the details of how they work. This research was primarily done by graduate and undergraduate students, many of whom are using their training to become independent researchers in their own right.  Another important part of the project was to involve bright students from a local community college, who otherwise would not have had the opportunity to do research or experience life in a lab doing cutting-edge research. These students from Monroe Community College came to the University of Rochester for ten weeks over the summer, and worked toward new organic and organometallic compounds. One paper was published with these valuable coworkers, and many of them are pursuing scientific careers. This grant also contributed to the intellectual development of several hardworking Ph.D. trainees, who are now involved in scientific careers in the United States.       Last Modified: 09/05/2013       Submitted by: Patrick L. Holland]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
