<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Fundamental Gas-Phase Properties of Non-Protein Amino Acids and Non-Protein Amino Acid - Containing Peptides</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2009</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2014</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>300000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>300000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03090004</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CHE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Chemistry</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Colby Foss</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>cfoss@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032925327</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>In this award, funded by the Experimental Physical Chemistry Program, Professor Poutsma from College of William and Mary and his students will investigate amino acids and their gas phase ion chemistry. The first goal is to understand the subtle interplay between the structure of amino acids and their gas-phase energetic properties. The researchers will focus on the gas phase thermochemistry of so-called non-protein amino acids (NPAA), many of which  are toxic to humans and other animals in part due to structural similarity to one or more of the twenty common protein amino acids (PAA). Absolute gas-phase thermochemical properties will be determined for naturally-occurring non-protein amino acids (NPAA) as compared to their PAA counterparts, both as isolated amino acids and when incorporated into small peptides.&lt;br/&gt;The second goal focuses on the effects of NPAA-substitution into small peptides which will be accomplished by studying fragmentation patterns of PAA peptides and their NPAA analogs.  There is biological relevance to this project in that many NPAA can mis-incorporate into peptides and proteins. Detailed knowledge of any unusual fragmentation behavior for peptides containing NPAAs will be necessary in order to interpret mass spectra from both top-down and bottom-up proteomics experiments.  The ultimate goal is to better understand the mechanisms for "selective" fragmentations in low-energy tandem mass spectrometry experiments that lead to incomplete sequence coverage for the peptide of interest.  &lt;br/&gt;The main function of a primarily undergraduate chemistry department is the preparation of future generations of scientists. At the College of William and Mary, this charge is accomplished through both classroom teaching and undergraduate research. Since over eighty percent of the College's chemistry majors perform undergraduate research, over the three years of this award it is anticipated that 15-20 undergraduate students will perform research in Professor Poutsma's laboratory.  Based on current demographics, approximately one-half of these students will be either female or a member of an underrepresented group.&lt;br/&gt;</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>09/06/2009</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/14/2010</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>0911244</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>John</FirstName>
<LastName>Poutsma</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>C</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>John C Poutsma</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>jcpout@wm.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>7572212548</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000348265</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/06/2009</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>College of William and Mary</Name>
<CityName>Williamsburg</CityName>
<ZipCode>231878795</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>7572213966</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>Office of Sponsored Programs</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[P.O. Box 8795]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Virginia</StateName>
<StateCode>VA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>VA02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>074762238</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>COLLEGE OF WILLIAM &amp; MARY, THE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>074762238</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[College of William and Mary]]></Name>
<CityName>Williamsburg</CityName>
<StateCode>VA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>231878795</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[Office of Sponsored Programs]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Virginia</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>VA02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1962</Code>
<Text>SPECTROSCOPY</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>0000</Code>
<Text>UNASSIGNED</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1982</Code>
<Text>BIOLOGICAL CHEMISTRY</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>OTHR</Code>
<Text>OTHER RESEARCH OR EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0109</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0110</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2009~100000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2010~200000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>During the course of our award period, my group continued our efforts to further understand the relationship between the structure of amino acids and their chemical properties.&nbsp; Amino acids are fundamental biological building blocks and great effort has been made to understand their properties.&nbsp; The twenty essential or "protein amino acids" that are used to form proteins have been widely studied, but when I began my research program 15 years ago, some of their most fundamental properties had not been completely agreed upon.&nbsp; Over the course o fthe last nine years, we have added to the growing body of literature on the fundamental acid/base properties of both the twenty protein amino acid, and a wide variety of their structural analogs, the non-protein amino acids.&nbsp; Many of these NPAAs are toxic to humans and are thought to cause diseases due to their ability to compete with PAAs in biochemical processes.&nbsp; The differences in fundamental chemical properties between PAAs and their structural analogs can be used by other researchers to design experiments to identify and quantify these important biological compounds in nature.</p> <p>In addition to the scientific merit of our work, we have also contributed to the training of the future generation of scientists.&nbsp; My research program is built around undergraduate researchers, many of whom start during their freshman year and continue for four full years.&nbsp; They take part in all aspects of the project from experiment planning to data collection and analysis to manuscript and presentation preparation in order to disseminate our results to the chemical community.&nbsp; During the 5 year cycle of this award, twenty five different undergraduate students worked on projects outlined in the original proposal.&nbsp; Most of them have continued their academic training in either chemistry graduate school or other post-graduate study.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 09/17/2014<br>      Modified by: John&nbsp;C&nbsp;Poutsma</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ During the course of our award period, my group continued our efforts to further understand the relationship between the structure of amino acids and their chemical properties.  Amino acids are fundamental biological building blocks and great effort has been made to understand their properties.  The twenty essential or "protein amino acids" that are used to form proteins have been widely studied, but when I began my research program 15 years ago, some of their most fundamental properties had not been completely agreed upon.  Over the course o fthe last nine years, we have added to the growing body of literature on the fundamental acid/base properties of both the twenty protein amino acid, and a wide variety of their structural analogs, the non-protein amino acids.  Many of these NPAAs are toxic to humans and are thought to cause diseases due to their ability to compete with PAAs in biochemical processes.  The differences in fundamental chemical properties between PAAs and their structural analogs can be used by other researchers to design experiments to identify and quantify these important biological compounds in nature.  In addition to the scientific merit of our work, we have also contributed to the training of the future generation of scientists.  My research program is built around undergraduate researchers, many of whom start during their freshman year and continue for four full years.  They take part in all aspects of the project from experiment planning to data collection and analysis to manuscript and presentation preparation in order to disseminate our results to the chemical community.  During the 5 year cycle of this award, twenty five different undergraduate students worked on projects outlined in the original proposal.  Most of them have continued their academic training in either chemistry graduate school or other post-graduate study.       Last Modified: 09/17/2014       Submitted by: John C Poutsma]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
