<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>HCC-Small: Collaborative Research: Assessing Technology Requirements for Preventing Teamwork Errors in Safety-Critical Settings</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/15/2009</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2012</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>73967.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>80092</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>05020000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>CSE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>IIS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Information &amp; Intelligent Systems</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Kevin Crowston</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The staff in trauma centers are faced with complex problems under time pressure.&lt;br/&gt;Despite the introduction of standard protocols, the diversity of injuries that can occur&lt;br/&gt;requires a coordinated approach to the evaluation and treatment for each patient.&lt;br/&gt;Trauma care involves complex teamwork under time pressure, and teamwork errors&lt;br/&gt;endanger patient care and increase costs. Our proposed ethnographic study will use&lt;br/&gt;observation and detailed analysis of video recordings of trauma resuscitations to&lt;br/&gt;determine the nature and extent of teamwork errors in a trauma center. This detailed&lt;br/&gt;study of complex teamwork will uncover the causes of teamwork errors in collaborative&lt;br/&gt;high-risk environments. Methods will be developed to understand how teams work and&lt;br/&gt;where difficulties arise. This work will yield detailed descriptions of errors and their&lt;br/&gt;causes, a taxonomy of teamwork errors, information on how to improve team&lt;br/&gt;performance, and guides to the use of technology for teamwork support. It extends the&lt;br/&gt;level of detail of ethnographic research so that we can achieve precision in the&lt;br/&gt;understanding of procedures which are difficult to monitor automatically but where&lt;br/&gt;step-by-step records are essential to detect the causes of errors.&lt;br/&gt;Understanding and improving the effectiveness of trauma teams has direct benefit to&lt;br/&gt;society. Further, complex collaborations are ubiquitous in modern enterprises and these&lt;br/&gt;results could improve collaborations both in terms of quality and productivity across&lt;br/&gt;organizations. In addition, this work will serve to develop the skills needed by a new&lt;br/&gt;cadre of researchers with knowledge of computer-supported collaborative work,&lt;br/&gt;video-content analysis and cooperative research.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>09/21/2009</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/29/2010</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.070</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>0915899</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Randall</FirstName>
<LastName>Burd</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>S</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Randall S Burd</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>rburd@cnmc.org</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2024766704</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000105457</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/21/2009</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>David</FirstName>
<LastName>Stockwell</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>David Stockwell</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>dstockwe@cnmc.org</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2028844021</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000521359</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/21/2009</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Children's Research Institute</Name>
<CityName>Washington, D.C.</CityName>
<ZipCode>200102970</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>3015658483</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>111 Michigan Avenue, NW</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>District of Columbia</StateName>
<StateCode>DC</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>00</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>DC00</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>143983562</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>CHILDREN'S RESEARCH INSTITUTE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>606977783</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Children's Research Institute]]></Name>
<CityName>Washington, D.C.</CityName>
<StateCode>DC</StateCode>
<ZipCode>200102970</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[111 Michigan Avenue, NW]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>District of Columbia</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>00</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>DC00</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<FoaInformation>
<Code>0116000</Code>
<Name>Human Subjects</Name>
</FoaInformation>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7367</Code>
<Text>HCC-Human-Centered Computing</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7367</Code>
<Text>Cyber-Human Systems</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7923</Code>
<Text>SMALL PROJECT</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7924</Code>
<Text>MEDIUM PROJECT</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9215</Code>
<Text>HIGH PERFORMANCE COMPUTING SYSTEMS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9251</Code>
<Text>REU SUPP-Res Exp for Ugrd Supp</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>HPCC</Code>
<Text>HIGH PERFORMANCE COMPUTING &amp; COMM</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0109</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0110</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2009~73967</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2010~6125</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>In complex, high-reliability work settings, most human work is performed by teams rather than by individuals. This teamwork is characterized by division of labor, mutual aid, and cooperative decision-making that can lead to errors. Understanding the nature and extent of human errors in complex work settings can suggest improved procedures new technologies that decrease errors. In the current proposal, we studied the work of multidisciplinary medical teams conducting the initial evaluation and management of injured patients in the emergency department (&ldquo;trauma resuscitation&rdquo;).&nbsp; Despite an important link between team performance and patient outcomes, this domain has few available technologies to support the work of teams. Trauma resuscitation serves as an example domain for studying and identifying the information needs of teams and evaluating the potential impact of new technologies in a complex work setting.</p> <p>During the funding period, we conducted several major studies.</p> <p><strong>1. Measures of leadership qualities during trauma resuscitation:</strong> The optimal qualities for leaders conducting trauma resuscitation were identified from surveys of team members and included the ability to provide a pre-event preparation of the team, the ability to prioritize and provide overviews of the event during its conduct and the ability to delegate tasks while maintaining respect for team members and their contributions.</p> <p><strong>2. Development of a digital capture and peripheral display system using digital pen and paper technology:</strong> Digital pen technology is an approach that allows users to write with ink on paper but captures the strokes of this writing for compute analysis. We developed a prototype system that uses a digital pen to capture information entered on a standard event form used during trauma resuscitation and then processes and presents this information on a large screen display. We tested this system in simulated trauma resuscitations and found to be a feasible approach for providing teams with information that is now only captured on a paper form. A key finding was that the information needs of different roles on the team varied, requiring that future design of the system incorporate these needs to be most effective.</p> <p><strong>3. Analysis of decision making tasks during trauma resuscitation</strong>: Interviews and video review was used to determine the decision making processes used by trauma team leaders. Four aspects of the trauma resuscitation environment were identified that complicate decision making: system complexity and diagnostic uncertainty, communication breakdowns, information reliability and the severity of patient injury. These findings suggested ways in which new information technology can facilitate decision making: providing more information about the patient, engaging other team members in the room and remote specialists and enabling comparison with past similar cases.</p> <p><strong>4. Analysis of visual attention of trauma teams through vital sign monitor use: </strong>A monitor in the trauma resuscitation area displays information about the patient&rsquo;s vitals signs that are needed for patient management, including the heart rate, blood pressure and respiratory rate. Analysis of the frequency and duration that team members look at the monitor give key insight into the information behaviors and needs of team members. We made several key findings using video analysis of trauma resuscitations: short looks at the monitor occur throughout the event and likely serve as background activity for maintaining awareness of the patient status, short looks increase in frequency during critical phases of the event, and longer interval looks at the monitor corresponded with key phases in which team members were making decisions about diagnoses and major treatments.</p> <p><strong>5. Measures of workloa...]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ In complex, high-reliability work settings, most human work is performed by teams rather than by individuals. This teamwork is characterized by division of labor, mutual aid, and cooperative decision-making that can lead to errors. Understanding the nature and extent of human errors in complex work settings can suggest improved procedures new technologies that decrease errors. In the current proposal, we studied the work of multidisciplinary medical teams conducting the initial evaluation and management of injured patients in the emergency department ("trauma resuscitation").  Despite an important link between team performance and patient outcomes, this domain has few available technologies to support the work of teams. Trauma resuscitation serves as an example domain for studying and identifying the information needs of teams and evaluating the potential impact of new technologies in a complex work setting.  During the funding period, we conducted several major studies.  1. Measures of leadership qualities during trauma resuscitation: The optimal qualities for leaders conducting trauma resuscitation were identified from surveys of team members and included the ability to provide a pre-event preparation of the team, the ability to prioritize and provide overviews of the event during its conduct and the ability to delegate tasks while maintaining respect for team members and their contributions.  2. Development of a digital capture and peripheral display system using digital pen and paper technology: Digital pen technology is an approach that allows users to write with ink on paper but captures the strokes of this writing for compute analysis. We developed a prototype system that uses a digital pen to capture information entered on a standard event form used during trauma resuscitation and then processes and presents this information on a large screen display. We tested this system in simulated trauma resuscitations and found to be a feasible approach for providing teams with information that is now only captured on a paper form. A key finding was that the information needs of different roles on the team varied, requiring that future design of the system incorporate these needs to be most effective.  3. Analysis of decision making tasks during trauma resuscitation: Interviews and video review was used to determine the decision making processes used by trauma team leaders. Four aspects of the trauma resuscitation environment were identified that complicate decision making: system complexity and diagnostic uncertainty, communication breakdowns, information reliability and the severity of patient injury. These findings suggested ways in which new information technology can facilitate decision making: providing more information about the patient, engaging other team members in the room and remote specialists and enabling comparison with past similar cases.  4. Analysis of visual attention of trauma teams through vital sign monitor use: A monitor in the trauma resuscitation area displays information about the patientÆs vitals signs that are needed for patient management, including the heart rate, blood pressure and respiratory rate. Analysis of the frequency and duration that team members look at the monitor give key insight into the information behaviors and needs of team members. We made several key findings using video analysis of trauma resuscitations: short looks at the monitor occur throughout the event and likely serve as background activity for maintaining awareness of the patient status, short looks increase in frequency during critical phases of the event, and longer interval looks at the monitor corresponded with key phases in which team members were making decisions about diagnoses and major treatments.  5. Measures of workload during trauma resuscitation: Understanding the perceived workload of different team members is needed to examine the burden of work for each team member and for identifying approaches for decreas...]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
