<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Collaborative Research: TLS: An Experimental Producer Price Index for Clinical Trials</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/15/2009</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2011</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>120411.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>169870</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>04000000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>SBE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>SBE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Joshua Rosenbloom</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Project Description.&lt;br/&gt;This research project studies the feasibility of constructing price indexes specifically for clinical trials, an important component of healthcare R&amp;D.  Increasing health care R&amp;D spending is an important policy issue, but changes in expenditure are very difficult to evaluate without knowing whether these increases are due to changes in the prices of inputs to biomedical research, as opposed to changes in the quantity of research being performed.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Intellectual Merit&lt;br/&gt;The project constructs a "price deflator" that decomposes growth in total expenditure into price and quantity components.  Very few of these price indexes have been constructed specifically for scientific research, not least because R&amp;D activities tend to be highly heterogeneous, and therefore difficult to compare meaningfully year-to-year or across different contexts.  Sufficiently detailed data make it possible both to make price comparisons that hold constant factors such as the stage of clinical development, therapeutic area, and number of patients, and to control for the complexity and work burden associated with different trial designs,  The methodology that is used "hedonic price analysis" has been well-established in many areas, such as constructing deflators for IT products, but not has not previously been applied to scientific research activity.  These price indexes, combined with data on clinical trial activity published in public registries such as clinicaltrials.gov, allow the construction of broad-based estimates of clinical trial expenditures broken out by state, country, and type of R&amp;D performer.  &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Broader Impact.&lt;br/&gt;Along with evidence on the evolution of the price of clinical research, this project sheds light on a number of methodological issues relating to the integration of R&amp;D investment into the national income accounts, and informs important policy debates surrounding the "outsourcing" and "offshoring" of US R&amp;D, and the global competitiveness of American medical research establishments.  Clinical trials are increasingly being performed outside traditional US academic medical centers, at physicians' offices, clinics, and provider networks, as well as by specialized for-profit entities.  Moreover, trials have become increasingly global, with a single protocol collecting data from sites in many different countries.  These new features of clinical trials are one example of broader changes under way in the distribution of R&amp;D activity across geographies, actors, and institutions.  This research project helps develop a better understanding of the economic forces underlying this phenomenon.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This approach can be used by BEA and other agencies in developing estimates of the impact of R&amp;D on real and nominal gross domestic product, even at the state or regional level, which is very difficult to do with current data.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/14/2009</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/29/2010</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.075</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>0915677</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Iain</FirstName>
<LastName>Cockburn</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>M</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Iain M Cockburn</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>cockburn@bu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6173533775</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000091484</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/14/2009</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Trustees of Boston University</Name>
<CityName>BOSTON</CityName>
<ZipCode>022151300</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6173534365</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>881 COMMONWEALTH AVE</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
<StateCode>MA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MA07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>049435266</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>TRUSTEES OF BOSTON UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>049435266</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Trustees of Boston University]]></Name>
<CityName>BOSTON</CityName>
<StateCode>MA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>022151300</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[881 COMMONWEALTH AVE]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MA07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7626</Code>
<Text>SciSIP-Sci of Sci Innov Policy</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>J256</Code>
<Text/>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>0000</Code>
<Text>UNASSIGNED</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>OTHR</Code>
<Text>OTHER RESEARCH OR EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0109</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0110</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2009~120411</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2010~49459</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>A large part of the cost of developing new medical treatments is clinical research: testing of new drug candidates or medical devices in clinical trials. &nbsp;Costs of conducting these trials have risen substantially over recent decades, raising serious concerns about the rate of return to investment in biomedical research. &nbsp;But the root causes of this increased expenditure are poorly understood. &nbsp;In this project, we investigate the feasibility of decomposing the rate of change in total expenditures on clinical trials into two components, that which is due to increases in the prices of the inputs of clinical research, and that part which is due to increases in the amount of inputs used. &nbsp;</p> <p>To do this, we conducted an econometric analysis of detailed data on over 200,000 contracts between trial sponsors (typically, but not always, a pharmaceutical company or an organization working on its behalf) and clinical investigators, who are the doctors or clinics who enroll patients into the trial and do the actual administration of the treatment and measurement of patient outcomes. &nbsp;Between 1989 and 2010 the average nominal price per patient paid by trial sponsors (i.e. not adjusted for inflation) in these contracts rose 4.5 times, much faster than the NIH's Biomedical R&amp;D Price Index which rose just over 2-fold during the same period. &nbsp;Our analysis shows that the difference is largely due to increases in the effort and complexity of the work required of investigators. &nbsp;After controlling for "site work effort" (a measure of time, resource, and difficulty of conducting the trial protocol)&nbsp;and other factors such as the disease being treated, whether the trial was early stage or late stage, the location of the investigator, and the &nbsp;we find that costs rose at a rate almost identical to the BRDPI index, which is based on tracking input costs such as salaries and lab equipment.&nbsp;&nbsp;This finding contributes to our understanding of the underlying causes of the increased cost of developing new medical treatements: state of the art clinical research is becoming much more resource intensive, as well as more expensive on a per-unit basis.</p> <p>An additional goal of this study was to investigate the usefulness of this type of commercial database, which was gathered by MediData Solutions Inc., to the US government agencies charged with measuring inflation in R&amp;D costs. &nbsp;Market transactions in &nbsp;R&amp;D services, of which this type of activity are a good example, are not easy to observe in the types of data that these agencies collect directly. &nbsp;This study shows that this type of commercial data source can provide valuable input to measurement of inflation, and may be very helpful to these agencies in developing a Producer Price Index for R&amp;D services.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 07/12/2013<br>      Modified by: Iain&nbsp;M&nbsp;Cockburn</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ A large part of the cost of developing new medical treatments is clinical research: testing of new drug candidates or medical devices in clinical trials.  Costs of conducting these trials have risen substantially over recent decades, raising serious concerns about the rate of return to investment in biomedical research.  But the root causes of this increased expenditure are poorly understood.  In this project, we investigate the feasibility of decomposing the rate of change in total expenditures on clinical trials into two components, that which is due to increases in the prices of the inputs of clinical research, and that part which is due to increases in the amount of inputs used.    To do this, we conducted an econometric analysis of detailed data on over 200,000 contracts between trial sponsors (typically, but not always, a pharmaceutical company or an organization working on its behalf) and clinical investigators, who are the doctors or clinics who enroll patients into the trial and do the actual administration of the treatment and measurement of patient outcomes.  Between 1989 and 2010 the average nominal price per patient paid by trial sponsors (i.e. not adjusted for inflation) in these contracts rose 4.5 times, much faster than the NIH's Biomedical R&amp;D Price Index which rose just over 2-fold during the same period.  Our analysis shows that the difference is largely due to increases in the effort and complexity of the work required of investigators.  After controlling for "site work effort" (a measure of time, resource, and difficulty of conducting the trial protocol) and other factors such as the disease being treated, whether the trial was early stage or late stage, the location of the investigator, and the  we find that costs rose at a rate almost identical to the BRDPI index, which is based on tracking input costs such as salaries and lab equipment.  This finding contributes to our understanding of the underlying causes of the increased cost of developing new medical treatements: state of the art clinical research is becoming much more resource intensive, as well as more expensive on a per-unit basis.  An additional goal of this study was to investigate the usefulness of this type of commercial database, which was gathered by MediData Solutions Inc., to the US government agencies charged with measuring inflation in R&amp;D costs.  Market transactions in  R&amp;D services, of which this type of activity are a good example, are not easy to observe in the types of data that these agencies collect directly.  This study shows that this type of commercial data source can provide valuable input to measurement of inflation, and may be very helpful to these agencies in developing a Producer Price Index for R&amp;D services.       Last Modified: 07/12/2013       Submitted by: Iain M Cockburn]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
