<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>PFI: Wireless Grid Innovation Testbed</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2009</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2014</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>599262.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>801006</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07070000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>IIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Industrial Innovation &amp; Partnersh</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Sara B. Nerlove</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This Partnerships for Innovation (PFI) project--a Type II (A:B) partnership  between Syracuse University, an NSF PFI graduate (0227879, initiated at Tufts University), and Virginia Tech University, which is currently a research site of another NSF-supported partnership program: I/UCRC Wireless Internet Center for Advanced Technology (WICAT) (0809036)--is focused on the creation of the first national Wireless Grid Innovation Testbed (WGiT).  The project integrates prior knowledge and technology.  Scientists at universities will work with a consortium of private organizations in a laboratory with the resources to support open innovation and user-created innovations in a system that supports their capture, documentation, and improvement. The intellectual merit of this project lies in the innovative combination of grid networking and wireless networking. The ultimate vision of the wireless grid is that of an adaptive network with secure, inexpensive, and coordinated real-time access to dynamic, heterogeneous resources, across geographic, political and cultural boundaries without forsaking stability, transparency, scalability, control and flexibility. Better assessment of wireless grids technology, network performance, and user behavior will inform design, manufacturing and commercialization of next generation information and resource sharing innovations. The test bed will support training and courses related to innovation, wireless grids technologies and business/social impact opportunities. Students within a variety of courses from middle school through doctoral levels, as well as community workforce training programs, through work at the associated labs and in the field, will be given the opportunity of hands-on experience in the use of the wireless grid beta applications as they become available. Students will have the opportunity to develop their own wireless grid applications, building upon the open platform provided. New knowledge will be generated both on innovation models and entrepreneurial ecosystems, and on wireless grids. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The broader impact of wireless grid connectivity specifications developed with WGiT support will be determined ultimately by their utility to user and device communities. Open source developers interested in wireless grids distributed collaboration and network mash-up features will be significant early users. A wide range of new applications is expected across industry sectors and social communities. Businesses, government agencies and private individuals will have new options for interacting within and across regions. The testbed will provide students, faculty, firms, and representatives of government an opportunity to learn from and participate in the growth of this new market.  &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Partners at the inception of the project are Academic Institutions: Syracuse University (lead institution), Virginia Tech University, Tufts University, Massachusetts Institute of Technology, and Instituto Superior Technico (IST), Lisbon, Portugal;  Private Sector Organizations: Center for Advanced Engineering &amp; Research, Inc. (CAER); Clear Channel Radio; MOD-ECO; Qualcomm, SenSyr LLV; Syracuse Research Corporation (SRC); Wireless Grids Corporation (WGC); Governmental and Intergovernmental Organizations:  Knowledge Society Agency (UMIC) Ministry of Science, Technology and Higher Education, Portugal; and Organization for Economic Co-operation and Development (OECD), France.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/31/2009</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>09/11/2013</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>0917973</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Tamal</FirstName>
<LastName>Bose</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Tamal Bose</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>tbose@arizona.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5206216193</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000239802</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/31/2009</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Lee</FirstName>
<LastName>McKnight</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>W</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Lee W McKnight</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>lmcknigh@syr.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>3154436891</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000199097</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/31/2009</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Peter</FirstName>
<LastName>Wong</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>Y</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Peter Y Wong</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>pwong@rwu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6175890220</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000104704</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/31/2009</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Bruce</FirstName>
<LastName>Kingma</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Bruce Kingma</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>brkingma@syr.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>3154434525</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000316162</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/31/2009</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Craig</FirstName>
<LastName>Watters</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Craig Watters</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>crwatter@syr.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>3154432807</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000191159</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/31/2009</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Syracuse University</Name>
<CityName>SYRACUSE</CityName>
<ZipCode>132441200</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>3154432807</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>OFFICE OF SPONSORED PROGRAMS</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[211 Lyman Hall]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>24</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NY24</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>002257350</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>SYRACUSE UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>002257350</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Syracuse University]]></Name>
<CityName>SYRACUSE</CityName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<ZipCode>132441200</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[OFFICE OF SPONSORED PROGRAMS]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>24</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NY24</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<FoaInformation>
<Code>0116000</Code>
<Name>Human Subjects</Name>
</FoaInformation>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1504</Code>
<Text>GOALI-Grnt Opp Acad Lia wIndus</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1662</Code>
<Text>PFI-Partnrships for Innovation</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>0000</Code>
<Text>UNASSIGNED</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1049</Code>
<Text>INDUSTRY-UNIV COOPERATIVE RSCH PROJECTS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>115E</Code>
<Text>RESEARCH EXP FOR TEACHERS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>116E</Code>
<Text>RESEARCH EXP FOR UNDERGRADS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>117E</Code>
<Text>TECHNOLOGY INNOVATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1504</Code>
<Text>GRANT OPP FOR ACAD LIA W/INDUS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1662</Code>
<Text>PARTNRSHIPS FOR INNOVATION-PFI</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>5761</Code>
<Text>INDUSTRY/UNIV COOP RES CENTERS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7651</Code>
<Text>OTHER COLLABORATIONS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7744</Code>
<Text>RAHSS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9177</Code>
<Text>ELEMENTARY/SECONDARY EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9178</Code>
<Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9251</Code>
<Text>REU SUPP-Res Exp for Ugrd Supp</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>OTHR</Code>
<Text>OTHER RESEARCH OR EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>SMET</Code>
<Text>SCIENCE, MATH, ENG &amp; TECH EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0109</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0111</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0112</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0113</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2009~599262</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2011~144000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2012~47744</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2013~10000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Significant outcomes of the NSF Partnerships for Innovation project #<span class="st">0917973&nbsp; include its recognition as the</span> 'TACNY Technology Project of the Year.' Other outcomes of this PFI Wireless Grid Innovation Testbed (WiGiT), and its 'Best Thesis Prize'-winning Veterans Research Supplement, and its 'Top 3 Innovation of Year' (Emergency Management Magazine) Advanced Situational Awareness System (ASAS) project supplements, were also supported by National Science Foundation Research Assistantships for High School Students (RAHSS), Research Exeperiences for Undergradauates (REU) and Research Experiences for Teachers (RET) awards. Outcomes include the use of WiGiT innovations for cultural heritage  preservation, and requirements including security which were both evaulated in  the WiGiT testbed.</p> <p>Building a distributed experimental testbed with 100 partner  campuses,  companies, and communities including the Syracuse Center of  Excellence  in Energy and Environmental Systems, Virginia Tech, Tufts  University,  Rochester Institute of Technology, Massachusetts Institute  of  Technology, school districts, start-up, small and multinational  firms,  and the Organization for Economic Cooperation and Development  (OECD) was itself a significant outcome.</p> <p>Enabling thousands of high school and university students,  healthcare, emergency management and other professionals and partner  organizations to engage in experiential learning with cognitive radio  machine to machine ad hoc network and wireless grid edgeware application  demonstrations and testbed experiments. The WiGiT project was through its deistributed tesbed the first to invent, evaluate and test edgeware,  and determine technical requirements for a wireless grid. By defining  wireless grid open specifications or standards for business, educational  and social emergency response uses of edgeware and related tools and  techniques.&nbsp; 6 doctoral theses elaborating upon the impact on society  beyong science and technology of diverse use cases including healthcare  as a service, healthcare workplace as a service, workplace as a service,  as well as defining and demonstrating key components of an advanced  situational awareness system, as well as distributed and collaborative  learning in K-12 and university contexts with wireless grids.</p> <p>Additional key outcomes of the WiGit project are the the refining of open  standards (WiGiT Open Specs, or specifications) for wireless grid  technical requirements and applications in:</p> <p>- software defined radio/cognitive radio</p> <p>- 'worst case scenario' emergency communication</p> <p>- distributed energy and environment</p> <p>- collaborative high school, university and professional education with ambient information in a wireless grid</p> <p>and</p> <p>-  workplace as a service/Bring Your Own Device frameworks developed in cooperation  with the information technology industry standards group TM Forum and  its Enterprise Cloud Leadership Council.</p> <p>The outcomes of several exemplary WiGiT project research efforts are elaborated upon below, with much more information available in the dozens of articles published by project researchers.</p> <p>Developing and evaluating wireless grid edgeware applications and cognitive radio (software defined  radio) ad hoc infrastructureless network technology innovations for applications such as telemedicine professional training for Post Traumatic Stress Disorder and Traumatic Brain injury (TBi) care. A NSF Veterans Research  Supplement (VRS)-supported study of doctors, nurses, and other healthcare  professionals at 2 major military hospitals completed in 2014 confirmed  the value for users of WiGiT project inventions and innovations.&nbsp; At a 95% statistical confidence  level, Dr. Dale Meyerrose doctoral thesis study found that new edgeware applications enabling healthcare workplace as a  service ...]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Significant outcomes of the NSF Partnerships for Innovation project #0917973  include its recognition as the 'TACNY Technology Project of the Year.' Other outcomes of this PFI Wireless Grid Innovation Testbed (WiGiT), and its 'Best Thesis Prize'-winning Veterans Research Supplement, and its 'Top 3 Innovation of Year' (Emergency Management Magazine) Advanced Situational Awareness System (ASAS) project supplements, were also supported by National Science Foundation Research Assistantships for High School Students (RAHSS), Research Exeperiences for Undergradauates (REU) and Research Experiences for Teachers (RET) awards. Outcomes include the use of WiGiT innovations for cultural heritage  preservation, and requirements including security which were both evaulated in  the WiGiT testbed.  Building a distributed experimental testbed with 100 partner  campuses,  companies, and communities including the Syracuse Center of  Excellence  in Energy and Environmental Systems, Virginia Tech, Tufts  University,  Rochester Institute of Technology, Massachusetts Institute  of  Technology, school districts, start-up, small and multinational  firms,  and the Organization for Economic Cooperation and Development  (OECD) was itself a significant outcome.  Enabling thousands of high school and university students,  healthcare, emergency management and other professionals and partner  organizations to engage in experiential learning with cognitive radio  machine to machine ad hoc network and wireless grid edgeware application  demonstrations and testbed experiments. The WiGiT project was through its deistributed tesbed the first to invent, evaluate and test edgeware,  and determine technical requirements for a wireless grid. By defining  wireless grid open specifications or standards for business, educational  and social emergency response uses of edgeware and related tools and  techniques.  6 doctoral theses elaborating upon the impact on society  beyong science and technology of diverse use cases including healthcare  as a service, healthcare workplace as a service, workplace as a service,  as well as defining and demonstrating key components of an advanced  situational awareness system, as well as distributed and collaborative  learning in K-12 and university contexts with wireless grids.  Additional key outcomes of the WiGit project are the the refining of open  standards (WiGiT Open Specs, or specifications) for wireless grid  technical requirements and applications in:  - software defined radio/cognitive radio  - 'worst case scenario' emergency communication  - distributed energy and environment  - collaborative high school, university and professional education with ambient information in a wireless grid  and  -  workplace as a service/Bring Your Own Device frameworks developed in cooperation  with the information technology industry standards group TM Forum and  its Enterprise Cloud Leadership Council.  The outcomes of several exemplary WiGiT project research efforts are elaborated upon below, with much more information available in the dozens of articles published by project researchers.  Developing and evaluating wireless grid edgeware applications and cognitive radio (software defined  radio) ad hoc infrastructureless network technology innovations for applications such as telemedicine professional training for Post Traumatic Stress Disorder and Traumatic Brain injury (TBi) care. A NSF Veterans Research  Supplement (VRS)-supported study of doctors, nurses, and other healthcare  professionals at 2 major military hospitals completed in 2014 confirmed  the value for users of WiGiT project inventions and innovations.  At a 95% statistical confidence  level, Dr. Dale Meyerrose doctoral thesis study found that new edgeware applications enabling healthcare workplace as a  service delivery and use across mobile devices meet  the needs of healthcare professionals for private, secure and flexible  access to and use of information in a wireless gri...]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
