<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>The Molecular Basis of Cadherin-Mediated Cell Adhesion</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2009</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2014</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>1018445.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>1018445</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>08070400</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>BIO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>MCB</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Molecular and Cellular Bioscience</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Kamal Shukla</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The main objective of this project is to understand the molecular basis of cadherin-mediated cell-cell adhesion. Cadherins are a family of molecules that are located on the surfaces of many cells. When like cells come in contact they adhere to one another whereas cells of different types tend to separate. This crucial property, which allows different tissues in the body to form and to separate from one another, can be traced to the molecular properties of individual cadherin molecules. But different cadherin family members are all similar to one another. What mechanisms allow small molecular differences to mediate highly specific cellular behavior? To address these questions, binding affinities of wild type and designed mutant cadherins will be carried out with the goal of modifying their behavior in controlled ways. The experimental work will be based on the use of theoretical methods that will elucidate the molecular basis of cadherin binding.  The second stage of the project will focus on relating molecular to cellular properties. Once cells containing cadherins begin to adhere, the cadherins on each cell tend to cluster together to form junctions. Simulations will be carried out to clarify how this occurs and, based on the results that are obtained, new theoretical methods to simulate cellular processes will be developed. This research project represents an integrated research effort involving both theory and experiment and spans quite diverse disciplines including molecular modeling and simulation, structural biology, solution biophysics, and cell biology.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The project is multi-scale and interdisciplinary in nature and the strategy  that  is being developed can serve as a model for other such efforts that integrate computational methods in cutting edge areas of modern biology. A particularly important element of the project is the development of scientists with expertise in both computational and experimental work including joint mentoring from senior researchers with very different backgrounds. The training of women and minority scientists is an integral component of the research. The lab participates in the EXROP (Exceptional Research Opportunities) program organized by HHMI and, in this context, hosts minority undergraduate students each summer. Both undergraduate and graduate minority students trained in the lab have become highly successful research scientists.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project is jointly supported by the Biomolecular Systems and Cellular Systems Clusters in the Division of Molecular and Cellular Biosciences.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/23/2009</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>04/11/2013</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.074</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>0918535</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Barry</FirstName>
<LastName>Honig</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Barry Honig</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>bh6@columbia.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2128514651</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000157401</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/23/2009</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Columbia University</Name>
<CityName>NEW YORK</CityName>
<ZipCode>100276902</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2128546851</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>2960 Broadway</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>10</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NY10</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>049179401</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>TRUSTEES OF COLUMBIA UNIVERSITY IN THE CITY OF NEW YORK, THE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>049179401</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Columbia University Col of Physicians and Surgeons]]></Name>
<CityName>New York</CityName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<ZipCode>10032</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>15</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NY15</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<FoaInformation>
<Code>0000099</Code>
<Name>Other Applications NEC</Name>
</FoaInformation>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1114</Code>
<Text>Cellular Dynamics and Function</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1144</Code>
<Text>Molecular Biophysics</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1114</Code>
<Text>CELLULAR SYSTEMS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1164</Code>
<Text>MOLECULAR BIOPHYSICS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7465</Code>
<Text>NANOSCALE BIO CORE</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9183</Code>
<Text>GENERAL FOUNDATIONS OF BIOTECHNOLOGY</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>BIOT</Code>
<Text>BIOTECHNOLOGY</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0109</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0110</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0111</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0112</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0113</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2009~193016</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2010~198676</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2011~203697</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2012~208864</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2013~214192</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Numerous cell-cell adhesion processes are mediated by the dimerization and subsequent oligomerization of proteins presented from apposing cell surface. Cells must be able to recognize other cells to adhere to them in a specific fashion so as to form larger cell aggregates and tissues. Such cell-cell adhesive specificity can ultimately be traced to highly specific protein-protein interactions between cell surface adhesion receptors. The long range goal of our research is to understand the molecular basis of cell-cell recognition and, in doing so, &nbsp;to bridge the gap between molecular and cellular behavior. &nbsp;We have made significant progress in this direction with particular emphasis on adhesion mediated by type I cadherins. We have discovered protein design principles through which these cadherins bind to each other with finely tuned affinities and, based on both experiment and theory, have identified mechanisms through which cadherins assemble into junctions on cell surfaces following cell-cell contact. In the context of this work we have identified new physical mechanisms of quite general relevance.</p> <p>Our lab has a long history in developing software tools that have been widely adopted and this activity is still ongoing. With regard to the current proposal, the integrated computational/experimental strategy we are developing can serve as a model for other such efforts in the future. A particularly important element of this strategy is the development of scientists with expertise in both computational and experimental work.</p> <p>In terms of training, our lab has produced outstanding graduate students and postdocs, many of whom have gone on to highly successful scientific careers. Women scientists constitute about 50% of our lab and, along with all lab alumni, continue to obtain outstanding positions in industry and academia. We have also been particularly active in outreach to undergraduate minority students and high school students. This past summer we also hosted a minority undergraduate from the SPURS (Summer Program for Underrepresented Students) program at Columbia, and our lab participates regularly in the EXROP (Exceptional Research Opportunities) program organized by HHMI and, in this context, host minority students each summer.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 02/12/2015<br>      Modified by: Barry&nbsp;Honig</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Numerous cell-cell adhesion processes are mediated by the dimerization and subsequent oligomerization of proteins presented from apposing cell surface. Cells must be able to recognize other cells to adhere to them in a specific fashion so as to form larger cell aggregates and tissues. Such cell-cell adhesive specificity can ultimately be traced to highly specific protein-protein interactions between cell surface adhesion receptors. The long range goal of our research is to understand the molecular basis of cell-cell recognition and, in doing so,  to bridge the gap between molecular and cellular behavior.  We have made significant progress in this direction with particular emphasis on adhesion mediated by type I cadherins. We have discovered protein design principles through which these cadherins bind to each other with finely tuned affinities and, based on both experiment and theory, have identified mechanisms through which cadherins assemble into junctions on cell surfaces following cell-cell contact. In the context of this work we have identified new physical mechanisms of quite general relevance.  Our lab has a long history in developing software tools that have been widely adopted and this activity is still ongoing. With regard to the current proposal, the integrated computational/experimental strategy we are developing can serve as a model for other such efforts in the future. A particularly important element of this strategy is the development of scientists with expertise in both computational and experimental work.  In terms of training, our lab has produced outstanding graduate students and postdocs, many of whom have gone on to highly successful scientific careers. Women scientists constitute about 50% of our lab and, along with all lab alumni, continue to obtain outstanding positions in industry and academia. We have also been particularly active in outreach to undergraduate minority students and high school students. This past summer we also hosted a minority undergraduate from the SPURS (Summer Program for Underrepresented Students) program at Columbia, and our lab participates regularly in the EXROP (Exceptional Research Opportunities) program organized by HHMI and, in this context, host minority students each summer.       Last Modified: 02/12/2015       Submitted by: Barry Honig]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
