<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Collaborative Research:  MSB: Microbial control of litter decay at the cellulose-lignin interface</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/15/2009</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2014</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>631515.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>631515</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>08010209</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>BIO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DEB</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Environmental Biology</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Henry L. Gholz</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The key scientific significance of this work is the integration of microbial community and chemical interactions during the long-term degradation and stabilization of plant litter because there has not yet been a working synthesis of this knowledge expressed in a comprehensive quantitative framework.  Plant litter decomposition is the main control on soil fertility and carbon (C) sequestration. There is growing interest in understanding the conditions under which soils gain or lose C, in part, because soils contain more C than the atmosphere and could play either a moderating or exacerbating role in global warming. An integrated field, laboratory, and modeling study of the biochemical mechanisms driving interactions between soil C sequestration, plant litter chemistry, and microbial community composition and activity during decomposition is needed to define these relationships. Moorhead and Sinsabaugh (2006) developed a new model that incorporates microbial dynamics into the decomposition process, the Guild Decomposition Model (GDM), which has generated a series of specific hypotheses about the mechanisms controlling the interactions between plant litter chemistry, C stabilization and microbial community composition and activity during decomposition. The proposed research will evaluate these hypotheses experimentally by monitoring changes in plant litter chemistry and microbial community composition and function during decomposition, with and without added N to mimic N deposition. Stable C isotope (13C) labeling will further determine the community composition of active microorganisms capable of metabolizing specific chemical components of plant litter. This research will provide mechanistic insight into the impacts on plant litter decomposition and soil C sequestration from N deposition, elevated CO2, plant community composition shifts, and climate change. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;An integrated education and outreach program will complement this research, assisted by the University of Toledo's Center for Creative Instruction (CCI). For this project, the CCI will develop an online interactive Model Of Leaf Decomposition (iMold) to provide educational outreach about decomposition for grades 5-12.  Visitors will be able to visualize the progress of the decomposition of litter as a whole, or different individual litter chemical constituents, along a time line to see how time, litter type, and environment relate to how quickly or slowly something decays. Teachers and students will be able to network between researchers and classrooms at other schools, enabling them to share data, ask questions, and collaborate on experiments. A communication center will be created so that the researchers and classrooms can share ideas and results, as well as ask questions in a blog-like environment.  Additionally, this project will provide training for several undergraduate and graduate students. University of Toledo and Kent State University serve significant populations of underrepresented groups in science, and  they will be recruited to this project.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>09/02/2009</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/06/2011</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.074</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>0918718</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Daryl</FirstName>
<LastName>Moorhead</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>L</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Daryl L Moorhead</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>Daryl.Moorhead@UToledo.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>4195302017</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000275674</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/02/2009</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Michael</FirstName>
<LastName>Weintraub</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>N</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Michael N Weintraub</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>Michael.Weintraub@utoledo.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>4195302585</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000160267</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/02/2009</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Toledo</Name>
<CityName>TOLEDO</CityName>
<ZipCode>436063390</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>4195302844</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>2801 W Bancroft St., MS 218</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Ohio</StateName>
<StateCode>OH</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>09</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>OH09</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>051623734</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF TOLEDO, THE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>051623734</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Toledo]]></Name>
<CityName>TOLEDO</CityName>
<StateCode>OH</StateCode>
<ZipCode>436063390</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[2801 W Bancroft St., MS 218]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Ohio</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>09</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>OH09</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1181</Code>
<Text>ECOSYSTEM STUDIES</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1181</Code>
<Text>ECOSYSTEM STUDIES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9169</Code>
<Text>BIODIVERSITY AND ECOSYSTEM DYNAMICS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>EGCH</Code>
<Text>ENVIRONMENT AND GLOBAL CHANGE</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0109</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0110</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0111</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2009~214484</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2010~205164</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2011~211867</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p class="PreformattedText">Plant litter decomposition is the main control on soil fertility and carbon (C) sequestration. At present there is growing interest in understanding the conditions under which soils gain or lose C in part because soils actually contain more C than the atmosphere and could play a mitigating role in global warming. A complicating factor is concomitant atmospheric nitrogen (N) deposition because interactions between elevated atmospheric CO<sub>2</sub> and N deposition alter plant litter chemistry. In turn, changing litter chemistry, climate and N availability influence soil C by altering the interactions between microbial activity and plant litter during decomposition. However, neither the magnitude nor even the direction of microbial responses to these effects is predictable, because the mechanisms controlling decomposition are not well understood. Thus, our goal was to conduct an integrated field, laboratory, and modeling study of the biochemical mechanisms driving interactions between soil C sequestration, plant litter chemistry, and microbial community composition and activity during decomposition to define these relationships.<strong> </strong>It has long been hypothesized that predictable changes in microbial community composition and activity accompany changes in litter chemistry during decomposition, and that changes in nutrient availability affect decomposition by altering the composition and function of the microbial community. However, previous models of litter decay lack sufficient resolution to reproduce these patterns, particularly at late stages of decomposition when C is sequestered (stabilized). Moorhead and Sinsabaugh (2006) developed a new model that incorporates microbial dynamics into the decomposition process, the Guild Decomposition Model (GDM), which has generated a series of specific hypotheses about the mechanisms controlling the interactions between plant litter chemistry, C stabilization and microbial community composition and activity during decomposition. Our research evaluated these hypotheses experimentally by monitoring changes in plant litter chemistry and microbial community composition and function during decomposition, with and without added N to mimic N deposition. Microbial DNA labeling was used to determine the community composition of active microorganisms capable of metabolizing specific chemical components of plant litter. This research has provided mechanistic insight into the impacts on plant litter decomposition and soil C sequestration from N deposition, elevated CO<sub>2</sub>, plant community composition shifts, and climate change. The key scientific significance of this work is the integration of microbial community and chemical interactions during the long-term degradation and stabilization of plant litter because there had not yet been a working synthesis of this knowledge expressed in a comprehensive quantitative framework. The results of this research are already being used to improve predictions of changes in decomposition rates with climate change, nitrogen deposition, and other disturbances.</p> <p class="PreformattedText">Additionally, we collaborated with the University of Toledo&rsquo;s <a href="http://www.utoledo.edu/centers/cci/">Center for Creative Instruction</a> (CCI) to create a novel, professionally developed educational activity associated with this research. The CCI develops and disseminates educational information technology, and collaborates with many UT faculty and departments on web based educational initiatives, training applications, research studies, and the distribution of content and data. For this project, CCI personnel set up an online <strong>i</strong>nteractive <strong>m</strong>odel <strong>o</strong>f <strong>l</strong>eaf <strong>d</strong>ecomposition (<a href="http://imold.utoledo.edu/" target="_blank">IMOLD</a>;&nbsp;<a href="http://imold.utoledo.edu/" tar...]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[Plant litter decomposition is the main control on soil fertility and carbon (C) sequestration. At present there is growing interest in understanding the conditions under which soils gain or lose C in part because soils actually contain more C than the atmosphere and could play a mitigating role in global warming. A complicating factor is concomitant atmospheric nitrogen (N) deposition because interactions between elevated atmospheric CO2 and N deposition alter plant litter chemistry. In turn, changing litter chemistry, climate and N availability influence soil C by altering the interactions between microbial activity and plant litter during decomposition. However, neither the magnitude nor even the direction of microbial responses to these effects is predictable, because the mechanisms controlling decomposition are not well understood. Thus, our goal was to conduct an integrated field, laboratory, and modeling study of the biochemical mechanisms driving interactions between soil C sequestration, plant litter chemistry, and microbial community composition and activity during decomposition to define these relationships. It has long been hypothesized that predictable changes in microbial community composition and activity accompany changes in litter chemistry during decomposition, and that changes in nutrient availability affect decomposition by altering the composition and function of the microbial community. However, previous models of litter decay lack sufficient resolution to reproduce these patterns, particularly at late stages of decomposition when C is sequestered (stabilized). Moorhead and Sinsabaugh (2006) developed a new model that incorporates microbial dynamics into the decomposition process, the Guild Decomposition Model (GDM), which has generated a series of specific hypotheses about the mechanisms controlling the interactions between plant litter chemistry, C stabilization and microbial community composition and activity during decomposition. Our research evaluated these hypotheses experimentally by monitoring changes in plant litter chemistry and microbial community composition and function during decomposition, with and without added N to mimic N deposition. Microbial DNA labeling was used to determine the community composition of active microorganisms capable of metabolizing specific chemical components of plant litter. This research has provided mechanistic insight into the impacts on plant litter decomposition and soil C sequestration from N deposition, elevated CO2, plant community composition shifts, and climate change. The key scientific significance of this work is the integration of microbial community and chemical interactions during the long-term degradation and stabilization of plant litter because there had not yet been a working synthesis of this knowledge expressed in a comprehensive quantitative framework. The results of this research are already being used to improve predictions of changes in decomposition rates with climate change, nitrogen deposition, and other disturbances. Additionally, we collaborated with the University of ToledoÆs Center for Creative Instruction (CCI) to create a novel, professionally developed educational activity associated with this research. The CCI develops and disseminates educational information technology, and collaborates with many UT faculty and departments on web based educational initiatives, training applications, research studies, and the distribution of content and data. For this project, CCI personnel set up an online interactive model of leaf decomposition (IMOLD; http://imold.utoledo.edu/) to provide educational outreach about decomposition for grades 9-12. The IMOLD virtual environment includes: professionally narrated and animated lessons about C cycling, leaf anatomy and decomposition; decomposition model simulations in which students can explore interactions between leaf litter chemistry and climate; and lesson plans for teachers with learning objectiv...]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
