<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Flowers as complex signals:   The role of signal uncertainty</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/15/2009</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2014</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>420000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>420000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>08090500</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>BIO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>IOS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Integrative Organismal Systems</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Michelle Elekonich</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>melekoni@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927202</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Flowers have been of keen interest to humans throughout history, owing partly to the multitude of ways in which they stimulate our senses. Their brilliant colors, unusual patterns and shapes, and alluring fragrance enthrall humans and play a pivotal role in plant pollination. Surprisingly little is understood about why flowers are so complex, consisting of multiple components in multiple sensory modalities.  In this project, the function of the multi-component floral signal in pollination is explored, using an integrative approach that addresses the pollinator's sensory and cognitive abilities and limitations. The main thesis of the research is that complex, multi-component signals convey information from plant to pollinator more reliably than simpler signals. To address this thesis, a laboratory-based model system involving bumble bees (Bombus impatiens) learning to forage for nectar rewards associated with color, shape, pattern and odor stimuli will be employed. Tests of learning and floral choice are guided by predictions, based in psychological and economic theory, about how signal complexity will affect the speed and accuracy of a bee's foraging behavior.  Although the proposed work uses bees and flowers as a model system, the insights furnished by the work will contribute broadly to the study of animal communication and cognition. Additionally, results will contribute to a body of knowledge used to address an ongoing national crisis in crop pollination by bees. The project aims to mentor undergraduates from underrepresented groups and will include a bumble bee-oriented workshop on science careers targeted at high school students.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/01/2009</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/16/2011</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.074</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>0921280</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Daniel</FirstName>
<LastName>Papaj</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>R</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Daniel R Papaj</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>papaj@email.arizona.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5206218988</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000129018</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/01/2009</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Anna</FirstName>
<LastName>Dornhaus</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Anna Dornhaus</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>dornhaus@email.arizona.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5206268586</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000101917</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/01/2009</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Arizona</Name>
<CityName>Tucson</CityName>
<ZipCode>857194824</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5206266000</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>888 N Euclid Ave</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Arizona</StateName>
<StateCode>AZ</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>AZ03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>806345617</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF ARIZONA</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>072459266</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Arizona]]></Name>
<CityName>Tucson</CityName>
<StateCode>AZ</StateCode>
<ZipCode>857194824</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[888 N Euclid Ave]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Arizona</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>AZ03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<FoaInformation>
<Code>0000099</Code>
<Name>Other Applications NEC</Name>
</FoaInformation>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7659</Code>
<Text>Animal Behavior</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9179</Code>
<Text>GRADUATE INVOLVEMENT</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9183</Code>
<Text>GENERAL FOUNDATIONS OF BIOTECHNOLOGY</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>BIOT</Code>
<Text>BIOTECHNOLOGY</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0109</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0110</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0111</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2009~140000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2010~140000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2011~140000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Flowers have been described as &lsquo;sensory billboards&rsquo;, attracting pollinators using multiple cues in multiple sensory modalities including light, smell, taste, touch, and even temperature.&nbsp; Traditionally, research has focused on floral cues in one particular modality; how the cues work together to attract pollinators has received far less attention.&nbsp; Our project on bumble bee nectar foraging is devoted to the study of how different cues in the complex floral display act together to mediate pollen transfer by the bees. Our last efforts in this project involved refinement of an optimality model which predicts the combination of speed and accuracy that is optimal for a particular combination of floral components. Complex flowers having multiple components are predicted to cause the bee to forage at a different optimal combination of speed and accuracy than will simple flowers.&nbsp; In recent experiments, the Papaj laboratory examined the multimodal basis of orientation to flowers during buzz pollination. They determined that bees are attracted to the visual stimulus of the petals, but that sonication of the anthers is mainly a function of chemical stimuli.&nbsp; Experience with the flower results in the bee learning the visual stimulus of the anthers.</p> <p>Our experimental results and conceptual formulations pertain not only to how bees find flowers but to the use of complex signals in other behavioral contexts such as predation and reproduction.&nbsp; Moreover, our results pertain not only to non-human animals other than bees, but also to humans, whose perception of complex multiple signals has increasingly become the focus of research.</p> <p>In the final year of the grant, a graduate student was trained in the Papaj lab&nbsp; under the auspices of our funding.&nbsp; Approximately one dozen undergraduate students were trained in research as well, either for course credit or salary, including &nbsp; A significant proportion of our undergraduate assistants were women; additionally students from under-represented groups including Hispanics and Native Americans participated in research in the Papaj lab.&nbsp; Our research team sponsored three workshops on our science for high school women students.&nbsp; We also participated in the University of Arizona&rsquo;s Insect Festival, which drew 5,000-8,000 people, including a large number of school children.&nbsp; The Papaj lab's Pollinator Paradise booth offered information about pollination biology and conservation, and included live butterflies and bees as well as videos of bee behavior.&nbsp; The Papaj Lab additionally manned a booth at the Animal Behavior Society's Outreach Fair in Boulder, Colorado in 2013.&nbsp; The Papaj lab also sponsored the filming of bee behavior by professional videographers on three occasions; these videos are expected to appear in future science documentaries as well as our own presentations to the scientific community and lay public alike.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 11/10/2014<br>      Modified by: Daniel&nbsp;R&nbsp;Papaj</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Images (<span id="selectedPhoto0">1</span> of <span class="totalNumber"></span>)           </div> <div class="galControls" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2014/0921280/0921280_10028774_1413207676554_IMG_0938--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2014/0921280/0921280_10028774_1413207676554_IMG_0938--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Pollinator Paradise"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2014/0921280/0921280_10028774_1413207676554_IMG_0938--rgov-66x44.jpg"...]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Flowers have been described as æsensory billboardsÆ, attracting pollinators using multiple cues in multiple sensory modalities including light, smell, taste, touch, and even temperature.  Traditionally, research has focused on floral cues in one particular modality; how the cues work together to attract pollinators has received far less attention.  Our project on bumble bee nectar foraging is devoted to the study of how different cues in the complex floral display act together to mediate pollen transfer by the bees. Our last efforts in this project involved refinement of an optimality model which predicts the combination of speed and accuracy that is optimal for a particular combination of floral components. Complex flowers having multiple components are predicted to cause the bee to forage at a different optimal combination of speed and accuracy than will simple flowers.  In recent experiments, the Papaj laboratory examined the multimodal basis of orientation to flowers during buzz pollination. They determined that bees are attracted to the visual stimulus of the petals, but that sonication of the anthers is mainly a function of chemical stimuli.  Experience with the flower results in the bee learning the visual stimulus of the anthers.  Our experimental results and conceptual formulations pertain not only to how bees find flowers but to the use of complex signals in other behavioral contexts such as predation and reproduction.  Moreover, our results pertain not only to non-human animals other than bees, but also to humans, whose perception of complex multiple signals has increasingly become the focus of research.  In the final year of the grant, a graduate student was trained in the Papaj lab  under the auspices of our funding.  Approximately one dozen undergraduate students were trained in research as well, either for course credit or salary, including   A significant proportion of our undergraduate assistants were women; additionally students from under-represented groups including Hispanics and Native Americans participated in research in the Papaj lab.  Our research team sponsored three workshops on our science for high school women students.  We also participated in the University of ArizonaÆs Insect Festival, which drew 5,000-8,000 people, including a large number of school children.  The Papaj lab's Pollinator Paradise booth offered information about pollination biology and conservation, and included live butterflies and bees as well as videos of bee behavior.  The Papaj Lab additionally manned a booth at the Animal Behavior Society's Outreach Fair in Boulder, Colorado in 2013.  The Papaj lab also sponsored the filming of bee behavior by professional videographers on three occasions; these videos are expected to appear in future science documentaries as well as our own presentations to the scientific community and lay public alike.       Last Modified: 11/10/2014       Submitted by: Daniel R Papaj]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
