<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Collaborative Research: Thermal Contraction, Oceanic Intraplate Deformation, and Plate Circuit Closure</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2009</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2012</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>128791.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>134791</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>06040200</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>GEO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>OCE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Ocean Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Bilal U. Haq</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Plate tectonics - the discovery that the Earth's surface is composed of a mosaic of rigid plates in motion, and that most significant events such as earthquakes and volcanic eruptions occur along the plate boundaries ? is the single most important theory about how he Earth works. If plates are truly rigid, it follows that where three plates meet, the sum of their motions must be zero, but observations clearly demonstrate that this condition is not met. This unresolved problem is of fundamental importance to our understanding of plate tectonics. One possible explanation is that the shapes of plates are slightly modified by thermal contraction as they age. This project has the aim of testing that hypothesis by quantifying the effects of the thermal contraction in a re-evaluation of the Pacific-Cocos-Nazca and Pacific-North America plate circuits. The results will contribute to our understanding ofht e workings of the Earth. The project will support a young investigator, and a graduate student, and the results will be shared with students in their coursework and through educational outreach.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/25/2009</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/30/2010</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.050</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>0928961</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Richard</FirstName>
<LastName>Gordon</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Richard Gordon</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>rgg@rice.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>7133485279</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000440057</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/25/2009</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>William Marsh Rice University</Name>
<CityName>Houston</CityName>
<ZipCode>770051827</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>7133484820</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>6100 MAIN ST</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Texas</StateName>
<StateCode>TX</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>TX02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>050299031</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>WILLIAM MARSH RICE UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>050299031</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[William Marsh Rice University]]></Name>
<CityName>Houston</CityName>
<StateCode>TX</StateCode>
<ZipCode>770051827</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[6100 MAIN ST]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Texas</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>TX02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<FoaInformation>
<Code>0204000</Code>
<Name>Oceanography</Name>
</FoaInformation>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1620</Code>
<Text>Marine Geology and Geophysics</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>0000</Code>
<Text>UNASSIGNED</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9251</Code>
<Text>REU SUPP-Res Exp for Ugrd Supp</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>OTHR</Code>
<Text>OTHER RESEARCH OR EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0109</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0110</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2009~128791</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2010~6000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><span style="font-family: Arial,sans-serif;"><span style="font-size: small;">The advent of plate tectonics in the 1960s revolutionized Earth science and captured one's imagination.&nbsp; Plate tectonics&nbsp;transformed the way that we view planet Earth from a static view to a dynamic and mobile view of a solid Earth in continual motion with continual deformation.&nbsp;&nbsp; Deep in the solid Earth, deformation is broadly distributed and occurs in the solid state, by mechanisms analogous to those by which metals, such as lead, can be deformed at Earth's surface without producing fractures.  Shallow in the solid Earth, to a first approximation, deformation is localized at tectonic plate boundaries characterized by faulting, fracturing, and in many places earthquakes.</span></span></p> <p><span style="font-family: Arial,sans-serif;"><span style="font-size: small;">The central assumption&nbsp;of plate tectonics is that the tectonic plates (except at plate boundaries) are rigid.&nbsp;&nbsp; The rigor of plate tectonics and the ability to make predictions depends on this assumption.&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; Most, if not all, Earth scientists understand, however, that this assumptions is really just an approximation.   Within the limitations of our measurement techniques it has proved challenging to quantify the non-rigidity of the plates.</span></span></p> <p><span style="font-family: Arial,sans-serif;"><span style="font-size: small;">At the same time it has been recognized that oceanic lithosphere subsides as it ages due to the contraction of oceanic lithosphere as it cools.   The focus of our investigation has been to quantify the part of the non-rigidity of tectonic plates that is a consequence of this well-documented cooling and contraction with age, and to make new predictions that can be compared with observations.  Our work has involved both computer modeling and theoretical or mathematical derivations to obtain useful approximations of different aspects of this process.    The former has included both numerical integration of differential equations and calculations over dense grids to approximate plate-scale deformation.   An undergraduate student and two graduate students have participated in this project, giving them useful technical skills that can be applied in many areas of science and engineering.</span></span></p> <p><span style="font-family: Arial,sans-serif;"><span style="font-size: small;">Building on prior work by others based on  half-space conductive cooling models, we developed a mathematical description of the rate at which oceanic tectonic plates cool and contract as a function of age.   We applied it to determine the rates of strain due to cooling for oceanic lithosphere of various ages.   We further investigated the way in which these strains accumulate horizontally across oceanic plates to determine rates of displacement between different points on the same &ldquo;rigid&rdquo; tectonic plate.  Our main focus has been on the Pacific plate, which underlies most of the Pacific Ocean.</span></span></p> <p><span style="font-family: Arial,sans-serif;"><span style="font-size: small;">Also following prior workers, we have hypothesized that the valleys of transform faults widen with age due to cooling and contraction of the intervening oceanic lithosphere, and have predicted the rates at which the transform valleys widen.   We hypothesized that the widening of the valleys would affect the azimuths of the strike-slip faults within the valleys and made quantitative predictions of the changes in azimuths.   We compared these predictions with a global data set of observed azimuths of the transform faults and found that the global data were fit significantly better by our new predictions than by the &ldquo;old&rdquo; predictions that assume that tectonic plates are rigid.</span></span></p> <p><span style="font-family: Arial,sans-serif;"><span style="font-size: sm...]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The advent of plate tectonics in the 1960s revolutionized Earth science and captured one's imagination.  Plate tectonics transformed the way that we view planet Earth from a static view to a dynamic and mobile view of a solid Earth in continual motion with continual deformation.   Deep in the solid Earth, deformation is broadly distributed and occurs in the solid state, by mechanisms analogous to those by which metals, such as lead, can be deformed at Earth's surface without producing fractures.  Shallow in the solid Earth, to a first approximation, deformation is localized at tectonic plate boundaries characterized by faulting, fracturing, and in many places earthquakes.  The central assumption of plate tectonics is that the tectonic plates (except at plate boundaries) are rigid.   The rigor of plate tectonics and the ability to make predictions depends on this assumption.    Most, if not all, Earth scientists understand, however, that this assumptions is really just an approximation.   Within the limitations of our measurement techniques it has proved challenging to quantify the non-rigidity of the plates.  At the same time it has been recognized that oceanic lithosphere subsides as it ages due to the contraction of oceanic lithosphere as it cools.   The focus of our investigation has been to quantify the part of the non-rigidity of tectonic plates that is a consequence of this well-documented cooling and contraction with age, and to make new predictions that can be compared with observations.  Our work has involved both computer modeling and theoretical or mathematical derivations to obtain useful approximations of different aspects of this process.    The former has included both numerical integration of differential equations and calculations over dense grids to approximate plate-scale deformation.   An undergraduate student and two graduate students have participated in this project, giving them useful technical skills that can be applied in many areas of science and engineering.  Building on prior work by others based on  half-space conductive cooling models, we developed a mathematical description of the rate at which oceanic tectonic plates cool and contract as a function of age.   We applied it to determine the rates of strain due to cooling for oceanic lithosphere of various ages.   We further investigated the way in which these strains accumulate horizontally across oceanic plates to determine rates of displacement between different points on the same "rigid" tectonic plate.  Our main focus has been on the Pacific plate, which underlies most of the Pacific Ocean.  Also following prior workers, we have hypothesized that the valleys of transform faults widen with age due to cooling and contraction of the intervening oceanic lithosphere, and have predicted the rates at which the transform valleys widen.   We hypothesized that the widening of the valleys would affect the azimuths of the strike-slip faults within the valleys and made quantitative predictions of the changes in azimuths.   We compared these predictions with a global data set of observed azimuths of the transform faults and found that the global data were fit significantly better by our new predictions than by the "old" predictions that assume that tectonic plates are rigid.  These results help us to better understand several things about the Earth:  (1) They give us an improved understand of the tectonic setting of transform faults, along which many major earthquakes occur; (2) They illuminate what may be the main process by which lateral distances change between different points on tectonic plates.  (3) They quantify the predictable non-rigidity of tectonic plates and thus improve and deepen our understanding of plate tectonics.               Last Modified: 08/12/2013       Submitted by: Richard Gordon]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
