<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Oxide and Metal Nanoparticles-The Interface between Life Sciences and Physical Sciences</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2009</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2015</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>2700000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>2787500</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03070001</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DMR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Materials Research</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Daniele Finotello</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Oxide and Metal Nanoparticles: The Interface between Life Sciences and Physical Sciences &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The University of Texas at San Antonio (UTSA) studies interfacial relationships between nanomaterials and the life sciences through its Partnership for Research and Education in Materials (PREM) with the Materials Research Science and Engineering Center (MRSEC) at Northwestern University (NU) and the University of Texas Health Science Center at San Antonio (UTHSCSA).  The PREM creates a permanent relationship between these institutions to broaden and foster collaborative research and education in materials science. The research entails three principal components: 1) collaborative research in nanomaterials and their applications in various fields, 2) education and training for undergraduate and graduate students, especially, women and other underrepresented minority students, and 3) outreach program for K-12 students and teachers.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The research participants are focused in six thrust areas: 1) Rare Earth-based Dual Purpose Biosensor, 2) Medical Applications of Nanoparticles, 3) Novel Nanomaterials and their Applications in Biology, 4) Using Metal Nanoparticles in Neuroscience, 5) Terahertz Characterization of Nanomaterials for Biological Imaging Applications, and 6) Functionalization of Fibers Employing Low Temperature Pulsed Laser Deposition and Atomic Layer Deposition. This PREM establishes a unique and highly cohesive team enabled to investigate fundamental science questions in these specific thrust areas.   The NU-MRSEC plays a critical role in establishing and guiding the PREM program at UTSA, as the NU Materials Research laboratories provide infrastructure and support staff currently not available to UTSA undergraduate and graduate students engaged in these types of research areas.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/25/2009</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/08/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>0934218</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Dhiraj</FirstName>
<LastName>Sardar</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>K</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Dhiraj K Sardar</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>dhiraj.sardar@utsa.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2104585462</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000375894</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/25/2009</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Igal</FirstName>
<LastName>Szleifer</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>G</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Igal G Szleifer</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>igalsz@northwestern.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>8474670674</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000168516</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/25/2009</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Fidel</FirstName>
<LastName>Santamaria</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Fidel Santamaria</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>fidel.santamaria@utsa.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2104586910</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000083719</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/25/2009</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Xomalin</FirstName>
<LastName>Peralta</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>G</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Xomalin G Peralta</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>xomalin.peralta@utsa.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2104587901</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000527752</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/25/2009</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Texas at San Antonio</Name>
<CityName>San Antonio</CityName>
<ZipCode>782491644</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2104584340</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>One UTSA Circle</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[Grants, Contracts & Ind. Agr.]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Texas</StateName>
<StateCode>TX</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>20</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>TX20</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>800189185</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF TEXAS AT SAN ANTONIO, THE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>042000273</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Texas at San Antonio]]></Name>
<CityName>San Antonio</CityName>
<StateCode>TX</StateCode>
<ZipCode>782491644</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[One UTSA Circle]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Texas</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>20</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>TX20</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<FoaInformation>
<Code>0106000</Code>
<Name>Materials Research</Name>
</FoaInformation>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1253</Code>
<Text>OFFICE OF MULTIDISCIPLINARY AC</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7913</Code>
<Text>PREM</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1359</Code>
<Text>RET SITE-Res Exp for Tchr Site</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7209</Code>
<Text>NEXT GEN CHEM &amp; BIO SENSORS &amp; SENSING SY</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7237</Code>
<Text>NANO NON-SOLIC SCI &amp; ENG AWD</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7573</Code>
<Text>BIO-RELATED MATERIALS RESEARCH</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7608</Code>
<Text>PREM</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7644</Code>
<Text>ENERGY FOR SUSTAINABILITY</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7913</Code>
<Text>PREM</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9162</Code>
<Text>MULTI DIVISION/UNIVERSITY</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9178</Code>
<Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9250</Code>
<Text>REU SITE-Res Exp for Ugrd Site</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>AMPP</Code>
<Text>ADVANCED MATERIALS &amp; PROCESSING PROGRAM</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>SMET</Code>
<Text>SCIENCE, MATH, ENG &amp; TECH EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0109</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0110</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0111</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0112</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0113</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0114</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2009~600000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2010~720000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2011~370000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2012~505000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2013~505000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~87500</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><strong>PROJECT OUTCOMES:</strong></p> <p><strong>Award Number: 0934218; Project Title: Oxide and Metal Nanoparticles-The Interface between Life Sciences and Physical Sciences; PI: Dhiraj Sardar</strong></p> <p>The UTSA-PREm in partnership with NU-MRsec had been very active and successful in publishing a large number of research articles in highly respected journals, in graduating a large number of students, majority of whom are minority students, and more importantly, most of these students are gainfully employed at different sectors including academia. Here is the list of Outcomes of UTSA PREM:</p> <ol> <li>The PREM has helped UTSA accelerate its materials research capabilities significantly due to strong ties between UTSA and NU. The PREM has significantly impacted the Materials Research activities at UTSA and South Texas Region.</li> <li>The 5-year program supported a total of <strong>26</strong> PhD students and <strong>15</strong>&nbsp;undergraduate students. Among the <strong>40</strong> PREM students, 58% belonged to underrepresented minority gorups including, <strong>Hispanic</strong>, <strong>African American </strong>and <strong>Women</strong>.</li> <li>Of the 40 PREM participants, <strong>16</strong> students have graduated with <strong>PhD</strong> and <strong>8</strong> with <strong>BS</strong> degrees from UTSA PREM Program.</li> <li>The scientific achievements during this funding period include a range of significant discoveries that have produced a large number of excellent publications, During the past 5-year funded period, we have published <strong>147 papers</strong> in high impact journals, e.g. <strong>Nature Communiacations, ACS Nano, Nanoscale, materials Lett, Nano Lett, </strong>and others.More thatn <strong>90%</strong> of the published papers are with PREM-supported <strong>graduate and undergraduate students as co-authors.</strong></li> </ol> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p><strong>List of Pending Patents based on PREM Research:</strong></p> <p><strong><ol> <li>Interface Sensible Hall Magnetic Sensor for Transmission Electron Microscopes.</li> <li>Zinc-Silica Composite Ceramic Coatings for Anti-Corrosive Protection of Steel Substrates.</li> <li>Label-Free Detection of Sialic Acid Using Surface-Enhanced Raman Scattering Microscopy.</li> </ol></strong></p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 11/05/2015<br>      Modified by: Dhiraj&nbsp;K&nbsp;Sardar</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ PROJECT OUTCOMES:  Award Number: 0934218; Project Title: Oxide and Metal Nanoparticles-The Interface between Life Sciences and Physical Sciences; PI: Dhiraj Sardar  The UTSA-PREm in partnership with NU-MRsec had been very active and successful in publishing a large number of research articles in highly respected journals, in graduating a large number of students, majority of whom are minority students, and more importantly, most of these students are gainfully employed at different sectors including academia. Here is the list of Outcomes of UTSA PREM:  The PREM has helped UTSA accelerate its materials research capabilities significantly due to strong ties between UTSA and NU. The PREM has significantly impacted the Materials Research activities at UTSA and South Texas Region. The 5-year program supported a total of 26 PhD students and 15 undergraduate students. Among the 40 PREM students, 58% belonged to underrepresented minority gorups including, Hispanic, African American and Women. Of the 40 PREM participants, 16 students have graduated with PhD and 8 with BS degrees from UTSA PREM Program. The scientific achievements during this funding period include a range of significant discoveries that have produced a large number of excellent publications, During the past 5-year funded period, we have published 147 papers in high impact journals, e.g. Nature Communiacations, ACS Nano, Nanoscale, materials Lett, Nano Lett, and others.More thatn 90% of the published papers are with PREM-supported graduate and undergraduate students as co-authors.      List of Pending Patents based on PREM Research:   Interface Sensible Hall Magnetic Sensor for Transmission Electron Microscopes. Zinc-Silica Composite Ceramic Coatings for Anti-Corrosive Protection of Steel Substrates. Label-Free Detection of Sialic Acid Using Surface-Enhanced Raman Scattering Microscopy.        Last Modified: 11/05/2015       Submitted by: Dhiraj K Sardar]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
