<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Collaborative Research: University Program of Detector Research for the ILD Detector Concept at the ILC (T-TPC)</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/15/2009</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2013</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>225000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>225000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03010000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>PHY</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Physics</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Saul Gonzalez</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>sgonzale@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922093</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This proposal will fund the R&amp;D needed for future lepton collider detector and in particular the International Large Detector (ILD) detector concept. The R&amp;D projects will address critical issues related to the design of the ILD concept and associated beam instrumentation. The future lepton collider is expected to be a frontier scientific facility, exploring the interactions of electrons and positrons at energy scales of up to about 1 TeV. To fully exploit the physics opportunities of such an accelerator, it is essential to design a particle physics detector of unprecedented granularity, robustness and precision, and demonstrate that its feasibility. ILD is based around particle flow, a paradigm which aims for reconstruction of individual particles, using a highly robust tracking system centered on a time projection chamber supplemented with silicon tracking, and high granularity "camera-like" electro-magnetic and hadronic calorimetry suited to separation of individual energy deposits. Particle Flow calorimeters offer an exciting new approach to achieve significant better energy resolution needed by the new physics. If proven to work they could be useful for many future applications in High energy and Nuclear Physics experiments. This proposal will support the development and validation of Particle Flow Algorithms using test beam data. The detector projects address complementary aspects associated with advancing the design of the ILD detector with projects focused on tracking, calorimetry as well as beam instrumentation. This proposal will support the development of Low mass TPC endplates and luminosity monitoring system. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The proposal will have broader impact in that a number of the R&amp;D projects utilize a significant numbers of undergraduate students who are highly integrated into the planned research. The university groups have a strong track record of encouraging the participation of under-represented groups in their research and this will continue to be emphasized. Many of the detector R&amp;D projects have potential to lead to applications in areas such as medical imaging, and will lead to a cadre of scientists well trained in the art of experimentation and detector technologies.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>09/02/2009</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/19/2011</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>0935316</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Daniel</FirstName>
<LastName>Peterson</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>P</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Daniel P Peterson</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>daniel.peterson@cornell.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6072555014</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000526361</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/02/2009</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Cornell University</Name>
<CityName>Ithaca</CityName>
<ZipCode>148502820</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6072555014</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>373 Pine Tree Road</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>23</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NY23</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>872612445</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>CORNELL UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>002254837</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Cornell University]]></Name>
<CityName>Ithaca</CityName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<ZipCode>148502820</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[373 Pine Tree Road]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>23</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NY23</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<FoaInformation>
<Code>0000099</Code>
<Name>Other Applications NEC</Name>
</FoaInformation>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1221</Code>
<Text>HEP-High Energy Physics</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>0000</Code>
<Text>UNASSIGNED</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>OTHR</Code>
<Text>OTHER RESEARCH OR EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0109</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0110</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0111</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2009~75000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2010~75000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2011~75000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Meeting discovery and measurement goals of the proposed International Linear Collider (ILC) requires unprecedented improvements in the performance of the detector charged particle track finding and measuring system. Both the ability to measure the momentum and the efficiency of finding individual tracks in an environment of significant background must be improved.&nbsp;</p> <p>The International Large Detector (ILD) is a collaboration designing a general purpose&nbsp;detector for the ILC.&nbsp;A Time Projection Chamber (TPC), as shown in figure 1, is chosen to meet the momentum measurement and efficiency requirements. The figure shows the endplates, circular disks at the ends of the cylindrical TPC,&nbsp;which are the topic of this research.</p> <p>Measurements using a TPC ultimately depend on the measurements of charged signals with electronics on the endplates. Briefly, charge particles traversing the TPC volume leave tracks of ionized gas molecules and free electrons. Electrons drift to the endplates under the influence of an applied electric field. The drift path is held straight under the influence of an applied magnetic field. The electrons from the original track are thus deposited on the endplate, ideally creating an image that is an accurate projection of the shape of the original track. To provide the finest pixelization of the image, the ILD group is employing Micro Pattern Gas Detector (MPGD) readout technology.</p> <p>The structure of the TPC endplate is constrained by several factors. Use of MPGD technology required that readout electronics be bundled into units (modules) that are mounted on the endplate. The accurate projection of the track shape onto the endplate required that the electric field be very uniform, which, in turn, requires that the endplate be very flat. The accurate projection of the track shape also relies on very accurate and stable positioning of the readout modules; the endplate must be rigid. Further requirements are placed on the endplate due to integrating the TPC into the&nbsp;overall ILD&nbsp;detector. Efficient operation of detector elements located outside the TPC requires that the TPC endplate have minimal material and have minimal thickness in the direction of the TPC cylinder axis. Simultaneously meeting these requirements is a challenge; requirements for minimal thickness and material compete with requirements for rigidity and a modular construction.</p> <p>In the research reported here, we investigate the ability to meet the competing requirements for the endplate with a space-frame design. &nbsp;The endplate for the ILD TPC measures 1.8 meters in diameter and has an allowed thickness of 0.1 meters. The total material is limited to 0.08 radiation lengths, which is equivalent to an average total thickness in aluminum of 0.007 meter. Full size prototypes are beyond the scope of this grant. Rather, endplate design candidates are modeled with a Computer Aided Design (CAD) program that allows the physical propertied to be modeled with Finite Element Analysis (FEA). Small sections of the endplate were produced as physical prototypes. Properties of the physical prototype were compared to the predictions from the FEA of the full-sized ILD TPC endplate to&nbsp;evaluate the accuracy of the FEA.</p> <p>Figure 2 shows the small section of the ILD TPC endplate that was produced as a physical prototype. With a radius of 0.77 meters, the surface area is about 5% that of the ILD TPC. As shown in figure 3, the surface will accommodate seven readout modules which are similar to the modules to be used in the ILD TPC. The construction of the space-frame utilizes finely adjustable struts, which change in length by 0.026 cm per turn. This will allow the precision adjustment required to meet the flatness requirement. &nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;Rigidity of the endplate is measured as the deflection when the endplate is exposed to the gas overpressure...]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Meeting discovery and measurement goals of the proposed International Linear Collider (ILC) requires unprecedented improvements in the performance of the detector charged particle track finding and measuring system. Both the ability to measure the momentum and the efficiency of finding individual tracks in an environment of significant background must be improved.   The International Large Detector (ILD) is a collaboration designing a general purpose detector for the ILC. A Time Projection Chamber (TPC), as shown in figure 1, is chosen to meet the momentum measurement and efficiency requirements. The figure shows the endplates, circular disks at the ends of the cylindrical TPC, which are the topic of this research.  Measurements using a TPC ultimately depend on the measurements of charged signals with electronics on the endplates. Briefly, charge particles traversing the TPC volume leave tracks of ionized gas molecules and free electrons. Electrons drift to the endplates under the influence of an applied electric field. The drift path is held straight under the influence of an applied magnetic field. The electrons from the original track are thus deposited on the endplate, ideally creating an image that is an accurate projection of the shape of the original track. To provide the finest pixelization of the image, the ILD group is employing Micro Pattern Gas Detector (MPGD) readout technology.  The structure of the TPC endplate is constrained by several factors. Use of MPGD technology required that readout electronics be bundled into units (modules) that are mounted on the endplate. The accurate projection of the track shape onto the endplate required that the electric field be very uniform, which, in turn, requires that the endplate be very flat. The accurate projection of the track shape also relies on very accurate and stable positioning of the readout modules; the endplate must be rigid. Further requirements are placed on the endplate due to integrating the TPC into the overall ILD detector. Efficient operation of detector elements located outside the TPC requires that the TPC endplate have minimal material and have minimal thickness in the direction of the TPC cylinder axis. Simultaneously meeting these requirements is a challenge; requirements for minimal thickness and material compete with requirements for rigidity and a modular construction.  In the research reported here, we investigate the ability to meet the competing requirements for the endplate with a space-frame design.  The endplate for the ILD TPC measures 1.8 meters in diameter and has an allowed thickness of 0.1 meters. The total material is limited to 0.08 radiation lengths, which is equivalent to an average total thickness in aluminum of 0.007 meter. Full size prototypes are beyond the scope of this grant. Rather, endplate design candidates are modeled with a Computer Aided Design (CAD) program that allows the physical propertied to be modeled with Finite Element Analysis (FEA). Small sections of the endplate were produced as physical prototypes. Properties of the physical prototype were compared to the predictions from the FEA of the full-sized ILD TPC endplate to evaluate the accuracy of the FEA.  Figure 2 shows the small section of the ILD TPC endplate that was produced as a physical prototype. With a radius of 0.77 meters, the surface area is about 5% that of the ILD TPC. As shown in figure 3, the surface will accommodate seven readout modules which are similar to the modules to be used in the ILD TPC. The construction of the space-frame utilizes finely adjustable struts, which change in length by 0.026 cm per turn. This will allow the precision adjustment required to meet the flatness requirement.     Rigidity of the endplate is measured as the deflection when the endplate is exposed to the gas overpressure inside the TPC cylinder.  This force is about 100N on the area of the prototype. Deflection due to this force was calculated with the FEA to be 0.0...]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
