<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>NEESR-CR:  Steel Truss Systems with Enhanced Seismic Safety and Performance</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>10/01/2009</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>09/30/2015</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>599543.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>635543</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CMMI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Civil, Mechanical, &amp; Manufact Inn</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Joy Pauschke</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>jpauschk@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927024</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This award is an outcome of the NSF 09-524 program solicitation "George E. Brown, Jr. Network for Earthquake Engineering Simulation (NEES) Research (NEESR)" competition and includes the University of Texas, Arlington (lead) and Valparaiso University (subaward). This award will utilize the NEES equipment site at the University of Minnesota, named the Multi-Axial Subassemblage Testing (MAST) Laboratory. The goal of this research is to advance seismic safety and design of building structures by studying two steel truss systems: special truss moment frames (STMFs) and staggered truss frames (STFs). Due to their ability to achieve large column-free floor spaces, STMFs and STFs are unique, valuable options for structural engineers. However, although STMFs and STFs offer a wide range of structural, architectural, and economical benefits, limited research data is available on the seismic performance of these systems. Because previous tests on STMFs do not adequately reflect the current practice in design and detailing, substantial improvement in design methodology and confidence could be gained for STMFs by further research. Despite the strong interest among the engineering community, the application of STFs to seismic regions has been restricted due to lack of research. The project will advance knowledge about the system behavior of STMFs and STFs and recommend innovations to improve the seismic performance of these two truss systems.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Intellectual Merit: The NEES-MAST facility will be used to impose cyclic loading on large-scale subassemblages that comprise the fundamental structural unit of a STMF or STF. The large-scale tests will be used to: (1) verify the behavior of STMFs constructed according to recommendations from recent research results; (2) explore specific truss configurations that could enhance the performance of STMFs; (3) clarify the system behavior of STFs under cyclic loading; and (4) identify preferred energy dissipation mechanisms for STFs. The structural engineering laboratory at Valparaiso University will be used to examine the cyclic loading performance of shear-stud connections between steel chord members and hollow core concrete planks. In addition, analytical studies will lead to general nonlinear analysis methods that represent the seismic behavior of STMFs and STFs and generate nonlinear time history analysis data for a set of representative building systems that utilize STMFs or STFs. Results from this research will promote wider use of STMFs and STFs.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Broader Impacts: This award will support undergraduate students at Valparaiso University and the University of Minnesota to participate in the research. The PI at Valparaiso University participates in an engineering education initiative to introduce scientific visualization using virtual reality systems. These systems will be used to create three-dimensional (3D) models of both the experimental tests and analytical models. The PIs will use the 3D models to aid dissemination of the research results to the professional and academic communities. The 3D models will also be used to develop educational tools to introduce K-12 and undergraduate students to earthquake engineering research activity, the significance of earthquake effects, and the functions of building structures. The educational tools will be made available in the public domain for use in virtual reality systems or with a traditional computer screen projector. Data from this project will be archived and made available to the public through the NEES data repository.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/17/2009</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/30/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>0936563</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Michael</FirstName>
<LastName>Hagenberger</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>J</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Michael J Hagenberger</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>michael.hagenberger@valpo.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2194645062</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000378682</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/17/2009</StartDate>
<EndDate>06/24/2014</EndDate>
<RoleCode>Former Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Shih-Ho</FirstName>
<LastName>Chao</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Shih-Ho Chao</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>shchao@uta.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>8172722105</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000497651</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/17/2009</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Texas at Arlington</Name>
<CityName>Arlington</CityName>
<ZipCode>760190145</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>8172722105</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>701 S Nedderman Dr, Box 19145</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Texas</StateName>
<StateCode>TX</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>06</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>TX06</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>064234610</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF TEXAS AT ARLINGTON</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>042000273</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Texas at Arlington]]></Name>
<CityName>Arlington</CityName>
<StateCode>TX</StateCode>
<ZipCode>760190145</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[701 S Nedderman Dr, Box 19145]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Texas</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>06</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>TX06</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<FoaInformation>
<Code>0304010</Code>
<Name>Earthquake</Name>
</FoaInformation>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7396</Code>
<Text>NEES RESEARCH</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>036E</Code>
<Text>CIVIL INFRASTRUCTURE</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>043E</Code>
<Text>EARTHQUAKE ENGINEERING</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1057</Code>
<Text>CIS BASE RESEARCH</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>116E</Code>
<Text>RESEARCH EXP FOR UNDERGRADS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1576</Code>
<Text>NATIONL EARTHQK HZRD REDCT PRG</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9178</Code>
<Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9231</Code>
<Text>SUPPL FOR UNDERGRAD RES ASSIST</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9251</Code>
<Text>REU SUPP-Res Exp for Ugrd Supp</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>CVIS</Code>
<Text>CIVIL INFRASTRUCTURE</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0109</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0111</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0112</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0113</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2009~599543</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2011~12000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2012~12000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2013~12000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Special truss moment frame (STMF) is a relatively new type of steel framing system used for buildings in seismic areas. One of the major advantages of the STMF system is that the truss girders can be economically extended over longer spans. In addition, the open-webs can easily accommodate mechanical and electrical ductwork. Research work carried out on STMFs with light angle sections as truss members during the 1990s led to the formulation of design code provisions. However, they did not adequately reflect the current practice in design and detailing where much heavier sections are needed for buildings in high seismic areas. In this project, component specimens consisted of double-channel and double-HSS built-up sections were tested under cyclic bending tests in order to study their viability. The specimens represented the chord members as well as the vertical web member in the special segment (a structural fuse used to dissipate earthquake energy) of prototype STMFs. Special detailing of the member-to-gusset plate connection was also developed through these component tests. Moreover, a short buckling restrained brace (BRB) was tested in order to understand its seismic application in STMFs. The findings from component tests were later used in full-scale STMF subassemblage tests at Multi-Axial Subassemblage Testing Laboratory, an NSF NEES facility. The first two specimens were made of double-channel sections and the third specimen was made of double-HSS sections. In the last specimen, the truss girder was made of double-channel sections with two short BRBs oriented in chevron pattern in the special segment of the truss. The test results proved that by using the detailing proposed in this research, STMFs&rsquo; seismic performance and safety can be enhanced. Moreover, BRBs can be incorporated into STMF system to enhance its damage control capability.</p> <p>Steel staggered truss framing (STF) system was first developed in the 1960s to achieve a more efficient structural framing system to resist wind loads and at the same time to provide versatility of floor layout with large open areas. The result was an efficient steel framing system for mid- to high-rise buildings that was simple to fabricate and erect, with low floor-to-floor heights and large column-free spaces. Because of the design flexibility, construction efficiency, and overall cost efficiencies, many STF buildings have been constructed in low-seismicity regions. However, STFs&rsquo; seismic performance is highly unknown and necessitates urgent research. In this project, limitations of the conventional STF for use in seismically active areas were extensively investigated through computer simulations. Subsequently, an alternative structural layout was investigated in which the conventional diaphragms composed of precast concrete hollow-core slabs are replaced by horizontal steel trusses as in-plane diaphragm to transmit the large diaphragm shears in the lower stories. In addition, diagonal braces were added in the non-truss frames to alleviate the large forces in columns. The preferred yield mechanism of the STF system is to have plastic hinges form only within Vierendeel panels located at the center of the truss similar to that in the special segments of STMFs. A single Vierendeel panel in the middle of a truss leads to extremely high rotational demands in the chord members even at small roof drift ratios. In order to increase the overall drift capacity of the structure, the Vierendeel panels were expanded over three panels. This reduced the rotational demand at the ends of the chord members in the truss and allowed the structure to reach larger drifts without strength degradation. The addition of diagonal braces alters the seismic load transfer path from a staggered pattern via floor diaphragms to a more direct path from upper truss to the non-truss at lower level. This, in turn, relives the high force dem...]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Special truss moment frame (STMF) is a relatively new type of steel framing system used for buildings in seismic areas. One of the major advantages of the STMF system is that the truss girders can be economically extended over longer spans. In addition, the open-webs can easily accommodate mechanical and electrical ductwork. Research work carried out on STMFs with light angle sections as truss members during the 1990s led to the formulation of design code provisions. However, they did not adequately reflect the current practice in design and detailing where much heavier sections are needed for buildings in high seismic areas. In this project, component specimens consisted of double-channel and double-HSS built-up sections were tested under cyclic bending tests in order to study their viability. The specimens represented the chord members as well as the vertical web member in the special segment (a structural fuse used to dissipate earthquake energy) of prototype STMFs. Special detailing of the member-to-gusset plate connection was also developed through these component tests. Moreover, a short buckling restrained brace (BRB) was tested in order to understand its seismic application in STMFs. The findings from component tests were later used in full-scale STMF subassemblage tests at Multi-Axial Subassemblage Testing Laboratory, an NSF NEES facility. The first two specimens were made of double-channel sections and the third specimen was made of double-HSS sections. In the last specimen, the truss girder was made of double-channel sections with two short BRBs oriented in chevron pattern in the special segment of the truss. The test results proved that by using the detailing proposed in this research, STMFsÆ seismic performance and safety can be enhanced. Moreover, BRBs can be incorporated into STMF system to enhance its damage control capability.  Steel staggered truss framing (STF) system was first developed in the 1960s to achieve a more efficient structural framing system to resist wind loads and at the same time to provide versatility of floor layout with large open areas. The result was an efficient steel framing system for mid- to high-rise buildings that was simple to fabricate and erect, with low floor-to-floor heights and large column-free spaces. Because of the design flexibility, construction efficiency, and overall cost efficiencies, many STF buildings have been constructed in low-seismicity regions. However, STFsÆ seismic performance is highly unknown and necessitates urgent research. In this project, limitations of the conventional STF for use in seismically active areas were extensively investigated through computer simulations. Subsequently, an alternative structural layout was investigated in which the conventional diaphragms composed of precast concrete hollow-core slabs are replaced by horizontal steel trusses as in-plane diaphragm to transmit the large diaphragm shears in the lower stories. In addition, diagonal braces were added in the non-truss frames to alleviate the large forces in columns. The preferred yield mechanism of the STF system is to have plastic hinges form only within Vierendeel panels located at the center of the truss similar to that in the special segments of STMFs. A single Vierendeel panel in the middle of a truss leads to extremely high rotational demands in the chord members even at small roof drift ratios. In order to increase the overall drift capacity of the structure, the Vierendeel panels were expanded over three panels. This reduced the rotational demand at the ends of the chord members in the truss and allowed the structure to reach larger drifts without strength degradation. The addition of diagonal braces alters the seismic load transfer path from a staggered pattern via floor diaphragms to a more direct path from upper truss to the non-truss at lower level. This, in turn, relives the high force demands in the diaphragms and the diaphragm-to-truss connections. Analysis results ...]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
