<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>NSEC - Center for Nanotechnology in Society at ASU</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/15/2010</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2016</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>6507000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>7185888</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Cooperative Agreement</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>04050000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>SBE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>SES</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Divn Of Social and Economic Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Frederick Kronz</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>fkronz@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927283</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The Center for Nanotechnology in Society at Arizona State University (CNS-ASU) is a Nano-scale Science and Engineering Center (NSEC) funded by the US National Science Foundation (NSF).  It implements an agenda of "real-time technology assessment" (RTTA) and clusters of thematic research in pursuit of a strategic vision of the "anticipatory governance" of nanotechnologies. The RTTA agenda comprises research programs in: 1) research and innovation systems assessment, which aims to map nano-scale science and engineering research activities using bibliometrics and patent analysis; 2) public opinion and values, which aims to understand the dynamics of public and expert opinion regarding emerging nanotechnologies; 3) anticipation and deliberation, which aims at deploying novel demonstrations of scenario development and public engagement activities to anticipate societal dimensions of emerging nanotechnologies; and 4) reflexivity and integration, which aims to bolster the ability of nano-scale science and engineering researchers to understand their own roles in responsible innovation through integrating social science and humanities with natural science and engineering.  CNS-ASU's two clusters of thematic research are: equity, equality and responsibility; and (beginning in Oct 2010) urban design, materials, and the built environment ("nano and the city").  To achieve its strategic vision, CNS-ASU unifies these research programs not only across several universities but also across three critical, component activities: foresight (of plausible future scenarios), integration (of social science and humanities research with nano-scale science and engineering), and engagement (of publics in deliberations). CNS-ASU also performs educational and training activities as well as public outreach and informal science education.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>09/28/2010</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/14/2015</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>CoopAgrmnt</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.075</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>0937591</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>David</FirstName>
<LastName>Guston</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>H</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>David H Guston</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>david.guston@asu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>4807278787</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000195728</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/28/2010</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Arizona State University</Name>
<CityName>TEMPE</CityName>
<ZipCode>852816011</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>4809655479</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>ORSPA</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[660 South Mill Avenue, Suite 310]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Arizona</StateName>
<StateCode>AZ</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>09</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>AZ09</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>943360412</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>ARIZONA STATE UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>806345658</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Arizona State University]]></Name>
<CityName>TEMPE</CityName>
<StateCode>AZ</StateCode>
<ZipCode>852816011</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[ORSPA]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Arizona</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>09</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>AZ09</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<FoaInformation>
<Code>0116000</Code>
<Name>Human Subjects</Name>
</FoaInformation>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1144</Code>
<Text>Molecular Biophysics</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1675</Code>
<Text>NANOSCALE: SCIENCE &amp; ENGIN CTR</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7412</Code>
<Text>Advanced Tech Education Prog</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>0000</Code>
<Text>UNASSIGNED</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1675</Code>
<Text>NANOSCALE: SCIENCE &amp; ENGIN CTR</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7237</Code>
<Text>NANO NON-SOLIC SCI &amp; ENG AWD</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7567</Code>
<Text>SOC STUDIES OF SCI, ENG &amp; TECH</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7702</Code>
<Text>SOCIETAL IMPLICATIONS OF NANO</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9162</Code>
<Text>MULTI DIVISION/UNIVERSITY</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9178</Code>
<Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9179</Code>
<Text>GRADUATE INVOLVEMENT</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>OTHR</Code>
<Text>OTHER RESEARCH OR EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0110</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0111</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0112</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0113</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0114</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0115</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0410</Code>
<Name>NSF Education &amp; Human Resource</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040106</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0411</Code>
<Name>NSF Education &amp; Human Resource</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040106</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0412</Code>
<Name>NSF Education &amp; Human Resource</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040106</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0413</Code>
<Name>NSF Education &amp; Human Resource</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040106</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0414</Code>
<Name>NSF Education &amp; Human Resource</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040106</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2010~1301400</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2011~1320290</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2012~1473900</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2013~1301400</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~1538898</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2015~250000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The Nanoscale Science and Engineering Center/Center for Nanotechnology in Society at Arizona State University (NSEC/CNS-ASU) combined research, training, and engagement to develop a new approach to governing emerging nanotechnologies. CNS-ASU used the methods of &ldquo;real-time technology assessment&rdquo; to enable a vision of anticipatory governance through enhanced foresight, engagement with lay publics, and integration of social science and humanistic work with NSE research and education.&nbsp; CNS-ASU developed two types of integrated research programs. Its real-time technology assessment programs were: <span style="text-decoration: underline;">Research and Innovation Systems Assessment</span>, using bibliometric and patent analyses to understand the evolving dynamics of NSE; <span style="text-decoration: underline;">Public Opinion and Values,</span> using surveys and quasi-experimental media studies to understand changing public and scientists&rsquo; perspectives on NSE; <span style="text-decoration: underline;">Anticipation and Deliberation</span>, using scenario development and other futuring techniques to foster deliberation on plausible NSE applications; and <span style="text-decoration: underline;">Reflexivity and Integration</span>, using participant-observation to assess the Center&rsquo;s influence on reflexivity among collaborators and participants. Its thematic research clusters, pursuing fundamental knowledge and creating linkages across methods, were: <span style="text-decoration: underline;">Equity, Equality and Responsibility</span>; and <span style="text-decoration: underline;">Urban Design, Materials, and the Built Environment</span>.</p> <p>The Center&rsquo;s mission was to: 1) <em>research</em> the societal dimensions of NSE; 2) <em>train</em> a community of scholars with new insight into these dimensions; 3) <em>engage</em> various publics and NSE researchers in dialogues about the goals and implications of NSE; and 4) <em>partner</em> with the NSE enterprise to generate greater <em>reflexiveness</em> in research, development, education and policy. CNS-ASU weaved together these activities to support the capacity for <em>anticipatory governance</em>.&nbsp; The Center made significant strides in accomplishing this mission. Its vision and methods were recognized in important scholarly and policy venues, from the National Nanotechnology Initiative to the National Nanotechnology Coordinated Infrastructure to policy development for responsible innovation.</p> <p>CNS-ASU broadly disseminated its results to enhance scientific and technical understanding. Center researchers have published, accepted or under review/contract: 13 books (7 primary), 99 book chapters (82 primary), 287 peer-reviewed journal articles (228 primary), 59 non-peer-reviewed journal articles, and 98 other publications. The Center&rsquo;s researchers have produced special issues of 7 peer-reviewed journals, and Center faculty helped found the <em>Journal of Responsible Innovation</em>. There are more than 11,100 citations to this work documented in Google Scholar (12/16).&nbsp;</p> <p>The CNS-ASU web site (<a href="http://cns.asu.edu">http://cns.asu.edu</a>) describes its programs &ndash; along with numerous videos and websites of associated projects &ndash; and its e-mail distribution list reached about 1400 individuals.&nbsp; Its researchers gave more than 900 talks. &nbsp;NISE Net disseminated CNS-ASU products to approximately 300 museums and other participants in NanoDays and other activities.</p> <p>The Center<em> </em>advanced discovery and understanding while promoting teaching, training, and learning, contributing to the completion of 45 doctoral theses, 3 master&rsquo;s theses, and 29 undergraduate honors theses. CNS-ASU conducted teaching, training, and learning projects from pre-college education to post-doctoral training, as well as ISE projects and training for scientists and engineers. CNS perspectives were incorporated into interdisciplinary graduate training in solar energy and person-centered design for disability.</p> <p>The Center broadened participation of underrepresented groups, developing a strong record of including women in research and leadership positions and recruiting members of under-represented groups into graduate and undergraduate research positions. The Center made diversity explicit in its research agenda, e.g., by creating an entire research program on Equity, Equality and Responsibility. Its Policy, Science, Technology and Society Scholars program recruited undergraduates from underrepresented backgrounds for local mentorship and DC workshops to better establish them on a trajectory toward graduate school.</p> <p>The Center enhanced the infrastructure for research and education by: hosting more than 120 international visitors from 26 countries; becoming a &ldquo;core partner&rdquo; in NISE Net; conducting the annual Winter School on the Anticipatory Governance of Emerging Technologies; hosting four Community Engagement Workshops on international collaborations and pro-poor technologies in three countries; and expanding its Virtual Institute for Responsible Innovation to 24 centers in thirteen countries. The Center nurtured ASU&rsquo;s Governing Emerging Technologies meeting and its <em>Emerge</em> event, as well as the Society for the Study of New and Emerging Technologies and the Communities of Integration programs. The Center shared data and instruments with researchers across the globe.&nbsp; It has catalyzed institutional change at ASU and its collaborating universities, crucially seeded the creation of ASU&rsquo;s School for the Future of Innovation in Society (SFIS).</p> <p>The Center contributed to what may be the concrete and demonstrable benefits to society. Its foresight activities created an opportunity for diverse publics to encounter, explore, and evaluate emerging technologies.&nbsp; Engagement activities created more informed citizens.&nbsp; Interactions with NSE researchers resulted in reflexively generated changes in knowledge, identity, and laboratory practice.&nbsp; The Center also exchanged information with decision makers at the Office of Science and Technology Policy and the President&rsquo;s Committee of Advisors for Science and Technology, mid-level science policy makers through ASU&rsquo;s Washington, DC office and through the Sackler Colloquium at the National Academy of Sciences and with Germany&rsquo;s Institute for Technology Assessment and Systems Analysis.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 12/29/2016<br>      Modified by: David&nbsp;H&nbsp;Guston</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The Nanoscale Science and Engineering Center/Center for Nanotechnology in Society at Arizona State University (NSEC/CNS-ASU) combined research, training, and engagement to develop a new approach to governing emerging nanotechnologies. CNS-ASU used the methods of "real-time technology assessment" to enable a vision of anticipatory governance through enhanced foresight, engagement with lay publics, and integration of social science and humanistic work with NSE research and education.  CNS-ASU developed two types of integrated research programs. Its real-time technology assessment programs were: Research and Innovation Systems Assessment, using bibliometric and patent analyses to understand the evolving dynamics of NSE; Public Opinion and Values, using surveys and quasi-experimental media studies to understand changing public and scientists? perspectives on NSE; Anticipation and Deliberation, using scenario development and other futuring techniques to foster deliberation on plausible NSE applications; and Reflexivity and Integration, using participant-observation to assess the Center?s influence on reflexivity among collaborators and participants. Its thematic research clusters, pursuing fundamental knowledge and creating linkages across methods, were: Equity, Equality and Responsibility; and Urban Design, Materials, and the Built Environment.  The Center?s mission was to: 1) research the societal dimensions of NSE; 2) train a community of scholars with new insight into these dimensions; 3) engage various publics and NSE researchers in dialogues about the goals and implications of NSE; and 4) partner with the NSE enterprise to generate greater reflexiveness in research, development, education and policy. CNS-ASU weaved together these activities to support the capacity for anticipatory governance.  The Center made significant strides in accomplishing this mission. Its vision and methods were recognized in important scholarly and policy venues, from the National Nanotechnology Initiative to the National Nanotechnology Coordinated Infrastructure to policy development for responsible innovation.  CNS-ASU broadly disseminated its results to enhance scientific and technical understanding. Center researchers have published, accepted or under review/contract: 13 books (7 primary), 99 book chapters (82 primary), 287 peer-reviewed journal articles (228 primary), 59 non-peer-reviewed journal articles, and 98 other publications. The Center?s researchers have produced special issues of 7 peer-reviewed journals, and Center faculty helped found the Journal of Responsible Innovation. There are more than 11,100 citations to this work documented in Google Scholar (12/16).   The CNS-ASU web site (http://cns.asu.edu) describes its programs &ndash; along with numerous videos and websites of associated projects &ndash; and its e-mail distribution list reached about 1400 individuals.  Its researchers gave more than 900 talks.  NISE Net disseminated CNS-ASU products to approximately 300 museums and other participants in NanoDays and other activities.  The Center advanced discovery and understanding while promoting teaching, training, and learning, contributing to the completion of 45 doctoral theses, 3 master?s theses, and 29 undergraduate honors theses. CNS-ASU conducted teaching, training, and learning projects from pre-college education to post-doctoral training, as well as ISE projects and training for scientists and engineers. CNS perspectives were incorporated into interdisciplinary graduate training in solar energy and person-centered design for disability.  The Center broadened participation of underrepresented groups, developing a strong record of including women in research and leadership positions and recruiting members of under-represented groups into graduate and undergraduate research positions. The Center made diversity explicit in its research agenda, e.g., by creating an entire research program on Equity, Equality and Responsibility. Its Policy, Science, Technology and Society Scholars program recruited undergraduates from underrepresented backgrounds for local mentorship and DC workshops to better establish them on a trajectory toward graduate school.  The Center enhanced the infrastructure for research and education by: hosting more than 120 international visitors from 26 countries; becoming a "core partner" in NISE Net; conducting the annual Winter School on the Anticipatory Governance of Emerging Technologies; hosting four Community Engagement Workshops on international collaborations and pro-poor technologies in three countries; and expanding its Virtual Institute for Responsible Innovation to 24 centers in thirteen countries. The Center nurtured ASU?s Governing Emerging Technologies meeting and its Emerge event, as well as the Society for the Study of New and Emerging Technologies and the Communities of Integration programs. The Center shared data and instruments with researchers across the globe.  It has catalyzed institutional change at ASU and its collaborating universities, crucially seeded the creation of ASU?s School for the Future of Innovation in Society (SFIS).  The Center contributed to what may be the concrete and demonstrable benefits to society. Its foresight activities created an opportunity for diverse publics to encounter, explore, and evaluate emerging technologies.  Engagement activities created more informed citizens.  Interactions with NSE researchers resulted in reflexively generated changes in knowledge, identity, and laboratory practice.  The Center also exchanged information with decision makers at the Office of Science and Technology Policy and the President?s Committee of Advisors for Science and Technology, mid-level science policy makers through ASU?s Washington, DC office and through the Sackler Colloquium at the National Academy of Sciences and with Germany?s Institute for Technology Assessment and Systems Analysis.       Last Modified: 12/29/2016       Submitted by: David H Guston]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
