<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Support for the Core Research Activities and Studies of the Computer Science and Telecommunications Board</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>10/01/2009</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>09/30/2014</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>540002.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>600002</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>05050000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>CSE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CNS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Computer and Network Systems</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Harriet Taylor</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This CISE special project award funds the core operations of the Computer Science and Telecommunications Board (CSTB) of the National Academy of Sciences. The CSTB provides objective, nonpartisan, scholarly analysis, blending expertise in computer science (CS), electrical engineering, telecommunications, and various applications and impacts of information technology (IT). It engages experts from the entire IT community in mixed collaborative groups, developing ideas, explanations, assessments, and recommendations reflecting diverse points of view and rigorous peer review. It is a focal point for engaging the research community in the development of new research agendas and in raising the level of policy debate. CSTB is a leader in information technology policy analysis, a source of strategic thinking for research funding agencies, and an exponent of how and why IT research should be done. Core support enables it to plan for, oversee, and follow up on projects and to be forward-thinking and proactive in formulating new activities. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;CSTB has an ambitious program of activities addressing the health of U.S. computer science, telecommunications, and their applications. It draws on the expertise and perspectives of a wide range of people from the public and private sectors with interests in the evolving nature and needs of research across computer science and telecommunications and the condition of the human resources and institutions responsible for producing IT. Projects leverage computer scientists? deep insights into what IT is, how it works, and where it is going together with insights from other fields such as biology, the social sciences, economics, and law.  CSTB's work is known and used by a wide and growing circle of agencies, officials, and experts in the field; CSTB has come to be seen as an authoritative source on IT trends, IT policies, and their implications for broader public policy. CSTB delivers its reports and provides briefings to key decision-makers and practitioners in the research, education, and policy-making communities. Its study groups engage significant numbers of women, minorities, and people from across the country. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Intellectual Merit: The results of studies and other activities enabled by this core support provide a source of strategic thinking for researchers, educator, and research funding agencies on IT trends and issues and their implications for broader public policy, including how and why IT research should be done. Much of this work also blends IT knowledge with insights from other fields such as biology, the social sciences, economics, and law to provide interdisciplinary perspectives on applications of IT and its social and economic impacts. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Broader Impact: CSTB provides a forum for the exchange of information on CS, IT, and telecommunications and for the exploration of how economic, social, and legal trends may shape and be shaped by the environment for IT in the future. The result of studies and other activities enable by this core support provide independent, authoritative information to a wide array of federal agencies and officials, researchers and educators, and information technology experts. They engage members of the IT technical and research communities in the development of new research agendas and in informing policy debates related to information technology. Reports and briefings are provided to key decision-makers and practitioners in the research, education, and policy-making communities. Experts participating in CSTB activities learn about the relationship between their research and larger contexts, both within IT research and within the larger economy and society.&lt;br/&gt;</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>09/24/2009</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>09/18/2012</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.070</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>0940372</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Jon</FirstName>
<LastName>Eisenberg</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>K</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Jon K Eisenberg</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>jeisenbe@nas.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2023342605</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000064760</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/24/2009</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>National Academy of Sciences</Name>
<CityName>Washington</CityName>
<ZipCode>200012721</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2023342254</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>500 FIFTH STREET NW</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>District of Columbia</StateName>
<StateCode>DC</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>00</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>DC00</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>041964057</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>NATIONAL ACADEMY OF SCIENCES</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>041964057</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[National Academy of Sciences]]></Name>
<CityName>Washington</CityName>
<StateCode>DC</StateCode>
<ZipCode>200012721</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[500 FIFTH STREET NW]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>District of Columbia</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>00</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>DC00</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1640</Code>
<Text>Information Technology Researc</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9218</Code>
<Text>BASIC RESEARCH &amp; HUMAN RESORCS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>HPCC</Code>
<Text>HIGH PERFORMANCE COMPUTING &amp; COMM</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0109</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0112</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2009~540002</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2012~60000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>This award provided partial support for the activities of the Computer Science and Telecommunications Board of the National Academies. &nbsp;CSTB &nbsp;provides objective, nonpartisan, scholarly analysis, blending expertise in computer science (CS), electrical engineering, telecommunications, and various applications and impacts of information technology (IT). &nbsp;It engaged experts from across the IT community in mixed collaborative groups, developing ideas, explanations, assessments, and recommendations reflecting diverse points of view and rigorous peer review. &nbsp;Largely separately supported but enabled in part by this award, CSTB issued reports covering future research directions, impact and implications of research, applications of IT, human resources in IT, and public policy impacts:</p> <p><br />At the Nexus of Cybersecurity and Public Policy: Some Basic Concepts and Issues presents fundamental concepts and principles that serve as points of departure for understanding specific cybersecurity incidents or proposals to improve security.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>Emerging and Readily Available Technologies and National Security: A Framework for Addressing Ethical, Legal, and Societal Issues recommends that interested military R&amp;D agencies ensure senior agency leadership engagement; develop and deploy screening, review, and monitoring processes; educate and sensitize program managers; build external expertise; and provide assistance to R&amp;D performers.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>Professionalizing the Nation&rsquo;s Cybersecurity Workforce? Criteria for Decision&shy; Making &nbsp;considers the role that professionalization could play in enhancing workforce capacity and capability and sets forth criteria for when, where, and how to professionalize the cybersecurity workforce.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>Geotargeted Alerts and Warnings: Report of a Workshop on Current Knowledge and Research Gaps explores what is known about how the public responds to geotargeted alerts and warnings, technologies and techniques for enhancing the geotargeting of alerts and warnings, and open research questions about how to effectively use them.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>Public Response to Alerts and Warnings Using Social Media: Summary of a Workshop on Current Knowledge and Research Gaps reviews current knowledge and explores the challenges and open research questions associated with delivery of alerts and warnings using social media, how officials may monitor social media information, and the associated privacy concerns.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>Continuing Innovation in Information Technology examines important research areas and some of the significant, billion&shy;dollar&shy;plus, IT industries that have resulted from those investments.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>Computing Research for Sustainability highlights opportunities for computer science research and IT innovation and urges the computing research community to bring its approaches and methodologies to bear in ways that will have significant, measurable impact on sustainability.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>Strategies and Priorities for Information Technology at the Centers for Medicare and Medicaid Services recommends that CMS embrace IT as a critical strategic capability for improving the efficiency, quality, safety, and equity of U.S. health care.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>Report of a Workshop on Pedagogical Aspects of Computational Thinking summarizes insights and approaches from educators who have addressed computational thinking in their work with K&shy;12 teachers and students and in settings for informal (non&shy;school) education.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>Wireless Technology Prospects and Policy Options describes key technology trends, their implications, and options for facilitating the introduction of enhanced and new services.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>The Future of Computing Performance: Game Over or Next Level? explores the causes and implications of t...]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ This award provided partial support for the activities of the Computer Science and Telecommunications Board of the National Academies.  CSTB  provides objective, nonpartisan, scholarly analysis, blending expertise in computer science (CS), electrical engineering, telecommunications, and various applications and impacts of information technology (IT).  It engaged experts from across the IT community in mixed collaborative groups, developing ideas, explanations, assessments, and recommendations reflecting diverse points of view and rigorous peer review.  Largely separately supported but enabled in part by this award, CSTB issued reports covering future research directions, impact and implications of research, applications of IT, human resources in IT, and public policy impacts:   At the Nexus of Cybersecurity and Public Policy: Some Basic Concepts and Issues presents fundamental concepts and principles that serve as points of departure for understanding specific cybersecurity incidents or proposals to improve security.     Emerging and Readily Available Technologies and National Security: A Framework for Addressing Ethical, Legal, and Societal Issues recommends that interested military R&amp;D agencies ensure senior agency leadership engagement; develop and deploy screening, review, and monitoring processes; educate and sensitize program managers; build external expertise; and provide assistance to R&amp;D performers.     Professionalizing the NationÆs Cybersecurity Workforce? Criteria for Decision&shy; Making  considers the role that professionalization could play in enhancing workforce capacity and capability and sets forth criteria for when, where, and how to professionalize the cybersecurity workforce.     Geotargeted Alerts and Warnings: Report of a Workshop on Current Knowledge and Research Gaps explores what is known about how the public responds to geotargeted alerts and warnings, technologies and techniques for enhancing the geotargeting of alerts and warnings, and open research questions about how to effectively use them.     Public Response to Alerts and Warnings Using Social Media: Summary of a Workshop on Current Knowledge and Research Gaps reviews current knowledge and explores the challenges and open research questions associated with delivery of alerts and warnings using social media, how officials may monitor social media information, and the associated privacy concerns.     Continuing Innovation in Information Technology examines important research areas and some of the significant, billion&shy;dollar&shy;plus, IT industries that have resulted from those investments.     Computing Research for Sustainability highlights opportunities for computer science research and IT innovation and urges the computing research community to bring its approaches and methodologies to bear in ways that will have significant, measurable impact on sustainability.     Strategies and Priorities for Information Technology at the Centers for Medicare and Medicaid Services recommends that CMS embrace IT as a critical strategic capability for improving the efficiency, quality, safety, and equity of U.S. health care.     Report of a Workshop on Pedagogical Aspects of Computational Thinking summarizes insights and approaches from educators who have addressed computational thinking in their work with K&shy;12 teachers and students and in settings for informal (non&shy;school) education.     Wireless Technology Prospects and Policy Options describes key technology trends, their implications, and options for facilitating the introduction of enhanced and new services.     The Future of Computing Performance: Game Over or Next Level? explores the causes and implications of the slowdown in the historically dramatic exponential growth of computing performance; the consequent need for a new era of parallelism; and the associated scientific, engineering, research, and education challenges.     Public Response to Alerts and Warnings on Mobile Devic...]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
