<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>DataNet Full Proposal: Terra Populus: A Global Population/Environment Data Network</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2011</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>7998550.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>8168230</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Cooperative Agreement</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>05090000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>CSE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>OAC</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Office of Advanced Cyberinfrastructure (OAC)</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Amy Walton</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>awalton@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924538</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Terra Populus: A Global Population/Environment Data Network (TerraPop) will develop organizational and technical infrastructure that will integrate, preserve, and disseminate data describing changes in the human population and environment over time. A plethora of high-quality environmental and population datasets are available, but they are widely dispersed, have incompatible or inadequate metadata, and have incompatible geographic identifiers. The project will enable researchers to identify and merge data from heterogeneous sources to study the relationships between human behavior and the natural world. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;TerraPop will focus on four specific kinds of data: (1) census and survey microdata describing the characteristics of individuals and their families and households; (2) aggregate census and survey data, describing the characteristics of places, including aggregate population characteristics, land use, and land cover; (3) remote-sensing data describing land cover and other environmental characteristics; and (4) climate data describing temperature, precipitation, and other climate-related variables. All four data types have an important temporal dimension; most of the data span the past five decades, and some sources reach back to the nineteenth century. TerraPop will make these data interoperable across time and space, disseminate them to the public and to multiple research communities, and preserve them for future generations. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Understanding of interactions between population and the environment has been hampered by the dearth of internationally comparable data. This infrastructure will expand the quality and quantity of such data while making them highly interoperable and easily accessible. Population data closely integrated with data on the environment will allow us to describe the unfolding transformation of human and ecological systems. Data on the human population are crucial for understanding changes in the Earth?s biological and climate processes; equally important, data on climate and land provide essential tools for understanding the impact of environmental change on human behavior. By creating a framework for locating, analyzing, and visualizing the world's population and environment in time and space, TerraPop will provide unprecedented opportunities for investigating the agents of change, assessing their implications for human society and the environment, and developing policies to meet future challenges. The data collection and its analysis tools will contribute to education and public understanding. It will allow teachers to integrate research and teaching, bringing the excitement of discovery into the classroom from primary school to graduate school. More broadly, TerraPop will be a model for the sustainable expansion, maintenance, and improvement of a global data resource.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>09/14/2011</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>02/04/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>CoopAgrmnt</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.070</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>0940818</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Jaideep</FirstName>
<LastName>Srivastava</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Jaideep Srivastava</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>srivasta@cs.umn.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6126254012</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000471277</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/14/2011</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Shashi</FirstName>
<LastName>Shekhar</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Shashi Shekhar</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>shekhar@cs.umn.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6126248307</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000467497</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/14/2011</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Steven</FirstName>
<LastName>Ruggles</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Steven Ruggles</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>ruggles@umn.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6126244081</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000116296</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/14/2011</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Victoria</FirstName>
<LastName>Interrante</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>L</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Victoria L Interrante</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>interran@cs.umn.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6126253543</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000160817</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/14/2011</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Steven</FirstName>
<LastName>Manson</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>M</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Steven M Manson</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>manson@umn.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6126254577</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000096168</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/14/2011</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Minnesota-Twin Cities</Name>
<CityName>Minneapolis</CityName>
<ZipCode>554552070</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6126245599</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>200 OAK ST SE</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Minnesota</StateName>
<StateCode>MN</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MN05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>555917996</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>REGENTS OF THE UNIVERSITY OF MINNESOTA</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>117178941</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Minnesota-Twin Cities]]></Name>
<CityName>Minneapolis</CityName>
<StateCode>MN</StateCode>
<ZipCode>554552070</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[200 OAK ST SE]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Minnesota</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MN05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7414</Code>
<Text>NSF Public Access Initiative</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7684</Code>
<Text>CESER-Cyberinfrastructure for</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7726</Code>
<Text>Data Cyberinfrastructure</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7433</Code>
<Text>CyberInfra Frmwrk 21st (CIF21)</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7726</Code>
<Text>DATANET</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0111</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0112</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0113</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0114</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2011~7678550</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2012~154716</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2013~160000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~174964</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Terra Populus (now known as IPUMS Terra, http://terra.ipums.org) enables deeper understanding of complex human and environmental systems by providing integrated population, land use/land cover, and climate data. The Terra Populus project assembled a massive collection of global population and environmental data, developed software for integrating data from different scientific domains, and created easy-to-use web-based data access systems. This data infrastructure allows researchers from a variety of social and natural science disciplines to quickly and easily acquire the data they need in an integrated package convenient for their analyses, saving many hundreds of hours of data manipulation work and duplicated effort.&nbsp;</p> <p>Data from different scientific domains are often structured in different ways, making them difficult to use in a combined analysis. Terra Populus addressed data integration across three major data structures used in the social and environmental sciences: microdata, area-level data, and raster data. Microdata are anonymized individual responses to a census or survey, typically provided as a sample of the responses from a population. Area-level data describe characteristics of the population in a place, such as the percent of workers in manufacturing or percent of households with internet access in each county. Raster data use a spatial grid to describe how characteristics such as land cover, crop yield, temperature, and precipitation vary over space.</p> <p>The Terra Populus database includes population census microdata from 85 countries and over 300 censuses; area-level population data for over 170 countries; and global raster data on land cover, harvested area and yield for 175 different crops, long-term climate averages, and monthly temperature and precipitation back to 1901. Terra Populus also developed spatial boundary data for the geographic units in the population data, including tracking how the units change over time. Software developed by Terra Populus uses these boundaries to integrate data across the three structures by summarizing raster data to create area-level environmental data, attaching area-level data to microdata records, tabulating microdata to create area-level data, and distributing area-level data across grid cells to create raster data.</p> <p>Terra Populus developed three web-based applications for researchers, educators, policy makers, and the public to access population and environmental data. The extract builder (https://data.terrapop.org) allows users to browse and select data from across the entire collection and combine diverse data sources into a customized dataset in the user&rsquo;s preferred data structure. TerraClip (https://data.terrapop.org/terraclip) provides an easy way to obtain country-level subsets of global raster datasets. TerraScope (https://data.terrapop.org/terrascope) provides a map-based interface for users to explore the area-level and raster portions of the collection, produce basic visualizations, and download customized area-level datasets.</p> <p>Using these resources, researchers investigate pressing global issues such as the relationship between climate conditions and migration, environmental determinants of maternal and childhood health, characteristics of environmentally vulnerable populations, environmental justice, interactions between agriculture and deforestation, and more.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 12/01/2017<br>      Modified by: Steven&nbsp;Ruggles</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Terra Populus (now known as IPUMS Terra, http://terra.ipums.org) enables deeper understanding of complex human and environmental systems by providing integrated population, land use/land cover, and climate data. The Terra Populus project assembled a massive collection of global population and environmental data, developed software for integrating data from different scientific domains, and created easy-to-use web-based data access systems. This data infrastructure allows researchers from a variety of social and natural science disciplines to quickly and easily acquire the data they need in an integrated package convenient for their analyses, saving many hundreds of hours of data manipulation work and duplicated effort.   Data from different scientific domains are often structured in different ways, making them difficult to use in a combined analysis. Terra Populus addressed data integration across three major data structures used in the social and environmental sciences: microdata, area-level data, and raster data. Microdata are anonymized individual responses to a census or survey, typically provided as a sample of the responses from a population. Area-level data describe characteristics of the population in a place, such as the percent of workers in manufacturing or percent of households with internet access in each county. Raster data use a spatial grid to describe how characteristics such as land cover, crop yield, temperature, and precipitation vary over space.  The Terra Populus database includes population census microdata from 85 countries and over 300 censuses; area-level population data for over 170 countries; and global raster data on land cover, harvested area and yield for 175 different crops, long-term climate averages, and monthly temperature and precipitation back to 1901. Terra Populus also developed spatial boundary data for the geographic units in the population data, including tracking how the units change over time. Software developed by Terra Populus uses these boundaries to integrate data across the three structures by summarizing raster data to create area-level environmental data, attaching area-level data to microdata records, tabulating microdata to create area-level data, and distributing area-level data across grid cells to create raster data.  Terra Populus developed three web-based applications for researchers, educators, policy makers, and the public to access population and environmental data. The extract builder (https://data.terrapop.org) allows users to browse and select data from across the entire collection and combine diverse data sources into a customized dataset in the user?s preferred data structure. TerraClip (https://data.terrapop.org/terraclip) provides an easy way to obtain country-level subsets of global raster datasets. TerraScope (https://data.terrapop.org/terrascope) provides a map-based interface for users to explore the area-level and raster portions of the collection, produce basic visualizations, and download customized area-level datasets.  Using these resources, researchers investigate pressing global issues such as the relationship between climate conditions and migration, environmental determinants of maternal and childhood health, characteristics of environmentally vulnerable populations, environmental justice, interactions between agriculture and deforestation, and more.       Last Modified: 12/01/2017       Submitted by: Steven Ruggles]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
