<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Motivating Change in Faculty Teaching Practices to Support a Diverse Student Body in Engineering</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/15/2010</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>09/30/2015</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>199999.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>239353</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>11040200</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>EHR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DUE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Undergraduate Education</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Myles Boylan</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>mboylan@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032928670</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Engineering - Other (59); Assessment/Research (91)&lt;br/&gt;A great deal of research has shown that specific teaching practices can improve student success and support a diverse student body in engineering.  Translation of this research to actual teaching practices has been slow at many institutions.  This project is seeking to generate a transformative change in teaching practices.  It is grounded in a strategic model that posits that efforts to encourage instructors to adopt the most effective teaching practices will have the greatest impact if they are (1) grounded in research about successful faculty teaching practices, (2) integrated with local evidence from the College of Engineering, including the institutional context, engineering student perspectives, and engineering faculty perspectives (about their own teaching practices, about how those practices affect student learning, and about factors that influence their motivation to change), and (3) informed by literature on institutional change models, faculty development research, and learning theory. &lt;br/&gt;This is a two year project that will advance knowledge of how to impact faculty change on a large scale. The project is comprised of four phases: &lt;br/&gt;     Phase 1: Contextualize the problem.  It entails synthesizing published literature about faculty teaching practices that support a diverse student body and situating that literature in the local context using data from multiple sources. The data include student demographic and academic data from the registrar, interviews with academic advisors, and classroom observations of engineering faculty who teach undergraduate engineering courses. &lt;br/&gt;     Phase 2: Understand the student perspective. It is comprised of interactions with students at all levels of academic achievement to identify teaching practices perceived by students to support or hinder their success in engineering.  &lt;br/&gt;     Phase 3: Understand the faculty perspective.  It begins with a survey all the engineering instructors and ends with one-on-one interviews with a few in order to: (a) to ascertain faculty beliefs about their own teaching practices and how these practices affect student learning and (b) to identify factors that motivate faculty to change their teaching practices. &lt;br/&gt; Phase 4 (Develop a plan for institutional change) builds on the first three phases. It will also incorporate knowledge derived from published literature on institutional change models, faculty development research, and learning theory. &lt;br/&gt;At the conclusion of the project, a faculty action team will be positioned to initiate an evidence-based change model that has the potential to transform the educational experience for all engineering students. The evidence-based approach to enabling institutional change may serve as a model for other institutions. The analyses of student and faculty data will contribute to the national understanding of issues in engineering education.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>09/20/2010</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>09/16/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.076</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>0941924</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>James</FirstName>
<LastName>Holloway</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>P</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>James P Holloway</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>jpholloway@unm.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5052772611</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000363749</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/20/2010</StartDate>
<EndDate>08/19/2014</EndDate>
<RoleCode>Former Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Cynthia</FirstName>
<LastName>Finelli</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>J</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Cynthia J Finelli</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>cfinelli@umich.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>7347640244</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000318938</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/20/2010</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Regents of the University of Michigan - Ann Arbor</Name>
<CityName>Ann Arbor</CityName>
<ZipCode>481091274</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>7347636438</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>3003 South State St. Room 1062</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Michigan</StateName>
<StateCode>MI</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>12</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MI12</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>073133571</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>REGENTS OF THE UNIVERSITY OF MICHIGAN</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>073133571</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Regents of the University of Michigan - Ann Arbor]]></Name>
<CityName>Ann Arbor</CityName>
<StateCode>MI</StateCode>
<ZipCode>481091274</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[3003 South State St. Room 1062]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Michigan</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>12</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MI12</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1998</Code>
<Text>IUSE</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7494</Code>
<Text>CCLI-Type 1 (Exploratory)</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8209</Code>
<Text>Improv Undergrad STEM Ed(IUSE)</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9178</Code>
<Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>SMET</Code>
<Text>SCIENCE, MATH, ENG &amp; TECH EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0410</Code>
<Name>NSF Education &amp; Human Resource</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040106</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0414</Code>
<Name>NSF Education &amp; Human Resource</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040106</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2010~199999</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~39354</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>There is ample evidence that the way college faculty teach their students can significantly impact student learning. Teaching practices that actively engage students in their own learning, for instance, have been shown to improve students' understanding of engineering concepts, critical thinking ability, and persistence in the engineering field. Such teaching practices have been shown to especially support a diverse group of students, including women and other minorities who are historically underrepresented in engineering. In spite of this evidence, though, many engineering faculty continue to teach using a passive lecture style rather than using other effective teaching practices that allow students to be actively engaged in their learning.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>To assist faculty in using more effective teaching practices, we designed and piloted a unique faculty professional development program at our large research institution. Our program connects local evidence we collected from our own students and faculty with national research about effective teaching and about models of change. In addition, it&nbsp; leverages factors that our research showed are important in motivating faculty to use effective teaching practices at our university (e.g., providing summaries of compelling research on effective teaching, emphasizing the impact of the teaching practices on student learning and diversity, and integrating opportunities to network with other faculty and learn from a supportive community).</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>To date, we have conducted our program six times (our applicant pool exceeded capacity for each offering), and 41 engineering faculty have participated. The program has successfully changed faculty's teaching practices, as measured in three ways. First, faculty's enthusiasm, clarity, and interaction increased significantly as a result of participating in our program, as reported in surveys we administered before and after the program. These indicators decreased for a control group of faculty that did not participate. Second, objective classroom observations conducted before and after the program by trained consultants show that participants&rsquo; teaching changed to include more student engagement and active learning over the term. And third, participant feedback has been overwhelmingly &nbsp;positive, as noted by these two sample comments:&nbsp;</p> <ul> <li>&ldquo;The possibility of changing my classroom from one of passive learning to one of active learning is the big take away point. I now believe that I can undertake such a transition in an incremental fashion that allows me to avoid huge risky time investments and to take corrective action in timely manner.&rdquo;</li> </ul> <ul> <li>&ldquo;The program got me to read helpful resources, which in turn got me thinking about my teaching, and gave me some good ideas about both some short-term easy improvements and some longer-term goals.&rdquo;</li> </ul> <p>&nbsp;</p> <ul> </ul> <ul> </ul> <p>This program can serve as a model for other universities interested in improving the success of their students by changing facuty teaching practices. Creating better engineering college teachers in this way will result in a college experience that is accessible to a more diverse group of students. In turn, this will allow us to&nbsp;graduate stronger students who are better prepared to change the world.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 10/30/2015<br>      Modified by: Cynthia&nbsp;J&nbsp;Finelli</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ There is ample evidence that the way college faculty teach their students can significantly impact student learning. Teaching practices that actively engage students in their own learning, for instance, have been shown to improve students' understanding of engineering concepts, critical thinking ability, and persistence in the engineering field. Such teaching practices have been shown to especially support a diverse group of students, including women and other minorities who are historically underrepresented in engineering. In spite of this evidence, though, many engineering faculty continue to teach using a passive lecture style rather than using other effective teaching practices that allow students to be actively engaged in their learning.     To assist faculty in using more effective teaching practices, we designed and piloted a unique faculty professional development program at our large research institution. Our program connects local evidence we collected from our own students and faculty with national research about effective teaching and about models of change. In addition, it  leverages factors that our research showed are important in motivating faculty to use effective teaching practices at our university (e.g., providing summaries of compelling research on effective teaching, emphasizing the impact of the teaching practices on student learning and diversity, and integrating opportunities to network with other faculty and learn from a supportive community).     To date, we have conducted our program six times (our applicant pool exceeded capacity for each offering), and 41 engineering faculty have participated. The program has successfully changed faculty's teaching practices, as measured in three ways. First, faculty's enthusiasm, clarity, and interaction increased significantly as a result of participating in our program, as reported in surveys we administered before and after the program. These indicators decreased for a control group of faculty that did not participate. Second, objective classroom observations conducted before and after the program by trained consultants show that participantsÆ teaching changed to include more student engagement and active learning over the term. And third, participant feedback has been overwhelmingly  positive, as noted by these two sample comments:   "The possibility of changing my classroom from one of passive learning to one of active learning is the big take away point. I now believe that I can undertake such a transition in an incremental fashion that allows me to avoid huge risky time investments and to take corrective action in timely manner."   "The program got me to read helpful resources, which in turn got me thinking about my teaching, and gave me some good ideas about both some short-term easy improvements and some longer-term goals."          This program can serve as a model for other universities interested in improving the success of their students by changing facuty teaching practices. Creating better engineering college teachers in this way will result in a college experience that is accessible to a more diverse group of students. In turn, this will allow us to graduate stronger students who are better prepared to change the world.       Last Modified: 10/30/2015       Submitted by: Cynthia J Finelli]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
