<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Collaborative Research: Statistical Content Helping to Empower Mathematicians at Two-Year Colleges (SCHEMATYC)</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>05/01/2010</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>10/31/2014</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>112604.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>112604</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>11040200</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>EHR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DUE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Undergraduate Education</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>John Haddock</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>jhaddock@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922671</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Mathematical Sciences (21)&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project is using workshops and a distance-learning course to improve the statistical expertise and pedagogical knowledge of instructors of introductory statistics at 2-year colleges.  The project is conducting a series of eight traveling workshops, each held in conjunction with a regional meeting of the American Mathematical Association of Two-Year Colleges (AMATYC), to disseminate best practices and statistical content knowledge to an audience of instructors who may have limited backgrounds in statistics and limited opportunities for professional development.  In addition, the project is conducting a 2-day workshop in conjunction with the 2010 national AMATYC meeting, is offering a distance learning course, and is establishing online discussion groups for instructors of introductory statistics.  All of these activities are aimed at 2-year college instructors and are addressing both statistical content and pedagogy following recognized national guidelines.  This project is preparing faculty at 2-year colleges to effectively teach introductory statistics by providing access to exemplary resources.  The workshops, distance course, and discussion groups are affecting substantial change in the way introductory statistics is taught at 2-year institutions, and are building a stronger community of introductory statistics instructors.&lt;br/&gt;</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/23/2010</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>03/18/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.076</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>0942924</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Deborah</FirstName>
<LastName>Rumsey</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>J</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Deborah J Rumsey</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>rumsey@stat.osu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6142923732</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000531109</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/23/2010</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Ohio State University</Name>
<CityName>Columbus</CityName>
<ZipCode>432101016</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6146888735</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>Office of Sponsored Programs</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[1960 Kenny Road]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Ohio</StateName>
<StateCode>OH</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>OH03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>832127323</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>OHIO STATE UNIVERSITY, THE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>001964634</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Ohio State University]]></Name>
<CityName>Columbus</CityName>
<StateCode>OH</StateCode>
<ZipCode>432101016</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[Office of Sponsored Programs]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Ohio</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>OH03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1536</Code>
<Text>S-STEM-Schlr Sci Tech Eng&amp;Math</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7494</Code>
<Text>CCLI-Type 1 (Exploratory)</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9178</Code>
<Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>SMET</Code>
<Text>SCIENCE, MATH, ENG &amp; TECH EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0410</Code>
<Name>NSF Education &amp; Human Resource</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040106</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>13XX</Code>
<Name>H-1B FUND, EHR, NSF</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>045176</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2010~112604</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><strong>Special activities coming from the grant:</strong></p> <p><strong>&ldquo;Special Panelist Presentation &ndash; SCHEMATYC Project (NSF)&rdquo;. Electronic Conference on Teaching Statistics, May, 2014. Leaders, Deborah Rumsey and Marjorie Bond. Invited session.</strong></p> <p>This session was viewed by close to 90 people across the world engaged in this electronic conference, hosted by CAUSE (Consortium for the Advancement of Undergraduate Statistics Education). It contained contributions from 4 panelists who were teachers who had been participants in previous SCHEMATYC workshops from the past year, who were now presenting to others on how they are using the ideas from SCHEMATYC in their classrooms.</p> <p>The panelists were:&nbsp;</p> <p><span>Julie </span><span>Couton</span><span>, University of Nebraska - Lincoln</span></p> <p><span>Stephanie Jernigan, Boston College</span></p> <p><span>Naomi Schmidt, New Mexico State University</span></p> <p><span>Karen Wells, Monroe Community College</span></p> <p><span>The presentation was lead by myself and Marjorie Bond. After the presentation was over, teachers who were listening in on the conference asked alot of good questions regarding how to implment the ideas from SCHEMATYC into their own classrooms. The main 'take-away' point, it seemed to me, is that teachers need to spend more time on finding out what their students do and do not understand, so that they can anticipate areas that will be more difficult, and increase their emphasis on intuitive ideas and concepts to help students be more successful. This discussion revolved around ways to do that.</span></p> <p><span>Also during this time, many teachers asked me for copies of the MC/TF questions that made up a big part of the Schematyc Workshops, with the goal of them being to help pinpoint student problems, determine why they are having the problem, and how we can address/head off the problem.&nbsp;</span></p> <p>The SCHEMATYC materials were also incorporated into the GTA (Graduate Teaching Assistant) training for Ohio State in August 2014. These materials were used in two ways: 1) it helped me gauge how well the GTAs themselves understood statistics; as many of them come from various backgrounds besides statistics; and 2) it helped them understand the manner in which we teach statistics at the introductory level. We ended up spending approximately 40% of the training time solely on the conceptual nature of teaching statistics, and how to tackle some of the more difficult topics for students to understand.&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p><span><br /></span></p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 09/15/2015<br>      Modified by: Deborah&nbsp;J&nbsp;Rumsey</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Special activities coming from the grant:  "Special Panelist Presentation &ndash; SCHEMATYC Project (NSF)". Electronic Conference on Teaching Statistics, May, 2014. Leaders, Deborah Rumsey and Marjorie Bond. Invited session.  This session was viewed by close to 90 people across the world engaged in this electronic conference, hosted by CAUSE (Consortium for the Advancement of Undergraduate Statistics Education). It contained contributions from 4 panelists who were teachers who had been participants in previous SCHEMATYC workshops from the past year, who were now presenting to others on how they are using the ideas from SCHEMATYC in their classrooms.  The panelists were:   Julie Couton, University of Nebraska - Lincoln  Stephanie Jernigan, Boston College  Naomi Schmidt, New Mexico State University  Karen Wells, Monroe Community College  The presentation was lead by myself and Marjorie Bond. After the presentation was over, teachers who were listening in on the conference asked alot of good questions regarding how to implment the ideas from SCHEMATYC into their own classrooms. The main 'take-away' point, it seemed to me, is that teachers need to spend more time on finding out what their students do and do not understand, so that they can anticipate areas that will be more difficult, and increase their emphasis on intuitive ideas and concepts to help students be more successful. This discussion revolved around ways to do that.  Also during this time, many teachers asked me for copies of the MC/TF questions that made up a big part of the Schematyc Workshops, with the goal of them being to help pinpoint student problems, determine why they are having the problem, and how we can address/head off the problem.   The SCHEMATYC materials were also incorporated into the GTA (Graduate Teaching Assistant) training for Ohio State in August 2014. These materials were used in two ways: 1) it helped me gauge how well the GTAs themselves understood statistics; as many of them come from various backgrounds besides statistics; and 2) it helped them understand the manner in which we teach statistics at the introductory level. We ended up spending approximately 40% of the training time solely on the conceptual nature of teaching statistics, and how to tackle some of the more difficult topics for students to understand.                    Last Modified: 09/15/2015       Submitted by: Deborah J Rumsey]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
