<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>EMSW21-MCTP:  The Carleton College Summer Mathematics Program for Women</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>05/01/2010</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>04/30/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>1000000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>1000000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DMS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Nandini Kannan</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>nakannan@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032928104</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The Carleton College Summer Mathematics Program (SMP) has operated since 1995.  It is designed to support, encourage and mentor the female participants through all the intellectual, professional, and personal transitions from early undergraduate math major through early career as a practicing professional mathematician.  The literature on increasing female and underrepresented minority participation in mathematics suggests that among the most effective techniques for increasing confidence and success are: emphasizing effort over ability, providing exposure to role models, normalizing struggle (i.e., show that everyone struggles), and employing group work that builds interdependence. The SMP consciously and deliberately uses all these techniques. The instructors and directors design the program and the courses so that every participant is deeply challenged and maximally supported so that her efforts lead to success. The large SMP community ---consisting of approximately three hundred female mathematicians ranging from undergraduate mathematics majors, to graduate students,  to young PhDs and mid-career professionals--- provides a rich resource of ready and willing mentors and role models. SMP participants self-report in post-program evaluations increased knowledge of graduate school and the mathematical community, increased confidence in their ability to earn a PhD, and increased likelihood of doing so. SMP alumnae surveyed post-PhD report that SMP was an important source of inspiration, knowledge and confidence building.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This proposal will fund i) a four-week intensive program of mathematical immersion for undergraduate female mathematics majors held at Carleton each summer from 2010 to 2014, ii) an annual summer reunion conference for program alumnae who subsequently earned PhDs in mathematics, and iii) an annual winter workshop for advising and mentoring program alumnae in graduate school working towards the PhD.   These activities are designed with the goal of increasing the number of female mathematical scientists in the US.   The summer undergraduate program does an exceptional job at helping our student participants make the transition from a computational view of mathematics to a more theoretical understanding. We advise and assist our alumnae in finding an appropriate experience for the summer between the junior and senior undergraduate years. And we provide counsel and support as they choose graduate programs and, increasingly in recent years, extensive advice and counsel to our PhD alumnae as they enter the academic job market.  The winter workshop for graduate students, a new feature with this proposal, is designed to renew our contacts with alumnae and aid them as they choose an advisor, make the transition from coursework to research and later from student to young professional.  By 2014, the end of the period of support sought under this proposal, we expect that SMP alumnae will have earned approximately 140 Masters degrees and at least 70 PhDs, with another 50-60 SMP alumnae in or entering graduate programs in mathematical sciences. Ultimately the community of PhD alumnae of SMP supported under this and previous grants should number approximately 140. (There is a seven- to ten-year lag in completing a PhD after completing SMP since program participants are women in their first two years of undergraduate study.) These women will not only have PhDs, they will have productive careers and the inclination to give back in the form of mentoring and encouraging other young women.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>04/15/2010</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>09/03/2013</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>0943597</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Stephen</FirstName>
<LastName>Kennedy</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>F</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Stephen F Kennedy</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>skennedy@carleton.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5076634333</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000092156</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/15/2010</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Deanna</FirstName>
<LastName>Haunsperger</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>B</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Deanna B Haunsperger</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>dhaunspe@carleton.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5072224362</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000387987</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/15/2010</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Carleton College</Name>
<CityName>Northfield</CityName>
<ZipCode>550574001</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5072224303</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>One North College Street</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Minnesota</StateName>
<StateCode>MN</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MN02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>068184449</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>CARLETON COLLEGE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>068184449</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Carleton College]]></Name>
<CityName>Northfield</CityName>
<StateCode>MN</StateCode>
<ZipCode>550574001</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[One North College Street]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Minnesota</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MN02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7335</Code>
<Text>WORKFORCE IN THE MATHEMAT SCI</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7302</Code>
<Text>MENTOR THR CRIT TRANS PTS IN THE MAT SCI</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0110</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0113</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2010~596716</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2013~403284</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The Carleton Summer Mathematics Program for Women (SMP) was established in 1995 as a summer program for early-stage undergraduate women interested in mathematics to address the paucity of women earning advanced degrees in mathematical sciences in the US. &nbsp;SMP was designed to give them some of the tools they need along with the information, role models, and confidence, to encourage them to earn an advanced degree in a mathematical science. &nbsp;The participants took two intense courses in areas of mathematics they wouldn't normally see as an undergraduate (such as Lie Theory or Low-Dimensional Dynamics), attended colloquia, had conversations about succeeding at graduate school and career possibilities with advanced degrees in mathematics, and they formed a kind of mathematical sisterhood and support network, ready to help each other through the sometimes-difficult transitions of graduate school.</p> <p>As the community of former participants grew over the years, mentoring at different stages of their progress through the pipeline was added, including a one day workshop, the Graduate Education Mentoring workshop, in conjunction with the Joint Mathematics Meetings to provide encouragement, information, and mentoring for women in graduate school in mathematics; the women discuss concerns they are having about their graduate experience, how to pick an advisor, how to get research started, and how to give a good talk. &nbsp;Also added over the years was a summer conference, the SMPosium, to honor women who finished their PhDs while giving them the opportunity to talk about the next stages of their careers: &nbsp;learning to teach, maintaining a research career, and work/life balance. &nbsp;</p> <p>This five-year grant, along with the two no-cost extensions, kept this community active for the past seven years. &nbsp;During that time, 92 young women participated in the summer program SMP, 108 (not unique) women participated in the SMPosium, and 104 (not unique) women participated in the Graduate Education Mentoring workshop. &nbsp;Twice yearly newsletters and information was sent out from the directors to keep the community active, and there was a reunion dinner once a year for participants from various years and various stages in their careers to meet each other. &nbsp;</p> <p>Most of the women who've been through the program credit the program for playing a role in their decision to apply to graduate school and their ability to earn an advanced degree. &nbsp;The numbers bear this out: &nbsp;of the approximately 350 undergraduates receiving mentoring under the program, 102 have earned PhDs in a mathematical science (six of those in cognate disciplines, like engineering). &nbsp;There are an additional 60 who are in graduate school currently. &nbsp;The program has been recognized by the American Mathematical Society as a "Program that Makes a Difference."</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 07/11/2017<br>      Modified by: Deanna&nbsp;B&nbsp;Haunsperger</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The Carleton Summer Mathematics Program for Women (SMP) was established in 1995 as a summer program for early-stage undergraduate women interested in mathematics to address the paucity of women earning advanced degrees in mathematical sciences in the US.  SMP was designed to give them some of the tools they need along with the information, role models, and confidence, to encourage them to earn an advanced degree in a mathematical science.  The participants took two intense courses in areas of mathematics they wouldn't normally see as an undergraduate (such as Lie Theory or Low-Dimensional Dynamics), attended colloquia, had conversations about succeeding at graduate school and career possibilities with advanced degrees in mathematics, and they formed a kind of mathematical sisterhood and support network, ready to help each other through the sometimes-difficult transitions of graduate school.  As the community of former participants grew over the years, mentoring at different stages of their progress through the pipeline was added, including a one day workshop, the Graduate Education Mentoring workshop, in conjunction with the Joint Mathematics Meetings to provide encouragement, information, and mentoring for women in graduate school in mathematics; the women discuss concerns they are having about their graduate experience, how to pick an advisor, how to get research started, and how to give a good talk.  Also added over the years was a summer conference, the SMPosium, to honor women who finished their PhDs while giving them the opportunity to talk about the next stages of their careers:  learning to teach, maintaining a research career, and work/life balance.    This five-year grant, along with the two no-cost extensions, kept this community active for the past seven years.  During that time, 92 young women participated in the summer program SMP, 108 (not unique) women participated in the SMPosium, and 104 (not unique) women participated in the Graduate Education Mentoring workshop.  Twice yearly newsletters and information was sent out from the directors to keep the community active, and there was a reunion dinner once a year for participants from various years and various stages in their careers to meet each other.    Most of the women who've been through the program credit the program for playing a role in their decision to apply to graduate school and their ability to earn an advanced degree.  The numbers bear this out:  of the approximately 350 undergraduates receiving mentoring under the program, 102 have earned PhDs in a mathematical science (six of those in cognate disciplines, like engineering).  There are an additional 60 who are in graduate school currently.  The program has been recognized by the American Mathematical Society as a "Program that Makes a Difference."          Last Modified: 07/11/2017       Submitted by: Deanna B Haunsperger]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
