<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Collaborative Research: Annual satellite era accumulation patterns over WAIS Divide: A study using shallow ice cores, near-surface radars and satellites</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2010</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2014</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>226727.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>232977</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>06090300</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>GEO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>OPP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Office of Polar Programs (OPP)</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Paul Cutler</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>pcutler@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924961</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This award supports a project to broaden the knowledge of annual accumulation patterns over the West Antarctic Ice Sheet by processing existing near-surface radar data taken on the US ITASE traverse in 2000 and by gathering and validating new ultra/super-high-frequency (UHF) radar images of near surface layers (to depths of ~15 m), expanding abilities to monitor recent annual accumulation patterns from point source ice cores to radar lines. Shallow (15 m) ice cores will be collected in conjunction with UHF radar images to confirm that radar echoed returns correspond with annual layers, and/or sub-annual density changes in the near-surface snow, as determined from ice core stable isotopes.  This project will additionally improve accumulation monitoring from space-borne instruments by comparing the spatial-radar-derived-annual accumulation time series to the passive microwave time series dating back over 3 decades and covering most of Antarctica. The intellectual merit of this project is that mapping the spatial and temporal variations in accumulation rates over the Antarctic ice sheet is essential for understanding ice sheet responses to climate forcing. Antarctic precipitation rate is projected to increase up to 20% in the coming century from the predicted warming.  Accumulation is a key component for determining ice sheet mass balance and, hence, sea level rise, yet our ability to measure annual accumulation variability over the past 5 decades (satellite era) is mostly limited to point-source ice cores. Developing a radar and ice core derived annual accumulation dataset will provide validation data for space-born remote sensing algorithms, climate models and, additionally, establish accumulation trends. The broader impacts of the project are that it will advance discovery and understanding within the climatology, glaciology and remote sensing communities by verifying the use of UHF radars to monitor annual layers as determined by visual, chemical and isotopic analysis from corresponding shallow ice cores and will provide a dataset of annual to near-annual accumulation measurements over the past ~5 decades across WAIS divide from existing radar data and proposed radar data. By determining if temporal changes in the passive microwave signal are correlated with temporal changes in accumulation will help assess the utility of passive microwave remote sensing to monitor accumulation rates over ice sheets for future decades. The project will promote teaching, training and learning, and increase representation of underrepresented groups by becoming involved in the NASA History of Winter project and Thermochron Mission and by providing K-12 teachers with training to monitor snow accumulation and temperature here in the US, linking polar research to the student?s backyard.  The project will train both undergraduate and graduate students in polar research and will encouraging young investigators to become involved in careers in science. In particular, two REU students will participate in original research projects as part of this larger project, from development of a hypothesis to presentation and publication of the results.  The support of a new, young woman scientist will help to increase gender diversity in polar research.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/11/2010</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/29/2013</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.078</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>0944730</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Summer</FirstName>
<LastName>Rupper</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>B</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Summer B Rupper</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>summer.rupper@geog.utah.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>8015859167</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000500016</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/11/2010</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Brigham Young University</Name>
<CityName>Provo</CityName>
<ZipCode>846021231</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>8014223360</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>A-285 ASB</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[Campus Drive]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Utah</StateName>
<StateCode>UT</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>UT03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>009094012</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>BRIGHAM YOUNG UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>001940170</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Brigham Young University]]></Name>
<CityName>Provo</CityName>
<StateCode>UT</StateCode>
<ZipCode>846021231</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[A-285 ASB]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Utah</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>UT03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>5116</Code>
<Text>ANT Glaciology</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>0000</Code>
<Text>UNASSIGNED</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9251</Code>
<Text>REU SUPP-Res Exp for Ugrd Supp</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>02XX</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2010~96140</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2011~71946</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2012~58641</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2013~6250</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The West Antarctic Ice Sheet (WAIS) is a dynamic ice sheet that has changed in the past and is still changing today. WAIS is a marine based ice sheet that is vulnerable to both atmospheric and oceanic warming. WAIS&rsquo;s unique setting causes concern that increased warming will increase ice mass loss, from both above and below, resulting in sea level rise. Consequently, WAIS has been the focus of numerous studies determining changes in ice dynamics, mass balance, temperature trends and accumulation, providing a rich historical setting and making it a well suited area to study recent variations in accumulation. As temperatures warm, and are predicted to warm, over WAIS, increases in precipitation are expected. While a clear trend has emerged for warming temperatures over WAIS, no clear trend has emerged for accumulation, which is most likely due to the lack of spatially and temporally extensive <em>in-situ </em>data and uncertainties in atmospheric models. In this project, we drilled 14 new, strategically placed ice cores in order to help fill this data need, and analyzed accumulation variability and trends close to the divide of the WAIS (Figure 1). Counter to expectations, we show that accumulation rates have decreased significantly over the period of significant warming (Figure 2). This is most likely due to associated trends in the atmospheric low pressure system off the coast of WAIS that play a significant role in WAIS weather patterns (Figure 3). The results suggest that, at least over the past few decades, temperature changes have not been the primary driver of accumulation changes. Instead, recent trends in accumulation are driven by the atmospheric circulation response to those temperature changes. Thus, changes in atmospheric circulation will have a significant influence on the spatial and temporal patterns in accumulation; therefore, a uniform change in accumulation should not be the expectation. Even if the entire ice sheet were to warm uniformly, even the sign of the accumulation response may differ from one region to the next.</p> <p>This NSF award benefited numerous students and early-career scientists. Thirteen undergraduate students and three graduate students participated in this project, gaining valuable research experience. Two, female, early-career scientists were also supported by these NSF funds. As part of our outreach efforts, all studetns and scientists focused efforts on sharing the results with the broader community. We kept a blog for elementary school students during the first field season, allowing them to track our progress and ask questions. We visited many of these classrooms following the field season. We kept a blog published through NASA aimed at the general public during the second field season, carefully responding to public comments. We have also given numerous public presentations through library speaker series, university forums, and the public school system throughout the project period. Finally, all data have been made publicly available, and will hopefully be of benefit to both the educational and scientific communities.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 12/06/2014<br>      Modified by: Summer&nbsp;B&nbsp;Rupper</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Images (<span id="selectedPhoto0">1</span> of <span class="totalNumber"></span>)           </div> <div class="galControls" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2014/0944730/0944730_10020236_1417894760695_SEATMap--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2014/0944730/0944730_10020236_1417894760695_SEATMap--rgov-800width.j...]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The West Antarctic Ice Sheet (WAIS) is a dynamic ice sheet that has changed in the past and is still changing today. WAIS is a marine based ice sheet that is vulnerable to both atmospheric and oceanic warming. WAISÆs unique setting causes concern that increased warming will increase ice mass loss, from both above and below, resulting in sea level rise. Consequently, WAIS has been the focus of numerous studies determining changes in ice dynamics, mass balance, temperature trends and accumulation, providing a rich historical setting and making it a well suited area to study recent variations in accumulation. As temperatures warm, and are predicted to warm, over WAIS, increases in precipitation are expected. While a clear trend has emerged for warming temperatures over WAIS, no clear trend has emerged for accumulation, which is most likely due to the lack of spatially and temporally extensive in-situ data and uncertainties in atmospheric models. In this project, we drilled 14 new, strategically placed ice cores in order to help fill this data need, and analyzed accumulation variability and trends close to the divide of the WAIS (Figure 1). Counter to expectations, we show that accumulation rates have decreased significantly over the period of significant warming (Figure 2). This is most likely due to associated trends in the atmospheric low pressure system off the coast of WAIS that play a significant role in WAIS weather patterns (Figure 3). The results suggest that, at least over the past few decades, temperature changes have not been the primary driver of accumulation changes. Instead, recent trends in accumulation are driven by the atmospheric circulation response to those temperature changes. Thus, changes in atmospheric circulation will have a significant influence on the spatial and temporal patterns in accumulation; therefore, a uniform change in accumulation should not be the expectation. Even if the entire ice sheet were to warm uniformly, even the sign of the accumulation response may differ from one region to the next.  This NSF award benefited numerous students and early-career scientists. Thirteen undergraduate students and three graduate students participated in this project, gaining valuable research experience. Two, female, early-career scientists were also supported by these NSF funds. As part of our outreach efforts, all studetns and scientists focused efforts on sharing the results with the broader community. We kept a blog for elementary school students during the first field season, allowing them to track our progress and ask questions. We visited many of these classrooms following the field season. We kept a blog published through NASA aimed at the general public during the second field season, carefully responding to public comments. We have also given numerous public presentations through library speaker series, university forums, and the public school system throughout the project period. Finally, all data have been made publicly available, and will hopefully be of benefit to both the educational and scientific communities.       Last Modified: 12/06/2014       Submitted by: Summer B Rupper]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
