<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Industry Defined Fundamental Research</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2009</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>09/30/2013</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>1177204.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>1199204</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07070000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>IIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Industrial Innovation &amp; Partnersh</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Prakash Balan</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>pbalan@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032925341</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>PROGRAM DIRECTOR'S RECOMMENDATION&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;0946275 Industrial Research Institute (IRI); Edward Bernstein&lt;br/&gt;   &lt;br/&gt;The purpose of this proposal is for IRI, leveraging its membership, connections and loyalty within American Industry, help define fundamental research requirements that will have a direct effect on the success of American Industry.  The proposed work will help create a new, original, method of developing a scientific agenda that can lead to exciting research in areas such as batteries, low-cost photovoltaics, and others.  &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The proposed work will promote partnerships between industry and academia and, therefore, will increase learning on both sides by exposure to new science and technology contained in each one?s organizations.  IRI is committed to diversity in all its programs and services.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/10/2009</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/28/2012</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>0946275</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Edward</FirstName>
<LastName>Bernstein</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Edward Bernstein</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>bernstein@iriweb.org</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>7036472580</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000532815</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/10/2009</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>INDUSTRIAL RESEARCH INSTITUTE INC</Name>
<CityName>Arlington</CityName>
<ZipCode>222013331</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>7036472595</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>2200 CLARENDON BLVD STE 1102</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Virginia</StateName>
<StateCode>VA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>08</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>VA08</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>078848744</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>INDUSTRIAL RESEARCH INSTITUTE, INC.</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[INDUSTRIAL RESEARCH INSTITUTE INC]]></Name>
<CityName>Arlington</CityName>
<StateCode>VA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>222013331</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[2200 CLARENDON BLVD STE 1102]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Virginia</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>08</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>VA08</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<FoaInformation>
<Code>0400000</Code>
<Name>Industry University - Co-op</Name>
</FoaInformation>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>5761</Code>
<Text>IUCRC-Indust-Univ Coop Res Ctr</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>0000</Code>
<Text>UNASSIGNED</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1049</Code>
<Text>INDUSTRY-UNIV COOPERATIVE RSCH PROJECTS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>122E</Code>
<Text>CENTERS: OTHER INDUSTRY-UNIV</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>5761</Code>
<Text>INDUSTRY/UNIV COOP RES CENTERS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>OTHR</Code>
<Text>OTHER RESEARCH OR EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0109</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0110</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2009~1177204</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2010~22000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The long-term competitiveness of the United States and its reliance on research and development has recently been the subject of several important studies. An analysis of these studies showed a consensus that the United States must do more to strengthen our capacity for science-based innovation.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>Furthermore, there is a need to use our global leadership in basic science to further the overall good. Federally financed basic science can and should lead to an improved quality of life for Americans by improving both the security and economy of America. This can be achieved by generating and acting on more direct input from across a number of industry sectors concerning NSF-funded basic science research conducted in universities.&nbsp;&nbsp; This project discovers and catalogs issues that arise in generating that input in order to inform and guide future efforts.&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p><span style="text-decoration: underline;">Intellectual Merit</span></p> <p>This approach provides a unique mechanism for defining fundamental research relevant to industry needs which will advance understanding of how NSF research can be effectively geared to meeting industry and national needs. This project has created a new, original, method of developing a scientific agenda which has led to the funding of basic research in fields that could increase our fundamental understanding of adhesion as well as develop lignin, a natural and domestically abundant feed-stock, as a source for new materials.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p><span style="text-decoration: underline;">Broader Impact</span></p> <p>The interaction of industry researchers with the academic institutions has enhanced the breadth of teaching experience by providing training for both academic and industry researchers in new methods of collaboration. Additionally, IRI is committed to diversity in all its programs and services. In our most recent CTO Forum, 40% of delegates were women or minorities; we have sought similar participation in this and all other IRI programs. Finally, by requiring partnerships between industry and academia, the United States has realized the wider application and use of the scientific advances.</p> <p><span style="text-decoration: underline;">Key outcomes or Other achievements</span>:</p> <p>Philippe H. Geubelle at the University of Illinois at Urbana Champaign was awarded $500,000 to research <em>Multiscale Modeling and Assessment of Interfacial Adhesion Failure in Polymeric Coatings andMultilayered Devices</em>. Contributions withing the discipline include:</p> <ul> <li>Laser-based extraction of fracture energy of strong interface between polymeric coating and Si;</li> <li>Quantification of impact of surface treatment and curing process for Si/Polyimide interface;</li> <li>First demonstration of laser-?&#8208;induced spallation test on coating/metal interface;</li> <li>Development of fully 3D Interface GFEM multiscale cohesive framework that extracts physically-motivated macroscopic cohesive failure laws for bonded; structures based on failure processes taking place in heterogeneous adhesive</li> <li>First study of impact of in-plane deformations on cohesive failure law for heterogeneous adhesives;</li> <li>Mulecular Dynamics (MD) modeling of interface between covalent solid (Si/SiO2) and soft-matter system (Polyimide), showing the key role played by the polymer layer relaxation on the predicted strength of the interface;</li> <li>Application of laser-induced spallation test and MD modeling to the failure assessment of molecular tailoring of Si/Au interfaces using self-?&#8208;assembled monolayers.</li> </ul> <p>Dimitris Argyropoulos at North Carolina State University was awarded $500,000 to research <em>Catalytic Oxidation Chemistry Aimed at Upgrading Lignin</em>. He&nbsp;evaluated&nbsp;three general strategies for the potential of transition metal complexes to cleave critical bonds in lignin streams. Lignin is the second in abundance component of woody plants with a highly branched and irregular structure. This material represents an integral component of the actual paper manufacturing process, since it is incinerated to recover energy and chemicals. Technical ligninsources represent potential fuel sources.</p> <p>The research concluded that the creation of functional dimers from vanillin or related oxidation products of lignin may offer new pathways for the synthesis of lignin based copolymers.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 07/31/2020<br>      Modified by: Edward&nbsp;Bernstein</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The long-term competitiveness of the United States and its reliance on research and development has recently been the subject of several important studies. An analysis of these studies showed a consensus that the United States must do more to strengthen our capacity for science-based innovation.     Furthermore, there is a need to use our global leadership in basic science to further the overall good. Federally financed basic science can and should lead to an improved quality of life for Americans by improving both the security and economy of America. This can be achieved by generating and acting on more direct input from across a number of industry sectors concerning NSF-funded basic science research conducted in universities.   This project discovers and catalogs issues that arise in generating that input in order to inform and guide future efforts.      Intellectual Merit  This approach provides a unique mechanism for defining fundamental research relevant to industry needs which will advance understanding of how NSF research can be effectively geared to meeting industry and national needs. This project has created a new, original, method of developing a scientific agenda which has led to the funding of basic research in fields that could increase our fundamental understanding of adhesion as well as develop lignin, a natural and domestically abundant feed-stock, as a source for new materials.     Broader Impact  The interaction of industry researchers with the academic institutions has enhanced the breadth of teaching experience by providing training for both academic and industry researchers in new methods of collaboration. Additionally, IRI is committed to diversity in all its programs and services. In our most recent CTO Forum, 40% of delegates were women or minorities; we have sought similar participation in this and all other IRI programs. Finally, by requiring partnerships between industry and academia, the United States has realized the wider application and use of the scientific advances.  Key outcomes or Other achievements:  Philippe H. Geubelle at the University of Illinois at Urbana Champaign was awarded $500,000 to research Multiscale Modeling and Assessment of Interfacial Adhesion Failure in Polymeric Coatings andMultilayered Devices. Contributions withing the discipline include:  Laser-based extraction of fracture energy of strong interface between polymeric coating and Si; Quantification of impact of surface treatment and curing process for Si/Polyimide interface; First demonstration of laser-?&#8208;induced spallation test on coating/metal interface; Development of fully 3D Interface GFEM multiscale cohesive framework that extracts physically-motivated macroscopic cohesive failure laws for bonded; structures based on failure processes taking place in heterogeneous adhesive First study of impact of in-plane deformations on cohesive failure law for heterogeneous adhesives; Mulecular Dynamics (MD) modeling of interface between covalent solid (Si/SiO2) and soft-matter system (Polyimide), showing the key role played by the polymer layer relaxation on the predicted strength of the interface; Application of laser-induced spallation test and MD modeling to the failure assessment of molecular tailoring of Si/Au interfaces using self-?&#8208;assembled monolayers.   Dimitris Argyropoulos at North Carolina State University was awarded $500,000 to research Catalytic Oxidation Chemistry Aimed at Upgrading Lignin. He evaluated three general strategies for the potential of transition metal complexes to cleave critical bonds in lignin streams. Lignin is the second in abundance component of woody plants with a highly branched and irregular structure. This material represents an integral component of the actual paper manufacturing process, since it is incinerated to recover energy and chemicals. Technical ligninsources represent potential fuel sources.  The research concluded that the creation of functional dimers from vanillin or related oxidation products of lignin may offer new pathways for the synthesis of lignin based copolymers.             Last Modified: 07/31/2020       Submitted by: Edward Bernstein]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
