<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>New, GK-12: Initiating New Science Partnerships in Rural Education (INSPIRE)</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>05/15/2010</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>04/30/2016</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>2881898.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>2881898</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>11010000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>EHR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DGE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Graduate Education</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Laura Regassa</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>&lt;br/&gt;The Initiating New Science Partnerships in Rural Education (INSPIRE) project between Mississippi State University and three rural school districts in North-Central Mississippi focuses on technology-supported, inquiry learning in the Earth and Space sciences for 7th-12th grade classrooms.  The interdisciplinary project will recruit 50 Fellows from three STEM disciplines (Geosciences, Physics, and Engineering) where they will be partnered 2:1 with a teacher.  The innovative aspect of this project includes the use of spatial analysis platforms (e.g., Google Earth) during the classroom implementation of graduate student research.  The project aims to achieve five essential goals: 1) enhance Fellows? communication, teaching, and team-building skills; 2) develop and implement technology-supported, inquiry-based instructional materials that infuse Fellows? STEM research; 3) increase K-12 science teachers? content knowledge and technological skills; 4) build partnerships between K-12 school districts and University STEM disciplines that serve to support K-12 students? pursuit of higher education and STEM-related careers; 5) provide international research experiences for Fellows and teachers where they receive training across geographic borders.  The intellectual merit of the project is the incorporation of Fellows? scientific research into the classroom through the use of technology and the extension of this research beyond our nation through international training experiences.  The broader impacts of the project include creating future STEM leaders that conduct cutting-edge science, have solid communication skills, and possess a passion for supporting science education; building a skilled STEM workforce in Mississippi; and developing sustainability and institutional change for GK-12 type activities at MSU beyond the lifetime of the project.  &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>05/17/2010</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>03/07/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.076</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>0947419</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Sandra</FirstName>
<LastName>Harpole</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>H</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Sandra H Harpole</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>sharpole@research.msstate.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6623252922</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000355507</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/17/2010</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Darrel</FirstName>
<LastName>Schmitz</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>W</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Darrel W Schmitz</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>schmitz@geosci.msstate.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6623252131</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000481656</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>03/07/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Darrel</FirstName>
<LastName>Schmitz</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>W</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Darrel W Schmitz</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>schmitz@geosci.msstate.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6623252131</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000481656</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/17/2010</StartDate>
<EndDate>03/07/2014</EndDate>
<RoleCode>Former Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Karen</FirstName>
<LastName>McNeal</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>S</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Karen S McNeal</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>karen.mcneal@auburn.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>3348444282</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000303255</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/17/2010</StartDate>
<EndDate>03/07/2014</EndDate>
<RoleCode>Former Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Lori</FirstName>
<LastName>Bruce</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>M</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Lori M Bruce</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>bruce@ece.msstate.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6623257404</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000507913</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/17/2010</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Donna</FirstName>
<LastName>Pierce</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Donna Pierce</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>dmp149@msstate.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6623252914</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000507924</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/17/2010</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Mississippi State University</Name>
<CityName>MISSISSIPPI STATE</CityName>
<ZipCode>397629662</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6623257404</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>PO Box 6156</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Mississippi</StateName>
<StateCode>MS</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MS03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>075461814</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>MISSISSIPPI STATE UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>075461814</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Mississippi State University]]></Name>
<CityName>MISSISSIPPI STATE</CityName>
<StateCode>MS</StateCode>
<ZipCode>397629662</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[PO Box 6156]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Mississippi</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MS03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>5284</Code>
<Text>GK-12</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7179</Code>
<Text>GRAD TEACHING FELLOWS IN K-12</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7179</Code>
<Text>GRAD TEACHING FELLOWS IN K-12</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9179</Code>
<Text>GRADUATE INVOLVEMENT</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>SMET</Code>
<Text>SCIENCE, MATH, ENG &amp; TECH EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0110</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0410</Code>
<Name>NSF Education &amp; Human Resource</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040106</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0411</Code>
<Name>NSF Education &amp; Human Resource</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040106</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0412</Code>
<Name>NSF Education &amp; Human Resource</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040106</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0413</Code>
<Name>NSF Education &amp; Human Resource</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040106</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2010~564855</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2011~571826</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2012~576784</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2013~1168433</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The Mississippi State University Initiating New Science Partnerships in Rural Education (INSPIRE) program was established to improve Science Technology Engineering Mathematics (STEM) education through interventions targeting a diverse group of stakeholders. The inclusion of Scientists, Teachers, K-12 Students, Graduate Student Fellows, and School Administrators, has lead to a robust understanding of our STEM education system. Intellectual merit achieved through this project includes the dissemination of Fellows&rsquo; research to an international community of scientists and the incorporation scientific research into the K-12 classroom. The broader impacts of this project include creating future STEM leaders that conduct cutting-edge science, have solid communication skills, and possess a passion for supporting science education.</p> <p>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; Outcomes were addressed through both short and long term goals. Four short term goals and objectives of INSPIRE included: (1) To meet a critical need for STEM graduate student training in research and teaching, while providing educational support through the use of inquiry based learning and increased STEM expertise of the Space and Earth Sciences. (2) Enhance STEM graduate students communication skills, and build strong mutual learning partnerships between Scientists, Fellows, Teachers and Administrators. (3) To provide international research experiences for Fellows and Teachers. (4) To help STEM Fellows expand their understanding science through the development of inquiry-based instructional materials connecting their research to K-12. Five long term goals of INSPIRE included: (1) To increase graduate student professional development in an effort to sustain future national success in science while better preparing STEM graduate students for their professions. (2) To strengthen the STEM graduate students communication ability. (3) To create lesson plans as a collaborative effort between Fellows and teachers that support the National Standards of Science and Mathematics. (4) To leverage partnerships formed between the K-12 school districts and the university STEM disciplines to support K-12 students&rsquo; pursuit of higher education and STEM related careers. (5) To increase K-12 participating STEM teachers&rsquo; content knowledge and technological skills.</p> <p>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; External evaluation confirmed that the MSU INSPIRE project through grant related activities, has not only met these goals but also developed new understandings about the pedagogical nature of teaching and preparing individuals to be effective science educators. The team aspect of instruction, including both the participant teachers and fellows, has proven to be a very powerful aspect of the INSPIRE program. This cooperative teaching model draws on the experience and background knowledge of both individuals. It requires them to plan and deliver content that is not only aligned with students&rsquo; prior knowledge, but also on target with the goals and objectives for future learning. Although classroom observations confirm the strength of this model, teachers explained that this relationship was not as productive in the beginning of the INSPIRE program. As participant teachers gained experience working with the fellows they began to open up their classroom and share more of the instruction time. To further explain this phenomenon, teachers described how initially they were skeptical of the fellows&rsquo; ability to teach. There was a reluctance to take on the role of teaching the fellows how to teach, but with time they slowly accepted the role of a coach or guide. In other words, as teachers become more experienced with the implementation of the cooperative teaching model their ability to impact the fellows&rsquo; perception of effective teaching increased. Training offered by Presentation Boot Camp (PBC) gave teachers a framework to provide structured feedback enabling them to address specific areas of concern with their fellows. Classroom observations revealed that participant teachers implemented elements of PBC into their classroom instruction directly improving instruction in the K-12 classroom. It is believed trainings such as this, in combination with experience in the cooperative teaching model, improve a teacher's ability to support fellows.</p> <p>As a result of their participation, the participant advisors and leadership team have shown improvement in these areas as well. The improved ability to effectively communicate scientific research and findings established through the MSU inspire program, has directly influenced the standards at which graduate students are expected to perform during a delivery of their thesis or dissertation. This measurable increase in expectations is an indicator of institutional change for GK-12 type activities at MSU and evidence of its impact that will extend beyond the lifetime of the project.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 07/29/2016<br>      Modified by: Darrel&nbsp;W&nbsp;Schmitz</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Images (<span id="selectedPhoto0">1</span> of <span class="totalNumber"></span>)           </div> <div class="galControls" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2016/0947419/0947419_10016082_1469818920668_CMS_Wx--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2016/0947419/0947419_10016082_1469818920668_CMS_Wx--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Weather Data Collection &amp; Comparison"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2016/0947419/0947419_10016082_1469818920668_CMS_Wx--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Weather Data Collection &amp; Comparison"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">8th grade students collecting weather data at Columbus Middle School using hand-held weather stations provided by NSF GK12 INSPIRE</div> <div class="imageCredit">Sarah Radencic</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Public Domain</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Darrel&nbsp;W&nbsp;Schmitz</div> <div class="imageTitle">Weather Data Collection & Comparison</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2016/0947419/0947419_10016082_1469818801061_GISday1--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2016/0947419/0947419_10016082_1469818801061_GISday1--rgov-800width.jpg" title="National GIS Day: Natural Hazards"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2016/0947419/0947419_10016082_1469818801061_GISday1--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="National GIS Day: Natural Hazards"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">7th grade Columbus Middle School student exploring ArcGIS to investigate possible safe routes during a natural hazard event during National GIS Day activities developed by NSF GK12 INSPIRE Fellows</div> <div class="imageCredit">Julian Carroll</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Public Domain</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Darrel&nbsp;W&nbsp;Schmitz</div> <div class="imageTitle">National GIS Day: Natural Hazards</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2016/0947419/0947419_10016082_1469819623204_CHS_GPS--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2016/0947419/0947419_10016082_1469819623204_CHS_GPS--rgov-800width.jpg" title="GPS, Geometry, and Engineering"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2016/0947419/0947419_10016082_1469819623204_CHS_GPS--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="GPS, Geometry, and Engineering"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Columbus High School geometry students using GPS units and Google Earth to triangulate locations to determine the height of neighboring buildings.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Sarah Radencic</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Darrel&nbsp;W&nbsp;Schmitz</div> <div class="imageTitle">GPS, Geometry, and Engineering</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2016/0947419/0947419_10016082_1469820249629_Calista_Australia--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2016/0947419/0947419_10016082_1469820249629_Calista_Australia--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Environmental Water Investigations in Australia"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2016/0947419/0947419_10016082_1469820249629_Calista_Australia--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Environmental Water Investigations in Australia"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">NSF GK12 INSPIRE Fellow, Calista Guthrie, conducting research of wetland environments with Charles Darwin University in Australia.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Calista Guthrie</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Public Domain</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Darrel&nbsp;W&nbsp;Schmitz</div> <div class="imageTitle">Environmental Water Investigations in Australia</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2016/0947419/0947419_10016082_1469820415033_Will_Poland--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2016/0947419/0947419_10016082_1469820415033_Will_Poland--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Poland Hydrology"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2016/0947419/0947419_10016082_1469820415033_Will_Poland--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Poland Hydrology"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">NSF GK12 INSPIRE Fellow, William McBryde, researching hydrologic systems of Poland in partnership with the Marie Curie - Sklodowska University of Lublin.</div> <div class="imageCredit">William McBryde</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Public Domain</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Darrel&nbsp;W&nbsp;Schmitz</div> <div class="imageTitle">Poland Hydrology</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2016/0947419/0947419_10016082_1469820793854_WS_GPS--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2016/0947419/0947419_10016082_1469820793854_WS_GPS--rgov-800width.jpg" title="INSPIRE Summer Workshop"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2016/0947419/0947419_10016082_1469820793854_WS_GPS--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="INSPIRE Summer Workshop"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">NSF GK12 INSPIRE Fellows, Nathan Owens and Amy Martin, work with their Starkville High School partner teacher, Kelli Dawkins, to solve a geocache activity during an INSPIRE summer training workshop.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Julian Carroll</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Public Domain</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Darrel&nbsp;W&nbsp;Schmitz</div> <div class="imageTitle">INSPIRE Summer Workshop</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The Mississippi State University Initiating New Science Partnerships in Rural Education (INSPIRE) program was established to improve Science Technology Engineering Mathematics (STEM) education through interventions targeting a diverse group of stakeholders. The inclusion of Scientists, Teachers, K-12 Students, Graduate Student Fellows, and School Administrators, has lead to a robust understanding of our STEM education system. Intellectual merit achieved through this project includes the dissemination of Fellows? research to an international community of scientists and the incorporation scientific research into the K-12 classroom. The broader impacts of this project include creating future STEM leaders that conduct cutting-edge science, have solid communication skills, and possess a passion for supporting science education.              Outcomes were addressed through both short and long term goals. Four short term goals and objectives of INSPIRE included: (1) To meet a critical need for STEM graduate student training in research and teaching, while providing educational support through the use of inquiry based learning and increased STEM expertise of the Space and Earth Sciences. (2) Enhance STEM graduate students communication skills, and build strong mutual learning partnerships between Scientists, Fellows, Teachers and Administrators. (3) To provide international research experiences for Fellows and Teachers. (4) To help STEM Fellows expand their understanding science through the development of inquiry-based instructional materials connecting their research to K-12. Five long term goals of INSPIRE included: (1) To increase graduate student professional development in an effort to sustain future national success in science while better preparing STEM graduate students for their professions. (2) To strengthen the STEM graduate students communication ability. (3) To create lesson plans as a collaborative effort between Fellows and teachers that support the National Standards of Science and Mathematics. (4) To leverage partnerships formed between the K-12 school districts and the university STEM disciplines to support K-12 students? pursuit of higher education and STEM related careers. (5) To increase K-12 participating STEM teachers? content knowledge and technological skills.              External evaluation confirmed that the MSU INSPIRE project through grant related activities, has not only met these goals but also developed new understandings about the pedagogical nature of teaching and preparing individuals to be effective science educators. The team aspect of instruction, including both the participant teachers and fellows, has proven to be a very powerful aspect of the INSPIRE program. This cooperative teaching model draws on the experience and background knowledge of both individuals. It requires them to plan and deliver content that is not only aligned with students? prior knowledge, but also on target with the goals and objectives for future learning. Although classroom observations confirm the strength of this model, teachers explained that this relationship was not as productive in the beginning of the INSPIRE program. As participant teachers gained experience working with the fellows they began to open up their classroom and share more of the instruction time. To further explain this phenomenon, teachers described how initially they were skeptical of the fellows? ability to teach. There was a reluctance to take on the role of teaching the fellows how to teach, but with time they slowly accepted the role of a coach or guide. In other words, as teachers become more experienced with the implementation of the cooperative teaching model their ability to impact the fellows? perception of effective teaching increased. Training offered by Presentation Boot Camp (PBC) gave teachers a framework to provide structured feedback enabling them to address specific areas of concern with their fellows. Classroom observations revealed that participant teachers implemented elements of PBC into their classroom instruction directly improving instruction in the K-12 classroom. It is believed trainings such as this, in combination with experience in the cooperative teaching model, improve a teacher's ability to support fellows.  As a result of their participation, the participant advisors and leadership team have shown improvement in these areas as well. The improved ability to effectively communicate scientific research and findings established through the MSU inspire program, has directly influenced the standards at which graduate students are expected to perform during a delivery of their thesis or dissertation. This measurable increase in expectations is an indicator of institutional change for GK-12 type activities at MSU and evidence of its impact that will extend beyond the lifetime of the project.          Last Modified: 07/29/2016       Submitted by: Darrel W Schmitz]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
