<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Science for a Sustainable Future: Developing the Next Generation of Diverse Scientists</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>02/15/2010</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>01/31/2016</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>2857595.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>2857595</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>11010000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>EHR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DGE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Graduate Education</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Laura Regassa</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Abstract&lt;br/&gt;Technical: This project will fund and engage 9 minority graduate students (GK-12 Fellows) per year to build their science and teaching portfolios and develop leadership and teaching skills, ultimately preparing top scholars in environmental, geological, and biological sciences.  The Fellows will serve as role models and instructors in Early College High School (ECHS) classes in a predominantly Hispanic community. The ECHS is an innovative program that enables students to earn up to two years of college credit in addition to their high school diploma, and provides them with skills to increase their success in college. ECHS students will benefit from interacting with GK-12 Fellows in their classrooms, from teacher training to improve long-term capacities for interdisciplinary science , and from the development of lesson plans in ?Science for a Sustainable Future? focused on the arid southwest.  The proposed ?Scientists in Residence? program may serve as a scalable model for recruiting students into science, technology, engineering, and mathematics (STEM) disciplines. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Non-Technical:  This proposal will actively recruit minority graduate students and will train them to be scientists, instructors, and leaders of the future.  With its growing Ph.D. programs, top faculty, and current demographic, UTEP is poised to lead the way for training minority Ph.D. future scientists and leaders, and will allow for the students to address specific challenges facing our border, desert populations, including limited water resources in a changing climate, the potential for alternative energy resources,  environmental health issues in a multi-national community, and  geological hazards facing the region.&lt;br/&gt; &lt;br/&gt;</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>02/16/2010</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/17/2013</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.076</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>0947992</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Aaron</FirstName>
<LastName>Velasco</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Aaron Velasco</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>aavelasco@utep.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>9157475101</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000452604</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>02/16/2010</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>William</FirstName>
<LastName>Robertson</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>H</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>William H Robertson</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>robertson@utep.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>9157478459</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000239715</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>02/16/2010</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Vanessa</FirstName>
<LastName>Lougheed</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Vanessa Lougheed</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>vlougheed@utep.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON/>
<NSF_ID>000170452</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>02/16/2010</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Texas at El Paso</Name>
<CityName>El Paso</CityName>
<ZipCode>799680001</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>9157475680</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>ADMIN BLDG RM 209</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[500 West University]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Texas</StateName>
<StateCode>TX</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>16</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>TX16</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>132051285</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF TEXAS AT EL PASO</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>042000273</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Texas at El Paso]]></Name>
<CityName>El Paso</CityName>
<StateCode>TX</StateCode>
<ZipCode>799680001</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[ADMIN BLDG RM 209]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Texas</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>16</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>TX16</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<FoaInformation>
<Code>0000099</Code>
<Name>Other Applications NEC</Name>
</FoaInformation>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7179</Code>
<Text>GRAD TEACHING FELLOWS IN K-12</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7179</Code>
<Text>GRAD TEACHING FELLOWS IN K-12</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9179</Code>
<Text>GRADUATE INVOLVEMENT</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>SMET</Code>
<Text>SCIENCE, MATH, ENG &amp; TECH EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0410</Code>
<Name>NSF Education &amp; Human Resource</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040106</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0411</Code>
<Name>NSF Education &amp; Human Resource</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040106</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0412</Code>
<Name>NSF Education &amp; Human Resource</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040106</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0413</Code>
<Name>NSF Education &amp; Human Resource</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040106</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2010~566199</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2011~569079</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2012~572044</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2013~1150273</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The University of Texas at El Paso (UTEP) received a grant in 2011 from the National Science Foundation (NSF) which will provide funding for graduate students (called GK-12 Fellows) in NSF-supported science, technology, engineering, and mathematics (STEM) disciplines to bring their leading research practice and findings into K-12 learning settings. &nbsp;The GK-12 program at UTEP focused on working with Early College High Schools (ECHS) in the El Paso area, schools that target students that would not traditionally seek college degrees.&nbsp; These students earn an Associates Degree plus a High School diploma upon graduation.</p> <p><strong>Intellectual Merit</strong></p> <p>Our program centered on the theme &ldquo;Science for a Sustainable Future&rdquo;, with a particular focus on the arid southwest.&nbsp; Specific challenges facing our border, desert populations were addressed: 1) limited water resources in a changing climate, 2) the potential for alternative energy resources; 3) a rapidly growing, diverse population and environmental health issues in a multi-national community; and 4) geological hazards facing the region.</p> <p>The UTEP GK-12 Program had a series of activities based on the expected outcomes: 1) increase the capacity of GK-12 Fellows to be effective teachers, researchers and collaborators and to be competitive in the current job market; 2) enhance the ECHS students&rsquo; interest in pursuing undergraduate and, ultimately, graduate education in the environmental, geological, and other sciences; 3) demonstrably enhance the ECHS science learning environment through increased teacher efficacy and conceptual understanding by students.&nbsp;</p> <p><strong>Broader Impacts</strong><br /> We were successful in our approach. Over the lifetime of the grant, we funded 31 graduate students, 21 were female (68%), 10 male (32%), with 24 (78%) being of Hispanic origin (22) or African American (2).&nbsp; A total of 22 Fellows were/are enrolled in Ph.D. programs from eight (8) different programs.&nbsp; Eleven (11) Fellows have successfully completed their Ph.D. degrees, with one defending their dissertation in May 2016. Two (2) have become Ph.D. candidates, and seven (7) remain in good standing in their programs.&nbsp; Nine (9) Fellows pursuing their Masters degrees have all completed their programs successfully. Hundreds of ECHS students were impacted by Fellow activities, from field trips to classroom activities, in a community that is 80% Hispanic.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 05/02/2016<br>      Modified by: Aaron&nbsp;Velasco</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The University of Texas at El Paso (UTEP) received a grant in 2011 from the National Science Foundation (NSF) which will provide funding for graduate students (called GK-12 Fellows) in NSF-supported science, technology, engineering, and mathematics (STEM) disciplines to bring their leading research practice and findings into K-12 learning settings.  The GK-12 program at UTEP focused on working with Early College High Schools (ECHS) in the El Paso area, schools that target students that would not traditionally seek college degrees.  These students earn an Associates Degree plus a High School diploma upon graduation.  Intellectual Merit  Our program centered on the theme "Science for a Sustainable Future", with a particular focus on the arid southwest.  Specific challenges facing our border, desert populations were addressed: 1) limited water resources in a changing climate, 2) the potential for alternative energy resources; 3) a rapidly growing, diverse population and environmental health issues in a multi-national community; and 4) geological hazards facing the region.  The UTEP GK-12 Program had a series of activities based on the expected outcomes: 1) increase the capacity of GK-12 Fellows to be effective teachers, researchers and collaborators and to be competitive in the current job market; 2) enhance the ECHS studentsÆ interest in pursuing undergraduate and, ultimately, graduate education in the environmental, geological, and other sciences; 3) demonstrably enhance the ECHS science learning environment through increased teacher efficacy and conceptual understanding by students.   Broader Impacts  We were successful in our approach. Over the lifetime of the grant, we funded 31 graduate students, 21 were female (68%), 10 male (32%), with 24 (78%) being of Hispanic origin (22) or African American (2).  A total of 22 Fellows were/are enrolled in Ph.D. programs from eight (8) different programs.  Eleven (11) Fellows have successfully completed their Ph.D. degrees, with one defending their dissertation in May 2016. Two (2) have become Ph.D. candidates, and seven (7) remain in good standing in their programs.  Nine (9) Fellows pursuing their Masters degrees have all completed their programs successfully. Hundreds of ECHS students were impacted by Fellow activities, from field trips to classroom activities, in a community that is 80% Hispanic.       Last Modified: 05/02/2016       Submitted by: Aaron Velasco]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
