<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>RUI: The Role of Outer Membrane Agglutinins In Bacterial Colonization</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>02/01/2010</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2013</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>453558.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>453558</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>08070700</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>BIO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>MCB</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Molecular and Cellular Bioscience</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Susanne von Bodman</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Intellectual Merit&lt;br/&gt;Certain bacteria can colonize external, mucosal and intracellular sites of eukaryotes.  Colonization is promoted by proteins on the outer surface of bacteria that mediate interactions with eukaryotic cells, solid surfaces, or other bacteria.  This project focuses on the agglutinins, a family of outer membrane proteins expressed by a broad repertoire of Gram-negative bacteria ranging from human intestinal colonizers to intracellular colonizers of insects.  Our laboratory has shown that the Heat Resistant Agglutinin 1 (Hra1) is an accessory colonization factor in Escherichia coli strains with exceptional colonization abilities.  This project will examine interplay of this protein with other surface factors, such as fimbriae, using cultured epithelial cells and the nematode worm Caenorhabditis elegans as model systems.  The research will additionally identify and validate colonization-associated motifs within Hra1 and related proteins from other intestinal colonizers.  The investigations will be extended to Wolbachia Surface Proteins (Wsps).  Wsps are agglutinins hypothesized to contribute to localization and interbacterial interactions of bacteria that reside inside the cells of insects and nematodes.  To get around difficulties with culturing and manipulating Wolbachia, we propose to study the Wsps by expressing them in E. coli and to apply the methods we are using to examine E. coli surface proteins towards elucidating Wsp function.  This work will advance the understanding of interactions among bacteria as well between bacteria and their eukaryotic hosts.&lt;br/&gt;Broader impact: &lt;br/&gt; Knowledge gained from this project will increase understanding of specific molecular interactions that allow bacteria to live on or in other organisms.  The research will be conducted at Haverford College, a small liberal arts institution and will largely be performed by mentored undergraduate researchers. The PI teaches microbiology and introductory genetics, stimulating interest in bacteriology in a number of undergraduates and will offer 3-8 students each year, including women and other groups underrepresented in the sciences, research opportunities associated with the project. Additionally, approximately 30 students a year will be taught in inquiry-based lab classes that test some hypotheses associated with the project. As in the past, some students so trained will work with the PI in microbiology workshops for K-12 students in the US or for students and Faculty in West Africa.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>12/18/2009</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>12/28/2011</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.074</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>0948460</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Iruka</FirstName>
<LastName>Okeke</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>N</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Iruka N Okeke</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>iokeke@haverford.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6108961470</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000231153</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>12/18/2009</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Haverford College</Name>
<CityName>Haverford</CityName>
<ZipCode>190411336</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6108961000</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>370 Lancaster Avenue</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Pennsylvania</StateName>
<StateCode>PA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>PA05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>002502615</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>CORPORATION OF HAVERFORD COLLEGE, THE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>002502615</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Haverford College]]></Name>
<CityName>Haverford</CityName>
<StateCode>PA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>190411336</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[370 Lancaster Avenue]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Pennsylvania</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>PA05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1114</Code>
<Text>Cellular Dynamics and Function</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>8011</Code>
<Text>Systems and Synthetic Biology</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1114</Code>
<Text>CELLULAR SYSTEMS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1136</Code>
<Text>SIGNAL TRANSDCTN/CELL REGULATN</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1228</Code>
<Text>MINORITY INVOLVEMENT -- BIO</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7465</Code>
<Text>NANOSCALE BIO CORE</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9183</Code>
<Text>GENERAL FOUNDATIONS OF BIOTECHNOLOGY</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9229</Code>
<Text>RES IN UNDERGRAD INST-RESEARCH</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>BIOT</Code>
<Text>BIOTECHNOLOGY</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0110</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0111</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0112</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2010~144193</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2011~145424</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2012~163941</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Intellectual Merit:</p> <p>This project advanced our understanding of how bacteria colonize multi-cellular organisms, using a model system based on <em>Escherichia coli </em>bacteria that are exceptional colonizers and a nematode worm.&nbsp; The bacteria we studied express the heat-resistant agglutinin 1 (Hra1), an outermembrane protein that enables bacteria to bind to cells of other organisms, and to other bacteria.&nbsp; Hra1 mediates bacterial colonization of exceptional colonizers in worms but not in a petridish.&nbsp; This project determined that in petri dishes, the surface of the cell is covered by an anti-aggregation protein, which coats Hra1, preventing it from adhering.&nbsp; The anti-aggregation protein is removed in the worm intestine, permitting Hra1-mediated binding.</p> <p>In the course of this research, we determined that Hra1 mediates bacteria-bacteria adherence by self association.&nbsp; Our research identified specific residues in three motifs involved in this binding.&nbsp; When these residues are deleted, Hra1 loses its ability to self-associate.&nbsp; We searched the protein database for other proteins containing these residues and found that one of them is in a Salmonella surface protein called Rck.&nbsp; Our laboratory has demonstrated that the motif also mediates self-association in Rck, as well as Hra1-Rck association.&nbsp; Thus we have identified a new bacterial auto-association motif that confers identical functions in different contexts.&nbsp; We have additionally identified a mechanism by which different bacteria can co-aggregate.</p> <p>Hra1 is a member of a family of outer-membrane proteins called the agglutinins.&nbsp; Agglutinin genes are present in a wide range of bacteria that colonize multi-cellular organisms.&nbsp; In the course of our research, we have determined that agglutinins from other bacterial species, including Salmonella, a human colonizer, and Wolbachia, which colonizes insects and worms, are also able to mediate autoaggregation.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>Broader impacts:</p> <p>Knowledge obtained in the course of this project enhances our understanding of how bacteria, the most common life form on earth, interact with other organisms.&nbsp; The project has also advanced general understanding of the structure and function of surface proteins in Gram negative bacteria.</p> <p>The principal investigator of this work teaches undergraduates and used aspects of this project to develop new teaching modules.&nbsp;The research that uncovered the findings presented in this report was largely performed by mentored seventeen undergraduate students, the majority of whom subsequently pursued careers in science.&nbsp;Two graduate research associates, both women, one African American also worked sequentially on the project.&nbsp; All the students and the two staff members received comprehensive training in responsible conduct of research, molecular genetics, microbiology research methods at Biosafety-level 2 and scientific communication. Select students were trained in cell culture, various microscopy techniques and nematode biology.</p> <p><br /><br /></p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 09/07/2013<br>      Modified by: Iruka&nbsp;N&nbsp;Okeke</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Intellectual Merit:  This project advanced our understanding of how bacteria colonize multi-cellular organisms, using a model system based on Escherichia coli bacteria that are exceptional colonizers and a nematode worm.  The bacteria we studied express the heat-resistant agglutinin 1 (Hra1), an outermembrane protein that enables bacteria to bind to cells of other organisms, and to other bacteria.  Hra1 mediates bacterial colonization of exceptional colonizers in worms but not in a petridish.  This project determined that in petri dishes, the surface of the cell is covered by an anti-aggregation protein, which coats Hra1, preventing it from adhering.  The anti-aggregation protein is removed in the worm intestine, permitting Hra1-mediated binding.  In the course of this research, we determined that Hra1 mediates bacteria-bacteria adherence by self association.  Our research identified specific residues in three motifs involved in this binding.  When these residues are deleted, Hra1 loses its ability to self-associate.  We searched the protein database for other proteins containing these residues and found that one of them is in a Salmonella surface protein called Rck.  Our laboratory has demonstrated that the motif also mediates self-association in Rck, as well as Hra1-Rck association.  Thus we have identified a new bacterial auto-association motif that confers identical functions in different contexts.  We have additionally identified a mechanism by which different bacteria can co-aggregate.  Hra1 is a member of a family of outer-membrane proteins called the agglutinins.  Agglutinin genes are present in a wide range of bacteria that colonize multi-cellular organisms.  In the course of our research, we have determined that agglutinins from other bacterial species, including Salmonella, a human colonizer, and Wolbachia, which colonizes insects and worms, are also able to mediate autoaggregation.     Broader impacts:  Knowledge obtained in the course of this project enhances our understanding of how bacteria, the most common life form on earth, interact with other organisms.  The project has also advanced general understanding of the structure and function of surface proteins in Gram negative bacteria.  The principal investigator of this work teaches undergraduates and used aspects of this project to develop new teaching modules. The research that uncovered the findings presented in this report was largely performed by mentored seventeen undergraduate students, the majority of whom subsequently pursued careers in science. Two graduate research associates, both women, one African American also worked sequentially on the project.  All the students and the two staff members received comprehensive training in responsible conduct of research, molecular genetics, microbiology research methods at Biosafety-level 2 and scientific communication. Select students were trained in cell culture, various microscopy techniques and nematode biology.              Last Modified: 09/07/2013       Submitted by: Iruka N Okeke]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
