<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>COLLABORATIVE RESEARCH:  WINTER CLIMATE CHANGE IN A NORTHERN HARDWOOD FOREST</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2010</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2014</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>161674.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>176174</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>08010209</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>BIO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DEB</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Environmental Biology</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Henry L. Gholz</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>In the northeastern U.S., climate is changing more rapidly in winter than in summer. The impacts of winter climate change on ecosystems are greatly complicated by effects on snow depth and soil freezing. Snow is important as an insulator of the soil, and many northern hardwood forest soils normally remain unfrozen during the winter. A lack of snow can result in soil freezing, which is a significant disturbance to forest ecosystems, potentially killing tree roots and microorganisms and disrupting nutrient cycling processes leading to losses of nutrients to water and air. These losses can decrease the productivity of the forest ecosystem and lead to air and water pollution. In this project investigators will use a landscape-scale approach to evaluate three aspects of the effects of changes in snow depth on soil freezing and the cycling of carbon and nitrogen in the northern hardwood forest at the Hubbard Brook Long Term Ecological Research site (HBR) in New Hampshire. First, the research will address uncertainty about the occurrence of colder soils in a warmer world, and whether this pattern will increase losses of nitrogen, an important plant nutrient and source of water and air pollution, from the northern hardwood forest at HBR. Uncertainty about the extent and effects of soil freezing in a warmer world is rooted in limitations in our understanding of where two "tipping points" occur across a forest landscape experiencing climate change; where snowpacks are too shallow to insulate the soil, and where air temperatures are too warm to freeze the soil. This uncertainty will be addressed by measuring and modeling snow depth, and soil climate across the entire ~3000 ha Hubbard Brook Experimental Forest (HBEF), which encompasses the range of climate variability that has been predicted for the northeastern U.S. over the next 50-100 years. Measurements of soil temperature, moisture and frost, and nitrogen losses to water and air will be made at 20 experimental field sites that experience a broad range of long-term snowpack regimes to explore critical uncertainties surrounding soil freezing events and their effects on nitrogen cycling. Second, the proposed research will address how winter climate change affects microbial and soil invertebrate processes and resultant changes in carbon flow during winter, testing the hypothesis that carbon flow is the key integrative regulator of winter microbial activity. To test this hypothesis, the movement of isotopically labeled carbon and nitrogen will be traced from sugar maple detritus into and through the soil ecosystem in six intensive study sites that represent the full range of variation in winter climate at HBEF. Third, the proposed research will address if soil freezing alters hydrologic controls of ecosystem nitrogen processing at snowmelt and subsequent export of nitrogen to receiving waters. Snowmelt dynamics will be tested by adding isotopically labeled nitrogen to the snowpack and tracing its movement into and through the soil ecosystem. Effects of soil freezing on export to receiving waters will be tested by analyzing nitrogen export and solutes that serve as natural tracers of hydrologic flowpaths on small watersheds that differ in winter climate/soil freezing.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The project will include education and policy activities that explore the effects of winter climate change in the Northeast U.S. on recreation, timber harvesting, biomass energy production, and other ecosystem services. The project will connect ecosystem researchers with relevant stakeholders and interest groups, including loggers and foresters, ski-area operators, maple sugar producers, recreational snowmobile users, conservation-oriented NGOs, citizen scientists, and public and private land managers through a "Science Links" program. There will also be two pilot educational initiatives: a winter field course for undergraduates and creation of a teaching guide for middle and high school teachers. Finally, the research will be well integrated into ongoing HBR research on modeling the effects of climate change, fostering extension of current climate change modeling studies to depict the hydrologic and biogeochemical response to soil freezing under future climate change scenarios.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>09/08/2010</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>04/02/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.074</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>0949301</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Melany</FirstName>
<LastName>Fisk</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>C</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Melany C Fisk</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>fiskmc@miamioh.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5135293181</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000287798</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/08/2010</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Miami University</Name>
<CityName>Oxford</CityName>
<ZipCode>450563653</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5135293600</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>500 E High Street</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[Roudebush Hall]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Ohio</StateName>
<StateCode>OH</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>08</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>OH08</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>041065129</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>MIAMI UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>041065129</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Miami University]]></Name>
<CityName>Oxford</CityName>
<StateCode>OH</StateCode>
<ZipCode>450563653</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[500 E High Street]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Ohio</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>08</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>OH08</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1181</Code>
<Text>ECOSYSTEM STUDIES</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1181</Code>
<Text>ECOSYSTEM STUDIES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1355</Code>
<Text>EGC EDUCATIONAL ACTIVITIES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9169</Code>
<Text>BIODIVERSITY AND ECOSYSTEM DYNAMICS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9178</Code>
<Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9251</Code>
<Text>REU SUPP-Res Exp for Ugrd Supp</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>EGCH</Code>
<Text>ENVIRONMENT AND GLOBAL CHANGE</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>SMET</Code>
<Text>SCIENCE, MATH, ENG &amp; TECH EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0110</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0111</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0112</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0114</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2010~55596</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2011~106078</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2012~7500</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~7000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p class="Default"><span>Changes in ecosystems during the non-growing season are important aspects of global change that require further attention.&nbsp; In forests of the northeastern US, development of snowpack over winter regulates the soil climate and influences plant nutrient availability and nutrient export during the growing season.&nbsp; In this research, we examined how differences in winter climate modify growing season nutrient recycling processes, in northern hardwood forests at the Hubbard Brook Experimental Forest, NH, USA.&nbsp; We tested the hypothesis that winter climate influences the recycling of C and N from leaf litter inputs by using different elevations as a source of variation in winter climate, and by using an isotopic tracing experiment that followed litter-derived C and N through the soil profile and into dissolved and plant-available forms. <span>We found strong retention of litter C and N in surface organic horizons in these northern hardwood forests.&nbsp; We also found differences in that retention between low and high elevations that suggest controls of N retention related to winter climate.&nbsp; More soil frost and soil freeze-thaw occurred in low-elevation sites where snowpack was shallower, compared to higher-elevation sites.&nbsp; These conditions associated with less snowpack corresponded with less total retention of litter-derived N in soil and more rapid vertical movement of that N from the surface of the soil into deeper horizons in low-elevation sites, and to stronger N retention in surface organic horizon under the deeper snowcover of high-elevation sites.&nbsp; Our results suggest that frost effects on recycling of nutrients from plant litter, while subtle, can contribute over time to observed landscape patterns of N availability, and are likely to contribute to lower N retention in surface organic soils at higher elevations as the winter climate warms.&nbsp;&nbsp;</span></span></p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 02/12/2015<br>      Modified by: Melany&nbsp;C&nbsp;Fisk</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[Changes in ecosystems during the non-growing season are important aspects of global change that require further attention.  In forests of the northeastern US, development of snowpack over winter regulates the soil climate and influences plant nutrient availability and nutrient export during the growing season.  In this research, we examined how differences in winter climate modify growing season nutrient recycling processes, in northern hardwood forests at the Hubbard Brook Experimental Forest, NH, USA.  We tested the hypothesis that winter climate influences the recycling of C and N from leaf litter inputs by using different elevations as a source of variation in winter climate, and by using an isotopic tracing experiment that followed litter-derived C and N through the soil profile and into dissolved and plant-available forms. We found strong retention of litter C and N in surface organic horizons in these northern hardwood forests.  We also found differences in that retention between low and high elevations that suggest controls of N retention related to winter climate.  More soil frost and soil freeze-thaw occurred in low-elevation sites where snowpack was shallower, compared to higher-elevation sites.  These conditions associated with less snowpack corresponded with less total retention of litter-derived N in soil and more rapid vertical movement of that N from the surface of the soil into deeper horizons in low-elevation sites, and to stronger N retention in surface organic horizon under the deeper snowcover of high-elevation sites.  Our results suggest that frost effects on recycling of nutrients from plant litter, while subtle, can contribute over time to observed landscape patterns of N availability, and are likely to contribute to lower N retention in surface organic soils at higher elevations as the winter climate warms.            Last Modified: 02/12/2015       Submitted by: Melany C Fisk]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
