<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Geoinformatics: Leveraging the Paleobiology Database for Research, Education, Mentorship, and Interoperability</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/15/2010</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2016</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>686632.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>765604</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>06030202</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>GEO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>EAR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Earth Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Judith Skog</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The Paleobiology Database has been its field's main driver of macroevolutionary&lt;br/&gt;research over the last decade. It has yielded major insights into local- to global-scale changes in biodiversity, the consequences of mass extinctions, the ecological impacts of environmental change, and the geological processes that structure the fossil record. This kind of research is the only concrete basis for predicting the long-term effects of current global change on nature. At the same time, the PaleoDB has served as an important teaching tool for university programs and a primary gateway into the literature for the paleobiological community. Over the past decade its 222 contributors have assembled 30,121references to publications, 808,807 taxonomic occurrence records, and 262,909 opinions on the classification of 120,842 taxa. Its website features an array of data entry, query,download, and analysis tools. It is integrated with GBIF and CHRONOS and offers several web services. It is governed by a 16-member Advisory Board that includes both contributors and representatives from allied organizations.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The PaleoDB's activities have resulted in 101 official publications written by 51 different senior authors, and it is cited as a reference on more than 3000 Wikipedia pages. It was singled out as an essential resource in the report of the 2006 Future Research Directions in Paleontology workshop and has since received limited funding from three major paleontological societies for its educational activities. Mirroring on three websites and baseline administrative and technical support has continued through a volunteer effort, but substantive development of new infrastructure is needed. Goals of this project include enhancement of web services for use of large-scale portals such as the Encyclopedia of Life; exchange of data with cognate databases such as the Fossil Record File and TreeBASE; integration with PaleoPortal and individual museum collection databases; and creation of new tools and data tables involving phylogenetics, stratigraphy, geochronology, and geochemistry. These enhancements will, for example, make it possible for geologists to access dynamically integrated information on stratigraphic sections, or for biologists to quickly and reliably calibrate molecular&lt;br/&gt;clocks.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/13/2010</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>10/20/2015</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.050</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>0949416</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Shanan</FirstName>
<LastName>Peters</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>E</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Shanan E Peters</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>peters@geology.wisc.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6082625987</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000270093</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/13/2010</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Wisconsin-Madison</Name>
<CityName>MADISON</CityName>
<ZipCode>537151218</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6082623822</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>21 North Park Street</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[Suite 6401]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Wisconsin</StateName>
<StateCode>WI</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>WI02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>161202122</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF WISCONSIN SYSTEM</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>041188822</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Wisconsin-Madison]]></Name>
<CityName>MADISON</CityName>
<StateCode>WI</StateCode>
<ZipCode>537151218</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[21 North Park Street]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Wisconsin</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>WI02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<FoaInformation>
<Code>0000099</Code>
<Name>Other Applications NEC</Name>
</FoaInformation>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7255</Code>
<Text>GEOINFORMATICS</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7459</Code>
<Text>Sedimentary Geo &amp; Paleobiology</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0110</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0111</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0112</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0113</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0116</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2010~222303</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2011~224763</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2012~239566</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2013~7299</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2016~71673</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><span>The Paleobiology Database (PBDB) is a public resource of information on more than 1.3 million fossil occurrences and 350,000 taxonomic names. The database is designed to address fundamental questions in Earth and life science and contains information that can be of use when characterizing and predicting the distribution of energy and water resources. The PBDB is organized and operated by a multi-disciplinary, multi-institutional, international collaborative group of more than 300 paleobiological researchers.</span></p> <p>A core objective of this NSF EAR Geoinformatics grant was to better capitalize on the more than 11 continuous person years of effort that have gone into the PBDB data entry and curation process and to establish a modern geoinformatics foundation capable of carrying the database into the future. We have accomplished these objectives by completely overhauling every aspect of the public interface of the PBDB (<a href="https://paleobiodb.org">https://paleobiodb.org</a>) and by provisioning the underlying databases and infrastructure with new physical hardware and software tools that improve performance and facilitate data availability, discoverability and use. The most important accomplishment in this regard was the development and public release of the PBDB Application Programming Interface (<a href="https://paleobiodb.org/data">https://paleobiodb.org/data</a>, also described at <a href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1017/pab.2015.39">http://dx.doi.org/10.1017/pab.2015.39</a>), which allows third party developers to independently design and build PBDB data-driven applications that are tailored to the specific and diverse needs of industry, research, and education users. The API is now deployed extensively in all three of these areas. In 2016, the PBDB transferred more than 184GB of data in response to more than 8 million individual API requests that were generated by at least 300,000 distinct users globally. Year-over-year, rates of PBDB data access and usage is on track to more than double in volume. Example apps included in the 2016 usage statistics are the commercial iOS app Mancos, the freely available geoscience mobile apps Flyover Country (<a href="http://fc.umn.edu">http://fc.umn.edu</a>) and Rockd (<a href="https://rockd.org">https://rockd.org</a>),&nbsp;and our own Navigator web application (<a href="https://paleobiodb.org/navigator">https://paleobiodb.org/navigator</a>). The entire ecosystem of PBDB-utilizing web and mobile applications that now exists was made possible by the informatics work supported by this grant. The interoperability of the Paleobiology Database, measured by its data connections to other biological and geoscience databases and resources, has also improved in response to the release of the API. For example, R packages created by individuals and the rOpenSci team have been released (<a href="https://paleobiodb.org/#/resources">https://paleobiodb.org/#/resources</a>), and some of these aim to serve non-paleontologist communities.</p> <p>The Paleobiology Database is community governed, and during the course of this grant the governance structure was substantively reorganized and new leadership chosen. The PBDB is managed by the Executive Committee, which sets overall database policy, oversees matters related to the membership and access to data. The Committee consists of 12 members, including a Chair, currently held by Mark D. Uhen, and a Secretary, currently held by Matthew Clapham. Primary software development has been carried out at the University of Wisconsin-Madison under the auspices of this grant. The PBDB also has an External Advisory Board that advises the Executive Committee on Database activities and policies, promotes the use of the Database among the scientific community, and forges links to other scientific communities and the general public.</p> <p>In addition to designing and releasing core infrastructure components, and reorganizing governance, we have designed, tested, and publicly released educational materials for a course in paleobiology that is designed to provide technical and analytical skills of wide utility to undergraduate students. Material for an entire semester-long course, including lab exercises that use the PBDB API, is available online (<a href="https://github.com/paleobiodb/teachPaleobiology">https://github.com/paleobiodb/teachPaleobiology</a>). A number of other educational resources are also available (<a href="https://paleobiodb.org/#/resources">https://paleobiodb.org/#/resources</a>). The PBDB website and Navigator application, developed as part of this grant activity, have also been used on campuses across the country, including in large online classes. The PBDB has also enjoyed several viral social media exposures, primarily via Instagram, that were prompted entirely by the release of our new data visualization and exploration tools.&nbsp;</p> <p>Facilitating primary scientific research and publication has remained the core of our mission, and since the July 2010 start date of this grant, more than 165 officially numbered scientific papers that use the database have been published (<a href="https://paleobiodb.org/#/publications">https://paleobiodb.org/#/publications</a>); many more publications are not included in this official list but have used the PBDB in some capacity (<a href="https://scholar.google.com/citations?user=PP946k4AAAAJ">https://scholar.google.com/citations?user=PP946k4AAAAJ</a>). The number of publications that draws on the PBDB continues to increase steadily year-over-year.</p> <p>In summary, the work accomplished over the period July 2010 to Dec. 2016, supported by this Geoinformatics grant, has met or exceeded the stated goals of better leveraging the Paleobiology Database for research, education, mentorship and interoperability. In particular, the decentralization and democratization of software development activities made possible by the development and release a public API has resulted in more efficient and widespread use of PBDB data in industry, research and in education. The potential of the new capabilities of the PBDB are only now beginning to be realized.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 02/07/2017<br>      Modified by: Shanan&nbsp;E&nbsp;Peters</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Images (<span id="selectedPhoto0">1</span> of <span class="totalNumber"></span>)           </div> <div class="galControls" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/0949416/0949416_10018366_1486483488241_PBDB_main--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/0949416/0949416_10018366_1486483488241_PBDB_main--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Paleobiology Database main page"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/0949416/0949416_10018366_1486483488241_PBDB_main--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Paleobiology Database main page"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">The public interface for the Paleobiology Database was completely overhauled as part of this award activity. The emphasis was on usability for the purposes of education and research. https://paleodbiodb.org</div> <div class="imageCredit">Paleobiology Database</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Public Domain</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Shanan&nbsp;E&nbsp;Peters</div> <div class="imageTitle">Paleobiology Database main page</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/0949416/0949416_10018366_1486483621651_PBDB_global--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/0949416/0949416_10018366_1486483621651_PBDB_global--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Paleobiology Database Global Fossil Distribution"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/0949416/0949416_10018366_1486483621651_PBDB_global--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Paleobiology Database Global Fossil Distribution"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Paleobiology Database Navigator, a web application powered by a public PBDB API, was designed and released publicly to give users easy access to information about fossil taxa in time and space. https://paleobiodb.org/navigator</div> <div class="imageCredit">Paleobiology Database</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Public Domain</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Shanan&nbsp;E&nbsp;Peters</div> <div class="imageTitle">Paleobiology Database Global Fossil Distribution</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/0949416/0949416_10018366_1486483773543_Tr--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/0949416/0949416_10018366_1486483773543_Tr--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Triassic global paleogeography"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/0949416/0949416_10018366_1486483773543_Tr--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Triassic global paleogeography"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">PBDB Navigator allows users to explore the geography of Earth at the time that fossil organisms lived. Paleogeographic reconstruction models and tools to visualize them have been integrated into the PBDB</div> <div class="imageCredit">Paleobiology Database</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Public Domain</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Shanan&nbsp;E&nbsp;Peters</div> <div class="imageTitle">Triassic global paleogeography</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/0949416/0949416_10018366_1486484310822_growth.001--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/0949416/0949416_10018366_1486484310822_growth.001--rgov-800width.jpg" title="PBDB Growth"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/0949416/0949416_10018366_1486484310822_growth.001--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="PBDB Growth"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">During the award period, the Paleobiology Database has grown significantly by all metrics, including data holdings, scientific members, and publications. The PBDB stands as the premier resources facilitating paleobiological research and education. https://scholar.google.com/citations?user=PP9</div> <div class="imageCredit">Paleobiology Database</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Creative Commons</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Shanan&nbsp;E&nbsp;Peters</div> <div class="imageTitle">PBDB Growth</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/0949416/0949416_10018366_1486484914875_growth.002--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/0949416/0949416_10018366_1486484914875_growth.002--rgov-800width.jpg" title="PBDB API and Apps"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/0949416/0949416_10018366_1486484914875_growth.002--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="PBDB API and Apps"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">The most important addition to the PBDB geoinformatics infrastructure made during this grant activity was the Application Programming Interface, which is now used by many third-party commercial and freely-available research and education-focused applications. https://paleobiodb.org/#/resources</div> <div class="imageCredit">Paleobiology Database</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Public Domain</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Shanan&nbsp;E&nbsp;Peters</div> <div class="imageTitle">PBDB API and Apps</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/0949416/0949416_10018366_1486491192626_growth.003--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/0949416/0949416_10018366_1486491192626_growth.003--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Paleobiology Database website usage"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/0949416/0949416_10018366_1486491192626_growth.003--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Paleobiology Database website usage"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Paleobiology Database is a primary source of data on the fossil record. Since Google Analytics tracking was implemented in 10/2013, ~160,000 users from all 50 states and DC visited 2.1 million pages on the main website (https://paleobiodb.org ; stats do not include API or Navigator applicatication).</div> <div class="imageCredit">Paleobiology Database, Google Analytics</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Creative Commons</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Shanan&nbsp;E&nbsp;Peters</div> <div class="imageTitle">Paleobiology Database website usage</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The Paleobiology Database (PBDB) is a public resource of information on more than 1.3 million fossil occurrences and 350,000 taxonomic names. The database is designed to address fundamental questions in Earth and life science and contains information that can be of use when characterizing and predicting the distribution of energy and water resources. The PBDB is organized and operated by a multi-disciplinary, multi-institutional, international collaborative group of more than 300 paleobiological researchers.  A core objective of this NSF EAR Geoinformatics grant was to better capitalize on the more than 11 continuous person years of effort that have gone into the PBDB data entry and curation process and to establish a modern geoinformatics foundation capable of carrying the database into the future. We have accomplished these objectives by completely overhauling every aspect of the public interface of the PBDB (https://paleobiodb.org) and by provisioning the underlying databases and infrastructure with new physical hardware and software tools that improve performance and facilitate data availability, discoverability and use. The most important accomplishment in this regard was the development and public release of the PBDB Application Programming Interface (https://paleobiodb.org/data, also described at http://dx.doi.org/10.1017/pab.2015.39), which allows third party developers to independently design and build PBDB data-driven applications that are tailored to the specific and diverse needs of industry, research, and education users. The API is now deployed extensively in all three of these areas. In 2016, the PBDB transferred more than 184GB of data in response to more than 8 million individual API requests that were generated by at least 300,000 distinct users globally. Year-over-year, rates of PBDB data access and usage is on track to more than double in volume. Example apps included in the 2016 usage statistics are the commercial iOS app Mancos, the freely available geoscience mobile apps Flyover Country (http://fc.umn.edu) and Rockd (https://rockd.org), and our own Navigator web application (https://paleobiodb.org/navigator). The entire ecosystem of PBDB-utilizing web and mobile applications that now exists was made possible by the informatics work supported by this grant. The interoperability of the Paleobiology Database, measured by its data connections to other biological and geoscience databases and resources, has also improved in response to the release of the API. For example, R packages created by individuals and the rOpenSci team have been released (https://paleobiodb.org/#/resources), and some of these aim to serve non-paleontologist communities.  The Paleobiology Database is community governed, and during the course of this grant the governance structure was substantively reorganized and new leadership chosen. The PBDB is managed by the Executive Committee, which sets overall database policy, oversees matters related to the membership and access to data. The Committee consists of 12 members, including a Chair, currently held by Mark D. Uhen, and a Secretary, currently held by Matthew Clapham. Primary software development has been carried out at the University of Wisconsin-Madison under the auspices of this grant. The PBDB also has an External Advisory Board that advises the Executive Committee on Database activities and policies, promotes the use of the Database among the scientific community, and forges links to other scientific communities and the general public.  In addition to designing and releasing core infrastructure components, and reorganizing governance, we have designed, tested, and publicly released educational materials for a course in paleobiology that is designed to provide technical and analytical skills of wide utility to undergraduate students. Material for an entire semester-long course, including lab exercises that use the PBDB API, is available online (https://github.com/paleobiodb/teachPaleobiology). A number of other educational resources are also available (https://paleobiodb.org/#/resources). The PBDB website and Navigator application, developed as part of this grant activity, have also been used on campuses across the country, including in large online classes. The PBDB has also enjoyed several viral social media exposures, primarily via Instagram, that were prompted entirely by the release of our new data visualization and exploration tools.   Facilitating primary scientific research and publication has remained the core of our mission, and since the July 2010 start date of this grant, more than 165 officially numbered scientific papers that use the database have been published (https://paleobiodb.org/#/publications); many more publications are not included in this official list but have used the PBDB in some capacity (https://scholar.google.com/citations?user=PP946k4AAAAJ). The number of publications that draws on the PBDB continues to increase steadily year-over-year.  In summary, the work accomplished over the period July 2010 to Dec. 2016, supported by this Geoinformatics grant, has met or exceeded the stated goals of better leveraging the Paleobiology Database for research, education, mentorship and interoperability. In particular, the decentralization and democratization of software development activities made possible by the development and release a public API has resulted in more efficient and widespread use of PBDB data in industry, research and in education. The potential of the new capabilities of the PBDB are only now beginning to be realized.          Last Modified: 02/07/2017       Submitted by: Shanan E Peters]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
