<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>RUI Collaborative Research: Untangling tropical diversity: a phylogenetic analysis of tritrophic interactions</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>02/15/2010</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>02/29/2016</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>270769.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>339551</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>08010000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>BIO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DEB</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Environmental Biology</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Simon Malcomber</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>smalcomb@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032928227</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Plants and insects represent the majority of multicellular species on Earth. Most of those species are tropical; yet, most species in the tropics remain undiscovered. The proposed research has three primary goals: 1) discover and describe species of parasitic wasps that attack a very diverse group of plant-feeding flies; 2) discover patterns of host-use by the wasps; and, 3) reconstruct the history of the wasps' diversification (the evolution of many wasp species). To reach these goals, the team of investigators and their students will collect and rear insects, analyze the DNA of immature stages and adults, and analyze physical traits of adults. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project addresses a major biological question: is diversification mediated by interactions among organisms or is diversification an ecologically neutral process? The project focuses on three groups of economically important organisms: plants related to pumpkins; fruit flies related to major agricultural pests; and wasps that attack the flies and are potentially important for pest control. Undergraduate education is a key component of the project. Undergraduates will be involved in all aspects of the research, including fieldwork in the tropics, molecular data collection and analysis in the laboratory, and communication and dissemination of the research.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>01/29/2010</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>12/05/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.074</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>0949361</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Martha</FirstName>
<LastName>Condon</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>A</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Martha A Condon</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>mcondon@cornellcollege.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>3198954154</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000176728</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>01/29/2010</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Cornell College</Name>
<CityName>Mount Vernon</CityName>
<ZipCode>523141098</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>3198954000</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>600 First Street West</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Iowa</StateName>
<StateCode>IA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>IA01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>010246015</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>CORNELL COLLEGE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Cornell College]]></Name>
<CityName>Mount Vernon</CityName>
<StateCode>IA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>523141098</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[600 First Street West]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Iowa</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>IA01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1171</Code>
<Text>PHYLOGENETIC SYSTEMATICS</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1198</Code>
<Text>Biodiversity: Discov &amp;Analysis</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1171</Code>
<Text>PHYLOGENETIC SYSTEMATICS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1228</Code>
<Text>MINORITY INVOLVEMENT -- BIO</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1355</Code>
<Text>EGC EDUCATIONAL ACTIVITIES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7218</Code>
<Text>RET SUPP-Res Exp for Tchr Supp</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9169</Code>
<Text>BIODIVERSITY AND ECOSYSTEM DYNAMICS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9177</Code>
<Text>ELEMENTARY/SECONDARY EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9178</Code>
<Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9218</Code>
<Text>BASIC RESEARCH &amp; HUMAN RESORCS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9229</Code>
<Text>RES IN UNDERGRAD INST-RESEARCH</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9251</Code>
<Text>REU SUPP-Res Exp for Ugrd Supp</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>EGCH</Code>
<Text>ENVIRONMENT AND GLOBAL CHANGE</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>SMET</Code>
<Text>SCIENCE, MATH, ENG &amp; TECH EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0110</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0111</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0112</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0113</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0114</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2010~278269</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2011~7500</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2012~22496</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2013~24942</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~6344</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><span>Intellectual Merit:</span></p> <p><span>Collections and Sequences: We collected in Costa Rica (March and August 2010), French Guiana (Feb 2011, January 2016), Bolivia (December 2011), Panama (February 2012), Brazil (June 2012), Peru (July-August 2012), and Suriname (June 2011, February 2015). Analyses of collections from Costa Rica and Peru were delayed until 2014 when "genetic access" permits were issued. We currently have ~7,000 sequences, which represent &gt;60 species of flies (most new to science) and &gt; 50 species of parasitic wasps (most new to science).</span></p> <p><span>Analyses: Analysis of collections from a single site in Peru revealed patterns of extreme host-specificity and diversity.&nbsp; Each species of parasitoid in the hymenopteran genus Bellopius successfully parasitizes only one species of Blepharoneura (flies in the family Tephritidae). Many Bellopius species attack more than one species of Blepharoneura, but never emerge as adults from more than one species of fly. This pattern suggests that each species of fly can defend itself against all but one species of Bellopius. These results were published in Science (Condon et al. 2014. Science 343: 1240-1244.) Analysis of non-specialist parasitoids resulted in a recent publication of a new species of figitid wasp (Buffington &amp; Condon 2013. Proc. Ent. Soc. Wash 115: 349-357). Analysis of specimens collected in Brazil likewise reveals extreme patterns of specificity: flies and their parasitoids distinguish among recently diverged host-plant species. </span></p> <p><span>Major finding: Parasitoids are not always lethal; they can be killed by their hosts. Adult flies (which survive parasitoid attack) contain DNA of parasitoids. Our 2014 Science paper reported patterns of bidirectional "lethality": parasitoids lethal to flies, and flies lethal to parasitoids; however, we had no evidence that flies that are lethal to parasitoids can actually survive to adulthood. We can now confirm that we can identify the DNA of unsuccessful (dead) parasitoids in those flies. </span></p> <p><span>Broader Impacts:</span></p> <p><span>We have trained international students (four Bolivian; two Peruvian; two Brazilian; six Mexican), two U.S. graduate students (Kristina Ottens, University of Iowa and Glen Hood, Notre Dame), at least 20 undergraduates (six Hispanic, two African American), a high school science teacher (African American) and two high school students (one African American). Three undergraduates (two Hispanic) pursued research projects for at least two summers with us, and four undergraduates (one Hispanic) participated in tropical field collection trips. &nbsp;At UNAM (Morelia, Mexico), I led seminars about citizen science; the seminars were attended by &gt;20 Mexican students training to be science teachers.</span></p> <p>With REU support, Adriana Vega carried out a comparative study of genitalia of sunflower flies and attended a conference of the Guild of Natural Science Illustrators. Jarod Armenta carried out a survey of populations of sunflower flies associated with several species of putative hosts, and analyzed the DNA of his collections. Supplementary RET awards allowed Darius Ballard (an African American who teaches high school in Cedar Rapids Iowa) to travel to Peru and to recruit high school students to study sunflower flies. Cornell College supported the work of three other undergraduates (two African Americans&mdash;Neisha Croffit and Demaceo Howard-- and Maren Elnes) who collected flies in Nebraska, Iowa, Illinois, and Wisconsin. Maren and three additional undergraduates (all women), repeated those collections the next summer and collaborated with students working with Andrew Forbes (University of Iowa). &nbsp;Two papers about that work are published (Forbes et al. 2013. Evol. Ecol.&nbsp; 27: 1017:1032; Hippee et al. 2016. Ecol. Entomol. DOI: 10.1111/een.12309). The first includes one...]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Intellectual Merit:  Collections and Sequences: We collected in Costa Rica (March and August 2010), French Guiana (Feb 2011, January 2016), Bolivia (December 2011), Panama (February 2012), Brazil (June 2012), Peru (July-August 2012), and Suriname (June 2011, February 2015). Analyses of collections from Costa Rica and Peru were delayed until 2014 when "genetic access" permits were issued. We currently have ~7,000 sequences, which represent &gt;60 species of flies (most new to science) and &gt; 50 species of parasitic wasps (most new to science).  Analyses: Analysis of collections from a single site in Peru revealed patterns of extreme host-specificity and diversity.  Each species of parasitoid in the hymenopteran genus Bellopius successfully parasitizes only one species of Blepharoneura (flies in the family Tephritidae). Many Bellopius species attack more than one species of Blepharoneura, but never emerge as adults from more than one species of fly. This pattern suggests that each species of fly can defend itself against all but one species of Bellopius. These results were published in Science (Condon et al. 2014. Science 343: 1240-1244.) Analysis of non-specialist parasitoids resulted in a recent publication of a new species of figitid wasp (Buffington &amp; Condon 2013. Proc. Ent. Soc. Wash 115: 349-357). Analysis of specimens collected in Brazil likewise reveals extreme patterns of specificity: flies and their parasitoids distinguish among recently diverged host-plant species.   Major finding: Parasitoids are not always lethal; they can be killed by their hosts. Adult flies (which survive parasitoid attack) contain DNA of parasitoids. Our 2014 Science paper reported patterns of bidirectional "lethality": parasitoids lethal to flies, and flies lethal to parasitoids; however, we had no evidence that flies that are lethal to parasitoids can actually survive to adulthood. We can now confirm that we can identify the DNA of unsuccessful (dead) parasitoids in those flies.   Broader Impacts:  We have trained international students (four Bolivian; two Peruvian; two Brazilian; six Mexican), two U.S. graduate students (Kristina Ottens, University of Iowa and Glen Hood, Notre Dame), at least 20 undergraduates (six Hispanic, two African American), a high school science teacher (African American) and two high school students (one African American). Three undergraduates (two Hispanic) pursued research projects for at least two summers with us, and four undergraduates (one Hispanic) participated in tropical field collection trips.  At UNAM (Morelia, Mexico), I led seminars about citizen science; the seminars were attended by &gt;20 Mexican students training to be science teachers.  With REU support, Adriana Vega carried out a comparative study of genitalia of sunflower flies and attended a conference of the Guild of Natural Science Illustrators. Jarod Armenta carried out a survey of populations of sunflower flies associated with several species of putative hosts, and analyzed the DNA of his collections. Supplementary RET awards allowed Darius Ballard (an African American who teaches high school in Cedar Rapids Iowa) to travel to Peru and to recruit high school students to study sunflower flies. Cornell College supported the work of three other undergraduates (two African Americans&mdash;Neisha Croffit and Demaceo Howard-- and Maren Elnes) who collected flies in Nebraska, Iowa, Illinois, and Wisconsin. Maren and three additional undergraduates (all women), repeated those collections the next summer and collaborated with students working with Andrew Forbes (University of Iowa).  Two papers about that work are published (Forbes et al. 2013. Evol. Ecol.  27: 1017:1032; Hippee et al. 2016. Ecol. Entomol. DOI: 10.1111/een.12309). The first includes one undergraduate author; the second includes three undergraduate authors.  In 2015 Kristina Ottens (a Cornell College graduate) earned her MS degree from the University of Iowa by carrying out an an...]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
