<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Protein Methylation and Flagellar Stability</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>03/01/2010</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2014</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>635954.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>635954</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>08070600</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>BIO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>MCB</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Molecular and Cellular Bioscience</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Gregory W. Warr</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Intellectual Merit:  Almost all living cells in the human body contain whip-like appendages called primary cilia.  These structures serve as cellular antennas that sense the external environment, detect signals, and transmit this information to the cell nucleus, which then responds appropriately according to the signals it receives.  This project uses the single celled green alga Chlamydomonas as the model system to study how cilia are assembled and function.  The two flagella of Chlamydomonas are analogous in almost all respects to primary cilia in humans.  Cells assemble and disassemble their cilia (and flagella) during each round of cell division.  Cells that are unable to disassemble their cilia cannot divide properly, and cells that cannot construct cilia cannot sense the environment properly.  This project is directed at understanding the factors that are important in controlling the process of ciliary disassembly that occurs prior to each cell division.  &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Broader Impact: This project will provide several educational opportunities for students at different levels: (a) Undergraduate students will become involved in original research, an activity that is consistent with data showing that undergraduate research experiences increase learning and foster deeper commitment by the participants.  In addition to deriving strong growth and development benefits, students gain a much greater understanding of the career options open to them. (b) A graduate student will participate as part of his/her thesis research leading to the Ph. D.  (c) Advanced high school biology students from Hartford (VT) High School will visit the lab and be exposed to these experiments and the microscopic techniques used to observe cells with cilia.  Through collaboration with Dartmouth's Office of Outreach, this project will be described to the local communities through a series of informal events called "science cafes". To achieve broad dissemination of relevant findings from this project Dartmouth's Office of Public Affairs will communicate new findings and significant publications to the news media as appropriate.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>03/10/2010</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>12/22/2011</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.074</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>0950402</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Roger</FirstName>
<LastName>Sloboda</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>D</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Roger D Sloboda</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>rds@dartmouth.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6036462377</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000183515</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>03/10/2010</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Dartmouth College</Name>
<CityName>HANOVER</CityName>
<ZipCode>037551421</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6036463007</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>OFFICE OF SPONSORED PROJECTS</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[11 ROPE FERRY RD #6210]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New Hampshire</StateName>
<StateCode>NH</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NH02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>041027822</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>TRUSTEES OF DARTMOUTH COLLEGE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>041027822</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Dartmouth College]]></Name>
<CityName>HANOVER</CityName>
<StateCode>NH</StateCode>
<ZipCode>037551421</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[OFFICE OF SPONSORED PROJECTS]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New Hampshire</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NH02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1114</Code>
<Text>Cellular Dynamics and Function</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1114</Code>
<Text>CELLULAR SYSTEMS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1132</Code>
<Text>CELLULAR ORGANIZATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7465</Code>
<Text>NANOSCALE BIO CORE</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0110</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0111</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0112</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2010~204266</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2011~210123</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2012~221565</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>We use Chlamydomonas (see figure), a green algal cell with two flagella (also called cilia on other cell types) to study how these structures are assembled and disassembled.&nbsp; Cilia and flagella (the terms are interchangeable) are long extensions from the cell surface that exist in most cells, and these organelles are assembled after cell division and must be disassembled before the cell can successfully complete the next round of cell division.&nbsp; We have discovered a series of reactions, collectively called protein methylation, that is specifically enhanced when a cell disassembles its cilia (or flagella).&nbsp; Methylations are added to specific proteins and can occur in one of two forms, called symmetric (sDMA) or asymmetric (aDMA).&nbsp; We have been studying the timing of these methylation reactions, the enzymes involved in producing them, and the mechanisms the cell uses to control when these modifications occur.&nbsp; Overall, here is what we have found:</p> <p>At the start of flagellar disassembly, six proteins become methylated (aDMA).&nbsp; Their names and locations in the flagellum are noted in the sketch of a flagellum in cross section in the figure appended.&nbsp; These aDMA modifications are produced by the action of enzymes called PRMT1 and PRMT2.&nbsp; In addition, full length and resorbing flagella contain another five proteins (not shown in the figure) that contain sDMA modifications, produced by the action of a different methyltransferase called PRMT5.&nbsp; These do not change with the assembly/disassembly state of the flagellum.</p> <p>All of the components necessary for protein methylation occur in the flagellum, and consist of a pathway of reactions involving four enzymes working in unison that are resident within flagella.&nbsp; The activity of the methylase, PRMT1, appears to be controlled itslef by yet another protein modification called phosphorylation.&nbsp; Our current working hypothesis is that one of the signals for the start of cell division (mitosis) causes phoshorylation of PRMT1, and this in turn methylates key structural component of the flagellum (indicated in the attached figure), destabiliziing the organelle and allowing it to be disassembled prior to mitosis.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 10/16/2014<br>      Modified by: Roger&nbsp;D&nbsp;Sloboda</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Images (<span id="selectedPhoto0">1</span> of <span class="totalNumber"></span>)           </div> <div class="galControls" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2014/0950402/0950402_10013980_1413484163152_Diagram1--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2014/0950402/0950402_10013980_1413484163152_Diagram1--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Methylated Proteins in Resorbing Flagella"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2014/0950402/0950402_10013980_1413484163152_Diagram1--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Methylated Proteins in Resorbing Flagella"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Diagram showing the relative positions of methylated proteins (carrying aDMA) in a resorbing flagellum.  Structure adapted from the work of Pigino et al. (2011), Yang et al. (2006), and Lin et al. (2011).</div> <div class="imageCredit">Roger Sloboda</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Roger&nbsp;D&nbsp;Sloboda</div> <div class="imageTitle">Methylated Proteins in Resorbing Flagella</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2014/0950402/0950402_10013980_1413485271673_Chlamy--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2014/0950402/0950402_10013980_1413485271673_Chlamy--rgov-800...]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ We use Chlamydomonas (see figure), a green algal cell with two flagella (also called cilia on other cell types) to study how these structures are assembled and disassembled.  Cilia and flagella (the terms are interchangeable) are long extensions from the cell surface that exist in most cells, and these organelles are assembled after cell division and must be disassembled before the cell can successfully complete the next round of cell division.  We have discovered a series of reactions, collectively called protein methylation, that is specifically enhanced when a cell disassembles its cilia (or flagella).  Methylations are added to specific proteins and can occur in one of two forms, called symmetric (sDMA) or asymmetric (aDMA).  We have been studying the timing of these methylation reactions, the enzymes involved in producing them, and the mechanisms the cell uses to control when these modifications occur.  Overall, here is what we have found:  At the start of flagellar disassembly, six proteins become methylated (aDMA).  Their names and locations in the flagellum are noted in the sketch of a flagellum in cross section in the figure appended.  These aDMA modifications are produced by the action of enzymes called PRMT1 and PRMT2.  In addition, full length and resorbing flagella contain another five proteins (not shown in the figure) that contain sDMA modifications, produced by the action of a different methyltransferase called PRMT5.  These do not change with the assembly/disassembly state of the flagellum.  All of the components necessary for protein methylation occur in the flagellum, and consist of a pathway of reactions involving four enzymes working in unison that are resident within flagella.  The activity of the methylase, PRMT1, appears to be controlled itslef by yet another protein modification called phosphorylation.  Our current working hypothesis is that one of the signals for the start of cell division (mitosis) causes phoshorylation of PRMT1, and this in turn methylates key structural component of the flagellum (indicated in the attached figure), destabiliziing the organelle and allowing it to be disassembled prior to mitosis.       Last Modified: 10/16/2014       Submitted by: Roger D Sloboda]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
