<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Role of Chemotaxis, Motility and Adhesins during Initiation of the Earthworm-Verminephrobacter Symbiosis</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/15/2010</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>09/30/2015</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>488000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>500000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>08090300</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>BIO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>IOS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Integrative Organismal Systems</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>rollie clem</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Most plants and animals, including humans, have beneficial bacterial partners that are necessary to enhance health, yet most information about bacterial interactions with hosts is  based on pathogen studies.  Earthworms, keystone members of the soil system, offer an experimental model for colonization of animal hosts by beneficial bacteria.  A common composting worm, Eisenia fetida, maintains bacteria within kidney-like organs and deposits these symbiotic bacteria into egg capsules to colonize earthworm embryos.  This study investigates mechanisms that enable bacterial symbionts to detect, migrate into and colonize a particular organ of their host during early development.  Crucial elements for the success of both pathogens and beneficial bacteria are the targeting of and attachment to appropriate tissue, followed by subsequent growth. Information about bacterial colonization gained in this study will better equip scientists and medical professionals to combat disease and promote beneficial microbes.  The study has several goals:  to (1) determine genes involved, (2) identify sensory mechanisms used by symbiotic bacteria to locate tissue, and (3) identify cell surface features of the host to which bacteria bind.  Approaches include genetics to analyze gene function, and biochemistry and cell staining methods to identify cell surface proteins and sugars.  This work will reveal key mechanisms beneficial bacterial use to successfully colonize the correct tissue.  Genomic data generated by this work will be available through appropriate public gene databases.  Findings will be published in a timely manner and updated on the lab website.  Activities include education of young scientists, including women, and public outreach in the form of hands-on demonstrations for children in grades 3-8, and webpage updates for both experienced scientists and the public.  This research will impact a range of scientific disciplines including developmental biology, pathobiology, and soil ecology.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/03/2010</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>01/05/2015</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.074</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>0951119</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Seana</FirstName>
<LastName>Davidson</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>K</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Seana K Davidson</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>skdavid@u.washington.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2066852626</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000436648</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/03/2010</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Washington</Name>
<CityName>Seattle</CityName>
<ZipCode>981950001</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2065434043</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>4333 Brooklyn Ave NE</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Washington</StateName>
<StateCode>WA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>WA07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>605799469</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF WASHINGTON</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>042803536</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Washington]]></Name>
<CityName>Seattle</CityName>
<StateCode>WA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>981950001</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[4333 Brooklyn Ave NE]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Washington</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>WA07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<FoaInformation>
<Code>0000099</Code>
<Name>Other Applications NEC</Name>
</FoaInformation>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7656</Code>
<Text>Symbiosis Infection &amp; Immunity</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1228</Code>
<Text>MINORITY INVOLVEMENT -- BIO</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9178</Code>
<Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9179</Code>
<Text>GRADUATE INVOLVEMENT</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9251</Code>
<Text>REU SUPP-Res Exp for Ugrd Supp</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0110</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0111</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0112</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2010~155000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2011~183000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2012~162000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The Davidson lab at the University of Washington studies interactions and functions of beneficial bacterial symbionts in earthworms. Earthworms harbor specific bacteria in their excretory kidney-like organs that are important for earthworm success in soil ecosystems.&nbsp; <em>Eisenia fetida</em>, a common composting worm, serves as a lab model.</p> <p><strong>Outcomes of this award:</strong>&nbsp; We established methods to disrupt genes in the bacterial symbiont <em>Verminephrobacter eiseniae</em> to observe changes in symbiont performance and survival when lacking targeted genes as a way to infer gene functions.&nbsp; Using gene disruption, we demonstrated two forms of bacterial motility, swimming and twitching, are required for symbiont migration into embryos to colonize the proper tissue.&nbsp; Swimming motility uses flagella, undulating fibers that move the bacteria.&nbsp; Twitching uses a fiber that acts as a grappling hook to bind a site, then rapidly pull the cell forward. Without one or the other, the bacteria cannot make it to the colonization site (Dulla et al., 2012<em>, ISMEJ</em>, <strong>6</strong>:1166-1175).</p> <p>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; In addition to the role of motility, work investigated the cues that allow bacteria to find their final colonization sites in the earthworm embryos.&nbsp; Bacteria follow a chemical cue to their destination - a behavior known as chemotaxis. We established high-throughput chemotaxis assays to test potentially attractive compounds. <em>V. eiseniae</em> was most highly attracted to compounds related to the function of the organ they inhabit, such as ammonia, urea, and select amino acids. &nbsp;The next step is to evaluate the chemotaxis of mutants with dysfunctional chemical sensors to confirm the requirement for colonization.</p> <p>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; An important discovery during this work was that the bacterial symbionts are able to take up DNA from their environment and incorporate it into their own genome.&nbsp; Uptake of free DNA is important for rapid adaptation of bacteria because it allows them to pick up genes that may help them adapt to changes in their environment. We were able to show that the symbionts will take up and incorporate DNA while in the egg capsule of the worm, and while in biofilm-like aggregates in culture. This may allow them to take up new DNA from other organisms and acquire new capabilities (Davidson, et al., Frontiers of Microbiology Journal, 2014).</p> <p>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; Finally, studies were conducted to characterize biofilm formations by <em>V. eiseniae.</em>&nbsp; Biofilms often occur in the environment as layers of bacterial cells on surfaces bound in a matrix produced by the bacteria.&nbsp; Pathogens and beneficial symbionts also form biofilms in hosts when attached to tissues.&nbsp; Some pathogens require biofilm formation to colonize hosts.&nbsp; We observed that the earthworm symbiont <em>V. eiseniae</em> formed biofilms in culture in the lab.&nbsp; Using <em>V. eiseniae</em> mutants with defects in their motility genes, and defects in their ability process glucose, we found that both bacterial pili, structures used for twitching motility, and flagella are required for biofilm formations displayed by the wild type.&nbsp; Flagellar swimming motility is needed to form larger aggregates that bind together to form the biofilms.&nbsp; Defects in the uptake and processing of glucose disrupted the formation of the biofilms, indicating that extracellular polysaccharides are likely needed to form larger aggregates. &nbsp;</p> <p><strong>Intellectual merit:</strong> NSF funding provided to the Davidson lab enabled important discoveries about how earthworm symbiotic bacteria find and colonize their specific sites in host worms during embryo develop...]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The Davidson lab at the University of Washington studies interactions and functions of beneficial bacterial symbionts in earthworms. Earthworms harbor specific bacteria in their excretory kidney-like organs that are important for earthworm success in soil ecosystems.  Eisenia fetida, a common composting worm, serves as a lab model.  Outcomes of this award:  We established methods to disrupt genes in the bacterial symbiont Verminephrobacter eiseniae to observe changes in symbiont performance and survival when lacking targeted genes as a way to infer gene functions.  Using gene disruption, we demonstrated two forms of bacterial motility, swimming and twitching, are required for symbiont migration into embryos to colonize the proper tissue.  Swimming motility uses flagella, undulating fibers that move the bacteria.  Twitching uses a fiber that acts as a grappling hook to bind a site, then rapidly pull the cell forward. Without one or the other, the bacteria cannot make it to the colonization site (Dulla et al., 2012, ISMEJ, 6:1166-1175).              In addition to the role of motility, work investigated the cues that allow bacteria to find their final colonization sites in the earthworm embryos.  Bacteria follow a chemical cue to their destination - a behavior known as chemotaxis. We established high-throughput chemotaxis assays to test potentially attractive compounds. V. eiseniae was most highly attracted to compounds related to the function of the organ they inhabit, such as ammonia, urea, and select amino acids.  The next step is to evaluate the chemotaxis of mutants with dysfunctional chemical sensors to confirm the requirement for colonization.              An important discovery during this work was that the bacterial symbionts are able to take up DNA from their environment and incorporate it into their own genome.  Uptake of free DNA is important for rapid adaptation of bacteria because it allows them to pick up genes that may help them adapt to changes in their environment. We were able to show that the symbionts will take up and incorporate DNA while in the egg capsule of the worm, and while in biofilm-like aggregates in culture. This may allow them to take up new DNA from other organisms and acquire new capabilities (Davidson, et al., Frontiers of Microbiology Journal, 2014).              Finally, studies were conducted to characterize biofilm formations by V. eiseniae.  Biofilms often occur in the environment as layers of bacterial cells on surfaces bound in a matrix produced by the bacteria.  Pathogens and beneficial symbionts also form biofilms in hosts when attached to tissues.  Some pathogens require biofilm formation to colonize hosts.  We observed that the earthworm symbiont V. eiseniae formed biofilms in culture in the lab.  Using V. eiseniae mutants with defects in their motility genes, and defects in their ability process glucose, we found that both bacterial pili, structures used for twitching motility, and flagella are required for biofilm formations displayed by the wild type.  Flagellar swimming motility is needed to form larger aggregates that bind together to form the biofilms.  Defects in the uptake and processing of glucose disrupted the formation of the biofilms, indicating that extracellular polysaccharides are likely needed to form larger aggregates.    Intellectual merit: NSF funding provided to the Davidson lab enabled important discoveries about how earthworm symbiotic bacteria find and colonize their specific sites in host worms during embryo development, and developed tools enabling continued research on mechanisms and functions of these widespread earthworm symbioses.  Work established methods to study the symbiont gene functions, providing a tool for identification of genes important for bacterial interactions with animal tissues.  The discovery of natural transformation in a bacterial symbiont provides a mechanism both for gene maintenance, and rapid adaptation in host-associated microbes...]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
