<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Doctoral Dissertation Research:  Learning of Novel Phonetic Categories After Training in Perception and Production</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>02/01/2010</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>01/31/2011</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>6860.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>6860</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>04040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>SBE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>BCS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Behavioral and Cognitive Sci</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>William Badecker</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>wbadecke@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032925069</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Humans possess a remarkable ability to produce and understand speech.  In order to successfully learn a language, an individual must learn what the sound categories in a particular language are and what makes various sounds different from one another.  For instance, "r" and "l" belong to different sound categories in English, but not in some other languages.  Learning how to differentiate between these sounds and produce them is an important part of learning a language. Currently much is known about how listeners learn to perceive the speech sound categories; however, significantly less is known about how speakers learn about speech categories in production and how learning in one modality (i.e., perception or production) is related to learning in the other modality.  The relationship between perception and production could take many forms.  Learning in one modality could always lead learning in the other (i.e., an individual would have to be able to perceive a distinction before they could produce it).  Category formation could occur in parallel for both modalities (i.e., both perception and production could learn about new sounds simultaneously).  Alternately, learning in one modality could actually hinder learning in another modality (e.g., learning in speech production could disrupt learning in speech perception).   This study aims to differentiate among these hypotheses. The experiments in this study are designed to train participants on novel sound categories with the training focusing on either perception or production.  Then participants are tested in both perception and production.  Untangling how new sound categories are formed and accessed in the two modalities will give insight not only into the learning process of new sound categories but also into how the two modalities are related. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The findings of this study will be significant in both theoretical and applied domains.  Having a better understanding of how categories are formed will help inform theories of learning for both first- and second-language learners.  Understanding how speech perception and production are related will be informative in the development of models of speech processing in both perception and production.  In the applied domain, understanding how perception and production interface, particularly at the level of sound categories, will be beneficial for second-language teachers.  Furthermore, clinicians, such as speech-language pathologists, will benefit from a better understanding of how the two modalities interact when learning (or re-learning) novel sound categories.  For instance, if patients have an impairment in speech production, they may be able to use their intact perceptual abilities to re-train the impaired modality.&lt;br/&gt;</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>02/05/2010</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>02/05/2010</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.075</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>0951943</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Matthew</FirstName>
<LastName>Goldrick</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>A</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Matthew A Goldrick</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>matt-goldrick@northwestern.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>8474677092</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000506109</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>02/05/2010</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Melissa</FirstName>
<LastName>Baese-Berk</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>M</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Melissa M Baese-Berk</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>MelissaBaeseBerk2010@u.northwestern.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>8474913003</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000537726</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>02/05/2010</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Northwestern University</Name>
<CityName>Chicago</CityName>
<ZipCode>606114579</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>3125037955</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>750 N. Lake Shore Drive</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[Rubloff 7th Floor]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Illinois</StateName>
<StateCode>IL</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>IL07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>160079455</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>NORTHWESTERN UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>005436803</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Northwestern University]]></Name>
<CityName>Chicago</CityName>
<StateCode>IL</StateCode>
<ZipCode>606114579</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[750 N. Lake Shore Drive]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Illinois</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>IL07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<FoaInformation>
<Code>0116000</Code>
<Name>Human Subjects</Name>
</FoaInformation>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1311</Code>
<Text>Linguistics</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1311</Code>
<Text>LINGUISTICS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9179</Code>
<Text>GRADUATE INVOLVEMENT</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>SMET</Code>
<Text>SCIENCE, MATH, ENG &amp; TECH EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0110</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2010~6860</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Humans possess a remarkable ability to produce and understand speech. In order to successfully learn a language, an individual must learn what the sound categories in a particular language are and what makes various sounds different from one another. For instance, "r" and "l" belong to different sound categories in English, but not in some other languages. Learning how to differentiate between these sounds and produce them is an important part of learning a language. Currently much is known about how listeners learn to perceive the speech sound categories; however, significantly less is known about how speakers learn about speech categories in production and how learning in one modality (i.e., perception or production) is related to learning in the other modality. The relationship between perception and production could take many forms. Learning in one modality could always lead learning in the other (i.e., an individual would have to be able to perceive a distinction before they could produce it).&nbsp; Learning under this type of hypothesis could result in synergistic learning, in which learning in one modality transfers to the other modality.&nbsp; Additionally, category formation could occur in parallel for both modalities (i.e., both perception and production could learn about new sounds simultaneously). Alternately, learning in one modality could actually hinder learning in another modality (e.g., learning in speech production could disrupt learning in speech perception). This study aimed to differentiate among these hypotheses. The experiments in this study were designed to train participants on novel sound categories with the training focusing on either perception or production. Then, participants were tested in both perception and production. Untangling how new sound categories are formed and accessed in the two modalities will give insight not only into the learning process of new sound categories but also into how the two modalities are related.</p> <p>The basic findings of this study demonstrate that learners whose training focused on perception demonstrate robust perceptual learning and a small amount of learning in production as well.&nbsp; This suggests that at least some learning in the perceptual domain transfers to production.&nbsp; Learners whose training focused on production demonstrate no significant perceptual learning after two days of training;&nbsp; however, they do demonstrate robust learning in production.&nbsp; Further examination suggests that differences in perceptual learning between the two training groups are alleviated by a third day of training.</p> <p>These findings suggest that the relationship between perception and production at the earliest stages of learning is complex, and does not fall easily into any one of the proposed hypotheses.&nbsp; After training in perception, learners demonstrate synergistic learning, in which learning in perception transfers to production.&nbsp; However, after training in production, we see an antagonistic relationship between the two modalities, in which production learning disrupts, or at least slows down, perceptual learning.&nbsp; This suggests that while the two modalities may share some connection, this connection is not an automatic link which shares all information between the two modalities.&nbsp; It is likely that the hypotheses proposed above are too simplistic in nature, and future examinations of the nature of the relationship between perception and production should include investigations of the roles of attention and processing resources during learning.<br /> <br /> The findings of this study are significant in both theoretical and applied domains. Having a better understanding of how categories are formed will help inform theories of learning for both first- and second-language learners. Understanding how speech perception and production are related will be informative in the de...]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Humans possess a remarkable ability to produce and understand speech. In order to successfully learn a language, an individual must learn what the sound categories in a particular language are and what makes various sounds different from one another. For instance, "r" and "l" belong to different sound categories in English, but not in some other languages. Learning how to differentiate between these sounds and produce them is an important part of learning a language. Currently much is known about how listeners learn to perceive the speech sound categories; however, significantly less is known about how speakers learn about speech categories in production and how learning in one modality (i.e., perception or production) is related to learning in the other modality. The relationship between perception and production could take many forms. Learning in one modality could always lead learning in the other (i.e., an individual would have to be able to perceive a distinction before they could produce it).  Learning under this type of hypothesis could result in synergistic learning, in which learning in one modality transfers to the other modality.  Additionally, category formation could occur in parallel for both modalities (i.e., both perception and production could learn about new sounds simultaneously). Alternately, learning in one modality could actually hinder learning in another modality (e.g., learning in speech production could disrupt learning in speech perception). This study aimed to differentiate among these hypotheses. The experiments in this study were designed to train participants on novel sound categories with the training focusing on either perception or production. Then, participants were tested in both perception and production. Untangling how new sound categories are formed and accessed in the two modalities will give insight not only into the learning process of new sound categories but also into how the two modalities are related.  The basic findings of this study demonstrate that learners whose training focused on perception demonstrate robust perceptual learning and a small amount of learning in production as well.  This suggests that at least some learning in the perceptual domain transfers to production.  Learners whose training focused on production demonstrate no significant perceptual learning after two days of training;  however, they do demonstrate robust learning in production.  Further examination suggests that differences in perceptual learning between the two training groups are alleviated by a third day of training.  These findings suggest that the relationship between perception and production at the earliest stages of learning is complex, and does not fall easily into any one of the proposed hypotheses.  After training in perception, learners demonstrate synergistic learning, in which learning in perception transfers to production.  However, after training in production, we see an antagonistic relationship between the two modalities, in which production learning disrupts, or at least slows down, perceptual learning.  This suggests that while the two modalities may share some connection, this connection is not an automatic link which shares all information between the two modalities.  It is likely that the hypotheses proposed above are too simplistic in nature, and future examinations of the nature of the relationship between perception and production should include investigations of the roles of attention and processing resources during learning.    The findings of this study are significant in both theoretical and applied domains. Having a better understanding of how categories are formed will help inform theories of learning for both first- and second-language learners. Understanding how speech perception and production are related will be informative in the development of models of speech processing in both perception and production. In the applied domain, understanding how perception and pr...]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
