<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>CAREER:   Advancing Macroecology Using Informatics and Entropy Maximization</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>03/15/2010</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>02/29/2016</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>649999.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>657499</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>08010208</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>BIO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DEB</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Environmental Biology</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Alan Tessier</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>atessier@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927198</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Climate change, invasive species and other important factors impacting ecological systems operate at continental to global scales. At these scales, conducting experiments can be difficult, if not impossible. Therefore, ecologists increasingly rely on analyses of large scale observational data to predict how these systems will respond to increasing changes in climate and habitat. Progress in this area of research has been slowed by the large number of patterns used to characterize ecological structure, and by the fact that most research focuses on a single group of species thus limiting the generality of the results. This project will increase the speed at which knowledge of ecological systems is acquired by characterizing the relationships among ecological patterns and focusing research on the small number of key patterns that need to be studied to understand the behavior of ecological systems. This will be accomplished using advanced methods from physics that characterize the most likely form of an ecological pattern given a small number of constraints on the system. This research will test the performance of this approach using data on wide variety of species. This method will then be combined with established ecological models to predict a suite of major ecological patterns using only a small number of environmental variables.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project will improve how ecologists test and establish the generality of theories by educating ecologists in advanced computational methods through online and university courses, by providing web-based resources on the collections of data that are available and how to utilize them, and by automating complicated database tasks using computer programs that download, configure, and install optimized versions of ecological databases, thus allowing the rapid incorporation of available data into research projects. This combined research and education program has the potential to substantially improve the rate at which the field of ecology advances by focusing the research effort on a smaller number of patterns and processes, and by allowing ecologists to rapidly determine if a given pattern or hypothesis is general and if not how it varies among ecological systems.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>03/04/2010</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>09/09/2011</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.074</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>0953694</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Ethan</FirstName>
<LastName>White</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>P</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Ethan P White</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>ethanwhite@ufl.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>4357601909</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000246060</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>03/04/2010</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Utah State University</Name>
<CityName>Logan</CityName>
<ZipCode>843221415</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>4357971226</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>Sponsored Programs Office</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[1415 Old Main Hill ~ Room 64]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Utah</StateName>
<StateCode>UT</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>UT01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>072983455</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UTAH STATE UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>072983455</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Utah State University]]></Name>
<CityName>Logan</CityName>
<StateCode>UT</StateCode>
<ZipCode>843221415</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[Sponsored Programs Office]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Utah</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>UT01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1182</Code>
<Text>POP &amp; COMMUNITY ECOL PROG</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1045</Code>
<Text>CAREER-Faculty Erly Career Dev</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1182</Code>
<Text>POP &amp; COMMUNITY ECOL PROG</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1187</Code>
<Text>PECASE- eligible</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1355</Code>
<Text>EGC EDUCATIONAL ACTIVITIES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9169</Code>
<Text>BIODIVERSITY AND ECOSYSTEM DYNAMICS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9178</Code>
<Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9251</Code>
<Text>REU SUPP-Res Exp for Ugrd Supp</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>EGCH</Code>
<Text>ENVIRONMENT AND GLOBAL CHANGE</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>SMET</Code>
<Text>SCIENCE, MATH, ENG &amp; TECH EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0110</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0111</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2010~135000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2011~522499</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The intellectual merit and broader impacts of this grant combine to help ecological research maximally benefit from the large amounts of data that are increasingly available for ecological systems and from new general theories that predict large numbers of ecological patterns simultaneously.<br /><br />Our research compares approaches to modeling ecological systems to find models that accurately describe patterns of diversity across different ecosystems and types of species. We do this by comparing the predictions of theoretical models to large compilations of ecological data from citizen science, government surveys, and academic research. We found that a new group models based on statistical physics showed potential for explaining a number of ecological patterns with only a small amount of information, but that these models exhibited several important deficiencies. We found that simple models based on birth, death, dispersal, and growth of organisms provided better descriptions of ecological patterns than the statistical physics approaches. We also developed a new set of methods for understanding how much information about ecological processes is present in different ecological patterns by describing the possible forms that these patterns can take. In combination our research is helping to change our approaches to testing ecological theory by leading the way in using data from across ecosystems, across the diversity of life, and across the array of predictions made by may theories.<br /><br />Our broader impacts involved educational and research tool initiatives that are targeted across scientific and engineering disciplines with the intent of broadly improving the acquisition of data skills and development of data scientists. This makes the kind of data-intensive research we do possible for the next generation of scientists through a combination of training, software, and access to information. We trained thousands of scientists online and hundreds in classrooms and workshops on how to efficiently create, store, manage, and analyze data. We created software that is widely used to automate data cleaning and restructuring tasks so that scientists can focus on doing science. We created online resources to help scientists quickly find the data they need to answer a question and learn how to work with it. We wrote a series of papers on best practices for data management and scientific computing that have been widely read and are having a major impact on how scientists conduct research.<br /><br />In addition to these broader community wide efforts, seven graduate students (including a veteran, two first-generation college students, an underrepresented minority, and a student with a chronic illness), two undergraduates, and two postdoctoral researchers, participated in this research and received in-depth training in advanced data and computational approaches to science. This prepared them for jobs in a diverse array of industries. Trainees from this grant are currently employed in the technology industry, government funded research organizations, research universities, and higher education.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 05/23/2016<br>      Modified by: Ethan&nbsp;P&nbsp;White</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The intellectual merit and broader impacts of this grant combine to help ecological research maximally benefit from the large amounts of data that are increasingly available for ecological systems and from new general theories that predict large numbers of ecological patterns simultaneously.  Our research compares approaches to modeling ecological systems to find models that accurately describe patterns of diversity across different ecosystems and types of species. We do this by comparing the predictions of theoretical models to large compilations of ecological data from citizen science, government surveys, and academic research. We found that a new group models based on statistical physics showed potential for explaining a number of ecological patterns with only a small amount of information, but that these models exhibited several important deficiencies. We found that simple models based on birth, death, dispersal, and growth of organisms provided better descriptions of ecological patterns than the statistical physics approaches. We also developed a new set of methods for understanding how much information about ecological processes is present in different ecological patterns by describing the possible forms that these patterns can take. In combination our research is helping to change our approaches to testing ecological theory by leading the way in using data from across ecosystems, across the diversity of life, and across the array of predictions made by may theories.  Our broader impacts involved educational and research tool initiatives that are targeted across scientific and engineering disciplines with the intent of broadly improving the acquisition of data skills and development of data scientists. This makes the kind of data-intensive research we do possible for the next generation of scientists through a combination of training, software, and access to information. We trained thousands of scientists online and hundreds in classrooms and workshops on how to efficiently create, store, manage, and analyze data. We created software that is widely used to automate data cleaning and restructuring tasks so that scientists can focus on doing science. We created online resources to help scientists quickly find the data they need to answer a question and learn how to work with it. We wrote a series of papers on best practices for data management and scientific computing that have been widely read and are having a major impact on how scientists conduct research.  In addition to these broader community wide efforts, seven graduate students (including a veteran, two first-generation college students, an underrepresented minority, and a student with a chronic illness), two undergraduates, and two postdoctoral researchers, participated in this research and received in-depth training in advanced data and computational approaches to science. This prepared them for jobs in a diverse array of industries. Trainees from this grant are currently employed in the technology industry, government funded research organizations, research universities, and higher education.       Last Modified: 05/23/2016       Submitted by: Ethan P White]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
