<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>CAREER: Markets for Network Services</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>02/01/2010</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>02/28/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>400000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>500000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>05050000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>CSE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CNS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Computer and Network Systems</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>John Brassil</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The economic model of network services, both services for basic connectivity as well as application layer services delivered via the network, is undergoing a period of unprecedented change. For instance, Internet Service Providers (ISPs) that offer services such as voice over IP are deciding to use proprietary forms of service differentiation to improve these service offerings over those of competitors. As more ISPs implement service differentiation in a proprietary way, there is a danger that the opportunity to have a coherent architectural approach to service differentiation will be lost. This issue is tied to the net neutrality debate, in which one core issue is how ISPs and content/application service providers should share revenue. Some fundamental questions include the following. What are the market effects of having only competition between proprietary service stacks versus having competition at each layer? What architectural principles should be established in law or standards to induce the development of a market structure that results in higher welfare for all the stakeholders? Should both standard interfaces and/or charging practices be enforced between providers? This project investigates questions such as these in order to achieve a more complete understanding of the coupling of architecture and economics in network services. The project develops game theoretic models of the interaction of selfish users and providers, and then uses these models to understand the welfare effects of different architectural choices. The results of this project will inform the development of both the architecture and market structure of the network services industry.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>01/25/2010</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/02/2017</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.070</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>0953884</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>John</FirstName>
<LastName>Musacchio</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>T</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>John T Musacchio</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>johnm@soe.ucsc.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>8314591385</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000277483</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>01/25/2010</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of California-Santa Cruz</Name>
<CityName>Santa Cruz</CityName>
<ZipCode>950641077</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>8314595278</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1156 High Street</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>20</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CA20</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>125084723</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF CALIFORNIA, SANTA CRUZ</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>071549000</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of California-Santa Cruz]]></Name>
<CityName>Santa Cruz</CityName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>950641077</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[1156 High Street]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>20</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CA20</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<FoaInformation>
<Code>0000912</Code>
<Name>Computer Science</Name>
</FoaInformation>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1640</Code>
<Text>Information Technology Researc</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7363</Code>
<Text>Networking Technology and Syst</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1045</Code>
<Text>CAREER-Faculty Erly Career Dev</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1187</Code>
<Text>PECASE- eligible</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0110</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0112</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0113</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0114</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2010~200000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2012~100000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2013~100000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~100000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The project was based on the premise that the economic model of network services, both services for basic connectivity as well as application layer services delivered via the network, is undergoing a period of unprecedented change. We investigated a number of fundamental issues in this context.&nbsp; One area relates to the net-neutrality debate that has been an area of controversy for over a decade. Our work in the project built on work began before the project to expose how different conditions can affect the competitive balance between and Internet Service Providers and Content Providers and thus affect whether or not a &ldquo;neutral&rdquo; network would result in a better outcome.&nbsp; (In our model, a &ldquo;neutral&rdquo; network means that ISPs that serve end users can charge content providers.)</p> <p>Another part of our work looked at the particular aspects of competition in networks in general. One particular line of investigation uncovered conditions of when a two-stage market can be more efficient than a single stage market. We also investigate selfish routing games in networks, and in particular the value in having sources route their traffic &ldquo;altruistically&rdquo;, that is considering at least to some degree the cost their routing choice imposes on the other traffic sources.</p> <p>Another part of our work explored the incentives of participants in the network as they relate to security. In one particular line of investigation, we studied how an individual that is part of a larger network sets their &ldquo;threshold&rdquo; of when deciding to act on the hypothesis that poor performance of their computer may be a symptom of being compromised by a botnet.&nbsp; In many cases, users are not as sensitive to these possible threats as would be socially optimal -- since individuals consider their own utility and not that their actions could block &ldquo;contagion&rdquo; from spreading to others. In another, related, line of work, we explore the fundamentals of adversarial classification games. In such games, it is often the (Nash) equilibrium for the party trying to evade classification to randomize their strategy, to make classification harder. Moreover, in equilibrium the party doing the classification also has an incentive to randomize their strategy as well.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 08/17/2018<br>      Modified by: John&nbsp;T&nbsp;Musacchio</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The project was based on the premise that the economic model of network services, both services for basic connectivity as well as application layer services delivered via the network, is undergoing a period of unprecedented change. We investigated a number of fundamental issues in this context.  One area relates to the net-neutrality debate that has been an area of controversy for over a decade. Our work in the project built on work began before the project to expose how different conditions can affect the competitive balance between and Internet Service Providers and Content Providers and thus affect whether or not a "neutral" network would result in a better outcome.  (In our model, a "neutral" network means that ISPs that serve end users can charge content providers.)  Another part of our work looked at the particular aspects of competition in networks in general. One particular line of investigation uncovered conditions of when a two-stage market can be more efficient than a single stage market. We also investigate selfish routing games in networks, and in particular the value in having sources route their traffic "altruistically", that is considering at least to some degree the cost their routing choice imposes on the other traffic sources.  Another part of our work explored the incentives of participants in the network as they relate to security. In one particular line of investigation, we studied how an individual that is part of a larger network sets their "threshold" of when deciding to act on the hypothesis that poor performance of their computer may be a symptom of being compromised by a botnet.  In many cases, users are not as sensitive to these possible threats as would be socially optimal -- since individuals consider their own utility and not that their actions could block "contagion" from spreading to others. In another, related, line of work, we explore the fundamentals of adversarial classification games. In such games, it is often the (Nash) equilibrium for the party trying to evade classification to randomize their strategy, to make classification harder. Moreover, in equilibrium the party doing the classification also has an incentive to randomize their strategy as well.       Last Modified: 08/17/2018       Submitted by: John T Musacchio]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
