<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>CAREER: Loop engineering of protein surfaces for tunable self-association and phase behavior</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>03/01/2010</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>02/29/2016</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>411872.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>438095</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07020000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CBET</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Chem, Bioeng, Env, &amp; Transp Sys</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Nora Savage</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>nosavage@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927949</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>0954450&lt;br/&gt;Tessier&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Antibodies represent an increasingly important class of molecules to treat human disease. There is significant interest in controlling the phase behavior of these macromolecules, ranging from preventing their condensation (in high concentration therapeutic formulations) to promoting it (for protein crystallization). The objective of this project is to elucidate how antibody self-association and phase behavior can be modulated in a systematic manner through alteration of solvent exposed loops on antibody surfaces. Importantly, little is known about how solvent exposed residues impact protein selfassociation and phase behavior, which we argue is due to: i) the lack of relevant homologous protein libraries with sequence variations only on their surface; ii) the inability to introduce significant, systematic alterations to protein surfaces without disrupting their folded structure; and iii) the difficulty in measuring protein self interactions in a reliable and rapid manner.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Intellectual Merit: In this project it is postulated that solvent-exposed peptide loops (5-20 residues) on the surface of small antibodies (12 kD) can be engineered to regulate the self-association and phase behavior of both natively and non-natively folded antibodies, and that these loops can be used to control the corresponding solution behavior of unrelated proteins via loop grafting. Moreover, it is postulated that small antibodies with well-defined surface loops are attractive model proteins for such studies since they are highly tolerant to large changes in loop size and composition without altering their folding stability. Therefore, to test these hypotheses, the investigators propose four Specific Aims that build on our unique strengths in biophysical analysis of protein solution thermodynamics, colloidal and interface science, and molecular biology and biochemistry. In Specific Aim 1, it is planned to investigate the impact of sequence variations (hydrophobicity, charge, length and flexibility) in a single solvent exposed antibody loop on native antibody self association (in terms of the osmotic second virial coefficient) and phase behavior. Next, in Specific Aim 2, they propose to elucidate the mechanisms by which antibody loops studied in Aim 1 influence native antibody self-interactions, and to determine if a subset of these loop sequences are capable of regulating the corresponding thermodynamic behavior of unrelated proteins via loop grafting. Then, in Specific Aim 3, they propose to ascertain if the unique non-native solubilities (after transient heat treatment) of antibody variants studied in Aims 1 and 2 (which differ only in their loop sequences) can be linked to measurements of their native protein self interactions, akin to the "crystallization slot" concept that links attractive protein self interactions to low solubility (and increased likelihood of protein crystallization) of natively folded proteins. Finally, in Specific Aim 4, they propose to elucidate how an antibody closely related to those studied in Aims 1-3 that is aggregation prone (in both its native and nonnative states) can be engineered to be aggregation resistant with minimal sequence alteration through comprehensive mutational and self-interaction analysis of the contribution of each loop residue to the undesirable antibody self-association behavior.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Broader Impacts: This project, deeply rooted in molecular thermodynamics and interfacial engineering science, has broad implications for preventing disease-associated protein aggregation, making potentially more stable therapeutic proteins, and manipulating assembly of protein crystals. In terms of education, the PIs are committed to modernizing their curricula at Rensselaer by introducing undergraduate and graduate students to molecular-level concepts through a new course (Biomolecular Engineering) and laboratory experiment&lt;br/&gt;(crystallization). They are also committed to strong outreach to underrepresented minorities and other disadvantaged peoples through two efforts: i) a 4th grade science outreach program in an elementary school with a significant fraction of reduced lunch (~80%) and African American (~40%) students focused on molecules using animated cartoons and hands-on activities to interest these students in science at an early age; and ii) a 12th grade outreach program to diverse students from rural towns in New York's Capital District lacking advanced science courses that involves these students in the process of discovery and development of a therapeutic antibody to encourage them to pursue biomolecular aspects of science and engineering during their undergraduate and graduate education.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>03/01/2010</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/13/2015</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>0954450</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Peter</FirstName>
<LastName>Tessier</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>M</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Peter M Tessier</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>ptessier@umich.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>7347631486</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000512553</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>03/01/2010</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Rensselaer Polytechnic Institute</Name>
<CityName>Troy</CityName>
<ZipCode>121803522</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5182766000</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>110 8TH ST</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>20</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NY20</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>002430742</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>RENSSELAER POLYTECHNIC INSTITUTE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>002430742</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Rensselaer Polytechnic Institute]]></Name>
<CityName>Troy</CityName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<ZipCode>121803522</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[110 8TH ST]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>20</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NY20</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1414</Code>
<Text>INTERFAC PROCESSES &amp; THERMODYN</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>004E</Code>
<Text>BIOMEDICAL ENG AND DIAGNOSTICS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>015E</Code>
<Text>Pollutant fate and transport</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>051E</Code>
<Text>Interfacial trans &amp; thermodynamic</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>054E</Code>
<Text>Molecular engineering</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1045</Code>
<Text>CAREER-Faculty Erly Career Dev</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1187</Code>
<Text>PECASE- eligible</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7237</Code>
<Text>NANO NON-SOLIC SCI &amp; ENG AWD</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0110</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0111</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0112</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0114</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0115</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2010~46693</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2011~85600</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2012~182398</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~97181</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2015~26223</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Antibodies are large proteins used by the immune system to recognize and neutralize foreign invaders such as viruses and bacteria. These affinity proteins are now being widely used as therapeutic molecules for treating human disorders ranging from arthritis to cancer. Nevertheless, there are a number of technological challenges that must be overcome to safely develop and deliver therapeutic antibodies that were the focus of this research study. The main hypothesis of this study was that the loops of antibodies &ndash; which normally mediate binding to their target molecules &ndash; are also responsible for mediating antibody self-interactions that lead to poor antibody solubility.</p> <p>To test this hypothesis, the investigators evaluated the impact of hydrophilic (water-loving) and hydrophobic (water-hating) mutations in antibody binding loops on antibody solubility and aggregation. Importantly, hydrophobic regions of antibody binding loops were often found to contribute disproportionately to poor antibody solubility. The investigators also discovered that charged (hydrophilic) mutations inserted near these hydrophobic regions could greatly improve antibody solubility without reducing antibody binding affinity to target molecules. Interestingly, the proximity of charged mutations relative to the hydrophobic regions within antibody binding loops was particularly important, and even small shifts in the position of such charged mutations away from the hydrophobic regions strongly reduced antibody solubility. The investigators also discovered that matching the charge of mutations (i.e., positive or negative) to the net charge of the corresponding antibody was particularly important, as positively-charged mutations in the binding loops were much more effective at improving the solubility of positively-charged antibodies and vice versa for negatively-charged mutations. Using these findings, the investigators designed antibodies that were specific for the Alzheimer&rsquo;s peptide, the latter of which aggregates and contributes to the death of brain cells. The designed Alzheimer&rsquo;s antibodies exploit the hydrophobic interactions that naturally mediate Alzheimer&rsquo;s peptide aggregation to mediate antibody binding, and charged mutations in the antibody binding loops to mediate high antibody solubility. These discoveries are expected to improve methods for designing and optimizing antibodies for a wide range of applications. &nbsp;</p> <p>This project has also led to a number of important broader impacts. The scientific findings of this study have broad implications for preventing disease-associated protein aggregation and increasing the stability of therapeutic proteins. In terms of education, the research project has also led to the development of more modern classes at Rensselaer by introducing undergraduate and graduate students to molecular-level concepts through new courses and laboratory experiments. In addition, this project has involved a strong outreach program to underrepresented minorities and other disadvantaged peoples in New York&rsquo;s Capital District. These efforts have encouraged such students to pursue biomolecular aspects of science and engineering during their undergraduate and graduate education.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 05/20/2016<br>      Modified by: Peter&nbsp;M&nbsp;Tessier</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Antibodies are large proteins used by the immune system to recognize and neutralize foreign invaders such as viruses and bacteria. These affinity proteins are now being widely used as therapeutic molecules for treating human disorders ranging from arthritis to cancer. Nevertheless, there are a number of technological challenges that must be overcome to safely develop and deliver therapeutic antibodies that were the focus of this research study. The main hypothesis of this study was that the loops of antibodies &ndash; which normally mediate binding to their target molecules &ndash; are also responsible for mediating antibody self-interactions that lead to poor antibody solubility.  To test this hypothesis, the investigators evaluated the impact of hydrophilic (water-loving) and hydrophobic (water-hating) mutations in antibody binding loops on antibody solubility and aggregation. Importantly, hydrophobic regions of antibody binding loops were often found to contribute disproportionately to poor antibody solubility. The investigators also discovered that charged (hydrophilic) mutations inserted near these hydrophobic regions could greatly improve antibody solubility without reducing antibody binding affinity to target molecules. Interestingly, the proximity of charged mutations relative to the hydrophobic regions within antibody binding loops was particularly important, and even small shifts in the position of such charged mutations away from the hydrophobic regions strongly reduced antibody solubility. The investigators also discovered that matching the charge of mutations (i.e., positive or negative) to the net charge of the corresponding antibody was particularly important, as positively-charged mutations in the binding loops were much more effective at improving the solubility of positively-charged antibodies and vice versa for negatively-charged mutations. Using these findings, the investigators designed antibodies that were specific for the AlzheimerÆs peptide, the latter of which aggregates and contributes to the death of brain cells. The designed AlzheimerÆs antibodies exploit the hydrophobic interactions that naturally mediate AlzheimerÆs peptide aggregation to mediate antibody binding, and charged mutations in the antibody binding loops to mediate high antibody solubility. These discoveries are expected to improve methods for designing and optimizing antibodies for a wide range of applications.    This project has also led to a number of important broader impacts. The scientific findings of this study have broad implications for preventing disease-associated protein aggregation and increasing the stability of therapeutic proteins. In terms of education, the research project has also led to the development of more modern classes at Rensselaer by introducing undergraduate and graduate students to molecular-level concepts through new courses and laboratory experiments. In addition, this project has involved a strong outreach program to underrepresented minorities and other disadvantaged peoples in New YorkÆs Capital District. These efforts have encouraged such students to pursue biomolecular aspects of science and engineering during their undergraduate and graduate education.       Last Modified: 05/20/2016       Submitted by: Peter M Tessier]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
