<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>CAREER: Algebraic Problems in Statistics and Biology</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2010</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2016</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>400000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>400000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DMS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Andrew Pollington</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>adpollin@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924878</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The long-term goal of the proposed research is to develop theoretical and computational methods to solve problems in algebraic statistics and its applications. The specific problem areas described in this proposal concern Gaussian graphical models and statistical models in evolutionary biology. The problems in the proposal have typically been open for many years and are fundamentally of an algebraic character; however, advanced algebraic techniques have rarely been applied to them.  The motivation for studying these problems comes from the fact that the statistical models under investigation in the proposal arise frequently in applications, including economics, computational biology, and sociology.  The specific problems that Sullivant will address for Gaussian graphical models are the identification problem, the computation and existence of maximum likelihood estimates, and the structure of covariance constraints.  The specific problems that Sullivant will address in evolutionary biology are the identifiability of mixture models, the computational and combinatorial complexity of gene trees and species trees, and the comparison of speciation models to tree building algorithms.  The techniques Sullivant will employ to address these problems come from computational algebra, algebraic geometry, and combinatorics.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Algebra is the mathematical study of sets with operations, for example the set of all polynomials with the operations of "adding polynomials" and "multiplying polynomials".  Statistics is the science of data analysis.  Parametric statistics uses statistical models  (families of probability distributions) as tools for analyzing data.  Algebra and statistics come together in the field of algebraic statistics, which is based on the observation that many parametric statistical models are described parametrically via polynomials.  Sullivant proposes to exploit the algebra/statistics connection to address a number of problems in algebraic statistics and its applications to evolutionary biology.  In evolutionary biology, Sullivant and his students will study phylogenetic models, which are statistical models for determining the ancestral relationships between a collection of extant species.  These models are used in applications in increasingly complicated ways, but even basic questions about the models remain open.  The projects in the proposal will involve research with both graduate and undergraduate students.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>04/13/2010</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/28/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>0954865</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Seth</FirstName>
<LastName>Sullivant</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>M</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Seth M Sullivant</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>smsulli2@ncsu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>9195137445</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000459001</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/13/2010</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>North Carolina State University</Name>
<CityName>Raleigh</CityName>
<ZipCode>276957514</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>9195152444</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>2601 Wolf Village Way</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[Admin. III, STE 240]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>North Carolina</StateName>
<StateCode>NC</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NC04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>042092122</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>NORTH CAROLINA STATE UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>142363428</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[North Carolina State University]]></Name>
<CityName>Raleigh</CityName>
<StateCode>NC</StateCode>
<ZipCode>276957514</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[2601 Wolf Village Way]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>North Carolina</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NC04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1264</Code>
<Text>ALGEBRA,NUMBER THEORY,AND COM</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1269</Code>
<Text>STATISTICS</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>0000</Code>
<Text>UNASSIGNED</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1045</Code>
<Text>CAREER-Faculty Erly Career Dev</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1187</Code>
<Text>PECASE- eligible</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>OTHR</Code>
<Text>OTHER RESEARCH OR EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0110</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0111</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0112</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0113</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0114</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2010~76449</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2011~76898</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2012~96494</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2013~83982</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~66177</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Statistical models are widely used as tools in the analysis of data.&nbsp; As data sets become increasingly more complicated, researchers develop increasingly more sophisticated models to handle the analysis of these data sets.&nbsp; Succesful application of statistical procedures based on these models depends on the models satisfying important theoretical properties --&nbsp; properties that can be difficult to verify on the complex models using standard techniques.&nbsp; The goal this project has been to develop techniques for mathematically analyzing the underlying statistical models.&nbsp; These results ensure that statistical analysis&nbsp; based on the models is well-founded.&nbsp; Specific families of statistical models studied in the project include the gaussian graphical models and phylogenetic models, both used in biological applications.</p> <p>The mathematical tools developed to address these problems come from the mathematical area of algebraic geometry.&nbsp; Algebra is the study of discrete structures and sets with operations.&nbsp; Key objects in algebra are polynomials and rational functions.&nbsp; Algebraic geometry is the study of solutions to systems of polynomial equations. Algebraic geometry arises in statistics because parametric statistical models often involve polynomials and rational functions.The fields of statistics and algebraic geometry come together in the field of "algebraic statistics".</p> <p>Some specific highlighted outcomes that were realized as a result of this project include:</p> <p>1)&nbsp; Developed the theory of the maximum likelihood threshold of a gaussian graphical model and showed its connection to combinatorial rigidity theory. These results help to answer the question: how much data do you need to be able to estimate parameters in these models?</p> <p>2)&nbsp; Performed a systematic computational study of identifiability of gaussian graphical models, and published results on a website.&nbsp; This help answer the question:&nbsp; which model parameters can be estimated from data?</p> <p>3)&nbsp; Proved the strongest available results on generic identifiability of phylogenetic mixture models.&nbsp; Thesse results help answer the question: how complex can certain models become without becoming too complex to perform data analysis?</p> <p>4)&nbsp; Studied the geometric decomposition of the space of metrics based on various phylogenetic tree reconstruction optimzation criteria and related heuristics.&nbsp; These results help answer the question: how well do fast heuristics work when problems are too hard to solve exactly, and when might they give the wrong answer?</p> <p>In addition to the research results mentioned above, this project supported the research of 5 PhD students including to help train them for careers either inside or outside academia.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 08/17/2016<br>      Modified by: Seth&nbsp;M&nbsp;Sullivant</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Statistical models are widely used as tools in the analysis of data.  As data sets become increasingly more complicated, researchers develop increasingly more sophisticated models to handle the analysis of these data sets.  Succesful application of statistical procedures based on these models depends on the models satisfying important theoretical properties --  properties that can be difficult to verify on the complex models using standard techniques.  The goal this project has been to develop techniques for mathematically analyzing the underlying statistical models.  These results ensure that statistical analysis  based on the models is well-founded.  Specific families of statistical models studied in the project include the gaussian graphical models and phylogenetic models, both used in biological applications.  The mathematical tools developed to address these problems come from the mathematical area of algebraic geometry.  Algebra is the study of discrete structures and sets with operations.  Key objects in algebra are polynomials and rational functions.  Algebraic geometry is the study of solutions to systems of polynomial equations. Algebraic geometry arises in statistics because parametric statistical models often involve polynomials and rational functions.The fields of statistics and algebraic geometry come together in the field of "algebraic statistics".  Some specific highlighted outcomes that were realized as a result of this project include:  1)  Developed the theory of the maximum likelihood threshold of a gaussian graphical model and showed its connection to combinatorial rigidity theory. These results help to answer the question: how much data do you need to be able to estimate parameters in these models?  2)  Performed a systematic computational study of identifiability of gaussian graphical models, and published results on a website.  This help answer the question:  which model parameters can be estimated from data?  3)  Proved the strongest available results on generic identifiability of phylogenetic mixture models.  Thesse results help answer the question: how complex can certain models become without becoming too complex to perform data analysis?  4)  Studied the geometric decomposition of the space of metrics based on various phylogenetic tree reconstruction optimzation criteria and related heuristics.  These results help answer the question: how well do fast heuristics work when problems are too hard to solve exactly, and when might they give the wrong answer?  In addition to the research results mentioned above, this project supported the research of 5 PhD students including to help train them for careers either inside or outside academia.          Last Modified: 08/17/2016       Submitted by: Seth M Sullivant]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
