<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>CAREER: Climate Informed Uncertainty Analyses for Integrated Water Resources Sustainability</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>06/01/2010</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>404351.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>424351</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07020000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CBET</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Chem, Bioeng, Env, &amp; Transp Sys</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Bruce Hamilton</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>bhamilto@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927066</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>0954405&lt;br/&gt;Arumugam&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The objectives of  this research are to (1) quantify the relative roles of climate variability in modulating seasonal streamflow and water quality variability over relatively undeveloped basins in the southeastern U.S., (2) investigate the utility of seasonal climate forecasts in improving water supply and water quality management and in developing adaptive water management plans for promoting water sustainability in regions such as the Neuse river basin, NC, (3) integrate research findings into (i) on-campus and distance education courses at NCSU, (ii) water-related courses at HCBUs in NC, and (iii) summer training programs for junior/senior high school students, and (4) demonstrate to federal and state agencies, research institutes and non-profits the use of climate forecasts in developing streamflow and water quality forecasts for impaired water bodies, for example, in NC.  Various measures will be employed to quantify the causal chain that associates climatic variability with streamflow and water quality variability.  Multiple General Circulation Models (GCMs) forecasts will be utilized to develop streamflow and water quality forecasts, which are ingested into water allocation and water quality management models.  Retrospective analyses using these forecasts will be performed to develop an integrated water management plan.  This research aims to create a fundamental body of knowledge on understanding the role of climate variability in modulating streamflow and water quality in river basins.  It is expected that findings from this research will offer insights on the vulnerability of water quality attributes to climatic variability.  Streamflow forecasts developed using GCM forecasts will reduce model uncertainty and improve seasonal water allocation and water quality management plans.  Generalizing the findings will help in understanding the potential utility of climate forecasts in promoting water resources sustainability.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>12/22/2009</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/16/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>0954405</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Sankarasubraman</FirstName>
<LastName>Arumugam</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Sankarasubraman Arumugam</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>sankar_arumugam@ncsu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>9195157700</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000104872</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>12/22/2009</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>North Carolina State University</Name>
<CityName>Raleigh</CityName>
<ZipCode>276957514</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>9195152444</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>2601 Wolf Village Way</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[Admin. III, STE 240]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>North Carolina</StateName>
<StateCode>NC</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NC04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>042092122</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>NORTH CAROLINA STATE UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>142363428</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[North Carolina State University]]></Name>
<CityName>Raleigh</CityName>
<StateCode>NC</StateCode>
<ZipCode>276957514</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[2601 Wolf Village Way]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>North Carolina</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NC04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7643</Code>
<Text>EnvS-Environmtl Sustainability</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>021E</Code>
<Text>Water management</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1045</Code>
<Text>CAREER-Faculty Erly Career Dev</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1187</Code>
<Text>PECASE- eligible</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0110</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0111</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0113</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0116</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2010~75556</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2011~158473</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2013~170322</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2016~20000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The primary objective of this CAREER research is to understand the causal linkages between climate, streamflow and water quality variability over the Southeast US (SEUS). Towards this, the project focused on 18 virgin basins over the SEUS spanning from seven states (VA to FL and MS). It is well known that climate drives streamflow and streamflow drives total nitrogen (TN) variability. Given this causal linkage, this study focused on developing TN forecasts using seasonal climate forecasts developed by using Sea Surface Temperature (SST) forecasts. &nbsp;The primary challenge in developing water quality forecasts is the limited availability of observed data. &nbsp;Hence, we used modeled water quality data to develop the climate data, but we systematically transformed the skill in predicting modeled values based on the water quality model skill. &nbsp;Analyses of 18 basins showed that there is considerable potential in developing forecasts of TN loadings for the winter season. The source of the skill in predicting winter loadings primarily arises from the El-Nino Southern Oscillation conditions. The study also evaluated the skill in forecasting daily TN loadings using the retrospective water quality forecasts. &nbsp;Analyses showed significant skill in predicting observed TN loadings using weather forecasts during the winter and spring seasons and limited skill in predicting summer and fall seasons. The limited skill in predicting TN loadings during the summer and fall seasons partly arises from the limited skill in predicting warm season precipitation. &nbsp;</p> <p><span>We also found the skill in forecasting TN loadings being higher than that of the skill in forecasting TN concentration. Since the skill in predicting TN concentration is lower, we developed a nonparametric procedure that resamples observed TN loadings and streamflow to develop a null distribution having no skill. Using this hypothesis test, one can test whether the skill in predicting concentration is statistically significant or not. The main advantage of this procedure is that it does not require any distributional assumption on the observed loadings. &nbsp;The study also focused on developing loadings forecasts using a mechanistic model, Soil and Water Assessment Tool (SWAT), for three basins over the Southeast US. Since the outputs from the mechanistic models are typically biased, we suggested a multi-variate bias correction procedure, Canonical Correlation Analysis (CCA), for preserving the observed moments of streamflow and loadings. To summarize, there is potential in developing TN loadings forecasts for exploring additional management scenarios to control nonpoint and point sources contingent on weather and climate forecasts.</span></p> <p><span>The study also focused on various aspects related to uncertainty reduction in streamflow forecasts/projections over various time scales. This includes model uncertainty reduction, variational data assimilation and reconstruction of annual flows, combining reconstructed streamflows and observed flows to size a reservoir and asynchronous approach for combining multiple GCMs projections. The study also assessed the potential for developing groundwater forecasts and power demand forecasts over the SEUS. Power demand forecasts were developed using population and temperature, whereas groundwater forecasts were developed using precipitation forecasts from climate models and previous month streamflow. &nbsp;Reservoir sizing analysis showed that paleo-information reduces the uncertainty in reservoir yield as opposed to using observed information alone. The primary emphasis from this CAREER project is on systematic uncertainty reduction across various spatio-temporal scales to improve streamflow and water quality forecasts/projections.</span></p> <p><span>This CAREER project also produced significant outreach by developing a&nbsp;<a href="http://climate.ncsu.edu/water/map/">hydroclimate forecasts portal</a>&nbsp;that forecasts streamflow and soil moisture over the Southeast US. This portal is totally automated and develops monthly-to-seasonal streamflow and soil moisture forecasts over the Southeast and also develops reservoir storage forecasts for two systems in NC. In collaboration with the State climate office of NC, we had two workshops that involved NC city water supply planners, USACE professionals and state climatologists. We hope this will serve the region in the years to come.</span></p> <p><span>PI also conducted a AGU Chapman Conference &nbsp;in Portland (August 2013) that involved climate scientists, water professionals and USACE water managers focusing on issues related to using streamflow forecasts for improving water management.&nbsp;</span></p> <p><span>This project supported a total of five PhD students and two undergraduate students. Of the three graduated PhD students, two students are in academia and another working in the R&amp;D. Two other PhD students are about to graduate in Fall 17. Two PhD students received USGS climate science fellowship and another student received UCAR fellowship for summer internship as part of the Advanced Study Program. One undergraduate student supported from this project also received NSF graduate fellowship.</span></p> <p><span>Totally 11 articles are published so far and another five are articles are under review. Apart from that, additionally four more articles are under preparation.</span></p> <p><span>This project also supported two scientists, Dr. Ashish Sharma from UNSW, Sydney and Dr. Bidroha Basu from Trinity College, from abroad. Two PhD students, received training from them and one manuscript is already published and one article is under review.</span></p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 09/26/2017<br>      Modified by: Sankarasubraman&nbsp;Arumugam</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The primary objective of this CAREER research is to understand the causal linkages between climate, streamflow and water quality variability over the Southeast US (SEUS). Towards this, the project focused on 18 virgin basins over the SEUS spanning from seven states (VA to FL and MS). It is well known that climate drives streamflow and streamflow drives total nitrogen (TN) variability. Given this causal linkage, this study focused on developing TN forecasts using seasonal climate forecasts developed by using Sea Surface Temperature (SST) forecasts.  The primary challenge in developing water quality forecasts is the limited availability of observed data.  Hence, we used modeled water quality data to develop the climate data, but we systematically transformed the skill in predicting modeled values based on the water quality model skill.  Analyses of 18 basins showed that there is considerable potential in developing forecasts of TN loadings for the winter season. The source of the skill in predicting winter loadings primarily arises from the El-Nino Southern Oscillation conditions. The study also evaluated the skill in forecasting daily TN loadings using the retrospective water quality forecasts.  Analyses showed significant skill in predicting observed TN loadings using weather forecasts during the winter and spring seasons and limited skill in predicting summer and fall seasons. The limited skill in predicting TN loadings during the summer and fall seasons partly arises from the limited skill in predicting warm season precipitation.    We also found the skill in forecasting TN loadings being higher than that of the skill in forecasting TN concentration. Since the skill in predicting TN concentration is lower, we developed a nonparametric procedure that resamples observed TN loadings and streamflow to develop a null distribution having no skill. Using this hypothesis test, one can test whether the skill in predicting concentration is statistically significant or not. The main advantage of this procedure is that it does not require any distributional assumption on the observed loadings.  The study also focused on developing loadings forecasts using a mechanistic model, Soil and Water Assessment Tool (SWAT), for three basins over the Southeast US. Since the outputs from the mechanistic models are typically biased, we suggested a multi-variate bias correction procedure, Canonical Correlation Analysis (CCA), for preserving the observed moments of streamflow and loadings. To summarize, there is potential in developing TN loadings forecasts for exploring additional management scenarios to control nonpoint and point sources contingent on weather and climate forecasts.  The study also focused on various aspects related to uncertainty reduction in streamflow forecasts/projections over various time scales. This includes model uncertainty reduction, variational data assimilation and reconstruction of annual flows, combining reconstructed streamflows and observed flows to size a reservoir and asynchronous approach for combining multiple GCMs projections. The study also assessed the potential for developing groundwater forecasts and power demand forecasts over the SEUS. Power demand forecasts were developed using population and temperature, whereas groundwater forecasts were developed using precipitation forecasts from climate models and previous month streamflow.  Reservoir sizing analysis showed that paleo-information reduces the uncertainty in reservoir yield as opposed to using observed information alone. The primary emphasis from this CAREER project is on systematic uncertainty reduction across various spatio-temporal scales to improve streamflow and water quality forecasts/projections.  This CAREER project also produced significant outreach by developing a hydroclimate forecasts portal that forecasts streamflow and soil moisture over the Southeast US. This portal is totally automated and develops monthly-to-seasonal streamflow and soil moisture forecasts over the Southeast and also develops reservoir storage forecasts for two systems in NC. In collaboration with the State climate office of NC, we had two workshops that involved NC city water supply planners, USACE professionals and state climatologists. We hope this will serve the region in the years to come.  PI also conducted a AGU Chapman Conference  in Portland (August 2013) that involved climate scientists, water professionals and USACE water managers focusing on issues related to using streamflow forecasts for improving water management.   This project supported a total of five PhD students and two undergraduate students. Of the three graduated PhD students, two students are in academia and another working in the R&amp;D. Two other PhD students are about to graduate in Fall 17. Two PhD students received USGS climate science fellowship and another student received UCAR fellowship for summer internship as part of the Advanced Study Program. One undergraduate student supported from this project also received NSF graduate fellowship.  Totally 11 articles are published so far and another five are articles are under review. Apart from that, additionally four more articles are under preparation.  This project also supported two scientists, Dr. Ashish Sharma from UNSW, Sydney and Dr. Bidroha Basu from Trinity College, from abroad. Two PhD students, received training from them and one manuscript is already published and one article is under review.       Last Modified: 09/26/2017       Submitted by: Sankarasubraman Arumugam]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
