<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>CAREER:  Coherent Mid-Infrared Molecular Dispersion Spectroscopy for Ultra-Sensitive Chemical Detection</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>02/01/2010</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>01/31/2016</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>405843.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>405843</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CMMI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Civil, Mechanical, &amp; Manufact Inn</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Massimo Ruzzene</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The research objective of this Faculty Early Career Development (CAREER) award is to study a new spectroscopic sensing technique. The planned approach takes advantage of the coherent laser radiation and combines the advantages of direct laser absorption spectroscopy with a precision and noise suppression capability that are characteristic to indirect, zero-baseline spectroscopic sensing methods. The research will include theoretical investigations of the molecular dispersion, spectroscopic modeling, studies of optimum detection techniques, and research on mid-IR lasers optimized for dispersion spectroscopy. To overcome the limitations of existing laser absorption spectroscopy techniques, a novel approach based on the measurement of dispersion will be investigated. Included in the investigation are fundamental physics and the solution of engineering problems in the construction of new EC-QC lasers. Sensitive and versatile chemical detection technology and new implementations in variety of field applications including distributed atmospheric sensor networks, and remote chemical detection are the expected outcome.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The research is expected to lead to development of highly sensitive gas and chemical sensors capable of pptv-level resolution. The application of the proposed technology to trace-gas detection will result in more sensitive, smaller and more versatile sensors. New applications including large area spectroscopic sensor networks for atmospheric monitoring, remote chemical sensing in defense and security, or hand-held/wearable gas exposure monitoring will benefit from the proposed research.  How the interdisciplinary nature of the project would provide a spectrum of education and training opportunities integrated with the research goals is presented.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>01/19/2010</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>01/19/2010</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>0954897</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Gerard</FirstName>
<LastName>Wysocki</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Gerard Wysocki</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>gwysocki@princeton.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6092588187</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000491891</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>01/19/2010</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Princeton University</Name>
<CityName>Princeton</CityName>
<ZipCode>085442020</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6092583090</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>Off. of Research &amp; Proj. Admin.</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[P.O. Box 36]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New Jersey</StateName>
<StateCode>NJ</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>12</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NJ12</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>002484665</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>TRUSTEES OF PRINCETON UNIVERSITY, THE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>002484665</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Princeton University]]></Name>
<CityName>Princeton</CityName>
<StateCode>NJ</StateCode>
<ZipCode>085442020</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[Off. of Research &amp; Proj. Adm]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New Jersey</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>12</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NJ12</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1639</Code>
<Text>SENSORS AND SENSING SYSTEMS</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>032E</Code>
<Text>SENSORS AND ACTUATORS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>036E</Code>
<Text>CIVIL INFRASTRUCTURE</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1045</Code>
<Text>CAREER-Faculty Erly Career Dev</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1057</Code>
<Text>CIS BASE RESEARCH</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1059</Code>
<Text>SENSORS AND SENSOR SYSTEMS FOR CIS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1187</Code>
<Text>PECASE- eligible</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7234</Code>
<Text>SENSORS NON-SOLICITATION RESEA</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>CVIS</Code>
<Text>CIVIL INFRASTRUCTURE</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0110</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2010~405843</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The project&rsquo;s main goal was focused on novel chemical detection technologies based on molecular optical dispersion measurements and their ultimate implementation in field sensing applications. The results have significant intellectual and practical impact both on the fundamental understanding of light-matter interactions as well as on advancements of chemical sensing technologies.</p> <p>We have identified that detection of anomalous molecular dispersion in the vicinity of molecular or atomic transition can offer several new capabilities over conventional laser absorption spectroscopy techniques while still providing simplicity and robustness required for real-world applications. To extract the molecular dispersion information and provide sensitive spectroscopic chemical detection, a new sensing technique has been developed based on a chirped laser source and a two-color dynamic interferometric heterodyne detection. A new spectroscopic sensing technology, the chirped laser dispersion spectroscopy (CLaDS),&nbsp;has been invented within this project and is being studied both theoretically as well as experimentally (see Fig. 1). In addition to CLaDS we have also investigated other dispersion techniques based on Faraday Effect for sensitive detection of paramagnetic species.</p> <p>The CLaDS technology evolved quickly over the recent years under this support (Fig. 2). We have proposed novel modulation and signal processing schemes, which provided enhanced sensitivity, true baseline-free spectroscopic detection, and capability of measurement of optically thick samples. We have performed careful studies of high-frequency modulation dynamics in quantum cascade lasers (QCLs), which led to discovery of unique modulation properties and enabled optimized CLaDS operation with simplified, directly-driven mid-infrared semiconductor lasers. We have also developed complete CLaDS systems, which with additional support have been deployed in the field to perform remote detection of greenhouse gases (see methane sensor deployment in Fig. 3). The developed technology has gained both academic and commercial interest. Several research groups are now studying and advancing molecular dispersion spectroscopy, and commercialization of the CLaDS technology is in progress.</p> <p>Ultra-sensitive, fast, in-situ molecular detection has a large number of applications in environmental studies, industrial emission monitoring and medical diagnostics. The project yielded a series of new discoveries and scientific advancements and its well-integrated educational program provided training at all academic levels ranging from high school students to post-doctoral researchers. The versatility of the project provided a full spectrum of education and training opportunities that supported a variety of career development goals ranging from academic to industrial placement of the participating students and post-docs. These contributions have already shown impact on the research field and the society by introducing a new generation of scientists and engineers.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 05/07/2016<br>      Modified by: Gerard&nbsp;Wysocki</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Images (<span id="selectedPhoto0">1</span> of <span class="totalNumber"></span>)           </div> <div class="galControls" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2016/0954897/0954897_10012954_1462638936245_CLaDS--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2016/0954897/0954897_10012954_1462638936245_CLaDS--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Fig. 1 Chirped Laser Dispersion Spectrometer (C...]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The projectÆs main goal was focused on novel chemical detection technologies based on molecular optical dispersion measurements and their ultimate implementation in field sensing applications. The results have significant intellectual and practical impact both on the fundamental understanding of light-matter interactions as well as on advancements of chemical sensing technologies.  We have identified that detection of anomalous molecular dispersion in the vicinity of molecular or atomic transition can offer several new capabilities over conventional laser absorption spectroscopy techniques while still providing simplicity and robustness required for real-world applications. To extract the molecular dispersion information and provide sensitive spectroscopic chemical detection, a new sensing technique has been developed based on a chirped laser source and a two-color dynamic interferometric heterodyne detection. A new spectroscopic sensing technology, the chirped laser dispersion spectroscopy (CLaDS), has been invented within this project and is being studied both theoretically as well as experimentally (see Fig. 1). In addition to CLaDS we have also investigated other dispersion techniques based on Faraday Effect for sensitive detection of paramagnetic species.  The CLaDS technology evolved quickly over the recent years under this support (Fig. 2). We have proposed novel modulation and signal processing schemes, which provided enhanced sensitivity, true baseline-free spectroscopic detection, and capability of measurement of optically thick samples. We have performed careful studies of high-frequency modulation dynamics in quantum cascade lasers (QCLs), which led to discovery of unique modulation properties and enabled optimized CLaDS operation with simplified, directly-driven mid-infrared semiconductor lasers. We have also developed complete CLaDS systems, which with additional support have been deployed in the field to perform remote detection of greenhouse gases (see methane sensor deployment in Fig. 3). The developed technology has gained both academic and commercial interest. Several research groups are now studying and advancing molecular dispersion spectroscopy, and commercialization of the CLaDS technology is in progress.  Ultra-sensitive, fast, in-situ molecular detection has a large number of applications in environmental studies, industrial emission monitoring and medical diagnostics. The project yielded a series of new discoveries and scientific advancements and its well-integrated educational program provided training at all academic levels ranging from high school students to post-doctoral researchers. The versatility of the project provided a full spectrum of education and training opportunities that supported a variety of career development goals ranging from academic to industrial placement of the participating students and post-docs. These contributions have already shown impact on the research field and the society by introducing a new generation of scientists and engineers.       Last Modified: 05/07/2016       Submitted by: Gerard Wysocki]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
