<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>CAREER:  Stochastic Optimization and Coordinating Control for the Next-Generation Electric Power System with Significant Wind Penetration</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/15/2010</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2016</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>399999.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>407999</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07010000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>ECCS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Electrical, Commun &amp; Cyber Sys</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Eyad Abed</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>eabed@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032920000</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Objectives:&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The objective of this research is to study the use of stochastic optimization and coordinating control to improve the stability, reliability, and economic efficiency of the next-generation power system with significant wind penetration.  The approach is to (1) develop novel modeling and optimization frameworks using probability-based decision-making approaches for security-constrained stochastic optimization of the power system; (2) enhance steady-state and transient performance of wind plants through novel wind-plant supervisory control; and (3) enhance overall power system dynamic performance and stability through novel wide-area coordinating control.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Intellectual Merit:  &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Through the creation of new philosophies for optimization and control design, this project will advance understanding of the critical operational issues of the next-generation power system and will lead to smarter power grids to provide better electric energy security, efficiency, and sustainability.  In addition to power systems, this research will create several fundamental frameworks and methodologies applicable to optimization and control of other interconnected, large-scale, stochastic, dynamical, complex systems.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Broader Impacts:  &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project will build a thriving and diversified power program through the integration of graduate and undergraduate research and teaching with K-12 outreach, which will provide a unique platform of learning for young individuals entering the power engineering profession.  This project will build multiple foreign research training and exchange programs to promote international collaborations in power engineering education and research.  The outcomes of this project will further exploit the benefits of wind power in reaching the goal of supplying 20% of the nation's electricity by wind and will benefit various sectors of the nation's economy.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>01/29/2010</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/17/2013</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>0954938</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Wei</FirstName>
<LastName>Qiao</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Wei Qiao</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>wqiao@engr.unl.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>4024729619</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000514408</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>01/29/2010</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</Name>
<CityName>Lincoln</CityName>
<ZipCode>685031435</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>4024723171</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>151 Prem S. Paul Research Center</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[2200 Vine St]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Nebraska</StateName>
<StateCode>NE</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NE01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>555456995</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>BOARD OF REGENTS OF THE UNIVERSITY OF NEBRASKA</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>068662618</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Nebraska-Lincoln]]></Name>
<CityName>Lincoln</CityName>
<StateCode>NE</StateCode>
<ZipCode>685031435</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[151 Prem S. Paul Research Center]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Nebraska</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NE01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7607</Code>
<Text>EPCN-Energy-Power-Ctrl-Netwrks</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1045</Code>
<Text>CAREER-Faculty Erly Career Dev</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>155E</Code>
<Text>Electric power networks</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9102</Code>
<Text>WOMEN, MINORITY, DISABLED, NEC</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9251</Code>
<Text>REU SUPP-Res Exp for Ugrd Supp</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0110</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0113</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2010~399999</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2013~8000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Under the support of this NSF CAREER project, the principal investigator has developed an integrated research and education program focusing on the next-generation electric power system with the long-term goal of contributing to electric energy security, efficiency, and sustainability. &nbsp;To address the uncertainties caused by intermittent wind power generation, prices, and loads in the electricity market, two probability-based decision-making frameworks based on stochastic programing and robust optimization, respectively, have been developed to cope with various market operation problems, such as stochastic wind power trading, finding market equilibria with the help of the game theory, security-constrained robust AC optimal power flow, and robust bidirectional dispatch of the large-scale vehicle-to-grid technology. &nbsp;New time series prediction models based on wavelet support vector machines, artificial neural networks, etc., have been developed for wind/solar power prediction in the proposed decision-making models. &nbsp;These models have improved the economic efficiency of the power system. &nbsp;Additionally, to enhance steady-state performance, dynamic response, and reliability while reducing the cost and complexity of wind energy conversion systems, various advanced control methods have been developed to control wind turbine generators. &nbsp;These include reinforcement learning-based intelligent wind speed sensorless maximum power point tracking control, rotor position/speed sensorless vector control, and direct torque/power control.&nbsp; Furthermore, advanced coordinating control methods have been developed for wind turbines and wind power plants with energy storage devices to enhance steady-state performance and transient stability of wind energy conversion systems and the associated power networks. &nbsp;These research findings have advanced understanding of the critical operational issues of the next-generation electric power system with significant wind penetration.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>The findings of this project have generated 22 peer-reviewed papers published in top-ranked journals, 24 peer-reviewed conference proceedings papers, 2 book chapters, 2 U.S. patents pending, 5 Ph.D. dissertations, and 1 Master&rsquo;s thesis. &nbsp;The master&rsquo;s thesis won first prize of the 2013 IEEE Industry Applications Society Graduate Student Thesis Contest. &nbsp;One Ph.D. student received the 2014 University of Nebraska-Lincoln (UNL) Outstanding Graduate Research Assistant Award for his outstanding achievement in the research supported in part by this project. &nbsp;With the collaboration with a leading manufacturer, the rotor position/speed sensorless control methods developed in this project have been transferred to control electric motors in hybrid electric vehicles and other electric drive systems. &nbsp;Moreover, based on the stochastic programming-based, decision-making models developed in this project, the principal investigator has collaborated with electric utilities to develop realistic decision-making models and a software package, which has been adopted by the electric utilities for trading their wind power in the electricity market. &nbsp;The outcomes of this research have benefited the local and national economies.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>The principal investigator has renovated and enhanced the electric power curriculum at UNL through the integration of state-of-the-art technologies and the results of this research. &nbsp;The undergraduate power electronics course was renovated by adding new lecture materials, hardware projects, and laboratory sessions. &nbsp;Two new courses, <em>Computational Intelligence</em> and <em>Advanced Power Electronics and Applications</em>, have been developed and taught every year. &nbsp;The enhanced curriculum and the integration of research and education have attracted more young individuals to the electric power engineering profession. &nbsp;The enrollments of electric power courses have increased significantly (more than 200% in some courses) during the first two years of this project and have remained stable during the last four years. &nbsp;In addition to students in the electric power area, some courses, e.g., <em>Computational Intelligence</em>, have attracted students from different disciplines, such as computer science, civil engineering, mechanical engineering, material engineering, biological systems engineering, mathematics, and other areas of electrical engineering. &nbsp;Various simulation models of wind turbines, wind power plants, energy storage systems, and power networks; two testbeds of wind turbines with different electrical generators; and a renewable-energy-based microgrid testbed have been developed. &nbsp;These models and testbeds have been used for teaching undergraduate and graduate students about renewable energy systems and are open to the public in the form of system demonstrations. &nbsp;A large amount of data generated from computer simulations and hardware tests conducted during this project is providing excellent resources for teaching and research in the field. &nbsp;More than ten undergraduates, supported through UNL&rsquo;s Undergraduate Creative Activities and Research Experiences (UCARE) program and REU supplement funds, have been supervised by the principal investigator and graduate students as they worked on the research conducted for this project. &nbsp;Moreover, the principal investigator and graduate students have offered various demonstrations and laboratory tours for K-12 students to learn the basic principles of electrical energy conversion and renewable energy systems.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>The principal investigator has collaborated with academic and industrial leaders from around the world in organizing conferences on wind energy and three special issues/sections on renewable energy published by IEEE journals. &nbsp;The conferences and special issues/sections provided unique platforms for academic and industrial communities to report recent technology advances and breakthroughs, identify technology gaps, and guide research and technology development in the field. <strong>&nbsp;</strong><em>&nbsp;</em></p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 10/26/2016<br>      Modified by: Wei&nbsp;Qiao</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Under the support of this NSF CAREER project, the principal investigator has developed an integrated research and education program focusing on the next-generation electric power system with the long-term goal of contributing to electric energy security, efficiency, and sustainability.  To address the uncertainties caused by intermittent wind power generation, prices, and loads in the electricity market, two probability-based decision-making frameworks based on stochastic programing and robust optimization, respectively, have been developed to cope with various market operation problems, such as stochastic wind power trading, finding market equilibria with the help of the game theory, security-constrained robust AC optimal power flow, and robust bidirectional dispatch of the large-scale vehicle-to-grid technology.  New time series prediction models based on wavelet support vector machines, artificial neural networks, etc., have been developed for wind/solar power prediction in the proposed decision-making models.  These models have improved the economic efficiency of the power system.  Additionally, to enhance steady-state performance, dynamic response, and reliability while reducing the cost and complexity of wind energy conversion systems, various advanced control methods have been developed to control wind turbine generators.  These include reinforcement learning-based intelligent wind speed sensorless maximum power point tracking control, rotor position/speed sensorless vector control, and direct torque/power control.  Furthermore, advanced coordinating control methods have been developed for wind turbines and wind power plants with energy storage devices to enhance steady-state performance and transient stability of wind energy conversion systems and the associated power networks.  These research findings have advanced understanding of the critical operational issues of the next-generation electric power system with significant wind penetration.     The findings of this project have generated 22 peer-reviewed papers published in top-ranked journals, 24 peer-reviewed conference proceedings papers, 2 book chapters, 2 U.S. patents pending, 5 Ph.D. dissertations, and 1 Master?s thesis.  The master?s thesis won first prize of the 2013 IEEE Industry Applications Society Graduate Student Thesis Contest.  One Ph.D. student received the 2014 University of Nebraska-Lincoln (UNL) Outstanding Graduate Research Assistant Award for his outstanding achievement in the research supported in part by this project.  With the collaboration with a leading manufacturer, the rotor position/speed sensorless control methods developed in this project have been transferred to control electric motors in hybrid electric vehicles and other electric drive systems.  Moreover, based on the stochastic programming-based, decision-making models developed in this project, the principal investigator has collaborated with electric utilities to develop realistic decision-making models and a software package, which has been adopted by the electric utilities for trading their wind power in the electricity market.  The outcomes of this research have benefited the local and national economies.     The principal investigator has renovated and enhanced the electric power curriculum at UNL through the integration of state-of-the-art technologies and the results of this research.  The undergraduate power electronics course was renovated by adding new lecture materials, hardware projects, and laboratory sessions.  Two new courses, Computational Intelligence and Advanced Power Electronics and Applications, have been developed and taught every year.  The enhanced curriculum and the integration of research and education have attracted more young individuals to the electric power engineering profession.  The enrollments of electric power courses have increased significantly (more than 200% in some courses) during the first two years of this project and have remained stable during the last four years.  In addition to students in the electric power area, some courses, e.g., Computational Intelligence, have attracted students from different disciplines, such as computer science, civil engineering, mechanical engineering, material engineering, biological systems engineering, mathematics, and other areas of electrical engineering.  Various simulation models of wind turbines, wind power plants, energy storage systems, and power networks; two testbeds of wind turbines with different electrical generators; and a renewable-energy-based microgrid testbed have been developed.  These models and testbeds have been used for teaching undergraduate and graduate students about renewable energy systems and are open to the public in the form of system demonstrations.  A large amount of data generated from computer simulations and hardware tests conducted during this project is providing excellent resources for teaching and research in the field.  More than ten undergraduates, supported through UNL?s Undergraduate Creative Activities and Research Experiences (UCARE) program and REU supplement funds, have been supervised by the principal investigator and graduate students as they worked on the research conducted for this project.  Moreover, the principal investigator and graduate students have offered various demonstrations and laboratory tours for K-12 students to learn the basic principles of electrical energy conversion and renewable energy systems.     The principal investigator has collaborated with academic and industrial leaders from around the world in organizing conferences on wind energy and three special issues/sections on renewable energy published by IEEE journals.  The conferences and special issues/sections provided unique platforms for academic and industrial communities to report recent technology advances and breakthroughs, identify technology gaps, and guide research and technology development in the field.             Last Modified: 10/26/2016       Submitted by: Wei Qiao]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
