<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>CAREER: Metabolic Determinants of Programmed Cell Death in Hepatic Lipotoxicity</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2010</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2016</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>400000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>411900</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07020000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CBET</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Chem, Bioeng, Env, &amp; Transp Sys</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Rajakkannu Mutharasan</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>0955251&lt;br/&gt;Young&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The overall objective of the current application is to elucidate the mechanism by which metabolic changes activate apoptotic signaling in hepatic cells exposed to elevated saturated fatty acids (SFAs).The central hypothesis is that endoplasmic reticulum (ER) stress induced by SFAs leads to altered coupling between central carbon pathways, which subsequently triggers mitochondrial accumulation of reactive oxygen species (ROS) resulting in apoptosis. The rationale for the proposed research is that, once it is known how metabolic pathway fluxes impact lipid-induced apoptosis, these pathways can be modulated by therapeutic interventions that target the underlying metabolic factors causing lipotoxicity. The plan is to test the central hypothesis by pursuing the following specific aims. First, to determine the mechanism by which SFAs induce ROS accumulation in hepatic cells. Second, to identify the lipid intermediate responsible for inducing ER stress in SFA-treated hepatic cells. These aims will be accomplished using a systems approach that focuses on integrated metabolic pathways versus individual reactions and where the concept of the metabolic network is of central importance. The approach involves both GC-MS metabolic profiling to track the relative concentrations and isotopic labeling patterns of many different intracellular metabolites simultaneously, as well as metabolic flux analysis (MFA) to reconstruct comprehensive flux maps that represent the dynamic flow of material throughout the network. By subjecting hepatic cells to a variety of treatments aimed at perturbing lipid and central carbon metabolism, they will dissect the pathways involved in SFA-induced lipotoxicity.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>04/27/2010</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/12/2012</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>0955251</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Jamey</FirstName>
<LastName>Young</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>D</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Jamey D Young</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>j.d.young@vanderbilt.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6153222631</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000513639</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/27/2010</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Vanderbilt University</Name>
<CityName>Nashville</CityName>
<ZipCode>372350002</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6153222631</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>Sponsored Programs Administratio</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[PMB 407749 2301 Vanderbilt Place]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Tennessee</StateName>
<StateCode>TN</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>TN05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>965717143</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>VANDERBILT UNIVERSITY, THE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>004413456</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Vanderbilt University]]></Name>
<CityName>Nashville</CityName>
<StateCode>TN</StateCode>
<ZipCode>372350002</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[Sponsored Programs Administratio]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Tennessee</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>TN05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1491</Code>
<Text>Cellular &amp; Biochem Engineering</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>009E</Code>
<Text>Metabolic engineering</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1045</Code>
<Text>CAREER-Faculty Erly Career Dev</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1187</Code>
<Text>PECASE- eligible</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1757</Code>
<Text>Quantitative sys bio and biotech</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9251</Code>
<Text>REU SUPP-Res Exp for Ugrd Supp</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0110</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0112</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2010~400000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2012~11900</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Intellectual Merit<br />This research applied <sup>13</sup>C metabolic flux analysis (MFA) and biochemical profiling to examine the metabolic alterations that occur in liver cells exposed to elevated free fatty acids (FFAs). FFAs are highly abundant in the blood of individuals who suffer from obesity and/or type-2 diabetes. Hepatic FFA overload leads to a condition known as nonalcoholic fatty liver disease (NAFLD), which is estimated to affect up to 30% of the U.S. population. As a result, NAFLD is now the leading cause of referrals to hepatology clinics in the U.S. Unfortunately, the factors that control disease severity are poorly understood, and there are currently no FDA-approved pharmacotherapies for NAFLD. Through our research, we have uncovered a novel mechanism by which saturated FFAs promote abnormal cell metabolism and oxidative stress in liver cells. This process involves the rapid incorporation of saturated FFAs into phospholipid side chains, resulting in oversaturation of cellular membranes and altered transport of calcium ions between subcellular organelles. Dysregulation of intracellular calcium homeostasis subsequently promotes increased mitochondrial oxidative metabolism and accumulation of toxic reactive oxygen species (ROS). Surprisingly, <sup>13</sup>C MFA revealed that these metabolic alterations were not driven by increased FFA oxidation, but instead were fueled by increased anaplerotic flux from glutamate. We have published ten journal articles describing these research findings and the technologies developed under this award. Furthermore, the MFA software tools developed under this award are publicly available to the scientific community at <a href="http://mfa.vueinnovations.com/">http://mfa.vueinnovations.com</a>. <br /> <br /> Broader Impacts<br /> Understanding how lipid-induced metabolic alterations give rise to NAFLD is expected to provide better strategies for disease prevention, diagnosis, or treatment. This has the potential to improve the health and quality of life of millions of patients who suffer from this disease. Additionally, we have worked to educate the general public about our research through outreach programs in the Nashville area. We have conducted laboratory programs at Nashville&rsquo;s Adventure Science Center to educate elementary-school aged children about the science behind their food choices in interactive, age-appropriate experiments. A hands-on science lesson called "Power of Food" was developed to teach middle school students about the energy content of different foods. The lesson plan and training presentation are publicly available at <a href="http://studentorgs.vanderbilt.edu/vsvs/lessons.html">http://studentorgs.vanderbilt.edu/vsvs/lessons.html</a>. Two PhD students and one MS student have been trained under this award. These students have been given the opportunity to develop the intellectual and professional skills required to become leaders in the biomedical research community. Both PhD students completed postdoctoral training and are now working in the life science industry. Training was also provided for six Vanderbilt undergraduate students, three MD students, two REU students, and a high school student. Out of these 15 students, six were female and three were underrepresented minorities in STEM. These students have been involved in both the research and outreach activities associated with this award. Of the eight undergrad and REU students, four have gone on to PhD programs in engineering and another is enrolled in medical school. All these students learned valuable engineering and life science skills that will enable them to contribute to the US biotechnology industry in order to enhance national excellence in this area.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 09/23/2016<br>      Modified by: Jamey&nbsp;D&nbsp;Young</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Intellectual Merit This research applied 13C metabolic flux analysis (MFA) and biochemical profiling to examine the metabolic alterations that occur in liver cells exposed to elevated free fatty acids (FFAs). FFAs are highly abundant in the blood of individuals who suffer from obesity and/or type-2 diabetes. Hepatic FFA overload leads to a condition known as nonalcoholic fatty liver disease (NAFLD), which is estimated to affect up to 30% of the U.S. population. As a result, NAFLD is now the leading cause of referrals to hepatology clinics in the U.S. Unfortunately, the factors that control disease severity are poorly understood, and there are currently no FDA-approved pharmacotherapies for NAFLD. Through our research, we have uncovered a novel mechanism by which saturated FFAs promote abnormal cell metabolism and oxidative stress in liver cells. This process involves the rapid incorporation of saturated FFAs into phospholipid side chains, resulting in oversaturation of cellular membranes and altered transport of calcium ions between subcellular organelles. Dysregulation of intracellular calcium homeostasis subsequently promotes increased mitochondrial oxidative metabolism and accumulation of toxic reactive oxygen species (ROS). Surprisingly, 13C MFA revealed that these metabolic alterations were not driven by increased FFA oxidation, but instead were fueled by increased anaplerotic flux from glutamate. We have published ten journal articles describing these research findings and the technologies developed under this award. Furthermore, the MFA software tools developed under this award are publicly available to the scientific community at http://mfa.vueinnovations.com.     Broader Impacts  Understanding how lipid-induced metabolic alterations give rise to NAFLD is expected to provide better strategies for disease prevention, diagnosis, or treatment. This has the potential to improve the health and quality of life of millions of patients who suffer from this disease. Additionally, we have worked to educate the general public about our research through outreach programs in the Nashville area. We have conducted laboratory programs at Nashville?s Adventure Science Center to educate elementary-school aged children about the science behind their food choices in interactive, age-appropriate experiments. A hands-on science lesson called "Power of Food" was developed to teach middle school students about the energy content of different foods. The lesson plan and training presentation are publicly available at http://studentorgs.vanderbilt.edu/vsvs/lessons.html. Two PhD students and one MS student have been trained under this award. These students have been given the opportunity to develop the intellectual and professional skills required to become leaders in the biomedical research community. Both PhD students completed postdoctoral training and are now working in the life science industry. Training was also provided for six Vanderbilt undergraduate students, three MD students, two REU students, and a high school student. Out of these 15 students, six were female and three were underrepresented minorities in STEM. These students have been involved in both the research and outreach activities associated with this award. Of the eight undergrad and REU students, four have gone on to PhD programs in engineering and another is enrolled in medical school. All these students learned valuable engineering and life science skills that will enable them to contribute to the US biotechnology industry in order to enhance national excellence in this area.       Last Modified: 09/23/2016       Submitted by: Jamey D Young]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
