<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>CAREER: Optimization and continuation methods in fluid mechanics</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>06/01/2010</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2015</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>404941.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>404941</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DMS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Henry Warchall</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>hwarchal@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924861</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Shape optimization in fluid mechanics is the study of how to design a body, such as a wing or propeller, to maximize lift or thrust while minimizing drag.  Tools developed for shape optimization can also be used to dramatically improve the performance of shooting methods for two-point boundary value problems governed by nonlinear partial differential equations.  This project concerns the development and implementation of new algorithms for shape optimization of Newtonian and viscoelastic fluids in nearly singular geometries, and for the computation of time-periodic solutions in fluid mechanics.  New adjoint-based optimal control methods will be developed to compute gradients of objective functions and constraints governed by partial differential equations featuring singular integrals, non-local operators, or hysteresis.  The solutions of these optimization and boundary value problems occur in multi-parameter families that will be studied using numerical continuation algorithms capable of identifying bifurcations and following folds in the manifold of solutions.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Shape optimization is fundamental in the design of a wide range of engineering systems such as fuel-efficient vehicles and aircraft or micro-fluidic "lab on a chip" devices used in chemistry and molecular biology.  One of the goals of this research is to develop shape optimization techniques for materials that behave partly as viscous fluids and partly as elastic solids.  Applications include designing inkjet printers, recycling and manufacturing plastics, and understanding bio-locomotion in invertebrates.  Another goal of this research is to develop numerical methods for computing solutions of the equations of fluid mechanics that evolve to an exact copy of their initial state at a later time and then repeat themselves forever. These solutions are helpful in understanding complex phenomena such as ocean waves or the onset of turbulence in a pipe.  They should also prove useful in dynamic shape optimization problems, where the goal might be to optimize the average speed over one cycle of a swimming stroke.  Broader impacts of this project include course and curriculum development, organization of seminars and minisymposia, community outreach, advising of students and postdocs, and hosting of DOE Computational Science Graduate Fellows who wish to do a summer practicum at Lawrence Berkeley National Laboratory.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>05/11/2010</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/11/2010</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>0955078</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Jon</FirstName>
<LastName>Wilkening</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Jon Wilkening</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>wilken@math.berkeley.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5106428109</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000535972</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/11/2010</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of California-Berkeley</Name>
<CityName>BERKELEY</CityName>
<ZipCode>947101749</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5106433891</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>Sponsored Projects Office</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[1608 Fourth Street, Suite 220]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>13</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CA13</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>124726725</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>REGENTS OF THE UNIVERSITY OF CALIFORNIA, THE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>071549000</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of California-Berkeley]]></Name>
<CityName>BERKELEY</CityName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>947101749</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[Sponsored Projects Office]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>13</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CA13</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1266</Code>
<Text>APPLIED MATHEMATICS</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1271</Code>
<Text>COMPUTATIONAL MATHEMATICS</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1045</Code>
<Text>CAREER-Faculty Erly Career Dev</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1187</Code>
<Text>PECASE- eligible</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9263</Code>
<Text>COMPUTATIONAL SCIENCE &amp; ENGING</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0110</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2010~404941</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Shape optimization in fluid mechanics is the study of how to design a body, such as a wing or propeller, to maximize lift or thrust while minimizing drag. &nbsp;The central goal of this proposal was to adapt numerical methods for shape optimization to more general optimization problems governed by partial differential equations, and to develop highly accurate numerical algorithms for solving and optimizing these PDEs.</p> <p>A major outcome of the proposal was the development of new tools for computing time-periodic solutions of PDEs by searching for the initial conditions and unknown period that minimize a function measuring the deviation from time-periodicity. This strategy is known as a "shooting method", since adjusting the initial conditions is similar to adjusting the scope on a rifle based on where the previous shot landed relative to the target. However, in the PDE context, there are infinitely many knobs to adjust instead of two. &nbsp;A novelty of the PI's approach was to pose the problem as an overdetermined system to improve robustness of the algorithm without sacrificing accuracy. &nbsp;The PI used this approach in a wide variety of applications ranging from abstract theoretical questions to practical applied problems.</p> <p>On the theoretical side, the PI disproved a famous 1952 conjecture of Penney and Price that the largest amplitude standing water wave features sharp crests with 90 degree corner angles. &nbsp;By increasing the resolution near the crest tip by a factor of more than 200 over previous numerical studies (through algorithm improvement and parallel implementation on a supercomputer), the PI showed that resonant effects prevent solutions from becoming self-similar (sharp) in the large amplitude limit. &nbsp;This had remained an open question for 60 years because it was not known how to model nearly singular free surface flows with enough accuracy to distinguish between true physics and numerical artifacts. &nbsp;An analogous conjecture of Stokes (from 1880) stating that the largest amplitude traveling wave contains sharp, 120 degree crest angles was proved to be true in 1982 by Amick, Fraenkel and Toland.</p> <p>On the practical side, the PI studied multi-pulsing instabilities in mode-locked lasers used in waveguide arrays for all-optical switching and signal processing applications; developed new algorithms for computing cyclic steady states in rolling vehicle tires and analyzing their dynamic stability; and developed new algorithms for optimizing intermittent water supply in urban pipe networks.</p> <p>Rolling tires are examples of engineering systems that are subjected to cyclic driving forces that are difficult to model yet play a critical role in their eventual mechanical failure. Proper management of water, snow and ice require complex, non-axisymmetric tread patterns that induce oscillations when they come in contact with the road. In collaboration with Sanjay Govindjee (UC Berkeley Civil Engineering), the PI and his student, Trevor Potter, developed a new technique for computing stress states in treaded tires without computing an expensive "spin-up" phase to eliminate transient dynamics through viscoelastic damping.</p> <p>Part of the focus of the project was on the development of high-order spatial and temporal discretizations of PDEs, which is a prerequisite to optimization. &nbsp;Our efforts in this direction included the development of spectrally accurate, arbitrary precision codes for the water wave equations, for kinetic equations in plasma physics, and for Wright-Fisher diffusion problems in population genetics. &nbsp;A method is spectrally accurate if the convergence rate is limited by the smoothness of the solution rather than the numerical scheme itself. In the cases considered here, the solutions are extremely smooth (in fact analytic), so the error decays exponentially with the number of grid points used. &nbsp;In the...]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Shape optimization in fluid mechanics is the study of how to design a body, such as a wing or propeller, to maximize lift or thrust while minimizing drag.  The central goal of this proposal was to adapt numerical methods for shape optimization to more general optimization problems governed by partial differential equations, and to develop highly accurate numerical algorithms for solving and optimizing these PDEs.  A major outcome of the proposal was the development of new tools for computing time-periodic solutions of PDEs by searching for the initial conditions and unknown period that minimize a function measuring the deviation from time-periodicity. This strategy is known as a "shooting method", since adjusting the initial conditions is similar to adjusting the scope on a rifle based on where the previous shot landed relative to the target. However, in the PDE context, there are infinitely many knobs to adjust instead of two.  A novelty of the PI's approach was to pose the problem as an overdetermined system to improve robustness of the algorithm without sacrificing accuracy.  The PI used this approach in a wide variety of applications ranging from abstract theoretical questions to practical applied problems.  On the theoretical side, the PI disproved a famous 1952 conjecture of Penney and Price that the largest amplitude standing water wave features sharp crests with 90 degree corner angles.  By increasing the resolution near the crest tip by a factor of more than 200 over previous numerical studies (through algorithm improvement and parallel implementation on a supercomputer), the PI showed that resonant effects prevent solutions from becoming self-similar (sharp) in the large amplitude limit.  This had remained an open question for 60 years because it was not known how to model nearly singular free surface flows with enough accuracy to distinguish between true physics and numerical artifacts.  An analogous conjecture of Stokes (from 1880) stating that the largest amplitude traveling wave contains sharp, 120 degree crest angles was proved to be true in 1982 by Amick, Fraenkel and Toland.  On the practical side, the PI studied multi-pulsing instabilities in mode-locked lasers used in waveguide arrays for all-optical switching and signal processing applications; developed new algorithms for computing cyclic steady states in rolling vehicle tires and analyzing their dynamic stability; and developed new algorithms for optimizing intermittent water supply in urban pipe networks.  Rolling tires are examples of engineering systems that are subjected to cyclic driving forces that are difficult to model yet play a critical role in their eventual mechanical failure. Proper management of water, snow and ice require complex, non-axisymmetric tread patterns that induce oscillations when they come in contact with the road. In collaboration with Sanjay Govindjee (UC Berkeley Civil Engineering), the PI and his student, Trevor Potter, developed a new technique for computing stress states in treaded tires without computing an expensive "spin-up" phase to eliminate transient dynamics through viscoelastic damping.  Part of the focus of the project was on the development of high-order spatial and temporal discretizations of PDEs, which is a prerequisite to optimization.  Our efforts in this direction included the development of spectrally accurate, arbitrary precision codes for the water wave equations, for kinetic equations in plasma physics, and for Wright-Fisher diffusion problems in population genetics.  A method is spectrally accurate if the convergence rate is limited by the smoothness of the solution rather than the numerical scheme itself. In the cases considered here, the solutions are extremely smooth (in fact analytic), so the error decays exponentially with the number of grid points used.  In the water wave application, the key challenge is computing the so called Dirichlet-Neumann operator (DNO). We developed an adaptive scheme f...]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
