<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>CAREER: Intrinsic Transport Properties of Graphene: Approaching the Elusive Ground State on Crystalline Substrates</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>02/15/2010</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>550000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>562825</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03070003</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DMR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Materials Research</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Germano Iannacchione</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>giannacc@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032920000</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>****NON-TECHNICAL ABSTRACT****&lt;br/&gt;Graphene, a single layer of graphite, possesses unique electronic properties important for both fundamental and applied nanoscale materials physics research. Charge carriers in graphene behave much like light. This unusual property of intrinsic disorder-free graphene can be exploited to explore the consequences of relativistic Quantum Electrodynamics on a chip, making graphene important for increasing our understanding of fundamental physics. The utility of graphene for electronic applications is demonstrated by the observed response of the charge carriers to an applied electric field (the field effect). Yet, because graphene is composed of only surface atoms, its intrinsic properties are sensitive to adsorbates and substrate-induced disorder. Adsorbate-induced disorder can now be eliminated, but so far substrate-induced disorder has not been controlled. Thus, the intrinsic properties of graphene remain unknown.  This Faculty Early Career Award supports projects seeking to uncover the intrinsic properties of graphene and pave a way for the exploration of Quantum Electrodynamics by utilizing crystalline substrates. Such substrates are expected to eliminate substrate-induced disorder, and create ?perfect? graphene.  The studies will also elucidate the intrinsic limitation of graphene-based devices. Thus, they have the potential to have a broad impact on electronic applications of graphene.  The graduate and undergraduate students participating in, and supported by, this project will receive training in cutting-edge-interdisciplinary-nanoscience research.  A course will be developed for upper-level undergraduates to bring the frontiers of nanoscience, particularly as exhibited by carbon nanostructures, to the classroom.  The research program will also be integrated with development of extensive educational outreach activities for the general public. The outreach program will be tailored for students in grades 6-12, K-12 educators, and the local community with emphasis on underrepresented minorities from a diverse population represented in the Central Florida region. The outreach efforts will be designed to recruit, educate and train the next generation scientists and to increase the overall scientific literacy of the community.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;****TECHNICAL ABSTRACT****&lt;br/&gt;Graphene, a single layer of graphite, is a perfect two-dimensional semi-metallic electronic material, which possesses a linear dispersion and electron-hole symmetry with a vanishing density of electronic states at the Fermi level. This unusual band structure, akin to the light dispersion in free space, has inspired many theoretical proposals for testing the consequences of relativistic Quantum Electrodynamics using graphene. Yet, the extreme sensitivity of graphene to adsorbates and substrates has made made it impossible to perform experiments on intrinsic disorder-free graphene.  While adsorbate-induced disorder can now be eliminated, substrate-induced disorder remains an issue. This Faculty Early Career Award supports projects that will pave the way for series of groundbreaking experiments, by enabling investigations of flat, atomically-clean graphene with minimal disorder using crystalline substrates. Intrinsic transport properties will be elucidated. The ability to access disorder-free graphene will be utilized as a broad foundation for exploring consequences of Quantum Electrodynamics with a high fine structure constant. The graduate and undergraduate students participating in this research will receive hands-on training in cutting-edge nanoscience techniques. A course will be developed for upper-level undergraduates to bring the frontiers of nanoscience to the classroom. The research program will be integrated with the development of extensive educational outreach activities for the general public. The outreach efforts will be designed to recruit, educate and train the next generation of scientists and to increase the overall scientific literacy of the community.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>02/04/2010</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>03/24/2017</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>0955625</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Masahiro</FirstName>
<LastName>Ishigami</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Masahiro Ishigami</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>ishigami@ucf.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5103018798</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000516420</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>02/04/2010</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>The University of Central Florida Board of Trustees</Name>
<CityName>Orlando</CityName>
<ZipCode>328168005</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>4078230387</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>4000 CNTRL FLORIDA BLVD</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Florida</StateName>
<StateCode>FL</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>FL07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>150805653</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF CENTRAL FLORIDA BOARD OF TRUSTEES, THE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>159621697</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[The University of Central Florida Board of Trustees]]></Name>
<CityName>Orlando</CityName>
<StateCode>FL</StateCode>
<ZipCode>328168005</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[4000 CNTRL FLORIDA BLVD]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Florida</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>FL07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<FoaInformation>
<Code>0106000</Code>
<Name>Materials Research</Name>
</FoaInformation>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1253</Code>
<Text>OFFICE OF MULTIDISCIPLINARY AC</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1710</Code>
<Text>CONDENSED MATTER PHYSICS</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1045</Code>
<Text>CAREER-Faculty Erly Career Dev</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1187</Code>
<Text>PECASE- eligible</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>6863</Code>
<Text>SEBML-MOORE'S LAW</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7237</Code>
<Text>NANO NON-SOLIC SCI &amp; ENG AWD</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7969</Code>
<Text>FY 2010 Funding for PTR</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9161</Code>
<Text>SINGLE DIVISION/UNIVERSITY</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9260</Code>
<Text>FASED</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>AMPP</Code>
<Text>ADVANCED MATERIALS &amp; PROCESSING PROGRAM</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0110</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0111</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0112</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0113</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0114</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2010~110000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2011~110000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2012~110000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2013~110000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~122825</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><strong><em>Intellectual Merit</em></strong></p> <p>This grant has enabled research on physical properties of graphene and related materials in the atomically-clean limit. Broad range of discoveries were made, resulting in 22 refereed publications.&nbsp;The most important discoveries are highlighted below:</p> <p><strong><em>Origin of variabilities in performance of graphene-based devices</em></strong></p> <p><strong>Ishigami&nbsp;</strong>has developed a significant expertise on difficult-to-perform transport measurements in ultra-high vacuum (UHV). This is a critical component for the proposed study. Ishigami has uncovered the relationship between substrates and device performance of graphene (<em>Physical Review B and Journal of Physics: Condensed Matter</em>.&nbsp;</p> <p><strong><em>High resolution STM/AFM</em></strong></p> <p>The NSF career grant allowed resolution of the stacking angle between graphene on hexagonal boron nitride (h-BN) in the device configuration. The result enabled verification of the Hofstadter?s butterfly effect, resulting a publication in&nbsp;<em>Nature</em>. In addition, the NSF support enabled resolution of electronic properties of ZrSiS, which was published in&nbsp;<em>Nano Letters</em>. These STM/AFM results demonstrate that Ishigami has the necessary STM/AFM expertise to carry out the proposed measurements.&nbsp;</p> <p><strong><em>Functionalization of graphene&nbsp;</em></strong></p> <p>The capability to clean graphene and nanotube was used to resolve the structure of a peptide functional group adsorbed on graphene (<em>Nano Letters)</em>.</p> <p><strong><em>Ballistic nanofriction on graphene</em></strong><em>&nbsp;</em></p> <p>Previous studies of friction as a function of speed has shown that friction becomes larger as the speed is increased. Ishigami showed that for gold nanocrystals on graphene the friction becomes vanishingly low at high speeds. This phenomenon, predicted by a previous theoretical study, is called ballistic nanofriction and is different from structural or super-lubricity. It drastically alters our understanding of nanoscale friction and solid lubricants in general. The results were published in&nbsp;<em>Scientific Reports</em>.</p> <p><strong><em>Broader Impacts</em></strong></p> <p>8 graduate students have been supported by this NSF grant. Out of these, 4 students have graduated with Ph.D. in Physics and 2 students have graduated with the master?s degree. Notably, Ishigami?s first graduate student, Jyoti Katoch, is now an assistant professor in the Department of Physics at Carnegie Mellon University.</p> <p>Ishigami has been heavily involved with making physics careers more accessible to underrepresented minorities. Ishigami encouraged the formation of the Physics Women?s Society, of which the first president was Jyoti Katoch. Ishigami has also used the supplemental award to the Career Award to make the laboratory accessible to those with mobility impairment.&nbsp;</p> <p>The supplementary award made the laboratory more accessible for Michael Lodge, a paraplegic. Ishigami was able to secure a special motorized wheelchair to make his scanning tunneling microscope accessible. Michael recently graduated with a Ph.D. degree with his thesis work focusing on the measurement of ballistic nanofriction as well as on scanning tunneling microscopy/spectroscopy of ZrSiS.&nbsp;&nbsp;He is now a postdoctoral fellow at the Nanyang National University in Singapore. We plan to use the developed expertise in improving accessibility in the future.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 11/01/2018<br>      Modified by: Masahiro&nbsp;Ishigami</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Images (<span id="selectedPhoto0">1</span> of <span class="totalNumber"></span>)           </div> <div class="galControls" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/0955625/0955625_10013296_1541104059909_Slide2--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/0955625/0955625_10013296_1541104059909_Slide2--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Nanoscale Structure of Graphene Device on Hexagonal Boron Nitride"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/0955625/0955625_10013296_1541104059909_Slide2--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Nanoscale Structure of Graphene Device on Hexagonal Boron Nitride"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Using high-resolution atomic force microscopy, we have been able to resolve the Moire pattern on graphene on h-BN. Such patterns can be used to identify the exact orientation angle of graphene with respect to h-BN.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Ishigami</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Masahiro&nbsp;Ishigami</div> <div class="imageTitle">Nanoscale Structure of Graphene Device on Hexagonal Boron Nitride</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/0955625/0955625_10013296_1541104192196_Slide3--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/0955625/0955625_10013296_1541104192196_Slide3--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Atomic and Electronic Structure of ZrSiS"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/0955625/0955625_10013296_1541104192196_Slide3--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Atomic and Electronic Structure of ZrSiS"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Techniques developed with this NSF grant have enabled us to resolve electronic properties of novel materials</div> <div class="imageCredit">Ishigami</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Masahiro&nbsp;Ishigami</div> <div class="imageTitle">Atomic and Electronic Structure of ZrSiS</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/0955625/0955625_10013296_1541103887860_UCF-Michael-Lodge--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/0955625/0955625_10013296_1541103887860_UCF-Michael-Lodge--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Michael Lodge, Ph.D. with his specialized wheelchair"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/0955625/0955625_10013296_1541103887860_UCF-Michael-Lodge--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Michael Lodge, Ph.D. with his specialized wheelchair"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Michael Lodge uses the specialized wheelchair, purchased using the NSF support to work on Ishigami?s STM/AFM system.</div> <div class="imageCredit">OW Media</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Masahiro&nbsp;Ishigami</div> <div class="imageTitle">Michael Lodge, Ph.D. with his specialized wheelchair</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/0955625/0955625_10013296_1541104546494_Slide1--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/0955625/0955625_10013296_1541104546494_Slide1--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Ballistic Nanofriction of Gold Nanocrystal on Graphene"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/0955625/0955625_10013296_1541104546494_Slide1--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Ballistic Nanofriction of Gold Nanocrystal on Graphene"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Previous studies of friction as a function of speed has shown that friction becomes larger as the speed is increased. Ishigami showed that for gold nanocrystals on graphene the friction becomes vanishingly low at high speeds. This phenomenon, predicted by a previous theoretical study, is called</div> <div class="imageCredit">Michael Lodge</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Masahiro&nbsp;Ishigami</div> <div class="imageTitle">Ballistic Nanofriction of Gold Nanocrystal on Graphene</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/0955625/0955625_10013296_1541104667383_Slide2--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/0955625/0955625_10013296_1541104667383_Slide2--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Structure of Oligopeptide on Graphene"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/0955625/0955625_10013296_1541104667383_Slide2--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Structure of Oligopeptide on Graphene"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Biofunctionalization of graphene is considered to be a viable path towards chemical and biosensors. Ishigami used the atomically clean graphene as the starting point to resolve structure of oligopeptides adsorbed on graphene.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Ishigami</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Masahiro&nbsp;Ishigami</div> <div class="imageTitle">Structure of Oligopeptide on Graphene</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Intellectual Merit  This grant has enabled research on physical properties of graphene and related materials in the atomically-clean limit. Broad range of discoveries were made, resulting in 22 refereed publications. The most important discoveries are highlighted below:  Origin of variabilities in performance of graphene-based devices  Ishigami has developed a significant expertise on difficult-to-perform transport measurements in ultra-high vacuum (UHV). This is a critical component for the proposed study. Ishigami has uncovered the relationship between substrates and device performance of graphene (Physical Review B and Journal of Physics: Condensed Matter.   High resolution STM/AFM  The NSF career grant allowed resolution of the stacking angle between graphene on hexagonal boron nitride (h-BN) in the device configuration. The result enabled verification of the Hofstadter?s butterfly effect, resulting a publication in Nature. In addition, the NSF support enabled resolution of electronic properties of ZrSiS, which was published in Nano Letters. These STM/AFM results demonstrate that Ishigami has the necessary STM/AFM expertise to carry out the proposed measurements.   Functionalization of graphene   The capability to clean graphene and nanotube was used to resolve the structure of a peptide functional group adsorbed on graphene (Nano Letters).  Ballistic nanofriction on graphene   Previous studies of friction as a function of speed has shown that friction becomes larger as the speed is increased. Ishigami showed that for gold nanocrystals on graphene the friction becomes vanishingly low at high speeds. This phenomenon, predicted by a previous theoretical study, is called ballistic nanofriction and is different from structural or super-lubricity. It drastically alters our understanding of nanoscale friction and solid lubricants in general. The results were published in Scientific Reports.  Broader Impacts  8 graduate students have been supported by this NSF grant. Out of these, 4 students have graduated with Ph.D. in Physics and 2 students have graduated with the master?s degree. Notably, Ishigami?s first graduate student, Jyoti Katoch, is now an assistant professor in the Department of Physics at Carnegie Mellon University.  Ishigami has been heavily involved with making physics careers more accessible to underrepresented minorities. Ishigami encouraged the formation of the Physics Women?s Society, of which the first president was Jyoti Katoch. Ishigami has also used the supplemental award to the Career Award to make the laboratory accessible to those with mobility impairment.   The supplementary award made the laboratory more accessible for Michael Lodge, a paraplegic. Ishigami was able to secure a special motorized wheelchair to make his scanning tunneling microscope accessible. Michael recently graduated with a Ph.D. degree with his thesis work focusing on the measurement of ballistic nanofriction as well as on scanning tunneling microscopy/spectroscopy of ZrSiS.  He is now a postdoctoral fellow at the Nanyang National University in Singapore. We plan to use the developed expertise in improving accessibility in the future.          Last Modified: 11/01/2018       Submitted by: Masahiro Ishigami]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
