<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>CAREER: Emergent reactive properties of far-from-equilibrium electrochemical systems</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2010</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2016</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>618248.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>618248</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03090000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CHE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Chemistry</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Colby Foss</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>cfoss@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032925327</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>In this CAREER award, funded by the Chemical Structure, Dynamics and Mechanisms Program of the Chemistry Division Professor Istvan Kiss of Saint Louis University, will study the effects of self-organization, such as oscillations and pattern formation, on the reactive properties of complex electrochemical systems. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Current-generating chemical reactions of practical importance (e.g., in batteries and fuel cells) are often far from their thermodynamic equilibrium state. Such systems are capable of exhibiting large temporal and spatial variations of chemical concentrations, which, in turn, can significantly alter reactive properties of the system. Professor Kiss and his students will explore cathode-anode interactions, dynamical features of spatially organized reactive electrochemical media, and complex kinetic responses of bioelectrocatalytic reactions. This will be accomplished with a multidisciplinary, methodological approach in which the mathematical and experimental toolkits of nonlinear science are combined with recent technical developments of on-chip electrode fabrication, microfluidics, and bioelectrocatalyis. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt; Identification of underlying organizing principles and experimental characterization of far-from-equilibrium systems have broad applications in physical, chemical, and biological systems. The investigation of coupled cathode-anode multi-electrode flow cells fills in the gap between the existing knowledge on complex behavior of electrochemical systems and the modeling needs of industrial applications of galvanic and electrolytic cells. Oscillatory electrochemical media allow for testing recent theories on synchronization and network dynamics that have importance in generation of circadian rhythms and hypersynchronous neural discharges in epileptic seizures. Characterization of emergent reactive properties of bioelectrocatalytic systems has broader impact in clean technology: features of spatial and temporal enzyme activities affect power curves of bioelectrodes.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;In this context, Professor Kiss will develop and demonstrate a set of experiments about self-organizing systems. These experiments (e.g., on chaotic corrosion) will show how to connect notions from different disciplines to interpret emergent phenomena. They will be used as an outreach tool to convey the importance multidisciplinary science, to distribute recent theories and notions in Nonlinear Science to current and future biologists, chemists, and physicists, and to educate the public about the emergence of complex, 'intelligent' behavior of abiotic systems.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>04/13/2010</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/25/2012</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>0955555</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Istvan</FirstName>
<LastName>Kiss</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>Z</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Istvan Z Kiss</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>izkiss@slu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>3149772139</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000243198</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/13/2010</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Saint Louis University</Name>
<CityName>St Louis</CityName>
<ZipCode>631032006</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>3149773925</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>221 N. Grand Blvd.</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Missouri</StateName>
<StateCode>MO</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MO01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>050220722</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>SAINT LOUIS UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>050220722</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Saint Louis University]]></Name>
<CityName>St Louis</CityName>
<StateCode>MO</StateCode>
<ZipCode>631032006</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[221 N. Grand Blvd.]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Missouri</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MO01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>6879</Code>
<Text>Structure,Dynamics &amp;Mechanisms</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>0000</Code>
<Text>UNASSIGNED</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1045</Code>
<Text>CAREER-Faculty Erly Career Dev</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1187</Code>
<Text>PECASE- eligible</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>OTHR</Code>
<Text>OTHER RESEARCH OR EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0110</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0111</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0112</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2010~353000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2011~177000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2012~88248</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Electrochemical devices (e.g., batteries and sensor) are often composed of many particles (e.g., the cathode and anode, i.e., the positive and negative signs of a battery) and also operate in far-from equilibrium conditions (e.g., the changing state of a battery being discharged). In order to build better electrochemical devices, key needs in our scientific knowledge of matter and energy include challenges related to collective phenomena of strongly correlated multiparticle systems and the behavior of matter far beyond equilibrium. The project explored organizing principles of emergent reactive properties of far-from-equilibrium electrochemical systems. While traditional approaches for description of electrochemical systems include multi-scale modeling through sets of partial differential equations, whose solution often requires supercomputers, our approach was based considering chemical reactions as nodes, their interactions as edges, and use graph theory to develop a fundamental description for the types of spatiotemporal patterns that occur in electrochemical systems.</p> <p>We constructed networks of electrochemical reactions, where the existence of fundamentally novel types of chemical pattern formations were confirmed. The figure with the chimera pattern shows an example of a network of 20 electrochemical reactions on ring, in which each reaction is coupled to seven neighbors in both directions. The reactions formed a pattern, called &lsquo;chimera state&rsquo;, where a group of elements exhibit oscillations with uniform reaction rates (chimera core), and the rest of the elements exhibit largely different rates. Formation of such structures in a simple chemical system attracts attention from other fields of physics and biology, for example, could provide a framework for understanding hemispheric sleep in marine animals and birds.</p> <p>To further investigate such patterns, we built a lab-on-chip device, where complex chemical reactions can be investigated. Such devices with simple reactions are often used in sensors. Integration of complex reaction is a major challenge because the interaction of many different types of processes (e.g., chemical reactions, mass transfer, and potential drops in the electrolyte) can produce a plethora of unexpected behaviors. We managed to decrypt the interaction through the electric field and constructed a mathematical formula by which the interaction strengths can be predicted. The figure with lab-on-chip device shows that in weakly interacting systems the reaction rates are very different, while in strongly interacting systems the system behaves uniformly. Another figure with a lab-on-chip device shows a novel type of pattern, where coupling and large heterogeneities produce a pattern along the reacting surface.</p> <p>We showed that not only these patterns emerge in electrochemical devices, but we developed efficient methods by which we can use the interactions to efficiently control the patterns. For example, we developed technique for coupling design by which essential oscillations (e.g., heartbeat) can be restored, or deviation from normal behavior can be quickly compensated. The figure on restoration of rhythmicity shows that essential oscillations can be restored by even a feeble deviation from the usual diffusive coupling by introducing a small feedback factor. Such control techniques have applications in mitigating jet-lag, heart pacemaker and deep brain stimulator designs, and constructing more robust power-grids.</p> <p>The project also involved a community engagement through the development of a &lsquo;Nonlinear Corner&rsquo; at Saint Louis University. We set up demonstration experiments that show how to connect notions from different disciplines to interpret emergent phenomena. We developed the first demonstration experiment on chemical chaos, and showed it at various local, city, and regional events to about 350 participants that included local high school students and teachers. The experiments show that a simple, abiotic electrochemical system in far-from-equilibrium &nbsp;condition can exhibit complex behavior, for example, can generate &lsquo;cyclic&rsquo; behavior that never repeats itself.&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 09/27/2016<br>      Modified by: Istvan&nbsp;Z&nbsp;Kiss</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Images (<span id="selectedPhoto0">1</span> of <span class="totalNumber"></span>)           </div> <div class="galControls" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2016/0955555/0955555_10014822_1474572880186_images.001--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2016/0955555/0955555_10014822_1474572880186_images.001--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Chimera pattern"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2016/0955555/0955555_10014822_1474572880186_images.001--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Chimera pattern"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Caption: Network of current generating electrochemical reaction (corroding nickel wires) that generates chimera pattern is discussed by graduate students Michael Hankins and Mahesh Wickramasinghe.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Istvan Z Kiss</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Istvan&nbsp;Z&nbsp;Kiss</div> <div class="imageTitle">Chimera pattern</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2016/0955555/0955555_10014822_1474572974557_images.002--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2016/0955555/0955555_10014822_1474572974557_images.002--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Pattern in lab-on-chip devices"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2016/0955555/0955555_10014822_1474572974557_images.002--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Pattern in lab-on-chip devices"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">A lab-on-chip electrochemical device is assembled by graduate student Yanxin Jia. The microscopic device allows generation of of self-organized synchronized or desynchronized electric spikes reminiscent of neural action potentials.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Istvan Z Kiss</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Istvan&nbsp;Z&nbsp;Kiss</div> <div class="imageTitle">Pattern in lab-on-chip devices</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2016/0955555/0955555_10014822_1474573084965_images.003--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2016/0955555/0955555_10014822_1474573084965_images.003--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Pattern in lab-on-chip devices II"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2016/0955555/0955555_10014822_1474573084965_images.003--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Pattern in lab-on-chip devices II"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Pattern formation in a lab-on-chip device with segmented electrodes.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Istvan Z Kiss</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Istvan&nbsp;Z&nbsp;Kiss</div> <div class="imageTitle">Pattern in lab-on-chip devices II</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2016/0955555/0955555_10014822_1474573238142_images.004--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2016/0955555/0955555_10014822_1474573238142_images.004--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Restoration of rhythmicity"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2016/0955555/0955555_10014822_1474573238142_images.004--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Restoration of rhythmicity"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Coupling design in a multiparticle electrochemical system. Interactions among the chemical oscillations can stop oscillations (middle part of the bottom panel), which  can be restored (right part) with adding a small feedback to the system.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Istvan Z Kiss</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Istvan&nbsp;Z&nbsp;Kiss</div> <div class="imageTitle">Restoration of rhythmicity</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Electrochemical devices (e.g., batteries and sensor) are often composed of many particles (e.g., the cathode and anode, i.e., the positive and negative signs of a battery) and also operate in far-from equilibrium conditions (e.g., the changing state of a battery being discharged). In order to build better electrochemical devices, key needs in our scientific knowledge of matter and energy include challenges related to collective phenomena of strongly correlated multiparticle systems and the behavior of matter far beyond equilibrium. The project explored organizing principles of emergent reactive properties of far-from-equilibrium electrochemical systems. While traditional approaches for description of electrochemical systems include multi-scale modeling through sets of partial differential equations, whose solution often requires supercomputers, our approach was based considering chemical reactions as nodes, their interactions as edges, and use graph theory to develop a fundamental description for the types of spatiotemporal patterns that occur in electrochemical systems.  We constructed networks of electrochemical reactions, where the existence of fundamentally novel types of chemical pattern formations were confirmed. The figure with the chimera pattern shows an example of a network of 20 electrochemical reactions on ring, in which each reaction is coupled to seven neighbors in both directions. The reactions formed a pattern, called ?chimera state?, where a group of elements exhibit oscillations with uniform reaction rates (chimera core), and the rest of the elements exhibit largely different rates. Formation of such structures in a simple chemical system attracts attention from other fields of physics and biology, for example, could provide a framework for understanding hemispheric sleep in marine animals and birds.  To further investigate such patterns, we built a lab-on-chip device, where complex chemical reactions can be investigated. Such devices with simple reactions are often used in sensors. Integration of complex reaction is a major challenge because the interaction of many different types of processes (e.g., chemical reactions, mass transfer, and potential drops in the electrolyte) can produce a plethora of unexpected behaviors. We managed to decrypt the interaction through the electric field and constructed a mathematical formula by which the interaction strengths can be predicted. The figure with lab-on-chip device shows that in weakly interacting systems the reaction rates are very different, while in strongly interacting systems the system behaves uniformly. Another figure with a lab-on-chip device shows a novel type of pattern, where coupling and large heterogeneities produce a pattern along the reacting surface.  We showed that not only these patterns emerge in electrochemical devices, but we developed efficient methods by which we can use the interactions to efficiently control the patterns. For example, we developed technique for coupling design by which essential oscillations (e.g., heartbeat) can be restored, or deviation from normal behavior can be quickly compensated. The figure on restoration of rhythmicity shows that essential oscillations can be restored by even a feeble deviation from the usual diffusive coupling by introducing a small feedback factor. Such control techniques have applications in mitigating jet-lag, heart pacemaker and deep brain stimulator designs, and constructing more robust power-grids.  The project also involved a community engagement through the development of a ?Nonlinear Corner? at Saint Louis University. We set up demonstration experiments that show how to connect notions from different disciplines to interpret emergent phenomena. We developed the first demonstration experiment on chemical chaos, and showed it at various local, city, and regional events to about 350 participants that included local high school students and teachers. The experiments show that a simple, abiotic electrochemical system in far-from-equilibrium  condition can exhibit complex behavior, for example, can generate ?cyclic? behavior that never repeats itself.           Last Modified: 09/27/2016       Submitted by: Istvan Z Kiss]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
