<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>CAREER: Novel Plasmonic Properties of Individual Nanoparticle Chains Investigated by Correlated Structural Imaging and Single Particle Spectroscopy</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>02/01/2010</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>10/31/2015</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>600000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>620190</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03090000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CHE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Chemistry</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>George Janini</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>gjanini@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032928840</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The Macromolecular, Supramolecular and Nanochemistry (MSN) program of the Division of Chemistry will support the CAREER development plan of Prof. Stephan Link of the Department of Chemistry at William Marsh Rice University. Prof. Link and his students will combine novel single particle optical spectroscopy techniques with electron microscopy methods in order to understand the energy coupling between metal nanoparticles in close packed nanoparticle assemblies. Understanding the energy transfer in nanoparticle assemblies will ultimately determine the feasibility and aid in the development of cost-effective platforms for bottom-up chemical synthesis and self-assembly of nanoparticle-based functional materials such as antennas and waveguides, which are tolerant of variations in NP size, shape, and ordering. The PI and his students will connect their excitement about research and discovery in nanotechnology with outreach activities to educate K-12 students about nanotechnology and inspire them about careers in science related fields. Specifically, the PI will develop lectures for K-12 students on how NP size and shape is related to color and how this correlation is observed in an ensemble vs. single particle study. These lectures will be presented in the Civic Scientist Program at Rice University. The proposed project will provide excellent training opportunities to graduate students at the research frontier of physical sciences.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>02/03/2010</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/15/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>0955286</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Stephan</FirstName>
<LastName>Link</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Stephan Link</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>slink@rice.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>7133484561</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000258874</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>02/03/2010</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>William Marsh Rice University</Name>
<CityName>Houston</CityName>
<ZipCode>770051827</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>7133484820</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>6100 MAIN ST</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Texas</StateName>
<StateCode>TX</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>TX02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>050299031</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>WILLIAM MARSH RICE UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>050299031</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[William Marsh Rice University]]></Name>
<CityName>Houston</CityName>
<StateCode>TX</StateCode>
<ZipCode>770051827</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[6100 MAIN ST]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Texas</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>TX02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>6885</Code>
<Text>Macromolec/Supramolec/Nano</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>0000</Code>
<Text>UNASSIGNED</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1045</Code>
<Text>CAREER-Faculty Erly Career Dev</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1187</Code>
<Text>PECASE- eligible</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7237</Code>
<Text>NANO NON-SOLIC SCI &amp; ENG AWD</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>OTHR</Code>
<Text>OTHER RESEARCH OR EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0110</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0111</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0112</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0114</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2010~240000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2011~240000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2012~123491</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~16699</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Nanoparticle-based materials are becoming increasingly popular in multiple areas of current technology. This CAREER award, titled &ldquo;Novel Plasmonic Properties of Individual Nanoparticle Chains Investigated by Correlated Structural Imaging and Single Particle Spectroscopy,&rdquo; was funded to investigate the interactions that occur between nanoparticles in assemblies of different shapes and numbers of particles, as well as in different environments. The results of this research point toward plasmonic nanoparticles as highly promising electro-optical components.</p> <p>The fundamental direction of this research has been to study the optical properties of chains of silver and gold nanoparticles. The surface plasmon, a collective oscillation of conduction band electrons in the metal nanoparticle upon excitation by light, can be launched to travel along the length of a nanowire. The Link research group determined that a plasmon can travel along a chain of nanoparticles similar to a solid nanowire. In addition though, a plasmon can propagate around a 90 degree corner in nanoparticle chains without significant losses, unlike in a nanowire. Long propagation distances can only be achieved via strong plasmon coupling in nanoparticles assembled from the bottom up. While self-assembly methods generally produce a larger variety of defects in nanoparticle size and positioning, compared to top-down lithography, the effect of disorder was found to be rather insignificant especially as the overall asembly size grew. Plasmon propagation was studied using a new optical technique developed in the Link group, called Bleach-Imaged Plasmon Propagation (BlIPP). In this technique, the nanostructure is coated with a fluorescent molecule and excited at one end with a laser. As the plasmon propagates down the wire or chain, it excites the fluorescent molecules and bleaches them. The amount of photobleaching is proportional to the plasmonic near-field and is indicative of the plasmon propagation distance.</p> <p>In complement to these chain studies investigating the plasmon propagation, the Link group also studied the scattering and extinction of assembled nanoparticle chains. Careful combination of theoretical calculations and optical experiments of nanoparticle chains of varying lengths demonstrated that chains of nanoparticles are analogous to chemical polymers. The size, shape, and material of the repeat unit in the chain are important&nbsp; to determine the optical properties of the structure.</p> <p>To better understand the optical characteristics of the large scale assemblies, the Link group has also optically characterized nanoparticle dimers, the smallest possible plasmonic assembly. In addition to scatttering, other optical techniques (potoluminescence) have been applied and new approaches were developed such as photothermal spectroscopy, which measures the absorption spectrum of individual nanoparticles and their assemblies. An important aspect throughout all of these studies has been the correlated imaging of individual nanostructures using electron microscopy.</p> <p>This CAREER award has supported research activities for 4 graduate students, 3 undergraduates, and 1 postdoctoral researchers. Those supported have had the opportunity to be involved in collaborative research, present their results at local and national conferences, and publish in peer-reviewed journals. In addition to the publications produced and collaborations cultivated, the Link lab has also published several review articles to contribute to the field of nano-plasmonics. These include topical reviews in current research, tutorial reviews to encourage new researchers to enter the field of plasmonics, and perspectives on current research. Outreach lectures within the Rice Civic Scientist program have also brought concepts of nanoscience to middle and high school students.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            ...]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Nanoparticle-based materials are becoming increasingly popular in multiple areas of current technology. This CAREER award, titled "Novel Plasmonic Properties of Individual Nanoparticle Chains Investigated by Correlated Structural Imaging and Single Particle Spectroscopy," was funded to investigate the interactions that occur between nanoparticles in assemblies of different shapes and numbers of particles, as well as in different environments. The results of this research point toward plasmonic nanoparticles as highly promising electro-optical components.  The fundamental direction of this research has been to study the optical properties of chains of silver and gold nanoparticles. The surface plasmon, a collective oscillation of conduction band electrons in the metal nanoparticle upon excitation by light, can be launched to travel along the length of a nanowire. The Link research group determined that a plasmon can travel along a chain of nanoparticles similar to a solid nanowire. In addition though, a plasmon can propagate around a 90 degree corner in nanoparticle chains without significant losses, unlike in a nanowire. Long propagation distances can only be achieved via strong plasmon coupling in nanoparticles assembled from the bottom up. While self-assembly methods generally produce a larger variety of defects in nanoparticle size and positioning, compared to top-down lithography, the effect of disorder was found to be rather insignificant especially as the overall asembly size grew. Plasmon propagation was studied using a new optical technique developed in the Link group, called Bleach-Imaged Plasmon Propagation (BlIPP). In this technique, the nanostructure is coated with a fluorescent molecule and excited at one end with a laser. As the plasmon propagates down the wire or chain, it excites the fluorescent molecules and bleaches them. The amount of photobleaching is proportional to the plasmonic near-field and is indicative of the plasmon propagation distance.  In complement to these chain studies investigating the plasmon propagation, the Link group also studied the scattering and extinction of assembled nanoparticle chains. Careful combination of theoretical calculations and optical experiments of nanoparticle chains of varying lengths demonstrated that chains of nanoparticles are analogous to chemical polymers. The size, shape, and material of the repeat unit in the chain are important  to determine the optical properties of the structure.  To better understand the optical characteristics of the large scale assemblies, the Link group has also optically characterized nanoparticle dimers, the smallest possible plasmonic assembly. In addition to scatttering, other optical techniques (potoluminescence) have been applied and new approaches were developed such as photothermal spectroscopy, which measures the absorption spectrum of individual nanoparticles and their assemblies. An important aspect throughout all of these studies has been the correlated imaging of individual nanostructures using electron microscopy.  This CAREER award has supported research activities for 4 graduate students, 3 undergraduates, and 1 postdoctoral researchers. Those supported have had the opportunity to be involved in collaborative research, present their results at local and national conferences, and publish in peer-reviewed journals. In addition to the publications produced and collaborations cultivated, the Link lab has also published several review articles to contribute to the field of nano-plasmonics. These include topical reviews in current research, tutorial reviews to encourage new researchers to enter the field of plasmonics, and perspectives on current research. Outreach lectures within the Rice Civic Scientist program have also brought concepts of nanoscience to middle and high school students.          Last Modified: 12/28/2015       Submitted by: Stephan Link]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
