<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>CAREER: Non-Equilibrium Physics of Biological Interfaces</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/15/2010</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2016</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>794533.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>794533</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03010000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>PHY</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Physics</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Krastan Blagoev</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>kblagoev@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924666</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>In this project the PI will quantify and understand the non-equilibrium behavior of biological membranes and membrane coupled processes in the context of dynamical systems. The objective will be met by employing physically reconstituted systems that are driven out of equilibrium in a controlled manner. This approach will allow the systematic and quantitative study of the bidirectional interrelations between dynamic membrane organization and the function of membrane associated proteins that arise in non-equilibrium situations. The following aims will be undertaken: Aim 1: The driving mechanisms based on simulated ion flux will be characterized and the concentration profile of multivalent ions at charged membranes will be studied. Aim 2 will focus on the aggregation dynamics of multivalent lipid species under ionic forcing. Aim 3: Study the modulation of protein action on multiply charged lipids in spatially heterogeneous membranes and the resulting structural response of membranes. Aim 4:  Will address the question how combined systems of membranes and proteins organize in time and space under simultaneous forcing. In addition the following outreach activities will be undertaken: (1) Initiation of a pre-college level outreach program that will use biophysics based tools to improve physical science education in local schools and connect students to people and academic research on campus. It includes class demonstrations and lecture units led by graduate students, development of experiment based class modules involving high school teachers and a lab- internship program for high school students. (2) Development of biophysics and soft condensed matter based laboratory modules for physics classes for non-majors. In addition, the PI will develop a biophysics course for upper-division physics majors and entry levels graduate students. The course will provide a basic foundation for students and enable them to understand physics in its relationship to other scientific fields. It will also equip the students for active interdisciplinary research at the intersection of the physical and life sciences. (3) By engaging in the research aims of this program, graduate and undergraduate students will be trained in biophysical methods and techniques and they will advance their knowledge and communication skills beyond the traditional boundaries of scientific disciplines. Detailed documents and assessments related to all of these endeavors will be made available to the broader community</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>09/11/2010</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/15/2012</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>0955945</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Martin</FirstName>
<LastName>Forstner</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>B</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Martin B Forstner</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>mbforstn@syr.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>3154433878</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000515874</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/11/2010</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Syracuse University</Name>
<CityName>SYRACUSE</CityName>
<ZipCode>132441200</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>3154432807</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>OFFICE OF SPONSORED PROGRAMS</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[211 Lyman Hall]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>24</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NY24</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>002257350</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>SYRACUSE UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>002257350</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Syracuse University]]></Name>
<CityName>SYRACUSE</CityName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<ZipCode>132441200</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[OFFICE OF SPONSORED PROGRAMS]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>24</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NY24</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7246</Code>
<Text>PHYSICS OF LIVING SYSTEMS</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1045</Code>
<Text>CAREER-Faculty Erly Career Dev</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1084</Code>
<Text>NANOTECHNOLOGY INITIATIVE</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0110</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0112</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2010~369617</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2012~424916</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p style="text-align: left;">Biomembranes are fluid lipid bilayers that together with their associated proteins play a vital role for proper cell function.&nbsp; Membranes compartmentalize the cell interior and separate the cytosolic inside from the extracellular environment.&nbsp; Thus, they are important platforms for biochemical reactions concerned with processing of information and signaling across the membrane.&nbsp; In fact, many diseases are intimately related to malfunctions of membrane associated processes and are thus identified as prime targets for therapeutic drugs.&nbsp; Yet, understanding of the interrelation between spatio-temporal membrane organization and biological functions has remained poor and the funded research set out to develop model systems to study some basic aspects of membrane organization in non-equilibrium and its relation to biological function. &nbsp;The original concept (aim 1) envisioned calcium gradients that change in time as mechanism mechanism to drive membrane systems out of equilibrium in a controlled way. While that endeavor met with challenges, some basic foundations for a system using light activated compounds that can release and scavenge calcium ions were laid.&nbsp; In an alternative effort to establish a driving mechanism for this kind of nonequilibrium membrane dynamics, we also set up a system that exploits controlled electroosmotic flows to reorganize the membrane content. Much effort was spent on characterize the influence of calcium at physiological concentrations on the behavior of multiply negatively charged lipid entities (aim 2). Using lipid membranes models systems of single molecular thickness, we were able to access the change in free energy in the intermolecular interactions and developed a theoretical model that describes that behavior. In addition, were also able to develop a system of supported lipid bilayers on modified glass surfaces that permitted us to study the aggregation of multiply negative charged lipid species due to calcium by fluorescence correlation spectroscopy. A sensitive dependence of the dynamics of the charged lipids on calcium levels was found. This change in diffusivity was exploited as an indicator of their degree of aggregation, whjich was observed even at very low calcium concentrations, that had previously not been considered in any depth. In that regime (0-1 &micro;Mol of calcium) highly charged negative lipids exhibit an initial increase of diffusive speed before returning to the initial value. This unexpected observation, might indicate a calcium dependent interaction of the charged lipid species with the surrounding bulk lipids, that leads to nanocluster formation in the absence of calcium. In order to proceed with the introduction of proteins to the system we developed a new way to anchor proteins to lipid membranes. This anchoring system exploits the presence of an encoded non-canonical amino acid to attach a lipid to a protein of interest. Through this modification, it is possible to separate the attachment process from the protein&rsquo;s spatial reorganization in the plane of the membrane. This new method is providing a general technique to augment lipid membranes with proteins. Similarly, in order to allow rapid measurement on multiple planar bilayers and different conditions we developed a technique that permits supported membrane experiments with an automated multi-plate reader. During the lifetime of this award a graduate level interdisciplinary class on &ldquo;Biological Physics of the Cell&rdquo; was developed. Bringing interested students from Biology, Chemistry, Physics as well as Biomedical and Chemical Engineering together to acquire a basic knowledge of cellular systems and systems and their quantitative mathematical description and modeling. &nbsp;This perspective was also utilized to update an existing undergraduate course &ldquo;Biological and Medical Physics&rdquo;. Working on this research facilitated the training and education of 3 PhD students, 4 Undergraduate students and one summer high school student.</p> <p style="text-align: left;">&nbsp;</p> <p style="text-align: left;">&nbsp;</p> <p style="text-align: left;">&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 02/22/2017<br>      Modified by: Martin&nbsp;B&nbsp;Forstner</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[Biomembranes are fluid lipid bilayers that together with their associated proteins play a vital role for proper cell function.  Membranes compartmentalize the cell interior and separate the cytosolic inside from the extracellular environment.  Thus, they are important platforms for biochemical reactions concerned with processing of information and signaling across the membrane.  In fact, many diseases are intimately related to malfunctions of membrane associated processes and are thus identified as prime targets for therapeutic drugs.  Yet, understanding of the interrelation between spatio-temporal membrane organization and biological functions has remained poor and the funded research set out to develop model systems to study some basic aspects of membrane organization in non-equilibrium and its relation to biological function.  The original concept (aim 1) envisioned calcium gradients that change in time as mechanism mechanism to drive membrane systems out of equilibrium in a controlled way. While that endeavor met with challenges, some basic foundations for a system using light activated compounds that can release and scavenge calcium ions were laid.  In an alternative effort to establish a driving mechanism for this kind of nonequilibrium membrane dynamics, we also set up a system that exploits controlled electroosmotic flows to reorganize the membrane content. Much effort was spent on characterize the influence of calcium at physiological concentrations on the behavior of multiply negatively charged lipid entities (aim 2). Using lipid membranes models systems of single molecular thickness, we were able to access the change in free energy in the intermolecular interactions and developed a theoretical model that describes that behavior. In addition, were also able to develop a system of supported lipid bilayers on modified glass surfaces that permitted us to study the aggregation of multiply negative charged lipid species due to calcium by fluorescence correlation spectroscopy. A sensitive dependence of the dynamics of the charged lipids on calcium levels was found. This change in diffusivity was exploited as an indicator of their degree of aggregation, whjich was observed even at very low calcium concentrations, that had previously not been considered in any depth. In that regime (0-1 &micro;Mol of calcium) highly charged negative lipids exhibit an initial increase of diffusive speed before returning to the initial value. This unexpected observation, might indicate a calcium dependent interaction of the charged lipid species with the surrounding bulk lipids, that leads to nanocluster formation in the absence of calcium. In order to proceed with the introduction of proteins to the system we developed a new way to anchor proteins to lipid membranes. This anchoring system exploits the presence of an encoded non-canonical amino acid to attach a lipid to a protein of interest. Through this modification, it is possible to separate the attachment process from the protein?s spatial reorganization in the plane of the membrane. This new method is providing a general technique to augment lipid membranes with proteins. Similarly, in order to allow rapid measurement on multiple planar bilayers and different conditions we developed a technique that permits supported membrane experiments with an automated multi-plate reader. During the lifetime of this award a graduate level interdisciplinary class on "Biological Physics of the Cell" was developed. Bringing interested students from Biology, Chemistry, Physics as well as Biomedical and Chemical Engineering together to acquire a basic knowledge of cellular systems and systems and their quantitative mathematical description and modeling.  This perspective was also utilized to update an existing undergraduate course "Biological and Medical Physics". Working on this research facilitated the training and education of 3 PhD students, 4 Undergraduate students and one summer high school student.             Last Modified: 02/22/2017       Submitted by: Martin B Forstner]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
