<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>RUI:Enhancing Single-Molecule Microscopy for Ion Channel Characterization in Lipid Membranes</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>05/15/2010</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2013</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>252000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>252000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03090000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CHE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Chemistry</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Charles Pibel</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>cpibel@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032920000</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The Chemical Measurement and Imaging Program supports the collaborative efforts of Profs.  Daniel Burden and Lisa Keranen-Burden at Wheaton College to develop new methodologies for monitoring aggregated proteins and ion channels in lipid membranes by improving single-molecule fluorescence imaging techniques.  The research uses the alpha-hemolysin channel from Staphylococcus aureus as a model.  This protein has been shown to play a significant role in the virulence of methicillin-resistant Staphylococcus aureus (MRSA) infections.  In recent years, MRSA ?superbugs? have been plaguing hospitals and schools nationwide, causing extreme human illness, and forcing draconian measures to keep outbreaks from spreading. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Beyond the immediate model target system, the work gains broad impact from the important role of lipid membrane protein channel assemblies in nervous signal transmission, intercellular communication, toxin potency, and disease states.  This highly interdisciplinary research offers extraordinary opportunities for involvement by undergraduate students, enhanced by a unique collaboration with Dr. John Kasianowicz at the National Institute of Standards and Technology. Aspects of the program will be integrated into the undergraduate curriculum, including general chemistry, advanced analytical chemistry, and the general biology laboratory.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>05/12/2010</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/02/2012</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>0957197</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Daniel</FirstName>
<LastName>Burden</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Daniel Burden</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>daniel.burden@wheaton.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6307525065</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000289519</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/12/2010</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Lisa</FirstName>
<LastName>Keranen-Burden</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Lisa Keranen-Burden</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>lisa.burden@wheaton.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6307527268</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000332565</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/12/2010</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Wheaton College</Name>
<CityName>Wheaton</CityName>
<ZipCode>601874919</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6307525833</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>501 College Avenue</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Illinois</StateName>
<StateCode>IL</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>06</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>IL06</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>068605054</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>TRUSTEES OF WHEATON COLLEGE, THE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>068605054</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Wheaton College]]></Name>
<CityName>Wheaton</CityName>
<StateCode>IL</StateCode>
<ZipCode>601874919</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[501 College Avenue]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Illinois</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>06</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>IL06</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1114</Code>
<Text>Cellular Dynamics and Function</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>6880</Code>
<Text>Chemical Measurement &amp; Imaging</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>6883</Code>
<Text>Chemistry of Life Processes</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>0000</Code>
<Text>UNASSIGNED</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>6880</Code>
<Text>CHEMICAL MEASUREMENT &amp; IMAGING</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9229</Code>
<Text>RES IN UNDERGRAD INST-RESEARCH</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>OTHR</Code>
<Text>OTHER RESEARCH OR EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0110</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0111</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0112</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2010~84000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2011~84000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2012~84000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><div><em><span style="text-decoration: underline;"><span style="font-size: small;"> <div>Intellectual Merit:</div> </span></span></em><span style="text-decoration: underline;"><span style="font-size: small;"> </span></span><span style="font-size: small;"> <div>&nbsp;</div> <div>This award enabled two senior investigators from the Chemistry and Biology departments at Wheaton College to lead a team of researchers in the development of new methodologies for monitoring aggregated proteins and ion channels in lipid membranes.&nbsp; The process of protein channel assembly in a lipid membrane environment is of fundamental importance to the general understanding of nervous signal transmission, intercellular communication, toxin potency, and disease states. The research used the alpha hemolysin channel from <em>Staphylococcus aureus</em> as a model.&nbsp; This protein has been shown to play a significant role in the virulence of methicillin-resistant <em>Staphylococcus aureus</em> (MRSA) infections.&nbsp; In recent years, MRSA "superbugs" have been plaguing hospitals and schools nationwide, causing extreme human illness, and forcing organizational administrators to enact draconian measures to keep outbreaks from spreading.</div> <div>&nbsp;</div> <div>During the award period, four peer-reviewed scientific papers, one patent application, four national conference presentations, and numerous web-based documents were produced and published.&nbsp; In addition, award funds were used to involve more than 15 undergraduate research positions, both during the summer and the academic year.&nbsp; See the following link for specific information:</div> </span></div> <div>&nbsp;</div> <div><a href="http://www.wheaton.edu/Academics/Faculty/B/Daniel-Burden"><span style="text-decoration: underline;"><span style="color: #0000ff; font-size: small;"><span style="color: #0000ff; font-size: small;"><span lang="EN">http://www.wheaton.edu/Academics/Faculty/B/Daniel-Burden</span></span></span></span><span style="color: #0000ff; font-size: small;">&nbsp;</span></a></div> <div><span style="font-size: small;"><span lang="EN"><em><span style="text-decoration: underline;"> <div>&nbsp;</div> <div>Broader Impacts:</div> </span></em> <div>During the award period, more than 15 research students (including chemistry, biology, computer science, and applied health science majors) participated in intensive, multiple-year long research experiences. These students and the supervising faculty capitalized on new infrastructure that Wheaton brought online to support the aims of this grant (i.e., a new science building and a new suite of specialized instrumentation).&nbsp; This award also helped promote an ongoing collaboration with the National Institute of Standards and Technology, located in Gaithersburg, MD.&nbsp; A special programmatic emphasis was given to sustaining our traditionally strong level of participation from female undergraduate researchers.&nbsp; Fifty percent of the research team was female over the duration of the grant.&nbsp; We also were involved in a new outreach program to minority students, entitled the Wheaton BRIDGE (Building Roads to Intellectual Diversity and Great Education).&nbsp; This program provided scientific opportunities for first-generation college-bound, low-income or African-American or Latino students from the Chicagoland area.&nbsp; Some of the most successful research projects were developed into exercises for advanced Analytical and Physical Chemistry teaching laboratories, which expanded the impact of research to many dozens of students each year.&nbsp; <strong> </strong></div> <strong><br /></strong></span></span><span style="font-family: Calibri; font-size: small;"></span></div><br> <p>            Last Modified: 11/04/2013<br>      Modified by: Daniel&nbsp;Burden</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Intellectual Merit:     This award enabled two senior investigators from the Chemistry and Biology departments at Wheaton College to lead a team of researchers in the development of new methodologies for monitoring aggregated proteins and ion channels in lipid membranes.  The process of protein channel assembly in a lipid membrane environment is of fundamental importance to the general understanding of nervous signal transmission, intercellular communication, toxin potency, and disease states. The research used the alpha hemolysin channel from Staphylococcus aureus as a model.  This protein has been shown to play a significant role in the virulence of methicillin-resistant Staphylococcus aureus (MRSA) infections.  In recent years, MRSA "superbugs" have been plaguing hospitals and schools nationwide, causing extreme human illness, and forcing organizational administrators to enact draconian measures to keep outbreaks from spreading.   During the award period, four peer-reviewed scientific papers, one patent application, four national conference presentations, and numerous web-based documents were produced and published.  In addition, award funds were used to involve more than 15 undergraduate research positions, both during the summer and the academic year.  See the following link for specific information:    http://www.wheaton.edu/Academics/Faculty/B/Daniel-Burden     Broader Impacts:  During the award period, more than 15 research students (including chemistry, biology, computer science, and applied health science majors) participated in intensive, multiple-year long research experiences. These students and the supervising faculty capitalized on new infrastructure that Wheaton brought online to support the aims of this grant (i.e., a new science building and a new suite of specialized instrumentation).  This award also helped promote an ongoing collaboration with the National Institute of Standards and Technology, located in Gaithersburg, MD.  A special programmatic emphasis was given to sustaining our traditionally strong level of participation from female undergraduate researchers.  Fifty percent of the research team was female over the duration of the grant.  We also were involved in a new outreach program to minority students, entitled the Wheaton BRIDGE (Building Roads to Intellectual Diversity and Great Education).  This program provided scientific opportunities for first-generation college-bound, low-income or African-American or Latino students from the Chicagoland area.  Some of the most successful research projects were developed into exercises for advanced Analytical and Physical Chemistry teaching laboratories, which expanded the impact of research to many dozens of students each year.            Last Modified: 11/04/2013       Submitted by: Daniel Burden]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
