<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>II New: A Network of Open Experimental Testbeds for Surgical Robotics Research</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>03/15/2010</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>02/29/2012</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>635045.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>635045</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>05050000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>CSE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CNS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Computer and Network Systems</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Richard Voyles</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>While areas of the US such as California and the East coast have major&lt;br/&gt;medical centers near every population center, there are many areas,&lt;br/&gt;even in developed countries, with a widely dispersed patient&lt;br/&gt;population with significant obstacles to advanced medical care.&lt;br/&gt;Victims of large scale natural disasters and battlefield casualties&lt;br/&gt;also lack state of the art care.  Telesurgery could potentially meet&lt;br/&gt;these needs. There is a growing interest in computational research on&lt;br/&gt;intelligent telesurgery.  Today's telesurgery systems do not integrate&lt;br/&gt;with medical imaging or have intelligent functions to assist the&lt;br/&gt;surgeon. This project is building seven teleoperated  surgical robot&lt;br/&gt;and surgeon-interface systems powerful and precise enough to support&lt;br/&gt;research on advanced robotic surgery techniques at seven major&lt;br/&gt;research universities.   University of Washington and University of&lt;br/&gt;California Santa Cruz are building the seven robots and will&lt;br/&gt;distribute them to Harvard, Johns Hopkins, University of Nebraska,&lt;br/&gt;U.C. Berkeley, and UCLA.   When completed, the seven research lab&lt;br/&gt;robots will be networked together for sharing of software,&lt;br/&gt;interoperability, and on-line telesurgery experiments.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Impact&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The results of this project will enable a network of  researchers to&lt;br/&gt;prototype advanced surgical robotics techniques, and evaluate them in&lt;br/&gt;realistic contexts including appropriate animal procedures.  Besides&lt;br/&gt;new and less invasive cures, such a technology can provide easier&lt;br/&gt;access to care in remote parts of the US, and the developing world.&lt;br/&gt; The seven cooperating labs, and external partners will be able to&lt;br/&gt;interconnect their systems, share modules of software, and replicate&lt;br/&gt;each others experiments.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>03/11/2010</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>01/18/2011</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.070</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>0958441</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Blake</FirstName>
<LastName>Hannaford</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Blake Hannaford</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>blake@ee.washington.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2065432197</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000316142</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>03/11/2010</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Washington</Name>
<CityName>Seattle</CityName>
<ZipCode>981950001</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2065434043</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>4333 Brooklyn Ave NE</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Washington</StateName>
<StateCode>WA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>WA07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>605799469</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF WASHINGTON</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>042803536</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Washington]]></Name>
<CityName>Seattle</CityName>
<StateCode>WA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>981950001</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[4333 Brooklyn Ave NE]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Washington</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>WA07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7359</Code>
<Text>CCRI-CISE Cmnty Rsrch Infrstrc</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9218</Code>
<Text>BASIC RESEARCH &amp; HUMAN RESORCS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>HPCC</Code>
<Text>HIGH PERFORMANCE COMPUTING &amp; COMM</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0110</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0111</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2010~524399</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2011~110646</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><strong>Goal</strong><br />The overriding goal of this project was to advance the field of robot-assisted surgery by creating a research surgical robot names "Raven" &nbsp;which builds collaboration. &nbsp;In this project we built eight research surgical robots and distributed them to researchers at Harvard, Johns Hopkins, University of Nebraska, UCLA, U.C. Berkeley, as well as our own institutions University of Washington and U.C. Santa Cruz. &nbsp; &nbsp;Researchers &nbsp;can program and modify the Raven system but it serves as a standard platform so that they can share their software and improvements. &nbsp; The Raven is designed to be an extensible, robust, and programmable research tool to allow researchers in engineering, surgery, and computer science, to experiment, innovate, and collaborate in the burgeoning field of robotic assisted surgery.</p> <p><br /><strong>Background</strong><br />Robotic Assisted Surgery began to be explored by medical and engineering researchers in the early 1990s. &nbsp; In the late 1990's Computer Motion Inc. of Santa Barbara, CA sold the first FDA approved surgical robotic system, the Zeus. &nbsp; In about 2000 Intuitive Surgical introduced the da Vinci system, acquired Computer Motion, and soon dominated the fast growing market.<br />Robotic assisted surgery is performed today in literally thousands of operating rooms around the world. &nbsp;Over 200,000 patents have been treated in robotic assisted procedures. &nbsp; The most common robotic assisted procedures today are prostatectomy (removal of the prostate gland) and hysterectomy. &nbsp; With both of these procedures the robotic instruments are inserted through very small incisions so that the patient &nbsp;has a quicker recovery with less post operative pain. &nbsp; At the same time, the surgeon gets improved dexterity in small spaces, and 3D high definition visualization.<br />Researchers worldwide are rushing to improve the capabilities of robotic assisted surgery, to develop and validate new surgical treatments using the technology, and to develop methods of training and assessment of students of robotic surgery. &nbsp;<br />A barrier to this research is that the da Vinci is a $1.8M device and its internal software cannot be modified. &nbsp; Until now, a researcher who wants to innovate in surgical robotics needed to develop their own robot from scratch. &nbsp;The software they write is therefore customized for that robot. &nbsp;Researchers cannot easily build on each others advancements.&nbsp;</p> <p><br />The Raven II was a joint project between University of Washington Biorobotics Lab and University of California, &nbsp;Santa Cruz Human Bionics Laboratory. &nbsp; Prof. Rosen's team at UCSC designed and assembled the Raven II mechanisms and Prof. Hannaford's team at UW designed and assembled the electronics and software and put the systems together. &nbsp; An earlier prototype, the Raven I system, was developed by Profs Rosen and Hannaford and their team at UW in 2005 with support from the US Army Medical Research and Materiel Command (MRMC) at Fort Detrick Md.&nbsp;</p> <p>Results</p> <p>In January 2012, we shipped the systems to all institutions in the project. &nbsp;Each site has set up their system and we are collaborating through an on-line discussion forum dedicated to the project. &nbsp; We have supported the sites through their process if setting up their systems and starting them up. &nbsp;In one case we shipped parts to fix shipping damage to one arm. &nbsp;</p> <p>Our project has attracted significant media attention including an article in The Economist ("An ope-source robo-surgeon", Economist Technology Quarterly, p6, March 3 2012). Interested poeple can track the Raven project through the Raven II developer's blog: <a href="http://r2db.tumblr.com/">http://r2db.tumblr.com/</a></p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 04/03/2012<br>      Modified by: Blake&nbs...]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Goal The overriding goal of this project was to advance the field of robot-assisted surgery by creating a research surgical robot names "Raven"  which builds collaboration.  In this project we built eight research surgical robots and distributed them to researchers at Harvard, Johns Hopkins, University of Nebraska, UCLA, U.C. Berkeley, as well as our own institutions University of Washington and U.C. Santa Cruz.    Researchers  can program and modify the Raven system but it serves as a standard platform so that they can share their software and improvements.   The Raven is designed to be an extensible, robust, and programmable research tool to allow researchers in engineering, surgery, and computer science, to experiment, innovate, and collaborate in the burgeoning field of robotic assisted surgery.   Background Robotic Assisted Surgery began to be explored by medical and engineering researchers in the early 1990s.   In the late 1990's Computer Motion Inc. of Santa Barbara, CA sold the first FDA approved surgical robotic system, the Zeus.   In about 2000 Intuitive Surgical introduced the da Vinci system, acquired Computer Motion, and soon dominated the fast growing market. Robotic assisted surgery is performed today in literally thousands of operating rooms around the world.  Over 200,000 patents have been treated in robotic assisted procedures.   The most common robotic assisted procedures today are prostatectomy (removal of the prostate gland) and hysterectomy.   With both of these procedures the robotic instruments are inserted through very small incisions so that the patient  has a quicker recovery with less post operative pain.   At the same time, the surgeon gets improved dexterity in small spaces, and 3D high definition visualization. Researchers worldwide are rushing to improve the capabilities of robotic assisted surgery, to develop and validate new surgical treatments using the technology, and to develop methods of training and assessment of students of robotic surgery.   A barrier to this research is that the da Vinci is a $1.8M device and its internal software cannot be modified.   Until now, a researcher who wants to innovate in surgical robotics needed to develop their own robot from scratch.  The software they write is therefore customized for that robot.  Researchers cannot easily build on each others advancements.    The Raven II was a joint project between University of Washington Biorobotics Lab and University of California,  Santa Cruz Human Bionics Laboratory.   Prof. Rosen's team at UCSC designed and assembled the Raven II mechanisms and Prof. Hannaford's team at UW designed and assembled the electronics and software and put the systems together.   An earlier prototype, the Raven I system, was developed by Profs Rosen and Hannaford and their team at UW in 2005 with support from the US Army Medical Research and Materiel Command (MRMC) at Fort Detrick Md.   Results  In January 2012, we shipped the systems to all institutions in the project.  Each site has set up their system and we are collaborating through an on-line discussion forum dedicated to the project.   We have supported the sites through their process if setting up their systems and starting them up.  In one case we shipped parts to fix shipping damage to one arm.    Our project has attracted significant media attention including an article in The Economist ("An ope-source robo-surgeon", Economist Technology Quarterly, p6, March 3 2012). Interested poeple can track the Raven project through the Raven II developer's blog: http://r2db.tumblr.com/       Last Modified: 04/03/2012       Submitted by: Blake Hannaford]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
