<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Infection Site-specific Analyses Elucidate Arabidopsis Host Processes and Components Mediating the Sustained Growth and Reproduction of a Compatible Obligate Biotroph</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>04/01/2010</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>03/31/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>637528.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>944913</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>08090300</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>BIO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>IOS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Integrative Organismal Systems</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Michael Mishkind</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>mmishkin@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032928413</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Powdery mildews are fungal plant pathogens that infect a variety of agronomic and ornamental species, as well as the model plant Arabidopsis thaliana.  Powdery mildews (PMs) establish specialized active feeding sites in the upper cell layer (epidermis) of the plant leaf through which they acquire all their nutrients.  They require living plant tissue for their growth and reproduction and dramatically modulate leaf function and metabolism at the site of infection.  Using lasers to specifically isolate only those cells at the site of PM infection, the investigators identified novel plant regulators and processes specifically altered by the sustained growth and reproduction of the PM Golovinomyces orontii on A. thaliana.  Sixty-seven regulators were identified with subsets of these playing known or inferred roles in photosynthesis, cold/dehydration responses, plant defense, hormone signaling, and the cell cycle.  The investigators will employ genetic, molecular, biochemical, and cytological approaches to characterize and classify these regulators based on their impact on PM growth and reproduction and the above processes.  Furthermore, two of these processes will be explored in more detail using the above approaches.  For example, using microscopic analysis, the investigators determined that the cell cycle is altered at the site of PM infection.  Specifically, the number of copies of chromosomal DNA is dramatically enhanced in the cells underlying the infected epidermal cell.  Furthermore, this increased copy number is required to maintain the full growth and reproduction of the fungus.  The investigators will further define the factors responsible for this fungal-induced increase in chromosomal DNA and its role in the sustained growth and reproduction of the PM on Arabidopsis.  Not only will this research identify targets for translational research in economically important plants impacted by PMs, but identified genes and processes may also impact other microbes that require living plant tissue and/or establish highly localized feeding sites.  In addition, this highly localized, PM-inducible system should allow the investigators to uncover regulatory mechanisms governing fundamental processes, such as the cell cycle, that are challenging to explore using traditional approaches.  Two postdoctoral scholars and four undergraduates, including students underrepresented in the sciences, will be trained in this interdisciplinary project.  Outreach to students of local public elementary schools will enhance scientific literacy and inquiry using plants and school gardening programs as accessible entry points.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>04/09/2010</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/01/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.074</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>0958100</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Mary</FirstName>
<LastName>Wildermuth</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>C</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Mary C Wildermuth</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>mwildermuth@berkeley.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5106845373</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000114168</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/09/2010</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of California-Berkeley</Name>
<CityName>BERKELEY</CityName>
<ZipCode>947101749</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5106433891</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>Sponsored Projects Office</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[1608 Fourth Street, Suite 220]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>13</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CA13</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>124726725</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>REGENTS OF THE UNIVERSITY OF CALIFORNIA, THE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>071549000</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[UNIVERSITY OF CALIFORNIA BERKELEY]]></Name>
<CityName>Berkeley</CityName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>947200001</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>13</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CA13</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<FoaInformation>
<Code>0000099</Code>
<Name>Other Applications NEC</Name>
</FoaInformation>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1119</Code>
<Text>Animal Developmental Mechanism</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7656</Code>
<Text>Symbiosis Infection &amp; Immunity</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7619</Code>
<Text>EQUIPMENT ACQUISITIONS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9178</Code>
<Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9183</Code>
<Text>GENERAL FOUNDATIONS OF BIOTECHNOLOGY</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9251</Code>
<Text>REU SUPP-Res Exp for Ugrd Supp</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>BIOT</Code>
<Text>BIOTECHNOLOGY</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>OTHR</Code>
<Text>OTHER RESEARCH OR EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0110</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0111</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0112</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0113</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0114</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2010~214120</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2011~435408</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2012~29385</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2013~260000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~6000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Powdery mildews are fungal plant pathogens that infect a variety of agricultural and ornamental species. Most gardeners have firsthand experience with powdery mildews as a white powder observed on their rose bushes or cucumber plants. Powdery mildews are obligate plant biotrophs meaning they require living plant tissue for their growth, development, and reproduction. In order to obtain host nutrients, they develop a specialized feeding site in an outer epidermal plant cell (<strong>Figure 1</strong>); all other fungal growth and reproduction occurs on the surface (e.g. of the leaf). Host metabolism is altered to supply the fungus with its requisite nutrients, while limiting defense responses that would incur resistance.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>Site-specific analyses determined that the powdery mildew <em>Golovinomyces orontii</em> induces a cell cycle variant called endoreduplication in the plant cells underlying the fungal feeding site (<strong>Fig. 1</strong>). Induced host endoreduplication is specifically associated with the metabolically demanding process of fungal asexual reproduction (spore production). With each round of endoreduplication, DNA replication occurs but the cells do not divide, resulting in a cell with doubled DNA content (<strong>Figure 2</strong>). In response to the powdery mildew, DNA content in endoreduplicated plant cells increases ~16-fold. Conserved cell cycle regulators and plant-specific proteins were identified that impact the DNA content of cells underlying the fungal feeding site. And, the extent of fungal reproduction correlates with the DNA content of these plant cells (<strong>Figure 3</strong>). This shows that induced plant cell endoreduplication acts in a dose-dependent manner to promote fungal reproduction.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>Endoreduplication has long been associated with enhanced metabolic capacity and has been associated with cellular nutrient supply (e.g. plant endosperm) and/or differentiation (e.g. plant trichomes). In addition, it is now clear that diverse plant biotrophs have converged on induced host endoreduplication as a mechanism to support their growth and development. These include: powdery mildew, cabbage leaf curl virus, root-cyst and root-knot nematodes, rhizobia, and arbuscular mycorrhizal fungi (<strong>Figure 4</strong>). In these interactions, induced host endoreduplication is associated with feeding/nutrient exchange site development and access to elevated host resources during metabolically demanding periods of growth or development. When induced endoreduplication is compromised, so too is biotroph growth and/or development.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>While increased DNA content itself can result in elevated metabolic capacity, global analysis of plant gene expression data associated with developmental or biotroph-induced endoreduplication identified specific metabolic pathways that are preferentially enhanced in endoreduplicated cells. This includes alternate metabolic pathways previously shown to support increased rates of nutrient and energy molecule synthesis. Disruption of one such pathway results in a dose-dependent decrease in powdery mildew spore production. And, metabolites from this pathway are incorporated into newly formed spores. This provides a specific mechanism by which biotroph-induced plant cell endoreduplication fuels biotroph proliferation.</p> <p>Potential applications include i) enhancing powdery mildew resistance of crops, ii) increasing production of pharmaceutical and biofuel compounds, and iii) limiting cancer cells that evade treatment (<strong>Figure 5</strong>). Powdery mildews are widespread pathogens of economically important plants. Repeated chemical treatment of these plants is ubiquitous as estimated yield losses without treatment are &gt;30%. The identification of plant genes that are used by powdery mildews to support their proliferation provides novel targets for plant breeding. Reducing their expression in <em>Arabidopsis</em> or tomato does not reduce plant biomass or visibly alter plant development making them viable commercial targets. In addition, manipulation of plant endoreduplication can be used to enhance yields and traits of products such as maize kernel and tomato fruit that undergo endoreduplication as part of their development. Finally, this knowledge could also enhance bioproduction of plant specialized metabolites including flavors and phytoceuticals by increasing the rate of energy-rich precursor synthesis. Novel regulators of the mitotic cell cycle and endoreduplication were uncovered through this research. As cancer cells that evade treatment often exhibit endoreduplication and many cell cycle components are conserved, our findings could provide novel targets/approaches to limit cancer development and metastasis.</p> <p>Three postdoctoral scholars, two graduate students, and six undergraduates, including students underrepresented in the sciences, were trained in plant molecular biology and genetics, cell biology, biochemistry, and plant pathology through this interdisciplinary project.&nbsp; Outreach to students of local public elementary schools enhanced scientific literacy and inquiry using plants and school gardening programs as accessible entry points. Furthermore, development and implementation of a new outreach program called Be A Scientist now has every 7<sup>th</sup> grader in Berkeley Public Schools (&gt;700 students) working with a UC Berkeley STEM graduate student volunteer to pursue a research question of their own design over the course of six week in-class program. More than 160 UC Berkeley graduate students have participated, allowing individualized attention and support for Berkeley public school students to develop the skills of being a scientist. Evidence-based scientific inquiry is part of the Next Generation Science Standards and an essential skill for our citizenry. This award-winning program can serve as a model for other University-public school STEM partnerships.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 07/19/2017<br>      Modified by: Mary&nbsp;C&nbsp;Wildermuth</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Images (<span id="selectedPhoto0">1</span> of <span class="totalNumber"></span>)           </div> <div class="galControls" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/0958100/0958100_10014720_1500511472053_Slide1--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/0958100/0958100_10014720_1500511472053_Slide1--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Figure 1"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/0958100/0958100_10014720_1500511472053_Slide1--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Figure 1"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Figure 1. Powdery mildews manipulate the plant cell cycle to fuel their proliferation.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Mary Wildermuth</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Mary&nbsp;C&nbsp;Wildermuth</div> <div class="imageTitle">Figure 1</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/0958100/0958100_10014720_1500510754668_Slide5--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/0958100/0958100_10014720_1500510754668_Slide5--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Figure 5"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/0958100/0958100_10014720_1500510754668_Slide5--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Figure 5"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Figure 5. Opportunities for Commercial Application.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Mary Wildermuth</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Mary&nbsp;C&nbsp;Wildermuth</div> <div class="imageTitle">Figure 5</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/0958100/0958100_10014720_1500511153889_Slide4--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/0958100/0958100_10014720_1500511153889_Slide4--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Figure 4"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/0958100/0958100_10014720_1500511153889_Slide4--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Figure 4"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Diverse plant biotrophs manipulate the host cell cycle to promote their growth and development.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Mary Wildermuth</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Mary&nbsp;C&nbsp;Wildermuth</div> <div class="imageTitle">Figure 4</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/0958100/0958100_10014720_1500511301764_Slide2--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/0958100/0958100_10014720_1500511301764_Slide2--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Figure 2"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/0958100/0958100_10014720_1500511301764_Slide2--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Figure 2"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Figure 2. Endoreduplication results in 2x DNA content per cycle.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Mary Wildermuth</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Mary&nbsp;C&nbsp;Wildermuth</div> <div class="imageTitle">Figure 2</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/0958100/0958100_10014720_1500510559686_Slide3--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/0958100/0958100_10014720_1500510559686_Slide3--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Figure 3"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/0958100/0958100_10014720_1500510559686_Slide3--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Figure 3"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Powdery mildew proliferation is highly correlated with DNA content of plant cells underlying fungal feeding structure</div> <div class="imageCredit">Mary Wildermuth</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Mary&nbsp;C&nbsp;Wildermuth</div> <div class="imageTitle">Figure 3</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Powdery mildews are fungal plant pathogens that infect a variety of agricultural and ornamental species. Most gardeners have firsthand experience with powdery mildews as a white powder observed on their rose bushes or cucumber plants. Powdery mildews are obligate plant biotrophs meaning they require living plant tissue for their growth, development, and reproduction. In order to obtain host nutrients, they develop a specialized feeding site in an outer epidermal plant cell (Figure 1); all other fungal growth and reproduction occurs on the surface (e.g. of the leaf). Host metabolism is altered to supply the fungus with its requisite nutrients, while limiting defense responses that would incur resistance.     Site-specific analyses determined that the powdery mildew Golovinomyces orontii induces a cell cycle variant called endoreduplication in the plant cells underlying the fungal feeding site (Fig. 1). Induced host endoreduplication is specifically associated with the metabolically demanding process of fungal asexual reproduction (spore production). With each round of endoreduplication, DNA replication occurs but the cells do not divide, resulting in a cell with doubled DNA content (Figure 2). In response to the powdery mildew, DNA content in endoreduplicated plant cells increases ~16-fold. Conserved cell cycle regulators and plant-specific proteins were identified that impact the DNA content of cells underlying the fungal feeding site. And, the extent of fungal reproduction correlates with the DNA content of these plant cells (Figure 3). This shows that induced plant cell endoreduplication acts in a dose-dependent manner to promote fungal reproduction.     Endoreduplication has long been associated with enhanced metabolic capacity and has been associated with cellular nutrient supply (e.g. plant endosperm) and/or differentiation (e.g. plant trichomes). In addition, it is now clear that diverse plant biotrophs have converged on induced host endoreduplication as a mechanism to support their growth and development. These include: powdery mildew, cabbage leaf curl virus, root-cyst and root-knot nematodes, rhizobia, and arbuscular mycorrhizal fungi (Figure 4). In these interactions, induced host endoreduplication is associated with feeding/nutrient exchange site development and access to elevated host resources during metabolically demanding periods of growth or development. When induced endoreduplication is compromised, so too is biotroph growth and/or development.     While increased DNA content itself can result in elevated metabolic capacity, global analysis of plant gene expression data associated with developmental or biotroph-induced endoreduplication identified specific metabolic pathways that are preferentially enhanced in endoreduplicated cells. This includes alternate metabolic pathways previously shown to support increased rates of nutrient and energy molecule synthesis. Disruption of one such pathway results in a dose-dependent decrease in powdery mildew spore production. And, metabolites from this pathway are incorporated into newly formed spores. This provides a specific mechanism by which biotroph-induced plant cell endoreduplication fuels biotroph proliferation.  Potential applications include i) enhancing powdery mildew resistance of crops, ii) increasing production of pharmaceutical and biofuel compounds, and iii) limiting cancer cells that evade treatment (Figure 5). Powdery mildews are widespread pathogens of economically important plants. Repeated chemical treatment of these plants is ubiquitous as estimated yield losses without treatment are &gt;30%. The identification of plant genes that are used by powdery mildews to support their proliferation provides novel targets for plant breeding. Reducing their expression in Arabidopsis or tomato does not reduce plant biomass or visibly alter plant development making them viable commercial targets. In addition, manipulation of plant endoreduplication can be used to enhance yields and traits of products such as maize kernel and tomato fruit that undergo endoreduplication as part of their development. Finally, this knowledge could also enhance bioproduction of plant specialized metabolites including flavors and phytoceuticals by increasing the rate of energy-rich precursor synthesis. Novel regulators of the mitotic cell cycle and endoreduplication were uncovered through this research. As cancer cells that evade treatment often exhibit endoreduplication and many cell cycle components are conserved, our findings could provide novel targets/approaches to limit cancer development and metastasis.  Three postdoctoral scholars, two graduate students, and six undergraduates, including students underrepresented in the sciences, were trained in plant molecular biology and genetics, cell biology, biochemistry, and plant pathology through this interdisciplinary project.  Outreach to students of local public elementary schools enhanced scientific literacy and inquiry using plants and school gardening programs as accessible entry points. Furthermore, development and implementation of a new outreach program called Be A Scientist now has every 7th grader in Berkeley Public Schools (&gt;700 students) working with a UC Berkeley STEM graduate student volunteer to pursue a research question of their own design over the course of six week in-class program. More than 160 UC Berkeley graduate students have participated, allowing individualized attention and support for Berkeley public school students to develop the skills of being a scientist. Evidence-based scientific inquiry is part of the Next Generation Science Standards and an essential skill for our citizenry. This award-winning program can serve as a model for other University-public school STEM partnerships.             Last Modified: 07/19/2017       Submitted by: Mary C Wildermuth]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
