<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Systematic Sampling of  the Gray Fossil Site Vertebrates:  A Unique Mio-Pliocene Fauna from the Southern Appalachians</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>05/01/2010</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>04/30/2016</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>324309.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>342509</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>06030207</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>GEO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>EAR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Earth Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Judith Skog</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Systematic Sampling of the Gray Fossil Site Vertebrates: A Unique Mio-Pliocene Fauna from the Southern Appalachians&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Steven C. Wallace and Blaine Schubert, East Tennesse State University&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;North America experienced dramatic environmental and biotic shifts during the late Miocene.  However, the fossil record of these changes comes almost exclusively from Florida - west to the Gulf Coast - then north through the Great Plains - and eventually to the Northwest, leaving most of eastern North America unrepresented. The late Miocene-early Pliocene Gray Fossil Site (GFS) of eastern Tennessee provides a unique and significant opportunity to further our understanding of the evolution of the North American biota (specifically the southern Appalachians) during this important period. Scientific questions to be addressed include: was there a connection between the forested ecosystems of eastern Asia and those of eastern North America (as indicated by the Asian components of the GFS biota), until at least the late Miocene? If so, how long was this connection present, and what were the dynamics of its breakup? Did the Appalachians act as a forested refugium while the remainder of North America underwent large-scale ecological transition? Moreover, because of its isolation, will the GFS preserve species of mammals which are disjunct from their closest Eurasian relatives (as observed in North American and Asian plant communities)? Lastly, what taphonomic processes resulted in such a dramatic accumulation of fossils in the first place?  This project will undertake systematic excavations of the GFS which will undoubtedly significantly augment the fossil content, species diversity and abundance. The new on site Natural History Museum, supported both by state and local governments is a superb facility for growing the fossil collections, assuring their professional preparation, study and publication.  There has been and will continue to be extensive student training and education on material collected at the Gray Fossil Site.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>04/22/2010</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/02/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.050</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>0958985</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Steven</FirstName>
<LastName>Wallace</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>C</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Steven C Wallace</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>wallaces@etsu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>4234396085</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000293692</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/22/2010</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Blaine</FirstName>
<LastName>Schubert</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Blaine Schubert</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>schubert@etsu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>4234396000</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000409881</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/22/2010</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>East Tennessee State University</Name>
<CityName>Johnson City</CityName>
<ZipCode>376141707</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>4234396000</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>P O Box 70565</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Tennessee</StateName>
<StateCode>TN</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>TN01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>051125037</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>EAST TENNESSEE STATE UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>878135631</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[East Tennessee State University]]></Name>
<CityName>Johnson City</CityName>
<StateCode>TN</StateCode>
<ZipCode>376141707</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[P O Box 70565]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Tennessee</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>TN01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<FoaInformation>
<Code>0000099</Code>
<Name>Other Applications NEC</Name>
</FoaInformation>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7459</Code>
<Text>Sedimentary Geo &amp; Paleobiology</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>0000</Code>
<Text>UNASSIGNED</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9251</Code>
<Text>REU SUPP-Res Exp for Ugrd Supp</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>OTHR</Code>
<Text>OTHER RESEARCH OR EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0110</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0111</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0112</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0114</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2010~90049</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2011~121301</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2012~121159</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~10000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><span>The Gray Fossil Site (GFS) of northeastern Tennessee represents a late Miocene &ndash; early Pliocene fossil locality that is unique and extraordinary.&nbsp; Based on the represented fauna, it dates to approximately 7 &ndash; 4.5 million years old.&nbsp; Millions of years separate the GFS from any other site in the Appalachians. &nbsp;</span></p> <p><span>The GFS was discovered in 2000 during road construction.&nbsp; Overall the site is huge, roughly 5 acres and up to 100 feet deep.&nbsp; Fossils are preserved in dark clay that is rich in plant and animal remains.&nbsp; The deposit formed when a pond developed in a sinkhole. &nbsp;Over time the surrounding limestone walls eroded away leaving behind the internal clay sediments, creating what is known as inverted topography.&nbsp; &nbsp;The site is managed and studied by East Tennessee State University, and a museum is located on site.&nbsp; Initial excavations were funded by a transportation grant.&nbsp;</span></p> <p><span>National Science Foundation support provided funds for excavations of GFS beginning in 2010.&nbsp; From 2010 &ndash; 2015 ETSU paleontologists, students, staff, and volunteers systematically excavated over 250,000 pounds (125 tons) of sediment from GFS.&nbsp; All fossils observed during excavation were mapped using a total station.&nbsp; All GFS excavated sediment is wet-screened and then sorted for microfauna and flora under microscopes in the lab.</span></p> <p><span>Fauna and flora from GFS are indicative of a forested ecosystem, which is incredibly rare for sites of this time in North America (most represent grasslands and are in the western United States).&nbsp; Thus, many of the fossils recovered from GFS represent new species or dramatic geographic or time range extensions.&nbsp; For example, the GFS represents one of two localities in the Americas where fossil red pandas (Ailuridae) have been discovered.&nbsp; The other locality is in Washington State (one tooth).&nbsp; The GFS red panda (<em>Pristinailurus bristoli</em>) is a new genus and species and relatively complete skeletons have been recovered.&nbsp; Red pandas are now restricted to the Himalayan region, and the primary fossil record is in Eurasia.&nbsp; Their presence in the Appalachians reflect a forested biome that once spread from eastern North America up through Canada to Eurasia.&nbsp; Excavations at the GFS continue to produce additional remnants of this ancient forested connection.&nbsp; This includes a new type of badger (<em>Arctomeles dimolodontes</em>), a browsing rhino (<em>Teleoceras</em>), and dwarf tapir (<em>Tapirus polkensis</em>), by far the most common animal of the site (MNI &gt;150).&nbsp; Small forest dwelling mammals are also being discovered, such as shrews and rodents. &nbsp;In addition, a number of forest indicative plant species with Asian affinities have been reported.&nbsp;</span></p> <p><span>Ongoing discoveries at the site support a unique forested ecosystem with a significant Eurasian component.&nbsp; In addition, new fossils and research continues to reinforce and refine the original age assessment.&nbsp; Thus far, the majority of recovered mammals lean towards the younger end of the 7 &ndash; 4.5 million year age bracket.&nbsp; If this is correct there appears to be at least some small mammals that are found at GFS millions of years after they disappeared elsewhere.&nbsp; This supports the hypothesis that the Appalachian Highlands served as a forested refugium during the late Miocene to early Pliocene.&nbsp;</span></p> <p><span>In addition to the mammals, the GFS has produced an extensive reptile, amphibian and fish fauna.&nbsp; While these have been less studied so far, it is clear that the fauna is diverse with some surprises.&nbsp; One example is the venomous beaded lizard&nbsp;<em>Heloderma</em>.&nbsp; Turtles are abundant, especially water turtles such as sliders and painted turtles.&nbsp; A new species of musk turtle (<em>Sternotherus paleodorus</em>) has been reported and others are in the works (e.g., a snapping turtle).&nbsp; Alligator remains are similar to modern <em>Alligator mississippiensis</em>&nbsp;but possess a unique combination of characteristics.&nbsp; Snake fossils are abundant, diverse, and dominated by aquatics.&nbsp; The salamanders are also diverse and some represent the earliest records for their respective groups.&nbsp; Frog remains are dominated by aquatic forms, but one unusual type of &ldquo;spade-foot&rdquo; is now being described.</span></p> <p><span>The GFS continues to provide a unique snapshot of eastern North America at a time that was previously missing from the fossil record.&nbsp; The surprises have been many, and there are surely many more to come as excavations continue.&nbsp; For example, over the past year we discovered our first, second, and third mastodon individuals!&nbsp; One of these is relatively complete and represents an incredibly large mastodon.&nbsp; Mastodons are rare from this time, and the relatively complete specimen from GFS will redefine what we know of their early record in North America.&nbsp; Despite extensive excavations, we have still barely scratched the surface of GFS.&nbsp; In sum, it is clear that the fossil site and museum, located in the southern Appalachians, provides an extraordinary opportunity for students and the general public to see science in action&hellip; to learn about the reality and implications of climate change, extinction, and life through time.&nbsp;</span></p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 10/10/2016<br>      Modified by: Blaine&nbsp;Schubert</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Images (<span id="selectedPhoto0">1</span> of <span class="totalNumber"></span>)           </div> <div class="galControls" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2016/0958985/0958985_10015115_1476107280743_GrayFossilSiteLocation--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2016/0958985/0958985_10015115_1476107280743_GrayFossilSiteLocation--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Location of Gray Fossil Site"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2016/0958985/0958985_10015115_1476107280743_GrayFossilSiteLocation--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Location of Gray Fossil Site"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Location of Gray Fossil Site.  Appalachians region highlighted.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Steven Wallace and Blaine Schubert</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Blaine&nbsp;Schubert</div> <div class="imageTitle">Location of Gray Fossil Site</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2016/0958985/0958985_10015115_1476107999474_GrayFossilSitemappedpoints--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2016/0958985/0958985_10015115_1476107999474_GrayFossilSitemappedpoints--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Gray Fossil Site mapped points"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2016/0958985/0958985_10015115_1476107999474_GrayFossilSitemappedpoints--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Gray Fossil Site mapped points"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Overview of Gray Fossil Site and Museum.  Red dots indicate areas where tapirs have been recovered, and green dots represent other animals.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Image prepared by Brett Woodward</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Blaine&nbsp;Schubert</div> <div class="imageTitle">Gray Fossil Site mapped points</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2016/0958985/0958985_10015115_1476108337158_ExcavationofFossilSite--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2016/0958985/0958985_10015115_1476108337158_ExcavationofFossilSite--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Excavation of Gray Fossil Site"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2016/0958985/0958985_10015115_1476108337158_ExcavationofFossilSite--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Excavation of Gray Fossil Site"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Excavation at the Gray Fossil Site with students.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Steven Wallace and Blaine Schubert</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Blaine&nbsp;Schubert</div> <div class="imageTitle">Excavation of Gray Fossil Site</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2016/0958985/0958985_10015115_1476108570364_GrayFossilSiteredpandaskull--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2016/0958985/0958985_10015115_1476108570364_GrayFossilSiteredpandaskull--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Red panda skull from Gray Fossil Site"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2016/0958985/0958985_10015115_1476108570364_GrayFossilSiteredpandaskull--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Red panda skull from Gray Fossil Site"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">One of two complete red panda skulls found at the Gray Fossil Site</div> <div class="imageCredit">Steven Wallace and Blaine Schubert</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Blaine&nbsp;Schubert</div> <div class="imageTitle">Red panda skull from Gray Fossil Site</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2016/0958985/0958985_10015115_1476108859126_Excavationoftapir--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2016/0958985/0958985_10015115_1476108859126_Excavationoftapir--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Excavation of tapir"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2016/0958985/0958985_10015115_1476108859126_Excavationoftapir--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Excavation of tapir"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Excavation of tapir remains at the Gray Fossil Site.  Note the articulated nature of the skeleton.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Steven Wallace and Blaine Schubert</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Blaine&nbsp;Schubert</div> <div class="imageTitle">Excavation of tapir</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2016/0958985/0958985_10015115_1476109439411_GrayFossilSiteexhibit--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2016/0958985/0958985_10015115_1476109439411_GrayFossilSiteexhibit--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Gray Fossil Site exhibit"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2016/0958985/0958985_10015115_1476109439411_GrayFossilSiteexhibit--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Gray Fossil Site exhibit"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Many animals at the Gray Fossil Site are represented by complete skeletons. The rhino and tapir shown here are examples.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Steven Wallace and Blaine Schubert</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Blaine&nbsp;Schubert</div> <div class="imageTitle">Gray Fossil Site exhibit</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The Gray Fossil Site (GFS) of northeastern Tennessee represents a late Miocene &ndash; early Pliocene fossil locality that is unique and extraordinary.  Based on the represented fauna, it dates to approximately 7 &ndash; 4.5 million years old.  Millions of years separate the GFS from any other site in the Appalachians.    The GFS was discovered in 2000 during road construction.  Overall the site is huge, roughly 5 acres and up to 100 feet deep.  Fossils are preserved in dark clay that is rich in plant and animal remains.  The deposit formed when a pond developed in a sinkhole.  Over time the surrounding limestone walls eroded away leaving behind the internal clay sediments, creating what is known as inverted topography.   The site is managed and studied by East Tennessee State University, and a museum is located on site.  Initial excavations were funded by a transportation grant.   National Science Foundation support provided funds for excavations of GFS beginning in 2010.  From 2010 &ndash; 2015 ETSU paleontologists, students, staff, and volunteers systematically excavated over 250,000 pounds (125 tons) of sediment from GFS.  All fossils observed during excavation were mapped using a total station.  All GFS excavated sediment is wet-screened and then sorted for microfauna and flora under microscopes in the lab.  Fauna and flora from GFS are indicative of a forested ecosystem, which is incredibly rare for sites of this time in North America (most represent grasslands and are in the western United States).  Thus, many of the fossils recovered from GFS represent new species or dramatic geographic or time range extensions.  For example, the GFS represents one of two localities in the Americas where fossil red pandas (Ailuridae) have been discovered.  The other locality is in Washington State (one tooth).  The GFS red panda (Pristinailurus bristoli) is a new genus and species and relatively complete skeletons have been recovered.  Red pandas are now restricted to the Himalayan region, and the primary fossil record is in Eurasia.  Their presence in the Appalachians reflect a forested biome that once spread from eastern North America up through Canada to Eurasia.  Excavations at the GFS continue to produce additional remnants of this ancient forested connection.  This includes a new type of badger (Arctomeles dimolodontes), a browsing rhino (Teleoceras), and dwarf tapir (Tapirus polkensis), by far the most common animal of the site (MNI &gt;150).  Small forest dwelling mammals are also being discovered, such as shrews and rodents.  In addition, a number of forest indicative plant species with Asian affinities have been reported.   Ongoing discoveries at the site support a unique forested ecosystem with a significant Eurasian component.  In addition, new fossils and research continues to reinforce and refine the original age assessment.  Thus far, the majority of recovered mammals lean towards the younger end of the 7 &ndash; 4.5 million year age bracket.  If this is correct there appears to be at least some small mammals that are found at GFS millions of years after they disappeared elsewhere.  This supports the hypothesis that the Appalachian Highlands served as a forested refugium during the late Miocene to early Pliocene.   In addition to the mammals, the GFS has produced an extensive reptile, amphibian and fish fauna.  While these have been less studied so far, it is clear that the fauna is diverse with some surprises.  One example is the venomous beaded lizard Heloderma.  Turtles are abundant, especially water turtles such as sliders and painted turtles.  A new species of musk turtle (Sternotherus paleodorus) has been reported and others are in the works (e.g., a snapping turtle).  Alligator remains are similar to modern Alligator mississippiensis but possess a unique combination of characteristics.  Snake fossils are abundant, diverse, and dominated by aquatics.  The salamanders are also diverse and some represent the earliest records for their respective groups.  Frog remains are dominated by aquatic forms, but one unusual type of "spade-foot" is now being described.  The GFS continues to provide a unique snapshot of eastern North America at a time that was previously missing from the fossil record.  The surprises have been many, and there are surely many more to come as excavations continue.  For example, over the past year we discovered our first, second, and third mastodon individuals!  One of these is relatively complete and represents an incredibly large mastodon.  Mastodons are rare from this time, and the relatively complete specimen from GFS will redefine what we know of their early record in North America.  Despite extensive excavations, we have still barely scratched the surface of GFS.  In sum, it is clear that the fossil site and museum, located in the southern Appalachians, provides an extraordinary opportunity for students and the general public to see science in action&hellip; to learn about the reality and implications of climate change, extinction, and life through time.           Last Modified: 10/10/2016       Submitted by: Blaine Schubert]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
