<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>MRI-R2: Development of a Precise and High Speed Hydrostatic Dynamometer System for Research and Education in Automotive Propulsion Systems</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>01/15/2010</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2011</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>807720.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>807720</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CMMI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Civil, Mechanical, &amp; Manufact Inn</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Christina L. Bloebaum</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This award is funded under the American Recovery and Reinvestment Act of 2009 (Public Law 111-5).&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The objective of this Major Research Instrumentation (MRI-R2) award is to develop a state-of-the-art, precise and highly flexible instrument for testing and measuring the fuel efficiency, emissions and performance of automotive propulsion systems. The centerpiece of the instrument is a precise and high-speed hydrostatic dynamometer, which absorbs (or provides) torques from (or to) the engine/powertrain so that the engine or powertrain can follow any desired rotational speed and acceleration profile. The hydrostatic dynamometer is utilized to experimentally mimic the drive train, vehicle load, and the alternative power sources in coordination with an engine control system and a hardware-in-the-loop vehicle driveline emulator. This instrument will allow all aspects of the vehicle propulsion system such as the engine, transmission, hybrid power sources, energy storage systems, emission control systems and driveline system to be tested or simulated in a real-world driving scenario without actually building the complete physical system.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;As a shared research infrastructure, the instrument will encourage the interaction and research collaboration of users from multiple departments at the University of Minnesota. Furthermore, it will help to prepare the next generation instrumentalists, researchers and engineers to design and build clean and efficient automotive propulsion systems. The developed instrument will also be integrated into core mechanical engineering curriculum for both undergraduate and graduate education. It will also enhance collaborations with industrial partners and help to disseminate research results to communities at large.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>01/14/2010</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>01/14/2010</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount>807720</ARRAAmount>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>0959741</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Kim</FirstName>
<LastName>Stelson</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>A</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Kim A Stelson</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>kstelson@me.umn.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6126256528</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000224875</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>01/14/2010</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>David</FirstName>
<LastName>Kittelson</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>B</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>David B Kittelson</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>kitte001@umn.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6126251808</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000381200</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>01/14/2010</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Zongxuan</FirstName>
<LastName>Sun</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Zongxuan Sun</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>zsun@umn.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6126252107</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000508946</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>01/14/2010</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Minnesota-Twin Cities</Name>
<CityName>Minneapolis</CityName>
<ZipCode>554552070</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6126245599</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>200 OAK ST SE</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Minnesota</StateName>
<StateCode>MN</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MN05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>555917996</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>REGENTS OF THE UNIVERSITY OF MINNESOTA</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>117178941</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Minnesota-Twin Cities]]></Name>
<CityName>Minneapolis</CityName>
<StateCode>MN</StateCode>
<ZipCode>554552070</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[200 OAK ST SE]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Minnesota</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MN05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1189</Code>
<Text>Major Research Instrumentation</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>6890</Code>
<Text>RECOVERY ACT ACTION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7217</Code>
<Text>RESEARCH INFRASTRUCTURE IMPROV</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7619</Code>
<Text>EQUIPMENT ACQUISITIONS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>01R9</Code>
<Name>RRA RECOVERY ACT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040101</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2010~807720</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>This Major Research Instrumentation grant allows us to develop a state-of-the-art, precise and highly flexible instrument for testing and measuring the fuel efficiency, emissions and performance of automotive propulsion systems, especially the hybrid powertrain. The instrument employs a hydrostatic dynamometer to load or motor the engine/powertrain to experimentally mimic the hybrid architecture, vehicle load, and the hybrid power sources in coordination with an engine control system and a hardware-in-the-loop vehicle driveline emulator. The hydraulic components, transient fuel and emissions measurement instruments, and control hardware and software have been acquired and integrated into the system. Models of the hybrid powertrain and controllers for the hydrostatic dynamometer as well as the hybrid energy management have been designed and implemented. System integration and testing demonstrate the expected performance and functionality of the developed instrument.</p> <p>This instrument has already become a critical part of our research on hybrid powertrains. It enables the evaluation of various hybrid architectures, controls, and after-treatment systems in real-world driving scenarios without actually building the complete physical system. It has offered insights of the hybrid powertrain dynamics that couldn&rsquo;t be obtained from simulations. In the future this instrument will help to further the collaborations among researchers from different fields, between academia and industry, as well as broaden the applications to other hybrid mobile applications beyond automobiles. This project has provided training opportunities for graduate and undergraduate students to develop state-of-the-art instruments. The instrument has also been used for both undergraduate and graduate classes. It was also showcased to the general public during several outreach activities.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 02/02/2012<br>      Modified by: Zongxuan&nbsp;Sun</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ This Major Research Instrumentation grant allows us to develop a state-of-the-art, precise and highly flexible instrument for testing and measuring the fuel efficiency, emissions and performance of automotive propulsion systems, especially the hybrid powertrain. The instrument employs a hydrostatic dynamometer to load or motor the engine/powertrain to experimentally mimic the hybrid architecture, vehicle load, and the hybrid power sources in coordination with an engine control system and a hardware-in-the-loop vehicle driveline emulator. The hydraulic components, transient fuel and emissions measurement instruments, and control hardware and software have been acquired and integrated into the system. Models of the hybrid powertrain and controllers for the hydrostatic dynamometer as well as the hybrid energy management have been designed and implemented. System integration and testing demonstrate the expected performance and functionality of the developed instrument.  This instrument has already become a critical part of our research on hybrid powertrains. It enables the evaluation of various hybrid architectures, controls, and after-treatment systems in real-world driving scenarios without actually building the complete physical system. It has offered insights of the hybrid powertrain dynamics that couldnÆt be obtained from simulations. In the future this instrument will help to further the collaborations among researchers from different fields, between academia and industry, as well as broaden the applications to other hybrid mobile applications beyond automobiles. This project has provided training opportunities for graduate and undergraduate students to develop state-of-the-art instruments. The instrument has also been used for both undergraduate and graduate classes. It was also showcased to the general public during several outreach activities.       Last Modified: 02/02/2012       Submitted by: Zongxuan Sun]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
