<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>MRI-R2: Development of Hyperspectral Optical Property Instrumentation (HOPI) for Biomedical and Environmental Research</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>03/01/2010</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>09/30/2013</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>524171.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>524171</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07020000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CBET</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Chem, Bioeng, Env, &amp; Transp Sys</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Leon Esterowitz</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>lesterow@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927942</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>0960000&lt;br/&gt;Mehrubeoglu&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;"This award is funded under the American Recovery and Reinvestment Act of 2009 (Public Law 111-5)."&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The overall goal of this project is to develop and test a novel two-module major research instrument for measurement of hyperspectral absorption and scattering properties of highly scattering materials. The instrument will enhance instrumentation and research capabilities useable by multiple programs and interdisciplinary researchers at Texas A&amp;M University-Corpus Christi. The following is a list of immediate projects that will utilize the instrument: 1) Optical Properties of Reef Inhabitants for Determination of Bleaching Resistance in Coral Species; 2) Correlation of satellite data and optical properties of coral reefs to determine global environmental effects on coral decline; 3) Determination of optical properties of breast cancer cells following treatment with mammalian cardenolides; 4) Comparison of optical properties of cancerous cell lines and perturbations; 5) Optical properties of nanoparticles, and correlation to size and concentration: basic research to determine biomedical and environmental impacts; 6) Hyperspectral investigation of optical properties of materials (1D) and structures (2D); and 7) Research Training of underrepresented groups.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>01/20/2010</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>03/25/2010</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount>524171</ARRAAmount>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>0960000</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Mirley</FirstName>
<LastName>Balasubramanya</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>K</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Mirley K Balasubramanya</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>mbalasub@tamus.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2107842224</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000388074</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>01/20/2010</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Lillian</FirstName>
<LastName>Waldbeser</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>S</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Lillian S Waldbeser</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>waldbese@falcon.tamucc.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>3618256050</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000474643</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>03/25/2010</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Kevin</FirstName>
<LastName>Strychar</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>B</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Kevin B Strychar</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>strychak@gvsu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6163318796</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000114313</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>01/20/2010</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Mehrube</FirstName>
<LastName>Mehrubeoglu</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Mehrube Mehrubeoglu</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>Ruby.Mehrubeoglu@tamucc.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>3618253378</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000492979</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>01/20/2010</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Kenneth</FirstName>
<LastName>Ihenetu</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>U</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Kenneth U Ihenetu</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>Kenneth.Ihenetu@tamucc.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>3618252177</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000311104</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>01/20/2010</StartDate>
<EndDate>03/25/2010</EndDate>
<RoleCode>Former Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Texas A&amp;M University Corpus Christi</Name>
<CityName>Corpus Christi</CityName>
<ZipCode>784125844</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>3618252730</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>6300 Ocean Dr.</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[Unit 5844]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Texas</StateName>
<StateCode>TX</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>27</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>TX27</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>095100152</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>TEXAS A&amp;M UNIVERSITY-CORPUS CHRISTI</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>042915991</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Texas A&amp;M University Corpus Christi]]></Name>
<CityName>Corpus Christi</CityName>
<StateCode>TX</StateCode>
<ZipCode>784125844</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[6300 Ocean Dr.]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Texas</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>27</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>TX27</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1189</Code>
<Text>Major Research Instrumentation</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>005E</Code>
<Text>Neuro-photonics</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>6890</Code>
<Text>RECOVERY ACT ACTION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9102</Code>
<Text>WOMEN, MINORITY, DISABLED, NEC</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>01R9</Code>
<Name>RRA RECOVERY ACT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040101</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2010~524171</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The following include the outcomes of the project:</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>1. Instrumentation:</p> <p>1.1&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; A double-integrating sphere system was assembled and built to measure scattering and transmittance properties of thin samples. A software interface was developed to store the signal values and view plots real-time.</p> <p>1.2&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; A hyperspectral imaging system with a hyperspectral camera was purchased and new capabilities added to acquire transmittance and reflectance mode measurements with the flip of a switch without altering the system or its configuration. This capability allows the same region of the test sample to be imaged both in transmittance and reflectance mode repeatedly. A semi-auto-focusing capability using a computer controlled application has been added to the system. This capability significantly reduces the time for optical focusing and alignment. The system is able to collect hyperspectral image cubes at macro levels. In addition, a supplemental microsystem allows the performance of cellular-level and other microscopic hyperspectral investigations. A supercontinuum laser has been added as an alternate light source to the broadband light to allow modeling experiments and broader wavelength capabilities for experiments in smaller areas.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>2. Research:</p> <p>Multiple research projects in multiple fields were enabled through the HOPI Project through collaborative efforts with multidisciplinary faculty and student mentees:</p> <p>1)&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; Hyperspectral imaging of coral state and water quality (marine biology, engineering, computer science)</p> <p>2)&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; Detecting structural changes in cell cultures (biomedical science, engineering, computer science)</p> <p>3)&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; Hyperspectral bulk properties of gold-metal nanoparticles&nbsp;(chemistry, physics, engineering, computer science)</p> <p>4)&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; Resolving algal species in algal mixtures (environmental sciences, engineering, computer science)</p> <p>5)&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; Hyperspectral investigation of bacterial colonies (biology, microbiology, engineering)</p> <p>6)&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; Investigation of mud samples for organismal mapping (environmental science, engineering)</p> <p>7)&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; Spectral and spatial investigation of seagrasses for water quality assessment (biology, coastal studies)</p> <p>8)&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; Remote real-time hyperspectral data viewing and modeling (computer science, engineering)</p> <p>9)&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; Data Management and User Authentication for the Remote HOPI System (computer science, engineering)</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>3. Outreach</p> <p>The project has provided many undergraduate and graduate students research, training and mentoring opportunities. Students have been trained to utilize the HOPI system for data acquisition, and have been exposed to novel data analysis tools. Students have utilized the technology for both undergraduate and graduate research projects with outcomes resulting in publications and presentations. The project has also enabled multiple faculty collaborations in multiple disciplines. Outreach activities have included research mentoring of a high-school student, and technology introduction in an elementary school during E-Week. Tours of the HOPI lab have been provided to multiple groups, including prospective students and their parents, high-school students, and other members of the public and visitors. One postdoctoral&nbsp;researcher was interested and engaged in a hyperspectral image processing project in the HOPI Lab&nbsp;and was trained on multidimensional image processing techniques.</p> <p>3.1&nbsp; Mentoring</p> <p>A total of 19 undergraduate students were mentored in research projects or t...]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The following include the outcomes of the project:     1. Instrumentation:  1.1       A double-integrating sphere system was assembled and built to measure scattering and transmittance properties of thin samples. A software interface was developed to store the signal values and view plots real-time.  1.2       A hyperspectral imaging system with a hyperspectral camera was purchased and new capabilities added to acquire transmittance and reflectance mode measurements with the flip of a switch without altering the system or its configuration. This capability allows the same region of the test sample to be imaged both in transmittance and reflectance mode repeatedly. A semi-auto-focusing capability using a computer controlled application has been added to the system. This capability significantly reduces the time for optical focusing and alignment. The system is able to collect hyperspectral image cubes at macro levels. In addition, a supplemental microsystem allows the performance of cellular-level and other microscopic hyperspectral investigations. A supercontinuum laser has been added as an alternate light source to the broadband light to allow modeling experiments and broader wavelength capabilities for experiments in smaller areas.     2. Research:  Multiple research projects in multiple fields were enabled through the HOPI Project through collaborative efforts with multidisciplinary faculty and student mentees:  1)      Hyperspectral imaging of coral state and water quality (marine biology, engineering, computer science)  2)      Detecting structural changes in cell cultures (biomedical science, engineering, computer science)  3)      Hyperspectral bulk properties of gold-metal nanoparticles (chemistry, physics, engineering, computer science)  4)      Resolving algal species in algal mixtures (environmental sciences, engineering, computer science)  5)      Hyperspectral investigation of bacterial colonies (biology, microbiology, engineering)  6)      Investigation of mud samples for organismal mapping (environmental science, engineering)  7)      Spectral and spatial investigation of seagrasses for water quality assessment (biology, coastal studies)  8)      Remote real-time hyperspectral data viewing and modeling (computer science, engineering)  9)      Data Management and User Authentication for the Remote HOPI System (computer science, engineering)     3. Outreach  The project has provided many undergraduate and graduate students research, training and mentoring opportunities. Students have been trained to utilize the HOPI system for data acquisition, and have been exposed to novel data analysis tools. Students have utilized the technology for both undergraduate and graduate research projects with outcomes resulting in publications and presentations. The project has also enabled multiple faculty collaborations in multiple disciplines. Outreach activities have included research mentoring of a high-school student, and technology introduction in an elementary school during E-Week. Tours of the HOPI lab have been provided to multiple groups, including prospective students and their parents, high-school students, and other members of the public and visitors. One postdoctoral researcher was interested and engaged in a hyperspectral image processing project in the HOPI Lab and was trained on multidimensional image processing techniques.  3.1  Mentoring  A total of 19 undergraduate students were mentored in research projects or through training. The diversity included 4 male Hispanic and 2 female Hispanic, 3 female (not Hispanic), 3 Asian, 2 low-income/first generation college students, 1 low-income (other than first generation), 2 male (other), 1 African American, and 1 Pacific Islander. The students ranged from biology, biomedical science, electrical engineering technology, mechanical engineering to computer science.  The HOPI Project enabled direct mentoring of a total of 14 graduate students in the HOPI Lab. The diversity o...]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
