<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Mobile Money, Mobile Regulation: What the "Savings Challenge" Means for Mobile Communications and Banking</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>06/01/2010</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2014</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>218685.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>218685</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>04050000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>SBE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>SES</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Divn Of Social and Economic Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>susan sterett</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Mobile Money, Mobile Regulation: What the "Savings Challenge" Means for Mobile Communications and Banking&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Abstract&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;In Kenya, over 6 million people subscribe to a service called M-PESA to send money to their friends and relatives cheaply and securely over their mobile phones. In the Philippines, people can remit money to family members on remote islands through a similar service called Globe GCASH, now used by 2 million people. Around the world, mobile phone-enabled money services like these are taking off. Given the rapidity of its emergence, "mobile money" is often being deployed in advance of regulatory guidelines. When telecommunications companies get into the business of money transfer and banking, there is the potential for a clash of cultures as well as risks to consumers, banks and the financial system itself. Who holds the deposits, and what do they do with them while they sit in people's accounts? If you lose your phone, do your savings go with it? &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project relies on interviews with regulatory and industry participants; archival data collection and analysis; and ethnography in industry and regulatory sites to understand the debates and knowledge transfers around emerging regulations for mobile money. It asks where regulatory innovations come from; how regulators triangulate among industry and nonprofit actors; whether regulatory knowledge transfers between developing world countries have become more important than from the developed to the developing world; and whether the regulation of mobile money can be seen as an instance of regulatory convergence or capture. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The research will enhance understanding of regulatory change under conditions of rapid technological and economic transformation. It has the potential to influence regulatory frameworks for mobile money. It will also contribute to refocusing development strategies from microfinance to microsavings. If various regulatory barriers can be overcome in a prudent manner that attends to risk, security and consumer protection, then mobile money for savings has the potential to transform the lives of the very poor, for whom the entry barriers and costs of savings are too high.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>01/22/2010</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>01/22/2010</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.075</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>0960423</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>William</FirstName>
<LastName>Maurer</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>M</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>William M Maurer</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>wmmaurer@uci.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>9498241415</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000180171</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>01/22/2010</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of California-Irvine</Name>
<CityName>Irvine</CityName>
<ZipCode>926977600</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>9498247295</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>160 Aldrich Hall</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>45</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CA45</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>046705849</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF CALIFORNIA, IRVINE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>071549000</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of California-Irvine]]></Name>
<CityName>Irvine</CityName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>926977600</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[160 Aldrich Hall]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>45</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CA45</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<FoaInformation>
<Code>0116000</Code>
<Name>Human Subjects</Name>
</FoaInformation>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1372</Code>
<Text>LSS-Law And Social Sciences</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>0000</Code>
<Text>UNASSIGNED</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>OTHR</Code>
<Text>OTHER RESEARCH OR EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0110</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2010~218685</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>We pay for things every day, but rarely spend much time thinking about what happens whenever we swipe our debit card at the grocery store, or when our paycheck gets deposited into our account. This project explored the regulatory and industry debate over a new means of payment&mdash;mobile phone-enabled money transfer and savings services. Dubbed &ldquo;mobile money,&rdquo; such services have taken off in Kenya and are gathering steam in other parts of the developing world. Mobile money in the developing world also inspired new payment services in the US. Over the past few years scores of new services have been launched (Square, LevelUp), as have partnerships between existing services (MCX) and heightened interest in new payment technologies that blur the line between money itself and payment infrastructure (Bitcoin).</p> <p>This project was motivated by the potential for electronic payment systems, using mobile devices and networks, to contribute to poverty alleviation. It focused on the legal conundrums that new digital systems for payment posed. When funds are in a mobile money service, what is their legal status? Are they "savings" if they sit in an account for more than a day? two days? a month? So-called &ldquo;mobile money&rdquo; services attracted wide media and philanthropic attention with Safaricom&rsquo;s M-Pesa. This service allowed people using basic mobile phones to send money to each other via text messages. In the space of seven years since its launch in 2007, M-Pesa attracted over 17 million customers, in a country of 43 million people&mdash;40% of all Kenyans are active subscribers. By 2010, more Kenyans subscribed to M-Pesa than had a bank account. Hence, development practitioners&rsquo; hope that services like M-Pesa can become a route to financial inclusion for people without access or the means to afford bank accounts.</p> <p>This project studied regulators and industry participants in the mobile money revolution. It also contributed to the regulatory discussion of such systems. Its focus on the regulation of mobile money spotlighted several key issues:</p> <p>1) consumer protection;</p> <p>2) the nature of payments infrastructures as a public good (on which, a&nbsp;<a href="http://siteresources.worldbank.org/EXTINFORMATIONANDCOMMUNICATIONANDTECHNOLOGIES/Resources/IC4D-2012-Chapter-4.pdf">World Bank</a>&nbsp;report cites work completed under this grant);</p> <p>3) the conceptual difficulty of distinguishing money's store of value function from its means of exchange function in prepaid services like most mobile payment products. When mobile money services allow people to store money, they start to look like banks. This poses safety and soundness issues, as well as the potential for money laundering, since mobile operators have not faced the same kind of regulatory scrutiny as banks.</p> <p>The research to date indicates that mobile money services do have the potential to incorporate more people into formal financial arrangements&mdash;thus mitigating risk of theft, crime, bribery, loss, and so forth that often accompany cash transactions &ndash;yet that the social element is crucial to the success to such services. &nbsp;Part of the social element includes regulators&rsquo; understandings of how these services work, legal definitions of money, and regulators' own &ldquo;folk&rdquo; understanding of what money is and how it functions, which impacts their professional judgment.</p> <p>The project contributes to sociolegal studies and the anthropology of law on the motivating factors for regulatory change in rapidly evolving technological contexts, as well as the social study of science. The rapid rise of mobile phone-enabled financial and money transfer services is fundamentally changing access to financial services, and reopening questions over the meaning and nature of money itself. The project contributes to the anthropology of money, and is h...]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ We pay for things every day, but rarely spend much time thinking about what happens whenever we swipe our debit card at the grocery store, or when our paycheck gets deposited into our account. This project explored the regulatory and industry debate over a new means of payment&mdash;mobile phone-enabled money transfer and savings services. Dubbed "mobile money," such services have taken off in Kenya and are gathering steam in other parts of the developing world. Mobile money in the developing world also inspired new payment services in the US. Over the past few years scores of new services have been launched (Square, LevelUp), as have partnerships between existing services (MCX) and heightened interest in new payment technologies that blur the line between money itself and payment infrastructure (Bitcoin).  This project was motivated by the potential for electronic payment systems, using mobile devices and networks, to contribute to poverty alleviation. It focused on the legal conundrums that new digital systems for payment posed. When funds are in a mobile money service, what is their legal status? Are they "savings" if they sit in an account for more than a day? two days? a month? So-called "mobile money" services attracted wide media and philanthropic attention with SafaricomÆs M-Pesa. This service allowed people using basic mobile phones to send money to each other via text messages. In the space of seven years since its launch in 2007, M-Pesa attracted over 17 million customers, in a country of 43 million people&mdash;40% of all Kenyans are active subscribers. By 2010, more Kenyans subscribed to M-Pesa than had a bank account. Hence, development practitionersÆ hope that services like M-Pesa can become a route to financial inclusion for people without access or the means to afford bank accounts.  This project studied regulators and industry participants in the mobile money revolution. It also contributed to the regulatory discussion of such systems. Its focus on the regulation of mobile money spotlighted several key issues:  1) consumer protection;  2) the nature of payments infrastructures as a public good (on which, a World Bank report cites work completed under this grant);  3) the conceptual difficulty of distinguishing money's store of value function from its means of exchange function in prepaid services like most mobile payment products. When mobile money services allow people to store money, they start to look like banks. This poses safety and soundness issues, as well as the potential for money laundering, since mobile operators have not faced the same kind of regulatory scrutiny as banks.  The research to date indicates that mobile money services do have the potential to incorporate more people into formal financial arrangements&mdash;thus mitigating risk of theft, crime, bribery, loss, and so forth that often accompany cash transactions &ndash;yet that the social element is crucial to the success to such services.  Part of the social element includes regulatorsÆ understandings of how these services work, legal definitions of money, and regulators' own "folk" understanding of what money is and how it functions, which impacts their professional judgment.  The project contributes to sociolegal studies and the anthropology of law on the motivating factors for regulatory change in rapidly evolving technological contexts, as well as the social study of science. The rapid rise of mobile phone-enabled financial and money transfer services is fundamentally changing access to financial services, and reopening questions over the meaning and nature of money itself. The project contributes to the anthropology of money, and is helping to bring to scholarly attention the payments industry &ndash;the collection of public and private infrastructures for the movement of money &ndash;at a time when that industry is undergoing a profound shift. The shift is caused by both the rise of mobile computing, the decline of revenue from f...]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
