<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Collaborative Research:  Benthic Exhange Events and Near-Boundary Mixing on the Continental Shelf</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2010</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2015</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>489328.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>489328</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>06040300</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>GEO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>OCE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Ocean Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Eric C. Itsweire</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>An innovative field study examining the dynamics of boundary-interior exchange events on the Monterey Bay shelf  will be conducted in Monterey Bay. The main focus is on boundary layer intrusions, often seen in the form of intermediate nepheloid layers (INLs) detaching from the continental margin. The objectives of the project are to (1) identify processes responsible for resuspension of benthic material on the mid- to outer-shelf, (2) improve our understanding of intrusion formation mechanisms, (3) investigate the fate of material transported in intrusions, and (4) investigate event-scale and seasonal variability in intrusion dynamics. The driving hypothesis is that gravitational collapse after internal-wave-forced mixing drives intrusions; however, the experiment is designed to resolve benthic exchange generally, including advective mechanisms such as eddies, shelf currents, or convergent bottom Ekman fluxes.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Measurements will include a central benthic station, an offshore moored profiler station and cross-shelf autonomous underwater vehicle (AUV) surveys spanning the fixed stations. The observational strategy is to directly observe benthic exchange: from the seafloor interface through the stratified outer boundary layer, across the entire water column, and then into the cross-shelf dimension. New "hybrid" turbulence packages designed to measure turbulence via both scalar dissipation and eddy correlation techniques will be deployed on each of the measurement platforms. High-resolution boundary layer measurements, including bottom shear stress, turbulent dissipation rate, suspended particulates, and erosion events, will be made from a benthic tripod and mooring. Offshore of this platform, a moored profiler will continuously measure, over the entire water column, CTD, optics, and turbulence. Both fixed stations will include full-water-column velocity profiles, from which we will quantify internal wave energy density flux and estimate lateral transport of intrusions/INLs. A long-ranging AUV, newly developed by PI Bellingham, will map both turbulence and intrusions in cross-shelf sections, resolving diapycnal and isopycnal transport processes. Two deployments, one in the late spring upwelling season and the other during stratified fall conditions, will provide unprecedented temporal coverage of full-water-column mixing, internal wave energy, benthic response, and INLs at both event and seasonal scales. The fixed instrumentation will be deployed for one-month-long periods during which the AUV will operate continuously for two weeks.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Intellectual Merit. Fundamental questions about the dynamics of boundary-interior exchange motivate this project. On deeper continental slopes this process has important consequences for global abyssal mixing. On continental shelves, particularly those of eastern boundary upwelling coasts, benthic exchange plays a crucial role in ecosystem functioning by providing benthic iron (a limiting micronutrient) and, potentially, benthic resting cysts to the interior and upper water column. Benthic exchange events may explain some of the paradoxical decoupling between upwelling and coastal blooms at the event level. Intrusions/INLs are commonly observed, yet very little is known about their temporal variability, dispersal rates and duration, or forcing. There is ample evidence for an association between INLs and internal wave interaction with topography. Yet, to date there has been no study directly testing the relationship between mixing and boundary intrusion dispersal on a continental margin. This study is focused on the shelf but the findings will be transferrable to deeper continental margins. Better understanding of these dynamics may improve parameterization of boundary mixing in global circulation models.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Broader Impacts. A valuable, innovative technique that will be developed as part of this collaborative work is the incorporation of turbulence instrumentation into the payload of the Monterey Bay Research Institute (MBARI) long-range Autonomous Underwater Vehicle (AUV). The transfer of this technology to a cutting-edge, and routinely operated, AUV system means it will be used in years to come in investigations of fine-resolution fluxes and transports of coastal biological systems. Un-funded collaborator John Ryan will investigate potential links to surface blooms. The project will include training and mentoring of a postdoctoral researcher and two graduate students, and the research findings will be incorporated into the graduate curricula at Moss Landing Marine Laboratory (MLML) and the Naval Postgraduate School. Public outreach and education will benefit from the established MLML Teacher Enhancement Program and MBARI's summer internship program.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/19/2010</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/19/2010</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.050</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>0961810</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Erika</FirstName>
<LastName>McPhee-Shaw</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Erika McPhee-Shaw</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>erika.mcphee-shaw@wwu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>3606503713</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000433531</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/19/2010</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>San Jose State University Foundation</Name>
<CityName>San Jose</CityName>
<ZipCode>951125569</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>4089241400</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>210 North Fourth Street</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>19</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CA19</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>056820715</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>SAN JOSE STATE UNIVERSITY RESEARCH FOUNDATION</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>056820715</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[San Jose State University]]></Name>
<CityName>san jose</CityName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>951920139</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[Washington Square]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>19</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CA19</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1610</Code>
<Text>PHYSICAL OCEANOGRAPHY</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0110</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2010~489328</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>This project combined asking some fundamental questions in physical oceanography (the study of circulation and the physics of water waves at many scales) with fundamental questions in marine geology and geomorphology. &nbsp;In this context, the geological questions were about the forcing for the basic shape of our planet&rsquo;s continental margins. What moves fine mud and sediment into the ubiquitous &ldquo;mud belts&rdquo; found throughout the continental shelves of our planet, mud that helps support the primary producers of coastal ecosystems with its high concentration of bioavailable iron and other important constituents?</p> <p>We found that <strong>internal waves</strong> (<em>subsurface</em> gravity waves supported by the ocean&rsquo;s thermal stratification) were important, and until now relatively ignored, players in this sediment transport mystery. On a continental shelf where the water depth scales as about 100 m, some of the most energetic forms of internal waves have scales as high as about 30 m, or 1/3 of the entire water column. In other words, during the passage of one of these waves, a density surface starting at 50m typically might ascend to 20 m depth over an interval of six hours. We found that the onshore-directed currents associated with such waves were a dominant form of motion by which sediment was pushed onshore in sequential, almost daily, pulses where the sediment would drift onshore while also gradually settling back down to the seafloor. This wave-driven process seems to be important in building up the mud belt feature local to the site of our study, the Monterey Bay shelf of the Central California continental margin, but the finding has implications for many other continental margins as well.</p> <p>But what got sediment from the seafloor up into mid-depth waters in the first place? One of our most exciting discoveries was the finding of occasional episodes of very abrupt, rapidly ascending density surfaces associated with a form of internal wave called a nonlinear wave, or internal hydraulic jump. Such waves are found in the natural environment in other, more easily visible phenomena. Examples include hydraulic jumps formed in rivers when the stream surface piles up behind a boulder and then abruptly drops. Dramatic internal-wave-type hydraulic jumps form in the atmosphere in the lee of mountain ranges and have been observed, for example, on the eastern slopes of the Sierras where intense down-drafting winds then updraft to bring topsoil and dust high up into the air, and are of intense interest to glider pilots. In our study we observed an undersea version of similar updrafts over the outer shelf. These updrafts lifted sediments off the seafloor up into the middle of the water column within just a few minutes. Remembering that water being 1000 times denser than air means that almost all circulation and wave phenomena are a bit more &ldquo;sluggish&rdquo; in the ocean than they are in the atmosphere, this is very rapid movement for ocean waters! Finding such abrupt wave events responsible for delivering and moving sediment on continental margins was a new discovery linking the sciences of wave physics and marine geology in a fundamentally new and exciting way.&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 10/30/2015<br>      Modified by: Erika&nbsp;Mcphee-Shaw</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Image         </div> <div class="galControls onePhoto" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation onePhoto" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2015/0961810/0961810_10018713_1446228038118_HydraulicJumpFigure--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/imag...]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ This project combined asking some fundamental questions in physical oceanography (the study of circulation and the physics of water waves at many scales) with fundamental questions in marine geology and geomorphology.  In this context, the geological questions were about the forcing for the basic shape of our planetÆs continental margins. What moves fine mud and sediment into the ubiquitous "mud belts" found throughout the continental shelves of our planet, mud that helps support the primary producers of coastal ecosystems with its high concentration of bioavailable iron and other important constituents?  We found that internal waves (subsurface gravity waves supported by the oceanÆs thermal stratification) were important, and until now relatively ignored, players in this sediment transport mystery. On a continental shelf where the water depth scales as about 100 m, some of the most energetic forms of internal waves have scales as high as about 30 m, or 1/3 of the entire water column. In other words, during the passage of one of these waves, a density surface starting at 50m typically might ascend to 20 m depth over an interval of six hours. We found that the onshore-directed currents associated with such waves were a dominant form of motion by which sediment was pushed onshore in sequential, almost daily, pulses where the sediment would drift onshore while also gradually settling back down to the seafloor. This wave-driven process seems to be important in building up the mud belt feature local to the site of our study, the Monterey Bay shelf of the Central California continental margin, but the finding has implications for many other continental margins as well.  But what got sediment from the seafloor up into mid-depth waters in the first place? One of our most exciting discoveries was the finding of occasional episodes of very abrupt, rapidly ascending density surfaces associated with a form of internal wave called a nonlinear wave, or internal hydraulic jump. Such waves are found in the natural environment in other, more easily visible phenomena. Examples include hydraulic jumps formed in rivers when the stream surface piles up behind a boulder and then abruptly drops. Dramatic internal-wave-type hydraulic jumps form in the atmosphere in the lee of mountain ranges and have been observed, for example, on the eastern slopes of the Sierras where intense down-drafting winds then updraft to bring topsoil and dust high up into the air, and are of intense interest to glider pilots. In our study we observed an undersea version of similar updrafts over the outer shelf. These updrafts lifted sediments off the seafloor up into the middle of the water column within just a few minutes. Remembering that water being 1000 times denser than air means that almost all circulation and wave phenomena are a bit more "sluggish" in the ocean than they are in the atmosphere, this is very rapid movement for ocean waters! Finding such abrupt wave events responsible for delivering and moving sediment on continental margins was a new discovery linking the sciences of wave physics and marine geology in a fundamentally new and exciting way.        Last Modified: 10/30/2015       Submitted by: Erika Mcphee-Shaw]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
