<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Collaborative Research:  Topography, Boundary Currents and the Submesoscale</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>06/15/2010</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2014</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>352444.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>352444</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>06040300</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>GEO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>OCE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Ocean Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Eric C. Itsweire</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This project addresses the dissipation of mesoscale, balanced flow in the ocean through the use of high resolution nesting experiments in two different numerical models (ROMS and the MIT general circulation model). The work specifically addresses the generation of sumesoscale, ageostrophic flows by mesoscale interactions with topography by explicitly resolving the relevant scales of 0.1-10 km in the horizontal. Numerical simulations will be designed to calculate the cascades of energy, enstrophy, and tracer variance and compare with theories, which will also be developed and improved within the scope of the project.  The high resolution simulations will be performed in the Kuroshio region where strong topographic features and the the western boundary current dynamics will allow robust testing of the hypotheses. It is hoped that the work will lead to new understandings of the submesoscale regime, the dynamics that connect balance and unbalanced flows, and perhaps even lead to new parameterizations which can be used to represent these processes in ocean and climate models.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/15/2010</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/15/2010</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.050</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>0961416</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>James</FirstName>
<LastName>McWilliams</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>C</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>James C McWilliams</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>jcm@atmos.ucla.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>3102062829</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000361923</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/15/2010</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of California-Los Angeles</Name>
<CityName>LOS ANGELES</CityName>
<ZipCode>900951406</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>3107940102</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>10889 Wilshire Boulevard</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[Suite 700]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>33</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CA33</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>092530369</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF CALIFORNIA, LOS ANGELES</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>071549000</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of California-Los Angeles]]></Name>
<CityName>LOS ANGELES</CityName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>900951406</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[10889 Wilshire Boulevard]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>33</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CA33</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1610</Code>
<Text>PHYSICAL OCEANOGRAPHY</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0110</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2010~352444</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><pre><pre><pre>Improving climate change modelsNSF: Type I - Collaborative Research:  Topography, Boundary Currents and the Submesoscale     (University of California, Los Angeles)     Type I - Collaborative Research:  Topography, Boundary Currents and the Submesoscale     (Florida State University)State:  California, FloridaCongressional Districts:California District 30, Florida District 02Research Areas:Earth &amp; EnvironmentOceanic currents flow along the side boundaries in their basins, mostoften along constant-depth contours on continental and island bottomslopes.  Measurements of chemical properties show that these currentsare typically leaky; i.e., distinctive water properties containedwithin the currents are often found within the adjacent interiorwaters in diluted concentrations.  The question is how this leakage occurs.NSF-funded researchers at the University of California at Los Angeles and <br />Florida State University have found that the drag of the currents against the <br />solid bottom generates strong horizontal gradients in the flow; that differential <br />pressure force against the bottom induces the current to separate from the <br />boundary; that after separation the current experiences an instability that <br />generates turbulent fluctuations on spatial scales of tens of meters vertically <br />and hundreds of meters horizontally (a.k.a. the submesoscale range); and that <br />these fluctuations both disperse the material concentration anomalies and <br />undergo a further "self-organization" process into long-lived submesoscale <br />coherent vortices--whirling water masses that hang together as they move <br />through the ocean--that disperse into the interior region. See the figure of <br />Monterey Bay, CA that shows where the submesoscale instability ensues and <br />the coherent vortex, central red patch, as a later-stage product of the <br />turbulent fluctuations.  This sequence of events is demonstrated in <br />computational simulations for both the California Undercurrent and the Gulf <br />Stream.  Some observations of the coherent vortices created by this process <br />confirm their existence.This project has thus provided an answer to how boundary currentwaters leak into the interior.  Ultimately, this advance could lead tomore accurate global circulation and climate models.  Such models mayreduce prediction errors in future climate forecasts.</pre> </pre> </pre><br> <p>            Last Modified: 08/12/2014<br>      Modified by: James&nbsp;C&nbsp;Mcwilliams</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Image         </div> <div class="galControls onePhoto" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation onePhoto" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2014/0961416/0961416_10017265_1407783787792_cuc_fig8a--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2014/0961416/0961416_10017265_1407783787792_cuc_fig8a--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Separating Boundary Currents"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2014/0961416/0961416_10017265_1407783787792_cuc_fig8a--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Separating Boundary Currents"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Snapshot of the spatial pattern of temperature (color bar, degrees Celsius) in a horizontal plane at a depth of 150m in Monterey Bay, CA. The California Undercurrent moves NW along the continental slope and separates at Pt. Sur (magenta line) where the coastline and topography curve into the Bay.</div> <div class="imageCredit">James C. McWilliams</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Royalty-free (unrestricted use)</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">James&nbsp;C&nbsp;Mcwilliams</div> <d...]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[Improving climate change modelsNSF: Type I - Collaborative Research:  Topography, Boundary Currents and the Submesoscale     (University of California, Los Angeles)     Type I - Collaborative Research:  Topography, Boundary Currents and the Submesoscale     (Florida State University)State:  California, FloridaCongressional Districts:California District 30, Florida District 02Research Areas:Earth &amp; EnvironmentOceanic currents flow along the side boundaries in their basins, mostoften along constant-depth contours on continental and island bottomslopes.  Measurements of chemical properties show that these currentsare typically leaky; i.e., distinctive water properties containedwithin the currents are often found within the adjacent interiorwaters in diluted concentrations.  The question is how this leakage occurs.NSF-funded researchers at the University of California at Los Angeles and  Florida State University have found that the drag of the currents against the  solid bottom generates strong horizontal gradients in the flow; that differential  pressure force against the bottom induces the current to separate from the  boundary; that after separation the current experiences an instability that  generates turbulent fluctuations on spatial scales of tens of meters vertically  and hundreds of meters horizontally (a.k.a. the submesoscale range); and that  these fluctuations both disperse the material concentration anomalies and  undergo a further "self-organization" process into long-lived submesoscale  coherent vortices--whirling water masses that hang together as they move  through the ocean--that disperse into the interior region. See the figure of  Monterey Bay, CA that shows where the submesoscale instability ensues and  the coherent vortex, central red patch, as a later-stage product of the  turbulent fluctuations.  This sequence of events is demonstrated in  computational simulations for both the California Undercurrent and the Gulf  Stream.  Some observations of the coherent vortices created by this process  confirm their existence.This project has thus provided an answer to how boundary currentwaters leak into the interior.  Ultimately, this advance could lead tomore accurate global circulation and climate models.  Such models mayreduce prediction errors in future climate forecasts.         Last Modified: 08/12/2014       Submitted by: James C Mcwilliams]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
