<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Econometric Shrinkage and Model Averaging</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2010</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2014</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>269782.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>269782</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>04050100</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>SBE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>SES</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Divn Of Social and Economic Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Nancy Lutz</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>nlutz@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927280</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>In the course of empirical research, economists typically estimate multiple models. This is partially because there is uncertainty about correct model specification, and is partially because of the desire to avoid over-parameterization. One might ask the question: Which of these models should be used? This is the question of model selection, which has been deeply explored in econometrics and statistics.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;In contemporary work, model selection has evolved into model averaging. Rather than selecting one model among a set of models, the entire ensemble can be averaged. Averaging reduces estimation variance. Averaging is quite popular in forecasting--newspapers and other outlets will commonly report the average forecast across a set of established forecasting models. This is one example of model averaging, but it extends to all areas of statistical and econometric estimation.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;In the context of model averaging, the critical question is how to select the weights. In the forecasting example listed above, the convention is to use equal weights. But this is a convention without justification. Instead, what is the best method to select model weights?&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This research is part of the attempt to answer this question.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This research expands the application of shrinkage in econometric estimation.  When there are two nested models, model averaging is equivalent with shrinkage estimation.  The PI will show that we can apply the modern theory of statistical shrinkage to parametric econometric estimators. The result is that we can construct shrinkage estimators which are more efficient than conventional estimators. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This research also extends the theory of shrinkage to the general model averaging case where the number of models exceeds two.  The Pi will develop non-Bayesian model averaging methods for econometric estimators.  &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Model averaging methods are growing in popularity in applied econometrics.  The methods proposed in this research project will have broad empirical application.  It can be expected that the theory and methods uncovered by this research will find productive use by applied economists, statisticians, and other social scientists both in academics and the public sector.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>03/15/2010</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>09/11/2011</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.075</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>0961258</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Bruce</FirstName>
<LastName>Hansen</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Bruce Hansen</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>behansen@wisc.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6082633880</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000448818</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>03/15/2010</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Wisconsin-Madison</Name>
<CityName>MADISON</CityName>
<ZipCode>537151218</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6082623822</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>21 North Park Street</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[Suite 6401]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Wisconsin</StateName>
<StateCode>WI</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>WI02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>161202122</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF WISCONSIN SYSTEM</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>041188822</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Wisconsin-Madison]]></Name>
<CityName>MADISON</CityName>
<StateCode>WI</StateCode>
<ZipCode>537151218</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[21 North Park Street]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Wisconsin</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>WI02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1320</Code>
<Text>Economics</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1333</Code>
<Text>Methodology, Measuremt &amp; Stats</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>0000</Code>
<Text>UNASSIGNED</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>OTHR</Code>
<Text>OTHER RESEARCH OR EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0110</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0111</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2010~89474</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2011~180308</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Model uncertainty is pervasive in applied economics. In most contexts, researchers have a set of plausible models, and do not know with certainty which model is correct, or the best approximation for the task at hand. A traditional solution is empirical model selection, which provides an evidence-based rule for selecting one model from a set of feasible models. A more modern approach is empirical model averaging, which averages the results across the set of plausible models. This project is concerned with the fundamental issue of constructing good empirical rules for determining the model weights.</p> <p>The project investigated the performance of empirical weight selection using a large sample statistical approximation. We found a number of important insights. Most importantly, we showed how to construct model weights which result in estimators which strictly dominate conventional estimation methods, in the sense of having strictly reduced mean-squared error, which is the standard method of evaluating the performance of econometric estimators.</p> <p>A major application of the methods is in economic forecasting, where the concept of model averaging is equivalently described as forecast combination. We have shown how to construct evidence-based rules for forecast combination. The resulting combined forecasts have lower out-of-sample forecast error than traditional forecasts</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 08/04/2014<br>      Modified by: Bruce&nbsp;Hansen</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Model uncertainty is pervasive in applied economics. In most contexts, researchers have a set of plausible models, and do not know with certainty which model is correct, or the best approximation for the task at hand. A traditional solution is empirical model selection, which provides an evidence-based rule for selecting one model from a set of feasible models. A more modern approach is empirical model averaging, which averages the results across the set of plausible models. This project is concerned with the fundamental issue of constructing good empirical rules for determining the model weights.  The project investigated the performance of empirical weight selection using a large sample statistical approximation. We found a number of important insights. Most importantly, we showed how to construct model weights which result in estimators which strictly dominate conventional estimation methods, in the sense of having strictly reduced mean-squared error, which is the standard method of evaluating the performance of econometric estimators.  A major application of the methods is in economic forecasting, where the concept of model averaging is equivalently described as forecast combination. We have shown how to construct evidence-based rules for forecast combination. The resulting combined forecasts have lower out-of-sample forecast error than traditional forecasts       Last Modified: 08/04/2014       Submitted by: Bruce Hansen]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
