<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Transient Diagenesis in Organic Poor Sediments: Lake Superior</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>06/01/2010</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2014</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>416961.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>416961</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>06040300</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>GEO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>OCE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Ocean Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Donald L. Rice</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>In this project, researchers at the University of Minnesota at Duluth will investigate the geochemistry of organic carbon, nitrogen, phosphorous, and iron in the sediments of Lake Superior and quantify their temporal and spatial variability.  The geochemical budgets of nitrogen and phosphorus in Lake Superior are presently unbalanced, and major trends in nutrient concentrations and primary productivity remain unexplained.  The researchers' preliminary data suggest that the sediments of Lake Superior have experienced large vertical migrations in the depth of oxygen penetration, analogous to those implicated in organic-poor sediments in the deep ocean. Given the importance of redox conditions for the sediment nutrient recycling, they hope to elucidate the seasonal and multi-decadal responses of these sediments to the temporal changes in water column chemistry and biological productivity. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The specific objectives are: (1) to characterize the geochemistry of organic carbon, nitrogen, phosphorus, and iron in Lake Superior sediments and quantify their temporal and spatial variability; (2) to simulate the diagenetic biogeochemical cycling in the lake and calculate the in situ rates of the organic carbon mineralization pathways and sediment-water nutrient fluxes at sites with different oxygen penetrations; (3) to elucidate seasonal and multi-decadal sediment responses to variations in the organic carbon sedimentation and bottom water concentrations of oxygen and nitrate, and quantify sediment contributions to the water column N and P budgets; and (4) to gain insights into the causes, consequences, and the dynamics of the increasing N:P imbalance in Lake Superior. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;These objectives will be accomplished using direct measurements of geochemical parameters in the lake and sediment incubations. Results will be integrated into sediment reactive-transport models and mass-balance water column models for examination of in situ process rates, reconstructions of past dynamics, and future projections. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Broader Impacts:  Arguably, study of these phenomena in Lake Superior will advance understanding of geochemical dynamics in other carbon-limited sediments.  The sediment chemistry models developed will contribute to the ongoing system-wide modeling efforts in Lake Superior, will serve the large community of Lake Superior researchers, and will be transferable to other environments.  Graduate and undergraduate students will be included on the research team.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>04/05/2010</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>04/05/2010</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.050</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>0961720</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Josef</FirstName>
<LastName>Werne</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>P</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Josef P Werne</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>jwerne@pitt.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>4126248775</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000393803</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/05/2010</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Sergei</FirstName>
<LastName>Katsev</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Sergei Katsev</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>skatsev@d.umn.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2187267582</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000508119</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/05/2010</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Robert</FirstName>
<LastName>Hecky</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>E</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Robert E Hecky</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>rhecky@d.umn.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2187267926</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000510225</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/05/2010</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Minnesota Duluth</Name>
<CityName>Duluth</CityName>
<ZipCode>558123011</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2187267582</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1049 University Drive</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Minnesota</StateName>
<StateCode>MN</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>08</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MN08</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>071508873</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>REGENTS OF THE UNIVERSITY OF MINNESOTA</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>117178941</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Minnesota Duluth]]></Name>
<CityName>Duluth</CityName>
<StateCode>MN</StateCode>
<ZipCode>558123011</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[1049 University Drive]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Minnesota</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>08</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MN08</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<FoaInformation>
<Code>0204000</Code>
<Name>Oceanography</Name>
</FoaInformation>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1670</Code>
<Text>Chemical Oceanography</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9189</Code>
<Text>WATER RESOURCES/COASTAL &amp; MARINE ENVIRON</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>EGCH</Code>
<Text>ENVIRONMENT AND GLOBAL CHANGE</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0110</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2010~416961</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The chemical processes that take place in the bottom sediments of Lake Superior, the largest freshwater lake in the World by surface area, were characterized in detail for the first time. These processes regulate the rates at which substances such as nutrients nitrogen and phosphorus are exchanged with the overlying water column where they can affect the biological productivity of the lake. The results helped understand the enigmatic accumulation of nitrate in Lake Superior, which has been continuing for the past 70 years. They also shed light on the reasons behind the exceptional scarcity of phosphorus in Lake Superoir, which restricts the lake's biological productivity. Interpretation of sediment records that contain information about the biological productivy of the lake over the past 8000 years revealed that in the last 200 years human influences have significantly altered the ecosystem of this large and generally considered pristine ecosystem. Investigations into the seasonal dynamics of the chemical processes in these sediments revealed their similarities to those in sediments in other low-productivity environments, such as in the Artctic Ocean. Sediment processes there respond strongly to the depth of oxygen penetration into the sediment, which is several centimeters deep and strongly responds to the seasonal deposition of organic material after the surface of the lake clears of ice. The developed comparison metrics will help in transfering research results between the marine and freshwater environments. In particular, the quantitative relationships developed in Lake Superior for the rates of sediment denitrification, a process that removes biologically available nitrogen into the non-reactive N<sub>2</sub>, will help understand the corresponding rates in the open ocean where data are presently scarce. In addition, investigations of microbial communities that catalyze the chemical reactions inside the sediments have hinted at the significance of several geochemical processes that previously have been investigated only in marine environments and whose significance in freshwater has not been yet recognized. &nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 03/31/2015<br>      Modified by: Sergei&nbsp;Katsev</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The chemical processes that take place in the bottom sediments of Lake Superior, the largest freshwater lake in the World by surface area, were characterized in detail for the first time. These processes regulate the rates at which substances such as nutrients nitrogen and phosphorus are exchanged with the overlying water column where they can affect the biological productivity of the lake. The results helped understand the enigmatic accumulation of nitrate in Lake Superior, which has been continuing for the past 70 years. They also shed light on the reasons behind the exceptional scarcity of phosphorus in Lake Superoir, which restricts the lake's biological productivity. Interpretation of sediment records that contain information about the biological productivy of the lake over the past 8000 years revealed that in the last 200 years human influences have significantly altered the ecosystem of this large and generally considered pristine ecosystem. Investigations into the seasonal dynamics of the chemical processes in these sediments revealed their similarities to those in sediments in other low-productivity environments, such as in the Artctic Ocean. Sediment processes there respond strongly to the depth of oxygen penetration into the sediment, which is several centimeters deep and strongly responds to the seasonal deposition of organic material after the surface of the lake clears of ice. The developed comparison metrics will help in transfering research results between the marine and freshwater environments. In particular, the quantitative relationships developed in Lake Superior for the rates of sediment denitrification, a process that removes biologically available nitrogen into the non-reactive N2, will help understand the corresponding rates in the open ocean where data are presently scarce. In addition, investigations of microbial communities that catalyze the chemical reactions inside the sediments have hinted at the significance of several geochemical processes that previously have been investigated only in marine environments and whose significance in freshwater has not been yet recognized.         Last Modified: 03/31/2015       Submitted by: Sergei Katsev]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
