<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Using Observations to Elucidate the Magnetic Structure of Erupting and Non-Erupting Filaments</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>06/01/2010</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2014</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>363145.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>363145</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>06020203</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>GEO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>AGS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Atmospheric &amp; Geospace Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Ilia Roussev</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>iroussev@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927436</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This investigation addresses the connection between coronal mass ejections (CMEs) and magnetic structures at the solar surface. Given the motivation that CMEs are recognized as the primary solar driver of non-recurrent geomagnetic storms, the Principal Investigator (PI) will focus on a comprehensive study of the structure, formation, and eruption of solar filaments, which are a basic component of most CME eruptions. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Among other tasks, the PI will use high-cadence magnetograms and the application of a Local Correlation Tracking numerical code to determine photospheric flows in the vicinity of the polarity inversion line during the formation of a filament channel.  She will then identify the locations of magnetic flux cancellation, coalescence, or fragmentation.  She will test the hypothesis that filament barbs are jet-like flows triggered by magnetic flux elements that cross the filament channel and cancel with majority-polarity flux on the other side. The PI also will perform a systematic survey of endpoint brightenings in erupting quiescent and active-region filaments, employing spacecraft observations in order to verify that these features occur at the outer edges of transient holes (and are distinct from the well-known footpoint brightenings associated with post-eruption arcades). Finally, using spacecraft data, she will carry out a systematic study of rotation in erupting filaments, in order to test the hypothesis that a filament/barb system has the opposite helicity sign to the overlying arcade, contrary to the standard flux-rope model for filaments.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The PI expects this study to lead to a better understanding of the underlying physical drivers of space weather. To enhance this broader impact, the PI will work closely with colleagues at the U.S. Naval Research Laboratory, who are actively involved in developing new operational techniques and instrumentation for space weather prediction for the U.S. Department of Defense.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>05/19/2010</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/22/2013</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.050</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>0962619</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Karin</FirstName>
<LastName>Muglach</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Karin Muglach</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>kmuglach@gmx.de</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>3012867332</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000541280</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/19/2010</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Artep Incorporated</Name>
<CityName>Ellicott City</CityName>
<ZipCode>210427614</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>4104802700</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>2922 Excelsior Springs Court</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Maryland</StateName>
<StateCode>MD</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MD07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>186413639</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>ARTEP, INC.</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Artep Incorporated]]></Name>
<CityName>Ellicott City</CityName>
<StateCode>MD</StateCode>
<ZipCode>210427614</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[2922 Excelsior Springs Court]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Maryland</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MD07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<FoaInformation>
<Code>0205000</Code>
<Name>Space</Name>
</FoaInformation>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1523</Code>
<Text>SOLAR-TERRESTRIAL</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>0000</Code>
<Text>UNASSIGNED</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>OTHR</Code>
<Text>OTHER RESEARCH OR EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0110</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0112</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0113</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2010~115584</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2012~120960</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2013~126601</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Solar filaments are large, thread-like structures that consist of cool, chromospheric material that is flowing high above the solar surface (the photosphere) embedded in the very hot outer atmosphere, the solar corona, which has over a one million degrees. Most of the filament mass is connected to the solar magnetic field.<br /><br />Filaments are always located where the photospheric line-of-sight magnetic field switches its sign, the polarity inversion line. This fact gives an important clue about the large-scale three-dimensional structure of the magnetic field that harbours filaments. The two basic competing ideas are that the filament magnetic field resembles either a sheared arcade of magnetic loops or the filament plasma is embedded in a twisted flux-rope structure. In both cases filaments can store a significant amount of magnetic engergy which can be explosively released in a filament eruption resulting in a coronal mass ejection (CME). CMEs heading towards Earth will interact with the Earth magnetosphere and can cause geomagnetic storms, disrupt navigation and communications systems and can harm both satellites and humans in space.<br /><br />As indicated by the title of the project it emphasises observational aspects of filaments related to their formation, dynamics and eruption. Results from this work have been published in five refereed journal papers, two conference proceedings papers and numerous posters and talks at international conferences. In the following paragraphs I will highlight two of the refereed journal papers.<br /><br />How filaments form in the first place is still an open question, especially as there are only a very small number of observed cases where the whole process of formation has been covered. In the paper 'The Evolution of Dark Canopies Around Active Regions' the authors study large circular areas around active regions with strong magnetic field, that have very low intensity in chromospheric and low coronal emission. Figure 1 shows an example of such an active region and it is found that the dark area surrounding it consists of low-lying magnetic field that spreads out from the central active region and forms a canopy around the bright center. The magnetic field in the early phase of the canopy lifetime is mostly radial with the active region at its center, but solar surface flows cause the field to interact with the magnetic field at the outer canopy boundaries leading to the highly sheared and somewhat twisted magnetic field configuration that is found in filaments. Figure 2 shows an example of a filament forming at the boundary of an active region canopy over the time of one solar rotation (around 27 days).<br /><br />The second paper reveals information on the structure and the strength of the magnetic field of a filament, parameters that are very difficult to measure. As a method to derive them large-amplitude longitudinal oscillations are used. These oscillations are triggered by a small jet-like event at one of the footpoints of the filament that injects energy into the system, which causes the plasma to move along threads of the magnetic field. The energy injection is not sufficient to lead to an eruption of the filament (destabilizing the whole structure), but the displaced mass is returning along the field line and eventually stops again at its equilibrium position on the magnetic field line. This back-and-forth movement of the plasma can be measured and an example of such a measurement is shown in Figure 3 (taken from the paper with the title 'Observations and Implications of Large-amplitude Longitudinal Oscillations in a Solar Filament'). Such oscillation patterns can then be fit with appropriate functions and various magnetic field parameters are derived using a damped pendulum model for the oscillation.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 03/21/2016<br>      Modified by: Karin&nbsp;Muglach</p> </...]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Solar filaments are large, thread-like structures that consist of cool, chromospheric material that is flowing high above the solar surface (the photosphere) embedded in the very hot outer atmosphere, the solar corona, which has over a one million degrees. Most of the filament mass is connected to the solar magnetic field.  Filaments are always located where the photospheric line-of-sight magnetic field switches its sign, the polarity inversion line. This fact gives an important clue about the large-scale three-dimensional structure of the magnetic field that harbours filaments. The two basic competing ideas are that the filament magnetic field resembles either a sheared arcade of magnetic loops or the filament plasma is embedded in a twisted flux-rope structure. In both cases filaments can store a significant amount of magnetic engergy which can be explosively released in a filament eruption resulting in a coronal mass ejection (CME). CMEs heading towards Earth will interact with the Earth magnetosphere and can cause geomagnetic storms, disrupt navigation and communications systems and can harm both satellites and humans in space.  As indicated by the title of the project it emphasises observational aspects of filaments related to their formation, dynamics and eruption. Results from this work have been published in five refereed journal papers, two conference proceedings papers and numerous posters and talks at international conferences. In the following paragraphs I will highlight two of the refereed journal papers.  How filaments form in the first place is still an open question, especially as there are only a very small number of observed cases where the whole process of formation has been covered. In the paper 'The Evolution of Dark Canopies Around Active Regions' the authors study large circular areas around active regions with strong magnetic field, that have very low intensity in chromospheric and low coronal emission. Figure 1 shows an example of such an active region and it is found that the dark area surrounding it consists of low-lying magnetic field that spreads out from the central active region and forms a canopy around the bright center. The magnetic field in the early phase of the canopy lifetime is mostly radial with the active region at its center, but solar surface flows cause the field to interact with the magnetic field at the outer canopy boundaries leading to the highly sheared and somewhat twisted magnetic field configuration that is found in filaments. Figure 2 shows an example of a filament forming at the boundary of an active region canopy over the time of one solar rotation (around 27 days).  The second paper reveals information on the structure and the strength of the magnetic field of a filament, parameters that are very difficult to measure. As a method to derive them large-amplitude longitudinal oscillations are used. These oscillations are triggered by a small jet-like event at one of the footpoints of the filament that injects energy into the system, which causes the plasma to move along threads of the magnetic field. The energy injection is not sufficient to lead to an eruption of the filament (destabilizing the whole structure), but the displaced mass is returning along the field line and eventually stops again at its equilibrium position on the magnetic field line. This back-and-forth movement of the plasma can be measured and an example of such a measurement is shown in Figure 3 (taken from the paper with the title 'Observations and Implications of Large-amplitude Longitudinal Oscillations in a Solar Filament'). Such oscillation patterns can then be fit with appropriate functions and various magnetic field parameters are derived using a damped pendulum model for the oscillation.          Last Modified: 03/21/2016       Submitted by: Karin Muglach]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
