<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>IRNC: ProNet: ACE - America Connects to Europe</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>06/01/2010</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>4609113.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>5266522</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Cooperative Agreement</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>05090000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>CSE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>OAC</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Office of Advanced Cyberinfrastructure (OAC)</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Kevin Thompson</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>kthompso@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924220</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Proposal Summary&lt;br/&gt;ACE proposes to provide multi-gigabit bandwidth and services connecting researchers in the US with their counterparts in Europe that will continue to serve current needs well but also extend the transatlantic exchange into further scientific fields and disciplines. ACE will deploy several 10Gbps waves between Europe and the US, starting with 40 Gbps and growing over the lifetime of the award.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Indiana University (IU), as the lead institution, will function as a cooperative partnership with Delivery of Advanced Network Technology to Europe (DANTE), Trans-European Research and Education Networking Association (TERENA), New York State Education and Research Network (NYSERNet ), and Internet2. DANTE is the operator of the pan-European network GÉANT, which interconnects all of the national R&amp;E networks in Europe, acts as the operating partner in several intercontinental research networking projects across Europe and Asia, and has long provisioned and operated multiple 10Gbps links across the Atlantic to interconnect its European partners with North American networks. NYSERNet is a partner in Manhattan Landing Exchange Point (MAN LAN) and is the optical terminus for many US telecommunications carriers and transatlantic cables. MAN LAN is owned and operated by Internet2 in partnership with NYSERNet and with NOC and engineering services from the IU Global NOC. Internet2 is the leading US research and education networking organization, representing 300 member institutions and connecting thousands of US educational, research, cultural, and related institutions, with partnership agreements with nearly 60 R&amp;E networks around the world. Through cooperative partnership with NYSERNet and the DANET/GÉANT community of more than 34 national R&amp;E networks that will be reachable through these connections, the ACE award will provide the best economies of scale in transatlantic connectivity, supporting a very broad community of users.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;One explicit goal of the ACE project is to develop tools and mechanisms to facilitate close operational integration among these network operators. IU and Internet2 have extensive experience in joint software development and deployment centered on the perfSONAR and dynamic circuit networking activities.  As a part of DICE, the ACE project will immediately deploy, expand, and enhance services in security, measurement, identity management, and operational integration in coordination with ongoing DICE activities.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Intellectual merit&lt;br/&gt;As part of the DICE collaboration, the ACE partners will expand and enhance services in security, measurement, identity management, and operational integration. Close cooperation among the DICE participants? efforts will maximize US-EU connectivity, increase collaborations (particularly with respect to security), ensure deployment of accurate and useful measurement technology, deploy dynamic circuit services to meet the needs of high-bandwidth applications, and decrease costs by eliminating duplication of effort.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Broader impact&lt;br/&gt;This project will procure significant additional bandwidth between the US and EU to support a wide range of collaboration between scientists and engineers. In addition, it will support collaboration on technical, operational, and planning exercises that are critical in supporting science and engineering research. Through cooperative partnership with DANTE and the GÉANT community of more than 34 national research and education networks, the ACE project will provide the best economies of scale in transatlantic connectivity, supporting a very broad community of users.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Integrating diversity with research and education is a strong component of the proposal. IU will partner with the existing Gerald L. Bepko Internship Program at IU, which has as its goal of identifying, connecting and working with students in populations under-represented in information technology, to extend educational reach and integrate diversity into the ACE program.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/16/2010</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>04/01/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>CoopAgrmnt</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.070</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>0962973</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Jennifer</FirstName>
<LastName>Schopf</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>M</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Jennifer M Schopf</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>jmschopf@indiana.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>7732947320</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000273004</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/30/2013</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>James</FirstName>
<LastName>Williams</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>James Williams</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>williams@indiana.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>8123276839</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000392993</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/16/2010</StartDate>
<EndDate>09/30/2013</EndDate>
<RoleCode>Former Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>John</FirstName>
<LastName>Hicks</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>John Hicks</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>jhicks@internet2.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>3177504765</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000644289</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>11/07/2013</StartDate>
<EndDate>03/24/2014</EndDate>
<RoleCode>Former Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Indiana University</Name>
<CityName>Bloomington</CityName>
<ZipCode>474013654</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>3172783473</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>509 E 3RD ST</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Indiana</StateName>
<StateCode>IN</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>09</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>IN09</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>006046700</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>TRUSTEES OF INDIANA UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>006046700</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Indiana University]]></Name>
<CityName>Bloomington</CityName>
<StateCode>IN</StateCode>
<ZipCode>474013654</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[509 E 3RD ST]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Indiana</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>09</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>IN09</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7369</Code>
<Text>International Res Ret Connect</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7369</Code>
<Text>INTERNATIONAL RES NET CONNECT</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7433</Code>
<Text>CyberInfra Frmwrk 21st (CIF21)</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7556</Code>
<Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0110</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0111</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0112</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0113</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2010~796264</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2011~3812849</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2012~46843</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2013~610566</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The America Connects to Europe (ACE) project supported circuits and network services between the US and Europe for seven years. The circuits connected the US east coast to Germany, France, and United Kingdom at different times over the project. The services included standard IP-level traffic to more advanced networking, including dynamic circuits and software defined networks (SDN). ACE supported a variety of measurement and monitoring tools, including SNMP, perfSONAR, and the collection of flow data. The project also worked closely with a variety of end user science projects to enable better data movement for research.</p> <p>Collaborations between scientists continue to grow, and ACE supported data sharing between US and European and African scientists. Figure 1 shows the growth in data transfers between June 2013 and December 2016, during which time hundreds of petabytes of data were transferred in support of collaborative science.</p> <p>To better understand the use of the network, ACE researchers implemented flow data collection, and analyzed the major sources and sinks of the transfers using the link. Figures 2 and 3 show examples of top talker data for Europe to US transfers during Year 7. The use of the link covered science in all domains supported by the National Science Foundation: physics, engineering, biology, geoscience, social science, computer science, astronomy, and chemistry, as well as educational uses.</p> <p>The ACE team also worked closely with both network engineers and scientists over the seven year project. Every year, team members traveled to SuperComputing, Internet2 meetings, and TERENA conferences. Most years, additional workshops were also attended, including GENI meetings, NSF-supported networking meetings, and joint workshops with Internet2, the Energy Sciences Network (ESnet), and the Network Startup Resource Center (NSRC). Over 7 years, team members attended meetings in 31 countries, several multiple times, as shown in Figure 4. At 90% of them, a presentation was given describing ACE or some feature of the project. A subset of the presentations can be found online at <a href="http://internationalnetworks.iu.edu/archives/index.html">http://internationalnetworks.iu.edu/archives/index.html</a>. ACE staff were involved in training efforts, including multiple CrossConnect courses with ESNet that brought together applications scientists ina given domain and network engineers to support them, teaching classes at Internet2 Joint tech meetings on SDN, PerfSonar, and Open flow, teaching at the Operating Innovative Networks (OIN) workshops, and at specialty workshops held as part of TNC, GLIF, PRAGMA, and Quilt meetings.</p> <p>In August 2014, ACE was awarded a supplement to work directly with end users sharing data between the US and Europe on a new 100G R&amp;E network. In Year 4 of the project, this meant adding on additional staff members and working more closely with end user scientists transferring data. At the outset, the thought was to support researchers looking to use the 100G transatlantic ANA link, however very quickly it was realized that few researchers had the necessary connections to use even 10G links, and that most connectivity to the ANA circuit was not at 100G. While many groups were contacted, very few were able to take advantage of the increased capacity at that time. Two notable cases of groups who did were the PanSTARRS astronomy group and a set of researchers at the European Bioinformatics Institute. This work was closely collaborated with the DANTE/GEANT user support group.</p> <p>The ACE project also significantly advanced pragmatic network research through its hands-on approach to supporting OpenFlow and Software Defined Networks (SDN) through prototype implementations and demonstrations. ACE staff established a three-continent dynamic layer-2 connection for large flows in Year 1 that was used throughout the life of the project in a series of coordinated experiments, primarily with JGN in Japan and GEANT in Europe to run more extensive tests. Interoperability of dynamic networking services were demonstrated at several conferences as early as SC11, where there was a demonstration of the Inter-Domain Controller Protocol. The Amsterdam-Chicago link was re-architected to create a US-EU OpenFlow capable testbed, to be connected to the Internet2 iNDDI infrastructure. That testbed was used for demonstrations during many SC and GLIF meetings until the link was decommissioned in 2015.</p> <p>Overall, ACE successfully supported the growing needs of the US science community in sharing data with their European and African colleagues, through work with end user scientists, prototype work with network engineers, and significant outreach and training efforts. The circuit capacity grew from 20G in 2010 to 130G by 2017, ongoing experiments for Software Defined Networks continued to advance the experimental networking field, and our focused on work with end user scientists resulted in increased capacity for data sharing.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 09/11/2017<br>      Modified by: Jennifer&nbsp;M&nbsp;Schopf</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Images (<span id="selectedPhoto0">1</span> of <span class="totalNumber"></span>)           </div> <div class="galControls" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/0962973/0962973_10017290_1505130569426_ACEMap--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/0962973/0962973_10017290_1505130569426_ACEMap--rgov-800width.jpg" title="ACE Circuits"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/0962973/0962973_10017290_1505130569426_ACEMap--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="ACE Circuits"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Map of the ACE circuits</div> <div class="imageCredit">jmschopf@iu.edu</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Public Domain</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Jennifer&nbsp;M&nbsp;Schopf</div> <div class="imageTitle">ACE Circuits</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/0962973/0962973_10017290_1505130404520_ACETopTeninboundbysource--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/0962973/0962973_10017290_1505130404520_ACETopTeninboundbysource--rgov-800width.jpg" title="ACE Traffic Analysis Inbound by Source"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/0962973/0962973_10017290_1505130404520_ACETopTeninboundbysource--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="ACE Traffic Analysis Inbound by Source"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Top Talker data for the 30G ACE LAG between WIX and Frankfurt for Year 7, inbound by source.</div> <div class="imageCredit">edmoyn@iu.edu</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Public Domain</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Jennifer&nbsp;M&nbsp;Schopf</div> <div class="imageTitle">ACE Traffic Analysis Inbound by Source</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/0962973/0962973_10017290_1505130494893_ACETopeteninboundbydest--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/0962973/0962973_10017290_1505130494893_ACETopeteninboundbydest--rgov-800width.jpg" title="ACE Traffic Analysis Inbound by Destination"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/0962973/0962973_10017290_1505130494893_ACETopeteninboundbydest--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="ACE Traffic Analysis Inbound by Destination"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Top Talker data for the 30G ACE LAG between WIX and Frankfurt for Year 7, inbound by destination.</div> <div class="imageCredit">edmoyn@iu.edu</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Public Domain</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Jennifer&nbsp;M&nbsp;Schopf</div> <div class="imageTitle">ACE Traffic Analysis Inbound by Destination</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/0962973/0962973_10017290_1505130045052_ACEaggregatetraffic--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/0962973/0962973_10017290_1505130045052_ACEaggregatetraffic--rgov-800width.jpg" title="ACE Aggregate Traffic"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/0962973/0962973_10017290_1505130045052_ACEaggregatetraffic--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="ACE Aggregate Traffic"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Aggregate traffic using smoothed daily averages for all ACE circuits, both NSF and GEANT-funded, for June 2013 to December 2016.</div> <div class="imageCredit">leea@iu.edu</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Public Domain</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Jennifer&nbsp;M&nbsp;Schopf</div> <div class="imageTitle">ACE Aggregate Traffic</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/0962973/0962973_10017290_1505131325619_ACETravelMap--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/0962973/0962973_10017290_1505131325619_ACETravelMap--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Map of locations to which ACE staff traveled during the seven year project."><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/0962973/0962973_10017290_1505131325619_ACETravelMap--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Map of locations to which ACE staff traveled during the seven year project."></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Map of the locations to which ACE team members attended meetings or conferences.</div> <div class="imageCredit">schevali@iu.edu</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Public Domain</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Jennifer&nbsp;M&nbsp;Schopf</div> <div class="imageTitle">Map of locations to which ACE staff traveled during the seven year project.</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The America Connects to Europe (ACE) project supported circuits and network services between the US and Europe for seven years. The circuits connected the US east coast to Germany, France, and United Kingdom at different times over the project. The services included standard IP-level traffic to more advanced networking, including dynamic circuits and software defined networks (SDN). ACE supported a variety of measurement and monitoring tools, including SNMP, perfSONAR, and the collection of flow data. The project also worked closely with a variety of end user science projects to enable better data movement for research.  Collaborations between scientists continue to grow, and ACE supported data sharing between US and European and African scientists. Figure 1 shows the growth in data transfers between June 2013 and December 2016, during which time hundreds of petabytes of data were transferred in support of collaborative science.  To better understand the use of the network, ACE researchers implemented flow data collection, and analyzed the major sources and sinks of the transfers using the link. Figures 2 and 3 show examples of top talker data for Europe to US transfers during Year 7. The use of the link covered science in all domains supported by the National Science Foundation: physics, engineering, biology, geoscience, social science, computer science, astronomy, and chemistry, as well as educational uses.  The ACE team also worked closely with both network engineers and scientists over the seven year project. Every year, team members traveled to SuperComputing, Internet2 meetings, and TERENA conferences. Most years, additional workshops were also attended, including GENI meetings, NSF-supported networking meetings, and joint workshops with Internet2, the Energy Sciences Network (ESnet), and the Network Startup Resource Center (NSRC). Over 7 years, team members attended meetings in 31 countries, several multiple times, as shown in Figure 4. At 90% of them, a presentation was given describing ACE or some feature of the project. A subset of the presentations can be found online at http://internationalnetworks.iu.edu/archives/index.html. ACE staff were involved in training efforts, including multiple CrossConnect courses with ESNet that brought together applications scientists ina given domain and network engineers to support them, teaching classes at Internet2 Joint tech meetings on SDN, PerfSonar, and Open flow, teaching at the Operating Innovative Networks (OIN) workshops, and at specialty workshops held as part of TNC, GLIF, PRAGMA, and Quilt meetings.  In August 2014, ACE was awarded a supplement to work directly with end users sharing data between the US and Europe on a new 100G R&amp;E network. In Year 4 of the project, this meant adding on additional staff members and working more closely with end user scientists transferring data. At the outset, the thought was to support researchers looking to use the 100G transatlantic ANA link, however very quickly it was realized that few researchers had the necessary connections to use even 10G links, and that most connectivity to the ANA circuit was not at 100G. While many groups were contacted, very few were able to take advantage of the increased capacity at that time. Two notable cases of groups who did were the PanSTARRS astronomy group and a set of researchers at the European Bioinformatics Institute. This work was closely collaborated with the DANTE/GEANT user support group.  The ACE project also significantly advanced pragmatic network research through its hands-on approach to supporting OpenFlow and Software Defined Networks (SDN) through prototype implementations and demonstrations. ACE staff established a three-continent dynamic layer-2 connection for large flows in Year 1 that was used throughout the life of the project in a series of coordinated experiments, primarily with JGN in Japan and GEANT in Europe to run more extensive tests. Interoperability of dynamic networking services were demonstrated at several conferences as early as SC11, where there was a demonstration of the Inter-Domain Controller Protocol. The Amsterdam-Chicago link was re-architected to create a US-EU OpenFlow capable testbed, to be connected to the Internet2 iNDDI infrastructure. That testbed was used for demonstrations during many SC and GLIF meetings until the link was decommissioned in 2015.  Overall, ACE successfully supported the growing needs of the US science community in sharing data with their European and African colleagues, through work with end user scientists, prototype work with network engineers, and significant outreach and training efforts. The circuit capacity grew from 20G in 2010 to 130G by 2017, ongoing experiments for Software Defined Networks continued to advance the experimental networking field, and our focused on work with end user scientists resulted in increased capacity for data sharing.       Last Modified: 09/11/2017       Submitted by: Jennifer M Schopf]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
