<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Understanding Credit Crises</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>03/15/2010</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>02/29/2016</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>442800.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>442800</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>04050100</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>SBE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>SES</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Divn Of Social and Economic Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Georgia Kosmopoulou</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>gkosmopo@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032920000</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Understanding Credit Crises&lt;br/&gt;Intellectual Merit:&lt;br/&gt;The PIs have spent the best part of their careers understanding financial institutions, and the role they play in the economy. In recent years, they have built up from financial institutions. They have studied the role of aggregate real liquidity (as well as the role of aggregate fiat money) on bank behavior. Particularly interesting has been the two-way interactions between banks' asset and liability structures and aggregate variables like liquidity. In their proposed work, they want to examine banker incentives - to set bank leverage, to choose between assets of varying liquidity, and to sell, liquidate, or keep assets - based both on aggregate variables such as liquidity as well as the actions of the government authorities/central bank. They hope thereby to understand the kind of actions banks might take that increase the risk of crises, as well as their behavior in the midst of a crisis. This then allows us to think more carefully about policy, both monetary (the links between monetary policy and risk taking behavior will be one of the important contributions of their work) and regulatory. As the PIs develop these ideas, they will also focus on testing some of the empirical implications of their theories, given the rich data from across the world that will be available from this crisis.&lt;br/&gt;Broader Impacts&lt;br/&gt;Rajan used some of the ideas the PIs had developed in their earlier work in providing an early warning to central bankers about the potential for a crisis of the kind we have witnessed. The PIs' joint, accessible, paper in the American Economic Review Papers and Proceedings (Diamond and Rajan (2009)), summarizing the causes of the crisis, has been widely downloaded, reprinted, and read. Both PIs have been very active, both in proposing actions to resolve the crisis, as well as in making suggestions for change. Both PIs are members of the Squam Lake Group, a non-partisan group of academics that has put together a set of memos on a number of aspects of regulatory reform. They have interacted with members of the Treasury, the Fed, and Congress, explaining the implications of different reforms in light of their theories. Their current proposal will help us understand better the kinds of incentives that led to the crisis, as well as to the kind of behavior observed in the crisis. Clearly, this will help guide policy formulation for the future. The PIs also hope to train a number of students, both through their teaching (they teach both MBA as well as specialized Ph.D. courses), their Ph.D. advisory role, as well as through their employment of research assistants.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>03/10/2010</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>02/06/2015</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.075</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>0962321</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Raghuram</FirstName>
<LastName>Rajan</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>G</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Raghuram G Rajan</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>raghuram.rajan@gsb.uchicago.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>7737024437</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000102592</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>03/10/2010</StartDate>
<EndDate>02/07/2014</EndDate>
<RoleCode>Former Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Douglas</FirstName>
<LastName>Diamond</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Douglas Diamond</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>Douglas.Diamond@chicagobooth.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>7737027283</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000308058</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>02/06/2015</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Douglas</FirstName>
<LastName>Diamond</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Douglas Diamond</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>Douglas.Diamond@chicagobooth.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>7737027283</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000308058</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>03/10/2010</StartDate>
<EndDate>02/07/2014</EndDate>
<RoleCode>Former Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>National Bureau of Economic Research Inc</Name>
<CityName>Cambridge</CityName>
<ZipCode>021385398</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6178683900</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1050 Massachusetts Avenue</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
<StateCode>MA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MA05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>054552435</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>NATIONAL BUREAU OF ECONOMIC RESEARCH, INC.</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>054552435</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[National Bureau of Economic Research Inc]]></Name>
<CityName>Cambridge</CityName>
<StateCode>MA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>021385398</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[1050 Massachusetts Avenue]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MA05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1320</Code>
<Text>Economics</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>0000</Code>
<Text>UNASSIGNED</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>OTHR</Code>
<Text>OTHER RESEARCH OR EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0110</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0111</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2010~295200</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2011~147600</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>This project develops frameworks to understand fluctuations in access to credit due to financial crises and other problems which interfere with the refinancing of maturing short-term debt.&nbsp;&nbsp; Extending some models we developed before the recent credit crisis as well as developing new models, we studied several key issues related to the world credit crisis of 2008-2010 and the policy responses to it.&nbsp;&nbsp;</p> <p>One framework studies the financial stability implications of central bank interest rate policies.&nbsp;&nbsp; It shows why a one-sided policy of reducing interest rates to respond to increases in bank funding costs by can backfire once the policy is anticipated by banks.&nbsp; &nbsp;&nbsp;To be effective, there must in addition be a symmetric anticipated policy of rate increases when bank funding cost fall.&nbsp; Otherwise, banks will increase their use of debt sufficiently to prevent the interest rate reductions from being effective or beneficial. &nbsp;The best polices avoid bank runs but do not subside banks on average.&nbsp; This research was published in the <em>Journal of Political Economy</em> in June 2012.</p> <p>Another framework studies the behavior of a financial system during a period when there is an increased risk of a financial crisis (such as a run on financial institutions funded with short-term debt).&nbsp;&nbsp; An increase in this risk can lead to a freeze in the trading of complicated securities (such as mortgage-backed securities) as well as a freeze in bank lending.&nbsp; If trading does not freeze, banks may instead have perverse incentives to increase their holdings of such complicated and potentially illiquid assets.&nbsp; There can be advantages to &ldquo;cleaning up&rdquo; the financial system at that point, forcing some institutions to instead slowly sell some of these illiquid assets.&nbsp; This can avoid a future fire sale of bank assets, reducing the severity of a crisis or even eliminating it.&nbsp; This research was published in the <em>Quarterly Journal of Economics</em> in May 2011.</p> <p>The project also developed a model providing new insights into the effects of the maturity of a firm&rsquo;s debt on its incentives to continue to invest in its business when the economic conditions fluctuate. &nbsp;&nbsp;The conventional wisdom was that very short-term debt provided larger incentives for a firm to invest efficiently.&nbsp; This was based on models which did not account for the dynamic effect on future investment incentives of fluctuations in future financing costs occurring when the firm refinances its short-term debt at maturity.&nbsp; Accounting for these dynamic effects can make shorter-term financing reduce the incentive for firms to invest.&nbsp; The results characterize the conditions which determine the maturity of debt that provides the best incentives for firms to invest efficiently. &nbsp;This research, by Douglas Diamond and Zhiguo He was published in the <em>Journal of Finance</em> in April 2014.</p> <p>The results in these models (and other research that we published during the term of this award) are relevant to understanding financial crises and potential responses to them.&nbsp; Most crises are triggered by the financial sector&rsquo;s inability to retain short-term funding and the inability to refinance it due to a bank run or a default.&nbsp; Taken together, our results provide new approaches to understanding the implications of the use of short-term funding by banks and firms and the potential effects of government or central bank responses to their funding problems.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 05/02/2016<br>      Modified by: Douglas&nbsp;Diamond</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ This project develops frameworks to understand fluctuations in access to credit due to financial crises and other problems which interfere with the refinancing of maturing short-term debt.   Extending some models we developed before the recent credit crisis as well as developing new models, we studied several key issues related to the world credit crisis of 2008-2010 and the policy responses to it.    One framework studies the financial stability implications of central bank interest rate policies.   It shows why a one-sided policy of reducing interest rates to respond to increases in bank funding costs by can backfire once the policy is anticipated by banks.    To be effective, there must in addition be a symmetric anticipated policy of rate increases when bank funding cost fall.  Otherwise, banks will increase their use of debt sufficiently to prevent the interest rate reductions from being effective or beneficial.  The best polices avoid bank runs but do not subside banks on average.  This research was published in the Journal of Political Economy in June 2012.  Another framework studies the behavior of a financial system during a period when there is an increased risk of a financial crisis (such as a run on financial institutions funded with short-term debt).   An increase in this risk can lead to a freeze in the trading of complicated securities (such as mortgage-backed securities) as well as a freeze in bank lending.  If trading does not freeze, banks may instead have perverse incentives to increase their holdings of such complicated and potentially illiquid assets.  There can be advantages to "cleaning up" the financial system at that point, forcing some institutions to instead slowly sell some of these illiquid assets.  This can avoid a future fire sale of bank assets, reducing the severity of a crisis or even eliminating it.  This research was published in the Quarterly Journal of Economics in May 2011.  The project also developed a model providing new insights into the effects of the maturity of a firmÆs debt on its incentives to continue to invest in its business when the economic conditions fluctuate.   The conventional wisdom was that very short-term debt provided larger incentives for a firm to invest efficiently.  This was based on models which did not account for the dynamic effect on future investment incentives of fluctuations in future financing costs occurring when the firm refinances its short-term debt at maturity.  Accounting for these dynamic effects can make shorter-term financing reduce the incentive for firms to invest.  The results characterize the conditions which determine the maturity of debt that provides the best incentives for firms to invest efficiently.  This research, by Douglas Diamond and Zhiguo He was published in the Journal of Finance in April 2014.  The results in these models (and other research that we published during the term of this award) are relevant to understanding financial crises and potential responses to them.  Most crises are triggered by the financial sectorÆs inability to retain short-term funding and the inability to refinance it due to a bank run or a default.  Taken together, our results provide new approaches to understanding the implications of the use of short-term funding by banks and firms and the potential effects of government or central bank responses to their funding problems.       Last Modified: 05/02/2016       Submitted by: Douglas Diamond]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
