<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Optimizing the utility of satellite altimetry for diagnosing  lateral stirring and mixing in the upper ocean</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>06/01/2010</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>11/30/2015</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>643325.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>643325</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>06040300</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>GEO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>OCE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Ocean Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Eric C. Itsweire</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The project will assess the significance of model error for mixing diagnostics deduced from satellite altimetry products, develop strategies for ameliorating its impact, and expand understanding of the theoretical relationships between measures of mixing. The sensitivity of mixing diagnostics to noise and spatial and temporal sampling resolution will be determined using high resolution primitive equation ocean models. A Lagrangian stochastic parameterization scheme for the unresolved flow will be developed and coupled to the observed flow calculated from satellite altimetry. Mixing diagnostic parameters will be averaged over ensembles of particles to provide statistically meaningful averages and confidence intervals. Data assimilation methods will be exploited to dynamically estimate stochastic parameters based upon successive observations of the flow field. Finally, the research will develop interrelationships among mixing diagnostics and between diagnostics and large-scale features of the flow using analytical techniques, simple kinematic flows, and idealized geophysical turbulence models.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The project aims to optimize the utility of satellite altimetry products and develop an extensively documented algorithm that can be utilized with any given gridded altimetry-derived velocity time-series. The results of this research will improve understanding of mixing in the ocean and our ability to model the transport of ocean-borne material with applications to a wide range of marine-based human activities.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>04/06/2010</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/21/2015</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.050</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>0962054</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Kendall</FirstName>
<LastName>Smith</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>S</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Kendall S Smith</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>shafer@cims.nyu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2129983176</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000292378</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/06/2010</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>New York University</Name>
<CityName>NEW YORK</CityName>
<ZipCode>100121019</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2129982121</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>70 WASHINGTON SQUARE S</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>10</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NY10</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>041968306</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>NEW YORK UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>041968306</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[New York University]]></Name>
<CityName>NEW YORK</CityName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<ZipCode>100121019</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[70 WASHINGTON SQUARE S]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>10</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NY10</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1610</Code>
<Text>PHYSICAL OCEANOGRAPHY</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0110</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2010~643325</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p class="p1"><span class="s1">The fundamental obstacle to our understanding of and ability to predict the ocean&rsquo;s circulation &mdash; the flywheel of Earth&rsquo;s climate &mdash; is the fact that we cannot &ldquo;see&rdquo; its interior with sufficient spatial and temporal detail.&nbsp; Direct measurements of the sub-surface rely on a sparse network of ship-based surveys and autonomous drifters and float.&nbsp; The surface itself, however, is observed globally by satellites, which measure its temperature and local elevation, from which currents in the upper ocean can be inferred.&nbsp; The inference uses a model based on knowledge of the physics, but only applies for some scales of motion, and the satellite measurements are limited in spatial resolution.&nbsp; As a result, estimates of the subsurface currents are limited in accuracy to roughly the first hundred meters in depth, and cannot reveal motions at horizontal scales smaller than about 100 kilometers. &nbsp;</span></p> <p class="p1"><span class="s1">The principle goals of the research conducted with support of this grant were to develop new methods to extend the range and accuracy of inferred subsurface currents to greater depths and smaller horizontal scales.&nbsp; This requires both investigation of the physics of the flows at the scales of interest, as well as new theories and algorithms to extract more information from the measurements.&nbsp; Our approach is to use numerical models to simulate real flows, both as a laboratory with which to better understand the physics, and as a testbed for new methods. &nbsp;</span>The major results include:</p> <p class="p1"><span class="s1">1. &nbsp; A method to use stochastic models to represent unresolved flow features such as small-scale eddies and fronts, with parameters that can be learned 'on-the-fly' from the observations themselves. Moreover, the methods exploit the fact that information about unresolved flow features are aliased into scales observed directly by satellites. By extracting this information, one can construct 'stochastically super-resolved&rsquo; velocity fields with a nominal resolution increase of a factor of two or more, and these fields can be used to infer lateral transport of heat and other tracers by the super-resolved flow.&nbsp;</span></p> <p class="p1"><span class="s1">2.&nbsp; A new set of &lsquo;basis functions&rsquo; that better represent motion at depth, given knowledge of the surface.&nbsp; Such functions can be used to infer (with imperfect accuracy) motion at depths of order one kilometer below the surface from an instantaneous snapshot of the surface temperature and height.</span></p> <p class="p1"><span class="s1">3.&nbsp; A new idealized model, with two parameters, that allows us to represent the range of mean flows found in the ocean, and thereby characterize the geography of the kind of fluid instabilities that generate eddies, and understand their nonlinear evolution, sizes and energies as a function of location on the globe. &nbsp; This is crucial to the tools developed in items 1 and 2. &nbsp;</span></p> <p class="p1"><span class="s1">This research discussed here was performed by the PI, former postdoctoral researcher Shane Keating, and former PhD student Xiao Xiao, all of whom received support from this grant.</span></p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 01/07/2016<br>      Modified by: Kendall&nbsp;S&nbsp;Smith</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[The fundamental obstacle to our understanding of and ability to predict the oceanÆs circulation &mdash; the flywheel of EarthÆs climate &mdash; is the fact that we cannot "see" its interior with sufficient spatial and temporal detail.  Direct measurements of the sub-surface rely on a sparse network of ship-based surveys and autonomous drifters and float.  The surface itself, however, is observed globally by satellites, which measure its temperature and local elevation, from which currents in the upper ocean can be inferred.  The inference uses a model based on knowledge of the physics, but only applies for some scales of motion, and the satellite measurements are limited in spatial resolution.  As a result, estimates of the subsurface currents are limited in accuracy to roughly the first hundred meters in depth, and cannot reveal motions at horizontal scales smaller than about 100 kilometers.   The principle goals of the research conducted with support of this grant were to develop new methods to extend the range and accuracy of inferred subsurface currents to greater depths and smaller horizontal scales.  This requires both investigation of the physics of the flows at the scales of interest, as well as new theories and algorithms to extract more information from the measurements.  Our approach is to use numerical models to simulate real flows, both as a laboratory with which to better understand the physics, and as a testbed for new methods.  The major results include: 1.   A method to use stochastic models to represent unresolved flow features such as small-scale eddies and fronts, with parameters that can be learned 'on-the-fly' from the observations themselves. Moreover, the methods exploit the fact that information about unresolved flow features are aliased into scales observed directly by satellites. By extracting this information, one can construct 'stochastically super-resolvedÆ velocity fields with a nominal resolution increase of a factor of two or more, and these fields can be used to infer lateral transport of heat and other tracers by the super-resolved flow.  2.  A new set of æbasis functionsÆ that better represent motion at depth, given knowledge of the surface.  Such functions can be used to infer (with imperfect accuracy) motion at depths of order one kilometer below the surface from an instantaneous snapshot of the surface temperature and height. 3.  A new idealized model, with two parameters, that allows us to represent the range of mean flows found in the ocean, and thereby characterize the geography of the kind of fluid instabilities that generate eddies, and understand their nonlinear evolution, sizes and energies as a function of location on the globe.   This is crucial to the tools developed in items 1 and 2.   This research discussed here was performed by the PI, former postdoctoral researcher Shane Keating, and former PhD student Xiao Xiao, all of whom received support from this grant.          Last Modified: 01/07/2016       Submitted by: Kendall S Smith]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
