<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>A Sustainable Energy Concepts Professional Development Model for Rural Schools and Its Extension to a Systemic Approach for Integrating STEM Research and Education</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/15/2010</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>02/28/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>1250000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>1250000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>11040100</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>EHR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DUE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Undergraduate Education</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Kathleen Bergin</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>kbergin@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032925171</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The Purdue University Innovation through Institutional Integration (I-3) project, "A Sustainable Energy Concepts Professional Development Model for Rural Schools and Its Extension to a Systemic Approach for Integrating STEM Research and Education" brings together an NSF/EHR Noyce award with other Purdue University programs around the I-3 integrative themes for broadening participation and the integration of research and education.  It is an innovative effort to establish a systemic approach which connects interdisciplinary STEM research activities with educational pursuits and has a deliberate focus on broadening participation in STEM disciplines in rural communities.  The project model is designed to engage teachers in rural high schools with researchers and their research activities.  Rural teachers and their students will be involved in global "grand challenge" research endeavors, initially associated with biofuels and sustainable energies, in order to spark interest in STEM disciplines.  &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The project uses a two-tiered approach: 1. The education and research integration model which consists of two parts: a) a professional development program that engages rural pre-service and in-service high school teachers in Indiana around sustainable energy research activities; and b) support of teachers in transforming their curricula and classroom practice by incorporating concepts of sustainable energy. 2. Refinement and establishment of a systemic approach for integrating research and educational activities using this model.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Purdue University is leveraging its existing strengths in interdisciplinary research and educational engagement through the integration of the following projects:  the NSF funded Noyce Scholars program for Preparation of Rural High School STEM Teachers; the Woodrow Wilson STEM Goes Rural Initiative; the Department of Energy Energy Frontier Research Center: C3Bio; the existing I-STEM (Indiana STEM) Resources Network; and the Purdue Rural Schools Network. The project is coordinated by the Discovery Learning Research Center, an educational research center at Purdue, in collaboration with the Office of the Provost and the Office of the Vice President for Research.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The model development component of this project provides summer experiences for teams of in-service and pre-service teachers through short courses in sustainable energy topics, developed in coordination with the scientists of C3Bio.  These teams take part in (and receive graduate school credits for) a problem-based learning (PBL) summer course in which they develop their own PBL units on sustainable energy to use in their classrooms.  During the academic year, teachers continue their interactions with one another, as well as with Purdue scientists and program personnel, through regional summits, web-enabled meetings and social networking.  Each year, the leadership team reviews evaluation data towards developing a generalizable framework for integrating research with education. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The project directly impacts approximately forty rural in-service teachers, eighty pre-service rural teachers and all of their students.  An additional approximately 400 rural in-service teachers and their students are indirectly impacted through academic year outreach activities of the project.  The ultimate outcome of this project is to develop a systemic approach to integrating research with education, allowing Purdue University to sustain the transformation of STEM education through the continued integration of cutting-edge STEM research with education using the refined project model.  &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The development, design, and evaluation will provide descriptive and empirical program models that can be replicated/modified in other situations. In addition, the project will contribute to the research base on rural STEM education.  This includes identifying and understanding factors that have an impact on improving preparation and retention of teachers in rural schools, as well as on the preparation and recruitment of rural students to STEM disciplines.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/20/2010</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/10/2015</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.076</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>0963621</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Timothy</FirstName>
<LastName>Sands</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>D</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Timothy D Sands</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>tsands@purdue.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>7654966105</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000451981</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/20/2010</StartDate>
<EndDate>04/21/2015</EndDate>
<RoleCode>Former Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Gabriela</FirstName>
<LastName>Weaver</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>C</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Gabriela C Weaver</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>gweaver@umass.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>4135450629</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000458095</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/20/2010</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Eric</FirstName>
<LastName>Riggs</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>M</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Eric M Riggs</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>emriggs@geos.tamu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>9798456529</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000384910</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/20/2010</StartDate>
<EndDate>08/19/2014</EndDate>
<RoleCode>Former Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Peggy</FirstName>
<LastName>Ertmer</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Peggy Ertmer</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>pertmer@purdue.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>7654944600</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000419862</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/20/2010</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Maureen</FirstName>
<LastName>McCann</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Maureen McCann</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>mmccann@purdue.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>7654969640</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000113431</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/20/2010</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Lisa</FirstName>
<LastName>Kirkham</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Lisa Kirkham</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>lkirkham@purdue.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>7654941055</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000661762</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/10/2015</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Debasish</FirstName>
<LastName>Dutta</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Debasish Dutta</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>dutta@purdue.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>7654949709</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000694384</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/21/2015</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Purdue University</Name>
<CityName>West Lafayette</CityName>
<ZipCode>479072114</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>7654941055</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>Young Hall</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[155 S Grant Street]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Indiana</StateName>
<StateCode>IN</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>IN04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>072051394</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>PURDUE UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>072051394</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Purdue University]]></Name>
<CityName>West Lafayette</CityName>
<StateCode>IN</StateCode>
<ZipCode>479072114</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[Young Hall]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Indiana</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>IN04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1795</Code>
<Text>Robert Noyce Scholarship Pgm</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9177</Code>
<Text>ELEMENTARY/SECONDARY EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>SMET</Code>
<Text>SCIENCE, MATH, ENG &amp; TECH EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>04XX</Code>
<Name>NSF Education &amp; Human Resource</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040106</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2010~502378</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2012~250000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2013~250000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~247622</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The goal of this project was to develop a systemic approach to connect interdisciplinary STEM research with educational activities.&nbsp; We proposed a two-tiered approach for developing a best practice model for delivering advanced science research topics into high school curricula:</p> <p>1. Develop a model for education and research integration that will consist of two parts:</p> <p>a. Initiate a professional development program that engages rural pre-service and in-service high school teachers in Indiana around sustainable energy research activities</p> <p>b. Support these teachers to transform their curricula and classroom practice by incorporating concepts of sustainable energy</p> <p>2.&nbsp; Use this model as a framework to establish a systemic approach for integrating research and education activities</p> <p>Over five years, program iteration continually improved this model for integrating research and education activities.&nbsp; Results of data collected from participants shaped the professional development program.&nbsp; In addition, debriefings with key personnel provided important insights that also formed the program.&nbsp; Results provided 1.) critical structures, 2.) key personnel and 3.) key steps necessary to develop strong professional development to connect grand challenge research and educational activities.</p> <p>Critical Structures:</p> <ul> <li>Scientists and engineers from 'grand challenge' research teams participate in some significant role and are actively prepared for that role</li> <li>Learning goals address both problem-based learning (PBL) and an interdisciplinary 'grand challenge' STEM topic</li> <li>A professional development program is team taught by PBL-focused and science-focused instructors</li> <li>Experienced "master teachers" serve as PBL coaches; PBL guest speakers are included</li> <li>Teachers produce a usable PBL unit on the cutting-edge STEM topic</li> <li>Teachers are provided with academic year support</li> </ul> <p>Key Personnel and Key Steps effect Critical Structures.</p> <p>Key Personnel:</p> <p>Identify <strong>Researchers</strong> from the 'grand challenge' topic who connect easily with people outside their field.&nbsp; They engage with teachers through semi-formal presentations.&nbsp; Researchers' work is very interdisciplinary, but they link presentations to a specific area of instruction: biological sciences, physical sciences, or mathematics.&nbsp; Teachers do high-school level science activities throughout the workshop, gaining in science knowledge.&nbsp; Research presentations are interspersed through the professional development program as teachers' knowledge level increases.</p> <p>Problem-based Learning (PBL) is the chosen pedagogy for the professional development program because it most closely resembles the work of researchers: identifying problems and questions, then engineering creative ways to solve those problems and answer questions.&nbsp; Teachers learn PBL from a <strong>PBL expert</strong>.&nbsp; Teachers develop a PBL unit during the professional development program.&nbsp; At the end, each teacher has a two-plus week unit suitable for the classroom.&nbsp; The <strong>PBL expert </strong>guides the teachers through the PBL unit development process.</p> <p>A <strong>science expert </strong>is available every day to answer teachers' questions about science content.&nbsp; Typically, a graduate student works with the project for the two weeks.&nbsp; This onsite expert deepens understandings begun by researchers' presentations.</p> <p>A <strong>college-level science educator </strong>makes up part of the team.&nbsp; The science educator moves between science content at the professional and high-school levels, and is fluent regarding PBL, helping teachers make connections across these.&nbsp; The science educator also designs and implements the science activities.&nbsp; This person can be a faculty member or graduate student in science education.</p> <p>Former participants return as <strong>Mentor Teachers </strong>to support current participants.</p> <p><strong>Teachers</strong> are obviously an integral component. Teachers can be at any career stage, teaching any STEM subject.&nbsp; However, Physical and Life Sciences are best fits for integration.&nbsp; Math was difficult due to the skills-based nature of the subject matter.&nbsp; Technology/Engineering were only part of our program one year.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>Lessons learned allowed iterations to improve the workshop.&nbsp; As the professional development program matured, key steps for implementation began to surface.</p> <p>Key Steps:</p> <ul> <li>Researchers must identify basic scientifc concepts their work entails.&nbsp; for example, nanotechnology researchers must explicitly identify size and scale, size dependent properties, forces, self-assembly, and surface area-to-volume ratio concepts</li> <li>Professional development must be planned for researchers to help them share their research at an appropriate level for use by grade 9-12 teachers in their classrooms</li> <li>Researcher delivery of presentations should be strategically limited to the development of content knowledge throughout the professional development program</li> <li>Scientific content must be mapped to state teaching standards and next Generation Science Standards (NGSS) making it relevant for teachers</li> <li>Professional development for teachers must include illustrative activities that demonstrate scientific concepts and these must be mapped to state and NGSS teaching standards</li> <li>The professional development must enable teachers to integrate the research content and PBL in meaningful ways</li> <li>Packets explicitly outlining activities and connections to standards should be given to teachers</li> <li>Follow-up during the academic year is important; this can occur using webinars, virtual field trips and presentations at state, regional, and national conferences</li> </ul> <p>Our findings indicate Critical Structures, enacted by Key Personnel through Key Steps, are necessary to achieve high quality professional development linking research and education.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 05/30/2017<br>      Modified by: Lisa&nbsp;Kirkham</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The goal of this project was to develop a systemic approach to connect interdisciplinary STEM research with educational activities.  We proposed a two-tiered approach for developing a best practice model for delivering advanced science research topics into high school curricula:  1. Develop a model for education and research integration that will consist of two parts:  a. Initiate a professional development program that engages rural pre-service and in-service high school teachers in Indiana around sustainable energy research activities  b. Support these teachers to transform their curricula and classroom practice by incorporating concepts of sustainable energy  2.  Use this model as a framework to establish a systemic approach for integrating research and education activities  Over five years, program iteration continually improved this model for integrating research and education activities.  Results of data collected from participants shaped the professional development program.  In addition, debriefings with key personnel provided important insights that also formed the program.  Results provided 1.) critical structures, 2.) key personnel and 3.) key steps necessary to develop strong professional development to connect grand challenge research and educational activities.  Critical Structures:  Scientists and engineers from 'grand challenge' research teams participate in some significant role and are actively prepared for that role Learning goals address both problem-based learning (PBL) and an interdisciplinary 'grand challenge' STEM topic A professional development program is team taught by PBL-focused and science-focused instructors Experienced "master teachers" serve as PBL coaches; PBL guest speakers are included Teachers produce a usable PBL unit on the cutting-edge STEM topic Teachers are provided with academic year support   Key Personnel and Key Steps effect Critical Structures.  Key Personnel:  Identify Researchers from the 'grand challenge' topic who connect easily with people outside their field.  They engage with teachers through semi-formal presentations.  Researchers' work is very interdisciplinary, but they link presentations to a specific area of instruction: biological sciences, physical sciences, or mathematics.  Teachers do high-school level science activities throughout the workshop, gaining in science knowledge.  Research presentations are interspersed through the professional development program as teachers' knowledge level increases.  Problem-based Learning (PBL) is the chosen pedagogy for the professional development program because it most closely resembles the work of researchers: identifying problems and questions, then engineering creative ways to solve those problems and answer questions.  Teachers learn PBL from a PBL expert.  Teachers develop a PBL unit during the professional development program.  At the end, each teacher has a two-plus week unit suitable for the classroom.  The PBL expert guides the teachers through the PBL unit development process.  A science expert is available every day to answer teachers' questions about science content.  Typically, a graduate student works with the project for the two weeks.  This onsite expert deepens understandings begun by researchers' presentations.  A college-level science educator makes up part of the team.  The science educator moves between science content at the professional and high-school levels, and is fluent regarding PBL, helping teachers make connections across these.  The science educator also designs and implements the science activities.  This person can be a faculty member or graduate student in science education.  Former participants return as Mentor Teachers to support current participants.  Teachers are obviously an integral component. Teachers can be at any career stage, teaching any STEM subject.  However, Physical and Life Sciences are best fits for integration.  Math was difficult due to the skills-based nature of the subject matter.  Technology/Engineering were only part of our program one year.     Lessons learned allowed iterations to improve the workshop.  As the professional development program matured, key steps for implementation began to surface.  Key Steps:  Researchers must identify basic scientifc concepts their work entails.  for example, nanotechnology researchers must explicitly identify size and scale, size dependent properties, forces, self-assembly, and surface area-to-volume ratio concepts Professional development must be planned for researchers to help them share their research at an appropriate level for use by grade 9-12 teachers in their classrooms Researcher delivery of presentations should be strategically limited to the development of content knowledge throughout the professional development program Scientific content must be mapped to state teaching standards and next Generation Science Standards (NGSS) making it relevant for teachers Professional development for teachers must include illustrative activities that demonstrate scientific concepts and these must be mapped to state and NGSS teaching standards The professional development must enable teachers to integrate the research content and PBL in meaningful ways Packets explicitly outlining activities and connections to standards should be given to teachers Follow-up during the academic year is important; this can occur using webinars, virtual field trips and presentations at state, regional, and national conferences   Our findings indicate Critical Structures, enacted by Key Personnel through Key Steps, are necessary to achieve high quality professional development linking research and education.       Last Modified: 05/30/2017       Submitted by: Lisa Kirkham]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
