<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>RI: Medium: Planning and Control for Dynamic Robotic Manipulation</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>04/15/2010</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>03/31/2016</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>830850.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>854050</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>05020000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>CSE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>IIS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Information &amp; Intelligent Systems</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>jeffrey trinkle</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Manipulation allows a robot to alter its environment by performing mechanical work on it.  Combined with locomotion, autonomous manipulation will be a key enabling capability in future robot systems for exploration, home care, military, industrial, and space applications.  While most current robotic manipulation consists of simple grasp-and-carry operations, the spectrum of manipulation methods is much broader, including throwing, pushing, rolling, sliding, tapping, etc.  Humans and animals make use of these methods on a daily basis, but robots do not.  What is missing is a theoretical framework for combining and sequencing such manipulation methods for automatic planning and control of robotic manipulation.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project is working toward autonomous manipulation by bridging the gap from individual robotic manipulation primitives to full manipulation sequence planning.  The project is developing theoretical tools, a mechanics-based manipulation planning framework, feedback control algorithms, and an experimental manipulation testbed incorporating high-speed vision.  The tools developed for autonomous planning and execution of manipulation sequences will allow future robot users to program robots at a much higher level of abstraction than currently possible.  For example, instead of programming low-level control of motors, the user can simply say "place object A on object B."  This will help grow the field of personal robotics, by allowing non-experts to interact with robots.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;International partners in this work include leading laboratories in Italy and Japan.  These collaborations provide unique access for graduate and undergraduate researchers to the world's leading experts in robotic manipulation.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>04/26/2010</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/23/2013</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.070</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>0964665</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Kevin</FirstName>
<LastName>Lynch</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>M</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Kevin M Lynch</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>kmlynch@northwestern.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>8474675451</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000225559</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/26/2010</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Northwestern University</Name>
<CityName>Chicago</CityName>
<ZipCode>606114579</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>3125037955</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>750 N. Lake Shore Drive</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[Rubloff 7th Floor]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Illinois</StateName>
<StateCode>IL</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>IL07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>160079455</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>NORTHWESTERN UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>005436803</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Northwestern University]]></Name>
<CityName>Chicago</CityName>
<StateCode>IL</StateCode>
<ZipCode>606114579</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[750 N. Lake Shore Drive]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Illinois</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>IL07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7495</Code>
<Text>Robust Intelligence</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>8013</Code>
<Text>NRI-National Robotics Initiati</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7495</Code>
<Text>ROBUST INTELLIGENCE</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7924</Code>
<Text>MEDIUM PROJECT</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8086</Code>
<Text>Natl Robotics Initiative (NRI)</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9251</Code>
<Text>REU SUPP-Res Exp for Ugrd Supp</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0110</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0111</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0112</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0113</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2010~206154</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2011~219366</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2012~412530</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2013~16000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Humans and animals manipulate objects by pushing, throwing, kicking, rolling, sliding, toppling, etc., but robots typically only grasp and carry. &nbsp;This severely limits robots' ability to integrate into the human world, to use human tools, etc. &nbsp;In this project we explored nonprehensile or "graspless" robot manipulation strategies to build toward more dexterous future robots.<br />One line of work pursued under this grant was to use a 6-dof vibratory platform to create a programmable conveyance system, capable of independently controlling the motions of parts on the surface of the platform using sliding friction. &nbsp;This system can be used for sorting, transporting, and positioning and orienting parts prior to assembly by a robot. &nbsp;The two patents generated as part of this work were licensed by an industrial automation company, transferring the research to practice. &nbsp;<br />Another line of work involved leveraging the new "ERIN" robot system developed at Northwestern, consisting of a 7-joint robot arm, a wrist force-torque sensor, a four-fingered hand with tactile sensor fingertips, and a 3D high-speed vision system. &nbsp;We showed that this robot can use fast motions of its hand to reposition and reorient an object within a grasp. &nbsp;This kind of manipulation approaches the dexterity of humans to perform "in-hand manipulation" of a type that has not been done before with robots.<br />A final research thrust involved building a custom 3-joint robot arm to manipulate objects on an air table, which allows us to operate in full Earth gravity down to zero-g environments, as in space. &nbsp;Our 3-joint robot demonstrated throwing, catching, and rolling primitives, all manipulation modes that we hope to combine into a "library" of advanced manipulation capabilities.<br />The project provided research topics for 2 PhD students and several MS and undergrad students. &nbsp;The work was demonstrated during National Robotics Week at the Chicago Museum of Science and Industry, reaching thousands of school-age children. &nbsp;It has resulted in both theoretical advances in robotic manipulation as well as practical advances now being exploited in industrial automation. &nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 06/25/2016<br>      Modified by: Kevin&nbsp;M&nbsp;Lynch</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Image         </div> <div class="galControls onePhoto" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation onePhoto" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2016/0964665/0964665_10015215_1466895365145_ERIN--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2016/0964665/0964665_10015215_1466895365145_ERIN--rgov-800width.jpg" title="The ERIN high-speed manipulation system."><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2016/0964665/0964665_10015215_1466895365145_ERIN--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="The ERIN high-speed manipulation system."></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">The ERIN high-speed manipulation system, capable of high-speed dexterous manipulation.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Jian Shi, Northwestern University</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Public Domain</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Kevin&nbsp;M&nbsp;Lynch</div> <div class="imageTitle">The ERIN high-speed manipulation system.</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Humans and animals manipulate objects by pushing, throwing, kicking, rolling, sliding, toppling, etc., but robots typically only grasp and carry.  This severely limits robots' ability to integrate into the human world, to use human tools, etc.  In this project we explored nonprehensile or "graspless" robot manipulation strategies to build toward more dexterous future robots. One line of work pursued under this grant was to use a 6-dof vibratory platform to create a programmable conveyance system, capable of independently controlling the motions of parts on the surface of the platform using sliding friction.  This system can be used for sorting, transporting, and positioning and orienting parts prior to assembly by a robot.  The two patents generated as part of this work were licensed by an industrial automation company, transferring the research to practice.   Another line of work involved leveraging the new "ERIN" robot system developed at Northwestern, consisting of a 7-joint robot arm, a wrist force-torque sensor, a four-fingered hand with tactile sensor fingertips, and a 3D high-speed vision system.  We showed that this robot can use fast motions of its hand to reposition and reorient an object within a grasp.  This kind of manipulation approaches the dexterity of humans to perform "in-hand manipulation" of a type that has not been done before with robots. A final research thrust involved building a custom 3-joint robot arm to manipulate objects on an air table, which allows us to operate in full Earth gravity down to zero-g environments, as in space.  Our 3-joint robot demonstrated throwing, catching, and rolling primitives, all manipulation modes that we hope to combine into a "library" of advanced manipulation capabilities. The project provided research topics for 2 PhD students and several MS and undergrad students.  The work was demonstrated during National Robotics Week at the Chicago Museum of Science and Industry, reaching thousands of school-age children.  It has resulted in both theoretical advances in robotic manipulation as well as practical advances now being exploited in industrial automation.               Last Modified: 06/25/2016       Submitted by: Kevin M Lynch]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
