<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Collaborative Research:  Examining Emotional Reactions to Standards of Justice</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2010</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2013</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>98155.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>98155</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>04050200</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>SBE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>SES</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Divn Of Social and Economic Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Patricia White</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>SES-0966536&lt;br/&gt;Jody Clay-Warner&lt;br/&gt;Dawn T. Robinson,&lt;br/&gt;University of Georgia&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;SES-0966488&lt;br/&gt;Lynn Smith-Lovin&lt;br/&gt;Duke University&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Theories of justice predict that people feel negative emotion when they receive either more than they deserve or less than they deserve. Research consistently confirms that receiving less than one deserves evokes negative emotion.  However, research regarding how people feel when over-rewarded is inconsistent.  The current project investigates the idea that these inconsistencies are the result of employing different standards of justice. The researchers hypothesize that people feel distress and guilt when over-reward results from violation of the equity standard of justice -- which is based on local comparisons with specific others. They also predict that people do not feel distress and guilt when over-reward results from a violation of the referential standard of justice -- which is based on distal comparisons to some generalized expectation. By this logic, a person would feel guilty if he worked the same number of hours as a coworker but was paid more than the coworker.  Conversely, he would not feel guilty if he were paid a higher wage than the typical ?going rate? for a particular job.  In order to test these predictions, the researchers will conduct a series of experiments to examine emotional reactions to over-reward that will disentangle the effects of the justice standard from the effects of contextual factors.  If the predictions are correct, then there may be fundamental differences in equity and referential comparison processes and thus a need for greater specification of justice theory. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Broader Impacts&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This research has broad implications for work settings, for policy discussions and for understanding social movements.  Since the under-rewarded typically lack the ability to gain more resources for themselves, it is often incumbent upon the over-rewarded to remedy unjust inequality.  As a result, understanding how the over-rewarded feel about their favored position will lead to a better understanding of how injustice may be remedied in a variety of settings.  The proposed research will also provide training and mentoring opportunities for a diverse group of undergraduate and graduate research assistants at two institutions</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>04/27/2010</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>04/27/2010</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.075</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>0966536</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Dawn</FirstName>
<LastName>Robinson</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>T</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Dawn T Robinson</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>sodawn@uga.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>7065422421</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000321933</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/27/2010</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Jody</FirstName>
<LastName>Clay-Warner</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Jody Clay-Warner</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>jclayw@uga.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>7065423217</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000350684</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/27/2010</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Georgia Research Foundation Inc</Name>
<CityName>ATHENS</CityName>
<ZipCode>306021589</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>7065425939</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>310 East Campus Rd</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[Tucker Hall Room 409]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Georgia</StateName>
<StateCode>GA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>10</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>GA10</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>004315578</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF GEORGIA RESEARCH FOUNDATION, INC.</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Georgia]]></Name>
<CityName>Athens</CityName>
<StateCode>GA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>306021589</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[310 East Campus Rd]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Georgia</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>10</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>GA10</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<FoaInformation>
<Code>0116000</Code>
<Name>Human Subjects</Name>
</FoaInformation>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1331</Code>
<Text>Sociology</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>0000</Code>
<Text>UNASSIGNED</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>OTHR</Code>
<Text>OTHER RESEARCH OR EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0110</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2010~98155</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>How do people feel when they receive more than they deserve? Under what conditions will individuals intervene to repair an unjust system from which they benefit? While it is well known that people feel angry when they receive less than they deserve, far less is known about emotional responses to over-reward. This issue has implications for understanding how privileged people respond to unjust pay decisions in the workplace and to injustice, more generally. Empirical research has produced apparently conflicting results, with some research finding that people feel guilt and other negative emotions when they receive more than they deserve, while other research finds that people are happy and satisfied when they are over-rewarded. The present research offered a new theoretical understanding of the relationship between justice and emotion.&nbsp; We both explained these earlier findings and offered new insights into the conditions under which individuals will strive toward justice &ndash; even when it does not benefit them personally. We proposed that people feel negative emotions when they are over-benefitted relative to those in their <em>local</em> environment, such as when someone receives higher pay than a coworker who performs the same job and has similar years of experience. In this situation, an equity standard of justice is violated. We predicted, in contrast, that people feel positive emotions when they are over-benefitted relative to other people like them in general, such as when a worker receives a higher salary than is <em>typical</em> for an abstract group of &ldquo;workers like them&rdquo; with similar characteristics and jobs. In this situation, a referential standard of justice is violated. &nbsp;We also sought to understand what it is about the equity and referential standards of justice that lead to differential responses. We predicted that when over-rewarded individuals expect to interact with those who are under-rewarded, which is typical in contexts of equity-based over-reward, they would be more likely to feel guilt and other negative emotions. We similarly expected to see more guilt and negative emotion when the over-reward was public and when the over-reward came at the cost to someone else (zero-sum situations). &nbsp;We performed three laboratory experiments to test our predictions.</p> <p>A key outcome of the project is the finding that the justice standard does affect emotional reactions to over-reward. As predicted, participants who experienced equity-based over-reward reported higher levels of negative emotion, including guilt, than did those who experienced referentially based over-reward. Second, we found that anticipation of future interaction is associated with negative emotional responses to over-reward. Likewise, public over-reward led to higher levels of negative emotions than did private over-reward. Finally, we determined that the zero-sum nature of equity-based over-reward accounts for the strong negative emotional reaction to equity-based over-reward. Levels of guilt, irritability, disgust and embarrassment were higher when over-reward came at the expense of another person. Finally, we discovered an unexpected finding: that people in general have more positive emotions when they can use referential standards to evaluate their rewards than when they can use local equity-based comparisons.&nbsp; This finding has implications for the design of institutional systems&mdash;although the implications for remediating injustice and for keeping people satisfied with unjust pay scales may be at odds with one another.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 11/11/2013<br>      Modified by: Jody&nbsp;Clay-Warner</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ How do people feel when they receive more than they deserve? Under what conditions will individuals intervene to repair an unjust system from which they benefit? While it is well known that people feel angry when they receive less than they deserve, far less is known about emotional responses to over-reward. This issue has implications for understanding how privileged people respond to unjust pay decisions in the workplace and to injustice, more generally. Empirical research has produced apparently conflicting results, with some research finding that people feel guilt and other negative emotions when they receive more than they deserve, while other research finds that people are happy and satisfied when they are over-rewarded. The present research offered a new theoretical understanding of the relationship between justice and emotion.  We both explained these earlier findings and offered new insights into the conditions under which individuals will strive toward justice &ndash; even when it does not benefit them personally. We proposed that people feel negative emotions when they are over-benefitted relative to those in their local environment, such as when someone receives higher pay than a coworker who performs the same job and has similar years of experience. In this situation, an equity standard of justice is violated. We predicted, in contrast, that people feel positive emotions when they are over-benefitted relative to other people like them in general, such as when a worker receives a higher salary than is typical for an abstract group of "workers like them" with similar characteristics and jobs. In this situation, a referential standard of justice is violated.  We also sought to understand what it is about the equity and referential standards of justice that lead to differential responses. We predicted that when over-rewarded individuals expect to interact with those who are under-rewarded, which is typical in contexts of equity-based over-reward, they would be more likely to feel guilt and other negative emotions. We similarly expected to see more guilt and negative emotion when the over-reward was public and when the over-reward came at the cost to someone else (zero-sum situations).  We performed three laboratory experiments to test our predictions.  A key outcome of the project is the finding that the justice standard does affect emotional reactions to over-reward. As predicted, participants who experienced equity-based over-reward reported higher levels of negative emotion, including guilt, than did those who experienced referentially based over-reward. Second, we found that anticipation of future interaction is associated with negative emotional responses to over-reward. Likewise, public over-reward led to higher levels of negative emotions than did private over-reward. Finally, we determined that the zero-sum nature of equity-based over-reward accounts for the strong negative emotional reaction to equity-based over-reward. Levels of guilt, irritability, disgust and embarrassment were higher when over-reward came at the expense of another person. Finally, we discovered an unexpected finding: that people in general have more positive emotions when they can use referential standards to evaluate their rewards than when they can use local equity-based comparisons.  This finding has implications for the design of institutional systems&mdash;although the implications for remediating injustice and for keeping people satisfied with unjust pay scales may be at odds with one another.       Last Modified: 11/11/2013       Submitted by: Jody Clay-Warner]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
