<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Collaborative Research: pH-responsive Capsules for Enhanced Delivery and Recovery of Cellulases for Biomass Hydrolysis</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/15/2010</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2014</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>309357.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>309357</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07020000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CBET</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Chem, Bioeng, Env, &amp; Transp Sys</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Maria Burka</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>0966574&lt;br/&gt;Voronov&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Effective, efficient, and economical conversion technologies are needed to meet the potential of using biobased feedstocks to produce liquid fuels and other high-value chemicals. Enzymatic hydrolysis of plant cell wall structural carbohydrates into soluble and fermentable sugars has been technically achievable for decades. Despite significant advances in the past five years, the economical production and use of cellulase enzymes for biomass hydrolysis remain key hurdles. This is true whether one is seeking hydrocarbons or economical cellulosic ethanol. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The key to conquering these obstacles according to the collaborating PIs Minko of Clarkson University in Potsdam, NY and Voronov and Pryor of North Dakota State University at Fargo rests in placing the enzymes in nanostructured capsules. These carefully designed and fabricated, hybrid organic-inorganic microcapsules are loaded with a cocktail of cellulase enzymes for the conversion of cellulose into fermentable glucose. These unique capsules protect the enzymes and preserve their activity, allow for a simple reuse/recovery process for the enzymes, and provide an opportunity to regulate enzymatic reactions using external signals, such as pH. This enzyme recovery and reuse, facilitated through the encapsulation process and magnetic separation, are expected to have significant impacts on processing costs to produce biomass-derived sugars. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The PIs plan to create a website as a means of sharing data and plans between the research groups at the two universities, and to allow public access to follow aspects of the project. They intend to utilize REU opportunities and high school researchers as a part of their outreach efforts. This is a challenging project for all of the researchers. There are many synthetic chemistry components that all must come together in the fabrication of the encapsulated enzymes. The successful development of reversible encapsulation technology for applications of enzymes would have far-reaching implications in a number of industrial processes and would constitute a significant advance in the field.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/14/2010</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/14/2010</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>0966574</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Andriy</FirstName>
<LastName>Voronov</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Andriy Voronov</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>andriy.voronov@ndsu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>7012319563</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000517195</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/14/2010</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Scott</FirstName>
<LastName>Pryor</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>W</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Scott W Pryor</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>scott.pryor@ndsu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>7012318432</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000526876</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/14/2010</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>North Dakota State University Fargo</Name>
<CityName>FARGO</CityName>
<ZipCode>581086050</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>7012318045</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>Dept 4000 - PO Box 6050</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[1735 Research Park Drive]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>North Dakota</StateName>
<StateCode>ND</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>00</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>ND00</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>803882299</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>NORTH DAKOTA STATE UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>803882299</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[North Dakota State University Fargo]]></Name>
<CityName>FARGO</CityName>
<StateCode>ND</StateCode>
<ZipCode>581086050</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[Dept 4000 - PO Box 6050]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>North Dakota</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>00</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>ND00</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1401</Code>
<Text>Catalysis</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>044E</Code>
<Text>CATALYSIS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0110</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2010~309357</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Technology for biofuel production may look simple, but only on a paper. One can use biocatalysts (enzymes) to convert cellulose in plant biomass into soluble sugars. The sugars are then fermented into bioethanol which is distilled into the fuel. One of the main challenges with this is approach is that the cost of the enzymes (cellulases) is quite high.&nbsp; Even though enzymes can theoretically be used over and over, there is currently no economical way of separating them after being used in one batch; they are therefore treated like a waste product and disposed. This is a major factor in the relatively high cost of making biofuels from non-food biomass. If there were a way to separate the enzymes, they could be reused to make more biofuel and lower the overall cost.</p> <p>To make the process of enzymatic bioconversion more economical, it may be useful to immobilize or restrain the cellulases on a particle that is easier to separate from the fermentation broth. A challenge with this approach is the need to confirm that they enzymes are similarly effective when they attached to the particles and that they work under the same conditions like temperature and pH. In this work, we developed a technology for cellulase immobilization where the enzymes are attracted to hair-like polymer strands that are attached to the outside of a nano-scale magnetic particle. Due to the presence of the magnetic core, the capsule with the enzymes can be recovered and recycled in at least four successive process cycles.</p> <p>The results show this method of enzyme immobilization is technologically feasible and the enzymes function in a fundamentally different way than other techniques for enzyme immobilization. Enzymes are not rigidly attached to the polymers but are rather just attracted to the outside layer, called a brush, where the enzymes remain mobile.&nbsp; The mobility of the enzymes within the brush layer allows them to function more similarly to the way enzymes would when they are freely dispersed in the solution. The enzymes have a high affinity for the polymer brush but remain reasonably effective at breaking down the cellulose into glucose. The fact that the enzymes are concentrated on the capsule surface appears to be beneficial in keeping the enzymes located at the surface of the solid biomass. We have determined that we can increase the loading of enzymes on the capsule surface without decreasing their effectiveness.&nbsp; This will increase overall process efficiency and help reduce costs. We also showed that the enzymes function similarly to free enzymes under a wide range of normal processing temperatures and pH values. The experiments demonstrated that this method allows the enzymes to produce sugar, or biofuel, yields approximately four-fold larger than with the conventional single use of cellulase enzymes.</p> <p>Although this technology was developed and tested for the biofuel industry, it has applications in a variety of other areas including biomedical applications, food processing, other biobased product industries, and environmental waste treatment.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 09/26/2014<br>      Modified by: Andriy&nbsp;Voronov</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Image         </div> <div class="galControls onePhoto" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation onePhoto" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2014/0966574/0966574_10018497_1411738391349_Capsule_NEW--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2014/0966574/0966574_10018497_1411738391349_Capsule_NEW--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Biocatalytic Capsule for Enzymes Immonilizati...]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Technology for biofuel production may look simple, but only on a paper. One can use biocatalysts (enzymes) to convert cellulose in plant biomass into soluble sugars. The sugars are then fermented into bioethanol which is distilled into the fuel. One of the main challenges with this is approach is that the cost of the enzymes (cellulases) is quite high.  Even though enzymes can theoretically be used over and over, there is currently no economical way of separating them after being used in one batch; they are therefore treated like a waste product and disposed. This is a major factor in the relatively high cost of making biofuels from non-food biomass. If there were a way to separate the enzymes, they could be reused to make more biofuel and lower the overall cost.  To make the process of enzymatic bioconversion more economical, it may be useful to immobilize or restrain the cellulases on a particle that is easier to separate from the fermentation broth. A challenge with this approach is the need to confirm that they enzymes are similarly effective when they attached to the particles and that they work under the same conditions like temperature and pH. In this work, we developed a technology for cellulase immobilization where the enzymes are attracted to hair-like polymer strands that are attached to the outside of a nano-scale magnetic particle. Due to the presence of the magnetic core, the capsule with the enzymes can be recovered and recycled in at least four successive process cycles.  The results show this method of enzyme immobilization is technologically feasible and the enzymes function in a fundamentally different way than other techniques for enzyme immobilization. Enzymes are not rigidly attached to the polymers but are rather just attracted to the outside layer, called a brush, where the enzymes remain mobile.  The mobility of the enzymes within the brush layer allows them to function more similarly to the way enzymes would when they are freely dispersed in the solution. The enzymes have a high affinity for the polymer brush but remain reasonably effective at breaking down the cellulose into glucose. The fact that the enzymes are concentrated on the capsule surface appears to be beneficial in keeping the enzymes located at the surface of the solid biomass. We have determined that we can increase the loading of enzymes on the capsule surface without decreasing their effectiveness.  This will increase overall process efficiency and help reduce costs. We also showed that the enzymes function similarly to free enzymes under a wide range of normal processing temperatures and pH values. The experiments demonstrated that this method allows the enzymes to produce sugar, or biofuel, yields approximately four-fold larger than with the conventional single use of cellulase enzymes.  Although this technology was developed and tested for the biofuel industry, it has applications in a variety of other areas including biomedical applications, food processing, other biobased product industries, and environmental waste treatment.          Last Modified: 09/26/2014       Submitted by: Andriy Voronov]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
