<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Colloidal Assembly of Biodegradable Multifunctional Nanoclusters</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>04/15/2010</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>03/31/2014</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>334875.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>334875</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07020000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CBET</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Chem, Bioeng, Env, &amp; Transp Sys</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Eddie Chang</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>0968038&lt;br/&gt;Johnston&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Intellectual Merit:&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;A major challenge in nanotechnology is to design stable particles smaller than 100 nm with multifunctionality, and in particular, strong optical and magnetic properties. It is difficult to achieve the required particle morphology in the common approach of atomic growth guided by surfactants. Thus, a robust and flexible alternative will be developed to assemble ~5 nm nanoparticle building blocks physically into multifunctional nanoclusters. This colloidal kinetic and interfacial assembly concept will be developed to obtain simultaneously sizes below 100 nm and extremely high loadings (&gt;80%) of gold and iron oxide particles to produce strong optical (NIR absorbance) and magnetic (magnetic moment/volume and spin-spin relaxivity, r2) properties. In addition, these clusters will disassemble back into the original primary nanoparticles upon breakdown of biodegradable polymer stabilizers, which is very important for their translation to the biomedical field.  Specifically, nanoclusters with high loadings of closely paced gold and iron oxide nanoparticles will be formed by tuning the colloidal interactions to control the cluster growth, size, and morphology. Weakly adsorbed polymer stabilizers will favor much higher inorganic particle loadings than in the case of equilibrium self-assembly, as well as cluster biodegradation. The spatial orientation of each type of nanoparticle in the cluster will be analyzed by high resolution TEM and TEM tomography at various tilt angles for a variety of nanoparticle compositions, surface coatings and stablilizing polymers. The NIR surface plasmon resonance and the spin-spin magnetic relaxivity will be measured and explained in terms of the cluster morphology. The cluster de-aggregation will be monitored in solution with spectroscopy and dynamic light scattering and in live cells with hyperspectral optical imaging and transmission electron microscopy. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Broader Impact: &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This robust kinetic assembly platform for the design of biodegradable nanoclusters with high inorganic particle loadings for strong multifunctional properties will offer broad opportunities in microelectronics, sensors, imaging and optoelectronics. The simplicity and flexibility of this colloidal approach to form novel classes of nanoclusters will likely spawn numerous experimental and theoretical studies to understand the relationship between the optical/magnetic properties and nanocluster morphology. Furthermore, the optical/magnetic nanoparticles can provide solutions to one of the major challenges of modern medicine efficient delivery of therapeutics and molecular specific treatment of pathology with real-time imaging (photoacoustic imaging and MRI) for guidance and monitoring. The biodegradation of nanoclusters into primary nanoparticles can overcome the major roadblock in nanotechnology that is toxicity upon accumulation in humans and in the broader environment.  &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;A key theme will be to show young students that engineering can play a major role in improving health care, by integrating scientific concepts in chemistry and biology to address practical problems. The PIs will develop educational material, laboratory experiments and provide student teachers for the nationally renowned UTeach Outreach program, which provides undergraduate students to serve as volunteer instructors for science lessons in the Austin Independent School District. In the UTeach Young Scientists Summer Camps, rising sixth grade students from heavily Hispanic elementary Schools will come to University of Texas for one week to participate in hands-on inquiry-based science lessons that stress academic rigor.  The PIs will add an engineering component to the science lessons and the summer camp to complement current efforts in chemistry and biology.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>04/08/2010</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>01/06/2012</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>0968038</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Keith</FirstName>
<LastName>Johnston</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>P</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Keith P Johnston</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>kpj@che.utexas.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5124714617</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000343007</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/08/2010</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Konstantin</FirstName>
<LastName>Sokolov</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Konstantin Sokolov</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>kostia@mail.utexas.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5124717440</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000388170</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/08/2010</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Texas at Austin</Name>
<CityName>Austin</CityName>
<ZipCode>787595316</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5124716424</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>3925 W Braker Lane, Ste 3.340</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Texas</StateName>
<StateCode>TX</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>10</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>TX10</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>170230239</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF TEXAS AT AUSTIN</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>042000273</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Texas at Austin]]></Name>
<CityName>Austin</CityName>
<StateCode>TX</StateCode>
<ZipCode>787595316</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[3925 W Braker Lane, Ste 3.340]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Texas</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>10</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>TX10</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1414</Code>
<Text>INTERFAC PROCESSES &amp; THERMODYN</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1415</Code>
<Text>PMP-Particul&amp;MultiphaseProcess</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>051E</Code>
<Text>Interfacial trans &amp; thermodynamic</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7237</Code>
<Text>NANO NON-SOLIC SCI &amp; ENG AWD</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0110</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0112</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2010~223250</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2012~111625</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Small gold nanoparticles may be injected into the bloodstream in order to image and treat cancer tumors upon absorbing near-infrared (NIR) radiation from a laser source. As the particles heat up, they produce acoustic waves that are shown as ultrasonic images of the tumor.&nbsp; Despite over a decade of research to design these gold particles, the translation from the lab to the clinic has been limited by concerns about their toxicity, if they are not cleared from the body.&nbsp; Presently, particles greater than about 40 nm are desired for strong absorbance of NIR light, where the blood is most transparent. These particles are too large for kidney clearance through the urine. Previous studies have indicated that nanoparticles with sizes less than ~ 6 nm may be cleared through the kidneys, but such small particles do not absorb NIR radiation. To overcome this dilemma, Johnston, Sokolov and their students in this grant have discovered and developed Au particles that absorb NIR light and then disassemble into particles smaller than 6 nm, which would be small enough for clearance through the kidneys.&nbsp;</p> <p>In this proposal, a number of challenges were overcome for the design of the biodegradable gold nanoparticles. Primary particles smaller than 6 nm were assembled into clusters with sizes from 30 to 100 nm, called nanoclusters. The nanoclusters exhibited very strong absorbance in the NIR region, and later reversibly underwent biodegradation back to primary particles. In order to control the assembly, it was important to coat the Au primary particles with the proper small molecules termed ligands. The ligands stabilize these particles, but also allow for the particles to form nanoclusters. The nanocluster formation was controlled upon mixing a dispersion of gold nanoparticles with a biodegradable polymer coating and evaporating the solvent, water. The polymer coating held the nanoclusters together. Upon biodegradation of the polymer, the nanoclusters completely dissociated back to the primary particles. A theory was developed to explain the size of the nanoclusters in terms of the charge on the primary particles and the relevant concentrations and amount of added biodegradable polymer.</p> <p>In order for the primary particles to remain smaller than 6 nm, it was necessary that they do not adsorb proteins in blood serum. It was discovered that upon coating gold particle surfaces with a mixture of two ligands, not even a single protein molecule adsorbed on the particle surface. This result was unexpected given that the particles were charged. This breakthrough may have broad implications for the design of a wide range of biomaterials for many applications.</p> <p>This project was the outgrowth of their earlier work in an NSF Science and Technology Center on Environmentally Responsible Solvents and Processes and a multiyear grant from the Dow Chemical Company to study poorly water soluble drug nanotechnology. This grant spawned numerous other studies. Johnston and collaborators including Tom Truskett have advanced a platform technology of self-assembly of nanoparticles to form nanoclusters of these particles for both inorganic and organic materials. With NIH funding we are studying these particles in cells and mice with the ultimate goal of translation to the clinic. We are also tuning colloidal interactions of therapeutic protein solutions to form low viscosity dispersions for subcutaneous injection to treat a wide range of diseases. This work has attracted funding from NSF in the <strong>INSPIRE</strong> awards program, intended to encourage investigators to submit bold, exceptional proposals,&nbsp;and by biopharmaceutical companies. In this work, Johnston is collaborating with Tom Truskett and Jennifer Maynard, both professors in his department. Finally the concept has been extended to magnetic particle nanoclusters that are being investigated for electromagnet...]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Small gold nanoparticles may be injected into the bloodstream in order to image and treat cancer tumors upon absorbing near-infrared (NIR) radiation from a laser source. As the particles heat up, they produce acoustic waves that are shown as ultrasonic images of the tumor.  Despite over a decade of research to design these gold particles, the translation from the lab to the clinic has been limited by concerns about their toxicity, if they are not cleared from the body.  Presently, particles greater than about 40 nm are desired for strong absorbance of NIR light, where the blood is most transparent. These particles are too large for kidney clearance through the urine. Previous studies have indicated that nanoparticles with sizes less than ~ 6 nm may be cleared through the kidneys, but such small particles do not absorb NIR radiation. To overcome this dilemma, Johnston, Sokolov and their students in this grant have discovered and developed Au particles that absorb NIR light and then disassemble into particles smaller than 6 nm, which would be small enough for clearance through the kidneys.   In this proposal, a number of challenges were overcome for the design of the biodegradable gold nanoparticles. Primary particles smaller than 6 nm were assembled into clusters with sizes from 30 to 100 nm, called nanoclusters. The nanoclusters exhibited very strong absorbance in the NIR region, and later reversibly underwent biodegradation back to primary particles. In order to control the assembly, it was important to coat the Au primary particles with the proper small molecules termed ligands. The ligands stabilize these particles, but also allow for the particles to form nanoclusters. The nanocluster formation was controlled upon mixing a dispersion of gold nanoparticles with a biodegradable polymer coating and evaporating the solvent, water. The polymer coating held the nanoclusters together. Upon biodegradation of the polymer, the nanoclusters completely dissociated back to the primary particles. A theory was developed to explain the size of the nanoclusters in terms of the charge on the primary particles and the relevant concentrations and amount of added biodegradable polymer.  In order for the primary particles to remain smaller than 6 nm, it was necessary that they do not adsorb proteins in blood serum. It was discovered that upon coating gold particle surfaces with a mixture of two ligands, not even a single protein molecule adsorbed on the particle surface. This result was unexpected given that the particles were charged. This breakthrough may have broad implications for the design of a wide range of biomaterials for many applications.  This project was the outgrowth of their earlier work in an NSF Science and Technology Center on Environmentally Responsible Solvents and Processes and a multiyear grant from the Dow Chemical Company to study poorly water soluble drug nanotechnology. This grant spawned numerous other studies. Johnston and collaborators including Tom Truskett have advanced a platform technology of self-assembly of nanoparticles to form nanoclusters of these particles for both inorganic and organic materials. With NIH funding we are studying these particles in cells and mice with the ultimate goal of translation to the clinic. We are also tuning colloidal interactions of therapeutic protein solutions to form low viscosity dispersions for subcutaneous injection to treat a wide range of diseases. This work has attracted funding from NSF in the INSPIRE awards program, intended to encourage investigators to submit bold, exceptional proposals, and by biopharmaceutical companies. In this work, Johnston is collaborating with Tom Truskett and Jennifer Maynard, both professors in his department. Finally the concept has been extended to magnetic particle nanoclusters that are being investigated for electromagnetic imaging of oil and gas reservoirs in a program funded by 8 industrial companies. The work has been presented in un...]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
