<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Astronomical Consequences of Fundamental Physics</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2011</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2015</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>120000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>120000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03010000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>PHY</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Physics</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Keith Dienes</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>kdienes@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032925314</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This award funds the research activities of Professors Ira Wasserman, Eanna Flanagan, and Rachel Bean at Cornell University.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;It has been more than a decade since the first hints that the expansion of the Universe is accelerating were inferred from observations of Type Ia supernovae at cosmological distances. This unexpected observation could be explained if the Universe is pervaded by dark energy, which could be in the form of a cosmological constant.  Although particle theories, including string theory, can accommodate a cosmological constant, they generally require a much larger value than is compatible with the nature of the Universe revealed by cosmological observations.  As a result, the ultimate cause of the acceleration of the Universe remains obscure, and other theoretical possibilities exist. The research of Wasserman, Flanagan, and Bean will examine these important issues in various different studies.  One study will examine how accurately it can be established that the dark energy is indeed a cosmological constant.  The PI's will also investigate phenomenological implications of higher dimensions for the expansion of the Universe.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This research will also have broader impacts, primarily via the training of Cornell Ph.D. students. The proposed research is multidisciplinary in nature, and will further develop already-existing ties between the particle physics, string theory and relativity groups at Cornell. In addition to disseminating their work via conventional academic channels (journal publications, seminars, conferences), the three investigators are deeply involved in programs aimed at communicating the latest scientific results to the general public.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/24/2011</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/08/2013</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>0968820</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Ira</FirstName>
<LastName>Wasserman</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>M</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Ira M Wasserman</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>ira@astro.cornell.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6072555867</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000173059</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/24/2011</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Eanna</FirstName>
<LastName>Flanagan</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Eanna Flanagan</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>flanagan@astro.cornell.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6072556534</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000488446</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/24/2011</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Rachel</FirstName>
<LastName>Bean</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>E</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Rachel E Bean</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>rbean@astro.cornell.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6072544920</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000198774</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/24/2011</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Cornell University</Name>
<CityName>Ithaca</CityName>
<ZipCode>148502820</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6072555014</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>373 Pine Tree Road</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>23</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NY23</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>872612445</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>CORNELL UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>002254837</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Cornell University]]></Name>
<CityName>Ithaca</CityName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<ZipCode>148502820</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[373 Pine Tree Road]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>23</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NY23</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1288</Code>
<Text>Particle Astrophysics &amp; Cosmol</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7969</Code>
<Text>FY 2010 Funding for PTR</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0111</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0112</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0113</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2011~40000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2012~40000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2013~40000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>INTELLECTUAL MERIT</p> <p>The expansion of the Universe is accelerating. There is still no definitive explanation for this empirical fact.</p> <p>A possible explanation is that the Universe is pervaded by dark energy, which may be a cosmological constant that never changes in time or varies in space, but may also be a completely new ``dynamical field'' that permeates the Universe but varies in time and space.</p> <p>Another possible explanation is that gravity is not well-described by the General Relativity on very large length and time scales, where the theory is untested.</p> <p>The research done on this grant probed these questions via a number of different investigations. One study investigated the effect of large scale structure on observed luminosities of distant light sources, and found typical variations of order a few percent, which would complicate the analysis of observations aiming to trace the time variation of dark energy. Other studies investigated ``effective theories'' that allow general modelling of both cosmic acceleration and the effects of modifying the properties of gravity on large scales. These studies have led to a generally applicable framework capable of addressing whether cosmic acceleration is due to dark energy or to new properties of gravity that only are discernible on cosmological distance and time scales.</p> <p>Not only is the expansion of the Universe accelerating today, but cosmological observations strongly support the notion that there was a period of super-rapid cosmic acceleration called inflation that ended with the onset of the Big Bang phase of cosmological evolution. Although some of the essential features of inflation have been determined reasonably well from observations, others remain unconstrained. One example is the duration of inflation. Observations indicate that the Universe is very nearly flat spatially, and that the temperature of the Cosmic Microwave Background Radiation (CMBR) is nearly uniform across the sky. A minimum duration of the inflationary period is needed to account for these observed properties of the Universe, but the actual duration could be far longer. Can observations tell if inflation did not last much longer than the minimum required duration? A study performed during this project indicates that CMBR observations in the near future will not be sensitive enough to probe this fundamental question.</p> <p>BROADER IMPACT</p> <p>During the period covered by this grant, research was done in collaboration<br />with graduate students and young postdocs who had just completed their PhDs. These vital collaborations contribute to the training of new generations of scientists, some of whom continue in academia, and others who move into other areas that employ their quantitative and computational skills. In addition to disseminating their work via conventional academic channels (journal publications, seminars, conferences) the senior investigators continued their commitment to educating the general public via lectures and essays. Some of this outreach has been done via interactions with Cornell alumni who are members of the Department of Astronomy's Friends of Astronomy group. For example, in May 2012 Flanagan participated in a panel discussion entitled ``Do We Understand the Big Bang?'' at a meeting of this alumni group. For a long period of time that ended toward the middle year of this particular NSF award, Wasserman wrote the answers in the question and answer column of the Friends of Astronomy's semi-annual newsletter.<br /><br /><br /><br />&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp...]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ INTELLECTUAL MERIT  The expansion of the Universe is accelerating. There is still no definitive explanation for this empirical fact.  A possible explanation is that the Universe is pervaded by dark energy, which may be a cosmological constant that never changes in time or varies in space, but may also be a completely new ``dynamical field'' that permeates the Universe but varies in time and space.  Another possible explanation is that gravity is not well-described by the General Relativity on very large length and time scales, where the theory is untested.  The research done on this grant probed these questions via a number of different investigations. One study investigated the effect of large scale structure on observed luminosities of distant light sources, and found typical variations of order a few percent, which would complicate the analysis of observations aiming to trace the time variation of dark energy. Other studies investigated ``effective theories'' that allow general modelling of both cosmic acceleration and the effects of modifying the properties of gravity on large scales. These studies have led to a generally applicable framework capable of addressing whether cosmic acceleration is due to dark energy or to new properties of gravity that only are discernible on cosmological distance and time scales.  Not only is the expansion of the Universe accelerating today, but cosmological observations strongly support the notion that there was a period of super-rapid cosmic acceleration called inflation that ended with the onset of the Big Bang phase of cosmological evolution. Although some of the essential features of inflation have been determined reasonably well from observations, others remain unconstrained. One example is the duration of inflation. Observations indicate that the Universe is very nearly flat spatially, and that the temperature of the Cosmic Microwave Background Radiation (CMBR) is nearly uniform across the sky. A minimum duration of the inflationary period is needed to account for these observed properties of the Universe, but the actual duration could be far longer. Can observations tell if inflation did not last much longer than the minimum required duration? A study performed during this project indicates that CMBR observations in the near future will not be sensitive enough to probe this fundamental question.  BROADER IMPACT  During the period covered by this grant, research was done in collaboration with graduate students and young postdocs who had just completed their PhDs. These vital collaborations contribute to the training of new generations of scientists, some of whom continue in academia, and others who move into other areas that employ their quantitative and computational skills. In addition to disseminating their work via conventional academic channels (journal publications, seminars, conferences) the senior investigators continued their commitment to educating the general public via lectures and essays. Some of this outreach has been done via interactions with Cornell alumni who are members of the Department of Astronomy's Friends of Astronomy group. For example, in May 2012 Flanagan participated in a panel discussion entitled ``Do We Understand the Big Bang?'' at a meeting of this alumni group. For a long period of time that ended toward the middle year of this particular NSF award, Wasserman wrote the answers in the question and answer column of the Friends of Astronomy's semi-annual newsletter.                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                       16,1          All       Last Modified: 09/09/2015       Submitted by: Ira M Wasserman]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
