<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>FRG: Collaborative Research: Dynamics of Thin Liquid Films: Mathematics and Experiments</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>06/01/2010</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2015</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>329191.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>329191</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DMS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Henry Warchall</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>hwarchal@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924861</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The science of thin liquid films has developed rapidly in recent years, with applications to coating flows, biofluids, microfluidic engineering, and medicine. In this project, we will focus on three groups of free-surface flow problems using a combination of mathematical modeling, analysis and numerical simulation, coupled to carefully chosen quantitative experiments. The three areas are: (i) flows driven by surface tension gradients, (ii) the role of inertia in regimes where lubrication is inadequate to model thin film flow, and (iii) vibrating thin films. Advances in our understanding of theoretical issues surrounding modeling these flows, and the exploration of new features of the flows through experiments will have direct applications to improving control and reliability of manufacturing processes in high-tech industries and to biomedical systems.&lt;br/&gt; &lt;br/&gt;The flow of thin liquid layers or films occurs in contexts including industrial coating flows, microfluidic engineering, and medicine. In this project, we focus on properties of thin liquid films such as the role of surface tension in driving flow, and the behavior of thin layers under rapid vibration.  Surface tension is an important mechanism in the dynamics of mucus layers in the lung, and is central to the treatment of premature infants by surfactant replacement therapy. The control of thin layer flow, through the temperature dependence of surface tension or using rapid vibrations, has the potential to eliminate damaging nonuniformities in industrial coating processes. Each of these areas and applications pose substantial scientific challenges that will be met with a collaborative effort between mathematicians and physicists, exploring theoretical and experimental methods in tandem. The project includes graduate and undergraduate student training in an interdisciplinary research program that&lt;br/&gt;will develop coordinated advanced skills in physics, engineering, and applied mathematics.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>04/27/2010</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>04/27/2010</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>0968252</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Thomas</FirstName>
<LastName>Witelski</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>P</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Thomas P Witelski</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>witelski@math.duke.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>9196602841</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000120778</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/27/2010</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Duke University</Name>
<CityName>Durham</CityName>
<ZipCode>277054010</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>9196843030</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>2200 W. Main St, Suite 710</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[Erwin Square]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>North Carolina</StateName>
<StateCode>NC</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NC01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>044387793</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>DUKE UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>044387793</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Duke University]]></Name>
<CityName>Durham</CityName>
<StateCode>NC</StateCode>
<ZipCode>277054010</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[2200 W. Main St, Suite 710]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>North Carolina</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NC01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1266</Code>
<Text>APPLIED MATHEMATICS</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1616</Code>
<Text>FOCUSED RESEARCH GROUPS IN MATH SCIENCES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0110</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2010~329191</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><span>Problems involving the dynamics of thin layers of fluids occur in countless contexts from the spreading of tear films on the eye, or oil in a frying pan to industrial processes like <span>spincoating</span> in the manufacture of silicon chips. All of these contexts share the same physical structure of a free-surface flow of a viscous fluid coating a solid surface. The drying of paint on walls is often</span> mentioned as a slow and straightforward process; while this can be a rather slowing evolving thin film problem, complex instabilities depending on details of materials properties of the solid and fluid can have dramatic effects the reliability of obtaining uniform coatings in many settings.<br /><br />While for general problems, simulations of the equations for fluid dynamics<span> require intensive computational resources, through the use of lubrication theory, thin film problems can be put into a tractable form for mathematical study as a single partial differential equation for the thickness of the layer. For problems at small physical scales, as in biological applications and the design of <span>microfluidic</span> devices, surface tension plays an important role and the geometry of the films can yields complicated dynamics. Taking the form of nonlinear fourth-order equations, these models have been the focus of mathematical research for the past three decades.</span><br /><br />There has been extensive use of thin film models in many branches of engineering, but this project has shown that more careful mathematical analysis is needed to understand the range of different behaviors that can result from (i) externally imposed non-uniform effects, (ii) boundary conditions and finite system sizes, and (iii) non-conservative influences, like evaporation and condensation. This project has explored these and related mathematical issues in thin films through several sub-projects that have involved analysis, mathematical modeling and computations or experimental studies.<br /><br /><span>In one of these studies, strong centrifugal forces produced by spinning a fluid layer in an open cylinder create a central circular spot. Halting the spinning yields an inward flow, also called a focusing flow. How this flow fills the central dry region depends sensitively on the balance between surface tension and body forces and has led to new approaches for quantifying scaling solutions in experimental and numerical studies. Another branch of work has uncovered new classes of behaviors in a <span>thermocapillary</span> flow problem where localized heating interacts with surface tension effects to control flows on an inclined plate. Previously observed steady solutions have been supplemented by new periodic wave states. A different sub-project has shown that a generalized form of an evaporative loss term can significantly change the dynamics of films relative to previously known results for non-evaporative systems. Further studies on all of these areas are being continued as well as examinations of other classes of special solutions for self-similar behavior and finite-time singularities in thin films.</span><br /><br />In addition to the training of mathematics graduate students on research in fluid dynamics, this project had also been instrumental in organizing an international research conference which brought together applied mathematicians, physicists, and engineers to discuss challenges in thin films and related problems in fluid dynamics.<br /><br /></p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 08/25/2015<br>      Modified by: Thomas&nbsp;P&nbsp;Witelski</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Images (<span id="selectedPhoto0">1</span> of <span class="totalNumber"></span>)           </div> <div class="galControls" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id...]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Problems involving the dynamics of thin layers of fluids occur in countless contexts from the spreading of tear films on the eye, or oil in a frying pan to industrial processes like spincoating in the manufacture of silicon chips. All of these contexts share the same physical structure of a free-surface flow of a viscous fluid coating a solid surface. The drying of paint on walls is often mentioned as a slow and straightforward process; while this can be a rather slowing evolving thin film problem, complex instabilities depending on details of materials properties of the solid and fluid can have dramatic effects the reliability of obtaining uniform coatings in many settings.  While for general problems, simulations of the equations for fluid dynamics require intensive computational resources, through the use of lubrication theory, thin film problems can be put into a tractable form for mathematical study as a single partial differential equation for the thickness of the layer. For problems at small physical scales, as in biological applications and the design of microfluidic devices, surface tension plays an important role and the geometry of the films can yields complicated dynamics. Taking the form of nonlinear fourth-order equations, these models have been the focus of mathematical research for the past three decades.  There has been extensive use of thin film models in many branches of engineering, but this project has shown that more careful mathematical analysis is needed to understand the range of different behaviors that can result from (i) externally imposed non-uniform effects, (ii) boundary conditions and finite system sizes, and (iii) non-conservative influences, like evaporation and condensation. This project has explored these and related mathematical issues in thin films through several sub-projects that have involved analysis, mathematical modeling and computations or experimental studies.  In one of these studies, strong centrifugal forces produced by spinning a fluid layer in an open cylinder create a central circular spot. Halting the spinning yields an inward flow, also called a focusing flow. How this flow fills the central dry region depends sensitively on the balance between surface tension and body forces and has led to new approaches for quantifying scaling solutions in experimental and numerical studies. Another branch of work has uncovered new classes of behaviors in a thermocapillary flow problem where localized heating interacts with surface tension effects to control flows on an inclined plate. Previously observed steady solutions have been supplemented by new periodic wave states. A different sub-project has shown that a generalized form of an evaporative loss term can significantly change the dynamics of films relative to previously known results for non-evaporative systems. Further studies on all of these areas are being continued as well as examinations of other classes of special solutions for self-similar behavior and finite-time singularities in thin films.  In addition to the training of mathematics graduate students on research in fluid dynamics, this project had also been instrumental in organizing an international research conference which brought together applied mathematicians, physicists, and engineers to discuss challenges in thin films and related problems in fluid dynamics.         Last Modified: 08/25/2015       Submitted by: Thomas P Witelski]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
