<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Four Mathematical Programming Paradigms with Operations Research Applications</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2010</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2014</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>240000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>240000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CMMI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Civil, Mechanical, &amp; Manufact Inn</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Donald Hearn</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This proposal aims at investigating four emerging modeling paradigms&lt;br/&gt;in mathematical programming that have gained increased attention in recent years due to their pervasive applications in operations research and other engineering fields as well as in economics and finance, but which have yet to receive wide popularity and lack focused research.  These paradigms are: competition, dynamics, hierarchy, and inverse problems.  The objective of the project is to develop a comprehensive and rigorous foundation for the sustained treatment and applications of these paradigms in the context of complex engineering and economic systems.  The proposed approach is to study the mathematical formulations of these paradigms in terms of extended mathematical and equilibrium programs, constrained continuous-time dynamical systems, and multi-agent and multi-level optimization.  Novel mathematical theories and advanced computational tools will be developed.  This will require the combined methodology of continuous and disjunctive programming, global optimization, continuous- and discrete-time dynamical systems theory, and contemporary mathematical tools such as variational and set-valued analysis.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;If successful, the results of the proposed research will lead to improved understanding and efficient solution of highly complex  engineering, economic, and biological systems characterized by four intrinsic elements: competition among multiple selfish agents, time evolution prior to the attainment of an optimum or equilibrium, hierarchical structure of the optimizing agents, and historical and/or observed data that need to be respected.  Due to its interdisciplinary nature, the proposed activity offers an opportunity to bring together experts in diverse disciplines to advance their individual fields and make joint contributions to significant societal problems such as efficient resource allocation in engineering and economic systems, congestion in transportation systems, and resolution of conflicts among competing selfish agents, to name a few areas of applications.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>04/19/2010</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>12/10/2013</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>0969600</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Jong-Shi</FirstName>
<LastName>Pang</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Jong-Shi Pang</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>jongship@usc.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2137407436</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000448307</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/19/2010</StartDate>
<EndDate>12/02/2013</EndDate>
<RoleCode>Former Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Angelia</FirstName>
<LastName>Nedich</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Angelia Nedich</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>Angelia.Nedich@asu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2178199580</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000099453</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>12/02/2013</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign</Name>
<CityName>Champaign</CityName>
<ZipCode>618207406</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2173332187</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1901 South First Street</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[Suite A]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Illinois</StateName>
<StateCode>IL</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>13</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>IL13</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>041544081</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF ILLINOIS</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>041544081</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign]]></Name>
<CityName>Champaign</CityName>
<StateCode>IL</StateCode>
<ZipCode>618207406</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[1901 South First Street]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Illinois</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>13</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>IL13</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<FoaInformation>
<Code>0107000</Code>
<Name>Operations Research</Name>
</FoaInformation>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>5514</Code>
<Text>OPERATIONS RESEARCH</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>073E</Code>
<Text>OPTIMIZATION &amp; DECISION MAKING</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9147</Code>
<Text>GENERIC TECHNOL FOR MANUFACTURING CELLS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>MANU</Code>
<Text>MANUFACTURING</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0110</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2010~240000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The project goal is to investigates several promising paradigms in mathematical programming models that have gained momentum in recent years due to their many applications in operations research and other engineering fields as well as in economics and finance.&nbsp; Specifically, the proposal addresses four practical modeling paradigms: competition, dynamics, hierarchy, and inverse problems, and aims at developing a comprehensive, rigorous foundation for their sustained treatment and applications.</p> <p>The impact is two-fold: 1) the project has advanced the broad field of optimization and operations research and has enriched the domain of their applications (such as wireless sensor and communicaton networks); &nbsp;and 2), new tools and methods are developed to deal with the technical challenges of the problems studied.&nbsp; The models are highly complex to solve, necessitating a careful study and further analysis. This project also opens new opportunities for a more aithful modeling of practical applications.</p> <p>The outcomes of this project have potential to impact the society by advancing the science and technology of complex systems, and by providing more realistic mathematical formulations and sound computational methods for dealing with a host of decision making problems, such as those involving competition, dynamics, and data. In particular, the applied domains that can be directly impacted by the new results and methods developed under this project include&nbsp;electricity markets, traffic planning, and signal processing for communication. &nbsp;</p> <p><strong>&nbsp;</strong></p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 08/17/2015<br>      Modified by: Angelia&nbsp;Nedich</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The project goal is to investigates several promising paradigms in mathematical programming models that have gained momentum in recent years due to their many applications in operations research and other engineering fields as well as in economics and finance.  Specifically, the proposal addresses four practical modeling paradigms: competition, dynamics, hierarchy, and inverse problems, and aims at developing a comprehensive, rigorous foundation for their sustained treatment and applications.  The impact is two-fold: 1) the project has advanced the broad field of optimization and operations research and has enriched the domain of their applications (such as wireless sensor and communicaton networks);  and 2), new tools and methods are developed to deal with the technical challenges of the problems studied.  The models are highly complex to solve, necessitating a careful study and further analysis. This project also opens new opportunities for a more aithful modeling of practical applications.  The outcomes of this project have potential to impact the society by advancing the science and technology of complex systems, and by providing more realistic mathematical formulations and sound computational methods for dealing with a host of decision making problems, such as those involving competition, dynamics, and data. In particular, the applied domains that can be directly impacted by the new results and methods developed under this project include electricity markets, traffic planning, and signal processing for communication.               Last Modified: 08/17/2015       Submitted by: Angelia Nedich]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
