<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Quantum Control of Mesoscopic Collective Spin States</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2010</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2014</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>261386.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>261386</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03010000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>PHY</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Physics</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Ann Orel</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Control of complex systems at the atomic scale is at the frontier of nano-technology.  At this scale, the effects of quantum mechanics allow for a fundamentally new generation of information processing devises such as quantum-computers, communication systems, and precise sensors.  These effects will be studied in a joint theoretical-experimental project involving ultra-cold vapors of approximately 1,000,000 cesium atoms trapped and probed by laser light.  This collection of atoms act as a single unit analogous to a spinning top.  The collective spin will be controlled with lasers and magnetic fields in order to create new quantum states that can form the foundation for encoding and communicating information at the quantum level.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The research will contribute to the knowledge base of quantum information science, and to the training of future scientists in this highly interdisciplinary field.  Students will be involved in all aspects of the project, including education, research, and the dissemination of results.  The project will become a cornerstone of the newly-formed Center for Quantum Information and Control. Video conferencing will be used to allow participation of CQuIC partners in the regular activities of CQuIC, including weekly group meetings and research seminars, and strengthen the connections between junior and senior members through an annual research retreat. All students and senior personnel will actively participate in the Southwest Quantum Information Technology (SQuInT) network, including the annual workshop. During its 11-year history SQuInT has provided a vibrant avenue for exchange of ideas and results in QIS, with particular emphasis given to PhD students, postdocs, and new researchers in the field.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/16/2010</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/16/2010</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>0969997</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Ivan</FirstName>
<LastName>Deutsch</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>H</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Ivan H Deutsch</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>ideutsch@unm.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5052778602</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000164864</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/16/2010</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of New Mexico</Name>
<CityName>Albuquerque</CityName>
<ZipCode>871310001</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5052774186</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1700 Lomas Blvd. NE, Suite 2200</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New Mexico</StateName>
<StateCode>NM</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NM01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>868853094</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF NEW MEXICO, THE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>784121725</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of New Mexico]]></Name>
<CityName>Albuquerque</CityName>
<StateCode>NM</StateCode>
<ZipCode>871310001</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[1700 Lomas Blvd. NE, Suite 2200]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New Mexico</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NM01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1284</Code>
<Text>AMO Theory/Atomic, Molecular &amp;</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>0000</Code>
<Text>UNASSIGNED</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7203</Code>
<Text>QUANTUM INFORMATION SCIENCE</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>OTHR</Code>
<Text>OTHER RESEARCH OR EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0110</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2010~261386</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><span style="font-size: 12px;">Control of &nbsp;complex systems is a grand challenge for science and technology. &nbsp;This is particularly true for technologies based on quantum physics, the physics that describes the sub-nanoscale world of atoms and particles. &nbsp;The challenge in developing quantum technologies is to bring these effects into the macroscopic world, where they can be applied to revolutionary devices for communications, computation, and sensing. &nbsp;In this grant we explored a particular platform -- ensembles of ultracold cesium atoms, cooled with laser beams, and collected in an atomic trap. &nbsp;At ultralow temperatures (about 1/100,000 of a degree from absolute zero), the atoms barely move and thus can be precisely controlled. &nbsp;In particular, we studied the control of the&nbsp;"spin" of the nucleus and electrons inside the ceisum atoms. &nbsp;These spins act like tiny tops. &nbsp;With this control one can develop ultra-precise sensors such as atomic clocks at the heart of GPS and magnetometers that can detect the smallest magnetic fields. &nbsp;Magnetic field sensors are important for the next generation of MRI to image the brain and other biological function.</span></p> <p>This grant support the training of students earning their PhDs in Physics. &nbsp;Students learned techniques in analytic modeling and computer simulations. &nbsp;They also worked in teams, in collaboration with experimentalists working in the the Unversity of Arizona. &nbsp;This training is essential for the next generation of scientists.&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 10/09/2014<br>      Modified by: Ivan&nbsp;H&nbsp;Deutsch</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Control of  complex systems is a grand challenge for science and technology.  This is particularly true for technologies based on quantum physics, the physics that describes the sub-nanoscale world of atoms and particles.  The challenge in developing quantum technologies is to bring these effects into the macroscopic world, where they can be applied to revolutionary devices for communications, computation, and sensing.  In this grant we explored a particular platform -- ensembles of ultracold cesium atoms, cooled with laser beams, and collected in an atomic trap.  At ultralow temperatures (about 1/100,000 of a degree from absolute zero), the atoms barely move and thus can be precisely controlled.  In particular, we studied the control of the "spin" of the nucleus and electrons inside the ceisum atoms.  These spins act like tiny tops.  With this control one can develop ultra-precise sensors such as atomic clocks at the heart of GPS and magnetometers that can detect the smallest magnetic fields.  Magnetic field sensors are important for the next generation of MRI to image the brain and other biological function.  This grant support the training of students earning their PhDs in Physics.  Students learned techniques in analytic modeling and computer simulations.  They also worked in teams, in collaboration with experimentalists working in the the Unversity of Arizona.  This training is essential for the next generation of scientists.        Last Modified: 10/09/2014       Submitted by: Ivan H Deutsch]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
