<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Bridges for SUCCESS (Bridges for Salisbury University's Connections to Careers for Every STEM Student</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>06/01/2010</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2016</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>996303.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>996303</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>11040200</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>EHR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DUE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Undergraduate Education</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Connie Della-Piana</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>cdellapi@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032925309</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Despite increasing enrollment at Salisbury University, the number of STEM majors has remained constant.  This project is designed to increase the number of graduates in selected STEM majors including chemistry, physics, mathematics, computer science and earth science.  Strategies to increase recruitment include providing career awareness to high school students and their parents as well as improved transition from community colleges.  Strategies to increase retention at the university include enhance mathematics tutoring and placement, early research opportunities for freshmen, living-learning communities and applied research opportunities for seniors.  A broad commitment by the university is led by the campus STEM Coordinator.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>05/03/2010</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>04/08/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.076</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>0969428</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Thomas</FirstName>
<LastName>Jones</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>W</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Thomas W Jones</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>twjones@salisbury.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>4106775381</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000230985</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/26/2011</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Thomas</FirstName>
<LastName>Jones</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>W</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Thomas W Jones</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>twjones@salisbury.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>4106775381</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000230985</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/03/2010</StartDate>
<EndDate>08/22/2010</EndDate>
<RoleCode>Former Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Karen</FirstName>
<LastName>Olmstead</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>L</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Karen L Olmstead</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>klolmstead@salisbury.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>4105483374</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000533683</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/26/2011</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Karen</FirstName>
<LastName>Olmstead</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>L</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Karen L Olmstead</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>klolmstead@salisbury.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>4105483374</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000533683</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/03/2010</StartDate>
<EndDate>08/22/2010</EndDate>
<RoleCode>Former Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Salisbury University</Name>
<CityName>Salisbury</CityName>
<ZipCode>218016837</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>4105436066</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1101 Camden Avenue</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Maryland</StateName>
<StateCode>MD</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MD01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>786365437</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>SALISBURY UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>003256088</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Salisbury University]]></Name>
<CityName>Salisbury</CityName>
<StateCode>MD</StateCode>
<ZipCode>218016837</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[1101 Camden Avenue]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Maryland</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MD01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1796</Code>
<Text>STEP-STEM Talent Expansn Pgm</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9178</Code>
<Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0410</Code>
<Name>NSF Education &amp; Human Resource</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040106</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0411</Code>
<Name>NSF Education &amp; Human Resource</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040106</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0414</Code>
<Name>NSF Education &amp; Human Resource</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040106</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2010~637695</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2011~177804</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~180804</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The primary goal of <em>Bridges for SUCCESS</em> was to increase the total number of graduates in selected STEM disciplines &ndash; chemistry, computer science, earth science, mathematics and physics &ndash; by 75% in five years. We used a portfolio approach to build enrollments, retain students and promote student success in these five targeted majors, collectively organized as STEM@SU.</p> <p>During the six-year grant period, we achieved our goal through several strategies to increase the recruitment, retention, preparation, and engagement of Chemistry, Computer Science, Earth Science, Mathematics, and Physics majors:</p> <p>1) engaging pre-college students in STEM majors and careers through outreach programs like Science Camp@SU, Science Nights, Maryland STEM Festival, Girls Get IT, science and mathematics competitions, and open houses.</p> <p>2) creating excitement about our programs through more effective marketing and social media, branding, and distinctive programming which included dual-enrollment and dual-degree programs in physics, engineering, computer science and cyber-security.</p> <p>3) increasing access for community college students through curriculum coordination, transfer student support, and stronger ties to our regional community college partners.</p> <p>4) supporting and engaging STEM majors throughout their academic careers with a living-learning community for less prepared students, early research experiences and an applied research course.</p> <p>STEM@SU activities brought prospective students in contact with our programs and faculty; allowed us to develop an effective brand; and supported students early and late in their academic programs. Rather than a single &lsquo;critical element,&rsquo; our portfolio approach allowed us to reach and support students at several points along their STEM pathways. As a result of these efforts, we increased enrollments by 71% and graduates by 94% in our targeted majors in six years. Most of this project's elements have been institutionalized and are supported by a number of faculty, staff, and budgets across campus.</p> <p>As noted above, our goal was to increase graduates in targeted STEM majors by 75%, but we significantly exceeded this goal with a near doubling of majors by AY2014-15 (Year 5 of STEP grant) and maintained this production of graduates in Year 6 of STEP funding. Also of interest was that our percent increase of graduates in targeted and total STEM majors far exceeded the percent increase at other institutions in the University System of Maryland over the duration of the grant. Our enrollment growth has nearly exceeded our capacity in some majors and we have been working to address faculty staffing and space challenges created by our burgeoning enrollments.</p> <p>Receiving a competitive STEP award demonstrated that our strategies to grow STEM graduates were sound and this vetting by NSF allowed us to work more effectively with campus faculty as well as leadership in Academic Affairs, Admissions, University Advancement, Institutional Research, and Finance and Administration. The campus-wide focus on STEM that was in part generated by the STEP award resulted in the annual re-allocation of $320,000 to create competitive scholarships for prospective STEM majors. Our results have been disseminated through annual STEP meetings, STEP Central Webinar and STEM Central as well as other conferences. Further, the project PI has participated in several workshops/panels regarding management of multi-faceted projects.</p> <p>At the end of the project, Salisbury University not only has significantly increased enrollments and graduates but has also institutionalized effective practices and built stronger ties to regional high schools, community colleges and employers.<strong></strong></p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 08/09/2016<br>      Modified by: Karen&nbsp;L&nbsp;Olmstead</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Images (<span id="selectedPhoto0">1</span> of <span class="totalNumber"></span>)           </div> <div class="galControls" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2016/0969428/0969428_10015554_1470750082969_IMG_2443--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2016/0969428/0969428_10015554_1470750082969_IMG_2443--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Science Campers"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2016/0969428/0969428_10015554_1470750082969_IMG_2443--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Science Campers"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">High school students in Salisbury University's Science Camp.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Kristen Paul</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Karen&nbsp;L&nbsp;Olmstead</div> <div class="imageTitle">Science Campers</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2016/0969428/0969428_10015554_1470747891117_stematsu-logo--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2016/0969428/0969428_10015554_1470747891117_stematsu-logo--rgov-800width.jpg" title="STEM at SU logo"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2016/0969428/0969428_10015554_1470747891117_stematsu-logo--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="STEM at SU logo"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Logo used in branding our portfolio approach to increasing STEM majors at Salisbury University.</div> <div class="imageCredit">SU Publications</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Karen&nbsp;L&nbsp;Olmstead</div> <div class="imageTitle">STEM at SU logo</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2016/0969428/0969428_10015554_1470751067802_veronicasciencenights--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2016/0969428/0969428_10015554_1470751067802_veronicasciencenights--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Polymer Chemistry at Science Nights"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2016/0969428/0969428_10015554_1470751067802_veronicasciencenights--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Polymer Chemistry at Science Nights"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">High school student at Salisbury University Science Nights whos subsequently enrolled as a Physics major at SU.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Kristen Paul</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Karen&nbsp;L&nbsp;Olmstead</div> <div class="imageTitle">Polymer Chemistry at Science Nights</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The primary goal of Bridges for SUCCESS was to increase the total number of graduates in selected STEM disciplines &ndash; chemistry, computer science, earth science, mathematics and physics &ndash; by 75% in five years. We used a portfolio approach to build enrollments, retain students and promote student success in these five targeted majors, collectively organized as STEM@SU.  During the six-year grant period, we achieved our goal through several strategies to increase the recruitment, retention, preparation, and engagement of Chemistry, Computer Science, Earth Science, Mathematics, and Physics majors:  1) engaging pre-college students in STEM majors and careers through outreach programs like Science Camp@SU, Science Nights, Maryland STEM Festival, Girls Get IT, science and mathematics competitions, and open houses.  2) creating excitement about our programs through more effective marketing and social media, branding, and distinctive programming which included dual-enrollment and dual-degree programs in physics, engineering, computer science and cyber-security.  3) increasing access for community college students through curriculum coordination, transfer student support, and stronger ties to our regional community college partners.  4) supporting and engaging STEM majors throughout their academic careers with a living-learning community for less prepared students, early research experiences and an applied research course.  STEM@SU activities brought prospective students in contact with our programs and faculty; allowed us to develop an effective brand; and supported students early and late in their academic programs. Rather than a single ?critical element,? our portfolio approach allowed us to reach and support students at several points along their STEM pathways. As a result of these efforts, we increased enrollments by 71% and graduates by 94% in our targeted majors in six years. Most of this project's elements have been institutionalized and are supported by a number of faculty, staff, and budgets across campus.  As noted above, our goal was to increase graduates in targeted STEM majors by 75%, but we significantly exceeded this goal with a near doubling of majors by AY2014-15 (Year 5 of STEP grant) and maintained this production of graduates in Year 6 of STEP funding. Also of interest was that our percent increase of graduates in targeted and total STEM majors far exceeded the percent increase at other institutions in the University System of Maryland over the duration of the grant. Our enrollment growth has nearly exceeded our capacity in some majors and we have been working to address faculty staffing and space challenges created by our burgeoning enrollments.  Receiving a competitive STEP award demonstrated that our strategies to grow STEM graduates were sound and this vetting by NSF allowed us to work more effectively with campus faculty as well as leadership in Academic Affairs, Admissions, University Advancement, Institutional Research, and Finance and Administration. The campus-wide focus on STEM that was in part generated by the STEP award resulted in the annual re-allocation of $320,000 to create competitive scholarships for prospective STEM majors. Our results have been disseminated through annual STEP meetings, STEP Central Webinar and STEM Central as well as other conferences. Further, the project PI has participated in several workshops/panels regarding management of multi-faceted projects.  At the end of the project, Salisbury University not only has significantly increased enrollments and graduates but has also institutionalized effective practices and built stronger ties to regional high schools, community colleges and employers.       Last Modified: 08/09/2016       Submitted by: Karen L Olmstead]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
