<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Collaborative Research: Experimental and Computational Investigation of Consolidation-Induced Contaminant Transport for High Water Content Geo-Materials</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2010</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2014</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>210000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>210000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CMMI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Civil, Mechanical, &amp; Manufact Inn</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Richard Fragaszy</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The goal of this project is to advance the state-of-the art with respect to our understanding of the mechanisms and significance of consolidation-induced contaminant transport for high water content geo-materials. The phenomenon of coupled consolidation and contaminant transport occurs for a variety of practical applications in geotechnical and geoenvironmental engineering. Such applications include confined disposal of contaminated high water content geo-materials (e.g., tailings, dredgings, sludges, and slurries) in ex situ engineered impoundments, mechanical dewatering of contaminated high water content geo-materials, in situ remediation of source zones contaminated with chlorinated solvents via injection of granular zero valent iron (ZVI) slurry and soil mixing, and in situ capping of subaqueous contaminated sediments. Research has demonstrated only very recently that consolidation-induced transport of contaminants is a valid transport mechanism that may have lasting effects on the contaminant migration behavior for a given system. However, little is known about the general significance of this mechanism for practical applications. Current understanding of consolidation-induced contaminant transport is limited with respect to: (1) the effects of higher chemical concentrations and multispecies contaminants, such that typically occur in field sites; (2) the importance of facilitated transport via colloidal particles, which is likely to be an important mechanism for natural fine-grained materials with highly sorbed contaminants; (3) testing of realistic geo-materials, such as mine tailings or dredged sediments; and (4) absence of work conducted for constant rate-of-strain or centrifuge loading conditions.  &lt;br/&gt;The proposed research will consist of a fundamental experimental and computational investigation of the mechanism of consolidation-induced contaminant transport for several materials and conditions, and then assess the significance of these findings for relevant geotechnical and geoenvironmental applications. The research plan has six tasks: (1) material procurement and characterization; (2) material property testing; (3) consolidation-induced transport testing; (4) development and validation of computational models; (5) computational simulations; and (6) project collaboration and dissemination of results. The proposed research has both intrinsic scientific merit in terms of a fundamental assessment of this transport mechanism and associated parameters as well as practical implications in terms of improving our ability to predict contaminant outflows from high water content geo-materials during consolidation. As a result, a better understanding of the mechanism and significance of consolidation-induced contaminant transport will be achieved, thereby enhancing the ability of designers and regulators to protect the public health and the environment from the effects of contaminants. Results from this research have the potential to transform the way contaminated high water content geo-materials are currently characterized, handled, dewatered and/or disposed.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>03/29/2010</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>03/29/2010</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>0969346</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Charles</FirstName>
<LastName>Shackelford</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>D</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Charles D Shackelford</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>shackel@engr.colostate.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>9704915051</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000313024</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>03/29/2010</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Colorado State University</Name>
<CityName>Fort Collins</CityName>
<ZipCode>805232002</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>9704916355</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>601 S Howes St</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Colorado</StateName>
<StateCode>CO</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CO02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>785979618</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>COLORADO STATE UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>948905492</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Colorado State University]]></Name>
<CityName>Fort Collins</CityName>
<StateCode>CO</StateCode>
<ZipCode>805232002</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[601 S Howes St]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Colorado</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CO02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1636</Code>
<Text>Geotechnical Engineering and M</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>036E</Code>
<Text>CIVIL INFRASTRUCTURE</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>037E</Code>
<Text>GEOTECHNICAL ENGINEERING</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1057</Code>
<Text>CIS BASE RESEARCH</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>CVIS</Code>
<Text>CIVIL INFRASTRUCTURE</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0110</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2010~210000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The goal of this project, which was a collaborative effort between the University of California-San Diego and Colorado State University, was to advance the state-of-the art with respect to the effect of consolidation-induced solute transport from contaminated materials. This phenomenon of coupled consolidation and contaminant transport occurs for a variety of practical applications in geotechnical and geoenvironmental engineering.&nbsp; Such applications include confined disposal and dewatering of high water content soil-like wastes (e.g., taconite tailings, red mud, phosphate slimes, precious metal tailings, uranium tailings, gypsum tailings, dredged spoils, paper mill sludge, flue gas desulfurization sludge, fly ash slurry, coal refuse, tar sand wastes) in <em>ex situ</em> engineered impoundments, <em>in situ</em> remediation of source zones contaminated with chlorinated solvents (e.g., carbon tetrachloride, trichloroethylene) via injection of slurry containing bentonite and granular zero valent iron during shallow soil mixing, and <em>in situ</em> capping of subaqueous contaminated sediments. The research included both intrinsic scientific merit in terms of a fundamental assessment of this transport mechanism and the associated parameters and practical implications in terms of improving our ability to predict contaminant outflows from high water content-geo-materials during consolidation. As a result of the research, consolidation-induced contaminant transport has been shown to be significant under certain conditions pertaining to the use of engineered barriers for containment and control of disposed wastes (e.g., landfills, contaminated dredged sediments) for protection of public health and the environment. The results from this research have the potential to transform the way contaminated high water content geo-materials are currently characterized, handled, and/or disposed.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>The project also produced several broader impacts. First, the project included the teaching, training and learning of two doctoral students, one of who is currently employed as a faculty member at a U.S. institution of higher learning. Second, the project provided for direct interaction among the principal investigators and their graduate students, which galvanized collaboration among all parties, such that the collaboration will continue beyond the formal time frame of the project in terms of research and outreach efforts (e.g., organization of sessions at conferences). Finally, the results of the research are being disseminated to the scientific and professional communities through oral presentations and refereed published papers, several of which include co-authors from each of the two collaborating universities.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 02/02/2015<br>      Modified by: Charles&nbsp;D&nbsp;Shackelford</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The goal of this project, which was a collaborative effort between the University of California-San Diego and Colorado State University, was to advance the state-of-the art with respect to the effect of consolidation-induced solute transport from contaminated materials. This phenomenon of coupled consolidation and contaminant transport occurs for a variety of practical applications in geotechnical and geoenvironmental engineering.  Such applications include confined disposal and dewatering of high water content soil-like wastes (e.g., taconite tailings, red mud, phosphate slimes, precious metal tailings, uranium tailings, gypsum tailings, dredged spoils, paper mill sludge, flue gas desulfurization sludge, fly ash slurry, coal refuse, tar sand wastes) in ex situ engineered impoundments, in situ remediation of source zones contaminated with chlorinated solvents (e.g., carbon tetrachloride, trichloroethylene) via injection of slurry containing bentonite and granular zero valent iron during shallow soil mixing, and in situ capping of subaqueous contaminated sediments. The research included both intrinsic scientific merit in terms of a fundamental assessment of this transport mechanism and the associated parameters and practical implications in terms of improving our ability to predict contaminant outflows from high water content-geo-materials during consolidation. As a result of the research, consolidation-induced contaminant transport has been shown to be significant under certain conditions pertaining to the use of engineered barriers for containment and control of disposed wastes (e.g., landfills, contaminated dredged sediments) for protection of public health and the environment. The results from this research have the potential to transform the way contaminated high water content geo-materials are currently characterized, handled, and/or disposed.     The project also produced several broader impacts. First, the project included the teaching, training and learning of two doctoral students, one of who is currently employed as a faculty member at a U.S. institution of higher learning. Second, the project provided for direct interaction among the principal investigators and their graduate students, which galvanized collaboration among all parties, such that the collaboration will continue beyond the formal time frame of the project in terms of research and outreach efforts (e.g., organization of sessions at conferences). Finally, the results of the research are being disseminated to the scientific and professional communities through oral presentations and refereed published papers, several of which include co-authors from each of the two collaborating universities.       Last Modified: 02/02/2015       Submitted by: Charles D Shackelford]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
