<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Studying Jet Modification using New Techniques in Direct Photon-Jet 2-Particle Correlation Measurements at RHIC/PHENIX</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2010</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2013</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>299091.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>404645</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03010000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>PHY</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Physics</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Bradley D. Keister</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This award will fund research conducted at the Relativistic Heavy Ion Collider at Brookhaven National Lab which will study the exotic state of matter called the quark-gluon plasma, created through collisions of large and highly energetic nuclei. The properties of this matter should be described primarily by the theory called Quantum Chromodynamics as manifestations of the same Strong force that not only holds protons and neutrons together within the atomic nucleus but also smaller particles called quarks and gluons together within the protons and neutrons themselves.  But little is known about how the quarks and gluons behave collectively when in the plasma state at high temperatures. Specifically the investigator will study interactions of the plasma with various probes.  Very high energy versions of X-rays called direct photons produced in the same collisions can penetrate the plasma and can thus provide important information.  Most promisingly, these photons can be compared with quarks produced at similar high energies but which should interact strongly with and mostly be stopped by the medium, in order to deduce major features of these interactions which are currently unknown. Analysis of such phenomena using a number of techniques including especially correlation measurements will be performed by the investigator, with both graduate and undergraduate students in training, on data collected by the PHENIX experiment at RHIC.   &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;In addition to these analysis projects, the investigator's group at Ohio University will support the upgrade of computing, analysis, and data-taking capabilities of PHENIX through software development and leadership of groups and projects of detector development and analysis. The project results in a number of broad benefits to society beyond the important goal of educating and training students: organizations are developed in the state of Ohio and beyond to exchange Heavy Ion knowledge; international collaboration of RHIC and other nuclear/particle physicists is strengthened; finally the project contributes to many general benefits to the development of future computing in the nation.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/19/2010</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/29/2012</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>0969986</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Justin</FirstName>
<LastName>Frantz</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Justin Frantz</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>frantz@ohio.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>7405931978</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000535432</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/19/2010</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Ohio University</Name>
<CityName>ATHENS</CityName>
<ZipCode>457012979</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>7405932857</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>108 CUTLER HL</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Ohio</StateName>
<StateCode>OH</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>15</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>OH15</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>041077983</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>OHIO UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>041077983</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Ohio University]]></Name>
<CityName>ATHENS</CityName>
<StateCode>OH</StateCode>
<ZipCode>457012979</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[108 CUTLER HL]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Ohio</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>15</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>OH15</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1233</Code>
<Text>NUCLEAR STRUCTURE &amp; REACTIONS</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7483</Code>
<Text>PHYSICS OF THE UNIVERSE</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0110</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0111</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0112</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2010~299091</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2011~81254</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2012~24300</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>This award funded research conducted at the Relativistic Heavy Ion Collider at Brookhaven National Lab to study the exotic state of matter called the quark-gluon plasma, created through collisions of large and highly energetic nuclei. The properties of this matter have been described primarily by the theory called Quantum Chromodynamics as manifestations of the same Strong force that not only holds protons and neutrons together within the atomic nucleus but also smaller particles called quarks and gluons together within the protons and neutrons themselves.&nbsp; But little was known before the project about how the quarks and gluons behave collectively when in the plasma state at high temperatures. The investigator and his research group at Ohio University studied interactions of the plasma with various probes to enlighten the situation.&nbsp; &nbsp;Very high energy versions of X-rays called direct photons produced in the same collisions can penetrate the plasma and can thus provide important information.&nbsp; In the project, these photons were compared with quarks produced at similar high energies but interacted strongly with, and were found to be mostly be stopped by, the medium.&nbsp; Accordingly some major features of the interactions of the high energy quarks and other color charges were able to be deduced.&nbsp; &nbsp;The most important feature discovered as part of the major goals specific to this project was the result that the interactions of the color charges cause an increase in the number of very low energy particles produced by the collisions.&nbsp; This enhancement is thought to be due to the direct loss of energy itself of the high energy color charges as they traverse the plasma, and consequently this energy being converted into extra low energy particles.</p> <p>Analysis of similar phenomena using a number of techniques including especially correlation measurements was performed by the investigator&rsquo;s group, with both graduate and undergraduate students in training, on data collected by the PHENIX experiment at RHIC.&nbsp; This included the first application of new identification techniques for finding real direct photons, called &ldquo;isolation cuts&rdquo; which were made for the first time at RHIC in this project in the most head-on Au+Au collisions.&nbsp; The results of this application were that, as expected, such techniques work, and can improve the precision and interpretations of the same types of measurements mentionned in the previous paragraph.&nbsp; Additionally they can provide new aspects of what can be measured by the probes, such as the more detailed nature of what kind of low energy particles are produced in the enhancement mentioned above. &nbsp;&nbsp;</p> <p>The above measurements were physically accomplished partially through the use of a detector which the project funds supported the repairs and maintenance of as part of its primary objectives.&nbsp; This detector is called the PHENIX Lead-Glass Electromagnetic calorimeter.&nbsp; As part of the project about 50 of the most problematic modules in this detector were replaced, and a set of well-tested spare parts together with procedures for continually making such replacements was established.&nbsp; Future upgrade concepts were also developed to modernize the nearly 20 year old, but still-very-important detector.</p> <p>Another major outcome of the project was made by the investigator himself through leadership of being one of three co-conveners of a physics working group that encompasses nearly a third of the approximately 500-person PHENIX collaboration, as well as through being one of three primary authors of another important PHENIX publication and measurement on something called "hydrodynamic flow".&nbsp; These duties demonstrate only a few examples of one of the other major objectives of the project which was to support &nbsp;the upgrade of computing, analysis, and da...]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ This award funded research conducted at the Relativistic Heavy Ion Collider at Brookhaven National Lab to study the exotic state of matter called the quark-gluon plasma, created through collisions of large and highly energetic nuclei. The properties of this matter have been described primarily by the theory called Quantum Chromodynamics as manifestations of the same Strong force that not only holds protons and neutrons together within the atomic nucleus but also smaller particles called quarks and gluons together within the protons and neutrons themselves.  But little was known before the project about how the quarks and gluons behave collectively when in the plasma state at high temperatures. The investigator and his research group at Ohio University studied interactions of the plasma with various probes to enlighten the situation.   Very high energy versions of X-rays called direct photons produced in the same collisions can penetrate the plasma and can thus provide important information.  In the project, these photons were compared with quarks produced at similar high energies but interacted strongly with, and were found to be mostly be stopped by, the medium.  Accordingly some major features of the interactions of the high energy quarks and other color charges were able to be deduced.   The most important feature discovered as part of the major goals specific to this project was the result that the interactions of the color charges cause an increase in the number of very low energy particles produced by the collisions.  This enhancement is thought to be due to the direct loss of energy itself of the high energy color charges as they traverse the plasma, and consequently this energy being converted into extra low energy particles.  Analysis of similar phenomena using a number of techniques including especially correlation measurements was performed by the investigatorÆs group, with both graduate and undergraduate students in training, on data collected by the PHENIX experiment at RHIC.  This included the first application of new identification techniques for finding real direct photons, called "isolation cuts" which were made for the first time at RHIC in this project in the most head-on Au+Au collisions.  The results of this application were that, as expected, such techniques work, and can improve the precision and interpretations of the same types of measurements mentionned in the previous paragraph.  Additionally they can provide new aspects of what can be measured by the probes, such as the more detailed nature of what kind of low energy particles are produced in the enhancement mentioned above.     The above measurements were physically accomplished partially through the use of a detector which the project funds supported the repairs and maintenance of as part of its primary objectives.  This detector is called the PHENIX Lead-Glass Electromagnetic calorimeter.  As part of the project about 50 of the most problematic modules in this detector were replaced, and a set of well-tested spare parts together with procedures for continually making such replacements was established.  Future upgrade concepts were also developed to modernize the nearly 20 year old, but still-very-important detector.  Another major outcome of the project was made by the investigator himself through leadership of being one of three co-conveners of a physics working group that encompasses nearly a third of the approximately 500-person PHENIX collaboration, as well as through being one of three primary authors of another important PHENIX publication and measurement on something called "hydrodynamic flow".  These duties demonstrate only a few examples of one of the other major objectives of the project which was to support  the upgrade of computing, analysis, and data-taking capabilities of PHENIX through software development and leadership of groups and projects of detector development and analysis.  The important "flow" publication and result in qu...]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
