<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Student Travel Support for the 2009 IEEE Conference on Decision and Control. To be held in Shanghai, China, on December 16-18, 2009.</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>02/15/2010</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>01/31/2011</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>15000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>15000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07010000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>ECCS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Electrical, Commun &amp; Cyber Sys</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Radhakisan Baheti</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This proposal requests support for student travel to the 48th IEEE Conference on Decision and Control (CDC) in Shanghai, China, December 16-18, 2009. In the pages that follow, it is argued that the proposed use of NSF funds has substantial INTELLECTUAL MERIT and will have a positive BROADER IMPACT on our technical community and the field at large.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;INTELLECTUAL MERIT: It is increasingly evident that current research on many technological frontiers is heavily influenced by foundational ideas from control and system theory. This research is creating advances in such diverse applications domains as communications and manufacturing networks, finance and risk management, cooperative control of systems of multiple autonomous agents, and systems biology. The IEEE CDC is the premier annual international conference on systems and automatic control research. The 48th CDC now has an expected level of participation over 1700. The overarching intellectual merit of the proposed use of funds is that graduate students will see firsthand how the foundations of control and systems are evolving and shaping the frontiers of research in many applications domains.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;BROADER IMPACT: With around 1500 reseach presentations, including several plenary lectures, numerous tutorial presentations, workshops and exhibits the CDC provides attendees with exposure to the state-of-the-art in emerging areas of control research and technology. The broader impact of this travel support is that it will help train the next generation of control researchers&lt;br/&gt;and practitioners. The future security and well-being of the United States relies on maintaining pools of trained scientists and engineers in critical areas such as control technology. The students to be supported under the proposed project represent the future technological leaders of the IEEE Control Systems Society, which is the world?s leading professional organization&lt;br/&gt;in the discipline.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>02/12/2010</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>02/12/2010</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>0970028</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>John</FirstName>
<LastName>Baillieul</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>John Baillieul</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>johnb@bu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6173539848</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000095539</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>02/12/2010</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Trustees of Boston University</Name>
<CityName>BOSTON</CityName>
<ZipCode>022151300</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6173534365</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>881 COMMONWEALTH AVE</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
<StateCode>MA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MA07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>049435266</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>TRUSTEES OF BOSTON UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>049435266</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Trustees of Boston University]]></Name>
<CityName>BOSTON</CityName>
<StateCode>MA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>022151300</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[881 COMMONWEALTH AVE]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MA07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1632</Code>
<Text>CONTROL SYSTEMS</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7354</Code>
<Text>CSR-Computer Systems Research</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7478</Code>
<Text>DYNAMICAL SYSTEMS</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7607</Code>
<Text>EPCN-Energy-Power-Ctrl-Netwrks</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0110</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2010~15000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Student Travel Support for the 2009 Combined 48th iEEE Conference on Decision and Control and 28th Chinese Control Conference</p> <p>Outcomes Report: NSF Grant ECCS-0970028</p> <p>John Baillieul, PI<br />March 31, 2011</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>Executive Summary</p> <p><br />This report describes the way in which NSF funds for student travel to the combined 48th IEEE Conference on Decision and Control and 28th Chinese Control Conference (CDC-CCC 2009) were used. The IEEE CDC is the premier annual international conference on systems and automatic control research. The subject project enabled thirteen graduate students studying in the United States to participate in a high quality, rigorously peer-reviewed conference that was attended by many of the world&rsquo;s leaders in systems and control.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>Final report Summary</p> <p>The combined 48-th IEEE Conference on Decision and Control and 28-th Chinese Control Conference (CDC-CCC) was held from December 16 through 18, 2009 at the Shanghai International Convention Center, Shanghai, China. As has been the custom for the Control Systems Society, travel subventions were allocated to support graduate student attendees at the conference. The Conference was well attended, with a total registration of 1500, of which many were students. The subject grant supported the travel of thirteen graduate students from universities in the United States who attended the conference.&nbsp; The students who received travel support under the subject grant were selected from a pool of applicants based on several criteria, including whether or not they were presenting research in conference oral and/or interactive sessions. Priority for funding was given to people who participated in a significant way in research that was presented at the Conference.</p> <p>The process by which the supported student were selected is as follows. The conference Student Travel Program issued a broad solicitation of applications from students seeking travel support. The award of funds involved a two-step process. The Chair of Student Activities of the IEEE Control Systems Society made an initial solicitation of applicants based on criteria such as level of&nbsp; involvement in the Conference, numbers of students from the same institution and research advisor receiving support and so forth. An eligibility<br />requirement for students receiving NSF travel funds is that they be enrolled in graduate degree programs at institutions in the United States. From a pool of thirty six (36) eligible applicants, twenty one (21) were recommended for funding. The list of recommended students was passed to me, and from this list, the grant was able to provide partial support for thirteen (13) graduate students.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 04/04/2011<br>      Modified by: John&nbsp;Baillieul</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Student Travel Support for the 2009 Combined 48th iEEE Conference on Decision and Control and 28th Chinese Control Conference  Outcomes Report: NSF Grant ECCS-0970028  John Baillieul, PI March 31, 2011     Executive Summary   This report describes the way in which NSF funds for student travel to the combined 48th IEEE Conference on Decision and Control and 28th Chinese Control Conference (CDC-CCC 2009) were used. The IEEE CDC is the premier annual international conference on systems and automatic control research. The subject project enabled thirteen graduate students studying in the United States to participate in a high quality, rigorously peer-reviewed conference that was attended by many of the worldÆs leaders in systems and control.     Final report Summary  The combined 48-th IEEE Conference on Decision and Control and 28-th Chinese Control Conference (CDC-CCC) was held from December 16 through 18, 2009 at the Shanghai International Convention Center, Shanghai, China. As has been the custom for the Control Systems Society, travel subventions were allocated to support graduate student attendees at the conference. The Conference was well attended, with a total registration of 1500, of which many were students. The subject grant supported the travel of thirteen graduate students from universities in the United States who attended the conference.  The students who received travel support under the subject grant were selected from a pool of applicants based on several criteria, including whether or not they were presenting research in conference oral and/or interactive sessions. Priority for funding was given to people who participated in a significant way in research that was presented at the Conference.  The process by which the supported student were selected is as follows. The conference Student Travel Program issued a broad solicitation of applications from students seeking travel support. The award of funds involved a two-step process. The Chair of Student Activities of the IEEE Control Systems Society made an initial solicitation of applicants based on criteria such as level of  involvement in the Conference, numbers of students from the same institution and research advisor receiving support and so forth. An eligibility requirement for students receiving NSF travel funds is that they be enrolled in graduate degree programs at institutions in the United States. From a pool of thirty six (36) eligible applicants, twenty one (21) were recommended for funding. The list of recommended students was passed to me, and from this list, the grant was able to provide partial support for thirteen (13) graduate students.       Last Modified: 04/04/2011       Submitted by: John Baillieul]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
