<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Experimental and Observational Study of Pressure Solution</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2000</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>01/31/2003</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>99999</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>06030204</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Earth Sciences</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Robin Reichlin</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>0000947 &lt;br/&gt;Scholtz, Christopher&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;An experimental study of pressure solution deformation will investigate and determine the mechanism and creep law of the process and to examine the effect of clay on its nature and rate. Pressure solution is an important rock deformation process known to modify porosity and permeability in sedimentary rocks, and to alter strength and strain along faults. Until recently, the main obstacle in investigating the mechanism and creep law of pressure solution was the poor constraints on the single most important factor in the process, the stress at the contact. A set of experiments will be conducted, utilizing a simple and cheap apparatus, that will enable us to follow pressure solution processes while monitoring the contact stress. By conducting experiments at various temperatures, stresses and clay contents and compositions, a well constrained definition of the mechanism and creep law will be obtained, as well as an understanding of the effect of clay on the process.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>06/22/2000</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>04/11/2001</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0000947</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Christopher</FirstName>
      <LastName>Scholz</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>scholz@ldeo.columbia.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>06/22/2000</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Columbia University</Name>
      <CityName>NEW YORK</CityName>
      <ZipCode>100276902</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>2128546851</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>2960 Broadway</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>New York</StateName>
      <StateCode>NY</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0000099</Code>
      <Name>Other Applications NEC</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
