<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Lubricant Film Thickness Mapping Using a Scanning Capacitance Technique with a Nanoscale Lateral Resolution</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>02/15/2000</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2002</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardAmount>99900</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<LongName>Div Of Civil, Mechanical, &amp; Manufact Inn</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Jorn Larsen-Basse</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>An SGER award will support development of a novel scanning capacitance measurement technique for lubricant film thickness mapping on engineering surfaces.  It is expected that this technique will allow non-destructive mapping of variations in lubricant thickness as small as 0.1 nm and with a nanoscale lateral resolution.  Existing techniques allow measurements only with a microscale lateral resolution.  The proposed technique is of great interest in applications where lubricant films of mono-molecular thickness are used.  It is expected that the proposed technique, if successful, can be developed for quality control purposes for the $ 100 billion per year magnetic storage industry, the emerging microdevices industry, and other applications using ultra-thin films.  An existing AFM will be adapted with a scanning capacitance microscopy module, which will be modified to operate with a sharp, conducting probe.  The measurements, as envisioned, will consist of an initial conventional AFM topography scan of the metal surface, followed by a scan in the same track but in the capacitance mode and with the tip at 100 nm height above the metal surface, as controlled by input from the topography scan.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>02/04/2000</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>02/08/2001</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>0001382</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Bharat</FirstName>
<LastName>Bhushan</LastName>
<EmailAddress>bhushan.2@osu.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>02/04/2000</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Ohio State University Research Foundation -DO NOT USE</Name>
<CityName>Columbus</CityName>
<ZipCode>432101016</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6146888734</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1960 KENNY RD</StreetAddress>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Ohio</StateName>
<StateCode>OH</StateCode>
</Institution>
<FoaInformation>
<Code>0308000</Code>
<Name>Industrial Technology</Name>
</FoaInformation>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1633</Code>
<Text>MATERIALS AND SURFACE ENG</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9146</Code>
<Text>MANUFACTURING BASE RESEARCH</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9231</Code>
<Text>SUPPL FOR UNDERGRAD RES ASSIST</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9237</Code>
<Text>SMALL GRANTS-EXPLORATORY RSRCH</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9251</Code>
<Text>RES EXPER FOR UNDERGRAD-SUPPLT</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>MANU</Code>
<Text>MANUFACTURING</Text>
</ProgramReference>
</Award>
</rootTag>
