<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>US National Committee for IUGG Support of the Secretariat</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>06/15/2000</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2005</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>149204</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>06000000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Louis B. Brown</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The principal investigator will, as Secretary-General of the International Union of Geodesy and Geophysics (IUGG), will provide leadership for and assist the IUGG to promote and coordinate physical, chemical, and mathematical studies of the Earth and its environment in space. These studies address a number of important scientific processes related to, inter alia, the dynamics of the Earth as a whole; all aspects of the oceans, the atmosphere and ionosphere; the Earth's internal structure; volcanism and rock formation; and the hydrological cycle. Many of these studies contribute to productive global-scale interdisciplinary research programs, such as the World Climate Research Programme (WCRP); the International Geosphere-Biosphere Programme (IGBP); and the International Decade for Natural Disaster Reduction. The PI will serve as Secretary-General of the IUGG. She will coordinate activities of the IUGG Bureau which manages all affairs of the Union, including development of guidance for the IUGG's scientific objectives. Specific activities to be supported include development, maintenance, and updating of an IUGG database, especially in electronic format; design, preparation and distribution of IUGG publications; and assistance with IUGG news releases.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>06/20/2000</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>06/10/2003</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0001695</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>JoAnn</FirstName>
      <LastName>Joselyn</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>jjoselyn@cires.colorado.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>06/20/2000</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Colorado at Boulder</Name>
      <CityName>Boulder</CityName>
      <ZipCode>803031058</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>3034926221</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>3100 Marine Street, Room 481</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Colorado</StateName>
      <StateCode>CO</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0204000</Code>
      <Name>Oceanography</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1679</Code>
      <Text>INTERNATIONAL COORDINATION ACT</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>5419</Code>
      <Text>INTERNATIONAL SUPPORT</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>0000</Code>
      <Text>UNASSIGNED</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>OTHR</Code>
      <Text>OTHER RESEARCH OR EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
