<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Khirbat al-Mudayna al Aliya: Production, Politics, and Power in an Iron Age Village</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2000</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2006</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardAmount>131676</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>04040400</Code>
<Directorate>
<LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<LongName>Division Of Behavioral and Cognitive Sci</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>John Yellen</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>With the support of the National Science Foundation, Dr. Routledge&lt;br/&gt;and his colleagues will conduct a program of archaeological excavation and&lt;br/&gt;survey in the vicinity Khirbat al-Mudayna al-`Aliya (KMA) on the eastern&lt;br/&gt;edge of Jordan's Karak Plateau, ca. 35 kilometers due east of the Dead Sea.&lt;br/&gt;KMA is an exceptionally well-preserved village occupied for a brief period&lt;br/&gt;of time in the last half of the eleventh century BC (Iron Age Ib).&lt;br/&gt;Importantly, this occupation immediately precedes the emergence of&lt;br/&gt;territorial states in the region, including the biblical state of Moab into&lt;br/&gt;which this part of Jordan was incorporated in the ninth century BC.  The&lt;br/&gt;founding, and brief occupation, of substantial villages in what is now an&lt;br/&gt;agriculturally marginal part of Jordan raises many questions about economic&lt;br/&gt;and political developments during this period of significant social change.&lt;br/&gt;Dr. Routledge's research aims to address these issues by elucidating the&lt;br/&gt;cultural form, political economy, and local ecology of Khirbat al-Mudayna&lt;br/&gt;al-'Aliya and its surrounding Iron Age settlement system.  In particular,&lt;br/&gt;evidence will be sought for past environmental change, crop husbandry&lt;br/&gt;practices, herding strategies and off-site pastoral activities, household&lt;br/&gt;organization, the spatial distribution of activity areas in relation to&lt;br/&gt;architectural variation, and exchange "paths" between households.  This&lt;br/&gt;evidence will not only shed light on the political economy of local&lt;br/&gt;agro-pastoral production strategies, it will also illumine the structuring&lt;br/&gt;practices of everyday life that are the social context for these&lt;br/&gt;strategies.  One key idea to be tested in this research is the suitability&lt;br/&gt;of African models of state formation that emphasize social relations over&lt;br/&gt;Eurasian models that emphasize control of land.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/11/2000</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/13/2005</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>0001661</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Jeremy</FirstName>
<LastName>Sabloff</LastName>
<EmailAddress>jsabloff@sas.upenn.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>04/23/2004</StartDate>
<EndDate>06/02/2005</EndDate>
<RoleCode>Former Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Richard</FirstName>
<LastName>Leventhal</LastName>
<EmailAddress>rml@sas.upenn.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>06/02/2005</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Bruce</FirstName>
<LastName>Routledge</LastName>
<EmailAddress>bruce.routledge@liv.ac.uk</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>07/11/2000</StartDate>
<EndDate>04/23/2004</EndDate>
<RoleCode>Former Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Pennsylvania</Name>
<CityName>Philadelphia</CityName>
<ZipCode>191046205</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2158987293</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>Research Services</StreetAddress>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Pennsylvania</StateName>
<StateCode>PA</StateCode>
</Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1391</Code>
<Text>ARCHAEOLOGY</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>0000</Code>
<Text>UNASSIGNED</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>OTHR</Code>
<Text>OTHER RESEARCH OR EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
</Award>
</rootTag>
