<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Late Pliocene Hominid Bahavior and Paleoecology at Kanjera South, Africa</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>07/15/2000</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2003</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>223831</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>04040400</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Behavioral and Cognitive Sci</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>John E. Yellen</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>With National Science Foundation support, Dr. Tom Plummer and colleagues &lt;br/&gt;will conduct two field seasons of excavation at Kanjera South, southwestern &lt;br/&gt;Kenya. The team brings together specialists in archaeology, paleontology, &lt;br/&gt;paleoecology and geology to conduct an interdisciplinary investigation of &lt;br/&gt;the behavior and paleoecology of hominids forming early archeological &lt;br/&gt;(Oldowan) sites. The appearance of Oldowan archeological sites at c. 2.5 &lt;br/&gt;million years ago (Ma) reflects a profound adaptive shift in human &lt;br/&gt;evolution, the incorporation of large mammal tissue into the diet. The &lt;br/&gt;proposed project will be the first to carry out a detailed study of site &lt;br/&gt;formation processes at Oldowan sites older than 2.0 Ma, using a wide range &lt;br/&gt;of traditional and innovative methodologies.&lt;br/&gt;Excavations in 1996 and 1997 located rich concentrations of artifacts and &lt;br/&gt;fossils in c. 2.2 Ma deposits in the Southern Exposures at Kanjera. Over &lt;br/&gt;1,000 stone tools and thousands of fossils were collected in carefully &lt;br/&gt;controlled taphonomic excavations. Documentation of relatively high &lt;br/&gt;archeological densities in three beds at two of five sites along a 70m &lt;br/&gt;transect suggests that hominid activity was spatially focused for a &lt;br/&gt;considerable length of time. Preliminary lab analysis has identified &lt;br/&gt;hominid marrow processing and carnivore damage to bone, as well as several &lt;br/&gt;artifact refits. Stable isotopic chemistry of paleosol carbonates and high &lt;br/&gt;equid frequencies indicate Oldowan hominid activities in a novel (open) &lt;br/&gt;paleohabitat. A high proportion of small, immature mammals is suggestive of &lt;br/&gt;small mammal hunting while medium to very large mammal remains (including a &lt;br/&gt;potentially butchered hippopotamus) may have been scavenged. Hominid &lt;br/&gt;transport of artifacts and raw material selectivity is suggested by lithic &lt;br/&gt;analysis.&lt;br/&gt;Expanding the samples of excavated material will allow reconstruction of &lt;br/&gt;hominid activities within their paleoecological context at Kanjera and &lt;br/&gt;facilitate meaningful comparisons with other large Oldowan site assemblages, &lt;br/&gt;particularly those from Olduvai Gorge, Tanzania and the Lake Turkana basin, &lt;br/&gt;Kenya and Ethiopia. Faunal analysis will provide information on hominid &lt;br/&gt;procurement and processing of animals as well as the role of carnivore &lt;br/&gt;activity in assemblage formation. Lithic analysis will document local &lt;br/&gt;technological characteristics and hominid transport behavior as well as the &lt;br/&gt;tasks chert artifacts were used for. Paleoenvironmental information will be &lt;br/&gt;obtained using multiple methodologies. Limb element ecomorphic analyses and &lt;br/&gt;isotopic analysis of carbonates will provide information on habitat &lt;br/&gt;structure. Ecomorphic analysis of mandibles and analysis of carbon isotopes &lt;br/&gt;from enamel will provide paleodietary information. Oxygen isotopes in tooth &lt;br/&gt;enamel will constrain paleotemperatures and the degree of seasonality during &lt;br/&gt;Kanjera Fm (S) deposition. Cementum analysis will be used to assess &lt;br/&gt;antelope season of death.&lt;br/&gt;Documentation of hominid utilization of open habitats at Kanjera may &lt;br/&gt;influence views of early hominid capabilities, including their ability to &lt;br/&gt;compete with large carnivores. This project should also contribute to the &lt;br/&gt;on-going debate over faunal acquisition strategies, by providing a test of &lt;br/&gt;whether small mammals were hunted. As the sample of medium and larger sized &lt;br/&gt;mammals increases, it may be possible to assess the timing of access to &lt;br/&gt;larger carcasses and thus whether hominids were passively or actively &lt;br/&gt;scavenging them. Our attempts to measure the intensity of seasonality &lt;br/&gt;through the sequence, as well as the influence of seasonality on hominid &lt;br/&gt;foraging for animal tissue, have not been conducted on this scale before and &lt;br/&gt;may provide valuable information on the motivation and frequency of Oldowan &lt;br/&gt;carnivory.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>07/26/2000</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>06/13/2001</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0001453</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Thomas</FirstName>
      <LastName>Plummer</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>thomas.plummer@qc.cuny.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/26/2000</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>CUNY Queens College</Name>
      <CityName>Flushing</CityName>
      <ZipCode>113671575</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>7189975400</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>65 30 Kissena Blvd</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>New York</StateName>
      <StateCode>NY</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
