<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Differentiation and Resistance Among St. Lucian Banana Growers</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/15/2001</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2005</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>70820.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>83048</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>04040400</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>SBE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>BCS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Behavioral and Cognitive Sci</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Deborah Winslow</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>0003965&lt;br/&gt;Moberg&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The viability of household-based agriculture in competition with corporate farm commodity producers has been an enduring interest of third-world development studies. This project assesses the effects of free trade policies in farming communities on St. Lucia, which has the largest number of banana farms in the Windward Islands, Caribbean. The research assesses the predictions prevalent in the Caribbean that the 1998 World Trade Organization ruling striking down a tariff-quota system of preferential treatment would be severely detrimental to household banana production.  However other theorists predict that household commodity producers can use their lower labor and production costs to remain competitive. In addition to testing these hypotheses the project will document the ways growers respond to globalization in the political realm given local traditions of intense rural political activity, as well as illustrate the extent to which neoliberal models of trade are politically sustainable in the Eastern Caribbean. The project will study farms in two nearby locales, testing hypotheses about differentiation, survival in farming and political activity through participant observation, semi-structured interviews of knowledgeable informants, and structured surveys of banana growers in the two regions. The new knowledge to be created will be valuable to development theorists as well as planners. &lt;br/&gt;</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>01/05/2001</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>12/04/2003</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>0003965</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Mark</FirstName>
<LastName>Moberg</LastName>
<EmailAddress>mmoberg@jaguar1.usouthal.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>01/05/2001</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of South Alabama</Name>
<CityName>Mobile</CityName>
<ZipCode>366880002</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2514606333</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>307 University Boulevard</StreetAddress>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Alabama</StateName>
<StateCode>AL</StateCode>
</Institution>
<FoaInformation>
<Code>0116000</Code>
<Name>Human Subjects</Name>
</FoaInformation>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1390</Code>
<Text>Cultural Anthropology</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>0000</Code>
<Text>UNASSIGNED</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>OTHR</Code>
<Text>OTHER RESEARCH OR EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
</Award>
</rootTag>
