<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>SGER:  Notilucent Cloud Occurance and Properties and Mid-Latitudes</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/15/2000</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2003</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardAmount>38373</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>06020201</Code>
<Directorate>
<LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<LongName>Div Atmospheric &amp; Geospace Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Robert B. Kerr</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Abstract ATM-0003684&lt;br/&gt;PI: Dr. M. J. Taylor&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;A SGER exploratory investigation of the occurrence and characteristics of noctilucent clouds (NLC) at mid-latitudes will be carried out to investigate the unususal occurrences of these events at mid-latitudes during the summer. These clouds are more typically observed at polar latitudes (&gt; 55 N) and the detection of NLCs during the 99 summer at Logan Utah on the two dates of 22/23 and 23/24 of June was by happenstance.  These two events may have been simply a rare occurrence with a low probability of re-occurrence. However, increases in NLC occurrence frequency and/or changes in their latitudinal extent have been linked to potentially serious changes taking place in the upper mesospheric climate.  This award will support a systematic series of optical observations with high resolution digital photography to determine the properties of these clouds were they to re-occur.  This work will be carried out over the summers of the next two years.  If the occurrence of mid-latitude NLC displays is indeed established and if they are found to be on the increase, then this study could have a profound influence on future NSF sponsored research efforts as such results may well portend major, long-term, global changes taking place in the upper atmosphere.&lt;br/&gt;</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/11/2000</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/05/2002</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>0003684</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Michael</FirstName>
<LastName>Taylor</LastName>
<EmailAddress>mike.taylor@usu.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>08/11/2000</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Utah State University Research Foundation</Name>
<CityName>Logan</CityName>
<ZipCode>843411947</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>4357133060</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1695 North Research Park Way</StreetAddress>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Utah</StateName>
<StateCode>UT</StateCode>
</Institution>
<FoaInformation>
<Code>0205000</Code>
<Name>Space</Name>
</FoaInformation>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1521</Code>
<Text>AERONOMY</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>0000</Code>
<Text>UNASSIGNED</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9237</Code>
<Text>SMALL GRANTS-EXPLORATORY RSRCH</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>OTHR</Code>
<Text>OTHER RESEARCH OR EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
</Award>
</rootTag>
