<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>SBIR Phase I:  Boron Nitride Nanotubes Manufacture</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>01/01/2001</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2001</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>100000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>100000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07070000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>IIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Industrial Innovation &amp; Partnersh</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Cynthia J. Ekstein</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This Small Business Innovation Research (SBIR) Phase I project will synthesize boron nitride nanotubes by a continuous pyrolysis method that can be readily scaled to produce industrial quantities at reasonable costs.  Intensive research is being conducted on single-walled carbon nanotubes (C-SWNTs) to take advantage of their incredibly high specific strength in composite material reinforcements, and their unusual electron&lt;br/&gt;transport properties in nanoscale electronic devices.  Their properties and applications stem from the defect-free arrangement of carbon atoms into a filament with extremely high aspect ratio (length/diameter), currently around 10,000.  However, the high aspect ratio, tubular geometry, and atomic perfection are not unique to carbon; nanotubes (NTs) can be formed from many other layered materials, including boron nitride.  BN-NTs, while also exhibiting high strength, have commercially attractive properties that are complementary to the C-SWNTs, based on the chemical differences between BN and graphite.  The most&lt;br/&gt;prominent characteristics unique to BN-NTs are oxidation resistance, optical transparency, and uniformity. BN-NTs are currently made in benchtop reactors by arc evaporation of boron rods, a low-throughput, uneconomical batch process.  By developing an improved synthetic method, BN-NTs will become available for materials research and applications.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Boron nitride nanotubes will have applications as reinforcements in high-end composite materials.  The best uses of BN nanotubes are complementary to those of C-SWNTs.  For example, the BN-NTs have the potential to form high strength, high temperature, form metal carbides.  As another example, BN-NT reinforcement of a polymer matrix will maintain the electrically insulating and optical transmission properties of the matrix,&lt;br/&gt;whereas C-SWNTs impart electrical conductivity and opacity to the polymer matrix.   Also, the improved chemical resistance, particularly to oxygen attack, will improve the BN-NT stability at elevated temperatures and other severe service conditions.&lt;br/&gt;</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>11/21/2000</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>11/21/2000</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>0060326</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Michael</FirstName>
<LastName>Diener</LastName>
<EmailAddress>mikee@tda.com</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>11/21/2000</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>TDA Research, Inc</Name>
<CityName>WHEAT RIDGE</CityName>
<ZipCode>800333191</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>3039402301</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>12345 W 52ND AVE</StreetAddress>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Colorado</StateName>
<StateCode>CO</StateCode>
</Institution>
<FoaInformation>
<Code>0308000</Code>
<Name>Industrial Technology</Name>
</FoaInformation>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>5371</Code>
<Text>SBIR Phase I</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1415</Code>
<Text>PARTICULATE &amp;MULTIPHASE PROCES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9163</Code>
<Text>SINGLE DIVISION/UNIVERSITY - INDUSTRY</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>AMPP</Code>
<Text>ADVANCED MATERIALS &amp; PROCESSING PROGRAM</Text>
</ProgramReference>
</Award>
</rootTag>
