<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Polynomial ergodic theorems and Ramsey theory</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2000</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2004</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>172416.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>176216</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03040100</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DMS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Dmitry Khavinson</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>ABSTRACT:&lt;br/&gt;The project concentrates on multiple recurrence and convergence in&lt;br/&gt;dynamical systems with a focus on polynomial actions of abelian and&lt;br/&gt;nilpotent groups. The problems considered lead to diverse applications of&lt;br/&gt;ergodic theory to combinatorics, number theory and algebra which are&lt;br/&gt;inaccessible so far by conventional methods. The polynomial Szemeredi and&lt;br/&gt;Hales-Jewett theorems proved by the proposers in the recent years have&lt;br/&gt;since been extended by the proposers and their colleagues in different&lt;br/&gt;directions, each providing a better understanding of the phenomenon of&lt;br/&gt;multiple recurrence along polynomials and offering new vistas of research.&lt;br/&gt;The directions of study touched upon in this proposal include&lt;br/&gt;(but are not limited to) the deeper study of multiple recurrence for&lt;br/&gt;nilpotent group actions and the investigation of polynomial multiple&lt;br/&gt;recurrence in the framework of IP-systems. Another interesting area&lt;br/&gt;considered in this proposal has to do with convergence of ergodic averages&lt;br/&gt;naturally appearing in the theory of multiple recurrence and its&lt;br/&gt;applications. The results recently obtained by the proposers indicate a&lt;br/&gt;dichotomy between the behavior of ergodic averages depending on whether&lt;br/&gt;the acting groups have polynomial or exponential growth. The&lt;br/&gt;related conjectures formulated in the last section of the proposal are&lt;br/&gt;shedding new light on these questions.&lt;br/&gt; &lt;br/&gt; The theory of multiple recurrence that we focus on in this project uses&lt;br/&gt;the ideas from several diverse areas of mathematics and aims to advance&lt;br/&gt;our knowledge about the intrinsic properties of dynamical systems which&lt;br/&gt;are related to their long range behavior. An example of a highly&lt;br/&gt;nontrivial fact stemming from our investigations is the regularity of the&lt;br/&gt;behavior of dynamical systems along polynomial time measurements. This&lt;br/&gt;fact, in its turn, has strong applications to seemingly distant areas of&lt;br/&gt;number theory and combinatorics.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/10/2000</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/22/2002</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>0070566</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Vitaly</FirstName>
<LastName>Bergelson</LastName>
<EmailAddress>vitaly@math.ohio-state.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>07/10/2000</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Alexander</FirstName>
<LastName>Leibman</LastName>
<EmailAddress>leibman.1@osu.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>07/10/2000</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Ohio State University Research Foundation -DO NOT USE</Name>
<CityName>Columbus</CityName>
<ZipCode>432101016</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6146888734</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1960 KENNY RD</StreetAddress>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Ohio</StateName>
<StateCode>OH</StateCode>
</Institution>
<FoaInformation>
<Code>0000099</Code>
<Name>Other Applications NEC</Name>
</FoaInformation>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1281</Code>
<Text>ANALYSIS PROGRAM</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>0000</Code>
<Text>UNASSIGNED</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9251</Code>
<Text>REU SUPP-Res Exp for Ugrd Supp</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>OTHR</Code>
<Text>OTHER RESEARCH OR EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
</Award>
</rootTag>
