<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Geometry and Topology of Counting Curves in Projective Manifolds</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/15/2000</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>11/30/2001</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>78124.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>78124</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03040200</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DMS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Christopher Stark</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Abstract&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Award:  DMS-0072182&lt;br/&gt;Principal Investigator:  Kefeng Liu&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;My project will focus on the understanding of the geometry and&lt;br/&gt;topology of mirror symmetry, in particular the aspect of counting&lt;br/&gt;curves in projective manifolds. More precisely there are three&lt;br/&gt;outstanding and closely related problems that I would like to&lt;br/&gt;work on and hope to solve. The first is to prove the most general&lt;br/&gt;mirror principle for counting rational curves in any projective&lt;br/&gt;manifold and its Calabi-Yau submanifolds; the second is to&lt;br/&gt;understand the geometry and algebra of the local mirror symmetry,&lt;br/&gt;in particular, of the surprising role played by the elliptic&lt;br/&gt;curves appeared in our computation by applying mirror principle;&lt;br/&gt;the third is to develop a mirror principle for counting curves of&lt;br/&gt;higher genus in projective manifolds. I hope to solve these&lt;br/&gt;problems by further extending the techniques we developed to&lt;br/&gt;prove the mirror principle for balloon manifolds. These three&lt;br/&gt;problems are the different aspects of a single problem: to prove&lt;br/&gt;and understand the mirror principle in its most general form.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Superstring theory, one of the most ambitious theory in sciences,&lt;br/&gt;is proposed for the grand unification of the laws of the nature.&lt;br/&gt;Based on this theory, string theorists have made many remarkable&lt;br/&gt;mathematical conjectures. Mirror symmetry is among one of them.&lt;br/&gt;The proofs of these conjectures will not only give beautiful&lt;br/&gt;mathematical results, but also help gain confidence in the&lt;br/&gt;physical theory. The mirror principle we developed has partially&lt;br/&gt;verified some of these conjectures. It has many interesting&lt;br/&gt;mathematical consequences and is remarkably compatible with the&lt;br/&gt;physical theory.&lt;br/&gt;</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/17/2000</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/17/2000</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>0072182</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Kefeng</FirstName>
<LastName>Liu</LastName>
<EmailAddress>liu@math.ucla.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>07/17/2000</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Stanford University</Name>
<CityName>Stanford</CityName>
<ZipCode>943052004</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6507232300</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>450 Jane Stanford Way</StreetAddress>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
</Institution>
<FoaInformation>
<Code>0000099</Code>
<Name>Other Applications NEC</Name>
</FoaInformation>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1265</Code>
<Text>GEOMETRIC ANALYSIS</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>0000</Code>
<Text>UNASSIGNED</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>OTHR</Code>
<Text>OTHER RESEARCH OR EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
</Award>
</rootTag>
