<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Dissertation Research: Anaerobic Mirobial Metabolism and the Biogeochemical Functioning of Wetlands</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>06/01/2000</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>11/30/2002</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardAmount>9970</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>08010208</Code>
<Directorate>
<LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<LongName>Division Of Environmental Biology</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Nancy C. Tuchman</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>00-72980&lt;br/&gt;Hamilton / Whitmire&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;DDIG: Anaerobic microbial metabolism and the biogeochemical functioning of wetlands&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Microbial decomposition of organic matter plays a central role in the functioning of wetlands, and much of this decomposition occurs in the absence of oxygen (e.g., anaerobic conditions).  Anaerobic microorganisms mediate chemical transformations that alter downstream water quality, and emit greenhouse gases such as methane to the atmosphere, thereby affecting climate.  By understanding how the nature and rates of microbial processes vary across a broad suite of wetland ecosystems, we can better predict the impacts of disturbance on the functions of wetlands. This research will evaluate these microbial processes in a variety of Michigan wetlands. Techniques developed for marine and groundwater studies will be employed to determine the dominant microbial processes.  Substances to be measured will include dissolved hydrogen gas, a universal intermediary in decomposition, as well as chemical byproducts of anaerobic metabolism. Specific process rates, including acetate turnover and sulfate reduction, will be measured to corroborate the findings.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/07/2000</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/21/2002</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>0072980</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Stephen</FirstName>
<LastName>Hamilton</LastName>
<EmailAddress>hamilton@msu.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>06/07/2000</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Michigan State University</Name>
<CityName>East Lansing</CityName>
<ZipCode>488242600</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5173555040</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>Office of Sponsored Programs</StreetAddress>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Michigan</StateName>
<StateCode>MI</StateCode>
</Institution>
<FoaInformation>
<Code>0510602</Code>
<Name>Ecosystem Dynamics</Name>
</FoaInformation>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1181</Code>
<Text>ECOSYSTEM STUDIES</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9169</Code>
<Text>BIODIVERSITY AND ECOSYSTEM DYNAMICS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>EGCH</Code>
<Text>ENVIRONMENT AND GLOBAL CHANGE</Text>
</ProgramReference>
</Award>
</rootTag>
