<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>The Isomorphism Conjectures for surgery L-groups, algebraic K-groups, and stable pseudo-isotopy spaces</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>06/15/2000</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>01/31/2004</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>147177</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03040200</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Benjamin M. Mann</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>DMS-0072349&lt;br/&gt;Lowell E. Jones&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Let G be an arbitrary discrete group. Jones and Farrell &lt;br/&gt;have conjectured ("Isomorphism Conjectures") that the &lt;br/&gt;surgery L-groups of G, L(G), and the algebraic K-groups &lt;br/&gt;of the integral group ring Z(G), K(Z(G)), should be &lt;br/&gt;computable in a simple way from the collections of all &lt;br/&gt;the groups L(H), K(Z(H)) where H is any cyclic by finite &lt;br/&gt;subgroup of G. The truth of these conjecutures would &lt;br/&gt;imply rigidity results for aspherical manifolds &lt;br/&gt;("Borel Conjecture") and also would yield much information &lt;br/&gt;about the spaces of homeomorphisms and diffeomorphisms &lt;br/&gt;of aspherical manifolds. Jones,in collaboration with Farrell, &lt;br/&gt;is trying to verify the isomorphism conjectures for any group &lt;br/&gt;G which acts properly discontinuously via isometries on a &lt;br/&gt;complete Riemannian manifold having non-positive curvature. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Modern day geometers and topologists are concerned with &lt;br/&gt;"spaces" and what they look like. The surface of a donut, &lt;br/&gt;the sphere and the plane are examples of 2-dimensional &lt;br/&gt;spaces which are all different from one another from both &lt;br/&gt;the perspective of geometry and topology. One way that &lt;br/&gt;topologists study spaces (not just of dimension 2 but of&lt;br/&gt;higher dimension also) is to associate to each space some &lt;br/&gt;algebraic gadgets. It is conjectured that for many &lt;br/&gt;interesting spaces these algebraic gadgets act like &lt;br/&gt;a "genetic code" for the space, in that they tell us &lt;br/&gt;most everything we want to know about the space. Thus &lt;br/&gt;there are two fundamental problems here: to verify this &lt;br/&gt;"genetic code conjecture"; and to decifer the genetic code &lt;br/&gt;for the spaces which are of interest to geometers and topologists.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>06/06/2000</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>02/19/2002</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0072349</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Lowell</FirstName>
      <LastName>Jones</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>lejones@math.sunysb.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>06/06/2000</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>SUNY at Stony Brook</Name>
      <CityName>Stony Brook</CityName>
      <ZipCode>117940001</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>6316329949</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>WEST 5510 FRK MEL LIB</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>New York</StateName>
      <StateCode>NY</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0000099</Code>
      <Name>Other Applications NEC</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1267</Code>
      <Text>TOPOLOGY</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>0000</Code>
      <Text>UNASSIGNED</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>OTHR</Code>
      <Text>OTHER RESEARCH OR EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
