<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>POWRE:  Molecular Control of Interfaces in Insitu Polymer-Hydroxyapatite Composites for Bone Replacement</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2000</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>01/31/2002</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>75000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>75000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CMMI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Civil, Mechanical, &amp; Manufact Inn</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Jorn Larsen-Basse</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>&lt;br/&gt;0074662&lt;br/&gt;Katti&lt;br/&gt;In the quest for new materials for bone replacement, it is of interest to design composites with mechanical properties similar to that of bone to avoid problems such as stress shielding of surrounding bone that are associated with the current coated metallic implants. The focus of this POWRE award is to investigate means of controlling mechanical properties in insitu hydroxyapatite(HAP)-polymer composites for their potential use as bone replacement. A molecular control of crystallization of inorganic phases by organic compounds has shown great promise for fabrication of new composites for several applications. Ionic polymers such as poly(acrylic acid) (PAAc) are suitable due to their ability to strongly bind Ca ions. The major aim of the proposed research is to identify and determine fundamental molecular interactions between HAP and polymeric additive during mineralization of HAP. This will allow for a control of microstructural evolution of HAP and hence the observed mechanical behavior in insitu HAP/polymer composites. The specific research objectives are: &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;1. To develop a fundamental understanding of molecular level interactions of organic and inorganic phases in polymer-hydroxyapatite insitu composites. The specific role of ionic polymer chains on microcrystalline aggregate formation and nucleation and growth of HAP will be investigated. &lt;br/&gt;2. Correlate molecular parameters (such as vibrational band intensity changes and shifts) to macroscopic mechanical behavior such as tensile and compressive strengths. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The PI is a new faculty at NDSU. The POWRE grant will help her establish an independent research program and further her career development. This grant will help the PI to develop a first research initiative to establish a Biomaterials research and education program at NDSU. The PI proposes to integrate research with education in the Biomaterials field by involving undergraduate women and/or minority students into active research. At the conclusion of the proposed studies, the PI plans to integrate results of the study into development of a new course on Biomaterials. This course will be focussed towards senior level and graduate engineering students and will promote the importance of Biomaterials in the engineering community at NDSU.&lt;br/&gt;*** &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/31/2000</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/31/2000</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>0074662</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Kalpana</FirstName>
<LastName>Katti</LastName>
<EmailAddress>kalpana.katti@ndsu.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>07/31/2000</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>North Dakota State University Fargo</Name>
<CityName>FARGO</CityName>
<ZipCode>581086050</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>7012318045</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>Dept 4000 - PO Box 6050</StreetAddress>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>North Dakota</StateName>
<StateCode>ND</StateCode>
</Institution>
<FoaInformation>
<Code>0308000</Code>
<Name>Industrial Technology</Name>
</FoaInformation>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1592</Code>
<Text>PROF OPPOR FOR WOMEN IN RSCH</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>X568</Code>
<Text/>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1592</Code>
<Text>PROF OPPOR FOR WOMEN IN RSCH</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9102</Code>
<Text>WOMEN, MINORITY, DISABLED, NEC</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9161</Code>
<Text>SINGLE DIVISION/UNIVERSITY</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>AMPP</Code>
<Text>ADVANCED MATERIALS &amp; PROCESSING PROGRAM</Text>
</ProgramReference>
</Award>
</rootTag>
