<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>POWRE: Evolution of Sociality in a Behaviorally Flexible Marmot</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/15/2000</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2002</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>50000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>50000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>08090300</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>BIO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>IOS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Integrative Organismal Systems</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>William E. Zamer</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>       Evolution of animal social behavior often involves a series of steps whereby individuals live near relatives, become more tolerant of each other, share more space and increasingly cooperate with those relatives.  One group of mammals, the marmots, offers excellent opportunities to study evolution of sociality because its members demonstrate many levels of sociality, ranging from the less social woodchuck to the highly social alpine marmot. Marmots may have evolved from an ancestor that most resembles today's woodchucks in terms of social behavior and organization.  Thus, by discerning the woodchuck's level of social organization, the evolution of sociality in marmots can be understood more completely.&lt;br/&gt;       This project will investigate social organization in woodchucks, which traditionally are described as asocial and aggressive but which show greater development of sociality in some populations. The objective is to assess genetic relationships among woodchucks, to document mating systems, behavioral and spatial patterns, and to explore relationships among these factors. Specifically, the PI will determine (1) if females settle closer to relatives than males do, forming kin groups, and (2) if close relatives are more tolerant of each other than distant relatives and share greater amounts of space. The PI will employ DNA fingerprinting techniques to assess genetic relatedness and the mating system. She also will use implanted radiotransmitters to gather information about where animals settle and patterns of space use, and she will observe marked individuals to collect information about interaction rates and about breeding pairs.&lt;br/&gt;       After five years in a tenure-track position, the PI moved to a new institution, which necessitated a change in research focus.  This POWRE award will allow her to learn the surgical and molecular techniques required for testing ideas about evolution of sociality.  It will lay foundations for future work and will provide exceptional opportunities for undergraduate students to gain valuable research experiences both in the field and in the laboratory.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/11/2000</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/11/2000</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>0074458</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Christine</FirstName>
<LastName>Maher</LastName>
<EmailAddress>cmaher@maine.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>08/11/2000</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Southern Maine</Name>
<CityName>Portland</CityName>
<ZipCode>041049300</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2072288536</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>96 Falmouth St</StreetAddress>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Maine</StateName>
<StateCode>ME</StateCode>
</Institution>
<FoaInformation>
<Code>0000099</Code>
<Name>Other Applications NEC</Name>
</FoaInformation>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1160</Code>
<Text>IBN ANIMAL BEHAVIOR</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1592</Code>
<Text>PROF OPPOR FOR WOMEN IN RSCH</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9169</Code>
<Text>BIODIVERSITY AND ECOSYSTEM DYNAMICS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>EGCH</Code>
<Text>ENVIRONMENT AND GLOBAL CHANGE</Text>
</ProgramReference>
</Award>
</rootTag>
