<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>POWRE:  Power Systems Stability in a Deregulated Environment</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/15/2000</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2002</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>55366.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>55366</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07010000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>ECCS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Electrical, Commun &amp; Cyber Sys</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Paul Werbos</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>0074280&lt;br/&gt;Fatehi&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;In the electric utility industry, a significant change is occurring with the move towards deregulation and an increase in competition.  This development in the industry will have a profound impact on the way power transmission systems are designed.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;One of the most significant effects of this change is that the transmission systems are being much more heavily used to transfer electric energy from one region of the country to another.  The motivating reason for the increased usage is purely economic, i.e., large wholesale energy buyers are able to satisfy their electric energy needs by purchasing less expensive energy from geographically distant regions and subsequently using the transmission system to move it to the place of consumption.  In this way, marketplace pressure is allowed to drive down the price of electric energy.  This will result in electric transmission systems being significantly more stressed as larger quantities of energy are transported over much longer distances.  Consequently, the future of the electric power industry requires a mechanism that allows for a competitive environment while ensuring that power system operating conditions are secure.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The goals of the proposed project are: 1) To study the total transfer capability and transient stability limit of western North American power system using large-scale simulation models 2) To investigate application of Flexible AC Transmission Systems (FACT) devices to enhance the power transfer capability and transient stability limits of the power systems. 3) To develop robust control strategies to improve maximum loadability of the transmission lines in a high order model of western North American power system.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The results of this research are expected to be of substantial value in the development of power systems in future and in providing more economic and secure electricity in the deregulated environment.  The funding of this project will result in an increase in the number of competent professional women with advanced knowledge of power systems and control theory.&lt;br/&gt;***&lt;br/&gt;</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/20/2000</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/20/2000</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>0074280</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Fereshteh</FirstName>
<LastName>Fatehi</LastName>
<EmailAddress>fatehi@ncat.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>07/20/2000</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>North Carolina Agricultural &amp; Technical State University</Name>
<CityName>Greensboro</CityName>
<ZipCode>274110001</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>3363347995</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1601 E. Market Street</StreetAddress>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>North Carolina</StateName>
<StateCode>NC</StateCode>
</Institution>
<FoaInformation>
<Code>0206000</Code>
<Name>Telecommunications</Name>
</FoaInformation>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1518</Code>
<Text>CONTROL, NETWORKS, &amp; COMP INTE</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>0000</Code>
<Text>UNASSIGNED</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1592</Code>
<Text>PROF OPPOR FOR WOMEN IN RSCH</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>OTHR</Code>
<Text>OTHER RESEARCH OR EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
</Award>
</rootTag>
