<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>The Empirical Analysis of Local Interaction Models</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2000</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2003</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>165783</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>04050100</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Divn Of Social and Economic Sciences</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Daniel H. Newlon</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This research project's common theme is the empirical evaluation of economic models in which agents' decisions and outcomes are affected by other agents' behavior directly, rather than being mediated by markets. A common assumption in these models is that individuals interact locally with a set of neighbors defined by a social or economic distance metric. The proposed research is concerned with analyzing models of local social interactions in the context of job search and urban unemployment.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The primary objectives of the project are threefold. First, the conditions under which one can identify the model parameters, or at least place bounds on the magnitude of the local interactions, are explored. Second, the project studies whether identification can still be attained when the researcher only has access to spatially aggregated data, and determines how the estimates change as one moves to different levels of aggregation (e.g., block groups, Census tracts, Community Areas). Third, this project aims at studying the dynamic properties of local interaction models: in particular, determining how long it takes to reach the stationary distribution, measuring the persistence of clusters generated by these models, and computing Impulse Response Functions in time and in space to exogenous shocks. The secondary objective of the project is to develop empirical methodologies in order to estimate and test the validity of such models. In particular, the identification analysis will guide the choice of the specific estimation strategy to be employed.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The proposed research uses Bureau of Census data, augmented by other sources, on several large U.S. cities. Spatial correlation patterns in the data are analyzed using a non-parametric estimator of Auto-Correlation Functions. When possible, point estimates of the structural parameters are provided via a Simulated Method of Moments methodology. Other non-parametric estimation methods are also used to compute bounds for the structural parameters or for the local interaction effects.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>07/27/2000</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>04/10/2002</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0080826</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Giorgio</FirstName>
      <LastName>Topa</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>giorgio.topa@nyu.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/27/2000</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>New York University</Name>
      <CityName>NEW YORK</CityName>
      <ZipCode>100121019</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>2129982121</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>70 WASHINGTON SQUARE S</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>New York</StateName>
      <StateCode>NY</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1320</Code>
      <Text>ECONOMICS</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1333</Code>
      <Text>METHOD, MEASURE &amp; STATS</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1352</Code>
      <Text>GEOGRAPHY AND SPATIAL SCIENCES</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>0000</Code>
      <Text>UNASSIGNED</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>OTHR</Code>
      <Text>OTHER RESEARCH OR EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
