<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Engineering Education for Inclusive Design</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>12/01/2000</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>11/30/2002</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>100000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>100000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07050000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>EEC</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Engineering Education and Centers</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Sue Kemnitzer</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>There is growing consensus in engineering that a fundamental change is required in the&lt;br/&gt;education of future engineers to ensure that they be well prepared for their roles in the&lt;br/&gt;21st century. The demands relate both to their success in the job market and to their&lt;br/&gt;responsibilities as inventors and innovators of powerful tools and technologies that are&lt;br/&gt;increasingly permeating all aspects of our society. In addition to strong technical&lt;br/&gt;capability and management skills, future engineers need to develop the understanding and&lt;br/&gt;skills needed to design products and services that can serve the diverse needs of different&lt;br/&gt;countries, cultures, and peoples.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;In response to an increasing global economy and marketplace, the changing&lt;br/&gt;demographics in our society and workforce, and government requirements for product&lt;br/&gt;accessibility, industry is increasingly developing more inclusive approaches to design.&lt;br/&gt;Inclusive design of technology means developing systems flexible enough to serve the&lt;br/&gt;broadest possible range of users. Curb cuts, for example, were originally designed for&lt;br/&gt;wheelchair users, but parents with strollers, bicyclists, youth on skateboards, and senior&lt;br/&gt;citizens benefit from them, too.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The proposed project is a collaborative effort between Rose-Hulman Institute of&lt;br/&gt;Technology (RHIT), Innoventure, the Education Development Center (EDC), and the&lt;br/&gt;CPB/WGBH National Center for Accessible Media (NCAM). The overall goal of this&lt;br/&gt;project is to develop and broadly disseminate curriculum materials and activities that&lt;br/&gt;facilitate the integration of inclusive design concepts into undergraduate engineering&lt;br/&gt;curricula. To accomplish this goal, the Engineering Education for Inclusive Design&lt;br/&gt;Project will undertake two major activities:&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;(1) RHIT faculty members, in collaboration with staff members from EDC and&lt;br/&gt;NCAM, will develop, implement and formatively evaluate case-based approaches&lt;br/&gt;towards teaching inclusive design concepts and skills to undergraduate&lt;br/&gt;engineering education students. Project staff will develop case studies of&lt;br/&gt;inclusive design projects and design instructional activities to accompany the case&lt;br/&gt;material. The case materials and activities will be incorporated in several&lt;br/&gt;different engineering courses at RHIT, evaluated for their impact on students, and&lt;br/&gt;revised based on the results of the pilot tests.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;(2) The inclusive design case materials and activities will be broadly disseminated&lt;br/&gt;both among faculty at RHIT and nationally among other engineering schools&lt;br/&gt;through a variety of means: (a) summer faculty workshops hosted by RHIT that&lt;br/&gt;will introduce participants to the case-based approach towards teaching inclusive&lt;br/&gt;design; (b) through the Engineering Case Library sponsored by the American&lt;br/&gt;Society for Engineering Education (ASEE) and housed at RHIT in print and&lt;br/&gt;electronic formats (world wide web); (c) and through papers and reports,&lt;br/&gt;including proceedings of the summer faculty seminars. These publications will be&lt;br/&gt;disseminated nationally in print and electronic formats to schools of engineering,&lt;br/&gt;professional organizations, industry councils, and foundations.&lt;br/&gt;</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>12/05/2000</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/08/2001</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>0080500</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Richard</FirstName>
<LastName>Stamper</LastName>
<EmailAddress>rstamper@eng.auburn.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>08/08/2001</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Barry</FirstName>
<LastName>Benedict</LastName>
<EmailAddress>babenedict@utep.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>12/05/2000</StartDate>
<EndDate>08/08/2001</EndDate>
<RoleCode>Former Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Rose-Hulman Institute of Technology</Name>
<CityName>Terre Haute</CityName>
<ZipCode>478033920</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>8128778972</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>5500 Wabash Avenue</StreetAddress>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Indiana</StateName>
<StateCode>IN</StateCode>
</Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1340</Code>
<Text>EngEd-Engineering Education</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9179</Code>
<Text>GRADUATE INVOLVEMENT</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>SMET</Code>
<Text>SCIENCE, MATH, ENG &amp; TECH EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
</Award>
</rootTag>
