<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>ITR:  Collaborative Research in Novel Dynamic Scheduling Methods with Application to Computation of Quantum Trajectories</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2000</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2004</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardAmount>425092</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>05010000</Code>
<Directorate>
<LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<LongName>Division of Computing and Communication Foundations</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Xiaodong Zhang</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This project will discover novel scheduling techniques for large scale applications on parallel computers, and will develop new parallel algorithms using those scheduling techniques to calculate quantum trajectories for electron scattering problems. Such research is important to help enable theoretical models as close as possible to real events, so that simulations of physical phenomenal derive accurate predictions. Since many application problems in science and engineering are irregular, large and computationally intensive, finding their best solution in terms of numerical properties and parallel performance represents an important contribution to the development of advanced computational science. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Technically, this project will develop new models for dynamic scheduling strategies used in scientific computing based on probabalistic and statistical analysis, and will evaluate their effectiveness on an analytical and experimental basis. The project specifcally addresses the following general issues: (1) to develop novel dynamic scheduling strategies that can accommodate applications with unpredictable behavior in load distribution, and evaluate their competitiveness with respect to existing technology; (2) to develop new parallel numerical algorithms using those strategies for the study of  scattering from an Eckart potential barrier in one dimension and electron scattering in three dimensions from the ground state hydrogen atom and one, two, three and four electrons bound to a hydrogen-like one and two dimensional multicharged ion; (3) to analyze the performance of this parallel application via new and predictive performance metrics. In addition, visualization methods will be applied to the calculation of quantum trajectories, leading to the possible identification of visual and quantified signatures of "quantum chaos." This is chaos in quantum mechanical systems defined in terms of the behavior of quantum trajectories.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>09/07/2000</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/24/2003</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>0081303</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Charles</FirstName>
<LastName>Weatherford</LastName>
<EmailAddress>charles.weatherford@famu.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>09/07/2000</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Ioana</FirstName>
<LastName>Banicescu</LastName>
<EmailAddress>ioana@cse.msstate.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>09/07/2000</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Jianping</FirstName>
<LastName>Zhu</LastName>
<EmailAddress>j.zhu94@csuohio.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>09/07/2000</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Mississippi State University</Name>
<CityName>MISSISSIPPI STATE</CityName>
<ZipCode>397629662</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6623257404</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>PO Box 6156</StreetAddress>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Mississippi</StateName>
<StateCode>MS</StateCode>
</Institution>
<FoaInformation>
<Code>0000099</Code>
<Name>Other Applications NEC</Name>
</FoaInformation>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1640</Code>
<Text>INFORMATION TECHNOLOGY RESEARC</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EPSCoR Co-Funding</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1652</Code>
<Text>HIGH END COMPUTATION AND INFRASTRUCTURE</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1660</Code>
<Text>ITR COMPETITION FOR UNDER $500K</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>4080</Code>
<Text>ADVANCED COMP RESEARCH PROGRAM</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9216</Code>
<Text>ADVANCED SOFTWARE TECH &amp; ALGOR</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>HPCC</Code>
<Text>HIGH PERFORMANCE COMPUTING &amp; COMM</Text>
</ProgramReference>
</Award>
</rootTag>
