<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Doctoral Dissertation Research: Social Networks of Migrant Women in Senegal and the Spread of HIV</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>08/15/2000</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2002</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>7500</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>04050200</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Divn Of Social and Economic Sciences</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Reeve D. Vanneman</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>SES 0083187&lt;br/&gt;PI: Alberto Palloni, Kristin A Velyvis&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project studies the social networks and religious beliefs of migrant women in Senegal. These economically disadvantaged women have a high risk for exposure to HIV, and this research seeks to identify network and belief structures that may be protective in reducing risks. Most of the data collection will occur in Dakar, the capital of Senegal, a destination for large numbers of migrant workers. Structured interviews will be conducted with women of two ethnic groups to establish demographic characteristics (age, education, occupation, migration history, marital status, and other facts), and those will be used to select probability samples corresponding to the migrant populations. Further interviews with women selected in the sampling will inquire about sexual partners and practices, friendship and family ties, and religious beliefs. Data analyses will focus on potentially protective effects of social networks and religious beliefs in reducing the incidence of unprotected sexual activity, the frequency of sexual activity, and the number of partners. Regressions, using density of social networks and homophily in ethnicity, village of origin, and religion as independent variables, permit assessment of hypotheses regarding social structures and sexual practices. Networks are expected to directly affect sexual practices, while effects of religion are expected to be indirect, operating through networks. Results of this research include developing network models, establishing a network data set, and improved understanding of how social networks interact with what might appear to be highly individual decisions regarding sexual practices.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/16/2000</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>08/16/2000</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0083187</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Alberto</FirstName>
      <LastName>Palloni</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>palloni@ssc.wisc.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/16/2000</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Wisconsin-Madison</Name>
      <CityName>MADISON</CityName>
      <ZipCode>537151218</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>6082623822</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>21 North Park Street</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Wisconsin</StateName>
      <StateCode>WI</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0116000</Code>
      <Name>Human Subjects</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
