<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>The Ozarks Rural Systemic Initiative</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2000</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2001</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardAmount>150000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>11070000</Code>
<Directorate>
<LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<LongName>DIVISION OF EDUCATIONAL SYSTEM REFORM</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Dr. Lura J. Chase</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The Ozarks RSI proposes to use an existing coalition of school districts in rural&lt;br/&gt;southwestern Missouri to initiate systemic reform of science, mathematics, engineering&lt;br/&gt;and technology. The target school districts evidence a desire for reform and the districts' &lt;br/&gt;26,090 students meet the criteria established by NSF.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;During the development year, the Southwest Center for Educational Excellence&lt;br/&gt;will take a strong leadership role in the collection of data and the delivery of services.&lt;br/&gt;The SCEE has strong performance capacity and has been active in professional&lt;br/&gt;development and curriculum training since its formation. The leadership team is headed&lt;br/&gt;by Dr. Arch Gordanier, Superintendent at Seneca R-1. Dr. Gordanier and the project&lt;br/&gt;director has experience with the El Paso USI and with TIMSS research. They expect to&lt;br/&gt;expand their coalition of local teachers, business leaders, community members, students&lt;br/&gt;and university officials throughout the development year.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The Ozarks RSI's primary goal is to ensure that in international comparisons all&lt;br/&gt;of our students achieve exemplary levels of mathematical and scientific understanding&lt;br/&gt;through creating partnerships and networks; applying research; and designing, sharing,&lt;br/&gt;implementing and disseminating exemplary programs and practices.&lt;br/&gt;</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/23/2000</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/23/2000</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>0086179</AwardID>
</Award>
</rootTag>
