<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Dull Knife-Northern Cheyenne Rural Systemic Initative</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2000</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>03/31/2007</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>0.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>1250000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>11060000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>EHR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>HRD</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Human Resource Development</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Lura Chase</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>&lt;br/&gt;The Dull Knife Memorial College (DKMC) Rural Systemic Initiative will be a five year effort                      that will sustain and amplify the transformations already begun in the educational experiences of                 the K-14 students on and the Northern Cheyenne Reservation.  The quality and quantity of the&lt;br/&gt;learning experiences in science, mathematics and technology within and beyond the school&lt;br/&gt;walls will be enhanced by professional development for teachers, adoption of effective&lt;br/&gt;strategies, and promotion of parental and community involvement in the educational&lt;br/&gt;process.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;An advisory committe to the principal will provide input on program direction, objectives&lt;br/&gt;and activities, policy decisions and special requests by program participants.&lt;br/&gt;The creation of fonnal "personal professional growth" plans for each individual teacher will &lt;br/&gt;be initiated with plans that are reviewed and updated annually but extended forward for&lt;br/&gt;a five-year period.  Professional development activities will be structured around cohorts &lt;br/&gt;teachers based on closely related job and interest factors that the teachers identify and &lt;br/&gt;a regional professional development committee will be formed to make training programs&lt;br/&gt;self-determined by the area teachers.  Emphasis will be placed on making the school site&lt;br/&gt;a place to learn for teachers and parents as well as students.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Alternative assessment methods and implementation will be included as a component&lt;br/&gt;of the professional development for school administrators and teachers.  Staff will include&lt;br/&gt;a local community member who will be employed to actively seek public and political support&lt;br/&gt;for educational priorities within the reservation community, one educational professional in&lt;br/&gt;mathematics/physical sciences and one in biological sciences who will work with area K-14 &lt;br/&gt;teachers. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>09/07/2000</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>11/16/2006</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>0086156</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Richard</FirstName>
<LastName>Littlebear</LastName>
<EmailAddress>rlbear@cdkc.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>09/07/2000</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Chief Dull Knife Memorial College</Name>
<CityName>Lame Deer</CityName>
<ZipCode>590430098</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>4064776215</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>P.O.Box 98</StreetAddress>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Montana</StateName>
<StateCode>MT</StateCode>
</Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1538</Code>
<Text>SYSTEMIC REFORM</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7366</Code>
<Text>RURAL SYSTEMIC INITIATIVE PROG</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9177</Code>
<Text>ELEMENTARY/SECONDARY EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>SMET</Code>
<Text>SCIENCE, MATH, ENG &amp; TECH EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
</Award>
</rootTag>
