<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Development of a Discrete Event Dynamic Systems Curriculum Using a Web-Based 'Real-Time' Simulated Factory</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>02/01/2001</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>01/31/2005</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>499678.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>505678</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07050000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>EEC</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Engineering Education and Centers</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Mary Poats</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This award provides funding for support of a three year Combined Research-Curriculum Development program entitled, "Development of a Discrete Event Dynamic Systems Curriculum using a Web-Based "Real-Time" Simulated Factory," at Boston University, under the direction of Dr. Pirooz Vakili.  The curriculum development component of the proposed project aims at an integrative and innovative approach to curriculum development that departs significantly from the current methods of teaching engineering methodology courses.  A course with a focus on manufacturing systems, a prime example of a Discrete Event System (DES), will be developed.  Two key innovations will be introduced: (a) the course will have a problem driven focus where industrial case studies will be the basis for the introduction of problems, key concepts, and solution methodologies, and (b) a web-based "real-time" simulated factory will be used that will serve as an interactive laboratory where students or teams of students will be managing the factory during the semester.  These innovations are intended to achieve the following pedagogical objectives: (i) motivate and engage the students from the outset, (ii) introduce a quantum leap in the degree to which students participate actively in the learning process, (iii) introduce team activity, (iv) break out of the limitations of "text book" and "classroom" examples, and (v) introduce research results and approaches in a context where their significance and contributions can be best appreciated.  The key project outcome will be to create a new model of curriculum development for DES courses.  Other outcomes  will include research results, development and integration of a new course in the curriculum of the Manufacturing Engineering Department at Boston University, and involvement of graduate students in research and curriculum development.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>02/08/2001</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/25/2001</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>0088073</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Christos</FirstName>
<LastName>Cassandras</LastName>
<EmailAddress>cgc@bu.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>02/08/2001</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Pirooz</FirstName>
<LastName>Vakili</LastName>
<EmailAddress>vakili@bu.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>02/08/2001</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Jian-Qiang</FirstName>
<LastName>Hu</LastName>
<EmailAddress>hqiang@bu.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>02/08/2001</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Trustees of Boston University</Name>
<CityName>BOSTON</CityName>
<ZipCode>022151300</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6173534365</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>881 COMMONWEALTH AVE</StreetAddress>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
<StateCode>MA</StateCode>
</Institution>
<FoaInformation>
<Code>0101000</Code>
<Name>Curriculum Development</Name>
</FoaInformation>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1340</Code>
<Text>EngEd-Engineering Education</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>0000</Code>
<Text>UNASSIGNED</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9178</Code>
<Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9251</Code>
<Text>REU SUPP-Res Exp for Ugrd Supp</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9299</Code>
<Text>COMB RESRCH-CURRC DEV IN TECH</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>OTHR</Code>
<Text>OTHER RESEARCH OR EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>SMET</Code>
<Text>SCIENCE, MATH, ENG &amp; TECH EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
</Award>
</rootTag>
