<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Rapid Product Development in International Production</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>02/01/2001</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2004</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>589216.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>589216</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07070000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>IIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Industrial Innovation &amp; Partnersh</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Sara B. Nerlove</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>0090582  &lt;br/&gt;Chen  &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award is to the University of Texas Pan American to support the activity described below for 24 months.  The proposal was submitted in response to the Partnerships for Innovation Program Solicitation (NSF 0082).&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Partners&lt;br/&gt;The partners for this award include the University of Texas Pan American; Michigan State University; Instituto Technologico Y De Estudios Superiores de Monterrey; General Electric Engine Services; Bissell; TRW; Automation Tooling Systems; Alpine Electronics.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Proposed Activities&lt;br/&gt;The activities for this award include a University/Industry/Economic Development Partnership to facilitate the process of taking academic research into product design and development. The target region is the US/Mexico border near Brownsville, Texas (predominantly Hispanic population with high unemployment-up to 20%), which is rapidly evolving from agriculture to industry.  The program provides internship for students in industry for design projects, virtual international design teams, technical support for small and medium businesses, experience and expertise in rapid product development, interdisciplinary teams (computer science, electrical engineering, mechanical engineering, and manufacturing engineering), and experience for students in a global environment.  Another goal is promotion of economic development in an impoverished region with a large under-represented minority population.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Proposed Innovation&lt;br/&gt;The innovation goals for this award include integration of university research and education to provide technical assistance for small and medium industry, education of a technologically literate workforce at the university level to enable innovation, creation of new industries, creation of new jobs, providing economic well-being in an impoverished region&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Potential Economic Impact&lt;br/&gt;The potential economic outcomes include producing graduate engineers with experience in rapid product development in an international setting; creation of new industries and new jobs; providing technical assistance to small and medium companies.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Potential Societal Impact&lt;br/&gt;This activity has the following potential benefits to society: economic wealth, jobs and workforce training to increase wages in an impoverished region, increased participation of Hispanic persons in the economic enterprise.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>02/27/2001</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>01/29/2004</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>0090582</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>John</FirstName>
<LastName>Villarreal</LastName>
<EmailAddress>VILLAJR@PANAM.EDU</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>08/21/2001</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Jen-Gwo</FirstName>
<LastName>Chen</LastName>
<EmailAddress>chen@panam.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>02/27/2001</StartDate>
<EndDate>08/21/2001</EndDate>
<RoleCode>Former Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Miguel</FirstName>
<LastName>Gonzalez</LastName>
<EmailAddress>gonzalezmig@uhcl.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>02/27/2001</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>The University of Texas Rio Grande Valley</Name>
<CityName>Edinburg</CityName>
<ZipCode>785392909</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>9566652889</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1201 West University Dr</StreetAddress>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Texas</StateName>
<StateCode>TX</StateCode>
</Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1464</Code>
<Text>ESD-Eng &amp; Systems Design</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1662</Code>
<Text>PFI-Partnrships for Innovation</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>0000</Code>
<Text>UNASSIGNED</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>OTHR</Code>
<Text>OTHER RESEARCH OR EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
</Award>
</rootTag>
