<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Behavioral Functions of Vocal Imitation in Parrots</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>03/15/2001</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>02/28/2005</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>235214.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>235214</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>08090300</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>BIO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>IOS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Integrative Organismal Systems</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Jerry  O. Wolff</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Behavioral Functions of Vocal Imitation in Parrots&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;PI:  Georg F. Striedter&lt;br/&gt;co-PI: Nancy T. Burley&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Why do some animals imitate complex sounds?  This question has most frequently been addressed in songbirds, which learn their songs primarily to defend a territory and/or attract a mate.  These explanations may not hold for the parrots, however, because parrots have evolved their remarkable imitative abilities independently of the songbirds.  So, why do parrots imitate sounds?  Recent data from the Striedter laboratory suggest that parrot vocal learning plays a role in pairbond formation.  Specifically, when male and female budgerigars are placed in pairs, the males consistently imitate the contact calls of the females with whom they are paired, while the females retain their original calls.  This sexual asymmetry in imitative behavior suggests that males imitate females in order to influence female mate choice.  If this hypothesis is correct, then three predictions should hold:  1)  Sexual selection should have led to an asymmetry in the vocal learning abilities of male and female budgerigars.  This hypothesis will be tested by comparing how quickly all-male and all-female groups of budgerigars develop shared contact calls.  If males are "better" at vocal learning, then vocal convergence should occur more quickly among males than among females.  2)  Males should preferentially imitate females whom they are courting.  This hypothesis will be tested by determining whether the time it takes for a male to learn a female's call is inversely correlated with his interest in this female, as measured by the frequency of other, well-known courtship behaviors.  The female's attractiveness will be manipulated by painting her cere, which is brown in mature females but pale blue in immature females.  3)  Female budgerigars should associate preferentially with males that have learned to imitate them.  This hypothesis will be tested by determining whether females give more courtship displays towards unfamiliar males that already know their call (because they were tutored by another female that shares the test female's call) than towards males that do not yet know the test female's call.  In a complementary experiment, some male budgerigars will be rendered imitation-impaired by selectively severing the connection between their auditory and vocal motor systems.  The proposed experiments could significantly impact the field of "sexual selection" and "female choice" because most prior studies focused on female choice for overt physical traits - not learning ability.  The proposed experiments also pave the way for a more mechanistic analysis of why male budgerigars imitate female calls. &lt;br/&gt;</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>03/09/2001</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>03/09/2001</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.074</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>0090620</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Nancy</FirstName>
<LastName>Burley</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>T</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Nancy T Burley</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>ntburley@uci.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>9498245440</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000245731</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>03/09/2001</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Georg</FirstName>
<LastName>Striedter</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>F</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Georg F Striedter</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>georg.striedter@gmail.com</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>9498245228</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000100018</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>03/09/2001</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of California-Irvine</Name>
<CityName>Irvine</CityName>
<CountyName/>
<ZipCode>926977600</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>9498247295</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>160 Aldrich Hall</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>45</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CA45</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>046705849</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF CALIFORNIA, IRVINE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>071549000</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of California-Irvine]]></Name>
<CityName>Irvine</CityName>
<CountyName/>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>926977600</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[160 Aldrich Hall]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>45</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CA45</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<FoaInformation>
<Code>0000099</Code>
<Name>Other Applications NEC</Name>
</FoaInformation>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1160</Code>
<Text>IBN ANIMAL BEHAVIOR</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>0000</Code>
<Text>UNASSIGNED</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>OTHR</Code>
<Text>OTHER RESEARCH OR EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0101</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2001~235214</FUND_OBLG>
</Award>
</rootTag>
