<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>SBIR Phase II: Carbon Monoxide-Tolerant Anode Catalysts for Proton Exchange Membrane Fuel Cells via Combustion Chemical Vapor Deposition</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>02/01/2001</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>01/31/2004</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>772219</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07070000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Industrial Innovation &amp; Partnersh</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Rosemarie D. Wesson</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This Small Business Innovation Research (SBIR) Phase II project seeks to implement a Combustion Chemical Vapor Deposition (CCVD) process for the production of anode electrocatalyst layers for Proton Exchange Membrane Fuel Cell (PEMFC) applications requiring reformate fuel feed gas. In Phase I it was demonstrated that fabrication of Pt:Ru electrocatalysts as unsupported, metallic nanoparticles is possible using CCVD. These electrocatalyst layers behave electrochemically in a similar manner to commercially available Pt:Ru electrocatalysts prepared on carbon supports using wet chemical methods, but can be deposited directly onto both gas diffusion media and proton exchange membranes. The Phase II project would involve optimization of catalyst composition, continued development of web coating technology for mass production of membrane electrode assemblies (MEAs) and commercialization of the technology through construction of production equipment and licensing.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Fuel cells are of huge interest to the marketplace, as illustrated by sizable investments in the technology and market capitalization of fuel cell companies. For example, Daimler Chrysler has targeted the year 2004 for planned production of fuel cell vehicles, and has slated more than $1.4 billion in investments to reach that goal. However, for commercial viability, performance and cost of the electrocatalyst layers must be improved. MCT, if successful, could contribute in both arenas.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>01/24/2001</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>04/30/2003</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0091624</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Peter</FirstName>
      <LastName>Faguy</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>pfaguy@microcoating.com</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>01/24/2001</StartDate>
      <EndDate>12/09/2002</EndDate>
      <RoleCode>Former Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Richard</FirstName>
      <LastName>Breitkopf</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>rbreitkopf@microcoating.com</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>12/09/2002</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>NGIMAT CO.</Name>
      <CityName>Norcross</CityName>
      <ZipCode>300932608</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>6782872400</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>1824 Willow Trail Pkwy</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Georgia</StateName>
      <StateCode>GA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0308000</Code>
      <Name>Industrial Technology</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
