<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>CAREER: Framework for Integrating Embedded Sensors in Durability Analysis of FRP Composites in Civil Infrastructure</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>03/15/2001</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>02/28/2007</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>375000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>375000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CMMI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Civil, Mechanical, &amp; Manufact Inn</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Ken Chong</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The CAREER proposal will develop a framework to characterize durability of composites in civil infrastructure by integrating fiber-optic embedded sensors with damage mechanics models and life prediction methods.  To tackle this problem, a combined analytical and experimental methodology is proposed, as follows: 1) Integrate embedded sensors in composites fabrication by VARTM and filament winding; 2) Implement strain, temperature, moisture and chemical degradation fiber-optic sensors; 3) Evaluate the embedded sensor system with controlled damage; 4) Develop a damage mechanics model and life-prediction methodology for durability analysis based on interrogating senors; 5) Assess reliability of sensor data and scale to composite structures (bridge decks and pipe walls); and 6) Validate the durability methodology and synthesize into a health-monitoring protocol.  The educational approach is two-fold encompassing student recruitment and advanced graduate education.  First, and educational collaboration is being developed with an applied technology center at a high school in Maine.  The objective is to introduce high school students to the engineering experience by collaborating with civil engineering juniors in a composite bridge design and fabrication project.  Second, an advanced graduate course on composites in civil engineering will be developed.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>02/21/2001</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>02/21/2001</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>0093678</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Roberto</FirstName>
<LastName>Lopez-Anido</LastName>
<EmailAddress>RLA@maine.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>02/21/2001</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Maine</Name>
<CityName>ORONO</CityName>
<ZipCode>044695717</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2075811484</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>5717 Corbett Hall</StreetAddress>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Maine</StateName>
<StateCode>ME</StateCode>
</Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1635</Code>
<Text>STRUCTURAL MATERIALS AND MECH</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1039</Code>
<Text>RENEWAL ENGINEERING</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1045</Code>
<Text>CAREER-Faculty Erly Career Dev</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1187</Code>
<Text>PECASE- eligible</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>CVIS</Code>
<Text>CIVIL INFRASTRUCTURE</Text>
</ProgramReference>
</Award>
</rootTag>
