<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>CAREER:  Multi-scale Mechanics of Soft Tissues</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>06/01/2001</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2005</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardAmount>380992</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07020000</Code>
<Directorate>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<LongName>Div Of Chem, Bioeng, Env, &amp; Transp Sys</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Gilbert B. Devey</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>0093969&lt;br/&gt;Livesay&lt;br/&gt;This CAREER project is to establish a productive, integrated research and educational program with a focus on the multi-scale mechanics of soft tissues. One promising approach for the analysis of materials possessing microstructure is homogenization, involving the analysis of a repeating microstructural unit coupled to a macroscopic level analysis. However, the applicability of this strategy to biologic soft tissues is currently limited, since it has thus far been restricted to linear elastic media. Further research and development are needed to extend the homogenization approach for anisotropic and non-homogeneous media. This project will develop a research and educational program on the multi-scale mechanics of soft tissues, through the following specific objectives:&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;1. Implement and optimize a homogenization approach for computational analysis of multi-scale mechanics under finite deformation. &lt;br/&gt;2. Perform experimental validation of the homogenization approach using synthetic tissues created with known microstructure.  &lt;br/&gt;3. Extend the homogenization approach for the analysis of synthetic tissues possessing both directional and spatial variation in material properties. &lt;br/&gt;4. Determine the multi-scale mechanical environment within biological soft tissue under simple loading. &lt;br/&gt;5. Integrate active learning experiences into existing undergraduate and new graduate Biomedical Engineering courses. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The fundamental research will develop critically important tools for the analysis of the multi-scale mechanics of biological soft tissues. The complementary educational improvements will increase student learning/retention and encourage further study of multi-scale mechanics, thus enhancing the quality of biomechanics education and research. &lt;br/&gt;</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>02/13/2001</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/01/2003</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>0093969</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Glen</FirstName>
<LastName>Livesay</LastName>
<EmailAddress>livesay@rose-hulman.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>02/13/2001</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Tulane University</Name>
<CityName>NEW ORLEANS</CityName>
<ZipCode>701185698</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5048654000</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>6823 ST CHARLES AVENUE</StreetAddress>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Louisiana</StateName>
<StateCode>LA</StateCode>
</Institution>
<FoaInformation>
<Code>0116000</Code>
<Name>Human Subjects</Name>
</FoaInformation>
<FoaInformation>
<Code>0203000</Code>
<Name>Health</Name>
</FoaInformation>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>5345</Code>
<Text>Engineering of Biomed Systems</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EPSCoR Co-Funding</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>0000</Code>
<Text>UNASSIGNED</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1045</Code>
<Text>CAREER: FACULTY EARLY CAR DEV</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1187</Code>
<Text>PECASE- eligible</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9251</Code>
<Text>RES EXPER FOR UNDERGRAD-SUPPLT</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>OTHR</Code>
<Text>OTHER RESEARCH OR EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
</Award>
</rootTag>
