<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Computer and Engineering Technology Scholars Program</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2001</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2003</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>182500.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>182500</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>11040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>EHR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DUE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Undergraduate Education</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Duncan E. McBride</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The Computer and Engineering Technology (CET) Scholars Program is designed to provide scholarships to 50 students studying in the areas of Computer Information Technology, Computer-Aided Drafting and Design, Microcomputer Electronics, Electronics Engineering Technology and Robotics and Automated Systems Technology. These majors are all considered advanced technology careers in the state of Pennsylvania. In addition to excellent career opportunities in the region for graduates, these programs offer transferability into baccalaureate programs at local four-year colleges. Working through the Affirmative Action Office of the college, multiple sources are used to contact interested young people, especially women and minorities. High school counselors, scout troops, church youth groups, a web site, and school and group presentations are some of the methods used for recruitment. Factors used by the scholarship selection committee are group diversity, financial need, grade point average (2.8 or higher for selection), letters of recommendation describing career potential, and commitment to career advancement. Working with the Financial Aid Office to build a complete package, the CET Scholars are awarded up to $2,500 per year toward their school expenses. Regardless of major, all CET Scholars complete a common one-year core of Technical Mathematics and Technical Physics designed specifically to enhance the use of these topics by the technology majors, encourage collaborative work, and to stress mastery of conceptual topics. A unique feature of the program is that all CET Scholars complete an external Work Keys Assessment Process. This assessment certifies, to the student, the employer, the school and the funding agencies, the quality of the education and training received. National Work Key Assessment Profiles are available for the careers being targeted by this project.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>01/16/2001</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>12/13/2001</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>0093024</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Pearley</FirstName>
<LastName>Cunningham</LastName>
<EmailAddress>pcunningham@ccac.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>01/16/2001</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Brenda</FirstName>
<LastName>Trettel</LastName>
<EmailAddress>btrettel@ccac.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>01/16/2001</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Community College of Allegheny County College Office</Name>
<CityName>Pittsburgh</CityName>
<ZipCode>152331804</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>4123232323</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>800 Allegheny Ave</StreetAddress>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Pennsylvania</StateName>
<StateCode>PA</StateCode>
</Institution>
<FoaInformation>
<Code>0000099</Code>
<Name>Other Applications NEC</Name>
</FoaInformation>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1536</Code>
<Text>S-STEM-Schlr Sci Tech Eng&amp;Math</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1536</Code>
<Text>CSEMS--CS, ENG &amp; MATH SCHOLAR</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9178</Code>
<Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>SMET</Code>
<Text>SCIENCE, MATH, ENG &amp; TECH EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
</Award>
</rootTag>
