<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>CAREER:  Development of a Split-Beam Method for Improved Laser Machining of Ceramics</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>01/01/2001</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>09/30/2002</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>375000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>150000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CMMI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Civil, Mechanical, &amp; Manufact Inn</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>george hazelrigg</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This Faculty Early Career Development (CAREER) award supports research efforts focusing on numerically modeling the relationships between the thermal transients caused by single- and dual-laser machining and the complex stresses that ultimately lead to premature fractures.  A probabilistic fracture model will be integrated with the stress calculations to help quantify the time and location of fracture as the laser progresses along the cutting path.  The resulting models will then be used with laser machining experiments to develop and optimize a process of simultaneously scoring the surface to help control the path and quality of the final fracture.  Another intriguing method that will be studied involves the use of the dual-laser to "actively stress" the fracture prone region into a state of thermoelastic compression to lower the probability of premature fracture.  &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The research program will also have a strong educational component that will provide high school and undergraduate students with hands-on research experience through focused outreach efforts.  All of the research and the evolving laser manufacturing methodology will be integrated with the curricula at three Washington State University campuses using the Washington Higher Education Telecommunications System (WHETS) and video.  As a result, the new methodologies will be able to reach a wide variety of individuals by using a blend of kinesthetic and visual methods that include numerous hands-on experiences combined with live and video demonstrations.  The overall goals of the project are to develop more efficient laser machining techniques for ceramics while at the same time helping to create and foster a positive image of engineering and manufacturing. &lt;br/&gt;</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>12/27/2000</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>10/12/2001</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>0093903</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Albert</FirstName>
<LastName>Segall</LastName>
<EmailAddress>aesegall@psu.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>12/27/2000</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Washington State University</Name>
<CityName>PULLMAN</CityName>
<ZipCode>991641060</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5093359661</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>280 Lighty</StreetAddress>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Washington</StateName>
<StateCode>WA</StateCode>
</Institution>
<FoaInformation>
<Code>0308000</Code>
<Name>Industrial Technology</Name>
</FoaInformation>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1468</Code>
<Text>Manufacturing Machines &amp; Equip</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1045</Code>
<Text>CAREER-Faculty Erly Career Dev</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9146</Code>
<Text>MANUFACTURING BASE RESEARCH</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>MANU</Code>
<Text>MANUFACTURING</Text>
</ProgramReference>
</Award>
</rootTag>
