<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>CAREER:  Using Photonic Crystals to Control the Emission of Rare Earth-Doped Semiconducting Polymers</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>02/01/2001</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>01/31/2006</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>375000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>375000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07010000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>ECCS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Electrical, Commun &amp; Cyber Sys</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Lawrence Goldberg</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Light-emitting diodes (LEDs) made with semiconducting (conjugated) polymers&lt;br/&gt;now have quantum efficiencies as high as 4 % and operating lifetimes of 50,000 hours.&lt;br/&gt;Several companies are developing flat panel displays with these LEDs. One of the&lt;br/&gt;limitations of polymer LEDs is that triplet excitons are non-emissive. Initial steps&lt;br/&gt;towards solving this problem by transferring energy to phosphorescent molecules and&lt;br/&gt;rare earth complexes have recently been taken. One of the goals of this project is to&lt;br/&gt;optimize energy transfer and charge transport in "doped" polymer films so that high&lt;br/&gt;quantum efficiencies, low operating voltages and high device stability can be obtained.&lt;br/&gt;Another limitation of current polymer LEDs is that most of the emitted photons are&lt;br/&gt;trapped in the device by total internal reflection and that the photons which do escape&lt;br/&gt;cannot conveniently be collimated into a beam or coupled into a waveguide. The second&lt;br/&gt;major goal of the project is use photonic crystals, e.g. one-dimensional dielectric stacks&lt;br/&gt;and two-dimensional gratings, to control the directionality of emission. Previous&lt;br/&gt;attempts to do this have not been fully successful because it was not possible to make&lt;br/&gt;photonic crystals with a photonic band gap wide enough to completely control the&lt;br/&gt;emission of conjugated polymers, which have an emission spectrum with a width of more&lt;br/&gt;than 100 nm. By using rare earth-doped polymers, which have emission bandwidths of&lt;br/&gt;less than 4 nm, it will be possible to use photonic crystals to control the directionality of&lt;br/&gt;emission. This project will not only increase the efficiency and functionality of polymer-based&lt;br/&gt;LEDs, but will also provide a convenient light source for developing the science&lt;br/&gt;and technology of photonic crystals.&lt;br/&gt;The project provides many excellent research opportunities for students. They&lt;br/&gt;will work with a team of chemists to design new rare earth complexes and learn the&lt;br/&gt;quantum mechanics that regulate energy transfer, charge transfer and light emission.&lt;br/&gt;They will interact with members of industry to learn how to optimize polymer LEDs.&lt;br/&gt;They will use computer modeling to design one-, two-, and three-dimensional photonic&lt;br/&gt;crystals to control the emission of light. They will also get to interact with a team of&lt;br/&gt;researchers at 3M and have the opportunity to push polymer-photonic crystal science and&lt;br/&gt;technology into new directions. Most of the research will be done by two graduate&lt;br/&gt;students, but there will be many opportunities for undergraduates and M.S. students to&lt;br/&gt;take on short-term projects.&lt;br/&gt;New courses on nanotechnology and organic optoelectronics will be developed to&lt;br/&gt;prepare students for research. The course on nanotechnology is designed to make&lt;br/&gt;students in several departments aware of the opportunities in this exciting area and to&lt;br/&gt;foster multidisciplinary research. The course on organic optoelectronics will have several&lt;br/&gt;lab sessions in the PI's labs so that students can reinforce what they learn in class. High&lt;br/&gt;school teachers will visit the labs during the summer and be trained to use a kit of optical&lt;br/&gt;equipment so that they can demonstrate photonics experiments to their students.&lt;br/&gt;</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>01/24/2001</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>01/24/2001</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>0093502</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Michael</FirstName>
<LastName>McGehee</LastName>
<EmailAddress>mmcgehee@stanford.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>01/24/2001</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Stanford University</Name>
<CityName>Stanford</CityName>
<ZipCode>943052004</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6507232300</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>450 Jane Stanford Way</StreetAddress>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
</Institution>
<FoaInformation>
<Code>0206000</Code>
<Name>Telecommunications</Name>
</FoaInformation>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1517</Code>
<Text>EPMD-ElectrnPhoton&amp;MagnDevices</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>0000</Code>
<Text>UNASSIGNED</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1045</Code>
<Text>CAREER-Faculty Erly Career Dev</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>OTHR</Code>
<Text>OTHER RESEARCH OR EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
</Award>
</rootTag>
