<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Computer Science, Engineering, and Mathematics Scholarship Program</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2001</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2004</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>91125.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>91125</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>11040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>EHR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DUE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Undergraduate Education</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Duncan E. McBride</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This program targets talented but financially disadvantaged youth by providing financial support, academic assistance, and student support services. The objectives and corresponding activities are carefully designed to create a comprehensive program by supplementing programs and structures already in place at St. Scholastica with the creation of new activities. The program includes activities that focus on providing the support and encouragement that students need to remain in school through graduation. Activities include faculty mentoring, tutoring, summer research opportunities, internship opportunities, and individual counseling sessions with the Program Administrator. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Through individual discussions with the Program Administrator and the College's Career Counselor, students receive both guidance and support as they consider the next step in their careers. Many of the same activities that lead to higher levels of degree attainment, such as mentoring, internships, and summer research opportunities also contribute to greater levels of preparedness as students move on to graduate school or employment. In addition, a series of workshops are provided for program participants that address such topics as graduate school exploration, professionalism, resume preparation, and research skills. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;By coordinating with local businesses, state agencies, and the College's Career Center Counselor, the Program Administrator creates new internship/research opportunities for program participants. Activities for this objective center on a structure of support and evaluation to ensure that the students, partnering businesses, and members of the College community all gain from these relationships.&lt;br/&gt;</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>01/08/2001</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>12/05/2001</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>0094910</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Kathleen</FirstName>
<LastName>Cargill</LastName>
<EmailAddress>kcargill@css.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>01/08/2001</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Guanshen</FirstName>
<LastName>Ren</LastName>
<EmailAddress>gren@css.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>01/08/2001</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>College of Saint Scholastica</Name>
<CityName>Duluth</CityName>
<ZipCode>558114199</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2187236072</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1200 Kenwood Avenue</StreetAddress>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Minnesota</StateName>
<StateCode>MN</StateCode>
</Institution>
<FoaInformation>
<Code>0000099</Code>
<Name>Other Applications NEC</Name>
</FoaInformation>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1536</Code>
<Text>S-STEM-Schlr Sci Tech Eng&amp;Math</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1536</Code>
<Text>CSEMS--CS, ENG &amp; MATH SCHOLAR</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9178</Code>
<Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>SMET</Code>
<Text>SCIENCE, MATH, ENG &amp; TECH EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
</Award>
</rootTag>
