<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Interstellar Astrochemistry</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>05/01/2001</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>10/31/2004</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>368397.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>368397</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03020416</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>AST</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Astronomical Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Randy Phelps</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>AST 0096491&lt;br/&gt;Herbst&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Molecules are found in many different environments in the Universe and are excellent probes of their surroundings.  Analysis of molecular spectral features yields important information, but more comprehensive analysis requires the comparison of many observations with detailed chemical and physical models of the assorted sources.  In a continuing research program, Dr. Eric Herbst, at the Ohio State University, hopes to understand and utilize chemistry to explain and guide astronomical observations of molecules, and to better our understanding of assorted interstellar and circumstellar objects.  During this award period, Dr. Herbst will pursue a wide variety of modeling studies, with concomitant improvements to his standard gas-phase and gas-grain models.  He will pay particular attention to the environments of star-forming regions of interstellar clouds.  He will also concentrate on improving his grain surface chemistry, since new experiments and theories are now beginning to bring some understanding to this field.  &lt;br/&gt;***&lt;br/&gt;</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>05/29/2001</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>04/30/2003</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>0096491</AwardID>
</Award>
</rootTag>
