<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Research Experiences for Undergraduates in Chemistry at James Madison University</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>04/01/2001</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>03/31/2004</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardAmount>234000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03090007</Code>
<Directorate>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<LongName>Division Of Chemistry</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Richard D. Foust</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This joint Chemistry Division and Division of Human Resources Development (Program for Persons with Disabilities) award supports the continuation of a Research Experiences for Undergraduates (REU) site at James Madison University (JMU).  Daniel Downey is the site's Program Director; Gina MacDonald is the Co-Program Director. Nine faculty will serve as REU student mentors.  During the award period (2001-2003), each summer eight undergraduate students (to include a minimum of one deaf student), one interpreter student, one high school teacher (who is either deaf or teaches the deaf), and two high school students (to include a minimum of one deaf student) will participate in a ten-week program.  Students will be recruited from regional colleges and universities as well as from JMU.  Recruitment efforts will target under-represented groups in science: namely, females, ethnic minorities and the deaf.  At least 75% of the student participants are expected to represent these underrepresented groups.  Research opportunities will be available in a variety of sub-disciplines including materials science, biochemistry, synthesis, environmental chemistry and spectroscopy.  In addition to the research objectives, there will be discussions on ethics in scientific research.  At the conclusion of the program, student participants will give oral presentations of their research and submit written reports summarizing their results and conclusions.  Project evaluation will include statistical studies of tracking the future of each participant.  A complex assessment process will begin with the entry of the participants into the program.  Career goals and professional direction will be monitored.&lt;br/&gt;</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>03/30/2001</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>01/14/2003</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>0097448</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Daniel</FirstName>
<LastName>Downey</LastName>
<EmailAddress>downeydm@jmu.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>03/30/2001</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Gina</FirstName>
<LastName>MacDonald</LastName>
<EmailAddress>macdongx@jmu.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>03/30/2001</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>James Madison University</Name>
<CityName>HARRISONBURG</CityName>
<ZipCode>228077000</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5405686872</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>MSC 5728</StreetAddress>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Virginia</StateName>
<StateCode>VA</StateCode>
</Institution>
<FoaInformation>
<Code>0000099</Code>
<Name>Other Applications NEC</Name>
</FoaInformation>
<FoaInformation>
<Code>0510400</Code>
<Name>Physically Disadvantaged</Name>
</FoaInformation>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1545</Code>
<Text>RES IN DISABILITIES ED</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1986</Code>
<Text>UNDERGRADUATE PROGRAMS IN CHEM</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1545</Code>
<Text>RES IN DISABILITIES ED</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9178</Code>
<Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9250</Code>
<Text>RES EXPER FOR UNDERGRADS-SITE</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>SMET</Code>
<Text>SCIENCE, MATH, ENG &amp; TECH EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
</Award>
</rootTag>
