<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Stochastic Control with Discretionary Stopping</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2001</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2006</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>358527.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>422663</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03040100</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DMS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Henry Warchall</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Pang, Jong-Shi&lt;br/&gt;From: Ioannis Karatzas [ik@math.columbia.edu]&lt;br/&gt;Sent: Friday, June 08, 2001 2:46 PM&lt;br/&gt;To: Pang, Jong-Shi&lt;br/&gt;Subject: Re: Abstract&lt;br/&gt;STOCHASTIC CONTROL WITH DISCRETIONARY STOPPING&lt;br/&gt;Proposal DMS-00-99690 to the National Science Foundation by&lt;br/&gt;Ioannis Karatzas, Columbia University&lt;br/&gt;May 2001&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;ABSTRACT&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Research is proposed on several open questions in Stochastic Analysis and&lt;br/&gt;Optimization, including the following:&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;(i)  Bounded-Velocity-Follower problems, that involve filtering, absolutely&lt;br/&gt;continuous stochastic control, and optimal stopping;&lt;br/&gt;(ii) Bounded-Variation, Finite-Fuel Follower problems, which combine&lt;br/&gt;features of singular stochastic control and optimal stopping;&lt;br/&gt;(iii) Leavable Control problems for one-dimensional diffusions, and on&lt;br/&gt;associated  stochastic games of the controller-and-stopper type;&lt;br/&gt;(iv)  Leavable Utility Maximization problems, with an embedded ``retirement&lt;br/&gt;option";&lt;br/&gt;(v)   the Hedging of American Contingent Claims under portfolio constraints;&lt;br/&gt;and&lt;br/&gt;(vi)  a General Probabilistic Theory for Leavable Stochastic Control&lt;br/&gt;Problems, based on martingales and on equivalent changes of measure.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Several of these problems share the following interesting feature: the&lt;br/&gt;qualitative nature of the optimal policy changes significantly, as the&lt;br/&gt;parameters weighing the relative importance of continuation cost, stopping&lt;br/&gt;cost, and discount rate pass through certain critical values. We propose to&lt;br/&gt;identify the critical parameters in problems of this type that admit exact&lt;br/&gt;solutions, and to describe as explicitly as possible the associated optimal&lt;br/&gt;control policies and stopping rules. It is expected that tools from&lt;br/&gt;stochastic analysis, martingales, convex duality theory, partial&lt;br/&gt;differential equations, and variational inequa-lities, will prove crucial in&lt;br/&gt;the resolution of these questions; and that valuable new tools will have to&lt;br/&gt;be developed, in order to deal with the non-standard issues that will arise.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The optimization questions that we plan to study over the next five years&lt;br/&gt;share a common feature, in that they involve elements of both  Stochastic&lt;br/&gt;Control  and of  Discretionary  Stopping. Such questions arise, for&lt;br/&gt;instance, in  target-tracking models, where one has to stay close to a&lt;br/&gt;target by spending fuel, to declare when one has arrived "sufficiently&lt;br/&gt; close" to the target, and then to decide whether to engage the target or&lt;br/&gt;not. Combined stochastic control / optimal stopping problems also arise in&lt;br/&gt;Mathematical Finance:  in&lt;br/&gt;.  the context of computing the upper- and lower- hedging prices of American&lt;br/&gt;   contingent claims under portfolio constraints;  in&lt;br/&gt;.   portfolio/consumption optimization with an embedded "retirement option";&lt;br/&gt;and in&lt;br/&gt;.   the study of dynamic measures for managing risk.&lt;br/&gt;The resolution of such problems, as suggested in this proposal, is expected&lt;br/&gt;to advance significantly our understanding of stochastic optimization and&lt;br/&gt;the frontiers of its applications.  The strong involvement of graduate&lt;br/&gt;students in our research activities is expected to continue, and to be a&lt;br/&gt;major factor in the advancement of Applied Probability and of the&lt;br/&gt;Mathematics of Finance.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;----------------------------------------------------------------------------&lt;br/&gt;---&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;----- Original Message -----&lt;br/&gt;From: Pang, Jong-Shi &lt;jpang@nsf.gov&gt;&lt;br/&gt;To: &lt;ik@math.columbia.edu&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Sent: Thursday, June 07, 2001 11:06 AM&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&gt; Professor Karatzas,&lt;br/&gt;&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&gt; Did you see the following email of mine sent May 30, 2001?  Please reply&lt;br/&gt;&gt; promptly so that I can process my recommendation.&lt;br/&gt;&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&gt; Looking forward to hearing from you.&lt;br/&gt;&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&gt; Jong-Shi&lt;br/&gt;&gt; %%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%&lt;br/&gt;&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&gt; Dear Professor Karatzas,&lt;br/&gt;&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&gt; I am ready to recommend an award to your NSF proposal.  Before I prepare&lt;br/&gt;&gt; the paperwork, I need to clarify one thing about your salary.&lt;br/&gt;Specifically,&lt;br/&gt;&gt; are you drawing 1 month salary from your current grant, which expires&lt;br/&gt;&gt; 07/31/01?&lt;br/&gt;&gt; If you are, then I will recommend a start date of 08/01/01 for your new&lt;br/&gt;&gt; grant.&lt;br/&gt;&gt; Otherwise, we can keep your requested 07/01/01 start date.  I plan to&lt;br/&gt;&gt; recommend&lt;br/&gt;&gt; a continuing grant to fund the requested amount of $358,529 for 60 months.&lt;br/&gt;&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&gt; I will need an abstract for the project, to be sent to me by email (do not&lt;br/&gt;&gt; send attachments).&lt;br/&gt;&gt; This abstract shall be no more than one page in&lt;br/&gt;&gt; length, and shall consist of two paragraphs. There shall be no special&lt;br/&gt;&gt; symbols or equations. The first paragraph shall&lt;br/&gt;&gt; be a technical description of the project, aimed at professional peers.&lt;br/&gt;&gt; Often the proposal summary is an appropriate start,&lt;br/&gt;&gt; phrased in the third person. The second paragraph will be a nontechnical&lt;br/&gt;&gt; description that presents the work, its motivation,&lt;br/&gt;&gt; and its significance. Think of the audience as a Congressman who asks&lt;br/&gt;"What&lt;br/&gt;&gt; are you doing?", "Why would you do that?"&lt;br/&gt;&gt; and "What does it mean?".&lt;br/&gt;&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&gt; The abstract is put in a public database, and may be read (and they have&lt;br/&gt;&gt; been read in the past!) by Congressmen and&lt;br/&gt;&gt; their staffers, so the second paragraph is important. Include any&lt;br/&gt;reference&lt;br/&gt;&gt; to areas of important federal interest, such&lt;br/&gt;&gt; as training or applications of strategic Federal interest.&lt;br/&gt;&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&gt; I will initiate the paperwork for my recommendation once I receive an&lt;br/&gt;answer&lt;br/&gt;&gt; to the salary issue and also&lt;br/&gt;&gt; the abstract.&lt;br/&gt;&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&gt; Best regards,&lt;br/&gt;&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&gt; Jong-Shi&lt;br/&gt;&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&gt;</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/10/2001</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/20/2005</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>0099690</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Ioannis</FirstName>
<LastName>Karatzas</LastName>
<EmailAddress>ik@math.columbia.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>07/10/2001</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Columbia University</Name>
<CityName>NEW YORK</CityName>
<ZipCode>100276902</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2128546851</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>2960 Broadway</StreetAddress>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
</Institution>
<FoaInformation>
<Code>0000099</Code>
<Name>Other Applications NEC</Name>
</FoaInformation>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1263</Code>
<Text>PROBABILITY</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1266</Code>
<Text>APPLIED MATHEMATICS</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>0000</Code>
<Text>UNASSIGNED</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>OTHR</Code>
<Text>OTHER RESEARCH OR EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
</Award>
</rootTag>
