<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Conference:  Student Paper Competition at the 2001 IEEE MTT-S International Microwave Symposium to be held in Phoenix, AZ on May 20-25, 2001.</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>04/01/2001</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>03/31/2002</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardAmount>12600</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07010000</Code>
<Directorate>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<LongName>Div Of Electrical, Commun &amp; Cyber Sys</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>James W. Mink</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>0099341&lt;br/&gt;Papapolymerou&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project requests travel support for 24 participants from U.S. universities in the Student Paper Competition at the 2001 IEEE MTT-S International Microwave Symposium (IMS).  The IMS is the annual meeting of the Microwave Theory and Techniques Society (MTT-S) of the Institute of Electrical and Electronics Engineers, Inc. (IEEE).  The IMS is also the major international symposium in the microwave field and a focus of research results in wireless telecommunications.  The 2001 IMS will be held in Phoenix, AZ, USA on May 20-25, 2001.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Each year, the Microwave Theory and Techniques Society promotes student education in microwave theory and techniques through a number of mechanisms.  One of the most important is the Student Paper Competition at the IMS.  This selective program brings the world's best students together in an integrated program in which they present their work not only to a technical audience but again to a group of judges.  The program helps develop the students' technical acumen as well as their communication and presentation skills.  It also helps introduce them to the international technical community and helps to build a community of students who will lead the next generation of microwave engineers.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The IMS provides financial support of various forms but does not reimburse travel expenses.  Travel support from NSF will ensure that the program is open to the widest range of interested applicants from U.S. universities.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>02/08/2001</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>02/08/2001</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>0099341</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Ioannis (John)</FirstName>
<LastName>Papapolymerou</LastName>
<EmailAddress>jpapapol@egr.msu.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>02/08/2001</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Institute of Electrical &amp; Electronics Engineers, Inc.</Name>
<CityName>Piscataway</CityName>
<ZipCode>088544141</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>7325626520</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>445 HOES LANE</StreetAddress>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New Jersey</StateName>
<StateCode>NJ</StateCode>
</Institution>
<FoaInformation>
<Code>0206000</Code>
<Name>Telecommunications</Name>
</FoaInformation>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1517</Code>
<Text>ELECT, PHOTONICS, &amp; MAG DEVICE</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>0000</Code>
<Text>UNASSIGNED</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>OTHR</Code>
<Text>OTHER RESEARCH OR EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
</Award>
</rootTag>
