<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Investigation of Vapor Phase Organic Coatings for High Reliability Microelectromechanical Systems (MEMS)</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2001</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2005</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>228647.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>228647</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CMMI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Civil, Mechanical, &amp; Manufact Inn</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Kevin Lyons</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This research project will explore the anti-stiction effectiveness of a number of organic coatings deposited from vapor phase.  Vapor-phase processes would be environmentally friendlier and more economical than standard liquid-phase processes.  Furthermore, dry processes may well result easier to scale-up from research stage to production, due to the potential for easier control and better uniformity.  Because silicon has excellent mechanical properties, there is a growing interest in developing technologies that use silicon as a mechanical material.  One such technology, called surface micromachining, consists of deposition and selective etching of multiple layers of structural and sacrificial thin films, and is a core technological processes underlying microelectromechanical systems (MEMS).  Despite significant advances in surface micromachining, stiction remains a key problem, severely limiting the realization and reliability of many MEMS devices. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The project will provide core training for a graduate student. The student will benefit from interdisciplinary training at the crossroads of surface science, electrical and mechanical engineering and materials science.  An additional pay-off is the achievement of higher reliability MEMS.  The PI will continue her ongoing commitment to education, including outreach activities to underrepresented groups, undergraduate research participation in the work to be performed, public presentations on the topics of microsystems technology and surface engineering, and active involvement in curriculum development on these topics.&lt;br/&gt;</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>04/05/2001</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>04/05/2001</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>0099765</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Roya</FirstName>
<LastName>Maboudian</LastName>
<EmailAddress>maboudia@berkeley.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>04/05/2001</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of California-Berkeley</Name>
<CityName>BERKELEY</CityName>
<ZipCode>947101749</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5106433891</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>Sponsored Projects Office</StreetAddress>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
</Institution>
<FoaInformation>
<Code>0308000</Code>
<Name>Industrial Technology</Name>
</FoaInformation>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1467</Code>
<Text>MATERIALS PROCESSING AND MANFG</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1468</Code>
<Text>Manufacturing Machines &amp; Equip</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1467</Code>
<Text>MATERIALS PROCESSING AND MANFG</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1468</Code>
<Text>MANUFACTURING &amp; CONST MACH EQP</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9102</Code>
<Text>WOMEN, MINORITY, DISABLED, NEC</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9146</Code>
<Text>MANUFACTURING BASE RESEARCH</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>MANU</Code>
<Text>MANUFACTURING</Text>
</ProgramReference>
</Award>
</rootTag>
