<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Non-Contact Experimental Technique to Characterize Interfacial Crack Propagation in Nano-Scale and Micro-Scale Thin Films</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>05/01/2008</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2012</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>250000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>256000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CMMI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Civil, Mechanical, &amp; Manufact Inn</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Martin L. Dunn</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Thin film interfacial delamination is an important reliability concern in a wide range of applications. Although a significant amount of interfacial delamination is caused by fatigue loading, existing literature has not adequately addressed this topic, especially for nano-scale thin films. This proposal aims to develop an innovative fatigue delamination test that can be used to monitor and characterize interfacial delamination propagation for nano-scale as well as micro-scale thin films. The proposed test has several intellectual aspects: it uses nano-scale metal traces to monitor the delamination propagation; it uses electromagnetic actuation to provide the driving force needed for delamination propagation, and thus the test method does not require any fixtures to apply loads; using an array of cantilevers placed in an external magnetic field and with in-situ crack propagation capabilities, the proposed test technique will be a significant advancement in interfacial fatigue crack testing. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Nano-scale thin films are being increasingly used in a wide range of applications such as solid-state devices, integrated electronic components, sensors, MEMS/NEMS, antireflective optical films for better light transmission, conductive films in display technologies, thin-film coating in solar cells, magnetic coatings for media storage, and flexible and bendable lenses for space exploration. The proposed research will have a strong impact on their reliability.   The research approach and the findings will be integrated in graduate and undergraduate education.  Also, students will get exposure to nano-scale thin film fabrication and testing.  The research methodology and results will be published in technical journals and presented in conferences to reach a wide-ranging audience.  &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>04/25/2008</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>04/29/2010</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>0800037</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Suresh</FirstName>
<LastName>Sitaraman</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>K</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Suresh K Sitaraman</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>suresh.sitaraman@me.gatech.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>4048943405</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000274859</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/25/2008</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Georgia Tech Research Corporation</Name>
<CityName>Atlanta</CityName>
<ZipCode>303320420</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>4048944819</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>Office of Sponsored Programs</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Georgia</StateName>
<StateCode>GA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>GA05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>097394084</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>GEORGIA TECH RESEARCH CORPORATION</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>097394084</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Georgia Institute of Technology]]></Name>
<CityName>Atlanta</CityName>
<StateCode>GA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>303320002</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[225 NORTH AVE NW]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Georgia</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>GA05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1630</Code>
<Text>Mechanics of Materials and Str</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7237</Code>
<Text>NANO NON-SOLIC SCI &amp; ENG AWD</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>022E</Code>
<Text>SOLID MECHANICS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>024E</Code>
<Text>MATERIALS DESIGN</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>036E</Code>
<Text>CIVIL INFRASTRUCTURE</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1057</Code>
<Text>CIS BASE RESEARCH</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>116E</Code>
<Text>RESEARCH EXP FOR UNDERGRADS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9161</Code>
<Text>SINGLE DIVISION/UNIVERSITY</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9178</Code>
<Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9231</Code>
<Text>SUPPL FOR UNDERGRAD RES ASSIST</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9251</Code>
<Text>REU SUPP-Res Exp for Ugrd Supp</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>AMPP</Code>
<Text>ADVANCED MATERIALS &amp; PROCESSING PROGRAM</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>CVIS</Code>
<Text>CIVIL INFRASTRUCTURE</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0108</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0110</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2008~250000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2010~6000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Micro-scale and nano-scale thin films are being increasingly used in a wide range of applications such as solid-state devices, integrated electronic components, sensors, MEMS/NEMS, nanocomposite hard thin-films for wear and abrasion resistance, anti-reflective optical films, conductive films in display technologies, thin-film coating in solar cells, magnetic coatings for media storage, and flexible and bendable lenses for space exploration. Debonding or delamination of such thin films, due to low adhesion strength and/or high stresses, will result in premature failure of the component.&nbsp; Although a significant amount of interfacial delamination is caused by fatigue loading, existing literature has not adequately addressed this topic, especially for nano-scale and micro-scale thin films.&nbsp; This is because the fixturing and application of fatigue loading for thin films is extremely challenging, and the monitoring of the delamination propagation under such fatigue loading is even more challenging.&nbsp;&nbsp; Therefore, there is a compelling and immediate need to develop experimental techniques to study the thin-film delamination propagation under fatigue loading.</p> <p><br />This research has developed an innovative delamination test that can be used to monitor and characterize interfacial delamination propagation for nano-scale and micro-scale thin films, under fatigue as well as monotonic loading. The developed test has several intellectual aspects: it uses metal trace marks to monitor the delamination propagation; it uses electromagnetic actuation to provide the driving force needed for delamination propagation, and thus the test method does not require any fixtures to apply loads; the max load, the load ratio, and the loading frequency can be changed in-situ without removing the sample; thousands of cycles can be carried out in one or two days, as opposed to several days in other test techniques; temperature and humidity effects on interfacial adhesion can be easily evaluated, as the test technique does not require fixtures.&nbsp; Using the test technique, interfacial fracture parameters for thin-film electroplated copper on a natively oxidized silicon substrate have been obtained under monotonic and fatigue loading conditions.&nbsp; Finite-element and analytical models have been developed for data extraction.&nbsp;</p> <p>Graduate students have gained exposure to cleanroom techniques and analysis techniques.&nbsp; Three undergraduate students and one high school student have worked on this project.&nbsp; One of the undergraduate students is currently a graduate student, and the other two have expressed interest in graduate studies.&nbsp; The high school student has chosen to major in engineering at Georgia Tech.&nbsp; Interfacial delamination topics were discussed in senior-level undergraduate as well as graduate microelectronic packaging courses. Several journal publications and conference and industry presentations have resulted from this work.&nbsp; Additional papers are in preparation, and also, efforts are underway to get funding from industry and other sources to further develop the test technique.&nbsp; The work has received good publicity in popular media. Please see:<br />&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; <br />&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; <a href="http://www.sciencedaily.com/releases/2012/04/120413101347.htm">http://www.sciencedaily.com/releases/2012/04/120413101347.htm</a><br />&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; <br />&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; <a href="http://www.gatech.edu/newsroom/release.html?nid=123581">http://www.gatech.edu/newsroom/release.html?nid=123581</a><br />&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; <br />The developed test method is generic and can study interfacial properties for thin films deposited through electroplating, sputtering, lamination, evaporation, and numerous others. The developed test method will help ensur...]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Micro-scale and nano-scale thin films are being increasingly used in a wide range of applications such as solid-state devices, integrated electronic components, sensors, MEMS/NEMS, nanocomposite hard thin-films for wear and abrasion resistance, anti-reflective optical films, conductive films in display technologies, thin-film coating in solar cells, magnetic coatings for media storage, and flexible and bendable lenses for space exploration. Debonding or delamination of such thin films, due to low adhesion strength and/or high stresses, will result in premature failure of the component.  Although a significant amount of interfacial delamination is caused by fatigue loading, existing literature has not adequately addressed this topic, especially for nano-scale and micro-scale thin films.  This is because the fixturing and application of fatigue loading for thin films is extremely challenging, and the monitoring of the delamination propagation under such fatigue loading is even more challenging.   Therefore, there is a compelling and immediate need to develop experimental techniques to study the thin-film delamination propagation under fatigue loading.   This research has developed an innovative delamination test that can be used to monitor and characterize interfacial delamination propagation for nano-scale and micro-scale thin films, under fatigue as well as monotonic loading. The developed test has several intellectual aspects: it uses metal trace marks to monitor the delamination propagation; it uses electromagnetic actuation to provide the driving force needed for delamination propagation, and thus the test method does not require any fixtures to apply loads; the max load, the load ratio, and the loading frequency can be changed in-situ without removing the sample; thousands of cycles can be carried out in one or two days, as opposed to several days in other test techniques; temperature and humidity effects on interfacial adhesion can be easily evaluated, as the test technique does not require fixtures.  Using the test technique, interfacial fracture parameters for thin-film electroplated copper on a natively oxidized silicon substrate have been obtained under monotonic and fatigue loading conditions.  Finite-element and analytical models have been developed for data extraction.   Graduate students have gained exposure to cleanroom techniques and analysis techniques.  Three undergraduate students and one high school student have worked on this project.  One of the undergraduate students is currently a graduate student, and the other two have expressed interest in graduate studies.  The high school student has chosen to major in engineering at Georgia Tech.  Interfacial delamination topics were discussed in senior-level undergraduate as well as graduate microelectronic packaging courses. Several journal publications and conference and industry presentations have resulted from this work.  Additional papers are in preparation, and also, efforts are underway to get funding from industry and other sources to further develop the test technique.  The work has received good publicity in popular media. Please see:               http://www.sciencedaily.com/releases/2012/04/120413101347.htm               http://www.gatech.edu/newsroom/release.html?nid=123581         The developed test method is generic and can study interfacial properties for thin films deposited through electroplating, sputtering, lamination, evaporation, and numerous others. The developed test method will help ensure that the structures that we design, build, and use from microelectronics to medical to aerospace to automotive applications will not prematurely fail and will be reliable.          Last Modified: 07/09/2012       Submitted by: Suresh K Sitaraman]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
