<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Extremal Problems in Quasiconformal Geometry and Nonlinear PDEs, an Invitation to n- Harmonic Hyperelasticity</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>06/01/2008</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2013</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>499339.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>499339</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DMS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Bruce P. Palka</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>In this project the principal investigator initiates a study of extremal problems for mappings of finite (usually unbounded) distortion, hoping to provide background for further developments in geometric function theory and nonlinear elliptic partial differential equations. The plan of attack relies on geometric and physical intuition, drawn especially from the theory of nonlinear elasticity and materials science. This represents a trend that in recent years has become more pronounced, and it has led to increasing efforts by pure and applied mathematicians to combine such ideas and results. The project centers on the remarkable relationship (first envisioned by the principal investigator and Jani Onninen) between mappings of finite distortion and hyperelasticity. Both theories are governed by variational principles and problems of compelling common mathematical interest. The new fronts that have been created in geometric function theory include polyconvex integrals of the distortion function and the associated total n-harmonic energy. Of special interest are mappings of smallest mean distortion, whose existence, regularity, and global invertibility are related to deep unsolved mathematical questions. For instance, the present proposal takes on difficult questions concerning deformations of spherical rings in Euclidean n-space, and a much studied conjecture of Nitsche (1962). This is a tentative first step toward an n-dimensional theory of moduli, a subject that hopefully will develop into a very coherent analogue of Teichmuller theory in higher dimensions. The project features new concepts (such as free Lagrangians) and challenging questions galore, some already prepared for answers, others of a more speculative, long-term character. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;With its elaborate design, this project will encourage the dissemination of modern geometric function theory, a classical field that has undergone a tremendous transformation in recent years, to a wider audience and will enhance the understanding of the subject's pervasive presence in applications. The project reflects continued efforts by the principal investigator to provide an active and welcoming research environment for graduate students and young scholars through effective training, the creation of educational materials, and the fostering of scientific partnerships both within the U.S. and overseas. This endeavor has hitherto been particularly effective for groups historically underrepresented in mathematics, especially women. The proposed problems will find considerable interest among geometric analysts, especially researchers in such physically relevant fields as partial differential equations, the calculus of variations, and nonlinear elasticity theory. &lt;br/&gt;</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>04/07/2008</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>04/02/2012</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>0800416</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Tadeusz</FirstName>
<LastName>Iwaniec</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Tadeusz Iwaniec</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>tiwaniec@mailbox.syr.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>3154431495</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000328599</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/07/2008</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Syracuse University</Name>
<CityName>SYRACUSE</CityName>
<ZipCode>132441200</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>3154432807</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>OFFICE OF SPONSORED PROGRAMS</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[211 Lyman Hall]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>24</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NY24</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>002257350</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>SYRACUSE UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>002257350</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Syracuse University]]></Name>
<CityName>SYRACUSE</CityName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<ZipCode>132441200</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[OFFICE OF SPONSORED PROGRAMS]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>24</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NY24</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<FoaInformation>
<Code>0000099</Code>
<Name>Other Applications NEC</Name>
</FoaInformation>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1281</Code>
<Text>ANALYSIS PROGRAM</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>0000</Code>
<Text>UNASSIGNED</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>OTHR</Code>
<Text>OTHER RESEARCH OR EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0108</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0109</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0110</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0111</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0112</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2008~112065</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2009~104364</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2010~84071</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2011~85731</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2012~113108</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><br /><br /></p> <p><strong><em>Intellectual Merit and Accomplishments</em></strong></p> <p>The major part of this proposal focusses on the long term research program of the PI to advance variational techniques in Geometric Function Theory (GFT).&nbsp; An aim is to strongly promote linkages between the modern &nbsp;Calculus of Variations (in its various manifestations) with GFT thereby bringing new ideas and results to each field.&nbsp; There are particular applications in mind, such as providing new models in fields such as Nonlinear Elasticity (NE) and the theoretical aspects of nonlinear materials science.<strong><em> </em></strong>The research focus is to provide an in-depth analysis of the concept of energy-minimal deformations predominantly in <strong><em>traction free problems</em></strong> in two dimensions.&nbsp; Thus we do not prescribe these deformations on the boundary and in this way we determine ``absolute energy minimizers''. We seek&nbsp; to gain new insight into the many&nbsp; phenomena encountered in the Calculus of Variations as well as in <strong><em>minimal<br />surface theory</em></strong>,&nbsp;<strong><em>harmonic mappings</em></strong>,&nbsp; <em><strong>NE</strong></em> (a key question here concerns the <strong><em>interpenetrability of matter</em></strong>), <strong><em>material science</em></strong>, and so forth.<strong><em> </em></strong>The<br />analysis of mappings between doubly connected regions led us to the <strong><em>Nitsche Conjecture</em></strong> - a charming connection with an old problem on minimal<br />surfaces.&nbsp; As we seek greater knowledge about the energy-minimal deformations, questions about general <strong><em>Sobolev homeomorphisms</em></strong> and their limits become ever more important to resolve.&nbsp;&nbsp;We showed that the weak and strong <strong><em>limits of Sobolev homeomorphisms</em></strong> are the same, a result of interest in mathematical models of elasticity.&nbsp; In traction free problems one needs to approximate a Sobolev homeomorphism with diffeomorphisms. &nbsp;We solved the <strong><em>approximation problem</em></strong> in planar domains (thin plates and films). But it remains completely open in higher dimensions.<strong><em> </em></strong></p> <p>Our variational approach turned out to be effective in better understanding of the old conjecture on the Lp -norm of the <strong><em>Beurling-Ahlfors Transform</em></strong> (a passage between two homotopy classes of the first order elliptic operators). Here our recent progress&nbsp; is due to a remarkable minimization (using new complex interpolation method) of the <strong><em>rank-one convex</em></strong> Burkholder functional which, in a different context, appeared already in the theory of martingales.<strong><em>&nbsp;</em></strong></p> <p>During the period of the NSF award DMS 0800416 the PI wrote<br />21 research papers and 3 survey articles. A <strong><em>monograph with Jani Onninen</em></strong><br />is in progress. Several challenging problems from this proposal were solved.These include the solution of the long standing <strong><em>Nitsche Conjecture</em></strong>. Perhaps the 6 most important publications are:</p> <p>[1]&nbsp; Iwaniec, T., Kovalev, L.V.,&nbsp; and&nbsp; Onninen, J.,&nbsp;<br /><strong><em>The Nitsche conjecture</em></strong>&nbsp; J. Amer. Math. Soc., 24 (2011), no. 2, 345--373.</p> <p>[2]&nbsp; Iwaniec, T., Koh, N-T, Kovalev, L.V.,&nbsp; and&nbsp; Onninen, J.,&nbsp;<br /><strong><em>Existence of energy-minimal diffeomorphisms between doubly connected domains.</em></strong> Invent. Math. 186 (2011), no. 3, 667--707.</p> <p>&nbsp;[3]&nbsp; Iwaniec, T., Kovalev, L.V.,&nbsp; and&nbsp; Onninen, J.,&nbsp; <strong><em>Diffeomorphic approximation of Sobolev homeomorphisms.</em></strong> Arch. Rat. Mech. Anal.&nbsp; 201 (2011), no. 3, 1047--1067.</p> <p>&nbsp; [4]&nbsp; Iwaniec, T., Kovalev, L.V.,&nbsp; and&nbsp; Onninen, J.,...]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[     Intellectual Merit and Accomplishments  The major part of this proposal focusses on the long term research program of the PI to advance variational techniques in Geometric Function Theory (GFT).  An aim is to strongly promote linkages between the modern  Calculus of Variations (in its various manifestations) with GFT thereby bringing new ideas and results to each field.  There are particular applications in mind, such as providing new models in fields such as Nonlinear Elasticity (NE) and the theoretical aspects of nonlinear materials science. The research focus is to provide an in-depth analysis of the concept of energy-minimal deformations predominantly in traction free problems in two dimensions.  Thus we do not prescribe these deformations on the boundary and in this way we determine ``absolute energy minimizers''. We seek  to gain new insight into the many  phenomena encountered in the Calculus of Variations as well as in minimal surface theory, harmonic mappings,  NE (a key question here concerns the interpenetrability of matter), material science, and so forth. The analysis of mappings between doubly connected regions led us to the Nitsche Conjecture - a charming connection with an old problem on minimal surfaces.  As we seek greater knowledge about the energy-minimal deformations, questions about general Sobolev homeomorphisms and their limits become ever more important to resolve.  We showed that the weak and strong limits of Sobolev homeomorphisms are the same, a result of interest in mathematical models of elasticity.  In traction free problems one needs to approximate a Sobolev homeomorphism with diffeomorphisms.  We solved the approximation problem in planar domains (thin plates and films). But it remains completely open in higher dimensions.   Our variational approach turned out to be effective in better understanding of the old conjecture on the Lp -norm of the Beurling-Ahlfors Transform (a passage between two homotopy classes of the first order elliptic operators). Here our recent progress  is due to a remarkable minimization (using new complex interpolation method) of the rank-one convex Burkholder functional which, in a different context, appeared already in the theory of martingales.   During the period of the NSF award DMS 0800416 the PI wrote 21 research papers and 3 survey articles. A monograph with Jani Onninen is in progress. Several challenging problems from this proposal were solved.These include the solution of the long standing Nitsche Conjecture. Perhaps the 6 most important publications are:  [1]  Iwaniec, T., Kovalev, L.V.,  and  Onninen, J.,  The Nitsche conjecture  J. Amer. Math. Soc., 24 (2011), no. 2, 345--373.  [2]  Iwaniec, T., Koh, N-T, Kovalev, L.V.,  and  Onninen, J.,  Existence of energy-minimal diffeomorphisms between doubly connected domains. Invent. Math. 186 (2011), no. 3, 667--707.   [3]  Iwaniec, T., Kovalev, L.V.,  and  Onninen, J.,  Diffeomorphic approximation of Sobolev homeomorphisms. Arch. Rat. Mech. Anal.  201 (2011), no. 3, 1047--1067.    [4]  Iwaniec, T., Kovalev, L.V.,  and  Onninen, J.,  Lipschitz regularity for inner-variational equations. Duke Mathematical Journal, Vol. 162, No.4. (2013), 643--672.  [5]   Astala, K., Iwaniec, T., Prause, I., and Saksman, E. ,  Burkholder integrals, Morrey's problem and quasiconformal mappings.  J. Amer. Math. Soc. 25 (2012), no. 2, 507--531.   [6]  Iwaniec, T. and  Onninen, J.,  Mappings of least Dirichlet energy and their Hopf differentials ,  Archive forRational Mechanics and Analysis, vol. 209 (2013) no. 2, 401--453 arXiv: 1202.1017.   Broader Impact  The results of the project have been encouraging and certainly merit further investigation as well as exploring them in the applied fields of mathematics. To get a glimpse of these, our results can be interpreted as saying that the physical law of the interpenetrability of matter comes exactly with the loss of the Lagrange equation.   Theoretical predictions for the deformation of...]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
