<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Strange Form Factors and Precision Standard Model Tests</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/15/2008</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2012</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>270000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>270000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03010600</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>PHY</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Physics</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Gail Dodge</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This grant supports research that seeks to answer a fundamental question about matter.  What is the nature of any new physics not described by the Standard Model of electroweak physics?  This question will be addressed by the Qweak experiment at the Thomas Jefferson National Accelerator Facility.  It will measure the proton's neutral weak charge via parity-violating electron scattering at very low momentum transfer.  The proton's weak charge has a well-defined prediction in the Standard Model; a precise measurement of it is sensitive to many popular scenarios for extending the Standard Model.  Our group is responsible for the design and construction of three pieces of hardware for the Qweak experiment - a set of drift chambers, a rotation device for rotating the drift chambers to the different desired positions, and a set of luminosity monitor detectors.  During the period of this grant, we will be completing construction, installation, and commissioning of the hardware.  We will also carry out the commissioning and a good fraction of the production running of the experiment.  The projects we are working on involve a wide range of hardware and software tasks that will contribute to the education of graduate and undergraduate students working on the project.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/04/2008</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/07/2010</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>0801305</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Mark</FirstName>
<LastName>Pitt</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>L</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Mark L Pitt</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>pitt@vt.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5402313015</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000262572</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/04/2008</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Norman</FirstName>
<LastName>Morgan</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME>Jr.</PI_SUFX_NAME>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Norman Morgan</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>nmorgan@vt.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5402315627</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000247620</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/04/2008</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University</Name>
<CityName>BLACKSBURG</CityName>
<ZipCode>240610001</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5402315281</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>Sponsored Programs 0170</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[300 Turner Street NW, Suite 4200]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Virginia</StateName>
<StateCode>VA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>09</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>VA09</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>003137015</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>VIRGINIA POLYTECHNIC INSTITUTE AND STATE UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>003137015</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University]]></Name>
<CityName>BLACKSBURG</CityName>
<StateCode>VA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>240610001</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[Sponsored Programs 0170]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Virginia</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>09</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>VA09</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<FoaInformation>
<Code>0000099</Code>
<Name>Other Applications NEC</Name>
</FoaInformation>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1232</Code>
<Text>Nuclear &amp; Hadron Quantum Chrom</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>0000</Code>
<Text>UNASSIGNED</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>OTHR</Code>
<Text>OTHER RESEARCH OR EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0108</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0109</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0110</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2008~90000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2009~90000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2010~90000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The research activities funded by this award were aimed at answering fundamental questions about matter.&nbsp; One question concerned the role played by the "sea" of strange quark anti-quark pairs in the electromagnetic structure of the proton.&nbsp; Results of the G0 experiment at Jefferson Lab that our group contributed to showed that the strange quark sea does not appear to play a large role.&nbsp; We also played a major role in analyzing data from the G0 expeirment that shed light on processes where two photons are exchanged.&nbsp; Another major question is what is the nature of any new physics that is not described by the Standard Model of electroweak physics?&nbsp; The Qweak experiment at Jefferson Lab aims to answer this question using parity-violating electron-proton elastic scattering.&nbsp; Our group made significant contributions toward carrying out this experiment by building and commissioning several pieces of apparatus (horizontal drift chambers and their rotation system, luminosity monitors, halo monitors).&nbsp;&nbsp; At the end of this grant period, the Qweak experiment was actively engaged in its production run.&nbsp; When that data-taking and analysis period is completed, the experiment will yield a measurement of the proton's weak charge which can be used to test the Standard Model and probe for new physics beyond it.</p> <p>This work provided numerous educational opportunities for undergraduate and graduate students via the wide range of hardware and software tasks needed to accomplish our goals.&nbsp; A total of four graduate students and four undergraduate students worked with us during the period of this award.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 06/30/2013<br>      Modified by: Mark&nbsp;L&nbsp;Pitt</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The research activities funded by this award were aimed at answering fundamental questions about matter.  One question concerned the role played by the "sea" of strange quark anti-quark pairs in the electromagnetic structure of the proton.  Results of the G0 experiment at Jefferson Lab that our group contributed to showed that the strange quark sea does not appear to play a large role.  We also played a major role in analyzing data from the G0 expeirment that shed light on processes where two photons are exchanged.  Another major question is what is the nature of any new physics that is not described by the Standard Model of electroweak physics?  The Qweak experiment at Jefferson Lab aims to answer this question using parity-violating electron-proton elastic scattering.  Our group made significant contributions toward carrying out this experiment by building and commissioning several pieces of apparatus (horizontal drift chambers and their rotation system, luminosity monitors, halo monitors).   At the end of this grant period, the Qweak experiment was actively engaged in its production run.  When that data-taking and analysis period is completed, the experiment will yield a measurement of the proton's weak charge which can be used to test the Standard Model and probe for new physics beyond it.  This work provided numerous educational opportunities for undergraduate and graduate students via the wide range of hardware and software tasks needed to accomplish our goals.  A total of four graduate students and four undergraduate students worked with us during the period of this award.             Last Modified: 06/30/2013       Submitted by: Mark L Pitt]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
