<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Educating Technicians for Building Automation and Sustainability</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/15/2008</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>01/31/2013</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>900000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>999716</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>11040100</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>EHR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DUE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Undergraduate Education</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Darryl N Williams</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The need for technicians with traditional skill sets as well as with experience in programming, networking, and systems integration knowledge is well-documented and technicians who can manage controls present an emerging and rapidly expanding market of high-wage employment for community college graduates. The lack of technicians qualified in building automation systems constitutes one of the greatest barriers to rapidly implementing energy efficiency, greenhouse gas reduction, and sustainability targets in commercial buildings. This project builds on previous efforts aimed at upgrading technician education to meet today's challenges for energy efficiency in buildings. Courses are being developed in the area of building automation and sustainability and a new associate's degree program will be offered in building automation, filling a critical gap in degree offerings. The project involves extensive collaboration with national ATE centers, with industry, and with four-year institutions. A Physics for Building Science and Sustainability high school summer program is being expanded and a teacher training component is being added through this project. Results from the project are being rigorously evaluated and disseminated on a national scale.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>09/04/2008</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/10/2011</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.076</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>0802595</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Peter</FirstName>
<LastName>Crabtree</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>L</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Peter L Crabtree</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>plcrabtree@berkeley.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5102130317</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000444397</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/04/2008</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Kristin</FirstName>
<LastName>Heinemeier</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME>Dr.</PI_SUFX_NAME>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Kristin Heinemeier</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>kheinemeier@ucdavis.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5104667300</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000080960</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/04/2008</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Peralta Community College District Office</Name>
<CityName>Oakland</CityName>
<ZipCode>946062844</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5104667300</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>333 East Eighth Street</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>13</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CA13</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>831327932</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>PERALTA COMMUNITY COLLEGE DISTRICT</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>076567718</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Laney College]]></Name>
<CityName>Oakland</CityName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>946074808</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[900 Fallon Street]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>13</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CA13</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<FoaInformation>
<Code>0116000</Code>
<Name>Human Subjects</Name>
</FoaInformation>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7412</Code>
<Text>Advanced Tech Education Prog</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1032</Code>
<Text>ADVANCED TECHNOLOGY EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9178</Code>
<Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>SMET</Code>
<Text>SCIENCE, MATH, ENG &amp; TECH EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0408</Code>
<Name>NSF Education &amp; Human Resource</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040106</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0411</Code>
<Name>NSF Education &amp; Human Resource</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040106</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2008~900000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2011~99716</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><strong><span style="text-decoration: underline;">&nbsp;</span></strong></p> <p>Commercial buildings are responsible for 20% of the nation&rsquo;s greenhouse gas emissions, and this percentage is expected to increase in the next few decades as the sector expands. Under this project, Laney College spearheaded curriculum, lab development, and research efforts to prepare a building technician workforce with the complex skills and knowledge needed to become sustainability agents in new and existing commercial buildings. Building systems technicians are skilled technicians who install, operate, and maintain building systems<span style="text-decoration: underline;">,</span> including mechanical and electrical, security, lighting, water, building automation, and energy management systems. Building systems technicians work on the frontline of the building operations and are key to the ability of owners to optimize building performance, contain operational costs, meet occupant needs for comfort, safety, and function and reduce the carbon footprint of&nbsp;buildings.</p> <p>Located in inner city Oakland, Laney is a minority-majority community college with a long history in advanced technology education. Partnering with Lawrence Berkeley National Laboratory, UC Berkeley, and other research and educational institutions regionally and nationally, and working closely with industry, Laney has earned a reputation for spearheading state-of-the-art curriculum reflecting the developments of a rapidly evolving building industry.</p> <p>Below we summarize key outcomes of this second NSF ATE project (continued from DUE 0402696), highlighting its intellectual merit and broader impacts:</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p><strong><span style="text-decoration: underline;">Intellectual Merit: Advancement of Knowledge and Understanding; Integration of Research and Education: </span></strong><strong>&nbsp;</strong></p> <p><strong>Program and Curriculum Development</strong></p> <ul> <li>Two-year certificate and AS degree in Building Automation Systems completed, certificate and AS degree in Commercial Energy Management in development</li> <li>Problem-based learning scenarios developed, tested, and enhanced, including a template that can be used across courses; website developed and resources disseminated nationwide; instructor-workshops and regular peer support meetings held for Laney ECT instructors</li> </ul> <p><strong>&nbsp;</strong></p> <p><strong>Research (in partnership with the Building Intelligence Group):</strong></p> <ul> <li>Conducted original national research (focus groups, interviews, surveys) to map the gaps between building technicians&rsquo; capabilities and building system management requirements. Published and disseminated report: <a href="http://www.laney.edu/wp/environmental_control_tech/building_operations_report">Current Situation and Trends in Buildings and Facility Operations</a> </li> <li>Published four case studies on best practices in facility operations: Fred Hutchinson Cancer Research Center, Adobe Headquarters, Smithsonian Institution, eBay Data Center </li> </ul> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p><strong><span style="text-decoration: underline;">Broader Impacts: Promotion of Teaching, Training, and Learning; Enhancement of Infrastructure for Research and Education; Broad Dissemination to Enhance Scientific Understanding; Broaden the Participation of Underrepresented Groups:</span></strong></p> <p><strong>STEM Pipeline</strong></p> <ul> <li>Physics for Building Science summer program held every summer and continuously refined; program documentation developed; 98% of students are minority populations. </li> <li>Network of high-school teachers and green academy instructors developed, a series of workshops with high school instructors held; new Physics for Energy Science curriculum high school course developed, modeled after Laney&rsquo;s Physics for Building Science, and articulated with Oakland...]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[    Commercial buildings are responsible for 20% of the nationÆs greenhouse gas emissions, and this percentage is expected to increase in the next few decades as the sector expands. Under this project, Laney College spearheaded curriculum, lab development, and research efforts to prepare a building technician workforce with the complex skills and knowledge needed to become sustainability agents in new and existing commercial buildings. Building systems technicians are skilled technicians who install, operate, and maintain building systems, including mechanical and electrical, security, lighting, water, building automation, and energy management systems. Building systems technicians work on the frontline of the building operations and are key to the ability of owners to optimize building performance, contain operational costs, meet occupant needs for comfort, safety, and function and reduce the carbon footprint of buildings.  Located in inner city Oakland, Laney is a minority-majority community college with a long history in advanced technology education. Partnering with Lawrence Berkeley National Laboratory, UC Berkeley, and other research and educational institutions regionally and nationally, and working closely with industry, Laney has earned a reputation for spearheading state-of-the-art curriculum reflecting the developments of a rapidly evolving building industry.  Below we summarize key outcomes of this second NSF ATE project (continued from DUE 0402696), highlighting its intellectual merit and broader impacts:     Intellectual Merit: Advancement of Knowledge and Understanding; Integration of Research and Education:    Program and Curriculum Development  Two-year certificate and AS degree in Building Automation Systems completed, certificate and AS degree in Commercial Energy Management in development Problem-based learning scenarios developed, tested, and enhanced, including a template that can be used across courses; website developed and resources disseminated nationwide; instructor-workshops and regular peer support meetings held for Laney ECT instructors      Research (in partnership with the Building Intelligence Group):  Conducted original national research (focus groups, interviews, surveys) to map the gaps between building techniciansÆ capabilities and building system management requirements. Published and disseminated report: Current Situation and Trends in Buildings and Facility Operations  Published four case studies on best practices in facility operations: Fred Hutchinson Cancer Research Center, Adobe Headquarters, Smithsonian Institution, eBay Data Center       Broader Impacts: Promotion of Teaching, Training, and Learning; Enhancement of Infrastructure for Research and Education; Broad Dissemination to Enhance Scientific Understanding; Broaden the Participation of Underrepresented Groups:  STEM Pipeline  Physics for Building Science summer program held every summer and continuously refined; program documentation developed; 98% of students are minority populations.  Network of high-school teachers and green academy instructors developed, a series of workshops with high school instructors held; new Physics for Energy Science curriculum high school course developed, modeled after LaneyÆs Physics for Building Science, and articulated with Oakland Unified School District, benefitting primarily minority populations      Professional Development  National Network of HVAC Instructors developed: Database of 500 community college HVAC and building performance programs developed; online survey and needs assessment conducted Two-day faculty forum hosted at Laney in 2011 for 12 community colleges, focusing on HVAC and building performance Three-day national training hosted for re-tuning/retrocommissioning of commercial buildings, in collaboration with Pacific Northwest National Labs Three webinars  for HVAC and building performance instructors held, with nationwide participation CA Community Colleges Energy Efficienc...]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
