<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Superconductivity and Proximity Effect in Two-Dimensional Films and Multilayers</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>04/01/2008</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>03/31/2011</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>440000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>440000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03070003</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DMR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Materials Research</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Daniele Finotello</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Non-Technical Abstract&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Quantum phase transitions continue to attract intense theoretical and experimental interest. Such transitions -- where changing an external parameter in the Hamiltonian induces a transition from one quantum ground state to another, fundamentally different one -- have been invoked to understand experimental data in many electronic systems, as well as to analyze more challenging quantum phenomena such as the limitations of quantum computing. A paradigm for quantum phase transitions has been the superconductor to insulator transition in two-dimensional films. This transition is found to have a variety of realizations depending on intrinsic properties of the materials used. Controlling the strength of superconductivity, disorder, or dimensionality of the films will impact the nature of the transition, which is accessed through the variation of external parameters such as temperature and magnetic field. This award supports a project to explore the superconductor to insulator transition in amorphous MgB2 films and multilayers. The uniqueness of this system is the ability to control the strength of superconductivity over a very wide range, control the disorder, and fabricate bilayers and multilayers. However, more uniquely, due to the lightness of both magnesium and boron, spin orbit interaction is probably the lowest that can be achieved in any thin film superconductor, providing us with new opportunities to study its effect on the transition. The proposed work is expected to impact science in several areas including shedding new light on the nature of quantum phase transitions in reduced dimensions, better understanding of the material science of amorphous superconducting films, and the development of new methodologies using novel measurements techniques. The program involves graduate students in this area of great interest to physics and future applications.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Technical Abstract&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Studies of the phase diagram of two-dimensional superconductors has been intimately connected to finding new materials. With each materials system a different set of properties is highlighted. Over the years, NSF support enabled the optimization of a variety of materials for studies of thin superconducting films in general and the superconductor to insulator transition (SIT) in particular. These include amorphous-MoGe films that allowed the discovery of "metallic phases," amorphous-InOx films that allowed the studies of the regime of strong disorder, and more recently amorphous- MgB2 films which in addition to the overlap in parameters with MoGe and InOx, also provide a new knob in the form of controlling spin-orbit interaction. A newly available, novel technique to fabricate multilayers of amorphous MgB2/MgO allows further exploration of dimensionality effects. This award supports a project to explore the rich physics this MgB2 model system offers. Experiments will be performed to study SIT in perpendicular magnetic field on MgB2 thin films bilayers of various types (e.g. proximity systems) and multilayers. Specific attention will be given to the effect of quantum melting near the SIT point. The manifestation of low spin-orbit interaction will be explored through measurements in parallel magnetic field searching for signatures of first order transition and irreversibility. In addition to transport measurements, mesoscopic effects near the transition will be explored using novel techniques including scanning tunneling potentiometry and Kerr microscopy. The proposed work is expected shed new light on the nature of quantum phase transitions in reduced dimensions, as well as impact the understanding of the material science of amorphous superconducting films, and the development of new methodologies using novel measurements techniques. The program involves graduate students in this area of great interest to fundamental physics and future applications.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>03/18/2008</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>04/26/2010</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>0803958</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Malcolm</FirstName>
<LastName>Beasley</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>R</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Malcolm R Beasley</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>beasley@stanford.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6507231196</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000229854</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>03/18/2008</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Aharon</FirstName>
<LastName>Kapitulnik</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Aharon Kapitulnik</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>aharonk@stanford.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6507233847</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000471229</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>03/18/2008</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Stanford University</Name>
<CityName>Stanford</CityName>
<ZipCode>943052004</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6507232300</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>450 Jane Stanford Way</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>18</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CA18</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>009214214</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>LELAND STANFORD JUNIOR UNIVERSITY, THE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>009214214</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Stanford University]]></Name>
<CityName>Stanford</CityName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>943052004</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[450 Jane Stanford Way]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>18</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CA18</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<FoaInformation>
<Code>0106000</Code>
<Name>Materials Research</Name>
</FoaInformation>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1710</Code>
<Text>CONDENSED MATTER PHYSICS</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9161</Code>
<Text>SINGLE DIVISION/UNIVERSITY</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>AMPP</Code>
<Text>ADVANCED MATERIALS &amp; PROCESSING PROGRAM</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0108</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0109</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0110</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2008~160000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2009~140000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2010~140000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The research performed under this NSF grant explored a very important set of concepts in condensed matter physics, which involve the behavior of materials in the extreme quantum limit. This limit has become increasingly important in modern technology as computer chips become so dense, that individual components start to be limited (or may benefit from) by the laws of quantum mechanics. &nbsp;Of particular interest to us are phase transitions in the extreme quantum limit, also called quantum phase transitions. Here, contrary to classical phase transitions, which are observed when the temperature is varied, quantum phase transitions can only be accessed by varying a physical parameter - such as magnetic field or pressure - at absolute zero temperature. The transition describes an abrupt change in the ground state of a many-particle system due to its quantum fluctuations.&nbsp;</p> <p><br />The system that we have been studying is a film that is so thin, that it is effectively behaving as a two-dimensional system. The knob that we are using is a magnetic field applied perpendicular to the surface of the film, and the transition that we are exploring is from a weak metallic behavior that can be described by a simple theory of electrons in disordered metals, to a new quantum state that is dominated by superconductivity (Superconductivity is a phenomenon of exactly zero electrical resistance occurring in certain materials below a characteristic temperature.) Of particular interest to us is to establish the phase diagram of such a system in the multi-space of temperature, magnetic field, disorder and strength of the affinity to superconductivity.</p> <p><br />Our accomplishments under this project include: i) Advances in materials fabrication, especially the fabrication of amorphous tantalum-nitride disordered superconductors; ii) A better understanding of the process by which a two-dimensional superconductor enters a superconducting state. Here we explored the nature of superconducting fluctuations on the Hall effect (that is, the production of a voltage difference (the Hall voltage) across an electrical conductor, transverse to an electric current in the conductor and a magnetic field perpendicular to the current,) which is a minute signal and was measured for the first time by us in this project; iii) the occurrence of an intervening, and non-classical metallic state prior to the transition into a superconducting state in these films. Such a metallic state was argued to be impossible within the simple theory of disordered two-dimensional metals. However, our present work, which builds upon our findings in the previous period of this grant, points to the fact the inclusion of strong superconducting fluctuations may yield a new quantum mechanical metallic state.&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 09/01/2011<br>      Modified by: Aharon&nbsp;Kapitulnik</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The research performed under this NSF grant explored a very important set of concepts in condensed matter physics, which involve the behavior of materials in the extreme quantum limit. This limit has become increasingly important in modern technology as computer chips become so dense, that individual components start to be limited (or may benefit from) by the laws of quantum mechanics.  Of particular interest to us are phase transitions in the extreme quantum limit, also called quantum phase transitions. Here, contrary to classical phase transitions, which are observed when the temperature is varied, quantum phase transitions can only be accessed by varying a physical parameter - such as magnetic field or pressure - at absolute zero temperature. The transition describes an abrupt change in the ground state of a many-particle system due to its quantum fluctuations.    The system that we have been studying is a film that is so thin, that it is effectively behaving as a two-dimensional system. The knob that we are using is a magnetic field applied perpendicular to the surface of the film, and the transition that we are exploring is from a weak metallic behavior that can be described by a simple theory of electrons in disordered metals, to a new quantum state that is dominated by superconductivity (Superconductivity is a phenomenon of exactly zero electrical resistance occurring in certain materials below a characteristic temperature.) Of particular interest to us is to establish the phase diagram of such a system in the multi-space of temperature, magnetic field, disorder and strength of the affinity to superconductivity.   Our accomplishments under this project include: i) Advances in materials fabrication, especially the fabrication of amorphous tantalum-nitride disordered superconductors; ii) A better understanding of the process by which a two-dimensional superconductor enters a superconducting state. Here we explored the nature of superconducting fluctuations on the Hall effect (that is, the production of a voltage difference (the Hall voltage) across an electrical conductor, transverse to an electric current in the conductor and a magnetic field perpendicular to the current,) which is a minute signal and was measured for the first time by us in this project; iii) the occurrence of an intervening, and non-classical metallic state prior to the transition into a superconducting state in these films. Such a metallic state was argued to be impossible within the simple theory of disordered two-dimensional metals. However, our present work, which builds upon our findings in the previous period of this grant, points to the fact the inclusion of strong superconducting fluctuations may yield a new quantum mechanical metallic state.        Last Modified: 09/01/2011       Submitted by: Aharon Kapitulnik]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
