<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>RI-Medium: Collaborative Research: Dynamically-Structured Conditional Random Fields for Complex, Natural Domains</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2008</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2013</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>449992.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>449992</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>05020000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>CSE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>IIS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Information &amp; Intelligent Systems</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Hector Munoz-Avila</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>hmunoz@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924481</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Recent progress in bioinformatics, natural language understanding, computer vision, information retrieval and other areas has been significantly enabled by "conditional random fields" (CRFs)---machine learning models of structured outputs, such as sequences, trees and grids.  However, many of the fundamental problems in these application areas involve not just fixed structures, but structures that must be inferred.  This structural ambiguity arises from interacting choices at different levels of representation (e.g. from character sequences to meaning, or from pixels to scene interpretation).  The project will move conditional random fields (CRFs) beyond fixed graphical structures to structures that are constructed dynamically during inference.  Such a capability will be key to building next-generation systems that solve, not just an individual piece of a problem, but complex multi-step problems, as found in natural language understanding and computer vision, in a unified way.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/17/2008</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/27/2010</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.070</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>0803847</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Andrew</FirstName>
<LastName>McCallum</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>K</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Andrew K McCallum</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>mccallum@cs.umass.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>4135451323</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000253651</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/17/2008</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Massachusetts Amherst</Name>
<CityName>Hadley</CityName>
<ZipCode>010359450</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>4135450698</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>Research Administration Building</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[100 Venture Way, Suite 201]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
<StateCode>MA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MA02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>153926712</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF MASSACHUSETTS</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Massachusetts Amherst]]></Name>
<CityName>Hadley</CityName>
<StateCode>MA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>010359450</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[Research Administration Building]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MA02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7495</Code>
<Text>Robust Intelligence</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7495</Code>
<Text>ROBUST INTELLIGENCE</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9215</Code>
<Text>HIGH PERFORMANCE COMPUTING SYSTEMS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>HPCC</Code>
<Text>HIGH PERFORMANCE COMPUTING &amp; COMM</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0108</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0109</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0110</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2008~147816</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2009~148966</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2010~153210</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Recent progress in bioinformatics, natural language understanding,computer vision, information retrieval and other areas has beensignificantly enabled by "conditional random fields" (CRFs)---machinelearning models of structured outputs, such as sequences, trees andgrids. &nbsp;However, many of the fundamental problems in these applicationareas involve not just fixed structures, but structures that must beinferred. &nbsp;This structural ambiguity arises from interacting choicesat different levels of representation (e.g. from character sequencesto meaning, or from pixels to scene interpretation). &nbsp;<br />This project has advanced conditional random fields (CRFs) theory,methodology and application beyond fixed graphical structures tostructures that are constructed dynamically during inference. &nbsp;Such acapability is key to building next-generation systems that solve, notjust an individual piece of a problem, but a complex multi-stepproblems in a unified way.</p> <p><br />Intellectual merit: We created and evaluated several new algorithms,including: (1) We have developed a new machine learning parameterestimation method that works efficiently by being embedded in thesampling-based inference methods that apply so naturally to CRFs withdynamic structure. &nbsp;This method, which we call SampleRank, yielded a33% reduction in error and new state-of-the-art experimental result inentity resolution (the problem of determining when two characterstrings or records are referring to the same entity or not, a keyproblem in information integration). &nbsp;(2) We have developed a newmethod of efficient Markov-chain Monte Carlo inference that focussesin the neighborhood of a query, exploiting dependency structure toachieve faster convergence to the answer in various large-scaleprobabilistic database queries. &nbsp;(3) We have developed a new inferencemethod based on delayed column generation for the LP relaxation of theMAP decoding problem. &nbsp;It forms part of an exciting and growing trendin machine learning and probabilistic inference in which ideas fromthe optimization literature are applied and extended to graphicalmodels. &nbsp;Experiments with our column-generation-based message passingshow our method to be twice as fast as exact as the previous standardalgorithm for newswire text part-of-speech tagging and over thirteentimes faster for a joint part-of-speed and named-entity-recognitiontask.</p> <p><br />Broad impact: (1) Deployment of algorithms: We leveraged our newalgorithms to create a hierarchically-shaped CRFs for entity-basedcoreference. &nbsp;This model provides great accuracy and scalabilityadvantages in large-scale entity resolution problems; there has beensignificant interest in these models from various government agencies,including the DoD and intelligence communities. &nbsp;The model is alreadybeing used internally in the intelligence community. &nbsp;(2) Creation ofnew data sets: In collaboration with colleagues at Google, wedeveloped, gathered and released a new data set for cross-documententity resolution containing over 40 million mentions and 3 millionentities, all automatically labeled due to the fact that the mentionscome from anchored hyperlinks to Wikipedia from across the web. &nbsp;Therelease of our dataset was covered in an article on TechCrunch.com.(3) This grant partially supported the creation of a new probabilisticprogramming language that is greatly accelerating our experiments.The toolkit is called FACTORIE, and it is specifically designed toease the creation of CRFs whose structure changes during inference.The toolkit is publicly released as open-source software, and isavailable at http://github.com/factorie. &nbsp;It has been used at severalsites outside of UMass, including Oracle Research Labs in Boston, CMU,UMD, BAE, and several small companies with DoD contracts.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 12/30/2013<br>    ...]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Recent progress in bioinformatics, natural language understanding,computer vision, information retrieval and other areas has beensignificantly enabled by "conditional random fields" (CRFs)---machinelearning models of structured outputs, such as sequences, trees andgrids.  However, many of the fundamental problems in these applicationareas involve not just fixed structures, but structures that must beinferred.  This structural ambiguity arises from interacting choicesat different levels of representation (e.g. from character sequencesto meaning, or from pixels to scene interpretation).   This project has advanced conditional random fields (CRFs) theory,methodology and application beyond fixed graphical structures tostructures that are constructed dynamically during inference.  Such acapability is key to building next-generation systems that solve, notjust an individual piece of a problem, but a complex multi-stepproblems in a unified way.   Intellectual merit: We created and evaluated several new algorithms,including: (1) We have developed a new machine learning parameterestimation method that works efficiently by being embedded in thesampling-based inference methods that apply so naturally to CRFs withdynamic structure.  This method, which we call SampleRank, yielded a33% reduction in error and new state-of-the-art experimental result inentity resolution (the problem of determining when two characterstrings or records are referring to the same entity or not, a keyproblem in information integration).  (2) We have developed a newmethod of efficient Markov-chain Monte Carlo inference that focussesin the neighborhood of a query, exploiting dependency structure toachieve faster convergence to the answer in various large-scaleprobabilistic database queries.  (3) We have developed a new inferencemethod based on delayed column generation for the LP relaxation of theMAP decoding problem.  It forms part of an exciting and growing trendin machine learning and probabilistic inference in which ideas fromthe optimization literature are applied and extended to graphicalmodels.  Experiments with our column-generation-based message passingshow our method to be twice as fast as exact as the previous standardalgorithm for newswire text part-of-speech tagging and over thirteentimes faster for a joint part-of-speed and named-entity-recognitiontask.   Broad impact: (1) Deployment of algorithms: We leveraged our newalgorithms to create a hierarchically-shaped CRFs for entity-basedcoreference.  This model provides great accuracy and scalabilityadvantages in large-scale entity resolution problems; there has beensignificant interest in these models from various government agencies,including the DoD and intelligence communities.  The model is alreadybeing used internally in the intelligence community.  (2) Creation ofnew data sets: In collaboration with colleagues at Google, wedeveloped, gathered and released a new data set for cross-documententity resolution containing over 40 million mentions and 3 millionentities, all automatically labeled due to the fact that the mentionscome from anchored hyperlinks to Wikipedia from across the web.  Therelease of our dataset was covered in an article on TechCrunch.com.(3) This grant partially supported the creation of a new probabilisticprogramming language that is greatly accelerating our experiments.The toolkit is called FACTORIE, and it is specifically designed toease the creation of CRFs whose structure changes during inference.The toolkit is publicly released as open-source software, and isavailable at http://github.com/factorie.  It has been used at severalsites outside of UMass, including Oracle Research Labs in Boston, CMU,UMD, BAE, and several small companies with DoD contracts.          Last Modified: 12/30/2013       Submitted by: Andrew K Mccallum]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
