<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>New Paths in Advanced Solar Hydrogen Materials</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2008</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2011</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>260000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>260000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03070007</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DMR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Materials Research</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Linda Sapochak</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>lsapocha@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924932</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This award by the Solid State Materials Chemistry program in the Division of Materials Research to Purdue University is to design and develop advanced photocatalytic materials based on anion-doped semiconductor metal-oxides of Indium and Tungsten for solar hydrogen production from water. Nanoparticles and thin films of these doped semiconductor metal-oxides will be synthesized and characterized by the following three experimental protocols: a) spray pyrolysis in which molecular precursors are mixed and cured in situ on an electrode surface, allowing a wide variety of molecular precursors; b) sol-gel process that will allow in situ analysis by liquid state NMR and UV/Vis to obtain detailed information on the bonding and coordination of the metal-ion and dopant species complexes; and c) electrochemical methods. Solid-state characterization methods including solid-state NMR, ESR, XPS, XRD and UV-Vis will be used to characterize the chemical and electronic environment of the hosts and dopant species in the nanoparticle and thin film materials. Evaluation of the doped metal oxides using photoelectrochemical methods will probe the size of activation barriers to water splitting, and measure the efficiency of the materials. The results from these experiments will provide vitally needed information on the electronic, structural, morphological, and kinetic parameters important for improving semiconductor nanoparticles for water splitting.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The development of new materials for an efficient solar hydrogen production from water for energy use could have far-reaching societal impact.  The proposal also seeks to train students ? high school, undergraduate and graduate - in a unique combination of advanced instruments and characterization methods such as solid state NMR, ESR, XPS, XRD, UV-vis, and other materials chemistry protocols.  Graduate and undergraduate students involved in this research will gain a broad education working in this effort to understand important issues in materials and surface chemistry.  Finally, the proposed research will impact the PI?s teaching efforts in General Chemistry where he is introducing a new thematic approach to the subject over the course of the semester. Results will also be disseminated to smaller universities and colleges, and general public.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/17/2008</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/29/2010</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>0805096</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Michael</FirstName>
<LastName>Raftery</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>D</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Michael D Raftery</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>draftery@uw.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2065439709</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000448530</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/17/2008</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Purdue University</Name>
<CityName>West Lafayette</CityName>
<ZipCode>479072114</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>7654941055</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>Young Hall</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[155 S Grant Street]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Indiana</StateName>
<StateCode>IN</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>IN04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>072051394</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>PURDUE UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>072051394</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Purdue University]]></Name>
<CityName>West Lafayette</CityName>
<StateCode>IN</StateCode>
<ZipCode>479072114</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[Young Hall]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Indiana</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>IN04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<FoaInformation>
<Code>0106000</Code>
<Name>Materials Research</Name>
</FoaInformation>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1762</Code>
<Text>SOLID STATE &amp; MATERIALS CHEMIS</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7237</Code>
<Text>NANO NON-SOLIC SCI &amp; ENG AWD</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9161</Code>
<Text>SINGLE DIVISION/UNIVERSITY</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>AMPP</Code>
<Text>ADVANCED MATERIALS &amp; PROCESSING PROGRAM</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0108</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0109</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0110</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2008~80000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2009~90000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2010~90000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>This NSF grant supported research over the past 3 years to make progress in developing a new material or catalyst that can split water using sunlight. This water splitting research program has made a number of interesting findings over the grant period, and published several papers in scientific journals as a result. A number of new semiconducting materials consisting of carbon or nitrogen doped metal oxides were synthesized with increased performance. Several of these materials that were synthesized as fine powders or nanoparticles could produce hydrogen. Our newest material, a mixture of cadmium and indium oxides that was doped with a small amount of carbon is surprisingly efficient in producing hydrogen from water splitting and can do so without a sacrificial reagent, unlike most of the currently available materials. While this material is not commercially viable at present due to its toxicity and insufficient efficiency, continued research may make commercially viable materials available in the future.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>In addition to the research accomplished, several graduate students and undergraduates were trained in how to conduct research on solar hydrogen materials. Three students who were at least partially supported by the grant graduated with their PhD,&nbsp; one student finished a Master&rsquo;s degree and one is finishing up his PhD.&nbsp; Also, the concepts of solar hydrogen production were incorporated into a course on General Chemistry at Purdue University. This topic a discussion of the main ideas and challenges related to alternative energy to almost 700 undergraduate per semester. There is great interest among undergraduates in energy issues, as they clearly see the needs and potential benefits. In addition, the results of the research have been also been disseminated in several journal articles, and at several conferences.<strong></strong></p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 12/12/2011<br>      Modified by: Michael&nbsp;D&nbsp;Raftery</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ This NSF grant supported research over the past 3 years to make progress in developing a new material or catalyst that can split water using sunlight. This water splitting research program has made a number of interesting findings over the grant period, and published several papers in scientific journals as a result. A number of new semiconducting materials consisting of carbon or nitrogen doped metal oxides were synthesized with increased performance. Several of these materials that were synthesized as fine powders or nanoparticles could produce hydrogen. Our newest material, a mixture of cadmium and indium oxides that was doped with a small amount of carbon is surprisingly efficient in producing hydrogen from water splitting and can do so without a sacrificial reagent, unlike most of the currently available materials. While this material is not commercially viable at present due to its toxicity and insufficient efficiency, continued research may make commercially viable materials available in the future.     In addition to the research accomplished, several graduate students and undergraduates were trained in how to conduct research on solar hydrogen materials. Three students who were at least partially supported by the grant graduated with their PhD,  one student finished a MasterÆs degree and one is finishing up his PhD.  Also, the concepts of solar hydrogen production were incorporated into a course on General Chemistry at Purdue University. This topic a discussion of the main ideas and challenges related to alternative energy to almost 700 undergraduate per semester. There is great interest among undergraduates in energy issues, as they clearly see the needs and potential benefits. In addition, the results of the research have been also been disseminated in several journal articles, and at several conferences.          Last Modified: 12/12/2011       Submitted by: Michael D Raftery]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
