<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Observations and Modeling of Ocean - Ice Sheet Interaction in Jakobshavn and Helheim Ice Fjords, Greenland</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2008</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2014</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>295754.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>389044</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>06090100</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>GEO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>OPP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Office of Polar Programs (OPP)</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>William J. Wiseman, Jr.</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Over the last decade, satellite observations have shown that the floating ice tongues in Greenland's fjords have been retreating and that some outlet glaciers are doubling speed en route to the ocean. The purpose of this project is to improve the understanding of the role of the ocean in such fast, dynamical changes at the margin of the Greenland Ice Sheet, and to quantify the potential for contribution of such change to future global sea level. This will be achieved by making oceanographic and meteorological observations over a period of five years at two key fjords: one on the west coast, Jakobshavn, and the other on the east coast, Helheim. Observations of the hydrography, particularly water temperature, and bathymetry deep into these fjords are critical elements in understanding how ocean waters interact with the margin of the Greenland Ice Sheet. The oceanographic and meteorological observations will be used to develop and validate a coupled ocean- ice sheet computer model that will enable improved understanding of processes that contribute to sea level rise. The broader impacts of the study include the involvement of two graduate students in the computer modeling and fieldwork. The principal investigator and graduate students will also give talks in the Greenland settlements where they will be based, and the PI will continue his collaboration with the Ilullisat Museum near Jakobshavn Fjord.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/26/2008</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/30/2010</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.078</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>0806393</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>David</FirstName>
<LastName>Holland</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>M</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>David M Holland</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>dmh4@nyu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2129983245</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000153243</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/26/2008</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>New York University</Name>
<CityName>NEW YORK</CityName>
<ZipCode>100121019</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2129982121</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>70 WASHINGTON SQUARE S</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>10</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NY10</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>041968306</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>NEW YORK UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>041968306</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[New York University Courant Institute of Mathematical Sciences]]></Name>
<CityName>New York</CityName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<ZipCode>100121110</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[251 Mercer Street]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>10</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NY10</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>5205</Code>
<Text>ARC Rsch Support &amp; Logistics</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>5219</Code>
<Text>ARCSS-Arctic System Science</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>5280</Code>
<Text>ANS-Arctic Natural Sciences</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>0000</Code>
<Text>UNASSIGNED</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1079</Code>
<Text>ARCTIC RESEARCH</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>OTHR</Code>
<Text>OTHER RESEARCH OR EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>02XX</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2008~295754</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2010~93290</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><span style="font-family: Times New Roman; font-size: small;"> <br /></span></p> <p style="margin: 0in 0in 0pt; line-height: normal;"><span style="font-family: Calibri;"><span style="font-size: small;">The greatest uncertainty in future global sea-level rise resides with the fate of the Earths&rsquo; great ice sheets, Greenland and Antarctica.</span><span style="mso-spacerun: yes;"><span style="font-size: small;">&nbsp; </span></span><span style="font-size: small;">Rapid disintegration of these ice sheets is widely believed to be possible through the interaction of the periphery of the ice sheets with deep, warm waters arriving there, and there is a growing body of observational data pointing to this fact.</span><span style="mso-spacerun: yes;"><span style="font-size: small;">&nbsp; </span></span><span style="font-size: small;">This project was focused on understanding the pathway by which deep, warm waters presently arrive along the east and west coast of Greenland, such waters ultimately being a derivative of warm water coming from the North Atlantic Ocean.</span><span style="mso-spacerun: yes;"><span style="font-size: small;">&nbsp; </span></span><span style="font-size: small;">Over the five-year duration of the project, ocean temperature and salinity observations were repeated each summer near the calving fronts of two major Greenland outlet glaciers, Jakobshavn and Helheim.</span><span style="mso-spacerun: yes;"><span style="font-size: small;">&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; </span></span><span style="font-size: small;">These observations, combined with observations taken further afield, by a suite of other international oceanographic projects, have resulted in a better understanding of the pathways of deep, warm waters.</span><span style="mso-spacerun: yes;"><span style="font-size: small;">&nbsp; </span></span><span style="font-size: small;">A key result is that the waters that actually come into contact with the glaciers result from a competition between shallow, cold waters coming from the Arctic Ocean (which pose no threat to the glaciers) and the deep, warm waters coming from the North Atlantic Ocean (which are capable of disintegrating the glaciers).</span><span style="mso-spacerun: yes;"><span style="font-size: small;">&nbsp; </span></span><span style="font-size: small;">The fraction of deep, warm water that finally reaches the glacier fronts is found to vary year by year largely affected by changes in large-scale wind patterns, but also greatly influenced by the presence of shallow sills rising from the seafloor that exist along the flow paths.</span><span style="mso-spacerun: yes;"><span style="font-size: small;">&nbsp;&nbsp; </span></span></span></p> <p><span style="font-family: Times New Roman; font-size: small;"> </span></p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 05/07/2015<br>      Modified by: David&nbsp;M&nbsp;Holland</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Image         </div> <div class="galControls onePhoto" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation onePhoto" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2015/0806393/0806393_10025347_1430843759786_recovery_by_zodiac--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2015/0806393/0806393_10025347_1430843759786_recovery_by_zodiac--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Oceanography at Jakobshavn Glacier"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2015/0806393/0806393_10025347_1430843759786_recovery_by_zodiac--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Oceanography at Jakobshavn Glacier"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">An underwater glider is recovered near the Jakobshavn Glacier.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Denise Holland</div> <d...]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[    The greatest uncertainty in future global sea-level rise resides with the fate of the EarthsÆ great ice sheets, Greenland and Antarctica.  Rapid disintegration of these ice sheets is widely believed to be possible through the interaction of the periphery of the ice sheets with deep, warm waters arriving there, and there is a growing body of observational data pointing to this fact.  This project was focused on understanding the pathway by which deep, warm waters presently arrive along the east and west coast of Greenland, such waters ultimately being a derivative of warm water coming from the North Atlantic Ocean.  Over the five-year duration of the project, ocean temperature and salinity observations were repeated each summer near the calving fronts of two major Greenland outlet glaciers, Jakobshavn and Helheim.    These observations, combined with observations taken further afield, by a suite of other international oceanographic projects, have resulted in a better understanding of the pathways of deep, warm waters.  A key result is that the waters that actually come into contact with the glaciers result from a competition between shallow, cold waters coming from the Arctic Ocean (which pose no threat to the glaciers) and the deep, warm waters coming from the North Atlantic Ocean (which are capable of disintegrating the glaciers).  The fraction of deep, warm water that finally reaches the glacier fronts is found to vary year by year largely affected by changes in large-scale wind patterns, but also greatly influenced by the presence of shallow sills rising from the seafloor that exist along the flow paths.             Last Modified: 05/07/2015       Submitted by: David M Holland]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
