<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Strategies towards one pot synthesis of 3D core-shell superstructures classified as mechanically strong aerogels</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2008</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2011</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>365000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>365000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03090005</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CHE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Chemistry</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Timothy Patten</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>tpatten@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927196</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This award in the Inorganic, Bioinorganic and Organometallic Chemistry program supports research by Professor Nicholas Leventis at the University of Missouri-Rolla to simplify processing of polymer crosslinked aerogels by deconvoluting the crosslinking chemistry from the gelation chemistry. The surface of the skeletal nanoparticles will be decorated with bi-dentate free radical initiators rendering the free-radical crosslinking chemistry  independent of the gelation chemistry, so that all reagents will be included together from the beginning, shortening the length of the whole process. In a second aim, the surface of the silica nanoparticles will be decorated with strained olefins (e.g., norbornene) and Ring Opening Metathesis Polymerization (ROMP) will be used to crosslink particles together with norbornene, norbornadiene or dicyclopentadiene, which will be included in the sol. Crosslinking of these types will be relevant not only to engineering plastics (e.g., polyimides and polycarbonates), but also to biocompatible (e.g., polyvinylpyrrolidone) and biodegradable (e.g., soybean oil) polymers for possible medical and disposable applications.  All materials will be prepared by systematically varying all preparation parameters using a statistical Design-of-Experiments approach, and will be characterized exhaustively by chemical and physical methods. Mechanical characterization, modeling and simulations will be conducted by Professor Hongbing Lu at the Mechanical and Aerospace Engineering Department of Oklahoma State University via a no-cost collaboration. &lt;br/&gt; &lt;br/&gt;This project will create an interdisciplinary intellectual environment for the education of graduate and undergraduate students in materials chemistry. Both PIs have worked with undergraduate minority and female students and actively participate in programs such as OURE (Opportunities for Undergraduate Research Experience) designed to increase the participation of women and minorities in sciences and engineering. Since the project addresses immediate needs for strong lightweight materials, short-term benefits are envisioned through commercialization of the technology, and through applications in the National Defense, Homeland Security, and the Space Program.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/30/2008</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/12/2010</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>0809562</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Nicholas</FirstName>
<LastName>Leventis</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Nicholas Leventis</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>leventis@mst.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5733414391</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000318920</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/30/2008</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Chariklia</FirstName>
<LastName>Sotiriou-Leventis</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Chariklia Sotiriou-Leventis</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>cslevent@mst.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5733414353</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000331400</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/30/2008</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Missouri University of Science and Technology</Name>
<CityName>Rolla</CityName>
<ZipCode>654096506</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5733414134</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>300 W 12th Street</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[202 Centennial Hall]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Missouri</StateName>
<StateCode>MO</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>08</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MO08</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>804883767</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF MISSOURI SYSTEM</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>006326904</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Missouri University of Science and Technology]]></Name>
<CityName>Rolla</CityName>
<StateCode>MO</StateCode>
<ZipCode>654096506</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[300 W 12th Street]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Missouri</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>08</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MO08</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1968</Code>
<Text>PHYSICAL INORGANIC</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7237</Code>
<Text>NANO NON-SOLIC SCI &amp; ENG AWD</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9146</Code>
<Text>MANUFACTURING BASE RESEARCH</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>MANU</Code>
<Text>MANUFACTURING</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0108</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0109</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0110</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2008~127000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2009~117000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2010~121000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><strong>&nbsp;&nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp;Background:</strong>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; As highly porous (&gt;90%), low-density (&lt;0.5 g cm<sup>-3</sup>) solids, aerogels (typically made of silica) are pursued for useful macroscopic properties such as very low thermal conductivity, low dielectric constant, and very high acoustic impedance. Silica aerogels, however, are fragile materials and thereby of limited use. The problem was traced to the weak interparticle &ldquo;necks&rdquo; on their skeletal framework and was resolved by casting a thin conformal polymer coating over their entire internal porous surface, connecting covalently (crosslinking) skeletal silica nanoparticles (Leventis, N. &ldquo;Nano-Engineering Strong Silica Aerogels,&rdquo; <em>Acc. Chem. Res. </em><strong>2007</strong>, <em>40</em>, 874-884). The new material combines the ultimate specific compressive strength of carbon fiber reinforced epoxy with the thermal conductivity of glass wool. Not only traditional aerogel applications, as in high performance thermal and acoustic insulation, gas filters and industrial absorbers, are now feasible, but also new applications unthinkable of aerogels before, as in lightweight ballistic protection, are now within reach (Leventis, N.; Lu, H. &ldquo;Polymer Crosslinked Aerogels,&rdquo; in <em>Aerogels Handbook, Advanced in Sol-Gel Derived Materials and Technologies</em>, Aegerter, M. A.; Leventis, N.; Koebel M. M. Eds., Springer: New York, NY, 2011, pp 251-285).</p> <p><strong>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; Objective:</strong> The objective of CHE-0809562 was to simplify the synthesis of polymer crosslinked aerogels by deconvoluting crosslinking from gelation by decorating the surface of silica nanoparticles with: (a) a bi-dentate free radical initiator, so that crosslinking (a free radical process) and gelation (an ionic process) could co-exist in one pot; or, (b) a strained olefin (e.g., norbornene) that could be zipped by Ring Opening Metathesis Polymerization (ROMP).</p> <p>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; <strong>Intellectual Merit:</strong> While that objective was completed successfully, CHE-0809562 pointed also to the technological significance of multifunctional porous <em>all-organic </em>3D assemblies of nanoparticles. Along this line, it was also realized that since the exceptional mechanical properties of crosslinked silica aerogels are ultimately attributed to the conformal polymer coating, purely polymeric aerogels with the same nanostructure and interparticle connectivity should have similar properties. Thus, we developed specific design rules calling for molecular crosslinking of multifunctional monomers; that induces early phase separation of &ldquo;live&rdquo; nanoparticles, which get crosslinked through their surface functional groups to a 3D network that resists collapse and can be dried into aerogels. Challenging that design rule further, phase separation of virtual nanoparticles is induced before gelation by employing eco-friendly emulsion polymerization in water. Our hypothesis was confirmed by the synthesis of a diverse variety of all-polymeric aerogels including polyureas, polyimides, polyamides (Kevlar-like), polybenzoxazines, graphitizable polyacrylonitrile and ROMP-derived polymers. Along the way, it was realized that conventional methods for bulk polymer synthesis are not necessarily the most efficient for robust porous nanostructured polymers and new synthetic methods were developed. It was also found that polymeric nanostructured matter may have different nanomorphologies (fibers vs. particles), but all consist of 3-5 nm in diameter primary particles. Entangled nanofibers are more desirable, because they yield much more robust bulk materials. The conditions under which primary particles &ldquo;decide&rdquo; to get organized into fibers vs. globules are currently investigated.</p> <p><strong>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; Broader I...]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[       Background:      As highly porous (&gt;90%), low-density (&lt;0.5 g cm-3) solids, aerogels (typically made of silica) are pursued for useful macroscopic properties such as very low thermal conductivity, low dielectric constant, and very high acoustic impedance. Silica aerogels, however, are fragile materials and thereby of limited use. The problem was traced to the weak interparticle "necks" on their skeletal framework and was resolved by casting a thin conformal polymer coating over their entire internal porous surface, connecting covalently (crosslinking) skeletal silica nanoparticles (Leventis, N. "Nano-Engineering Strong Silica Aerogels," Acc. Chem. Res. 2007, 40, 874-884). The new material combines the ultimate specific compressive strength of carbon fiber reinforced epoxy with the thermal conductivity of glass wool. Not only traditional aerogel applications, as in high performance thermal and acoustic insulation, gas filters and industrial absorbers, are now feasible, but also new applications unthinkable of aerogels before, as in lightweight ballistic protection, are now within reach (Leventis, N.; Lu, H. "Polymer Crosslinked Aerogels," in Aerogels Handbook, Advanced in Sol-Gel Derived Materials and Technologies, Aegerter, M. A.; Leventis, N.; Koebel M. M. Eds., Springer: New York, NY, 2011, pp 251-285).        Objective: The objective of CHE-0809562 was to simplify the synthesis of polymer crosslinked aerogels by deconvoluting crosslinking from gelation by decorating the surface of silica nanoparticles with: (a) a bi-dentate free radical initiator, so that crosslinking (a free radical process) and gelation (an ionic process) could co-exist in one pot; or, (b) a strained olefin (e.g., norbornene) that could be zipped by Ring Opening Metathesis Polymerization (ROMP).        Intellectual Merit: While that objective was completed successfully, CHE-0809562 pointed also to the technological significance of multifunctional porous all-organic 3D assemblies of nanoparticles. Along this line, it was also realized that since the exceptional mechanical properties of crosslinked silica aerogels are ultimately attributed to the conformal polymer coating, purely polymeric aerogels with the same nanostructure and interparticle connectivity should have similar properties. Thus, we developed specific design rules calling for molecular crosslinking of multifunctional monomers; that induces early phase separation of "live" nanoparticles, which get crosslinked through their surface functional groups to a 3D network that resists collapse and can be dried into aerogels. Challenging that design rule further, phase separation of virtual nanoparticles is induced before gelation by employing eco-friendly emulsion polymerization in water. Our hypothesis was confirmed by the synthesis of a diverse variety of all-polymeric aerogels including polyureas, polyimides, polyamides (Kevlar-like), polybenzoxazines, graphitizable polyacrylonitrile and ROMP-derived polymers. Along the way, it was realized that conventional methods for bulk polymer synthesis are not necessarily the most efficient for robust porous nanostructured polymers and new synthetic methods were developed. It was also found that polymeric nanostructured matter may have different nanomorphologies (fibers vs. particles), but all consist of 3-5 nm in diameter primary particles. Entangled nanofibers are more desirable, because they yield much more robust bulk materials. The conditions under which primary particles "decide" to get organized into fibers vs. globules are currently investigated.        Broader Impact: With chemistry as the point of departure, the most important outcome of CHE-0809562 has been the creation of an interdisciplinary educational environment. Our recent graduates are employed in all sections of the economy: industry, government, academia in the U.S. and abroad. In addition to graduate student training, both PIs are actively involved in programs such as OURE (O...]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
