<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Collaborative Research: Dynamics at the Base of a Pseudotachylyte-bearing Fault System</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/15/2008</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2012</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>209999.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>209999</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>06030103</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>GEO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>EAR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Earth Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Stephen Harlan</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>sharlan@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927707</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>&lt;br/&gt;A concerted effort through EarthScope is currently underway to better understand seismicity along the San Andreas Fault, which poses serious threats to society from large-magnitude earthquakes. The San Andreas Fault Observatory at Depth features an instrumented drill hole, allowing characterization of the rocks, fluids, kinematics, and stress orientations and magnitudes within the fault zone to depths of approximately 3 km. These studies are designed partly to investigate the strength of the San Andreas Fault, which is critical for seismic forecasting. In conjunction with these studies it is important that we locate and study appropriate exhumed examples of similar faults at the surface today.  One of the very few surface occurrences of an analog for the San Andreas Fault is the Norumbega Fault System (NFS), which cuts across the entire State of Maine and is the field site for this study.  Through the NFS study we hope to clarify the value of near-surface stress measurements on the San Andreas Fault as indicators for the strength of the fault. This work is intended to support the dissertation of a female PhD student, and several undergraduate student theses. Our close cooperation with the Maine Geological Survey, and our involvement with K-12 Earth Science teachers in Maine, lends additional societal relevance to the work.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Due to the large elastic moduli of solid Earth materials elastic stresses are transmitted over great distances and depths within the Earth. For this reason, the stress orientations and magnitudes measured near Earths surface provide only a partial picture of the state of stress on active faults. For a more complete picture, we must understand the state of stress on faults at greater depths, particularly near the frictional-to-viscous transition where the strongest part of the crust occurs.   For this reason we are focusing on the deeply exhumed NFS.  To provide relatively tight constraints on the stress tensor the field locality should contain irrefutable evidence for coseismic rupture (pseudotachylyte), and be characterized by: (a) tightly constrained kinematic boundary conditions, (b) microstructures amenable to estimates of differential stress and mean kinematic vorticity, and (c) lithological (rheological) heterogeneity providing natural variability in the stress and vorticity estimates. In such a system, 3D numerical experiments can provide best-fit solutions for the field-derived stress and vorticity estimates, and in doing so solve for the principal and Cartesian stresses. Our work in the NFS involves field mapping, microstructural analysis using optical and electron-beam techniques, and 3D numerical modeling that is tightly constrained by the field-derived data. Our primary aims are to: (a) systematically evaluate the microstructural variation across the strain gradient in the fault zone mylonites, (b) use microstructural measurements to calculate temperatures, differential stresses and mean kinematic vorticity numbers for numerous samples across the field area, (c) use these calculated values and 3D numerical experiments to help constrain the stress tensor at the time when this mylonite zone was overlain by a seismically active fault, and (d) extend our numerical modeling to the surface to explore how kinematic boundary conditions and stresses at depth influence active faults above. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/24/2008</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>04/15/2010</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.050</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>0810039</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Scott</FirstName>
<LastName>Johnson</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>E</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Scott E Johnson</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>johnsons@maine.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2075812142</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000473291</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/24/2008</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Peter</FirstName>
<LastName>Koons</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>O</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Peter O Koons</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>Peter.Koons@maine.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2075812158</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000087531</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/24/2008</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Maine</Name>
<CityName>ORONO</CityName>
<ZipCode>044695717</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2075811484</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>5717 Corbett Hall</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Maine</StateName>
<StateCode>ME</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>ME02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>186875787</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF MAINE SYSTEM</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>071750426</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Maine]]></Name>
<CityName>ORONO</CityName>
<StateCode>ME</StateCode>
<ZipCode>044695717</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[5717 Corbett Hall]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Maine</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>ME02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<FoaInformation>
<Code>0000099</Code>
<Name>Other Applications NEC</Name>
</FoaInformation>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1572</Code>
<Text>Tectonics</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>0000</Code>
<Text>UNASSIGNED</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>OTHR</Code>
<Text>OTHER RESEARCH OR EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0108</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0109</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0110</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2008~61332</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2009~78284</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2010~70383</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><span style="white-space: pre;"> </span>Seismogenic fault systems are important targets for scientific study because of the hazards that they present for humans as well as the fact that they are rich sources of information about how rocks deform and how deformation localizes over long-term time scales. &nbsp;This project was focused on characterizing a fault (Sandhill Corner shear zone, Maine, USA) exhumed from depths of ~10-15km, a zone in the crust where the style of deformation changes with depth (from frictional to viscous) and varies over time with the seismic cycle. &nbsp;The aim of the study was to collect micro-scale data from a large suite of samples to evaluate how they change across and along the fault. &nbsp; The major findings that result from this project focus on efforts to (1) evaluate the methods for measuring the kinematic vorticity number, (2) to characterize quartz CPO patterns, (3) to identify the structures that resulted from earthquake-related deformation, and (4) to develop a description of the across-strike architecture of the fault. &nbsp;</p> <p style="padding-left: 30px;"><br />1. &nbsp; The kinematic vorticity number (Wk), a number that reflects the amount of shearing during deformation, can be calculated from the microstructures preserved in the rock. &nbsp; Using samples collected across the shear zone, the different methods for calculating Wk were evaluated. &nbsp;One method produced a consistently lower number than another. &nbsp;Hypotheses for describing the reason for this difference were investigated using a new numerical technique. &nbsp;This research is an important contribution for the geologic community because it quantitatively addresses the longstanding problem of why different methods may produce different Wk values.&nbsp;</p> <p style="padding-left: 30px;"><br />2. &nbsp;Quartz deforms viscously in a predictable way causing the orientations of the individual mineral grains to line up and create recognizable patterns when their c-axes are plotted. &nbsp;These crystallographic preferred orientation (CPO) patterns preserve a lot of information about the conditions of deformation, but it is important to identify which stage of deformation the patterns preserve, whether early or late. &nbsp;CPO patterns from inside and outside the shear zone were compared in order to identify the host rock patterns that represented an earlier an unrelated period of deformation from the new sheared fabric formed during fault zone formation. This research showed that the inherited host rock fabric persists in the shear zone even with significant shearing and that the inherited fabric must be considered when interpreting CPO patterns from other fault zones. &nbsp; This research is of importance because inherited fabrics complicate the interpretation CPO patterns, but few studies have actually documented in detail their persistence in CPO patterns from major shear zones.</p> <p style="padding-left: 30px;"><br />3. &nbsp; Within a fault zone, slip during an earthquake causes fracturing, rapid offset along the fracture, and flash melting of the rock powder along the fracture surface. &nbsp;The thin vein of melted rock instantaneously quenches to glass forming a structure known as a pseudotachylyte. &nbsp;In the time between earthquakes at depths of ~10-15km, the glass in these veins is replaced by minerals and then deformed. The micro-scale differences among pseudotachylyte veins at different stages of recrystallization and deformation were documented to create a four-stage conceptual model for how this processes occurred. &nbsp;Based on these observations, a list of criteria for the identification of deformed pseudotachylyte veins in fault zones was compiled; such a comprehensive list has not been previously published. &nbsp;This is of importance because deformed pseudotachylyte is difficult to identify in the field and because it is probable that ...]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[  Seismogenic fault systems are important targets for scientific study because of the hazards that they present for humans as well as the fact that they are rich sources of information about how rocks deform and how deformation localizes over long-term time scales.  This project was focused on characterizing a fault (Sandhill Corner shear zone, Maine, USA) exhumed from depths of ~10-15km, a zone in the crust where the style of deformation changes with depth (from frictional to viscous) and varies over time with the seismic cycle.  The aim of the study was to collect micro-scale data from a large suite of samples to evaluate how they change across and along the fault.   The major findings that result from this project focus on efforts to (1) evaluate the methods for measuring the kinematic vorticity number, (2) to characterize quartz CPO patterns, (3) to identify the structures that resulted from earthquake-related deformation, and (4) to develop a description of the across-strike architecture of the fault.    1.   The kinematic vorticity number (Wk), a number that reflects the amount of shearing during deformation, can be calculated from the microstructures preserved in the rock.   Using samples collected across the shear zone, the different methods for calculating Wk were evaluated.  One method produced a consistently lower number than another.  Hypotheses for describing the reason for this difference were investigated using a new numerical technique.  This research is an important contribution for the geologic community because it quantitatively addresses the longstanding problem of why different methods may produce different Wk values.   2.  Quartz deforms viscously in a predictable way causing the orientations of the individual mineral grains to line up and create recognizable patterns when their c-axes are plotted.  These crystallographic preferred orientation (CPO) patterns preserve a lot of information about the conditions of deformation, but it is important to identify which stage of deformation the patterns preserve, whether early or late.  CPO patterns from inside and outside the shear zone were compared in order to identify the host rock patterns that represented an earlier an unrelated period of deformation from the new sheared fabric formed during fault zone formation. This research showed that the inherited host rock fabric persists in the shear zone even with significant shearing and that the inherited fabric must be considered when interpreting CPO patterns from other fault zones.   This research is of importance because inherited fabrics complicate the interpretation CPO patterns, but few studies have actually documented in detail their persistence in CPO patterns from major shear zones.  3.   Within a fault zone, slip during an earthquake causes fracturing, rapid offset along the fracture, and flash melting of the rock powder along the fracture surface.  The thin vein of melted rock instantaneously quenches to glass forming a structure known as a pseudotachylyte.  In the time between earthquakes at depths of ~10-15km, the glass in these veins is replaced by minerals and then deformed. The micro-scale differences among pseudotachylyte veins at different stages of recrystallization and deformation were documented to create a four-stage conceptual model for how this processes occurred.  Based on these observations, a list of criteria for the identification of deformed pseudotachylyte veins in fault zones was compiled; such a comprehensive list has not been previously published.  This is of importance because deformed pseudotachylyte is difficult to identify in the field and because it is probable that many localities containing deformed pseudotachylyte have since gone unrecognized.   4.  Finally, maps displaying the spatial distribution of observations and data were made and used to develop an architecture of a fault zone at 10-15km depth that includes a shear zone core rich in deformed pseudotachylyte, an inner...]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
