<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>How Does RNase III Regulate Antibiotic Production in Streptomyces Coelicolor?</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2008</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2012</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>479503.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>585414</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>08070100</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>BIO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>MCB</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Molecular and Cellular Bioscience</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Arcady Mushegian</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>amushegi@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032928528</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Nearly 70% of all antibiotics used in clinical and veterinary medicine are synthesized by members of the bacterial genus, Streptomyces. Ribonuclease III (RNase III) is a double strand specific endoribonuclease distributed widely in bacteria and eukaryotes. Mutations in the RNase III gene in Streptomyces coelicolor reduce or abolish synthesis of all four antibiotics normally produced by the organism. Thus, RNase III is a global regulator of antibiotic synthesis in S. coelicolor. RNA immunoprecipitation followed by microarray analysis (a RIP-Chip approach) will be used to examine the mechanism of RNase III regulation of antibiotic production. Antibody to a mutant form of RNase III will be used to precipitate complexes formed between the enzyme and its target RNAs. RNAs will be extracted from the immunoprecipitates and used to synthesize complementary DNAs (cDNAs). The cDNAs will be used in microarray studies to identify RNAs that are enriched in the immunoprecipitates. RNAs that may be involved in the regulation of gene expression, e.g. mRNAs for RNA polymerase sigma factors, repressors, activators, etc. will be studied further. Cleavage assays will verify that these mRNAs are substrates for RNase III. The corresponding genes will be disrupted and the effects of disruption on antibiotic production assessed. In this way, genes whose products are substrates for RNase III and which regulate antibiotic production in S. coelicolor will be identified.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Many of the planned experiments will lend themselves to performance by undergraduates and undergraduate researchers, especially minority and women undergraduates, will be recruited to the project. The research will also involve collaboration between the applicant lab and a lab in the UK, furthering the NSF goal of fostering international research collaborations. The project will also provide an excellent training opportunity for the postdoctoral fellows associated with it. Results of the research will be disseminated to the scientific community extending our understanding of the mechanisms involved in the production of useful antibiotics.&lt;br/&gt;</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/27/2008</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>04/18/2012</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.074</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>0817177</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>George</FirstName>
<LastName>Jones</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>H</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>George H Jones</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>george.h.jones@emory.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>4047270712</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000105986</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/27/2008</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Emory University</Name>
<CityName>Atlanta</CityName>
<ZipCode>303224250</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>4047272503</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1599 Clifton Rd NE, 4th Floor</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[1599-001-1BA]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Georgia</StateName>
<StateCode>GA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>GA05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>066469933</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>EMORY UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>066469933</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Emory University]]></Name>
<CityName>Atlanta</CityName>
<StateCode>GA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>303224250</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[1599 Clifton Rd NE, 4th Floor]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Georgia</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>GA05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1112</Code>
<Text>Genetic Mechanisms</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1112</Code>
<Text>GENES AND GENOME SYSTEMS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1156</Code>
<Text>MICROBIAL GENETICS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1228</Code>
<Text>MINORITY INVOLVEMENT -- BIO</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7465</Code>
<Text>NANOSCALE BIO CORE</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9178</Code>
<Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9183</Code>
<Text>GENERAL FOUNDATIONS OF BIOTECHNOLOGY</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9251</Code>
<Text>REU SUPP-Res Exp for Ugrd Supp</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>BIOT</Code>
<Text>BIOTECHNOLOGY</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>SMET</Code>
<Text>SCIENCE, MATH, ENG &amp; TECH EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0108</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0109</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0110</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0111</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0112</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2008~159503</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2009~170011</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2010~160000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2011~38580</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2012~57320</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Nearly 75% of all antibiotics used in clinical and veterinary medicine worldwide are produced by soil-dwelling members of the bacterial genus, <em>Streptomyces</em>. These organisms make antibiotics as natural products during the normal course of their growth and development. While much information has been obtained in recent years relating to the mechanism and regulation of antibiotic biosynthesis, many important questions remain unanswered. Among these questions are:&nbsp; 1) what are the molecular signals that initiate antibiotic synthesis in producing organisms? 2) how are the various regulatory mechanisms that are known to affect antibiotic production coordinated by the cell? 3) how do organisms that are capable of producing more than one antibiotic coordinate those production pathways? 4) why do bacteria (and other organisms) produce antibiotics? 5) how did antibiotic production evolve?</p> <p>We are examining these and related questions in two model streptomycetes, <em>Streptomyces coelicolor,</em> which makes four different antibiotics<em> </em>and <em>Streptomyces antibioticus</em>. <em>S. antibioticus</em> produces actinomycin, an antibiotic that is used in the treatment of certain cancers.&nbsp; We are especially interested in the relationship between RNA degradation and antibiotic synthesis.&nbsp; In particular, our work follows on the discovery several years ago that knocking out the gene for an enzyme that degrades ribonucleic acid (the ribonuclease RNase III) diminishes production of all four of the antibiotics produced by <em>S. coelicolor</em>.&nbsp; The research project supported by the NSF over the last four years has been designed to identify the intracellular targets for RNase III regulation of antibiotic production in <em>S. coelicolor</em>.</p> <p>To explore this question we have exploited an emerging experimental technique known as RNA-seq.&nbsp; This technique involves the use of DNA sequencing technologies to determine the sequences of small DNA molecules that are copies of RNA molecules.&nbsp; The technique thus allows the simultaneous identification of all of the RNA molecules in a given preparation subjected to RNA-seq and the determination of the relative amounts of each RNA molecule in that preparation.&nbsp; Applying the technique to <em>S. coelicolor</em> RNAs allowed the identification of ca. 800 RNA species that bind specifically to RNase III.&nbsp; We believe that among those RNAs are the species that are targets for RNase III, viz. the RNA species responsible for the ability of RNase III to regulate antibiotic production in <em>S. coelicolor</em>.&nbsp; We also determined that knocking out the RNase III gene in <em>S. antibioticus</em> abolished actinomycin production.&nbsp; Thus, it appears that RNase III is a general regulator of antibiotic production in the bacterial genus <em>Streptomyces</em>.</p> <p>In other experiments we demonstrated that RNase III is involved in the regulation of the expression of a very important pair of genes in <em>S. coelicolor</em>, viz. the gene for a protein component of ribosomes, which are the sites of protein synthesis in cells, and the gene for another important ribonuclease, the enzyme polynucleotide phosphorylase.&nbsp; Moreover, we demonstrated that the activity of polynucleotide phosphorylase is regulated by the small molecule, guanosine tetraphosphate.&nbsp; This mode of regulation appears to be unique to members of the genus <em>Streptomyces</em> and some related organisms.</p> <p>In addition to the research accomplishments the NSF-funded project provided an excellent opportunity for the training of undergraduate researchers.&nbsp; A total of five undergraduates worked on the project during its course, including one from a sister institution, Morehouse College.&nbsp; These students not only received training in the various experimental techniques required for the research but they were ...]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Nearly 75% of all antibiotics used in clinical and veterinary medicine worldwide are produced by soil-dwelling members of the bacterial genus, Streptomyces. These organisms make antibiotics as natural products during the normal course of their growth and development. While much information has been obtained in recent years relating to the mechanism and regulation of antibiotic biosynthesis, many important questions remain unanswered. Among these questions are:  1) what are the molecular signals that initiate antibiotic synthesis in producing organisms? 2) how are the various regulatory mechanisms that are known to affect antibiotic production coordinated by the cell? 3) how do organisms that are capable of producing more than one antibiotic coordinate those production pathways? 4) why do bacteria (and other organisms) produce antibiotics? 5) how did antibiotic production evolve?  We are examining these and related questions in two model streptomycetes, Streptomyces coelicolor, which makes four different antibiotics and Streptomyces antibioticus. S. antibioticus produces actinomycin, an antibiotic that is used in the treatment of certain cancers.  We are especially interested in the relationship between RNA degradation and antibiotic synthesis.  In particular, our work follows on the discovery several years ago that knocking out the gene for an enzyme that degrades ribonucleic acid (the ribonuclease RNase III) diminishes production of all four of the antibiotics produced by S. coelicolor.  The research project supported by the NSF over the last four years has been designed to identify the intracellular targets for RNase III regulation of antibiotic production in S. coelicolor.  To explore this question we have exploited an emerging experimental technique known as RNA-seq.  This technique involves the use of DNA sequencing technologies to determine the sequences of small DNA molecules that are copies of RNA molecules.  The technique thus allows the simultaneous identification of all of the RNA molecules in a given preparation subjected to RNA-seq and the determination of the relative amounts of each RNA molecule in that preparation.  Applying the technique to S. coelicolor RNAs allowed the identification of ca. 800 RNA species that bind specifically to RNase III.  We believe that among those RNAs are the species that are targets for RNase III, viz. the RNA species responsible for the ability of RNase III to regulate antibiotic production in S. coelicolor.  We also determined that knocking out the RNase III gene in S. antibioticus abolished actinomycin production.  Thus, it appears that RNase III is a general regulator of antibiotic production in the bacterial genus Streptomyces.  In other experiments we demonstrated that RNase III is involved in the regulation of the expression of a very important pair of genes in S. coelicolor, viz. the gene for a protein component of ribosomes, which are the sites of protein synthesis in cells, and the gene for another important ribonuclease, the enzyme polynucleotide phosphorylase.  Moreover, we demonstrated that the activity of polynucleotide phosphorylase is regulated by the small molecule, guanosine tetraphosphate.  This mode of regulation appears to be unique to members of the genus Streptomyces and some related organisms.  In addition to the research accomplishments the NSF-funded project provided an excellent opportunity for the training of undergraduate researchers.  A total of five undergraduates worked on the project during its course, including one from a sister institution, Morehouse College.  These students not only received training in the various experimental techniques required for the research but they were also schooled in principles of research ethics, interpretation an analysis of original literature and the presentation of research results.       Last Modified: 08/13/2012       Submitted by: George H Jones]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
