<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Center for Magnetic Self-Organization in Laboratory and Astrophysical Plasmas</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2008</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2016</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>11760000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>15538000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Cooperative Agreement</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03010800</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>PHY</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Physics</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Jean Allen</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>jcallen@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032928783</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The goal of the Center for Magnetic Self-Organization in Laboratory and Astrophysical Plasmas (CMSO), initiated in September, 2003, is to unite laboratory and astrophysical plasma scientists to advance critical plasma physics topics common to both fields. The sense of the CMSO research mission is captured by two large questions: Why is the universe magnetized? How do magnetic fields affect the structure of plasmas? CMSO encompasses and is organized around four, coupled processes: magnetic reconnection, dynamo effects, momentum transport, and magnetic turbulence.  The heart of the effort is focused on answering fundamental questions in each area through experiment, computation, and theory, and applying the understanding to important astrophysical problems. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;These physics problems are addressed by a team of scientists from seven institutions that collectively provide unique tools (seven experiments and an arsenal of computational resources) and great breadth of expertise from the lab to astrophysics, and from experiment to theory to computation. The member institutions are the University of Wisconsin, Princeton University and the Princeton Plasma Physics Laboratory, Los Alamos National Laboratory, the University of Chicago, the University of New Hampshire, Swarthmore College, and Science Applications International Corporation. Participating experiments include three toroidal plasma experiments that exhibit many features of self-organization: the MST reversed field pinch (Wisconsin) and two merging plasma experiments, MRX (Princeton) and SSX (Swarthmore); two linear experiments for line-tied reconnection: RSX (Los Alamos), RWX (Wisconsin); and two liquid metal experiments: the MRI experiment (Princeton) for studying the magnetorotational instability, and the Madison Dynamo Experiment. National laboratory participation (Los Alamos, Princeton) will be supported by DOE, as is the experimental infrastructure; thus, CMSO is very much a partnership between NSF and DOE. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The educational outreach program is based on The Wonders of Physics lecture-demonstration program through the University of Wisconsin.  Under the auspices of this program CMSO representatives make over 100 presentations per year reaching an audience of school children and the general public of 10,000 persons per year.  In the past year, presentations were made to 2000 African American children through specially targeted presentations and extensively to Native Americans and rural communities.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>09/04/2008</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/13/2015</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>CoopAgrmnt</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>0821899</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Ellen</FirstName>
<LastName>Zweibel</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>G</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Ellen G Zweibel</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>zweibel@astro.wisc.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6082627921</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000196751</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/13/2015</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Ellen</FirstName>
<LastName>Zweibel</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>G</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Ellen G Zweibel</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>zweibel@astro.wisc.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6082627921</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000196751</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/04/2008</StartDate>
<EndDate>04/27/2009</EndDate>
<RoleCode>Former Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Paul</FirstName>
<LastName>Terry</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>W</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Paul W Terry</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>pwterry@wisc.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6082630487</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000426007</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/27/2009</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Stewart</FirstName>
<LastName>Prager</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>C</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Stewart C Prager</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>scprager@facstaff.wisc.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6082627768</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000160653</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/04/2008</StartDate>
<EndDate>04/27/2009</EndDate>
<RoleCode>Former Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Masaaki</FirstName>
<LastName>Yamada</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Masaaki Yamada</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>MYAMADA@PPPL.GOV</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6092432566</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000303071</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/04/2008</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Fausto</FirstName>
<LastName>Cattaneo</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Fausto Cattaneo</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>cattaneo@flash.uchicago.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>3127020562</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000417926</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/04/2008</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Hantao</FirstName>
<LastName>Ji</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Hantao Ji</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>hji@pppl.gov</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6092432162</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000339095</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/04/2008</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Wisconsin-Madison</Name>
<CityName>MADISON</CityName>
<ZipCode>537151218</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6082623822</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>21 North Park Street</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[Suite 6401]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Wisconsin</StateName>
<StateCode>WI</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>WI02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>161202122</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF WISCONSIN SYSTEM</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>041188822</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Wisconsin-Madison]]></Name>
<CityName>MADISON</CityName>
<StateCode>WI</StateCode>
<ZipCode>537151218</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[21 North Park Street]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Wisconsin</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>WI02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<FoaInformation>
<Code>0000099</Code>
<Name>Other Applications NEC</Name>
</FoaInformation>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1646</Code>
<Text>PHYSICS FRONTIER CENTER</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>0000</Code>
<Text>UNASSIGNED</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1062</Code>
<Text>BASIC PLASMA SCIENCE &amp; ENGINEERING</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1646</Code>
<Text>PHYSICS FRONTIER CENTER</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>OTHR</Code>
<Text>OTHER RESEARCH OR EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0108</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0109</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0110</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0111</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0112</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0113</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0114</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0115</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2008~2250000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2009~2250000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2010~2420000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2011~2420000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2012~2420000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2013~2178000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~1200000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2015~400000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><strong>Project Outcomes Report for NSF 0821899</strong></p> <p>This award funded the Center for Magnetic Self-Organization in Laboratory and Astrophysical Plasmas (CMSO) from 2008 &ndash; 2014 with a two-year supplement from 2014-2016 as an NSF Physics Frontiers Center.</p> <p>CMSO brought together researchers from U. Wisconsin, U. Chicago, Princeton Univ. and the Princeton Plasma Physics Lab, Swarthmore College, U. New Hampshire, and Los Alamos National Laboratory to study basic plasma physics problems that arise in the study of laboratory and natural plasmas. Magnetic Self-Organization &ndash; the tendency for magnetized systems to evolve to an energetically favorable state, was the umbrella theme, and much of the research was motivated by two overarching questions:</p> <p>How is the universe magnetized?</p> <p>How do magnetic fields affect the motions of plasmas?</p> <p>Some of the main tangible research outcomes of CMSO include three major experiments, one to study magnetic field generation (MPDX) and two to study magnetic reconnection (TREX and FLARE); CMSO did not fund these experiments but laid much of the intellectual groundwork for them. Major collaborations with NASA space experiments that study magnetic reconnection and solar wind turbulence were initiated and strengthened along the same lines. This work is having a major impact on our understanding of magnetic explosions across the Universe, solar activity, how stars are built, and how black holes grow over cosmic time. &nbsp;CMSO sponsored scientific conferences, workshops, and winter schools both for the membership and for the scientific community. CMSO researchers gave literally hundreds of invited talks at scientific institutions and scientific meetings, and wrote hundreds of papers.&nbsp;</p> <p>CMSO also had a public mission - senior staff, students, and outreach professionals reached K12 students and the general public throughout the US with demonstrations in plasma science and general physics.</p> <p>Most of the CMSO budget funded people &ndash; undergraduate students, graduate students, and postdoctoral researchers, many of who went on to permanent positions in plasma science and astronomy at universities, government labs, and in the private sector. Several senior investigators were selected as Fellows of the American Physical Society, and two won the APS Maxwell Prize for Plasma Physics.</p> <p>The story of one particular scientist exemplifies the impact of CMSO on research, education, and human resources. A U. Wisconsin Astronomy graduate student supported by CMSO wanted to learn computational physics, and wrote his thesis on the MRX experiment at the Princeton Plasma Physics Lab under the joint supervision of a U. Wisconsin astronomer and an engineering physicist, both CMSO members. Intriguing effects caused by the toroidal shape of MRX led him to wonder whether the same effects might occur in reconnection of the solar magnetic field. A senior CMSO faculty member brought him together with a Harvard solar physicist, who found the idea very promising, hired him into a postdoctoral position at Harvard and later supported his appointment as a permanent staff member, where he teaches plasma astrophysics to graduate students and works with summer undergraduate research interns. Recently he has come full circle, collaborating with Princeton Plasma Lab scientists to perform computer simulations of a new experiment. This integration of laboratory and natural plasma physics, cross-institutional collaboration, and integration of research with teaching was what CMSO was all about. &nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 12/19/2016<br>      Modified by: Ellen&nbsp;G&nbsp;Zweibel</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Project Outcomes Report for NSF 0821899  This award funded the Center for Magnetic Self-Organization in Laboratory and Astrophysical Plasmas (CMSO) from 2008 &ndash; 2014 with a two-year supplement from 2014-2016 as an NSF Physics Frontiers Center.  CMSO brought together researchers from U. Wisconsin, U. Chicago, Princeton Univ. and the Princeton Plasma Physics Lab, Swarthmore College, U. New Hampshire, and Los Alamos National Laboratory to study basic plasma physics problems that arise in the study of laboratory and natural plasmas. Magnetic Self-Organization &ndash; the tendency for magnetized systems to evolve to an energetically favorable state, was the umbrella theme, and much of the research was motivated by two overarching questions:  How is the universe magnetized?  How do magnetic fields affect the motions of plasmas?  Some of the main tangible research outcomes of CMSO include three major experiments, one to study magnetic field generation (MPDX) and two to study magnetic reconnection (TREX and FLARE); CMSO did not fund these experiments but laid much of the intellectual groundwork for them. Major collaborations with NASA space experiments that study magnetic reconnection and solar wind turbulence were initiated and strengthened along the same lines. This work is having a major impact on our understanding of magnetic explosions across the Universe, solar activity, how stars are built, and how black holes grow over cosmic time.  CMSO sponsored scientific conferences, workshops, and winter schools both for the membership and for the scientific community. CMSO researchers gave literally hundreds of invited talks at scientific institutions and scientific meetings, and wrote hundreds of papers.   CMSO also had a public mission - senior staff, students, and outreach professionals reached K12 students and the general public throughout the US with demonstrations in plasma science and general physics.  Most of the CMSO budget funded people &ndash; undergraduate students, graduate students, and postdoctoral researchers, many of who went on to permanent positions in plasma science and astronomy at universities, government labs, and in the private sector. Several senior investigators were selected as Fellows of the American Physical Society, and two won the APS Maxwell Prize for Plasma Physics.  The story of one particular scientist exemplifies the impact of CMSO on research, education, and human resources. A U. Wisconsin Astronomy graduate student supported by CMSO wanted to learn computational physics, and wrote his thesis on the MRX experiment at the Princeton Plasma Physics Lab under the joint supervision of a U. Wisconsin astronomer and an engineering physicist, both CMSO members. Intriguing effects caused by the toroidal shape of MRX led him to wonder whether the same effects might occur in reconnection of the solar magnetic field. A senior CMSO faculty member brought him together with a Harvard solar physicist, who found the idea very promising, hired him into a postdoctoral position at Harvard and later supported his appointment as a permanent staff member, where he teaches plasma astrophysics to graduate students and works with summer undergraduate research interns. Recently he has come full circle, collaborating with Princeton Plasma Lab scientists to perform computer simulations of a new experiment. This integration of laboratory and natural plasma physics, cross-institutional collaboration, and integration of research with teaching was what CMSO was all about.            Last Modified: 12/19/2016       Submitted by: Ellen G Zweibel]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
