<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>International Collaboration in Chemistry:   Microphase Photo-Electrochemistry:   Light-Driven Liquid-Liquid Ion Transfer Processes and Two-Phase Micro-Photovoltaic Systems</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2008</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2012</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>225000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>225000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03090006</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CHE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Chemistry</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Zeev Rosenzweig</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>In this research supported by the NSF Chemistry Division, Analytical and Surface Chemistry Program and Office of International Science and Engineering, Blanchard (Michigan State University) and Marken (University of Bath, UK) research groups focus on studying photo-electrochemical processes at microphase liquid:liquid interfaces and at triple phase boundaries.  Such structures offer a unique environment where excited molecules and reaction intermediates are in close proximity to both electrode surfaces and liquid:liquid interfaces.  The goal in studying such systems lies in the critical role that these types of structure play in processes such as photosynthetic light harvesting.  The project is divided into four main, interconnected parts:  (A) the study of electrochemically or photo-electrochemically driven ion transfer processes using fluorescent probe anions, (B) the study and screening of simultaneous electron and ion transfer at liquid:liquid interfaces and triple phase boundaries, (C) the investigation of two-phase processes involving electron and ion transfer at selected interfaces, and (D) characterizing the local environment at liquid:liquid interfaces using fluorescent probe molecules for the purpose of understanding how the potential of the interface and flux of ions across the interface affects the local environment.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The larger purpose of this research program, beyond understanding photo-electrochemical dynamics at complex interphase systems, is to educate students at the cutting edge of multidisciplinary science.  It is imperative that the United States train a diverse population of students to be globally competitive for careers in science.  This research serves as an important vehicle in that effort.  By fostering a synergistic relationship between the Blanchard (Michigan State University) and Marken (University of Bath UK) research groups, a multinational cohort of globally competitive scientists will be educated, directly benefiting both the United States and the United Kingdom.  This project will facilitate the creation of a bilateral think tank and will foster the free exchange of ideas in a field of research and development that has direct impact on science at the interface between biosystems and energy conversion.  The ideas and experiments developed in this collaborative study can help screen and identify new light harvesting processes, possibly mimicking natural processes, and therefore contribute to new energy harvesting/storage/management systems.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/07/2008</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/04/2010</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>0822422</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Gary</FirstName>
<LastName>Blanchard</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>J</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Gary J Blanchard</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>blanchard@chemistry.msu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5173531105</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000087491</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/07/2008</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Michigan State University</Name>
<CityName>East Lansing</CityName>
<ZipCode>488242600</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5173555040</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>Office of Sponsored Programs</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[426 Administration Bldg, Rm2]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Michigan</StateName>
<StateCode>MI</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>08</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MI08</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>193247145</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>MICHIGAN STATE UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>053343976</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Michigan State University]]></Name>
<CityName>East Lansing</CityName>
<StateCode>MI</StateCode>
<ZipCode>488242600</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[Office of Sponsored Programs]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Michigan</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>08</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MI08</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1972</Code>
<Text>ELECTROCHEMISTRY &amp; SURFACE CHE</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7298</Code>
<Text>International Research Collab</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>0000</Code>
<Text>UNASSIGNED</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>090E</Code>
<Text>Chem/Bio and Physical Diagnostics</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1517</Code>
<Text>ELECT, PHOTONICS, &amp; DEVICE TEC</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1972</Code>
<Text>ELECTROCHEMISTRY &amp; SURFACE CHE</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>5946</Code>
<Text>UNITED KINGDOM</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>5979</Code>
<Text>Europe and Eurasia</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7644</Code>
<Text>ENERGY FOR SUSTAINABILITY</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>OTHR</Code>
<Text>OTHER RESEARCH OR EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0108</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0109</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0110</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2008~75000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2009~75000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2010~75000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>In this research supported by the Analytical and Surface Chemistry Program, we have focused on studying photo-electrochemical processes at microphase liquid:liquid interfaces and at triple phase boundaries.&nbsp; Such structures offer a unique environment where excited molecules and reaction intermediates are in close proximity to both electrode surfaces and liquid:liquid interfaces.&nbsp; Our goal in studying such systems lies in the critical role that these types of structure play in processes such as photosynthetic light harvesting.&nbsp; The project has been divided into four main, interconnected parts:&nbsp; (1) the study of electrochemically or photo-electrochemically driven ion transfer processes using fluorescent probe anions, (2) the study and screening of simultaneous electron and ion transfer at liquid:liquid interfaces and triple phase boundaries, (3) the investigation of two-phase processes involving electron and ion transfer at selected interfaces, and (4) characterizing the local environment at liquid:liquid interfaces using fluorescent probe molecules for the purpose of understanding how the potential of the interface and flux of ions across the interface affects the local environment.&nbsp; The work we have published demonstrates that the properties of liquid-liquid interfaces can be exploited for the organization of molecules as well as to control the passage of ions between two different liquids in contact with one another.</p> <p>The larger purpose of this research program, beyond understanding photo-electrochemical dynamics at complex interphase systems, has been to educate students at the cutting edge of multidisciplinary science.&nbsp; It is imperative that the United States train a diverse population of students to be globally competitive for careers in science.&nbsp; This research serves as an important vehicle in that effort.&nbsp;By fostering a synergistic relationship between the Blanchard (Michigan State University) and Marken (University of Bath UK) research groups, a multinational cohort of globally competitive scientists has been educated, directly benefiting both the United States and the United Kingdom.&nbsp; This project facilitated the creation of a bilateral think tank and has fostered the free exchange of ideas in a field of research and development that has direct impact on science at the interface between biosystems and energy conversion.&nbsp;The ideas developed and experiments performed in this collaborative study will aid in identifying new light harvesting processes, possibly mimicking natural processes, and therefore contribute to new energy harvesting/storage/management systems.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 08/03/2012<br>      Modified by: Gary&nbsp;J&nbsp;Blanchard</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ In this research supported by the Analytical and Surface Chemistry Program, we have focused on studying photo-electrochemical processes at microphase liquid:liquid interfaces and at triple phase boundaries.  Such structures offer a unique environment where excited molecules and reaction intermediates are in close proximity to both electrode surfaces and liquid:liquid interfaces.  Our goal in studying such systems lies in the critical role that these types of structure play in processes such as photosynthetic light harvesting.  The project has been divided into four main, interconnected parts:  (1) the study of electrochemically or photo-electrochemically driven ion transfer processes using fluorescent probe anions, (2) the study and screening of simultaneous electron and ion transfer at liquid:liquid interfaces and triple phase boundaries, (3) the investigation of two-phase processes involving electron and ion transfer at selected interfaces, and (4) characterizing the local environment at liquid:liquid interfaces using fluorescent probe molecules for the purpose of understanding how the potential of the interface and flux of ions across the interface affects the local environment.  The work we have published demonstrates that the properties of liquid-liquid interfaces can be exploited for the organization of molecules as well as to control the passage of ions between two different liquids in contact with one another.  The larger purpose of this research program, beyond understanding photo-electrochemical dynamics at complex interphase systems, has been to educate students at the cutting edge of multidisciplinary science.  It is imperative that the United States train a diverse population of students to be globally competitive for careers in science.  This research serves as an important vehicle in that effort. By fostering a synergistic relationship between the Blanchard (Michigan State University) and Marken (University of Bath UK) research groups, a multinational cohort of globally competitive scientists has been educated, directly benefiting both the United States and the United Kingdom.  This project facilitated the creation of a bilateral think tank and has fostered the free exchange of ideas in a field of research and development that has direct impact on science at the interface between biosystems and energy conversion. The ideas developed and experiments performed in this collaborative study will aid in identifying new light harvesting processes, possibly mimicking natural processes, and therefore contribute to new energy harvesting/storage/management systems.       Last Modified: 08/03/2012       Submitted by: Gary J Blanchard]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
