<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>BRIGE: Morphological Characterization of Nanomaterials by Atomic Force Microscopy</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2008</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2010</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>175000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>175000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CMMI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Civil, Mechanical, &amp; Manufact Inn</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Mary Toney</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The research objective of this award is the development of an advanced nanomaterials characterization program based on state-of-the-art techniques such as atomic force microscopy (AFM).  Research on the morphology of nanomaterials as determined by AFM will provide insight into the structure-property relationship of materials at the nanometer scale.  This type of information is critical to advancing the understanding of new nanomaterials, and provides insights into these materials that are difficult to obtain using other techniques. This award will support initial efforts to develop appropriate techniques for analysis of advanced nanomaterials such as nanoshells and carbon nanotubes.  Specific topics to be examined include evaluation of nanotube density, nanotube orientation, and alignment.  This will provide a unique database of information that is highly relevant to technical areas such as nanoelectronics.  As materials and their understanding are fundamental to many engineering advancements and challenges, the establishment of a nanomaterials characterization program is critical in defining the techniques and protocols needed to develop revolutionary materials.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;If successful, this program will provide a cornerstone to the development of a strong nanomaterials characterization program at Union College.  Research in nanomaterials characterization using AFM supported by this grant will expose undergraduate students to state-of-the-art nanomaterials, and to the very real changes that are occurring at the interfaces between historical disciplines.  The immediate impact of this will therefore be to provide all students including underrepresented undergraduates from engineering and science disciplines with a substantial comprehension of nanoscale science and technology.  This will provide them with an excellent foundation upon which an outstanding career in nanotechnology can be established.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/31/2008</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/31/2008</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>0824341</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Rebecca</FirstName>
<LastName>Cortez</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Rebecca Cortez</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>cortezr@union.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5183888784</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000498561</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/31/2008</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Union College</Name>
<CityName>Schenectady</CityName>
<CountyName>SCHENECTADY</CountyName>
<ZipCode>123083103</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5183886101</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>807 Union Street</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>20</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NY20</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>059375584</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>TRUSTEES OF UNION COLLEGE IN THE TOWN OF SCHENECTADY IN THE STATE OF NEW YORK</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>059375584</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name>Union College</Name>
<CityName>Schenectady</CityName>
<CountyName>SCHENECTADY</CountyName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<ZipCode>123083103</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress>807 Union Street</StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>20</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NY20</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7741</Code>
<Text>BRIGE-Broad Partic in Eng</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9146</Code>
<Text>MANUFACTURING BASE RESEARCH</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>MANU</Code>
<Text>MANUFACTURING</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0108</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2008~175000</FUND_OBLG>
</Award>
</rootTag>
