<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>URM:  Enhancing Diversity in Environmental Biology</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>01/01/2009</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2015</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>563564.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>563564</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>08080300</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>BIO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DBI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Biological Infrastructure</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Sally O'Connor</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>soconnor@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924552</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The URM proposal entitled Enhancing Diversity in Environmental Biology (EDEB) is a university partnership to recruit and mentor underrepresented undergraduate students from Xavier and Tulane Universities and prepares them for admission and completion of environmental biology graduate programs.  A structured and collaborative program, EDEB will be administered through the Tulane/Xavier Center for Bioenvironmental Research (CBR).  The CBR represents a nineteen-year university partnership in bioenvironmental research; increasing diversity in this field is a core concept in its mission. Nationally only 3.4% of the doctoral degrees in biology are awarded to African Americans (NSF Science and Engineering Doctorate Awards: 2005), and only a small fraction of these become environmental biologists. An important method to increase interest in environmental biology is to combine undergraduate lectures with student research in close collaboration with faculty mentors. Recent studies focusing on undergraduate students in research programs support this approach, particularly for first generation college and/or minority students. EDEB will implement a training program in environmental biology that includes research tools and techniques; mentored laboratory and field experiences; and critical thinking and career exploration activities. Students will receive a unique, collaborative mentoring experience utilizing a ?mentoring triad? concept in which they will be jointly mentored by a Tulane University faculty member and a Xavier University faculty member.  This project will fortify the successful majority-minority institutional alliance between Tulane and Xavier Universities by building on the strengths of the CBR. For additional information, contact PIs: Dr. John McLachlan jmclach@tulane.edu or Dr. Syed Muniruzzaman smuniruz@xula.edu . For additional information, visit http://www.cbr.tulane.edu/ .</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/12/2008</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/01/2011</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.074</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>0829236</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>John</FirstName>
<LastName>McLachlan</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>A</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>John A McLachlan</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>jmclach@tulane.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5049886910</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000208726</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/12/2008</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Tulane University</Name>
<CityName>NEW ORLEANS</CityName>
<ZipCode>701185698</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5048654000</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>6823 ST CHARLES AVENUE</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Louisiana</StateName>
<StateCode>LA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>LA01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>053785812</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>ADMINISTRATORS OF THE TULANE EDUCATIONAL FUND, THE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>053785812</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Tulane University]]></Name>
<CityName>NEW ORLEANS</CityName>
<StateCode>LA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>701185698</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[6823 ST CHARLES AVENUE]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Louisiana</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>LA01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7783</Code>
<Text>UNGRAD RES MENTORING IN BIO</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EPSCoR Co-Funding</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1228</Code>
<Text>MINORITY INVOLVEMENT -- BIO</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7783</Code>
<Text>UNGRAD RES MENTORING IN BIO</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9178</Code>
<Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>SMET</Code>
<Text>SCIENCE, MATH, ENG &amp; TECH EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0108</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0111</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2008~512827</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2011~50737</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p class="bodytext"><strong>Tulane/Xavier <em>Enhancing Diversity in Environmental Biology </em>(EDEB) program</strong></p> <p class="bodytext">&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; As part of a long standing partnership between Tulane University (a Carnegie I University) and Xavier University (an Historically Black University), a research mentoring program was established in 2009 to recruit underrepresented minority students to the basic or applied biological sciences and improve the diversity of the national environmental science work force. <em>Enhancing Diversity in Environmental Biology </em>(EDEB) program utilized a mentoring triad of Tulane faculty with Xavier faculty and a student from either university. The program recruited only a small number of students each year so that they could be intensively mentored and followed long term. Fifteen years of experience in mentoring minority students, post docs and faculty led us to believe that small numbers mentored over the long-term work best. We also were committed to identifying students who had aptitude and interest in science even though their academic records were less than outstanding. We focused on providing the tools for scientific literacy and success for students who would become part of the scientific workforce.</p> <p class="bodytext">At the beginning of each fellowship, the student had a summer long orientation where faculty mentors and other students interacted with the new fellows to introduce them to the research opportunities in the program. The focal component of this orientation is the Environmental Bio-techniques Course.&nbsp; Key elements include:&nbsp; <strong>effective mentor selection, scientific ethics, successful navigation of graduate school, GRE preparation, and platform presentation preparation</strong>.&nbsp; Successful completion of the orientation is followed by 3 semesters of mentored research in the laboratories of Tulane and Xavier faculty.&nbsp; &nbsp;&nbsp;</p> <p class="bodytext">Once a permanent laboratory is selected, the intern is required to give a platform presentation during the Annual Summer Research Academy Symposium.&nbsp; This experience provides each intern with constructive criticism from Faculty mentors.&nbsp; In addition to faculty, staff and students many family members of the fellows attend and have a chance to interact with other students and faculty. We have found that this public involvement adds to the viability of the students in the program.</p> <p class="bodytext"><strong>EDEB fellows also make poster or oral presentations at the various national conferences such as ABRCMS, ERN and NIMHD.</strong> Some of these conferences are the largest professional conferences for minority students interested in STEM disciplines with over a thousand of undergraduate participants.&nbsp; It has been an ideal forum for networking with other students and faculty as well as an opportunity for connection and recruitment from over 500 graduate programs.</p> <p class="bodytext">Over the time period of EDEB, 35 under represented minority (as defined by NSF) undergraduates were chosen for the program. Of these, 27 were Xavier students and 8 were Tulane undergraduates. The students ranged from first year to third year undergraduates at the time of entry to the program. During this program 11 Xavier and 7 Tulane faculty members have served as the research mentors for these URM students. Out of these 35 URM students 3 are co-authors on peer reviewed journal publication with their mentors at the present time, although others may join this group as additional papers are written in the respective labs.</p> <p>While 6 students are still undergraduates, of those who have graduated, 4 students are in PhD program and one student in MS program (Tulane University, University of Michigan, Virginia Tech, LSU-New Orleans). &nbsp;Also one student is enrolled in an MS...]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[Tulane/Xavier Enhancing Diversity in Environmental Biology (EDEB) program             As part of a long standing partnership between Tulane University (a Carnegie I University) and Xavier University (an Historically Black University), a research mentoring program was established in 2009 to recruit underrepresented minority students to the basic or applied biological sciences and improve the diversity of the national environmental science work force. Enhancing Diversity in Environmental Biology (EDEB) program utilized a mentoring triad of Tulane faculty with Xavier faculty and a student from either university. The program recruited only a small number of students each year so that they could be intensively mentored and followed long term. Fifteen years of experience in mentoring minority students, post docs and faculty led us to believe that small numbers mentored over the long-term work best. We also were committed to identifying students who had aptitude and interest in science even though their academic records were less than outstanding. We focused on providing the tools for scientific literacy and success for students who would become part of the scientific workforce. At the beginning of each fellowship, the student had a summer long orientation where faculty mentors and other students interacted with the new fellows to introduce them to the research opportunities in the program. The focal component of this orientation is the Environmental Bio-techniques Course.  Key elements include:  effective mentor selection, scientific ethics, successful navigation of graduate school, GRE preparation, and platform presentation preparation.  Successful completion of the orientation is followed by 3 semesters of mentored research in the laboratories of Tulane and Xavier faculty.     Once a permanent laboratory is selected, the intern is required to give a platform presentation during the Annual Summer Research Academy Symposium.  This experience provides each intern with constructive criticism from Faculty mentors.  In addition to faculty, staff and students many family members of the fellows attend and have a chance to interact with other students and faculty. We have found that this public involvement adds to the viability of the students in the program. EDEB fellows also make poster or oral presentations at the various national conferences such as ABRCMS, ERN and NIMHD. Some of these conferences are the largest professional conferences for minority students interested in STEM disciplines with over a thousand of undergraduate participants.  It has been an ideal forum for networking with other students and faculty as well as an opportunity for connection and recruitment from over 500 graduate programs. Over the time period of EDEB, 35 under represented minority (as defined by NSF) undergraduates were chosen for the program. Of these, 27 were Xavier students and 8 were Tulane undergraduates. The students ranged from first year to third year undergraduates at the time of entry to the program. During this program 11 Xavier and 7 Tulane faculty members have served as the research mentors for these URM students. Out of these 35 URM students 3 are co-authors on peer reviewed journal publication with their mentors at the present time, although others may join this group as additional papers are written in the respective labs.  While 6 students are still undergraduates, of those who have graduated, 4 students are in PhD program and one student in MS program (Tulane University, University of Michigan, Virginia Tech, LSU-New Orleans).  Also one student is enrolled in an MS program in Science Education at Xavier while currently working as an elementary school teacher. Some students are employed as research technicians in laboratories. In professional fields, three students are in the College of Pharmacy at Xavier University; these students are engaged in research in the College of Pharmacy. Two students are in Dental School and two students are i...]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
