<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>NEESR-II: Evaluation of Seismic Levee Deformation Potential by Destructive Cyclic Field Testing</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>10/01/2008</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>03/31/2013</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>375000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>429526</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CMMI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Civil, Mechanical, &amp; Manufact Inn</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Richard Fragaszy</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The Sacramento-San Joaquin Delta levees are critical components of California?s water distribution system. The Delta supplies fresh water to 22 million people in southern and central California as well as eastern portions of the San Francisco Bay area and directly supports $400 billion/year of economic activity within the State of California. The ?islands? circumscribed by the network of levees are commonly 3 to 5 meters below sea level, and are protected by only about 1 to 1.5 meters of freeboard at high tide.  A breach in a levee causes water from the channel to flow into the island thereby inundating farmland and wildlife habitat, and drawing saline water from the San Francisco Bay into the Delta. This is a potentially catastrophic scenario, as saline contamination could halt water delivery to central and southern California, removing the sole water source for many communities.  This scenario is unlikely in the event of an individual levee breach caused by burrowing animals and other local hazards because the existing emergency response system can respond to a single breach within a matter of hours and affect repair within a matter of weeks. On the other hand, seismic hazard is an extraordinary threat because of the potential for multiple simultaneous breaches inundating many islands within the Delta. Such widespread system failure has been forecast to cause up to 28 months of time during which fresh water deliveries from the Delta would not be possible. Some in fact question whether such a sequence of breaches might permanently change the regional morphology such that either alternative water sources would need to be identified or major sectors of the California economy/population would need to be reconfigured or relocated.  The influence of earthquake shaking on the behavior of the levees is uncertain because the cyclic deformation potential of the underlying peaty organic soils not well understood, and there is an urgent need to investigate the behavior of these materials.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Intellectual Merit and Scope: This award will support full-scale testing of an existing earth embankment (very similar in geometry to a levee, but not currently holding water) to investigate the in situ deformation potential of peaty organic foundation soils under realistic stresses and boundary conditions. The test conditions and instrumentation will be designed to measure the deformation mechanisms that can result in a critical loss of freeboard leading to a breach.  Data of this sort is essential for the development of more rational analysis tools for assessing the seismic vulnerability of levees. The field testing will be supplemented by an extensive laboratory testing program to further investigate key material response characteristics such as soil strength loss and volume reduction caused by shaking. The improved knowledge of levee seismic vulnerability will be broadly applicable wherever these earth structures are founded on organic soils.  Testing activities will be closely coordinated with engineers at the California Department of Water Resources to identify a suitable site.  Insights gained from this project could fundamentally alter the manner in which Delta seismic risk is assessed and retrofit decisions are made. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Broader Impacts: The most important societal impact of this research will be improvement of seismic risk assessment in the Delta, which in turn will result in better informed retrofit and/or construction decisions and a water delivery system that is more likely to maintain functionality during and following earthquake shaking. This award will also support development of education modules that leverage NEES resources to contribute to the broader NEESinc goals for education, outreach and training (EOT). The modules will teach about the current water delivery system, the network of levees in the Delta, the link between water delivery and the levee network, the engineering properties of these levees, the potential seismic failure mechanisms of the levees, and the consequences on the availability of water for drinking and irrigation. Included with the modules will be a study guide containing suggestions regarding implementation of the modules at different levels (i.e., undergraduates and K-12). &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Data from this project will be made available through the NEES data repository (http://www.nees.org)&lt;br/&gt;</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/13/2008</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/17/2012</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>0830081</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Jonathan</FirstName>
<LastName>Stewart</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Jonathan Stewart</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>jstewart@seas.ucla.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>3102062990</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000468081</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/13/2008</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Scott</FirstName>
<LastName>Brandenberg</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>J</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Scott J Brandenberg</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>sjbrandenberg@ucla.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>3108259819</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000065501</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/13/2008</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of California-Los Angeles</Name>
<CityName>LOS ANGELES</CityName>
<ZipCode>900951406</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>3107940102</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>10889 Wilshire Boulevard</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[Suite 700]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>33</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CA33</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>092530369</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF CALIFORNIA, LOS ANGELES</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>071549000</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of California-Los Angeles]]></Name>
<CityName>LOS ANGELES</CityName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>900951406</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[10889 Wilshire Boulevard]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>33</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CA33</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<FoaInformation>
<Code>0308000</Code>
<Name>Industrial Technology</Name>
</FoaInformation>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7396</Code>
<Text>NEES RESEARCH</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>036E</Code>
<Text>CIVIL INFRASTRUCTURE</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>037E</Code>
<Text>GEOTECHNICAL ENGINEERING</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>041E</Code>
<Text>HAZARD AND DISASTER REDUCTION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>043E</Code>
<Text>EARTHQUAKE ENGINEERING</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1057</Code>
<Text>CIS BASE RESEARCH</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>116E</Code>
<Text>RESEARCH EXP FOR UNDERGRADS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1576</Code>
<Text>NATIONL EARTHQK HZRD REDCT PRG</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9146</Code>
<Text>MANUFACTURING BASE RESEARCH</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9178</Code>
<Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9251</Code>
<Text>REU SUPP-Res Exp for Ugrd Supp</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>CVIS</Code>
<Text>CIVIL INFRASTRUCTURE</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>MANU</Code>
<Text>MANUFACTURING</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0108</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0112</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2008~375000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2012~54526</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The Sacramento-San Joaquin Delta is an estuary at the confluence of the Sacramento and San Joaquin Rivers. Prior to reclamation of the Delta through the construction of levees and upstream water storage, the Delta was characterized as a variable salinity environment that frequently flooded. Reclamation has maintained the Delta as a fresh water conveyance system that is a sensitive ecosystem and an agricultural and recreational area.</p> <p>The Delta levees are critical components of California&rsquo;s water distribution system. The Delta supplies fresh water to over 22 million people in southern and central California as well as eastern portions of the bay area and directly supports California's $400 billion/year economy. The levees circumscribe &ldquo;islands&rdquo; that are commonly 3 to 5 meters below sea level. These levees continuously retain water within the river channels with only about 1 to 1.5 meters of freeboard at high tide. A levee breach floods the island, inundating farmland and wildlife habitat. The risk posed to the Delta by a strong earthquake is particularly onerous due to the potential for levee failures that would flood many islands simultaneously, drawing saline water from the San Francisco Bay into the Delta, which in turn would degrade water quality to an extent that delivery would be halted. Our ability to properly evaluate the risks associated with this seismic scenario is limited because the cyclic deformation potential of peaty organic soils underlying many levees is not well understood.</p> <p>This project utilized NEES@UCLA mobile field shakers to impose shaking demands on a model levee resting atop peaty organic soil on Sherman Island at the western margin of the Delta. The heavily instrumented model was shaken with ground motion intensities that are broadly consistent with seismic hazard in the Delta. Long-term monitoring was performed before and after dynamic testing to measure settlement. The field testing was supplemented by a separately-funded laboratory testing program to measure the response of the peat soil to cyclic loading.</p> <p>Interpretation of the test data is ongoing, and we anticipate formulating conclusions from the test data and publishing these conclusions in journal papers, and presentations. Nevertheless, some preliminary conclusions are presented here. First, our shaking induced negligible settlement of the levee. We had postulated that some post-cyclic settlement might occur as a result of shear strains imposed on the peat soil during shaking, but this settlement did not occur because the levels of shear strain imposed on the peat were below the levels required to trigger such deformations. Contributing factors to the unexpectedly modest strain demands include an unrealistic boundary condition and limitations of the shaker system. Second, the model levee exhibited significant rocking and translation during shaking. These sources of compliance in the levee-foundation system are currently not included in typical seismic levee analysis methodologies, and are anticipated to contribute to stress concentrations in the levee fill and underlying soils. Future work is required to fully develop this concept so that it may be incorporated into seismic levee evaluation procedures.</p> <p>In addition to the preliminary conclusions we have drawn from the study, we feel that we must address erroneous conclusions made by other observers of our tests. Following the test in 2011, several individuals who were not part of our project team and conjectured in media reports that our test proved that Delta levees are seismically stable because our model levee did not &ldquo;fail&rdquo;. This conclusion is false for two important reasons.</p> <ol> <li>We deliberately constructed our model embankment to be nonliquefiable and much stronger than typical Delta levees so that the forces imposed by our shaker could be driven into the underly...]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The Sacramento-San Joaquin Delta is an estuary at the confluence of the Sacramento and San Joaquin Rivers. Prior to reclamation of the Delta through the construction of levees and upstream water storage, the Delta was characterized as a variable salinity environment that frequently flooded. Reclamation has maintained the Delta as a fresh water conveyance system that is a sensitive ecosystem and an agricultural and recreational area.  The Delta levees are critical components of CaliforniaÆs water distribution system. The Delta supplies fresh water to over 22 million people in southern and central California as well as eastern portions of the bay area and directly supports California's $400 billion/year economy. The levees circumscribe "islands" that are commonly 3 to 5 meters below sea level. These levees continuously retain water within the river channels with only about 1 to 1.5 meters of freeboard at high tide. A levee breach floods the island, inundating farmland and wildlife habitat. The risk posed to the Delta by a strong earthquake is particularly onerous due to the potential for levee failures that would flood many islands simultaneously, drawing saline water from the San Francisco Bay into the Delta, which in turn would degrade water quality to an extent that delivery would be halted. Our ability to properly evaluate the risks associated with this seismic scenario is limited because the cyclic deformation potential of peaty organic soils underlying many levees is not well understood.  This project utilized NEES@UCLA mobile field shakers to impose shaking demands on a model levee resting atop peaty organic soil on Sherman Island at the western margin of the Delta. The heavily instrumented model was shaken with ground motion intensities that are broadly consistent with seismic hazard in the Delta. Long-term monitoring was performed before and after dynamic testing to measure settlement. The field testing was supplemented by a separately-funded laboratory testing program to measure the response of the peat soil to cyclic loading.  Interpretation of the test data is ongoing, and we anticipate formulating conclusions from the test data and publishing these conclusions in journal papers, and presentations. Nevertheless, some preliminary conclusions are presented here. First, our shaking induced negligible settlement of the levee. We had postulated that some post-cyclic settlement might occur as a result of shear strains imposed on the peat soil during shaking, but this settlement did not occur because the levels of shear strain imposed on the peat were below the levels required to trigger such deformations. Contributing factors to the unexpectedly modest strain demands include an unrealistic boundary condition and limitations of the shaker system. Second, the model levee exhibited significant rocking and translation during shaking. These sources of compliance in the levee-foundation system are currently not included in typical seismic levee analysis methodologies, and are anticipated to contribute to stress concentrations in the levee fill and underlying soils. Future work is required to fully develop this concept so that it may be incorporated into seismic levee evaluation procedures.  In addition to the preliminary conclusions we have drawn from the study, we feel that we must address erroneous conclusions made by other observers of our tests. Following the test in 2011, several individuals who were not part of our project team and conjectured in media reports that our test proved that Delta levees are seismically stable because our model levee did not "fail". This conclusion is false for two important reasons.  We deliberately constructed our model embankment to be nonliquefiable and much stronger than typical Delta levees so that the forces imposed by our shaker could be driven into the underlying peat. Liquefaction of loose coarse grained saturated soils is a phenomenon that is well understood based on many case histor...]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
