<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>RITES:Rhode Island Technology Enhanced Science Program</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>10/01/2008</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>03/31/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>12499987.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>11287781</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>11090000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>EHR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DRL</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Research On Learning</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Kathleen Bergin</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>kbergin@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032925171</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The University of Rhode Island (URI), Rhode Island College (RIC), Johnston Public Schools and the Rhode Island Department of Education (RIDE) are Core Partners in a comprehensive, statewide effort to improve the quality of science teaching and learning at all secondary schools.  The Education Alliance at Brown University, which will evaluate the project, is a supporting partner together with the Community College of Rhode Island, the Rhode Island Economic Development Corporation and the Concord Consortium. &lt;br/&gt;Rhode Island Technology Enhanced Science (RITES) is based upon structural reform initiated with the support of the Governor. An action plan developed by a PK-16 council resulted in an investment of $15 million to establish a permanent STEM Center that features two new tenure track positions and will provide support to all schools.  The comprehensive statewide STEM education reform also has support from all levels of government and academia and RITES represents a valuable experiment in organization and structure within that effort.  &lt;br/&gt;The RITES project will, in five years of NSF funding, transform the quality of science teaching and learning at all secondary schools, with the goal of increasing the number and diversity of students who are proficient in science and pursue careers in Science, Engineering, Technology, and Mathematics (STEM).  The heart of the project is the seamless integration of all segments of the Rhode Island educational community (i.e., teachers and school systems, higher education science departments and schools of education, the various state offices that monitor and support STEM education and the private sector). &lt;br/&gt;RITES will impact all 686 middle school and high school teachers and all of their 83,339 students with excellent, challenging, computer-based, standards-aligned, science materials.  Pairs of high schools and feeder middle schools will join the Partnership together by developing a unified, comprehensive, middle and high school science action plan that will integrate RITES resources, for professional development of teachers and materials for students, with school needs and ongoing school reform.  Schools that participate in the project will be expected to have the active engagement of the school leadership and at least 75% of the science teachers.  Teachers will attend short courses not only to deepen their content knowledge and pedagogy but also to learn how to customize the newly designed curricular materials for their own classrooms. &lt;br/&gt;The comprehensive evaluation plan will include annual reviews of the New England Common Assessments Program (NECAP) science assessment,which will be administered for the first time in Spring 2008.  Results will be disaggregated by race, gender and disabilities and income. Specific benchmarks for student achievement, teacher professional development and workforce diversity will be used to track progress.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>09/19/2008</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>01/31/2017</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.076</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>0831974</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Anne</FirstName>
<LastName>Veeger</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>I</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Anne I Veeger</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>veeger@uri.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>4018742187</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000315451</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/15/2011</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Daniel</FirstName>
<LastName>Murray</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>P</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Daniel P Murray</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>dpmurray@uri.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>4018744502</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000308452</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/19/2008</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Robert</FirstName>
<LastName>Tinker</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>F</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Robert F Tinker</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>bob@concord.org</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>9784053222</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000224400</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/19/2008</StartDate>
<EndDate>04/15/2011</EndDate>
<RoleCode>Former Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Glenisson</FirstName>
<LastName>deOliveira</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Glenisson deOliveira</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>gdeoliveira@ric.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>4014569697</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000061255</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/19/2008</StartDate>
<EndDate>01/31/2017</EndDate>
<RoleCode>Former Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Peter</FirstName>
<LastName>McLaren</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Peter McLaren</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>Peter.Mclaren@ride.ri.gov</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>4018745138</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000502790</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/19/2008</StartDate>
<EndDate>01/31/2017</EndDate>
<RoleCode>Former Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Kathryn</FirstName>
<LastName>Crowley</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Kathryn Crowley</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>rid06269@ride.ri.net</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>4018745138</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000502795</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/19/2008</StartDate>
<EndDate>08/06/2011</EndDate>
<RoleCode>Former Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Alicia</FirstName>
<LastName>Storey</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>j</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Alicia j Storey</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>astorey@westerly.k12.ri.us</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>4013151517</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000591944</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/06/2011</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Victor</FirstName>
<LastName>Fay-Wolfe</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Victor Fay-Wolfe</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>wolfe@cs.uri.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>4018742701</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000619265</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>01/31/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Rhode Island</Name>
<CityName>KINGSTON</CityName>
<ZipCode>028811967</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>4018742635</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>RESEARCH OFFICE</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[70 LOWER COLLEGE ROAD]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Rhode Island</StateName>
<StateCode>RI</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>RI02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>144017188</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF RHODE ISLAND</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>075705780</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Rhode Island]]></Name>
<CityName>KINGSTON</CityName>
<StateCode>RI</StateCode>
<ZipCode>028811967</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[RESEARCH OFFICE]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Rhode Island</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>RI02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<FoaInformation>
<Code>0116000</Code>
<Name>Human Subjects</Name>
</FoaInformation>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1792</Code>
<Text>MSP-TARGETED AWARDS</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1996</Code>
<Text>STEM - Computing Partnerships</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7382</Code>
<Text>Computing Ed for 21st Century</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7578</Code>
<Text>CS 10K</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9177</Code>
<Text>ELEMENTARY/SECONDARY EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9178</Code>
<Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>SMET</Code>
<Text>SCIENCE, MATH, ENG &amp; TECH EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0114</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0408</Code>
<Name>NSF Education &amp; Human Resource</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040106</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0411</Code>
<Name>NSF Education &amp; Human Resource</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040106</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0412</Code>
<Name>NSF Education &amp; Human Resource</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040106</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0413</Code>
<Name>NSF Education &amp; Human Resource</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040106</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0414</Code>
<Name>NSF Education &amp; Human Resource</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040106</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2008~4938034</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2011~2975949</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2012~1990931</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2013~912742</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~470125</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><!-- p.p1 {margin: 6.0px 0.0px 6.0px 0.0px; font: 11.0px Arial; color: #424242} p.p2 {margin: 6.0px 0.0px 6.0px 0.0px; font: 11.0px Arial} p.p3 {margin: 0.0px 0.0px 8.0px 0.0px; font: 11.0px Arial} li.li2 {margin: 6.0px 0.0px 6.0px 0.0px; font: 11.0px Arial} span.s1 {text-decoration: underline} span.s2 {font: 11.0px 'Times New Roman'} span.s3 {font: 11.0px Symbol} span.s4 {text-decoration: underline ; color: #0079cd} span.Apple-tab-span {white-space:pre} ul.ul1 {list-style-type: disc} --> <p>This is our <strong>Project Outcomes Report.</strong> The reader is directed as appropriate to the complete Final Report for further details. - The full Final and previous Annual Reports are posted at <a href="http://ritesc.org/">http://ritesc.org/</a><strong>.</strong></p> <p>Rhode Island Technology Enhanced Sciences, or RITES, was funded as a National Science Foundation (NSF) Math-Science Partnership in October 2008. RITES continued to evolve its partnership and programs through March 2019. The partnership's host partners are the University of RI (URI), RI College, Johnston, Providence and Westerly Public Schools. See (<strong>Figure 1</strong>) for eventual partnership statewide reach. <strong>&nbsp;</strong></p> <p>RITES mission statement is "Through the collaborative partnership of RI's public higher education and districts, RITES aims to transform the quality of science teaching and learning at all middle and secondary schools, with the goal of increasing the number and diversity of students who are proficient in science and pursue careers in STEM."<strong>&nbsp;</strong></p> <p>RITES is teacher-centric, focusing on science teachers in public middle and high schools. Its program has three (3) overarching goals: <em>One</em>, Develop and sustain a partnership centered on K-12 and higher education (HE) communities, but inclusive of other stakeholders that share a vision for improved STEM education throughout the state (<strong>Figure 2</strong>)<strong>;</strong> <em>Two, </em>Through a rich offering of professional development (PD) and technology-enhanced materials (TEM) <strong>(Figure 6</strong>) effect improvements in teacher pedagogy and student success in STEM fields (<strong>Figures 3, 4</strong>)<strong>;</strong> and, <em>Three</em>, Document successes and challenges in these efforts, in a manner that informs other STEM initiatives. See Final Report for compilation of documentation.</p> <p>RITES' PD and TEMs are developed by Resource Teams. These teams are higher education (HE) and K-12 faculties collaborating on high-need standards identified by the School Council. This Council is a set of teachers, appointed by their districts, to meet semi-annually with the RPP to advise RITES+C on priority classroom practices and curriculum needs. These products are shared through RITES' publications and presentations. (<strong>Figures 6a,b,c</strong>) See Final Report for complete list of participants.</p> <p>In 2014, RITES received a supplement from NSF to extend its program and goals to include computer science education (CSE), initially targeting the new AP Computer Science Principles course. The partnership, faculty and staff demonstrated that RITES' structures and processes were also effective in K-12 CSE. As a result, RITES rebranded itself to become today's RITES+C: i.e., RITES <em>and computing. </em>(See banner in <strong>Figure 1.</strong>)</p> <p>The RITES partnership evolved over the first 3 years to a peer collaborative partnership. All decision-making is shared equally among partners, and a separate School Council was formed to provide a structure for regular feed-back and design ideas directly from teachers to the partnership. (<strong>Figure 2</strong>)<strong> </strong>The partnership continues today with an expanded focus on STEM and computer science disciplines. In line with that, RITES+C is transforming itself from the MSP model to a <em>Researcher-Practitioner Partnership</em> model, with a networked improvement community process replacing its design-based implementation research model.</p> <p>The most significant impacts of RITES are:</p> <ul> <li>75% of RI districts and 70% of science teachers and their students benefit from the science PD. (<strong>Figure 1</strong>)</li> </ul> <ul> <li>25 high schools have added the AP Computer Science Principles course.</li> </ul> <ul> <li>Students of RITES teachers performed significantly higher than students of non-RITES teachers on the state's standardized science assessment of inquiry skills. (<strong>Figure 3</strong>)</li> </ul> <ul> <li>Using teacher generated tests from standardized, national science inventories, 90% of classes and 70% of students achieved high normalized learning gains. (<strong>Figure 4a</strong>)</li> </ul> <ul> <li>Using RT generated tests from standardized, national science inventories, 75% of short course teachers achieved moderate to high normalized learning gains.<strong> </strong>(<strong>Figure 4b</strong>)<strong>&nbsp;</strong></li> </ul> <ul> <li>80% of higher education RT members reported a positive impact on their teaching and a shift in their classroom practices towards student-centered, inquiry-rich lessons.<strong> </strong>(<strong>Figure 4c</strong>)<strong>&nbsp;</strong></li> </ul> <ul> <li>The equity profile of RITES+C CSE and MSP classes parallel the profile of the host schools, excepting gender in CSE. The current ratio there is 1.5 male-to-female. (<strong>Figure 5</strong>)<strong>&nbsp;</strong></li> </ul> <ul> <li>In-class technology use increased significantly, with 94% of RITES teachers increasing their use of technology and 85% of teachers incorporating RITES Investigations into their permanent curricula.</li> </ul> <ul> <li>A total of 41 science investigations were created. The 12 most used investigations have been re-aligned strongly with Common Core State and Next-Generation Science Standards, as both standards-systems were implemented in RI after the investigations were created. (<strong>Figure 6</strong>)</li> </ul> <p>RITES+C continues at URI, progressing towards its vision to effect systemic gains in STEM and computational literacy throughout Rhode Island, and to provide models that can be profitably applied to K-12 systems elsewhere in the country. Its continuing progress and growth can be followed on its website <a href="http://ritesc.org/">http://ritesc.org/</a>. The website itself, like RITES+C, continues to be a work in progress.</p> <p class="p1">&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 05/31/2019<br>      Modified by: Daniel&nbsp;P&nbsp;Murray</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Images (<span id="selectedPhoto0">1</span> of <span class="totalNumber"></span>)           </div> <div class="galControls" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/0831974/0831974_10124342_1558709743403_Fig1_final--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/0831974/0831974_10124342_1558709743403_Fig1_final--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Fig 1. Partnership's Statewide Reach"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/0831974/0831974_10124342_1558709743403_Fig1_final--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Fig 1. Partnership's Statewide Reach"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">The map shows the expansion of RITES across the state, reaching 27 of 36 districts (75%). This was the target set by the project. The right-hand image names the persons and organizations who made the MSP and CS extension possible during their first years.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Howard L. Dooley, Jr.</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Daniel&nbsp;P&nbsp;Murray</div> <div class="imageTitle">Fig 1. Partnership's Statewide Reach</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/0831974/0831974_10124342_1558710095355_Fig2--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/0831974/0831974_10124342_1558710095355_Fig2--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Fig 2. Partnership Success"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/0831974/0831974_10124342_1558710095355_Fig2--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Fig 2. Partnership Success"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">The RITES partnership matured and deepened over the course of the grant, through 2016. The lines show a clear movement towards a level of 'Accomplished' in all 5 aspects measured.Note: RITES used the PRISM rubric for this, which was developed by an MSP. See http://prism.mspnet.org/index.cfm/14307</div> <div class="imageCredit">Howard L. Dooley, Jr. & Gl?nnison de Oliviera</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Creative Commons</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Daniel&nbsp;P&nbsp;Murray</div> <div class="imageTitle">Fig 2. Partnership Success</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/0831974/0831974_10124342_1558710256568_Fig3table--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/0831974/0831974_10124342_1558710256568_Fig3table--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Fig 3. Gains in Inquiry-based Skills"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/0831974/0831974_10124342_1558710256568_Fig3table--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Fig 3. Gains in Inquiry-based Skills"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">New England Common Assessment Program (NECAP) scores show differences in the Science Inquiry sub-scores between RITES and non-RITES students. The left graph visualizes one district, as an example. The right table highlights percent differences.The RITES NECAP Report is in the Year 4 Annual Report.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Howard L. Dooley, Jr. & Stephen Brand</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Daniel&nbsp;P&nbsp;Murray</div> <div class="imageTitle">Fig 3. Gains in Inquiry-based Skills</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/0831974/0831974_10124342_1558714694263_Fig4abc_land--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/0831974/0831974_10124342_1558714694263_Fig4abc_land--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Fig 4. Effects on Stakeholders"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/0831974/0831974_10124342_1558714694263_Fig4abc_land--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Fig 4. Effects on Stakeholders"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">All RITES stakeholders ? Students, Teachers and Higher Ed Faculty ? demonstrated significant changes in their science knowledge & skills after RITES: students by using investigations, teachers by attending the Summer Institute workshops, and HE faculty by co-creating investigations & workshops.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Howard L. Dooley, Jr., Sarah Knowlton, Jay Fogleman, Frieda Reichsman, Joshua Caulkins</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Creative Commons</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Daniel&nbsp;P&nbsp;Murray</div> <div class="imageTitle">Fig 4. Effects on Stakeholders</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/0831974/0831974_10124342_1558715111935_Fig_5--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/0831974/0831974_10124342_1558715111935_Fig_5--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Fig 5. RITES Demographics"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/0831974/0831974_10124342_1558715111935_Fig_5--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Fig 5. RITES Demographics"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">RITES demographics are commensurate with statewide demographics for EL, Special Education, minority and economically disadvantaged. Descriptive statistics are well-aligned in each cohort. All districts & schools are conscientiously working towards equity.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Howard L. Dooley, Jr. & Michael Conti</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Creative Commons</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Daniel&nbsp;P&nbsp;Murray</div> <div class="imageTitle">Fig 5. RITES Demographics</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/0831974/0831974_10124342_1558717009050_FIG6abc_land--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/0831974/0831974_10124342_1558717009050_FIG6abc_land--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Fig 6. Growth of RITES Investigations"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/0831974/0831974_10124342_1558717009050_FIG6abc_land--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Fig 6. Growth of RITES Investigations"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">The growth of the RITES investigations. 6a. Investigations provide ?learning science by doing science?. 6b. Investigations are widely used, by class number & individual students. 6c. Investigations change with changing educational environments. In this way, RITES remains relevant.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Howard L. Dooley, Jr., Amy O'Donnell &  Henry Wladkowski</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Creative Commons</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Daniel&nbsp;P&nbsp;Murray</div> <div class="imageTitle">Fig 6. Growth of RITES Investigations</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[  This is our Project Outcomes Report. The reader is directed as appropriate to the complete Final Report for further details. - The full Final and previous Annual Reports are posted at http://ritesc.org/.  Rhode Island Technology Enhanced Sciences, or RITES, was funded as a National Science Foundation (NSF) Math-Science Partnership in October 2008. RITES continued to evolve its partnership and programs through March 2019. The partnership's host partners are the University of RI (URI), RI College, Johnston, Providence and Westerly Public Schools. See (Figure 1) for eventual partnership statewide reach.    RITES mission statement is "Through the collaborative partnership of RI's public higher education and districts, RITES aims to transform the quality of science teaching and learning at all middle and secondary schools, with the goal of increasing the number and diversity of students who are proficient in science and pursue careers in STEM."   RITES is teacher-centric, focusing on science teachers in public middle and high schools. Its program has three (3) overarching goals: One, Develop and sustain a partnership centered on K-12 and higher education (HE) communities, but inclusive of other stakeholders that share a vision for improved STEM education throughout the state (Figure 2); Two, Through a rich offering of professional development (PD) and technology-enhanced materials (TEM) (Figure 6) effect improvements in teacher pedagogy and student success in STEM fields (Figures 3, 4); and, Three, Document successes and challenges in these efforts, in a manner that informs other STEM initiatives. See Final Report for compilation of documentation.  RITES' PD and TEMs are developed by Resource Teams. These teams are higher education (HE) and K-12 faculties collaborating on high-need standards identified by the School Council. This Council is a set of teachers, appointed by their districts, to meet semi-annually with the RPP to advise RITES+C on priority classroom practices and curriculum needs. These products are shared through RITES' publications and presentations. (Figures 6a,b,c) See Final Report for complete list of participants.  In 2014, RITES received a supplement from NSF to extend its program and goals to include computer science education (CSE), initially targeting the new AP Computer Science Principles course. The partnership, faculty and staff demonstrated that RITES' structures and processes were also effective in K-12 CSE. As a result, RITES rebranded itself to become today's RITES+C: i.e., RITES and computing. (See banner in Figure 1.)  The RITES partnership evolved over the first 3 years to a peer collaborative partnership. All decision-making is shared equally among partners, and a separate School Council was formed to provide a structure for regular feed-back and design ideas directly from teachers to the partnership. (Figure 2) The partnership continues today with an expanded focus on STEM and computer science disciplines. In line with that, RITES+C is transforming itself from the MSP model to a Researcher-Practitioner Partnership model, with a networked improvement community process replacing its design-based implementation research model.  The most significant impacts of RITES are:  75% of RI districts and 70% of science teachers and their students benefit from the science PD. (Figure 1)   25 high schools have added the AP Computer Science Principles course.   Students of RITES teachers performed significantly higher than students of non-RITES teachers on the state's standardized science assessment of inquiry skills. (Figure 3)   Using teacher generated tests from standardized, national science inventories, 90% of classes and 70% of students achieved high normalized learning gains. (Figure 4a)   Using RT generated tests from standardized, national science inventories, 75% of short course teachers achieved moderate to high normalized learning gains. (Figure 4b)    80% of higher education RT members reported a positive impact on their teaching and a shift in their classroom practices towards student-centered, inquiry-rich lessons. (Figure 4c)    The equity profile of RITES+C CSE and MSP classes parallel the profile of the host schools, excepting gender in CSE. The current ratio there is 1.5 male-to-female. (Figure 5)    In-class technology use increased significantly, with 94% of RITES teachers increasing their use of technology and 85% of teachers incorporating RITES Investigations into their permanent curricula.   A total of 41 science investigations were created. The 12 most used investigations have been re-aligned strongly with Common Core State and Next-Generation Science Standards, as both standards-systems were implemented in RI after the investigations were created. (Figure 6)   RITES+C continues at URI, progressing towards its vision to effect systemic gains in STEM and computational literacy throughout Rhode Island, and to provide models that can be profitably applied to K-12 systems elsewhere in the country. Its continuing progress and growth can be followed on its website http://ritesc.org/. The website itself, like RITES+C, continues to be a work in progress.         Last Modified: 05/31/2019       Submitted by: Daniel P Murray]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
