<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Collaborative Research: Development of 2D IR Spectroscopy as a Quantitative Probe of Protein Structure, with Applications to Membrane and Aggregated Proteins</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2008</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2012</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>480000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>480000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03090007</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CHE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Chemistry</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Charles Pibel</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>cpibel@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032920000</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Prof. Martin Zanni at the University of Wisconsin in Madison, and collaborators James Skinner (UW-Madison), Daniel Raleigh (SUNY at Stony Brook), and Sean Decatur (Oberlin College) are supported by the Collaborative Research in Chemistry Program to devise and test methods based on two-dimensional infrared (2D IR) spectroscopy for characterization of protein structure and function.   The techniques are particularly important for studying systems for which NMR and x-ray crystallography are difficult to apply, such as proteins in cell membranes and protein aggregates.  The work brings together a diverse and complementary team of researchers to develop a rigorous protocol for calculating 2D IR spectra from atomistic structural models through a novel combination of theory, experiment, and synthesis.  To develop the theoretical methodology, well-characterized proteins are either isotope-labeled or mutated at individual residues so that the linewidths and/or couplings of specific residues can be measured with 2D IR spectroscopy.  &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;While the work is primarily directed toward developing 2D IR as a tool for protein kinetics, it can be applied to other systems as well.  Undergraduate and graduate students and postdocs involved in this study are being trained to work in a collaborative interdisciplinary and inter-institutional environment.   Participation of underrepresented groups derives from exchange programs among Oberlin, Howard University, Stony Brook, and Wisconsin.  Cyber-infrastructure components include web-conferences to discuss research progress and dissemination of user-friendly software for the theoretical calculation of spectra.  An undergraduate physical chemistry lab experiment is being developed to show how FTIR spectroscopy can be used as a tool for protein secondary structure determination; the experiment will be tested in the physical chemistry lab courses at Wisconsin, Stony Brook, Oberlin, and Howard, and then made available to the broader academic community.  Institutions that lack the needed instrumentation will be able to incorporate this experiment into their curriculum by taking advantage of the web-based remote access features being developed.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>09/03/2008</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/14/2010</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>0832580</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Daniel</FirstName>
<LastName>Raleigh</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>P</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Daniel P Raleigh</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>daniel.raleigh@stonybrook.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6316329547</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000457923</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/03/2008</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>SUNY at Stony Brook</Name>
<CityName>Stony Brook</CityName>
<ZipCode>117940001</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6316329949</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>WEST 5510 FRK MEL LIB</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NY01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>804878247</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>RESEARCH FOUNDATION FOR THE STATE UNIVERSITY OF NEW YORK, THE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>020657151</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[SUNY at Stony Brook]]></Name>
<CityName>Stony Brook</CityName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<ZipCode>117940001</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[WEST 5510 FRK MEL LIB]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NY01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1144</Code>
<Text>Molecular Biophysics</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1991</Code>
<Text>CHEMISTRY PROJECTS</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7246</Code>
<Text>PHYSICS OF LIVING SYSTEMS</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>0000</Code>
<Text>UNASSIGNED</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1144</Code>
<Text>BIOMOLECULAR SYSTEMS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1974</Code>
<Text>ANALYTICAL SEPARATIONS &amp; MEAS.</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1991</Code>
<Text>Chemistry Projects</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7246</Code>
<Text>PHYSICS OF LIVING SYSTEMS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7298</Code>
<Text>COLLABORATIVE RESEARCH</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7468</Code>
<Text>INSTR RES AND INSTR DEVEL FOR BIO RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>OTHR</Code>
<Text>OTHER RESEARCH OR EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0108</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0109</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0110</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2008~240000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2009~120000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2010~120000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>This project was devoted to developing new methods to study the structure of proteins with a focus on types of protein structures that are difficult to study with current methods. Proteins play vital structural and functional roles in cells; they are responsible for catalyzing the chemical reactions necessary for life, for the control &nbsp;of both intra and inter cellular communication, for providing structural scaffolds, for acting as pores or channels through membranes and for controlling metabolism. &nbsp;Protein function is normally related to protein structure. The traditional methods for deducing the structure of protein molecules involves either NMR or X-ray crystallography. While both methods are powerful they can be difficult to apply to protein found in membranes (as many key proteins are) or to aggregated proteins. Protein aggregation occurs in a wide range of diseases and also has important practical consequences for the biotech and biopharma industries. The collaborative team developed new methods based on multi-dimensional infrared spectroscopy (IR) to study the structure of this class of proteins. IR is sensitive to bond vibrations and there are certain vibrations within proteins which report on their structure. Unfortunately, limits in resolution and sensitivity have hindered the application of these methods. The collaborative team developed methods to overcome these problems and demonstrated their new approaches using a type of protein aggregate known as amyloid. The approach involved labeling a site of interest with 13C18O (heavy carbon and heavy oxygen). This shifts the vibration of interest away from the rest of the protein peaks. Two dimensional techniques were developed to provide information on the type of secondary structure formed at the labeled site; i.e. alpha-helix, vs. beta-sheet, vs. turns etc. New methods for labeling proteins had to be developed, the spectroscopic techniques required further refinement and new computational methods had to be established to analyze the resulting data and relate it to structural features. The collaborative team accomplished these goals and demonstrated them using the amyloid structures formed by islet amyloid polypeptide (IAPP). IAPP is a naturally occurring protein which forms amyloid in type-2 diabetes and kills the insulin producing beta cells.</p> <p>The work involved considerable broader impacts and outreach. A partnership was established with a historically black college. Nemours undergraduates form Wisconsin, Stony brook and Oberlin College took part in the work. A wide range of PhD students were trained. In addition, new laboratory exercises were introduced in our first year chemistry courses.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 12/31/2012<br>      Modified by: Daniel&nbsp;P&nbsp;Raleigh</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ This project was devoted to developing new methods to study the structure of proteins with a focus on types of protein structures that are difficult to study with current methods. Proteins play vital structural and functional roles in cells; they are responsible for catalyzing the chemical reactions necessary for life, for the control  of both intra and inter cellular communication, for providing structural scaffolds, for acting as pores or channels through membranes and for controlling metabolism.  Protein function is normally related to protein structure. The traditional methods for deducing the structure of protein molecules involves either NMR or X-ray crystallography. While both methods are powerful they can be difficult to apply to protein found in membranes (as many key proteins are) or to aggregated proteins. Protein aggregation occurs in a wide range of diseases and also has important practical consequences for the biotech and biopharma industries. The collaborative team developed new methods based on multi-dimensional infrared spectroscopy (IR) to study the structure of this class of proteins. IR is sensitive to bond vibrations and there are certain vibrations within proteins which report on their structure. Unfortunately, limits in resolution and sensitivity have hindered the application of these methods. The collaborative team developed methods to overcome these problems and demonstrated their new approaches using a type of protein aggregate known as amyloid. The approach involved labeling a site of interest with 13C18O (heavy carbon and heavy oxygen). This shifts the vibration of interest away from the rest of the protein peaks. Two dimensional techniques were developed to provide information on the type of secondary structure formed at the labeled site; i.e. alpha-helix, vs. beta-sheet, vs. turns etc. New methods for labeling proteins had to be developed, the spectroscopic techniques required further refinement and new computational methods had to be established to analyze the resulting data and relate it to structural features. The collaborative team accomplished these goals and demonstrated them using the amyloid structures formed by islet amyloid polypeptide (IAPP). IAPP is a naturally occurring protein which forms amyloid in type-2 diabetes and kills the insulin producing beta cells.  The work involved considerable broader impacts and outreach. A partnership was established with a historically black college. Nemours undergraduates form Wisconsin, Stony brook and Oberlin College took part in the work. A wide range of PhD students were trained. In addition, new laboratory exercises were introduced in our first year chemistry courses.             Last Modified: 12/31/2012       Submitted by: Daniel P Raleigh]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
