<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>CREST: Center for Innovative Information Systems Engineering</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2008</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2016</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>5000000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>5715513</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Cooperative Agreement</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>11060000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>EHR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>HRD</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Human Resource Development</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Victor Santiago</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>vsantiag@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924673</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Florida International University?s (FIU?s) proposed second-phase NSF CREST Center for Innovative Information Systems Engineering brings together a multidisciplinary group of researchers, large-scale collaborative relationships, and a broad ecosystem of partners to perform research that will lead to information technologies that help to solve critical societal problems of national priority. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Intellectual Merit: Each of the Center?s mutually-supportive subprojects builds on the strong research foundation established by FIU?s first-phase CREST award and each sets ambitious research goals that will result in the increased competitiveness of FIU?s CISE researchers. By intertwining these multidisciplinary research goals with CREST?s comprehensive education environment and by leveraging the synergistic academic and industry partnerships introduced above, the Subprojects provide one another with strong impetus for cohesiveness and potential for new research findings and educational breakthroughs: Subproject 1: Effective Access to Complex Multimodal Data with Applications in Disaster Mitigation will focus on developing effective techniques for managing and providing access to data that varies in type, source, location, time, and certainty by addressing storage optimization, data management, indexing and search, query techniques, and data presentation. Among its applications, it seeks to develop techniques to get the right information to the right people at the right time, thereby helping to mitigate disasters and to recover from them quickly. Subproject 2: Integrated Approach to Information Processing in Neuroscience focuses on an integrated imaging/signal processing approach that will result in comprehensive views of the human brain in greater depth and detail through faster, affordable, more effective, and less invasive methods. Subproject 3: Human Computer Interaction for Universal Access has a long-term goal of enabling any prospective computer user to interact with computer-based systems, regardless of their disability status and regardless of the interaction challenges derived from the context in which the interaction is taking place. Subproject 4: Complex System Modeling, Analysis, and Realization will focus on essential methodologies for modeling complex systems, a unified underlying semantic model, fundamental methods for compositional model analysis, and model-driven engineering technologies. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Broader Impacts: The Center will build upon the solid research foundation and flourishing educational pipeline developed over the course of FIU's first-phase CREST funding. Its research program will develop effective techniques for managing information, for modeling information, natural, and man-made systems, and for providing access to information while its educational program strives to become the nation?s leader in training underrepresented Ph.D. students in Computer Science and Computer Engineering. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The proposed research areas cross the boundaries of computer science and engineering, information processing, situational awareness, assistive technology, and neuroscience; this integrative approach of research will significantly advance the body of knowledge in these important fields and will make strides to solving some of society?s critical problems.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/26/2008</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>11/16/2015</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>CoopAgrmnt</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.076</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>0833093</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Naphtali</FirstName>
<LastName>Rishe</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>D</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Naphtali D Rishe</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>rishen@cs.fiu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>3053482025</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000462518</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/26/2008</StartDate>
<EndDate>07/10/2009</EndDate>
<RoleCode>Former Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Naphtali</FirstName>
<LastName>Rishe</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>D</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Naphtali D Rishe</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>rishen@cs.fiu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>3053482025</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000462518</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>11/16/2015</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Xudong</FirstName>
<LastName>He</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Xudong He</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>hex@cs.fiu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>3053481831</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000245346</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/26/2008</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Malek</FirstName>
<LastName>Adjouadi</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Malek Adjouadi</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>adjouadi@fiu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>3053483019</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000365625</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/26/2008</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Yi</FirstName>
<LastName>Deng</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Yi Deng</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>Yi.Deng@uncc.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>7046878450</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000485719</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/26/2008</StartDate>
<EndDate>07/10/2009</EndDate>
<RoleCode>Former Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Armando</FirstName>
<LastName>Barreto</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>B</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Armando B Barreto</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>barretoa@fiu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>3053483711</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000483295</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/26/2008</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Shu-Ching</FirstName>
<LastName>Chen</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Shu-Ching Chen</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>chens@cs.fiu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>3053483480</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000289573</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/25/2009</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Florida International University</Name>
<CityName>Miami</CityName>
<ZipCode>331990001</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>3053482494</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>11200 SW 8TH ST</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[MARC 430]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Florida</StateName>
<StateCode>FL</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>26</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>FL26</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>071298814</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>FLORIDA INTERNATIONAL UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>159621697</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Florida International University]]></Name>
<CityName>Miami</CityName>
<StateCode>FL</StateCode>
<ZipCode>331990001</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[11200 SW 8TH ST]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Florida</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>26</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>FL26</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<FoaInformation>
<Code>0116000</Code>
<Name>Human Subjects</Name>
</FoaInformation>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1714</Code>
<Text>Special Projects - CNS</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>6892</Code>
<Text>CI REUSE</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>9131</Code>
<Text>Centers for Rsch Excell in S&amp;T</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7433</Code>
<Text>CyberInfra Frmwrk 21st (CIF21)</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9131</Code>
<Text>CENTERS FOR RSCH EXCELL IN S&amp;T</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9179</Code>
<Text>GRADUATE INVOLVEMENT</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>SMET</Code>
<Text>SCIENCE, MATH, ENG &amp; TECH EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0112</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0115</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0408</Code>
<Name>NSF Education &amp; Human Resource</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040106</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0410</Code>
<Name>NSF Education &amp; Human Resource</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040106</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0411</Code>
<Name>NSF Education &amp; Human Resource</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040106</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0412</Code>
<Name>NSF Education &amp; Human Resource</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040106</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0415</Code>
<Name>NSF Education &amp; Human Resource</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040106</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2008~2000000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2010~2075000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2011~1175000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2012~175000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2015~290513</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Florida International University's (FIU's) Center for Innovative Information Systems Engineering (http://crest.fiu.edu), the second phase of a National Science Foundation Center for Excellence in Science and Technology (CREST) had six major objectives across four research subprojects. CREST's subprojects included (1) Effective Access to Complex Multimodal Data with Applications in Disaster Mitigation, (2) Integrated Approach to Information Processing in Neuroscience, (3) Human Computer Interaction for Universal Access, and (4) Complex System Modeling, Analysis, and Realization; these subprojects combined to perform synergistic transformative research with direct relevance to critical societal problems of national priority, including disaster management, universal access, and brain research/neuroscience. Presented below are achievements made toward each objective as well as ways that this award established a foundation for further efforts.</p> <p class="p1">Objective 1: <em>Enhancement of the research capabilities developed as a result of this funding in the subproject areas</em>. Each research subproject produced strong research papers and were awarded peer-reviewed funding to build upon the research capabilities made possible by CREST. Four of our CREST faculty members received NSF CAREER awards; one of them also received a US Department of Energy Early Career PI award. Other examples included an NSF PFI/AIR award that enabled us to strengthen our ability to move CREST research into the pipeline for technology transfer as well as an NSF III Large award, where FIU was the lead partner in a collaboration with UIC, Northwestern, and Brown, to study Moving Object Databases for Exploration of Virtual and Real Environments http://cake.fiu.edu/MOD/.</p> <p class="p1">Objective 2: <em>Produce new knowledge. </em>Each research thrust conducted deepening research in its area of concentration. This CREST facilitated new knowledge formation by hosting international research conferences, which showcased FIU&rsquo;s strengths as an up and coming university.</p> <p class="p1">Objective 3: <em>Augment the national research competitiveness of individual faculty and students. </em>CREST helped us build FIU's infrastructure for research. For example, the donation of a $3.6 million supercomputing cluster by IBM resulted in the School of Computer Science retrofitting a suite of rooms with additional cooling and electrical capacity to enable the use of this hardware. We developed new courses in data mining and have revamped our courses in distributed processing to better enable the dissemination of our research to students. Recent MRI and MRI-R2 awards are enabling CREST faculty teams to build instruments with new capabilities that will enhance our research competitiveness by enabling new basic research and by merging engineering and computing disciplines in the realm of neuroscience. As an example, FIU is developing an Integrated Neuroimaging Instrument with Temporal and Spatial Alignments that will lead to new understanding of the functional mappings of the brain in its normal and pathology states focusing on key neurological disorders.</p> <p class="p1">Objective 4: <em>Promote organizational connections and linkages between FIU and other organizations. </em>We established strong research collaborations with industry, with other universities, and with the local community. These research collaborations have resulted in the submission of proposals to the NSF and other funding agencies and have resulted in a $1.4M endowment for CREST-related research, a wide-ranging international PIRE collaboration, a Broadening Participation in Computing Alliance, a thriving multi-institutional NSF Industry/University Cooperative Research Center, and a USDOT TIGER-funded effort to support an innovative package of smart transit and parking technology http://uc.fiu.edu.</p> <p class="p1">Objective 5: <em>Foster integration of research and education. </em>Our students were actively involved in research and co-authored papers in each thrust. Students regularly attended cross-thrust research presentations to get a feel for the work being performed in each subproject and attended regular in-thrust research discussions to keep each other up to speed on what is going on in their own research.</p> <p class="p1">Objective 6: <em>To increase participation in CISE disciplines by diverse student population. </em>This CREST made significant impacts to the number of minority and women PhD graduates in computing. The most recent CRA Taulbee Survey reported that, among 2014-2015 computer science PhD graduates, fewer than 3% were Hispanic or Black and fewer than 19% were women; the figures in computer engineering were even lower. This CREST graduated 87 PhD students in computer science and computer engineering - 31% were Hispanic or Black and 28% were women; it also graduated 81 MS students in these fields - 46% were Hispanic or Black and 26% were women. The caliber of our student assistant group is exemplified by Shonda and Shalisha Witherspoon, who were undergraduate research assistants of Dr. Rishe, till both these African American women graduated with the highest GPA in the College of Engineering and Computing for the Spring 2016 commencement: 3.95, and have become our graduate assistants from Fall 2016.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 03/29/2017<br>      Modified by: Naphtali&nbsp;D&nbsp;Rishe</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Images (<span id="selectedPhoto0">1</span> of <span class="totalNumber"></span>)           </div> <div class="galControls" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/0833093/0833093_10026483_1490789672572_Rishe-Witherspoon--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/0833093/0833093_10026483_1490789672572_Rishe-Witherspoon--rgov-800width.jpg" title="CREST PI and Students"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/0833093/0833093_10026483_1490789672572_Rishe-Witherspoon--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="CREST PI and Students"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Shonda and Shalisha Witherspoon, then undergraduate research assistants of Dr. Rishe, both graduated with the highest GPA in the College of Engineering and Computing for the Spring 2016 commencement: 3.95. Shonda and Shalisha became graduate assistants in the Fall of 2016.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Florida International University</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Naphtali&nbsp;D&nbsp;Rishe</div> <div class="imageTitle">CREST PI and Students</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/0833093/0833093_10026483_1490790079178_2016Cover--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/0833093/0833093_10026483_1490790079178_2016Cover--rgov-800width.jpg" title="FIU Technology Featured on Cover of I/UCRC Compendium"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/0833093/0833093_10026483_1490790079178_2016Cover--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="FIU Technology Featured on Cover of I/UCRC Compendium"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">The 2016 edition of the NSF Industry-Nominated Technology Breakthroughs of NSF Industry/University Cooperative Research Centers (I/UCRC) featured FIU technology; the FIU I/UCRC Center for Advanced Knowledge Enablement was leveraged from the FIU CREST.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Public Domain NSF Report</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Public Domain</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Naphtali&nbsp;D&nbsp;Rishe</div> <div class="imageTitle">FIU Technology Featured on Cover of I/UCRC Compendium</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/0833093/0833093_10026483_1490790219267_2014_NSF-IUCRC-Compendium_2014-cover-showing_TerraFly_and_ALTA--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/0833093/0833093_10026483_1490790219267_2014_NSF-IUCRC-Compendium_2014-cover-showing_TerraFly_and_ALTA--rgov-800width.jpg" title="FIU Technology Featured on Cover of I/UCRC Compendium"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/0833093/0833093_10026483_1490790219267_2014_NSF-IUCRC-Compendium_2014-cover-showing_TerraFly_and_ALTA--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="FIU Technology Featured on Cover of I/UCRC Compendium"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">The 2014 edition of the NSF Industry-Nominated Technology Breakthroughs of NSF Industry/University Cooperative Research Centers (I/UCRC) featured FIU technology; the FIU I/UCRC Center for Advanced Knowledge Enablement was leveraged from the FIU CREST.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Public Domain NSF Report</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Public Domain</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Naphtali&nbsp;D&nbsp;Rishe</div> <div class="imageTitle">FIU Technology Featured on Cover of I/UCRC Compendium</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Florida International University's (FIU's) Center for Innovative Information Systems Engineering (http://crest.fiu.edu), the second phase of a National Science Foundation Center for Excellence in Science and Technology (CREST) had six major objectives across four research subprojects. CREST's subprojects included (1) Effective Access to Complex Multimodal Data with Applications in Disaster Mitigation, (2) Integrated Approach to Information Processing in Neuroscience, (3) Human Computer Interaction for Universal Access, and (4) Complex System Modeling, Analysis, and Realization; these subprojects combined to perform synergistic transformative research with direct relevance to critical societal problems of national priority, including disaster management, universal access, and brain research/neuroscience. Presented below are achievements made toward each objective as well as ways that this award established a foundation for further efforts. Objective 1: Enhancement of the research capabilities developed as a result of this funding in the subproject areas. Each research subproject produced strong research papers and were awarded peer-reviewed funding to build upon the research capabilities made possible by CREST. Four of our CREST faculty members received NSF CAREER awards; one of them also received a US Department of Energy Early Career PI award. Other examples included an NSF PFI/AIR award that enabled us to strengthen our ability to move CREST research into the pipeline for technology transfer as well as an NSF III Large award, where FIU was the lead partner in a collaboration with UIC, Northwestern, and Brown, to study Moving Object Databases for Exploration of Virtual and Real Environments http://cake.fiu.edu/MOD/. Objective 2: Produce new knowledge. Each research thrust conducted deepening research in its area of concentration. This CREST facilitated new knowledge formation by hosting international research conferences, which showcased FIU?s strengths as an up and coming university. Objective 3: Augment the national research competitiveness of individual faculty and students. CREST helped us build FIU's infrastructure for research. For example, the donation of a $3.6 million supercomputing cluster by IBM resulted in the School of Computer Science retrofitting a suite of rooms with additional cooling and electrical capacity to enable the use of this hardware. We developed new courses in data mining and have revamped our courses in distributed processing to better enable the dissemination of our research to students. Recent MRI and MRI-R2 awards are enabling CREST faculty teams to build instruments with new capabilities that will enhance our research competitiveness by enabling new basic research and by merging engineering and computing disciplines in the realm of neuroscience. As an example, FIU is developing an Integrated Neuroimaging Instrument with Temporal and Spatial Alignments that will lead to new understanding of the functional mappings of the brain in its normal and pathology states focusing on key neurological disorders. Objective 4: Promote organizational connections and linkages between FIU and other organizations. We established strong research collaborations with industry, with other universities, and with the local community. These research collaborations have resulted in the submission of proposals to the NSF and other funding agencies and have resulted in a $1.4M endowment for CREST-related research, a wide-ranging international PIRE collaboration, a Broadening Participation in Computing Alliance, a thriving multi-institutional NSF Industry/University Cooperative Research Center, and a USDOT TIGER-funded effort to support an innovative package of smart transit and parking technology http://uc.fiu.edu. Objective 5: Foster integration of research and education. Our students were actively involved in research and co-authored papers in each thrust. Students regularly attended cross-thrust research presentations to get a feel for the work being performed in each subproject and attended regular in-thrust research discussions to keep each other up to speed on what is going on in their own research. Objective 6: To increase participation in CISE disciplines by diverse student population. This CREST made significant impacts to the number of minority and women PhD graduates in computing. The most recent CRA Taulbee Survey reported that, among 2014-2015 computer science PhD graduates, fewer than 3% were Hispanic or Black and fewer than 19% were women; the figures in computer engineering were even lower. This CREST graduated 87 PhD students in computer science and computer engineering - 31% were Hispanic or Black and 28% were women; it also graduated 81 MS students in these fields - 46% were Hispanic or Black and 26% were women. The caliber of our student assistant group is exemplified by Shonda and Shalisha Witherspoon, who were undergraduate research assistants of Dr. Rishe, till both these African American women graduated with the highest GPA in the College of Engineering and Computing for the Spring 2016 commencement: 3.95, and have become our graduate assistants from Fall 2016.       Last Modified: 03/29/2017       Submitted by: Naphtali D Rishe]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
