<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>A Randomized Study of the Impact of STEM Mentors with Disabilities on High School Students with Disabilities</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>10/01/2008</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>09/30/2012</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>690000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>766481</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>11060000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>EHR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>HRD</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Human Resource Development</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Mark Leddy</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>mleddy@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924655</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>A Randomized Study of the Impact of STEM Mentors with Disabilities on High School Students with Disabilities is an investigation of the impact of mentoring by adults with disabilities on youth with disabilities in STEM. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The first aim of the Project is to conduct an exploratory randomized clinical trial investigating the extent to which systematic interaction with STEM (science, technology, engineering and mathematics) mentors with disabilities promotes the STEM-related career planning knowledge, self-efficacy, engagement and performance of high school students with disabilities. The proposed study will build upon an established conceptual framework explaining the role of mentors in facilitating students' self-efficacy and achievement, and previous research documenting the benefits of mentoring and, most specifically the benefits of mentoring of youth with disabilities by successful adults with disabilities (e.g., Burgstahler &amp; Cronheim, 2001; Cory &amp; Burgstahler, 2007;Hibbard, Cantor, Charatz, Rosenthal, Ashman, Gundersen, Ireland-Knight, Gordon, Avner, &amp; Gartner, 2002; Powers, Sowers, &amp; Stevens, 1995). The study will feature a three-independent group, randomized block, repeated measures design utilizing multiple-agents, multiple methods, and established protocols and measurement methods. The study includes a three-group comparison: 1) high school students with disabilities exposed to STEM mentors with disabilities; 2) high school students with disabilities exposed to STEM mentors without disabilities; and 3) and high school students with disabilities who are not exposed to mentors. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The second aim of the Project is to specify efficacious STEM mentor program methods and evaluation strategies, based on the study's summative and formative findings, which will be used to advance adoption of efficacious STEM mentoring approaches through a larger replication study of strategic impacts. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;An independent evaluation of the project will be conducted by Kasey McKraken from David Heil and Associates, an organization specializing in the design of science-based education programs, products, and services including project evaluation design and implementation.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The following dissemination strategies will be utilized:&lt;br/&gt;1. In line with the second aim of the project, a replication manual detailing STEM mentor program methods and evaluation approaches, based on the summative and formative findings, will be prepared and comprehensively disseminated.&lt;br/&gt;2. At least 2 manuscripts will be published in professional journals in STEM education, such as Journal of Research in Science Teaching and Journal of Research on Technology in Education, and Science and Technology Policy.&lt;br/&gt;3. The methodology and findings will be presented at a minimum of 4 regional and national conferences, such as the National Science Foundation Annual PI Meeting, American Educational Research Association (AERA) and American Academy for the Advancement of Science (AAAS).&lt;br/&gt;4. Findings will be posted on the Internet through Portland State University?s-Regional Research Institute's web site (http://pdx.edu/rri)&lt;br/&gt;</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>09/04/2008</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>09/14/2010</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.076</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>0834195</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>JoAnn</FirstName>
<LastName>Sowers</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>JoAnn Sowers</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>sowersj@pdx.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5037253423</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000267804</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/04/2008</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Laurie</FirstName>
<LastName>Powers</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Laurie Powers</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>powersl@pdx.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5037253423</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000499981</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/04/2008</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Portland State University</Name>
<CityName>Portland</CityName>
<ZipCode>972070751</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5037259900</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1600 SW 4th Ave</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[Attn: Sponsored Projects Admin]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Oregon</StateName>
<StateCode>OR</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>OR03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>052226800</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>PORTLAND STATE UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>052226800</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Portland State University]]></Name>
<CityName>Portland</CityName>
<StateCode>OR</StateCode>
<ZipCode>972070751</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[1600 SW 4th Ave]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Oregon</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>OR03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<FoaInformation>
<Code>0116000</Code>
<Name>Human Subjects</Name>
</FoaInformation>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1545</Code>
<Text>RES IN DISABILITIES ED</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9178</Code>
<Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>SMET</Code>
<Text>SCIENCE, MATH, ENG &amp; TECH EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0408</Code>
<Name>NSF Education &amp; Human Resource</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040106</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0410</Code>
<Name>NSF Education &amp; Human Resource</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040106</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2008~690000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2010~76481</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The goal of the STEM&nbsp; (Science, Technology, Engineering, and Math) Mentor project was to evaluate the&nbsp; impact of STEM mentors on the STEM-related knowledge, engagement, and&nbsp; confidence of high school students who experience disabilities.&nbsp;<br /><strong>Study&nbsp; Design&nbsp;</strong><br />&nbsp;&nbsp; Participants were70 &nbsp;high school students who&nbsp; either had an Individual Education Plan (IEP) or received accommodations for&nbsp; their disability through a 504 plan.&nbsp;&nbsp;The students were randomly assigned to one of three groups:&nbsp; a) a mentor with a disability, b) a mentor without a disability, and c) no&nbsp; mentor.<br />&nbsp;Measures were&nbsp; collected at three time points: a) at baseline, b) after the mentoring&nbsp; intervention, and c) 4 months after the mentoring intervention was completed. Students were assessed about their knowledge of STEM college, majors, careers, and things that they could do to successfully purse a STEM area; their involvement in STEM extracurricular activities, and their confidence about planning for a STEM career.</p> <p><br /><strong>Key Findings</strong></p> <p>Students who received a STEM mentor made significantly greater gain in their knowledge of STEM major, careers, and activities that they could do to pursue a STEM fields, as well as in engagement in STEM extracurricular activities and their confidence in their ability to plan for a STEM career.There&nbsp; was minimal difference between the gains made by students who had a mentor with&nbsp; a disability and those with a mentor without a disability.Older&nbsp; students (16 to 17 years) made greater gains than younger students (14 to 15&nbsp; years).</p> <p><strong>Key Implications</strong></p> <p>This&nbsp; is the first attempt to experimentally evaluate the impact of STEM mentors on&nbsp; individuals with disabilities. The data suggests that STEM mentoring is an&nbsp; effective means for increasing the knowledge and engagement of youth with&nbsp; disabilities related to STEM, and their confidence to plan for a STEM education&nbsp; and career.</p> <p>Youth&nbsp; with disabilities can and should be included in typical youth programs in which&nbsp; they are matched with mentors without disabilities. However, most will benefit&nbsp; by having the opportunity to interact with some adults with disabilities in&nbsp; STEM fields.</p> <p>The&nbsp; type of mentoring needs to be tailored to the age of the youth. A program in&nbsp; which more &ldquo;fun&rdquo; STEM-related activities were included may have been effective&nbsp; for the younger students in the study.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 01/02/2013<br>      Modified by: Joann&nbsp;Sowers</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The goal of the STEM  (Science, Technology, Engineering, and Math) Mentor project was to evaluate the  impact of STEM mentors on the STEM-related knowledge, engagement, and  confidence of high school students who experience disabilities.  Study  Design     Participants were70  high school students who  either had an Individual Education Plan (IEP) or received accommodations for  their disability through a 504 plan.  The students were randomly assigned to one of three groups:  a) a mentor with a disability, b) a mentor without a disability, and c) no  mentor.  Measures were  collected at three time points: a) at baseline, b) after the mentoring  intervention, and c) 4 months after the mentoring intervention was completed. Students were assessed about their knowledge of STEM college, majors, careers, and things that they could do to successfully purse a STEM area; their involvement in STEM extracurricular activities, and their confidence about planning for a STEM career.   Key Findings  Students who received a STEM mentor made significantly greater gain in their knowledge of STEM major, careers, and activities that they could do to pursue a STEM fields, as well as in engagement in STEM extracurricular activities and their confidence in their ability to plan for a STEM career.There  was minimal difference between the gains made by students who had a mentor with  a disability and those with a mentor without a disability.Older  students (16 to 17 years) made greater gains than younger students (14 to 15  years).  Key Implications  This  is the first attempt to experimentally evaluate the impact of STEM mentors on  individuals with disabilities. The data suggests that STEM mentoring is an  effective means for increasing the knowledge and engagement of youth with  disabilities related to STEM, and their confidence to plan for a STEM education  and career.  Youth  with disabilities can and should be included in typical youth programs in which  they are matched with mentors without disabilities. However, most will benefit  by having the opportunity to interact with some adults with disabilities in  STEM fields.  The  type of mentoring needs to be tailored to the age of the youth. A program in  which more "fun" STEM-related activities were included may have been effective  for the younger students in the study.       Last Modified: 01/02/2013       Submitted by: Joann Sowers]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
