<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Collaborative Research: CDI-Type II: Discovery of Succinct Dynamical Relationships in Large-Scale Biological Data Sets</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/15/2008</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>02/28/2013</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>540000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>589697</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>05010000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>CSE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CCF</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division of Computing and Communication Foundations</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Sankar Basu</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>sabasu@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927843</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>&lt;br/&gt;Collaborative Research:&lt;br/&gt;0836656 (Peter Doerschuk, Cornell University)&lt;br/&gt;0836649 (Bud Mishra, NYU)&lt;br/&gt;0836720 (Sanjoy Mitter and Emery Brown, MIT)&lt;br/&gt;Title: Discovery of Succinct Dynamical Relationships in Large-Scale Biological Data Sets&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;ABSTRACT:&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Many types of information in neuroscience and molecular biology can be described as a set of measurements taken repeatedly as some index changes its value.  In some situations, such as transcriptomic data measuring gene activities, the index is time while in other situations, such as in genetics association study, the index is position in a genomic DNA sequence and, in any case, the complete collection of data is referred to as a time series.  Inference is the process of taking such time series, probably corrupted by errors, and computing answers to the following sorts of questions: (1) What is the system that generated the time series?  For instance, if the system is known to be a differential equation of a specific type, what are the parameter values in the differential equation? (2) Given a completely specified system and a time series, did that system generate that time series?  For instance, if a biologist has hypothesized a system that describes gene expression for a particular set of genes and then measures expression data, is the data compatible with the system, or equivalently, the hypothesis?  (3) Given two time series, were they generated by the same system?  For instance, if the pattern of nerve firings in a neural system is recorded in two different experimental situations, is the pattern the same or is it different?  The four Principal Investigators are focused on three different biological application domains at three different biological scales: (1) the phenotyping of animal and human ethanol-consumption behavior (whole organism scale), (2) the pattern of action potentials measured on ensembles of neurons (cell-population scale), and (3) the time course of gene expressions as governed by the regulatory circuits of the cell (cellular scale).  The types of challenges that are encountered in these applications include the following characteristics: the information is distributed over long periods of time rather than concentrated in time; the systems include delays and feedback paths; and the systems are highly nonlinear, including switching behavior, rather than linear.  The major methodologies that will be developed and combined to solve inference problems in these application areas are: (a) information theory and stochastic control, (b) multi-scale approaches to learning the geometry of the data, and (c) computer algebra and symbolic computation.  For example, to deal with the presence of delay and feedback in neuroscience systems, especially in the context of the interaction between information and stochastic control, requires a fundamental rethinking of classical information theory as it is employed in technology-based communication systems.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;As the cost of computing decreases, computing becomes increasingly pervasive.  A major purpose of pervasive computing is the real-time collection of high-dimensional time series of very diverse types of data including biological, medical, financial, communication systems status, power systems status, etc.  The project will provide computational algorithms and software to analyze this data in more sophisticated ways and thereby extract more sophisticated information.  Action taken upon this more sophisticated information, e.g., personalized medicine based on individualized genomic information or more accurate and flexible control of power systems thereby avoiding blackouts, will have important human and economic benefits to society.  An important component of the project is educational, e.g., three graduate students working on the project will receive tuition and stipend and an unrestricted number of undergraduates will participate through a variety of ways, e.g., project courses.  By attracting talented students to science and technology and providing challenging research experiences, the project will have important work force benefits to society.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>09/02/2008</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/11/2011</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.070</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>0836720</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Sanjoy</FirstName>
<LastName>Mitter</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>K</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Sanjoy K Mitter</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>mitter@mit.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6172532160</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000286025</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/02/2008</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Emery</FirstName>
<LastName>Brown</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>N</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Emery N Brown</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>enbrown1@mit.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6172531000</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000081671</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/02/2008</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Massachusetts Institute of Technology</Name>
<CityName>Cambridge</CityName>
<ZipCode>021394301</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6172531000</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>77 MASSACHUSETTS AVE</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[NE18-901]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
<StateCode>MA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MA07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>001425594</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>MASSACHUSETTS INSTITUTE OF TECHNOLOGY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>001425594</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Massachusetts Institute of Technology]]></Name>
<CityName>Cambridge</CityName>
<StateCode>MA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>021394301</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[77 MASSACHUSETTS AVE]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MA07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<FoaInformation>
<Code>0000912</Code>
<Name>Computer Science</Name>
</FoaInformation>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7751</Code>
<Text>CDI TYPE II</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7798</Code>
<Text>Software &amp; Hardware Foundation</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7721</Code>
<Text>FROM DATA TO KNOWLEDGE</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7752</Code>
<Text>CDI NON SOLICITED RESEARCH</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7945</Code>
<Text>DES AUTO FOR MICRO &amp; NANO SYST</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9218</Code>
<Text>BASIC RESEARCH &amp; HUMAN RESORCS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>HPCC</Code>
<Text>HIGH PERFORMANCE COMPUTING &amp; COMM</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0108</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0111</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2008~540000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2011~49697</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>This project aims to make a contribution to the emerging field of data science, and on the unification of the fields of signal processing, communication and control.&nbsp; The availability of large data sets related to speech signals, images, gene expression data and functional magnetic resonance imaging makes this an important field of study.</p> <p>Fundamentally, there are two different ways the data sets may be exploited.&nbsp; One may seek to understand the limits of what might be learned from data, viewed as observables without making any reference to internal models as generators of the data.&nbsp; On the other hand, one may have generative models (theories) for the production of the data which act as a guide for discovering important phenomena buried in the observable data.&nbsp; An example of this would be looking for the Higgs Boson in the data generated in the Large Hadron Collider.</p> <p>In either case, it is of considerable interest to know whether such data lie in the vicinity of a low-dimensional manifold and if so, constructing such a manifold.&nbsp; This would lead to a better understanding of the topology, structure and symmetries of the data, economical storage and faster algorithms.</p> <p>We have made a rigorous study of this problem, the first of its kind; determined the statistical complexity of testing this hypothesis and also presented an abstract convex programming algorithm for determining the manifold. (Joint work: Charles Fefferman, Princeton; Sanjoy Mitter, MIT; Hariharan Narayanan, U Washington, formerly postdoc at MIT.)</p> <p>In other research, we have generalized the Source-channel Separation Theory of Shannon to certain network settings even when the medium of communication is unknown.&nbsp; This result has important implications for the architecture of communication.&nbsp; (Doctoral thesis of Mukul Agarwal.)</p> <p>Finally, we have assembled a whole neuronal wiring diagram of C. elegans completing earlier work of Sidney Brenner&rsquo;s group and new electron micrographs.&nbsp;</p> <p>The results of our research have been presented in such prestigious conferences as NIPS, and prestigious journals such as <em>IEEE Trans. on Information Theory</em>.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 06/14/2013<br>      Modified by: Emery&nbsp;N&nbsp;Brown</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ This project aims to make a contribution to the emerging field of data science, and on the unification of the fields of signal processing, communication and control.  The availability of large data sets related to speech signals, images, gene expression data and functional magnetic resonance imaging makes this an important field of study.  Fundamentally, there are two different ways the data sets may be exploited.  One may seek to understand the limits of what might be learned from data, viewed as observables without making any reference to internal models as generators of the data.  On the other hand, one may have generative models (theories) for the production of the data which act as a guide for discovering important phenomena buried in the observable data.  An example of this would be looking for the Higgs Boson in the data generated in the Large Hadron Collider.  In either case, it is of considerable interest to know whether such data lie in the vicinity of a low-dimensional manifold and if so, constructing such a manifold.  This would lead to a better understanding of the topology, structure and symmetries of the data, economical storage and faster algorithms.  We have made a rigorous study of this problem, the first of its kind; determined the statistical complexity of testing this hypothesis and also presented an abstract convex programming algorithm for determining the manifold. (Joint work: Charles Fefferman, Princeton; Sanjoy Mitter, MIT; Hariharan Narayanan, U Washington, formerly postdoc at MIT.)  In other research, we have generalized the Source-channel Separation Theory of Shannon to certain network settings even when the medium of communication is unknown.  This result has important implications for the architecture of communication.  (Doctoral thesis of Mukul Agarwal.)  Finally, we have assembled a whole neuronal wiring diagram of C. elegans completing earlier work of Sidney BrennerÆs group and new electron micrographs.   The results of our research have been presented in such prestigious conferences as NIPS, and prestigious journals such as IEEE Trans. on Information Theory.          Last Modified: 06/14/2013       Submitted by: Emery N Brown]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
