<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Lightning Initiation by Streamer Emission from Thundercloud Hydrometeors</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>01/15/2009</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2012</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>235912.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>235912</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>06020105</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>GEO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>AGS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Atmospheric &amp; Geospace Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Bradley F. Smull</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The exact mechanisms responsible for initiation of lightning within thunderstorms is a longstanding and fundamental problem in the field of atmospheric electricity.  Conventional theory rests on the as-yet unproven hypothesis that electron avalanches lead to the formation and growth (through branching) of "streamers," which are comparatively low-temperature filamentary ionization channels.  Existing observational evidence nonetheless indicates that electric fields within thunderstorms rarely exceed 10% of the threshold breakdown field value needed to trigger such avalanches.  It has thus been suggested that streamers may originate in the vicinity of individual hydrometeors (precipitation particles) near which the electric field is locally amplified.  This process has been demonstrated through controlled laboratory experiments.  In pursuit of better understanding of how this process may work in the free atmosphere, the PIs will employ numerical modeling of relevant processes using simplified representations of cloud properties and evaluate their results against available observations. Some specific questions for which answers will be pursued include:&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;   1) What are the perturbations of the thundercloud electric field caused by different types of hydrometeors?&lt;br/&gt;   2) How does a streamer initiate and develop in the vicinity of the hydrometeors?  What is the onset condition of the streamer emission from the hydrometeors?  What are the characteristics of the streamer thus formed?&lt;br/&gt;   3) What are the electrical interactions between streamers and hydrometeors?  What are the effects of the joule heating on the streamer stem?  What is the leader inception condition in the vicinity of hydrometeors?&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The intellectual merit of this work rests on improved understanding of the processes through which lightning is triggered within electrically charged clouds, as well as further critical evaluation of the ability of existing observations to accurately capture the upper-limit of electric field strength achievable within thunderstorms.  Broader impacts will be primarily through graduate and undergraduate student education, dissemination of results via peer-reviewed journals, and the long-term potential for reduced risk to life and property that would come with a better understanding (and hence ability to predict) key processes that initiate lightning within thunderstorms.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>01/08/2009</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>02/04/2011</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.050</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>0838867</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Hamid</FirstName>
<LastName>Rassoul</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>K</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Hamid K Rassoul</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>rassoul@fit.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>3216748778</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000375976</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>01/08/2009</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Joseph</FirstName>
<LastName>Dwyer</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>R</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Joseph R Dwyer</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>Joseph.Dwyer@unh.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6038625408</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000448232</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>01/08/2009</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Ningyu</FirstName>
<LastName>Liu</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME>Dr</PI_SUFX_NAME>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Ningyu Liu</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>Ningyu.Liu@unh.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6038622313</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000211580</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>01/08/2009</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Florida Institute of Technology</Name>
<CityName>MELBOURNE</CityName>
<ZipCode>329016975</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>3216748000</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>150 W UNIVERSITY BLVD</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Florida</StateName>
<StateCode>FL</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>08</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>FL08</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>053396669</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>FLORIDA INSTITUTE OF TECHNOLOGY, INC.</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>053396669</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Florida Institute of Technology]]></Name>
<CityName>MELBOURNE</CityName>
<StateCode>FL</StateCode>
<ZipCode>329016975</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[150 W UNIVERSITY BLVD]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Florida</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>08</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>FL08</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<FoaInformation>
<Code>0000099</Code>
<Name>Other Applications NEC</Name>
</FoaInformation>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1525</Code>
<Text>Physical &amp; Dynamic Meteorology</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>0000</Code>
<Text>UNASSIGNED</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>OTHR</Code>
<Text>OTHER RESEARCH OR EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0109</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0110</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0111</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2009~79823</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2010~76716</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2011~79373</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Electrical breakdown of air leading to lightning initiation in thunderclouds requires that thundercloud electric field exceed the so-called conventional breakdown threshold field. However, many years of thundercloud field measurements consistently give a value about an order of magnitude smaller than that threshold field. It has been suggested that thundercloud electric field can be amplified by thundercloud hydrometeors (small water droplets or ice particles) to trigger the precursors of lightning known as &ldquo;streamers,&rdquo; which are cold filamentary plasma channels.</p> <p>This project completed a theoretical and modeling study of initiation of streamers from thundercloud hydrometeors. Computer simulations were performed to model this process. It was found that streamers can indeed be initiated from thundercloud hydrometeors in the maximum thundercloud electric field measured so far. It was also found that the dimension of the hydrometeor is critical for this process.&nbsp; The modeling results further indicate that the streamers initiated in this way exhibit similar characteristics as those initiated from small electrodes connected to high voltage sources in laboratory experiments or those existing in high-altitude electrical discharges known as sprites. So knowledge of streamers obtained by previous studies on laboratory streamers and sprite streamers can be applied to hydrometeor streamers. &nbsp;In addition, a computer model was developed to study corona discharges &ndash; relatively diffuse, less intense discharges around thundercloud hydrometeors, which normally precede streamer activities. It was found that the maximum hydrometeor charge set by corona discharges agrees with the measured maximum precipitation charge. Overall, the results shed light on the lightning initiation process, a longstanding problem in atmospheric electricity.</p> <p>This project has advanced the current understanding of lightning initiation in thunderstorms. Together with other measurements of thunderstorm activities, improved knowledge of lightning initiation helps make more accurate and timely forecast of severe weather, which are believed to occur more frequently due to climate change. The results also help improve lightning protection practice and mitigate its damage.&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 06/17/2013<br>      Modified by: Ningyu&nbsp;Liu</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Electrical breakdown of air leading to lightning initiation in thunderclouds requires that thundercloud electric field exceed the so-called conventional breakdown threshold field. However, many years of thundercloud field measurements consistently give a value about an order of magnitude smaller than that threshold field. It has been suggested that thundercloud electric field can be amplified by thundercloud hydrometeors (small water droplets or ice particles) to trigger the precursors of lightning known as "streamers," which are cold filamentary plasma channels.  This project completed a theoretical and modeling study of initiation of streamers from thundercloud hydrometeors. Computer simulations were performed to model this process. It was found that streamers can indeed be initiated from thundercloud hydrometeors in the maximum thundercloud electric field measured so far. It was also found that the dimension of the hydrometeor is critical for this process.  The modeling results further indicate that the streamers initiated in this way exhibit similar characteristics as those initiated from small electrodes connected to high voltage sources in laboratory experiments or those existing in high-altitude electrical discharges known as sprites. So knowledge of streamers obtained by previous studies on laboratory streamers and sprite streamers can be applied to hydrometeor streamers.  In addition, a computer model was developed to study corona discharges &ndash; relatively diffuse, less intense discharges around thundercloud hydrometeors, which normally precede streamer activities. It was found that the maximum hydrometeor charge set by corona discharges agrees with the measured maximum precipitation charge. Overall, the results shed light on the lightning initiation process, a longstanding problem in atmospheric electricity.  This project has advanced the current understanding of lightning initiation in thunderstorms. Together with other measurements of thunderstorm activities, improved knowledge of lightning initiation helps make more accurate and timely forecast of severe weather, which are believed to occur more frequently due to climate change. The results also help improve lightning protection practice and mitigate its damage.        Last Modified: 06/17/2013       Submitted by: Ningyu Liu]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
