<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>New GK-12: Partnership between Educators and Researchers for Enhancing Classroom Teaching (PERFECT)</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>04/01/2009</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>03/31/2015</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>1650303.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>2736518</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>11010000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>EHR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DGE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Graduate Education</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Laura Regassa</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>For this new GK-12 project the Virginia Institute of Marine Science will partner with four secondary schools in the Chesapeake Bay region serving students from 15 school districts, from urban to suburban and rural areas. The partners include schools with traditional STEM curricula, as well as schools with a special focus on marine and environmental sciences. A high percentage of the students are from groups traditionally underrepresented in STEM disciplines. The project will allow graduate fellows and faculty to incorporate state-of-the-art science and technology into K-12 STEM education, and use Chesapeake Bay as a locally relevant example to inspire the graders. Each GK-12 graduate fellow will team with an in-service teacher throughout the year. This buddy team format allows the fellow and the teacher to mentor and learn from each other. Teachers will gain valuable hands-on research experience by participating in fellows? research projects. In return, teachers will guide fellows to develop appropriate teaching materials and conduct classroom teaching. Special courses and workshops will be offered to further enhance fellows? and teachers? content understanding and communication skills.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Through this project graduate fellows will gain valuable pedagogical skills and teaching experiences that are not available in traditional graduate training. More importantly, they will cultivate a life-long interest to contribute to K-12 science education via formal and informal means. The project will also strengthen the partnership between researchers and educators in the Chesapeake Bay region, and produce new teaching materials that will benefit the broader K-12 science education communities. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>04/03/2009</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>04/12/2013</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.076</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>0840804</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Iris</FirstName>
<LastName>Anderson</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>C</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Iris C Anderson</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>iris@vims.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>8046847811</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000100420</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/03/2009</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Kam</FirstName>
<LastName>Tang</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>W</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Kam W Tang</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>kamtang@vims.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>8046847602</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000117389</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/03/2009</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>College of William &amp; Mary Virginia Institute of Marine Science</Name>
<CityName>Gloucester Point</CityName>
<ZipCode>230621346</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>8046847000</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>P.O. Box 1346</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Virginia</StateName>
<StateCode>VA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>VA01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>169516213</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>VIRGINIA INSTITUTE OF MARINE SCIENCE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[College of William &amp; Mary Virginia Institute of Marine Scien]]></Name>
<CityName>Gloucester Point</CityName>
<StateCode>VA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>230621346</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[P.O. Box 1346]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Virginia</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>VA01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<FoaInformation>
<Code>0000099</Code>
<Name>Other Applications NEC</Name>
</FoaInformation>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>5284</Code>
<Text>GK-12</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7179</Code>
<Text>GRAD TEACHING FELLOWS IN K-12</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7179</Code>
<Text>GRAD TEACHING FELLOWS IN K-12</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9179</Code>
<Text>GRADUATE INVOLVEMENT</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>SMET</Code>
<Text>SCIENCE, MATH, ENG &amp; TECH EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0109</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0409</Code>
<Name>NSF Education &amp; Human Resource</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040106</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0410</Code>
<Name>NSF Education &amp; Human Resource</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040106</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0411</Code>
<Name>NSF Education &amp; Human Resource</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040106</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0413</Code>
<Name>NSF Education &amp; Human Resource</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040106</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2009~542230</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2010~1085208</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2011~545197</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2013~563883</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><span style="text-decoration: underline;">Intellectual Merits</span></p> <p>It is the mission of the Virginia Institute of Marine Science (VIMS) to prepare future ocean science leaders. Such leaders must be at the forefront of scientific knowledge in their discipline, and be able to apply their research to solving the many problems afflicting marine and aquatic systems and resources. In order for scientific knowledge to impact society as a whole, it is essential that the public is educated and informed of the latest scientific discoveries, yet research scientists are often poorly trained to communicate their science to a wide audience. Not only are Ocean Sciences often lacking from public school curricula, even in many coastal districts, but few teachers are trained to apply examples from the Ocean Sciences to STEM education. Because the Ocean Sciences are highly interdisciplinary, integrating them into K-12 curricula is an ideal way to demonstrate the interconnectedness of various STEM disciplines, and their application to real life problems.</p> <p>&nbsp;For this GK-12 project, VIMS partnered with two middle schools and three high schools serving students from 15 school districts. A high percentage of the students came from underrepresented minority or economically disadvantaged groups. The project supported graduate Fellows from VIMS, who performed as scientists-in-residence in partnering schools, bringing real-life, hands-on Ocean Sciences activities to the classrooms. Selected Teachers from partnering schools were also supported by the project to serve as mentors to the Fellows. By allowing the Fellows and Partner Teachers to work in teams, the project provided the graduate Fellows with opportunities to improve their ability to communicate Ocean Sciences to the public, to develop teaching skills, and to demonstrate to K-12 students and teachers the applicability of STEM education to solving problems related to coastal ocean ecosystems. In return, Fellows helped Teachers to learn the state-of-the-art Ocean Sciences, to develop new teaching ideas and materials, and to pursue the life-long learning necessary for them to educate the future stewards of our ocean systems.</p> <p>Final statistics:</p> <p>47 Graduate Fellowships awarded</p> <p>52 Teachers Fellowships awarded</p> <p>26 VIMS faculty advisors engaged</p> <p>13,160 total classroom hours spent by Fellows</p> <p>~5,500 total grade school students directly impacted by the project</p> <p>&gt;40 new SoL-compliant lesson plans developed</p> <p>&gt;30 new teaching resources developed</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p><span style="text-decoration: underline;">GK-12 impacts as seen by Graduate Fellows</span></p> <p>These are some comments that Fellows provided as they reflected on the impacts that the project had on themselves and the students with whom they interacted:</p> <p>&nbsp;<em>&ldquo;GK-12 has been an amazing experience for me.&nbsp; I have truly grown as a person and as a scientist during the duration of the fellowship. It has definitely made me realize how important communication is.&rdquo;</em></p> <p>&nbsp;<em>&ldquo;I&rsquo;ve gotten better at thinking on my feet, spontaneously creating interactive examples to illustrate concepts.&rdquo;</em></p> <p>&nbsp;<em>&ldquo;I think that the students&rsquo; perception of science/scientists has changed because of my presence in the classroom. &ldquo;</em></p> <p>&nbsp;<em>&ldquo;I think students are thinking more about science because of my presence&hellip;: They tell me about the things they took home to their parents, questions they thought of while I was away and experiences they had that made them think of something they learned in class.&ldquo;</em></p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;<span style="text-decoration: underline;">GK-12 impacts as seen by Partner Teachers</span></p> <p>When Teachers were asked what benefits accrued from having Fellows in their classroom, typical r...]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Intellectual Merits  It is the mission of the Virginia Institute of Marine Science (VIMS) to prepare future ocean science leaders. Such leaders must be at the forefront of scientific knowledge in their discipline, and be able to apply their research to solving the many problems afflicting marine and aquatic systems and resources. In order for scientific knowledge to impact society as a whole, it is essential that the public is educated and informed of the latest scientific discoveries, yet research scientists are often poorly trained to communicate their science to a wide audience. Not only are Ocean Sciences often lacking from public school curricula, even in many coastal districts, but few teachers are trained to apply examples from the Ocean Sciences to STEM education. Because the Ocean Sciences are highly interdisciplinary, integrating them into K-12 curricula is an ideal way to demonstrate the interconnectedness of various STEM disciplines, and their application to real life problems.   For this GK-12 project, VIMS partnered with two middle schools and three high schools serving students from 15 school districts. A high percentage of the students came from underrepresented minority or economically disadvantaged groups. The project supported graduate Fellows from VIMS, who performed as scientists-in-residence in partnering schools, bringing real-life, hands-on Ocean Sciences activities to the classrooms. Selected Teachers from partnering schools were also supported by the project to serve as mentors to the Fellows. By allowing the Fellows and Partner Teachers to work in teams, the project provided the graduate Fellows with opportunities to improve their ability to communicate Ocean Sciences to the public, to develop teaching skills, and to demonstrate to K-12 students and teachers the applicability of STEM education to solving problems related to coastal ocean ecosystems. In return, Fellows helped Teachers to learn the state-of-the-art Ocean Sciences, to develop new teaching ideas and materials, and to pursue the life-long learning necessary for them to educate the future stewards of our ocean systems.  Final statistics:  47 Graduate Fellowships awarded  52 Teachers Fellowships awarded  26 VIMS faculty advisors engaged  13,160 total classroom hours spent by Fellows  ~5,500 total grade school students directly impacted by the project  &gt;40 new SoL-compliant lesson plans developed  &gt;30 new teaching resources developed     GK-12 impacts as seen by Graduate Fellows  These are some comments that Fellows provided as they reflected on the impacts that the project had on themselves and the students with whom they interacted:   "GK-12 has been an amazing experience for me.  I have truly grown as a person and as a scientist during the duration of the fellowship. It has definitely made me realize how important communication is."   "IÆve gotten better at thinking on my feet, spontaneously creating interactive examples to illustrate concepts."   "I think that the studentsÆ perception of science/scientists has changed because of my presence in the classroom. "   "I think students are thinking more about science because of my presence&hellip;: They tell me about the things they took home to their parents, questions they thought of while I was away and experiences they had that made them think of something they learned in class."      GK-12 impacts as seen by Partner Teachers  When Teachers were asked what benefits accrued from having Fellows in their classroom, typical responses included:  "More real-world data relevant to our environment in the Chesapeake Bay, not just &hellip; examples in a textbook."   "I am now better able to demonstrate the practical/applied value of scientific research, based on the work that fellows are doing ..."   "The program has brought greater variety into the classroom, more areas of science, greater diversity of teaching styles, plus real science career exposure for students that wouldnÆt have it othe...]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
