<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>A Deep-Biosphere Research Coordination Network</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>06/01/2009</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2015</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>499418.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>499418</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>08010206</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>BIO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DEB</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Environmental Biology</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Simon Malcomber</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>smalcomb@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032928227</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Scientists have postulated the existence of a widespread community of microorganisms living at high temperatures kilometers below the Earth's surface, supported by geological energy sources.  The purpose of this Research Coordination Network is to foster a growing, dynamic, and predominantly young community of scientists studying life that exists in the dark, deep marine biosphere.  The ramifications of this subsurface hidden biosphere are numerous and may lead to paradigm shifts in the biosciences and geosciences.  To date, deep biosphere studies have focused on microbes in relatively shallow marine sediments or in terrestrial mines, wells, and drill-core samples.  However, these data do not permit a true global census of subsurface life.  The largest potential subsurface biome is also the least accessible:  the deep ocean subsurface.  This biome also has importance for global-scale biogeochemical processes, including the carbon, energy, and nutrient cycles.  Depending on geothermal gradients and physico-chemical limits of life, the subsurface biosphere may extend to a depth of 5-10 km, or more, and occupy a volume several orders of magnitude greater than the continental biosphere.  &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The RCN will develop coordinate science activities in the community of deep-biosphere researchers.  It will also promote education among several disciplines that contribute to the research through interlaboratory exchanges for students in this field.  The RCN will meet these goals through meetings, workshops, student exchanges, and a web site.  Additional activities for outreach include newsletters, web sites for information on tools and techniques, and special sessions at scientific meetings.  The RCN will establish a research institute named DEBI (Dark Energy Biosphere Institute) that will foster the growth of research into the deep biosphere.&lt;br/&gt;</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>05/22/2009</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/26/2013</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.074</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>0840985</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Jan</FirstName>
<LastName>Amend</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>P</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Jan P Amend</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>janamend@usc.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2138212267</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000449896</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/22/2009</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Katrina</FirstName>
<LastName>Edwards</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>J</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Katrina J Edwards</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>kje@usc.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2137406779</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000279010</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/22/2009</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Southern California</Name>
<CityName>Los Angeles</CityName>
<ZipCode>900890001</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2137407762</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>University Park</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[3720 S. Flower St.]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>37</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CA37</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>072933393</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF SOUTHERN CALIFORNIA</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>072933393</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Southern California]]></Name>
<CityName>Los Angeles</CityName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>900890001</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[University Park]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>37</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CA37</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1620</Code>
<Text>Marine Geology and Geophysics</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1650</Code>
<Text>BIOLOGICAL OCEANOGRAPHY</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>5720</Code>
<Text>OCEAN DRILLING PROGRAM</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7374</Code>
<Text>Systematics &amp; Biodiversity Sci</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1664</Code>
<Text>RESEARCH COORD NETWK IN BIO SC</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9169</Code>
<Text>BIODIVERSITY AND ECOSYSTEM DYNAMICS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>EGCH</Code>
<Text>ENVIRONMENT AND GLOBAL CHANGE</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0109</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0110</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0111</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0112</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0113</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2009~128188</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2010~94292</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2011~96924</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2012~88772</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2013~91242</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The marine subsurface may be the largest biome on Earth, but it is also the least accessible. The last decade has seen a tremendous growth in deep biosphere research activities, focusing on global-scale biogeochemical cycling of carbon and energy and on a census of subsurface life and metabolic activities.&nbsp; This RCN supported and enhanced a growing, dynamic, and predominantly young community of scientists interested in life deep in rocks and sediments, away from sunlight and surface nutrients.</p> <p>Participation in this RCN was open to and encouraged for all scientists in the US and abroad with serious interests in deep biosphere research. An overall growth of our program was evidenced by the number of participants in year one (203) compared to currently (over 900).&nbsp; We developed a comprehensive website (<a href="http://www.darkenergybiosphere.org/RCN">http://www.darkenergybiosphere.org/RCN</a>) with archived information about our programs and activities.&nbsp; These programs have a lasting legacy in C-DEBI which continues to identify research, education and outreach activities in the website and bi-weekly newsletter.</p> <p>The goals of this RCN were to:</p> <ul> <li>Develop an      interactive <em>community</em> of      deep-biosphere researchers;</li> <li>Facilitate <em>coordination</em> of science <em>between</em> deep-biosphere drilling      projects;</li> <li>Stimulate <em>interaction</em> and <em>education</em> among the disparate      disciplines that contribute to and benefit from deep-biosphere research;</li> <li>Enable <em>synthesis</em> and <em>integration</em> of data and technology advances generated from      deep-biosphere projects;</li> <li>Support <em>interlaboratory</em> exchanges for      students in deep-biosphere research, towards building not only a <em>present</em>, but also a <em>future</em> community of deep-biosphere      researchers.</li> </ul> <p>Annual, theme-based meetings addressed the research and coordination efforts of the deep biosphere community. These meetings enabled scientists and students to exchange ideas in deep biosphere studies, to learn about practical developments and study opportunities in the field, and to coordinate research and education activities. Each meeting was part <em>scientific conference</em> and part <em>training workshop;</em>&nbsp;both parts focused on a specific theme within deep biosphere research. In the conference portion, research activities and findings were presented to a broadly trained, but scientifically focused audience. In the training workshop, key research techniques and methods that are commonly employed were presented objectively and the pros and cons were discussed and debated.</p> <p>The key themes at these meetings included microbiology in sediments and basement rock, organic geochemistry and biosignatures, bioenergetics, hydrogeology, and drilling and sampling technology. The meetings were chaired by steering committee members from the University of Hawaii (2009), University of North Carolina (2011), MARUM, University of Bremen, Germany (2012), and University of Southern California (2014) and held in proximity.&nbsp; Of the 205 total workshop attendees, 57 were graduate students, 38 were postdoctoral scholars, and another 30-40 &nbsp;attendees fell into the &lsquo;young scientist&rsquo; category. A summary report that highlights key findings and method protocols was posted after each meeting on the RCN website.</p> <p>Our research exchange program provided support to students and postdoctoral scholars to travel to state-of-the-art laboratories around the world.&nbsp; For example, students could apply to spend 1-6 months in a host lab to carry out key experiments, use specialized analytical equipment, learn new modeling approaches, or join a research cruise &ndash; research activities that may be prohibitively difficult or impossible at their home institutions.&nbsp; Six g...]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The marine subsurface may be the largest biome on Earth, but it is also the least accessible. The last decade has seen a tremendous growth in deep biosphere research activities, focusing on global-scale biogeochemical cycling of carbon and energy and on a census of subsurface life and metabolic activities.  This RCN supported and enhanced a growing, dynamic, and predominantly young community of scientists interested in life deep in rocks and sediments, away from sunlight and surface nutrients.  Participation in this RCN was open to and encouraged for all scientists in the US and abroad with serious interests in deep biosphere research. An overall growth of our program was evidenced by the number of participants in year one (203) compared to currently (over 900).  We developed a comprehensive website (http://www.darkenergybiosphere.org/RCN) with archived information about our programs and activities.  These programs have a lasting legacy in C-DEBI which continues to identify research, education and outreach activities in the website and bi-weekly newsletter.  The goals of this RCN were to:  Develop an      interactive community of      deep-biosphere researchers; Facilitate coordination of science between deep-biosphere drilling      projects; Stimulate interaction and education among the disparate      disciplines that contribute to and benefit from deep-biosphere research; Enable synthesis and integration of data and technology advances generated from      deep-biosphere projects; Support interlaboratory exchanges for      students in deep-biosphere research, towards building not only a present, but also a future community of deep-biosphere      researchers.   Annual, theme-based meetings addressed the research and coordination efforts of the deep biosphere community. These meetings enabled scientists and students to exchange ideas in deep biosphere studies, to learn about practical developments and study opportunities in the field, and to coordinate research and education activities. Each meeting was part scientific conference and part training workshop; both parts focused on a specific theme within deep biosphere research. In the conference portion, research activities and findings were presented to a broadly trained, but scientifically focused audience. In the training workshop, key research techniques and methods that are commonly employed were presented objectively and the pros and cons were discussed and debated.  The key themes at these meetings included microbiology in sediments and basement rock, organic geochemistry and biosignatures, bioenergetics, hydrogeology, and drilling and sampling technology. The meetings were chaired by steering committee members from the University of Hawaii (2009), University of North Carolina (2011), MARUM, University of Bremen, Germany (2012), and University of Southern California (2014) and held in proximity.  Of the 205 total workshop attendees, 57 were graduate students, 38 were postdoctoral scholars, and another 30-40  attendees fell into the æyoung scientistÆ category. A summary report that highlights key findings and method protocols was posted after each meeting on the RCN website.  Our research exchange program provided support to students and postdoctoral scholars to travel to state-of-the-art laboratories around the world.  For example, students could apply to spend 1-6 months in a host lab to carry out key experiments, use specialized analytical equipment, learn new modeling approaches, or join a research cruise &ndash; research activities that may be prohibitively difficult or impossible at their home institutions.  Six graduate students and postdoctoral scholars from across the US were supported in research exchanges to laboratories with cutting edge facilities and distinguished expertise including the Lawrence Berkeley National Laboratory, University of Hawaii, University of Bremen (MARUM, Germany), and Kochi Institute for Core Sample Research (JAMSTEC, Japan).  These exc...]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
