<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Collaborative Research:Feammox-a new pathway for nitrogen loss from terrestrial ecosystems</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>05/01/2009</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>04/30/2014</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>188676.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>202210</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>08010209</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>BIO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DEB</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Environmental Biology</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Henry L. Gholz</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Nitrogen is a key nutrient to microbes, plants and animals, and considerable research has been directed at understanding the controls on it's retention and loss in terrestrial ecosystems. Despite this effort, much uncertainty remains, especially with regard to gaseous nitrogen losses. This is particularly troubling in the context of human modification of the nitrogen cycle, which is dramatically increasing nitrogen pollution, runoff, and the emission of nitrous oxide, a radiatively important greenhouse gas. This research will contribute to our understanding of the terrestrial nitrogen cycle by quantifying the role of "Feammox", a newly discovered pathway in the global nitrogen cycle. Feammox is the anaerobic oxidation of ammonium coupled to ferric iron [Fe (III)] reduction. It has the potential to produce inert dinitrogen gas as well as reactive nitrite, which could subsequently be reduced to gaseous or organic nitrogen, or ammonium under anaerobic conditions. Given the potential gaseous loss of nitrogen from terrestrial environments, this pathway may play a significant role in the global nitrogen cycle. The proposed research will place this newly discovered nitrogen transformation pathway in the context of the larger nitrogen cycle by (i) determining if Feammox is mediated by soil microbes, and if so identify the responsible organisms, (ii) determining the relative importance of iron- and nitrogen-containing compounds as controls on Feammox, and (iii) quantifying the role of Feammox in total nitrogen gas emissions from soils. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The collaborative research between a soil biogeochemistry laboratory at the University of California at Berkeley and a microbial biogeochemistry laboratory at the University of Nebraska, Lincoln will improve the mechanistic understanding of terrestrial nitrogen cycling. Field work will take place at the Luquillo Long Term Ecological Research site in Puerto Rico. The research addresses a previously unquantified pathway in terrestrial ecosystems that not only has implications for nutrient retention in soils, but could also evolve nitrous oxide, a greenhouse gas implicated in global change. This project will support for an early career female scientist, two graduate students, one undergraduate student, and one postdoctoral researcher. In concert with sample collection in Puerto Rico workshops and training activities will be held for Puerto Rican high school students. Science cafes in Puerto Rico and California will provide an ecology and global change educational outreach component to the public at large.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>04/15/2009</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>02/10/2011</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.074</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>0841993</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Karrie</FirstName>
<LastName>Weber</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>A</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Karrie A Weber</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>kweber2@unl.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>4024721825</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000508365</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/15/2009</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</Name>
<CityName>Lincoln</CityName>
<ZipCode>685031435</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>4024723171</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>151 Prem S. Paul Research Center</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[2200 Vine St]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Nebraska</StateName>
<StateCode>NE</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NE01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>555456995</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>BOARD OF REGENTS OF THE UNIVERSITY OF NEBRASKA</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>068662618</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Nebraska-Lincoln]]></Name>
<CityName>Lincoln</CityName>
<StateCode>NE</StateCode>
<ZipCode>685031435</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[151 Prem S. Paul Research Center]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Nebraska</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NE01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1181</Code>
<Text>ECOSYSTEM STUDIES</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EPSCoR Co-Funding</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1181</Code>
<Text>ECOSYSTEM STUDIES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1228</Code>
<Text>MINORITY INVOLVEMENT -- BIO</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1355</Code>
<Text>EGC EDUCATIONAL ACTIVITIES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9169</Code>
<Text>BIODIVERSITY AND ECOSYSTEM DYNAMICS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9178</Code>
<Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9251</Code>
<Text>REU SUPP-Res Exp for Ugrd Supp</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>EGCH</Code>
<Text>ENVIRONMENT AND GLOBAL CHANGE</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>SMET</Code>
<Text>SCIENCE, MATH, ENG &amp; TECH EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0109</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0110</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0111</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2009~188676</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2010~5999</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2011~7535</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Nitrogen is a nutrient required by all life.&nbsp; As such it is important to understand nitrogen retention and loss in soils within terrestrial ecosystems. The oxidation of ammonium to nitrate can lead to nitrogen loss either through leaching from the soil into groundwater or denitrification reactions producing gaseous nitrogen in terrestrial ecosystems.&nbsp; However in anoxic aquatic environments ammonium can be oxidized leading to gaseous dinitrogen gas production through a process called anammox. As a result of this project we identified a new process in the nitrogen cycle leading to the oxidation of ammonium coupled to the reduction of iron oxides or &ldquo;rust&rdquo;.&nbsp; This process has been termed Feammox.&nbsp; This process was determined to account for a significant amount of nitrogen loss from the soil.&nbsp; This likely to be a globally significant process that can account for nitrogen losses from ecosystems rich in iron minerals.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>This collaborative research project between the University of California at Berkeley and the University of Nebraska, Lincoln has improved the mechanistic understanding of terrestrial nitrogen retention and loss in soils.&nbsp; This project supported an early career female scientist, one female postdoctoral researcher, two graduate students, and undergraduate students. From among the undergraduates supported by this project, three of the students that participated in this study are members of underrepresented populations in the STEM fields (African American, Native American, and a woman).&nbsp; The Native American student enrolled at Little Priest Tribal College in Nebraska was supported by REU supplements during the summer of 2010 and 2011. Additional public outreach events were held through numerous venues and events with the YWCA Smart Girls Club and the University of Nebraska State Museum (Dinosaurs and Disasters and Sunday with a Scientist) to communicate the results of this project to the public.&nbsp; &nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 01/14/2016<br>      Modified by: Karrie&nbsp;A&nbsp;Weber</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Nitrogen is a nutrient required by all life.  As such it is important to understand nitrogen retention and loss in soils within terrestrial ecosystems. The oxidation of ammonium to nitrate can lead to nitrogen loss either through leaching from the soil into groundwater or denitrification reactions producing gaseous nitrogen in terrestrial ecosystems.  However in anoxic aquatic environments ammonium can be oxidized leading to gaseous dinitrogen gas production through a process called anammox. As a result of this project we identified a new process in the nitrogen cycle leading to the oxidation of ammonium coupled to the reduction of iron oxides or "rust".  This process has been termed Feammox.  This process was determined to account for a significant amount of nitrogen loss from the soil.  This likely to be a globally significant process that can account for nitrogen losses from ecosystems rich in iron minerals.        This collaborative research project between the University of California at Berkeley and the University of Nebraska, Lincoln has improved the mechanistic understanding of terrestrial nitrogen retention and loss in soils.  This project supported an early career female scientist, one female postdoctoral researcher, two graduate students, and undergraduate students. From among the undergraduates supported by this project, three of the students that participated in this study are members of underrepresented populations in the STEM fields (African American, Native American, and a woman).  The Native American student enrolled at Little Priest Tribal College in Nebraska was supported by REU supplements during the summer of 2010 and 2011. Additional public outreach events were held through numerous venues and events with the YWCA Smart Girls Club and the University of Nebraska State Museum (Dinosaurs and Disasters and Sunday with a Scientist) to communicate the results of this project to the public.          Last Modified: 01/14/2016       Submitted by: Karrie A Weber]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
