<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Collaborative research:   Effects of herbivores and mycorrhizas on N-fixers across soil and climate gradients in the Serengeti</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>03/01/2009</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>02/28/2013</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>621093.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>621093</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>08010209</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>BIO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DEB</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Environmental Biology</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Henry L. Gholz</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Shortages of plant-available forms of soil nitrogen and phosphorus frequently limit plant production in natural and agricultural ecosystems. Microorganisms in the soil can help relieve this limitation, as nitrogen-fixing bacteria convert atmospheric nitrogen-gas into forms of nitrogen that plants can use, and mycorrhizal fungi help plants acquire phosphorus. These microorganisms are suspected to be important regulators of ecosystem productivity, but surprisingly little is known about what controls their abundance and activities. Research in the Serengeti grassland in East Africa provides an unprecedented opportunity to learn how herbivorous animals, the plants they consume, and soil microorganisms all interact together to generate a remarkably stable ecosystem. This research will apply cutting-edge molecular methods in two new manipulative experiments plus an ongoing long-term grazer exclosure experiment to assess how strongly herbivores and mycorrhizal fungi stimulate or limit the abundance and N-fixing activity of soil microbes, and whether these effects are mediated by rainfall and soil minerals. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Human reliance on chemical fertilizers could be reduced if nitrogen-fixing bacteria and mycorrhizal fungi could be more effectively managed. This work will provide the scientific basis for developing management strategies to maximize the benefits of these soil organisms for sustainable production of food and fiber in semi-arid grasslands, savannas and other tropical ecosystems. The results will also make it possible to estimate more closely the contribution of natural nitrogen inputs, relative to elevated human-induced nitrogen deposition across the globe. The research will build scientific capacity in Tanzania, and hence this award is co-funded by NSF's Office of International Science and Engineering.&lt;br/&gt;</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>03/06/2009</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>03/26/2012</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.074</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>0842230</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Mark</FirstName>
<LastName>Ritchie</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>E</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Mark E Ritchie</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>meritchi@syr.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>3154432479</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000375941</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>03/06/2009</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Samuel</FirstName>
<LastName>McNaughton</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>J</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Samuel J McNaughton</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>sjmcnaug@syr.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>3154433507</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000399055</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>03/06/2009</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Ramesh</FirstName>
<LastName>Raina</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Ramesh Raina</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>raraina@syr.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>3154434546</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000228647</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>03/06/2009</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Syracuse University</Name>
<CityName>SYRACUSE</CityName>
<ZipCode>132441200</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>3154432807</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>OFFICE OF SPONSORED PROGRAMS</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[211 Lyman Hall]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>24</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NY24</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>002257350</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>SYRACUSE UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>002257350</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Syracuse University]]></Name>
<CityName>SYRACUSE</CityName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<ZipCode>132441200</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[OFFICE OF SPONSORED PROGRAMS]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>24</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NY24</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1181</Code>
<Text>ECOSYSTEM STUDIES</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7298</Code>
<Text>International Research Collab</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1181</Code>
<Text>ECOSYSTEM STUDIES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>5976</Code>
<Text>AFRICA, NEAR EAST, &amp; SO ASIA</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>5991</Code>
<Text>KENYA</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7388</Code>
<Text>NETWORKING RESEARCH (NR)</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9169</Code>
<Text>BIODIVERSITY AND ECOSYSTEM DYNAMICS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>EGCH</Code>
<Text>ENVIRONMENT AND GLOBAL CHANGE</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0109</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0110</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0111</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0112</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2009~187599</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2010~230391</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2011~117383</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2012~85720</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>This project sought to determine the influence of limiting nutrients, mycorrhizal soil fungi, and herbivory on nitrogen fixation, or the conversion of nitrogen from the atmosphere into mineral forms that plants and soil microbes can use, in the Serengeti grazing ecosystem in East Africa. Several hypotheses were tested, including that (1) grasses would establish biofilms of nitrogen-fixing bacteria on their roots and fix measureable amountsof nitrogen, (2) that nitrogen fixation on plant roots would be greater under higher rainfall and lower soil nitrogen conditions, (3) that nitrogen fixation by free-living bacteria in the soil would be greater under grazed conditions, and (4) that grazing would promote nitrogen fixation in legumes (relatives of beans) by removing the canopy of tall grasses that might limit available light.</p> <p>The abundance of nitrogen-fixing bacteria, as determined by the density of the gene for the enzyme nitrogenase, or nifH, using complicated DNA extraction techniques (that took more than a year to work) &nbsp;and real-time PCR (polymerase chain reaction) methods, was measured on grass and legume roots and in the soil. NifH density was measured in years 2 and 3 along with on-site uptake by roots and soils of isotopically labelled nitrogen (15N) as a direct measure of N fixation in three different experiments: a long-term (10 year) exclusion of grazers from small (4 x 4 m) fenced plots across eight sites that differed in annual rainfall, soil nitrogen and phosphorus, a short-term (2 year) exclusion of grazing animals crossed with additions of limiting nitrogen, phosphorus, or both elements together, and a short-term pot experiment in which legumes were to be grown from seed in sterilized and unsterilized soil under different nitrogen and phosphorus addition rates.</p> <p>As predicted, grass roots displayed densities of the nifH gene that approached that of legumes in some locations, but unexpectedly these locations were strongly phosphorus-limited soils under grazed conditions. NifH in the soil occurred at the highest densities under grazed conditions also at low soil phosphorus. In contrast, NifH densities were highest on legume roots in low nitrogen soil and at higher rainfall. We were unable to obtain reliable direct measures of N-fixation in association with NifH densities. Unexpectedly high costs of labelled nitrogen, delays in the success in extracting DNA from plants and soils, and a lack of response by legumes to fencing and nitrogen and phosphorus addition caused deferrment of nifH density and N-fixation measurements in the nutrient x grazing experiment. Despite several trials with multiple legume species, legumes failed to grow from seed in sterilized soil in pots.</p> <p>As a side benefit, it was discovered that intermediate leveks of grazing led to storage of large amounts of carbon in the soil. This result led to the generation of a new soil carbon dynamic model to predict soil carbon stocks and potential greenhouse gas removals in response to grazing and fire management. The model appears to be an improvement over other more sophisticated models because of its focus on more realistic effects of grazing animals and the actions of termites and dung beetles (decomposers) in inadvertently injecting carbon in animal dung into the soil. This work led to considerable broader impacts by exporting the model to help local pastoralist communities develop grazing and fire management projects to earn carbon credits by storing carbon in the soil.</p> <p>Though corroboration of nifH gene density with actual measurements of nitrogen-fixation was not obtained, the results strongly suggest that the redtop grass (Themeda triandra) may fix considerable nitrogen in the Serengeti ecosystem. If so, this could explain the virtual ubiquity of the grass within the ecosystem and its dominance on heavy clay water-logged soils in areas prone to fire and ni...]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ This project sought to determine the influence of limiting nutrients, mycorrhizal soil fungi, and herbivory on nitrogen fixation, or the conversion of nitrogen from the atmosphere into mineral forms that plants and soil microbes can use, in the Serengeti grazing ecosystem in East Africa. Several hypotheses were tested, including that (1) grasses would establish biofilms of nitrogen-fixing bacteria on their roots and fix measureable amountsof nitrogen, (2) that nitrogen fixation on plant roots would be greater under higher rainfall and lower soil nitrogen conditions, (3) that nitrogen fixation by free-living bacteria in the soil would be greater under grazed conditions, and (4) that grazing would promote nitrogen fixation in legumes (relatives of beans) by removing the canopy of tall grasses that might limit available light.  The abundance of nitrogen-fixing bacteria, as determined by the density of the gene for the enzyme nitrogenase, or nifH, using complicated DNA extraction techniques (that took more than a year to work)  and real-time PCR (polymerase chain reaction) methods, was measured on grass and legume roots and in the soil. NifH density was measured in years 2 and 3 along with on-site uptake by roots and soils of isotopically labelled nitrogen (15N) as a direct measure of N fixation in three different experiments: a long-term (10 year) exclusion of grazers from small (4 x 4 m) fenced plots across eight sites that differed in annual rainfall, soil nitrogen and phosphorus, a short-term (2 year) exclusion of grazing animals crossed with additions of limiting nitrogen, phosphorus, or both elements together, and a short-term pot experiment in which legumes were to be grown from seed in sterilized and unsterilized soil under different nitrogen and phosphorus addition rates.  As predicted, grass roots displayed densities of the nifH gene that approached that of legumes in some locations, but unexpectedly these locations were strongly phosphorus-limited soils under grazed conditions. NifH in the soil occurred at the highest densities under grazed conditions also at low soil phosphorus. In contrast, NifH densities were highest on legume roots in low nitrogen soil and at higher rainfall. We were unable to obtain reliable direct measures of N-fixation in association with NifH densities. Unexpectedly high costs of labelled nitrogen, delays in the success in extracting DNA from plants and soils, and a lack of response by legumes to fencing and nitrogen and phosphorus addition caused deferrment of nifH density and N-fixation measurements in the nutrient x grazing experiment. Despite several trials with multiple legume species, legumes failed to grow from seed in sterilized soil in pots.  As a side benefit, it was discovered that intermediate leveks of grazing led to storage of large amounts of carbon in the soil. This result led to the generation of a new soil carbon dynamic model to predict soil carbon stocks and potential greenhouse gas removals in response to grazing and fire management. The model appears to be an improvement over other more sophisticated models because of its focus on more realistic effects of grazing animals and the actions of termites and dung beetles (decomposers) in inadvertently injecting carbon in animal dung into the soil. This work led to considerable broader impacts by exporting the model to help local pastoralist communities develop grazing and fire management projects to earn carbon credits by storing carbon in the soil.  Though corroboration of nifH gene density with actual measurements of nitrogen-fixation was not obtained, the results strongly suggest that the redtop grass (Themeda triandra) may fix considerable nitrogen in the Serengeti ecosystem. If so, this could explain the virtual ubiquity of the grass within the ecosystem and its dominance on heavy clay water-logged soils in areas prone to fire and nitrogen loss. The results speak to the difficulty in employing modern molecular and isotope ...]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
