<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Collaborative Research:   Multisensory guidance of marine animal navigation and prey capture</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>04/15/2009</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>03/31/2014</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>295939.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>307875</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>08090200</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>BIO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>IOS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Integrative Organismal Systems</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>David Coppola</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Understanding how animals navigate under water is not only fascinating in its own right, it also contributes to instrumentation designs of underwater vehicles, robots and surface vessels, impacts management of fisheries, and helps protect the marine environment.  Sharks have been chosen to demonstrate how they navigate.  While they can not detect a drop of blood a mile away, as often stated, sharks do have impressive prey tracking capabilities.  Sharks are important in fisheries worldwide and have been severely depleted in recent decades, often taken as unwanted by-catch in other fisheries.  Yet, they are essential top predators needed to maintaining a healthy ecosystem.  This research project will show how sharks use all their senses in hunting behavior, starting with initial prey detection, through tracking and locating, and ending with striking their prey.  For more complete understanding, we compare a few shark species that appear to use their senses differently mostly because they specialize in different prey in different habitats.  A team of experts in sensory and shark biology, using unique testing facilities in Massachusetts and Florida, has been assembled including graduate students being trained in the many technical approaches needed for work on live sharks.  The research directly involves undergraduate and high school students and provides extensive outreach to other students of all ages and to the public in general.  The accumulated knowledge should lead to a model of shark navigation and predation that can be used for the conservation of sharks, protection of humans, and the engineering design of underwater steering algorithms.  The inevitable presentation of this research in future television programs and video documentaries will disseminate new knowledge to the public at large, both of sharks and of rigorous science.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>04/03/2009</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>02/28/2011</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.074</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>0843440</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Jelle</FirstName>
<LastName>Atema</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Jelle Atema</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>atema@bu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6173532432</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000324797</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/03/2009</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Trustees of Boston University</Name>
<CityName>BOSTON</CityName>
<ZipCode>022151300</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6173534365</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>881 COMMONWEALTH AVE</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
<StateCode>MA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MA07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>049435266</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>TRUSTEES OF BOSTON UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>049435266</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Trustees of Boston University]]></Name>
<CityName>BOSTON</CityName>
<StateCode>MA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>022151300</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[881 COMMONWEALTH AVE]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MA07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<FoaInformation>
<Code>0000099</Code>
<Name>Other Applications NEC</Name>
</FoaInformation>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7713</Code>
<Text>Activation</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1096</Code>
<Text>NEURAL SYSTEMS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9178</Code>
<Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9179</Code>
<Text>GRADUATE INVOLVEMENT</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9183</Code>
<Text>GENERAL FOUNDATIONS OF BIOTECHNOLOGY</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9251</Code>
<Text>REU SUPP-Res Exp for Ugrd Supp</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>BIOT</Code>
<Text>BIOTECHNOLOGY</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>SMET</Code>
<Text>SCIENCE, MATH, ENG &amp; TECH EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0109</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0110</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0111</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2009~121821</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2010~88533</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2011~97521</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Sharks are known as efficient and dangerous predators hunting by smell. Statements such as &ldquo;sharks can detect a drop of blood from a mile away&rdquo; are common in the popular press. The origin of this myth is understandable: many sharks are attracted to fishing gear after chumming the water with a bucket full of bloody animal remains; they suddenly appear seemingly out of nowhere. Rational thinking would consider that we do not know when and from how far these sharks were attracted or how many sharks were in the area and followed the boat. Perhaps sharks have learned that the sounds or wakes of fishing boats can lead them to food so that they can snatch a hooked fish being reeled in. This lack of information led us to initiate a project to better understand how sharks use all their senses to detect, track and capture their prey. We emphasized the sense of smell as most sharks do not initiate hunting behavior without smell. We also considered learning behavior. Their social behavior is even less known.</p> <p>Hunting involves a sequence of steps with increasing sensory information as the predator approaches the prey, starting with detection, proceeding with tracking and ending with capture. Different senses can be involved as the hunting sequence unfolds.&nbsp; The sharks&rsquo; hunting behavior was filmed for later analysis of details. The final strike is so fast that it required high-speed video. Each animal was tested before and after we blocked one or more senses: smell, water flow detection (with an organ known as &ldquo;lateral line&rdquo;), vision, and electroreception. The results showed that odor was generally the first signal detected, followed by odor-motivated flow tracking. Closer to the prey, the preferred sensory modality used by the species varied, with vision, water flow imaging, and electroreception being important for orienting to, striking at, and finally capturing the prey. In the absence of odor, the blacktip could see and did strike at the prey from several meters away, while the nurse shark would not respond at all. The sense of touch turned out to play a role in prey capture when other senses were not available. In the nurse shark, touch also aided in tracking along the bottom. The results also show that the sharks switched to alternate senses when one or more were no longer available.</p> <p>These behavioral results correspond to the way in which different stimuli &ndash;light, odor, waster flow, electrical current- disperse through the marine environment and are therefore expected to be generally applicable underwater. This could include the use of multiple sensors in steering algorithms for underwater vehicles. This is the first comprehensive analysis of multisensory hunting behavior in sharks.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>Spurred by the current awareness of ocean acidification and its effects on fish olfaction, we conducted an initially unplanned 2-year study on the effects of elevated carbon-dioxide levels on the odor plume tracking behavior of the smooth dogfish. The levels predicted to be reached at the late 21<sup>st</sup> century (given current carbon emission levels) caused deleterious effects: the sharks started to<em> avoid</em> the food odor plume in our test tank. These discoveries have generated considerable press coverage and shark research is becoming an area of interest approaching the interest in marine mammals.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>In our research we have trained many students: from high school volunteers to college and graduate students, to postdoctoral researchers. We have regularly demonstrated our research to visiting elementary school classes and their teachers, and we have worked with several reporters to bring our results to the general public. In summer 2014 the BBC will be filming for their upcoming &ldquo;Shark&rdquo; program some of the experiments described above in our Woods Hole lab.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>A fi...]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Sharks are known as efficient and dangerous predators hunting by smell. Statements such as "sharks can detect a drop of blood from a mile away" are common in the popular press. The origin of this myth is understandable: many sharks are attracted to fishing gear after chumming the water with a bucket full of bloody animal remains; they suddenly appear seemingly out of nowhere. Rational thinking would consider that we do not know when and from how far these sharks were attracted or how many sharks were in the area and followed the boat. Perhaps sharks have learned that the sounds or wakes of fishing boats can lead them to food so that they can snatch a hooked fish being reeled in. This lack of information led us to initiate a project to better understand how sharks use all their senses to detect, track and capture their prey. We emphasized the sense of smell as most sharks do not initiate hunting behavior without smell. We also considered learning behavior. Their social behavior is even less known.  Hunting involves a sequence of steps with increasing sensory information as the predator approaches the prey, starting with detection, proceeding with tracking and ending with capture. Different senses can be involved as the hunting sequence unfolds.  The sharksÆ hunting behavior was filmed for later analysis of details. The final strike is so fast that it required high-speed video. Each animal was tested before and after we blocked one or more senses: smell, water flow detection (with an organ known as "lateral line"), vision, and electroreception. The results showed that odor was generally the first signal detected, followed by odor-motivated flow tracking. Closer to the prey, the preferred sensory modality used by the species varied, with vision, water flow imaging, and electroreception being important for orienting to, striking at, and finally capturing the prey. In the absence of odor, the blacktip could see and did strike at the prey from several meters away, while the nurse shark would not respond at all. The sense of touch turned out to play a role in prey capture when other senses were not available. In the nurse shark, touch also aided in tracking along the bottom. The results also show that the sharks switched to alternate senses when one or more were no longer available.  These behavioral results correspond to the way in which different stimuli &ndash;light, odor, waster flow, electrical current- disperse through the marine environment and are therefore expected to be generally applicable underwater. This could include the use of multiple sensors in steering algorithms for underwater vehicles. This is the first comprehensive analysis of multisensory hunting behavior in sharks.     Spurred by the current awareness of ocean acidification and its effects on fish olfaction, we conducted an initially unplanned 2-year study on the effects of elevated carbon-dioxide levels on the odor plume tracking behavior of the smooth dogfish. The levels predicted to be reached at the late 21st century (given current carbon emission levels) caused deleterious effects: the sharks started to avoid the food odor plume in our test tank. These discoveries have generated considerable press coverage and shark research is becoming an area of interest approaching the interest in marine mammals.     In our research we have trained many students: from high school volunteers to college and graduate students, to postdoctoral researchers. We have regularly demonstrated our research to visiting elementary school classes and their teachers, and we have worked with several reporters to bring our results to the general public. In summer 2014 the BBC will be filming for their upcoming "Shark" program some of the experiments described above in our Woods Hole lab.     A final result worth mentioning is the construction of a unique flume-testing laboratory on the campus of the Woods Hole Oceanographic Institution. We developed sea water systems in which we can h...]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
