<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>CAREER: Novel Techniques for Detecting and Localizing Hardware Trojans in Integrated Circuits</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>06/01/2009</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2015</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>399995.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>415995</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>05050000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>CSE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CNS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Computer and Network Systems</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Nina Amla</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>namla@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927991</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Proposal ID: 0844995, PI Name: Mohammad Tehranipoor, PI Institution: University of Connecticut, Title: CAREER: Novel Techniques for Detecting and Localizing Hardware Trojans in Integrated Circuits&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Abstract: &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Design and fabrication of integrated circuits (ICs) are becoming increasingly vulnerable to malicious activities and alterations with globalization. These vulnerabilities have raised serious concerns regarding possible threats to many critical applications. An adversary can introduce a Trojan designed to disable and/or destroy a system at some future time or the Trojan may serve to leak confidential information covertly to the adversary. This research develops efficient procedures for detection of malicious alterations and subtle modifications in integrated circuits. Side-channel signal analysis methods as well on-chip measurement structures are developed to detect and localize the inserted Trojans in very deep submicron ICs. Novel design-for-hardware-trust techniques are developed in this project to increase the capabilities and effectiveness of the detection and isolation strategies. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The Intellectual Merit of the research is the development of techniques optimized to improve the level of confidence that an IC will carry out its intended function and nothing more. The broader impact is (i) the development of techniques for hardware authentication that would be of interests to US government, agencies and many fab-less semiconductor companies, (ii)  the societal benefits that include trustworthy electronics for healthcare, defense weapons and dependable computing platforms for intelligence, weather forecasting, and transportation, (iii) the education of undergraduate and graduate students, (iv) the development of new courses, and (v) the dissemination of data and methodologies to researchers in academia and industry.&lt;br/&gt;</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>02/23/2009</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/14/2013</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.070</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>0844995</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Mark</FirstName>
<LastName>Tehranipoor</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Mark Tehranipoor</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>tehranipoor@ece.ufl.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>3523922585</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000069461</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>02/23/2009</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Connecticut</Name>
<CityName>Storrs</CityName>
<ZipCode>062691133</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>8604863622</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>438 Whitney Road Ext.</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[Unit 1133]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Connecticut</StateName>
<StateCode>CT</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CT02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>614209054</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF CONNECTICUT</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>004534830</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Connecticut]]></Name>
<CityName>Storrs</CityName>
<StateCode>CT</StateCode>
<ZipCode>062691133</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[438 Whitney Road Ext.]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Connecticut</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CT02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<FoaInformation>
<Code>0000912</Code>
<Name>Computer Science</Name>
</FoaInformation>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>4090</Code>
<Text>ADVANCED NET INFRA &amp; RSCH</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7795</Code>
<Text>TRUSTWORTHY COMPUTING</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>8060</Code>
<Text>Secure &amp;Trustworthy Cyberspace</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1045</Code>
<Text>CAREER-Faculty Erly Career Dev</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1187</Code>
<Text>PECASE- eligible</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7434</Code>
<Text>CNCI</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9178</Code>
<Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9218</Code>
<Text>BASIC RESEARCH &amp; HUMAN RESORCS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9251</Code>
<Text>REU SUPP-Res Exp for Ugrd Supp</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>HPCC</Code>
<Text>HIGH PERFORMANCE COMPUTING &amp; COMM</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0109</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0110</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0111</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0112</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0113</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2009~79999</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2010~79999</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2011~79999</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2012~95999</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2013~79999</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><strong>Award Title:&nbsp;</strong>CAREER: Novel Techniques for Detecting and Localizing Hardware Trojans in Integrated Circuits</p> <p><strong>Federal Award ID:&nbsp;</strong>0844995</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>This project investigated several approaches for detection and prevention of hardware Trojans in integrated circuits. The PI and his team first developed the most comprehensive taxonomy of hardware Trojans. They then analyzed circuit side channel information, i.e., delay and power supply transient current signals, to detect and locate hardware Trojans. The intellectual merits are development of a better understanding of Trojans and their actions in an integrated circuit, and side-channel signal analysis techniques optimized to improve the level of confidence that an IC will carry out its intended function and nothing more. The specific intellectual merits of this proposal include 1) development of a novel method called clock frequency sweeping for targeting Trojans in presence of variations, 2) development of statistical analysis for detection of Trojans using transient power signal, 3) development of new design-for-hardware-trust (DFHT) techniques to increase the resolution of detection and localization methods, and finally 4) development of prevention techniques.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>The proposed techniques are optimized to enable hardware authentication and would be of high interests to US government, agencies and many fab-less semiconductor companies. Benefits for society include trustworthy electronics for healthcare, defense weapons and dependable computing platforms for intelligence, weather forecasting, financial transactions, transportation, etc., and realization of the much sought-after "zero-defects" for automotive applications. Since our methods can target both ASIC and COTS, all companies that use these chips such as car makers, home appliance companies, etc. will benefit from this research. The results of this project were disseminated in IEEE/ACM conferences and workshops. The PI also presented the findings of these methods in many tutorials, panels, and invited presentations to universities, companies and government agencies.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>This research impacted the education of students and professionals through courses, online materials, and on- and off-campus seminars. By integrating the results of this project into various existing courses and offering new courses (e.g., Introduction to Hardware Security and Trust) in undergraduate and graduate curriculum, the PI brought an excellent engineering knowledge to electrical and computer engineering students and helped improve their skills on design, hardware security, verification and test. The PI has supervised and graduated three PhD students and fine undergraduate students of which two were from an underrepresented group.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>The major finding and accomplishment of this project include:</p> <p>&nbsp;<strong>Students</strong>: Hassan Salmani, a PhD student      partly supported by this project, graduated in September 2011. He was a      post-doctoral fellow at the University of Connecticut. He then joined      Howard University as an Assistant Professor. Xuehui Zhang started her PhD      program at UConn in January 2009. She graduated in May 2013 and joined      Oracle. Finally, Kan Xiao, the third PhD student supported partly by this      project will graduate by Dec. 2014.</p> <p><strong>Publication</strong>: The PI led the effort to publish the first and most comprehensive book in hardware security: M. Tehranipoor and C. Wang, <strong>Introduction to Hardware Security and Trust</strong>, Springer, 2011. The PI also published second book focused on hardware Trojans and counterfeit electronics, Titled: M. Tehranipoor, H. Salmani, and X. Zhang, Integrated Circuit Authentication: Hardware Trojan and Counterfeit Detection, Springer, 2014. Further, the PI published two book ch...]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Award Title: CAREER: Novel Techniques for Detecting and Localizing Hardware Trojans in Integrated Circuits  Federal Award ID: 0844995     This project investigated several approaches for detection and prevention of hardware Trojans in integrated circuits. The PI and his team first developed the most comprehensive taxonomy of hardware Trojans. They then analyzed circuit side channel information, i.e., delay and power supply transient current signals, to detect and locate hardware Trojans. The intellectual merits are development of a better understanding of Trojans and their actions in an integrated circuit, and side-channel signal analysis techniques optimized to improve the level of confidence that an IC will carry out its intended function and nothing more. The specific intellectual merits of this proposal include 1) development of a novel method called clock frequency sweeping for targeting Trojans in presence of variations, 2) development of statistical analysis for detection of Trojans using transient power signal, 3) development of new design-for-hardware-trust (DFHT) techniques to increase the resolution of detection and localization methods, and finally 4) development of prevention techniques.     The proposed techniques are optimized to enable hardware authentication and would be of high interests to US government, agencies and many fab-less semiconductor companies. Benefits for society include trustworthy electronics for healthcare, defense weapons and dependable computing platforms for intelligence, weather forecasting, financial transactions, transportation, etc., and realization of the much sought-after "zero-defects" for automotive applications. Since our methods can target both ASIC and COTS, all companies that use these chips such as car makers, home appliance companies, etc. will benefit from this research. The results of this project were disseminated in IEEE/ACM conferences and workshops. The PI also presented the findings of these methods in many tutorials, panels, and invited presentations to universities, companies and government agencies.     This research impacted the education of students and professionals through courses, online materials, and on- and off-campus seminars. By integrating the results of this project into various existing courses and offering new courses (e.g., Introduction to Hardware Security and Trust) in undergraduate and graduate curriculum, the PI brought an excellent engineering knowledge to electrical and computer engineering students and helped improve their skills on design, hardware security, verification and test. The PI has supervised and graduated three PhD students and fine undergraduate students of which two were from an underrepresented group.     The major finding and accomplishment of this project include:   Students: Hassan Salmani, a PhD student      partly supported by this project, graduated in September 2011. He was a      post-doctoral fellow at the University of Connecticut. He then joined      Howard University as an Assistant Professor. Xuehui Zhang started her PhD      program at UConn in January 2009. She graduated in May 2013 and joined      Oracle. Finally, Kan Xiao, the third PhD student supported partly by this      project will graduate by Dec. 2014.  Publication: The PI led the effort to publish the first and most comprehensive book in hardware security: M. Tehranipoor and C. Wang, Introduction to Hardware Security and Trust, Springer, 2011. The PI also published second book focused on hardware Trojans and counterfeit electronics, Titled: M. Tehranipoor, H. Salmani, and X. Zhang, Integrated Circuit Authentication: Hardware Trojan and Counterfeit Detection, Springer, 2014. Further, the PI published two book chapter and more than twenty journal articles and conference papers from the support of this project.  Research: The PI developed the first set of design-for-hardware-trust techniques, the first set of prevention techniques and leveraging the split m...]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
