<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>CAREER: Characterizing, Understanding, and Integrating Complex Problem Solving in Engineering Education</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>02/15/2009</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>02/29/2016</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>400000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>479975</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07050000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>EEC</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Engineering Education and Centers</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Elliot Douglas</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This CAREER project will research how engineering students?s learn complex problem solving.  With global competitiveness and the rapid pace of technological change, engineers must learn to adapt to complex and rapidly changing problem solving environments as well as remain effective in innovation. Undergraduate research and industry experiences provide a strong basis for our students to learn these essential, problem-based, and globally competitive skills. Yet, although such experiences offer many benefits and enable engineering students to begin the practice of solving real-world complex problems, there are two main pitfalls: (a) lack of research and empirical studies on students? learning outcomes as a result of participating in these experiences, and (b) the majority of engineering students do not get exposed to these experiences during their undergraduate education (this is particularly true for undergraduate research experiences, which only the best students get selected to participate in). Our overarching goal is to characterize and understand complex problem solving in real-world engineering settings as a means of integrating these essential problem solving skills in engineering education settings. Guided by six research questions, it is anticipated that: (a) classification of real-world research- and industry-based problems will lead to a understanding and characterizing complex problem solving domains and processes, (b) students? learning outcomes (cognitive, affective, social, and professional) will be assessed in order to understand how different problems enable different outcomes and cognitive abilities, (c) innovative instruments and assessment tools, that can be transferred across institutions, programs, departments, and experiences, will be developed, and (d) strategies for  implementing complex problem solving in engineering education will be investigated and presented. We will employ a mixed-methods approach to effectively classify undergraduate research and industry problems as well as assess engineering students? learning outcomes (including performance and achievement motivation, self-efficacy, problem solving and critical thinking skills, professional identity, adaptive expertise and cognitive flexibility) during these two highly promoted experiences. Grounded on the results and findings of the research, the well-integrated educational component will involve the development, implementation, and evaluation of instructional material focused on transferring complex problem solving, based on research and industry experiences, in three settings: (1) undergraduate courses within JMU?s engineering program, (2) high school level engineering course for female students, and (3) K-12 education focused on students and teacher educators.&lt;br/&gt;</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>02/05/2009</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/22/2015</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>0846468</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Kurtis</FirstName>
<LastName>Paterson</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>G</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Kurtis G Paterson</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>paterskg@jmu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5405688110</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000393311</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/22/2015</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Olga</FirstName>
<LastName>Pierrakos</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Olga Pierrakos</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>pierrao@wfu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5402307465</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000244660</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>02/05/2009</StartDate>
<EndDate>06/22/2015</EndDate>
<RoleCode>Former Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>James Madison University</Name>
<CityName>HARRISONBURG</CityName>
<ZipCode>228077000</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5405686872</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>MSC 5728</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[800 South Main Street]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Virginia</StateName>
<StateCode>VA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>00</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>VA00</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>879325355</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>JAMES MADISON UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>879325355</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[James Madison University]]></Name>
<CityName>HARRISONBURG</CityName>
<StateCode>VA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>228077000</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[MSC 5728]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Virginia</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>00</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>VA00</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<FoaInformation>
<Code>0116000</Code>
<Name>Human Subjects</Name>
</FoaInformation>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1340</Code>
<Text>EngEd-Engineering Education</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7492</Code>
<Text>CCLI-Type 2 (Expansion)</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>0000</Code>
<Text>UNASSIGNED</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1045</Code>
<Text>CAREER-Faculty Erly Career Dev</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>110E</Code>
<Text>EDUCATION RESEARCH</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1187</Code>
<Text>PECASE- eligible</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1340</Code>
<Text>ENGINEERING EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9178</Code>
<Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>CL10</Code>
<Text>CLB-Career Life Balance</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>OTHR</Code>
<Text>OTHER RESEARCH OR EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>SMET</Code>
<Text>SCIENCE, MATH, ENG &amp; TECH EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0109</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0112</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0409</Code>
<Name>NSF Education &amp; Human Resource</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040106</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2009~400000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2012~79975</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The overaching goals for this project are:</p> <p>(1) RESEARCH - Effectively investigate (using mixed-methods approaches)&nbsp;engineering students&rsquo; learning outcomes (knowledge, skills, attitudes, perceptions, behaviors) during complex problem sovling environments like undergraduate research, industry experiences, and capstone design projects.</p> <p>(2) EDUCATION - Transfer features of real-world and complex problem solving into the classroom in effective and novel ways so as to develop more adaptive problem solvers.</p> <p>This project has research goals and education goals, which are designed to allow for research to practice translation as recommended and outlined in ASEE&rsquo;s 2009 Phase 1 Report on<em>Creating a Culture for Scholarly and Systematic Innovation in Engineering Education</em>. Educational practice leads to innovative educational research questions and research questions lead to transformational educational practice.</p> <p><em>Research Goals</em></p> <p><strong>(R1) &ndash;&nbsp;</strong>Investigate the nature of complex problem solving in a variety of engineering education contexts (i.e. research experiences, design projects, industry experiences, engineering coursework).</p> <p><strong>(R2)</strong>&nbsp;&ndash; Investigate complex problem solving from cognitive, non-cognitive, and environmental impacts and perspectives (i.e. knowledge, skills, attitudes, problem solving environment, facilitator role).</p> <p><strong>(R3) &ndash;&nbsp;</strong>Investigate contextual factors that impact complex problem solving environments and student learning.</p> <p><strong>(R4)&nbsp;</strong>&ndash; Measure students&rsquo; learning outcomes across a variety of complex problem solving contexts and environments (i.e. knowledge gains, goal orientation, motivation, salience of engineering identity, grit, growth mindset, creativity, adaptive expertise, etc.).</p> <p><em>Educational Goals</em></p> <p><strong>(E1) &ndash;&nbsp;</strong>Promote and integrate authentic, real-world, and complex problem solving in the undergraduate engineering classroom.</p> <p><strong>(E2) &ndash;&nbsp;</strong>Design and implement innovative pedagogical models that enhance learning in undergraduate engineering classrooms and also enhance students&rsquo; abilities to deal with complex problem solving.<strong>&nbsp;</strong></p> <p><strong>(E3) &ndash;&nbsp;</strong>Develop innovative approaches to support faculty<strong>&nbsp;</strong>and students with understanding and integrating complex problem solving in the classroom.</p> <p><strong>(E4)</strong>&nbsp;&ndash; Support faculty with engaged with the innovative cycle of educational practice and research.</p> <p>During this project, we have learned that effort contingent learning environments make an impact in student learnings.&nbsp;&nbsp; Motivation, engagement, mastery orientation, self-efficacy, creativity, grit, and sense of belonging were constructs and outcomes that were enhanced in classroom environments where effort, collaboration, innovation, multiple perspectives were valued and rewarded. We have implemented a novel and adaptive PBL model in the JMU engineering program, which annually impact 400 plus students. Faculty workshops on PBL and complex problem solving have impacted over 600 faculty. &nbsp;Further, as a result of this project, a new program, the JMU Engaged Teacher Scholars, was launched in the spring 2015 and selected faculty are working within their colleges to build capacity for evidenced-based teaching and learning practices. &nbsp;Over 10 workshops/seminars have already taken place across JMU under this new program being implemented.&nbsp; The hope is that more JMU faculty will take part in evidenced-based teaching and learning practices.&nbsp; The home for this program is the Center for Faculty Innovation at JMU. Engaging a team that brings diverse expertise has been the strength of this effort.&nbsp...]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The overaching goals for this project are:  (1) RESEARCH - Effectively investigate (using mixed-methods approaches) engineering studentsÆ learning outcomes (knowledge, skills, attitudes, perceptions, behaviors) during complex problem sovling environments like undergraduate research, industry experiences, and capstone design projects.  (2) EDUCATION - Transfer features of real-world and complex problem solving into the classroom in effective and novel ways so as to develop more adaptive problem solvers.  This project has research goals and education goals, which are designed to allow for research to practice translation as recommended and outlined in ASEEÆs 2009 Phase 1 Report onCreating a Culture for Scholarly and Systematic Innovation in Engineering Education. Educational practice leads to innovative educational research questions and research questions lead to transformational educational practice.  Research Goals  (R1) &ndash; Investigate the nature of complex problem solving in a variety of engineering education contexts (i.e. research experiences, design projects, industry experiences, engineering coursework).  (R2) &ndash; Investigate complex problem solving from cognitive, non-cognitive, and environmental impacts and perspectives (i.e. knowledge, skills, attitudes, problem solving environment, facilitator role).  (R3) &ndash; Investigate contextual factors that impact complex problem solving environments and student learning.  (R4) &ndash; Measure studentsÆ learning outcomes across a variety of complex problem solving contexts and environments (i.e. knowledge gains, goal orientation, motivation, salience of engineering identity, grit, growth mindset, creativity, adaptive expertise, etc.).  Educational Goals  (E1) &ndash; Promote and integrate authentic, real-world, and complex problem solving in the undergraduate engineering classroom.  (E2) &ndash; Design and implement innovative pedagogical models that enhance learning in undergraduate engineering classrooms and also enhance studentsÆ abilities to deal with complex problem solving.   (E3) &ndash; Develop innovative approaches to support faculty and students with understanding and integrating complex problem solving in the classroom.  (E4) &ndash; Support faculty with engaged with the innovative cycle of educational practice and research.  During this project, we have learned that effort contingent learning environments make an impact in student learnings.   Motivation, engagement, mastery orientation, self-efficacy, creativity, grit, and sense of belonging were constructs and outcomes that were enhanced in classroom environments where effort, collaboration, innovation, multiple perspectives were valued and rewarded. We have implemented a novel and adaptive PBL model in the JMU engineering program, which annually impact 400 plus students. Faculty workshops on PBL and complex problem solving have impacted over 600 faculty.  Further, as a result of this project, a new program, the JMU Engaged Teacher Scholars, was launched in the spring 2015 and selected faculty are working within their colleges to build capacity for evidenced-based teaching and learning practices.  Over 10 workshops/seminars have already taken place across JMU under this new program being implemented.  The hope is that more JMU faculty will take part in evidenced-based teaching and learning practices.  The home for this program is the Center for Faculty Innovation at JMU. Engaging a team that brings diverse expertise has been the strength of this effort.  Bringing on board a user experience expert has been immense and through this collaboration we are also enhancing aspects of the design curriculum at JMU.          Last Modified: 06/01/2016       Submitted by: Kurtis G Paterson]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
