<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>CAREER: Holomorphic Curves in Algebraic Geometry and Symplectic Topology</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/15/2009</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2015</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>443068.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>443068</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DMS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Christopher Stark</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>cstark@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924869</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Abstract&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Award:  DMS-0846978&lt;br/&gt;Principal Investigator:  Aleksey Zinger&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The invention of pseudo-holomorphic curves techniques in the&lt;br/&gt;1980s revolutionized symplectic topology, profoundly impacted&lt;br/&gt;algebraic geometry, and led to astounding connections with string&lt;br/&gt;theory.  This project has three distinct directions, motivated by&lt;br/&gt;this interplay between different fields. The primary one is a&lt;br/&gt;detailed study of deformations of such curves, for arbitrary as&lt;br/&gt;well as generic complex structures. It aims at the fundamental&lt;br/&gt;understanding of properties of pseudo-holomorphic curves,&lt;br/&gt;including Gromov-Witten invariants (counts of such curves) and&lt;br/&gt;more qualititative aspects of their behavior (e.g. existence,&lt;br/&gt;uniruledness, etc.).  The aim of another direction is to apply&lt;br/&gt;techniques employed in the PI's proof of the string theory&lt;br/&gt;prediction for the genus 1 GW-invariants of a quintic threefold&lt;br/&gt;in many other setting, testing additional mirror predictions and&lt;br/&gt;going beyond them. The third direction would further develop the&lt;br/&gt;PI's local excess intersection approach and its applications to&lt;br/&gt;classical enumerative geometry.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;String theory is a physical model that represents elementary&lt;br/&gt;particles by vibrating strings with the aim of unifying the four&lt;br/&gt;fundamental forces of nature. As such srings move in space, they&lt;br/&gt;sweep out Riemann surfaces, also called holomorphic curves. While&lt;br/&gt;string theory is one of the main paradigms in physics today, it&lt;br/&gt;has yet to make any experimentally testable predictions. However,&lt;br/&gt;it has generated plenty of mathematical predictions and led to&lt;br/&gt;fundamental developments in symplectic topology and algebraic&lt;br/&gt;geometry, especially in relation to (pseudo-) holomorphic&lt;br/&gt;curves. This proposal aims to further test string theory&lt;br/&gt;mathematically, while deepening the mathematical understanding of&lt;br/&gt;such curves with an eye toward applications to more classical&lt;br/&gt;problems in geometry. Some of the projects in this proposal will&lt;br/&gt;pursued by graduate students under the PI's supervision.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award is jointly supported by the programs in Geometric Analysis and in Algebra, Number Theory, and Combinatorics.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/04/2009</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/17/2013</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>0846978</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Aleksey</FirstName>
<LastName>Zinger</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Aleksey Zinger</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>azinger@math.sunysb.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6316328288</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000492747</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/04/2009</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>SUNY at Stony Brook</Name>
<CityName>Stony Brook</CityName>
<ZipCode>117940001</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6316329949</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>WEST 5510 FRK MEL LIB</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NY01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>804878247</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>RESEARCH FOUNDATION FOR THE STATE UNIVERSITY OF NEW YORK, THE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>020657151</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[SUNY at Stony Brook]]></Name>
<CityName>Stony Brook</CityName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<ZipCode>117940001</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[WEST 5510 FRK MEL LIB]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NY01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<FoaInformation>
<Code>0000099</Code>
<Name>Other Applications NEC</Name>
</FoaInformation>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1264</Code>
<Text>ALGEBRA,NUMBER THEORY,AND COM</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1265</Code>
<Text>GEOMETRIC ANALYSIS</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>0000</Code>
<Text>UNASSIGNED</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1045</Code>
<Text>CAREER-Faculty Erly Career Dev</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1187</Code>
<Text>PECASE- eligible</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>OTHR</Code>
<Text>OTHER RESEARCH OR EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0109</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0110</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0111</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0112</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0113</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2009~83049</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2010~85858</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2011~88558</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2012~91354</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2013~94249</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>String theory is a physical model that represents elementary&nbsp;particles by vibrating strings with the aim of unifying the four&nbsp;fundamental forces of nature. As such strings move in space, they&nbsp;sweep out Riemann surfaces, also called holomorphic curves. While&nbsp;string theory is one of the main paradigms in physics today, it&nbsp;has yet to make any experimentally testable predictions. However,&nbsp;it has generated plenty of mathematical predictions and led to&nbsp;fundamental developments in symplectic topology and algebraic&nbsp;geometry, especially in relation to (pseudo-) holomorphic&nbsp;curves.&nbsp;</p> <p>The aim project was to further test string theory mathematically and to deepen the understanding of related mathematical phenomena with an eye toward applications to more classical problems in geometry. The mathematical outputs of this project include the first mirror symmetry formula for the stable quotients invariants that has led to followup discoveries of a whole range of mirror phenomena for stable quotients invariants by others. The introduction of normal crossings symplectic divisors into symplectic topology has extended the fundamental notion of smooth symplectic divisor to settings playing a central role in the Gross-Siebert program for a direct proof of the now-classical mirror symmetry predictions of string theory. <span>The construction of real Gromov-Witten and enumerative invariants in all genera has opened the door to a multitude of developments in real algebraic geometry, tropical geometry, and mirror symmetry for real algebraic varieties.</span></p> <p><span>This project has resulted&nbsp;</span>in about 20 research publciations and pre-prints, as well as expository notes on different topics. It has led to two completed PhD theses, a third thesis close to completion, and very productive collaborations with three junior researchers on different aspects of this project.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 09/14/2015<br>      Modified by: Aleksey&nbsp;Zinger</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ String theory is a physical model that represents elementary particles by vibrating strings with the aim of unifying the four fundamental forces of nature. As such strings move in space, they sweep out Riemann surfaces, also called holomorphic curves. While string theory is one of the main paradigms in physics today, it has yet to make any experimentally testable predictions. However, it has generated plenty of mathematical predictions and led to fundamental developments in symplectic topology and algebraic geometry, especially in relation to (pseudo-) holomorphic curves.   The aim project was to further test string theory mathematically and to deepen the understanding of related mathematical phenomena with an eye toward applications to more classical problems in geometry. The mathematical outputs of this project include the first mirror symmetry formula for the stable quotients invariants that has led to followup discoveries of a whole range of mirror phenomena for stable quotients invariants by others. The introduction of normal crossings symplectic divisors into symplectic topology has extended the fundamental notion of smooth symplectic divisor to settings playing a central role in the Gross-Siebert program for a direct proof of the now-classical mirror symmetry predictions of string theory. The construction of real Gromov-Witten and enumerative invariants in all genera has opened the door to a multitude of developments in real algebraic geometry, tropical geometry, and mirror symmetry for real algebraic varieties.  This project has resulted in about 20 research publciations and pre-prints, as well as expository notes on different topics. It has led to two completed PhD theses, a third thesis close to completion, and very productive collaborations with three junior researchers on different aspects of this project.                Last Modified: 09/14/2015       Submitted by: Aleksey Zinger]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
