<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>RUI: Nanoparticle Film Assemblies: Interfaces for Controlling the Nanoscale Adsorption Environment and Electrochemical Behavior of Immobilized Redox Proteins</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>02/15/2009</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>01/31/2013</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>255000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>255000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03090006</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CHE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Chemistry</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Zeev Rosenzweig</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Professor Michael C. Leopold of the University of Richmond is supported by the Analytical and Surface Chemistry Program in the Division of Chemistry to conduct research leading to the development of chemically modified gold nanoparticles assembled onto conducting surfaces, known as monolayer-protected clusters (MPCs), and to use this platform as a functional electrode component for protein monolayer electrochemistry to probe the electron transfer properties of immobilized redox proteins, while preserving their biological function.  Experiments will be conducted to study the role of the core size and functionality of the MPCs, and the dependence of electron transfer rates on distance through the MPCs.  Understanding of the interactions and charge transfer properties of proteins with these substrates will lead to a better realization of the potential of MPCs in many applications in bioanalytical chemistry leading to the development of miniaturized biosensors.  This research will involve undergraduate students in an undergraduate institution in modern research methods and train them in state-of-the-art instrumentation.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>02/05/2009</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>12/06/2010</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>0847145</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Michael</FirstName>
<LastName>Leopold</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>C</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Michael C Leopold</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>mleopold@richmond.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>8042876329</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000412374</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>02/05/2009</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Richmond</Name>
<CityName>RICHMOND</CityName>
<ZipCode>231730001</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>8042898100</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>110 UR Drive</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Virginia</StateName>
<StateCode>VA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>VA07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>056915069</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF RICHMOND</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>056915069</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Richmond]]></Name>
<CityName>RICHMOND</CityName>
<StateCode>VA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>231730001</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[110 UR Drive]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Virginia</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>VA07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1972</Code>
<Text>ELECTROCHEMISTRY &amp; SURFACE CHE</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>0000</Code>
<Text>UNASSIGNED</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7237</Code>
<Text>NANO NON-SOLIC SCI &amp; ENG AWD</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9229</Code>
<Text>RES IN UNDERGRAD INST-RESEARCH</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>OTHR</Code>
<Text>OTHER RESEARCH OR EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0109</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0110</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0111</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2009~85000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2010~85000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2011~85000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><strong>Project Outcomes Report (NSF-CHE-0847145)</strong></p> <p>&ldquo;<em>Nanoparticle Film Assemblies: Interfaces for Controlling the Nanoscale Adsorption Environment and Electrochemical Behavior of Immobilized Redox Proteins</em>,&rdquo; Funding: $255,000 from 2/15/2009-1/31/2013.</p> <p>As nanomaterials continue to emerge in both the scientific field and in products of everyday life, fundamental understanding of their structures, interconnection, and functionality continues to be an important goal of research.&nbsp; The primary focus of our NSF funded project was to investigate gold nanoparticle (NP) film assemblies as an adsorption platform/interface for adsorbing proteins that are electrochemically active &ndash; fundamental bioanalytical chemistry related to important future medical applications.&nbsp; The merger of such proteins with and man-made materials is a significant foundation for future sensor development, including real-time, implantable sensors for the continuous monitoring of clinically relevant species (e.g., glucose for diabetics or lactate for sepsis diagnosis) as well as general biocompatible materials.&nbsp; We proposed the use of electrodes modified with a film ensemble of colloidal gold NPs as an alternative platform for fundamental studies of this nature.&nbsp; &nbsp;&nbsp;In 2008, we introduced the use of <em>non-aqueous</em> NP films as a protein adsorption platform publishing our findings in the <em>J. Am. Chem. Soc.</em>.&nbsp; That work became the premise of the NSF proposal (CHE-0847145) which proposed specific experiments performed exclusively by undergraduates and aimed at a greater understanding of the NP film as this type of interface.&nbsp; Our model system, blue copper azurin protein (Az) adsorbed to NP films, was used study different aspects of the NP film platform related to signal-to-noise (S/N), the most significant <strong>intellectual merit</strong> of our efforts described below.&nbsp;</p> <p>At traditional interfaces, protein electrochemical signals, crucial to their incorporation in sensors, was distance limited, a property&nbsp;negatively affecting&nbsp;S/N.&nbsp; Our analysis of Az at NP film assemblies (Figure 1) resulted in relative distance independence of the electrochemical signal, up to distances 20 times greater than adsorption platforms without NPs, work published in <em>Langmuir </em>(2010). &nbsp;&nbsp;As part of this study, we utilized a novel cross-sectional TEM imaging technique that we published in <em>J. Visualized Experiments</em> (2011) to independently measure the thickness of our NP film assemblies.&nbsp; This student-directed video documentation of our procedures will benefit future research as a training video, saving valuable time and resources.&nbsp; Another important aspect of our work with S/N issues within these NP systems is differentiating the analytical signal from the background noise, a property we found to be dependent on interparticle linkages within the NP film.&nbsp; We explored this aspect of the protein at NP films using alternative electrochemical techniques known for their ability to discriminate against background noise (<em>J. Electroanal. Chem. </em>(2011)).&nbsp; &nbsp;Other undergraduate researchers established that the NP film assemblies provided interfaces for protein adsorption that were homogeneous, a property resulting in more uniform electrochemical signals which we visualized using atomic force microscopy.&nbsp; These findings were published in the <em>J. Colloid and Interface Science</em> (2010).&nbsp; Our success with these fundamental studies prompted our efforts to expand to alternative <em>aqueous </em>NPs, such as gold nano<em>shells </em>and silver nano<em>triangles</em>&nbsp;as well as optical sensing NP films described in work published in <em>Thin Solid Films </em>(2010) and <em>J. Materials Science </em>(2011) where we were able to establish the relativ...]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Project Outcomes Report (NSF-CHE-0847145)  "Nanoparticle Film Assemblies: Interfaces for Controlling the Nanoscale Adsorption Environment and Electrochemical Behavior of Immobilized Redox Proteins," Funding: $255,000 from 2/15/2009-1/31/2013.  As nanomaterials continue to emerge in both the scientific field and in products of everyday life, fundamental understanding of their structures, interconnection, and functionality continues to be an important goal of research.  The primary focus of our NSF funded project was to investigate gold nanoparticle (NP) film assemblies as an adsorption platform/interface for adsorbing proteins that are electrochemically active &ndash; fundamental bioanalytical chemistry related to important future medical applications.  The merger of such proteins with and man-made materials is a significant foundation for future sensor development, including real-time, implantable sensors for the continuous monitoring of clinically relevant species (e.g., glucose for diabetics or lactate for sepsis diagnosis) as well as general biocompatible materials.  We proposed the use of electrodes modified with a film ensemble of colloidal gold NPs as an alternative platform for fundamental studies of this nature.    In 2008, we introduced the use of non-aqueous NP films as a protein adsorption platform publishing our findings in the J. Am. Chem. Soc..  That work became the premise of the NSF proposal (CHE-0847145) which proposed specific experiments performed exclusively by undergraduates and aimed at a greater understanding of the NP film as this type of interface.  Our model system, blue copper azurin protein (Az) adsorbed to NP films, was used study different aspects of the NP film platform related to signal-to-noise (S/N), the most significant intellectual merit of our efforts described below.   At traditional interfaces, protein electrochemical signals, crucial to their incorporation in sensors, was distance limited, a property negatively affecting S/N.  Our analysis of Az at NP film assemblies (Figure 1) resulted in relative distance independence of the electrochemical signal, up to distances 20 times greater than adsorption platforms without NPs, work published in Langmuir (2010).   As part of this study, we utilized a novel cross-sectional TEM imaging technique that we published in J. Visualized Experiments (2011) to independently measure the thickness of our NP film assemblies.  This student-directed video documentation of our procedures will benefit future research as a training video, saving valuable time and resources.  Another important aspect of our work with S/N issues within these NP systems is differentiating the analytical signal from the background noise, a property we found to be dependent on interparticle linkages within the NP film.  We explored this aspect of the protein at NP films using alternative electrochemical techniques known for their ability to discriminate against background noise (J. Electroanal. Chem. (2011)).   Other undergraduate researchers established that the NP film assemblies provided interfaces for protein adsorption that were homogeneous, a property resulting in more uniform electrochemical signals which we visualized using atomic force microscopy.  These findings were published in the J. Colloid and Interface Science (2010).  Our success with these fundamental studies prompted our efforts to expand to alternative aqueous NPs, such as gold nanoshells and silver nanotriangles as well as optical sensing NP films described in work published in Thin Solid Films (2010) and J. Materials Science (2011) where we were able to establish the relative importance of electronic communication within the NP assembly.  Collectively these fundamental studies enabled the final stage of our research, preliminary studies using NP networks as a functional component of an actual sensor.  The viability of the NP networks in this capacity was shown with the successful incorporation of NPs within a si...]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
