<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>CAREER:  Ground-truthing Ozone and Particulate Matter Sensitivities to Emissions Trends</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2009</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2014</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>497768.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>497768</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>06020104</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>GEO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>AGS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Atmospheric &amp; Geospace Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Sylvia Edgerton</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>sedgerto@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032928522</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The research will consider recent abatement efforts in the United States as a real-world experiment in emissions perturbations, developing innovative techniques to ground-truth pollutant sensitivities to emissions trends.  An iterative inverse modeling method with four-dimensional data assimilation will be extended and applied to quantify long-term emissions trends and to evaluate ozone and particulate matter (PM) responsiveness to those trends.  The inverse modeling will identify leading contributors to uncertainty in sensitivities and investigate potential adjustments to improve the accuracy of photochemical modeling.  Scientific investigations and environmental decision-making rely on environmental models to accurately simulate not only pollutant concentrations but also their sensitivities to emissions.  Simulating sensitivities is especially challenging for air pollutants such as ozone and PM that exhibit nonlinear and highly variable responses to multiple precursor emissions. Whereas models are routinely evaluated against observations for pollutant concentrations, much less is known about the accuracy of pollutant sensitivities that cannot be directly observed.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Broader impacts will include an education plan that will engage a significant number of fifth-grade students in hands-on, inquiry-based learning about meteorology and air pollution.  Students will develop hypotheses and conduct hands-on measurements to investigate how weather and pollutant conditions vary on their school campuses.  Lesson plans will be developed and implemented at a pilot school and then used to train teachers from across the Houston region to teach scientific environmental inquiry at their own campuses.  The principal investigator will also engage undergraduate and graduate students in scientific learning and research through vertically-integrated research experiences and the development of new curriculum and colloquia.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>02/05/2009</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>04/08/2013</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.050</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>0847386</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Daniel</FirstName>
<LastName>Cohan</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>S</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Daniel S Cohan</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>cohan@rice.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>7133485129</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000497610</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>02/05/2009</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>William Marsh Rice University</Name>
<CityName>Houston</CityName>
<ZipCode>770051827</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>7133484820</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>6100 MAIN ST</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Texas</StateName>
<StateCode>TX</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>TX02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>050299031</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>WILLIAM MARSH RICE UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>050299031</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[William Marsh Rice University]]></Name>
<CityName>Houston</CityName>
<StateCode>TX</StateCode>
<ZipCode>770051827</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[6100 MAIN ST]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Texas</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>TX02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<FoaInformation>
<Code>0000099</Code>
<Name>Other Applications NEC</Name>
</FoaInformation>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1524</Code>
<Text>Atmospheric Chemistry</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>0000</Code>
<Text>UNASSIGNED</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1045</Code>
<Text>CAREER-Faculty Erly Career Dev</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1187</Code>
<Text>PECASE- eligible</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>OTHR</Code>
<Text>OTHER RESEARCH OR EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0109</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0110</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0111</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0112</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0113</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2009~153014</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2010~79152</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2011~87756</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2012~90068</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2013~87778</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>This NSF CAREER project yielded substantial progress toward better characterizing how ambient air quality responds to long term trends in emissions. With billions of dollars spent each year to control emissions, characterizing the resulting benefits is critical to gauging progress and targeting subsequent efforts. Atmospheric models such as the ones used in this study are the most widely used tools for assessing these impacts, but their accuracy is representing atmospheric responsiveness has long been uncertain. This project capitalized upon recent cases of major emissions controls, ranging from local to interstate scales, along with observational data made available by field campaigns, regulatory monitors, and improved satellite retrievals, to develop enhanced techniques for dynamic evaluation of photochemical models&rsquo; abilities to represent atmospheric sensitivities. Across much of the eastern United States, our analysis showed that models tended to underpredict the ozone reductions that resulted from reductions in nitrogen oxide emissions. Our analysis was able to demonstrate that much of this underprediction may have resulted from precursor emissions declining faster than indicated by the emissions inventories, and thus that the photochemical model itself was reasonably accurate in representing the trends in ozone. This finding was reinforced by separate analyses of regulatory modeling used in attainment plans for both ozone and fine particulate matter. In both cases, we found that the attainment modeling reasonably predicted the improvements in ozone and particulate matter levels that were observed in most non-attainment regions.</p> <p>In addition to the multi-region analyses, we focused a portion of our research efforts on characterizing air quality sensitivities and trends in Texas, where two intensive field campaigns across a span of six years gave us the opportunity to incorporate specialized data from aircraft and other sources. In one published paper from this work, we characterized the evolution of ozone and particulate matter in coal-fired power plant plumes as they dispersed downwind. Another paper applied a highly detailed photochemical mechanism to quantify changes in ozone production rates and radical chemistry across the six year span; it showed that hydrocarbon emission reductions had played an important role along with nitrogen oxide reductions in contributing to observed improvements in ozone in the Houston region.</p> <p>Beyond the numerous journal papers and conference presentations that disseminated the findings of our scientific research, substantial broader impacts were achieved through education and outreach. The PI worked with elementary school science teachers and curriculum specialists to develop the Rice Air Curriculum (available via the Connexions digital education library), which enables students to conduct hands-on inquiry involving measurements of ozone and meteorological conditions. Subsequent work with high school science teachers adapted some of these lessons for use in high school environmental science classes. The PI also conducted curricular innovations in his Energy and the Environment class at Rice, sharing these innovations in a journal article.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 09/23/2014<br>      Modified by: Daniel&nbsp;S&nbsp;Cohan</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ This NSF CAREER project yielded substantial progress toward better characterizing how ambient air quality responds to long term trends in emissions. With billions of dollars spent each year to control emissions, characterizing the resulting benefits is critical to gauging progress and targeting subsequent efforts. Atmospheric models such as the ones used in this study are the most widely used tools for assessing these impacts, but their accuracy is representing atmospheric responsiveness has long been uncertain. This project capitalized upon recent cases of major emissions controls, ranging from local to interstate scales, along with observational data made available by field campaigns, regulatory monitors, and improved satellite retrievals, to develop enhanced techniques for dynamic evaluation of photochemical modelsÆ abilities to represent atmospheric sensitivities. Across much of the eastern United States, our analysis showed that models tended to underpredict the ozone reductions that resulted from reductions in nitrogen oxide emissions. Our analysis was able to demonstrate that much of this underprediction may have resulted from precursor emissions declining faster than indicated by the emissions inventories, and thus that the photochemical model itself was reasonably accurate in representing the trends in ozone. This finding was reinforced by separate analyses of regulatory modeling used in attainment plans for both ozone and fine particulate matter. In both cases, we found that the attainment modeling reasonably predicted the improvements in ozone and particulate matter levels that were observed in most non-attainment regions.  In addition to the multi-region analyses, we focused a portion of our research efforts on characterizing air quality sensitivities and trends in Texas, where two intensive field campaigns across a span of six years gave us the opportunity to incorporate specialized data from aircraft and other sources. In one published paper from this work, we characterized the evolution of ozone and particulate matter in coal-fired power plant plumes as they dispersed downwind. Another paper applied a highly detailed photochemical mechanism to quantify changes in ozone production rates and radical chemistry across the six year span; it showed that hydrocarbon emission reductions had played an important role along with nitrogen oxide reductions in contributing to observed improvements in ozone in the Houston region.  Beyond the numerous journal papers and conference presentations that disseminated the findings of our scientific research, substantial broader impacts were achieved through education and outreach. The PI worked with elementary school science teachers and curriculum specialists to develop the Rice Air Curriculum (available via the Connexions digital education library), which enables students to conduct hands-on inquiry involving measurements of ozone and meteorological conditions. Subsequent work with high school science teachers adapted some of these lessons for use in high school environmental science classes. The PI also conducted curricular innovations in his Energy and the Environment class at Rice, sharing these innovations in a journal article.          Last Modified: 09/23/2014       Submitted by: Daniel S Cohan]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
