<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>SBIR Phase II:  Shape Variations in the Development of Miniature Micropumps</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>03/01/2009</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>09/30/2012</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>500000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>891010</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07070000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>IIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Industrial Innovation &amp; Partnersh</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Muralidharan Nair</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>mnair@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927059</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This Small Business Innovation Research (SBIR) Phase II research project focuses on the development of a product line of miniature pumping systems for the controlled delivery of fluids in ultra-low flow rate range (nanoliters to microliters per minute). This line of micropump systems will provide pulse-free flow and controlled micro-volume dispensing in this challenging low volume regime. The non-mechanical nature and operating principles of this pump afford an unusual degree of freedom in pump design. The ability to tailor the shape and size of the micropump to specific applications can be very valuable, particularly in small devices where the available space is significantly constrained (for example, point-of-care devices, portable chemical and biological analysis systems, and micro-dosing devices). &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;There is a growing diversity of chemical and biological analyses that are taking place within small chips, as well as in the rising demand for ultra-small dosing systems. Such analyses are continuing to shrink in size and measurements that have conventionally been performed in a laboratory and are now being adapted to handheld devices. These micro-analysis systems can provide immediate results without waiting for laboratory analyses. For example, the analysis of blood samples is being adapted to small devices, so important results are available at the point-of-care. Likewise, the desire is growing for small, portable dosing systems for animal studies and for human medications (like insulin and chronic pain management). All of these applications require micropumps for the controlled delivery of compounds. Fundamental engineering constraints mean that conventional mechanical pumps cannot be simply decreased in size to meet this challenge. These miniature non-mechanical pumps require very little power, can be controlled to deliver at constant flow rate or specific dispensing volumes, and offer the pulse-less flow that is not accessible by other pumps. This provides a significant market opportunity in the liquid pumping market (roughly $160 million presently), into the animal dosing (valued at approximately $90 million per year) and human drug delivery (valued at $80 billion presently) markets.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>02/20/2009</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>12/14/2011</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>0848253</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Christine</FirstName>
<LastName>Evans</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Christine Evans</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>ceevans@sfc-fluidics.com</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>4795712592</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000067610</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>02/20/2009</StartDate>
<EndDate>03/04/2010</EndDate>
<RoleCode>Former Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Forrest</FirstName>
<LastName>Payne</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Forrest Payne</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>forrest.payne@sfc-fluidics.com</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>4795276810</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000557257</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>03/04/2010</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>SFC Fluidics, Inc</Name>
<CityName>Fayetteville</CityName>
<ZipCode>727016534</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>4795276810</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>534 W RESEARCH BLVD, SUITE 260</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Arkansas</StateName>
<StateCode>AR</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>AR03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>125518428</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>SFC FLUIDICS, INC.</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[SFC Fluidics, Inc]]></Name>
<CityName>Fayetteville</CityName>
<StateCode>AR</StateCode>
<ZipCode>727016534</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[534 W RESEARCH BLVD, SUITE 260]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Arkansas</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>AR03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<FoaInformation>
<Code>0308000</Code>
<Name>Industrial Technology</Name>
</FoaInformation>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>5373</Code>
<Text>SBIR Phase II</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1185</Code>
<Text>SENSORY SYSTEMS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>165E</Code>
<Text>SBIR Phase IIB</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>169E</Code>
<Text>SBIR Tech Enhan Partner (TECP)</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9139</Code>
<Text>INFORMATION INFRASTRUCTURE &amp; TECH APPL</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>HPCC</Code>
<Text>HIGH PERFORMANCE COMPUTING &amp; COMM</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0109</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0111</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0112</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2009~500000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2011~100000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2012~291010</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p style="text-align: center;"><strong>SBIR Phase II/TECP/IIIB (#0848253) </strong></p> <p style="text-align: center;"><strong>Shape Variations in the Development of Miniature Micropumps </strong></p> <p style="text-align: center;"><strong>SBIR Phase II/TECP/IIB Project Outcomes Report for General Public</strong></p> <p><strong>&nbsp;</strong></p> <p><span style="white-space: pre;"> </span>The overarching goal of this Phase II project is to apply our innovative electrochemical actuation technology, ePump<sup>&reg;</sup>, to develop and commercialize a product line of miniature pumping systems for controlled delivery of fluids in the ultra-low flow rate regime.&nbsp; &nbsp;&nbsp;The project resulted in the development of two stand-alone pumping systems:&nbsp; the &nbsp;ePump Solvent Delivery System&trade;, and the <em>vivo</em>Pump Animal Dosing System&trade;. ePump is an electrochemical actuation technology that SFC Fluidics uses to make microfluidic pumps.&nbsp; The non-mechanical nature of the pumps allows them to be made in virtually any shape of size, use very little power, and provide truly pulse-free flow.&nbsp; The development of the two distinct pumping systems exemplifies the ability of ePump to be designed with minimal constraints on size and shape. The ePump Solvent Delivery System (renamed the ePump Model 190) consists of a miniature ePump (~1 in<sup>3</sup>) and a controller that allows users to control either the flow rate or the dispensed volume of the pump. &nbsp;The <em>vivo</em>Pump, or Model 220 ePump, contains its own power source and is small enough to fit on the back of a small animal (rat, rabbit, or larger animal). This pump is controlled wirelessly from a computer controlled USB transmitter, so that the animal will be free to move around while still receiving the necessary dosage of fluids.</p> <p class="Default"><span style="white-space: pre;"> </span>In of March 2011, the ePump Model 190 was launched as a commercial product for use as a bench-top laboratory pumping system.&nbsp; NSF funding in the form of a TECP extension to the Phase II grant allowed remote operation functionality to be added to the Model 190.&nbsp; Several of these have been sold to various research institutions and tested by medical device manufacturers.&nbsp; World Precision Instruments, Inc. (WPI) is in negotiations to carry the Model 190 as one of their pumps for use in the research market.&nbsp; The Model 190 is currently listed on their website (<a href="http://www.wpiinc.com/">www.wpiinc.com</a>, product # SF-PF190), and it has been displayed it at several trade shows.&nbsp; It is highlighted as the only microfluidic pump WPI carries that can deliver truly pulse-free flow. &nbsp;Founded in 1967, WPI is a leading global provider of powerful, cutting-edge laboratory solutions for the life sciences.&nbsp; In addition to showing the pump at trade shows and listing us in their catalogue, they will have sales representatives who visit universities and other research institutions to market the ePump.&nbsp; Additionally, WPI works with several animal research labs and will facilitate the initiation of the beta testing of the Model 220 wireless pumping system.&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; The biggest confirmation of the ePumps&rsquo; imminent success has been the development of a partnership between SFC Fluidics and a major medical device company to develop a pump for a specific high-value target application.&nbsp; The work done in this Phase II, especially Phase IIB, has led to a development agreement between SFC Fluidics and this company.&nbsp; Many of the Objectives of the Phase IIB were geared toward pump functionality required by the company.&nbsp; Thankfully, the Phase IIB funding allowed SFC to advance the pump technology to the point that we have been commissioned by this company to develop an ePump system specific t...]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[SBIR Phase II/TECP/IIIB (#0848253)  Shape Variations in the Development of Miniature Micropumps  SBIR Phase II/TECP/IIB Project Outcomes Report for General Public      The overarching goal of this Phase II project is to apply our innovative electrochemical actuation technology, ePump&reg;, to develop and commercialize a product line of miniature pumping systems for controlled delivery of fluids in the ultra-low flow rate regime.    The project resulted in the development of two stand-alone pumping systems:  the  ePump Solvent Delivery System&trade;, and the vivoPump Animal Dosing System&trade;. ePump is an electrochemical actuation technology that SFC Fluidics uses to make microfluidic pumps.  The non-mechanical nature of the pumps allows them to be made in virtually any shape of size, use very little power, and provide truly pulse-free flow.  The development of the two distinct pumping systems exemplifies the ability of ePump to be designed with minimal constraints on size and shape. The ePump Solvent Delivery System (renamed the ePump Model 190) consists of a miniature ePump (~1 in3) and a controller that allows users to control either the flow rate or the dispensed volume of the pump.  The vivoPump, or Model 220 ePump, contains its own power source and is small enough to fit on the back of a small animal (rat, rabbit, or larger animal). This pump is controlled wirelessly from a computer controlled USB transmitter, so that the animal will be free to move around while still receiving the necessary dosage of fluids.  In of March 2011, the ePump Model 190 was launched as a commercial product for use as a bench-top laboratory pumping system.  NSF funding in the form of a TECP extension to the Phase II grant allowed remote operation functionality to be added to the Model 190.  Several of these have been sold to various research institutions and tested by medical device manufacturers.  World Precision Instruments, Inc. (WPI) is in negotiations to carry the Model 190 as one of their pumps for use in the research market.  The Model 190 is currently listed on their website (www.wpiinc.com, product # SF-PF190), and it has been displayed it at several trade shows.  It is highlighted as the only microfluidic pump WPI carries that can deliver truly pulse-free flow.  Founded in 1967, WPI is a leading global provider of powerful, cutting-edge laboratory solutions for the life sciences.  In addition to showing the pump at trade shows and listing us in their catalogue, they will have sales representatives who visit universities and other research institutions to market the ePump.  Additionally, WPI works with several animal research labs and will facilitate the initiation of the beta testing of the Model 220 wireless pumping system.               The biggest confirmation of the ePumpsÆ imminent success has been the development of a partnership between SFC Fluidics and a major medical device company to develop a pump for a specific high-value target application.  The work done in this Phase II, especially Phase IIB, has led to a development agreement between SFC Fluidics and this company.  Many of the Objectives of the Phase IIB were geared toward pump functionality required by the company.  Thankfully, the Phase IIB funding allowed SFC to advance the pump technology to the point that we have been commissioned by this company to develop an ePump system specific to their needs.  The advantage of ePump is that it can meet target flow specifications in an embodiment that is small, can be battery operated, is inexpensive enough to be disposable and is accurate and reliable.  SFC is currently working closely with the scientists, engineers and business development team of the medical device company to develop the pumps, valves, and control system that they need.           Last Modified: 12/27/2012       Submitted by: Forrest Payne]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
