<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Collaborative Research:  Creation of a coastal current - The transition of an energetic river discharge from buoyant jet to geostrophic plume</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>03/15/2009</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>02/28/2013</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>326944.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>363444</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>06040303</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>GEO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>OCE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Ocean Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Eric C. Itsweire</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The mid-field river plume is a transition area where a multitude of geophysical mechanisms act to constrain and transform a strongly inertial jet into a geostrophic coastal current. The near-field jet is the area over which the estuarine outflow is supercritical, where advection and shear mixing dominate the dynamics, where the shape of the estuary mouth is important in determining the shape of the near-field plume flow structure, and where the flow is often directed offshore. This is distinct from the geostrophic far-field river plume where the earth?s rotation, wind, and background flow dominate the evolution of the plume, and the flow is primarily along-shore. Although entrainment of ambient water is high in the near-field, the far-field plume tends to form a coastally-trapped boundary current where entrainment is quite small in the absence of other forcing mechanisms such as winds and tides. Within the mid-field, plume spreading must be arrested, mixing reduced, and the flow directed along-shore. Rotation or background currents may arrest plume spreading, preventing plume acceleration and reducing further mixing in the plume. Frontal processes enhance mixing locally, but have an unknown effect on the core of the plume. The contribution of each of these processes to the spreading and mixing of the plume is expected to depend strongly on the scale of the plume. A quantitative understanding of the relative role of these processes is necessary for determining the dynamical role of river plumes of different scales on shelf circulation and transport.&lt;br/&gt;The overall objective of this proposal is to better understand how small scale processes of O(1 km) operating near an estuary mouth transition to larger-scale (O(100 km)) buoyancy driven coastal currents through the intermediate scales of O(10 km). The central hypothesis is that a suite of processes operating in the mid-field plume modify the plume spreading and mixing and thus the transition between the near- and far-field plumes. The proposed work will establish the relative influence of a number of key mechanisms in setting the spatial and temporal scales of the near- and mid-field plume regions. It will constrain the total water mass modification in the initial evolution of the plume and help understand how continental shelf-scale coastal currents are formed. The following three specific objectives will be pursued:&lt;br/&gt;1) Quantify the processes that arrest plume spreading,&lt;br/&gt;2) Relate reduced mixing rates to arrested plume spreading and&lt;br/&gt;3) Determine net mixing in the near- and mid-field regions.&lt;br/&gt;The approach will be one that  integrates field observations, laboratory experiments and numerical model experiments. Such an approach is necessary to accurately describe and quantify the full array of physical processes that contribute to mixing in natural plumes and to determine how these processes are modified across a broad parameter space. Detailed field measurements in the Merrimack River plume will be complimented with non-rotating and rotating laboratory experiments and laboratory and geophysical scale numerical model experiments. This work will fill an important gap in the ability to relate fresh water discharge to large scale coastal ocean circulation.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The broader impacts of the study are two-fold: better understanding the role of river plumes in coastal oceanography, and education of graduate and undergraduate students. The study will determine how river inflows affect water properties over a large area influenced by plumes and provide better predictive capability to coastal managers. It will fund three graduate students, one at each of the three participating institutions. In addition, the field campaigns will provide a unique learning experience not only for the three funded graduate students, but for additional graduate and undergraduate students. The use of a number of small vessels for synoptic research will require graduate students to assume chief scientist responsibilities on individual vessels, providing a level of autonomy and responsibility rare for larger scale physical oceanographic field programs.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>03/10/2009</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/18/2011</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.050</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>0850847</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Alexander</FirstName>
<LastName>Horner-Devine</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Alexander Horner-Devine</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>arhd@u.washington.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2066853032</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000488762</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>03/10/2009</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Washington</Name>
<CityName>Seattle</CityName>
<ZipCode>981950001</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2065434043</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>4333 Brooklyn Ave NE</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Washington</StateName>
<StateCode>WA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>WA07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>605799469</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF WASHINGTON</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>042803536</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Washington]]></Name>
<CityName>Seattle</CityName>
<StateCode>WA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>981950001</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[4333 Brooklyn Ave NE]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Washington</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>WA07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<FoaInformation>
<Code>0204000</Code>
<Name>Oceanography</Name>
</FoaInformation>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1610</Code>
<Text>PHYSICAL OCEANOGRAPHY</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>0000</Code>
<Text>UNASSIGNED</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9251</Code>
<Text>REU SUPP-Res Exp for Ugrd Supp</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>OTHR</Code>
<Text>OTHER RESEARCH OR EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0109</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0110</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0111</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2009~338944</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2010~8500</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2011~16000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Rivers play an important role in the health of coastal ecosystems as they carry a diverse array of river-borne materials such as contaminants, sediments and small organisms that originate in the watershed. Contamination from rivers usually tracks with the river water as it is carried into the coastal ocean, where it can have deleterious environmental impacts resulting in closed fisheries and beaches, for example. In addition, the freshwater from rivers is an important source of buoyancy along the coast, which drives alongshore currents and contributes to coastal transport processes. For this reason, a good understanding of the processes that mix and disperse the river water and the material it carries is important for management of coastal waters.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>The objective of this study, known as the Merrimack River Mixing and Divergence Experiment II (MeRMADE II) is to understand the mechanisms responsible for the mixing of the discharge from the estuary as it enters the ocean. As river water first enters the coastal ocean it behaves somewhat like a jet, which has been well-studied in engineering research. The principle difference is that river water is buoyant compared with the ocean water due to the difference in salinity; this tends to reduce the rate at which mixing with ocean water occurs. The density-stratified jet-like region is referred to as the near-field plume. After this initial dilution occurs, a host of processes begin to be important that further modify the mixing process, including the effect of the earth&rsquo;s rotation, the role of existing currents along the coast, and the influence of the wind. We refer to the region where these secondary processes become important as the mid-field plume. Beyond this mid-field region, the river plume transitions to a coastally trapped current whose dynamics are dominated by the effects of earth&rsquo;s rotation. The objective of the work in this project was to better understand the mixing processes in the near- and mid-field plume, focusing especially on understanding how the mid-field processes may shut down the high mixing rates typically observed in the near-field.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>Intellectual merit: The project tackled this question using three parallel, but coupled, scientific approaches. We carried out laboratory experiments and computer simulations to develop theory and test hypotheses, and then we made measurements in the Merrimack River plume off the coast of Massachusetts to test the theoretical results and develop new ideas about how this complex system works. The primary findings from the work were: 1) laboratory experiments showed that, while lateral plume spreading significantly modifies the structure of the plume and the total mixing, it doesn&rsquo;t change the turbulent processes at the base of the plume, as is suggested by field observations; 2) two adjacent plumes may significantly interact with each other, especially if they are close enough together; 3) moderate winds have a much stronger influence on the dynamics of many plumes, even in the early phases of plume evolution, than was previously assumed; and, 4) the plume front contains lobe-cleft structures that are characteristic of other gravity currents with a non-slip bottom, such as avalanches and turbidity currents.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p><em>Broader impacts:</em> This work contributed to our understanding of dynamics that are important for the health and maintenance of coastal ecosystems. Improvements in our understanding of the underlying physics and our ability to model these systems with computer models will aid in the management of coastal ecosystems and prediction of the response of these systems to environmental changes. The project supported one PhD student, whose dissertation was focused on the laboratory experiments. She has now finished and is starting a postdoc. It also supported 5 undergraduate students who he...]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Rivers play an important role in the health of coastal ecosystems as they carry a diverse array of river-borne materials such as contaminants, sediments and small organisms that originate in the watershed. Contamination from rivers usually tracks with the river water as it is carried into the coastal ocean, where it can have deleterious environmental impacts resulting in closed fisheries and beaches, for example. In addition, the freshwater from rivers is an important source of buoyancy along the coast, which drives alongshore currents and contributes to coastal transport processes. For this reason, a good understanding of the processes that mix and disperse the river water and the material it carries is important for management of coastal waters.     The objective of this study, known as the Merrimack River Mixing and Divergence Experiment II (MeRMADE II) is to understand the mechanisms responsible for the mixing of the discharge from the estuary as it enters the ocean. As river water first enters the coastal ocean it behaves somewhat like a jet, which has been well-studied in engineering research. The principle difference is that river water is buoyant compared with the ocean water due to the difference in salinity; this tends to reduce the rate at which mixing with ocean water occurs. The density-stratified jet-like region is referred to as the near-field plume. After this initial dilution occurs, a host of processes begin to be important that further modify the mixing process, including the effect of the earthÆs rotation, the role of existing currents along the coast, and the influence of the wind. We refer to the region where these secondary processes become important as the mid-field plume. Beyond this mid-field region, the river plume transitions to a coastally trapped current whose dynamics are dominated by the effects of earthÆs rotation. The objective of the work in this project was to better understand the mixing processes in the near- and mid-field plume, focusing especially on understanding how the mid-field processes may shut down the high mixing rates typically observed in the near-field.     Intellectual merit: The project tackled this question using three parallel, but coupled, scientific approaches. We carried out laboratory experiments and computer simulations to develop theory and test hypotheses, and then we made measurements in the Merrimack River plume off the coast of Massachusetts to test the theoretical results and develop new ideas about how this complex system works. The primary findings from the work were: 1) laboratory experiments showed that, while lateral plume spreading significantly modifies the structure of the plume and the total mixing, it doesnÆt change the turbulent processes at the base of the plume, as is suggested by field observations; 2) two adjacent plumes may significantly interact with each other, especially if they are close enough together; 3) moderate winds have a much stronger influence on the dynamics of many plumes, even in the early phases of plume evolution, than was previously assumed; and, 4) the plume front contains lobe-cleft structures that are characteristic of other gravity currents with a non-slip bottom, such as avalanches and turbidity currents.     Broader impacts: This work contributed to our understanding of dynamics that are important for the health and maintenance of coastal ecosystems. Improvements in our understanding of the underlying physics and our ability to model these systems with computer models will aid in the management of coastal ecosystems and prediction of the response of these systems to environmental changes. The project supported one PhD student, whose dissertation was focused on the laboratory experiments. She has now finished and is starting a postdoc. It also supported 5 undergraduate students who helped with laboratory experiments and field measurements during their summers in order to learn about the scientific process. All of these un...]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
