<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>An Interdisciplinary Materials Science REU Program at James Madison University</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>04/01/2009</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>09/30/2012</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>255000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>255000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03070002</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DMR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Materials Research</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Michael J. Scott</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The James Madison University (JMU) Center for Materials Science offers a Research Experience for Undergraduates in the unique environment of a primarily undergraduate university with strong support for interdisciplinary research in materials science. Students in this program work in small groups with other undergraduates under the direct supervision of a JMU faculty member. The students and faculty come from a wide variety of backgrounds including physics, chemistry, engineering, geology, and mathematics. Projects include the fabrication of microfluidic devices, the growth and characterization of carbon nanotubes, the modeling of granular materials and crystallization processes, and the chemistry associated with technically important metal oxides and organic molecules that have potential uses in molecular motors.  Students will work with state of the art equipment in a class 10000 clean room, metal deposition and photolithography tools, scanning probe and electron microscopes and optical spectrometers.  Students also participate in activities that enhance their technical communication and presentation skills and are given the opportunity to travel to regional and national meetings to present their work before a broader audience.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This Research Experience for Undergraduates (REU) Site is co-funded by the Department of Defense in partnership with the NSF REU program and NSF Division of Materials Research in the Mathematical and Physical Sciences Directorate.&lt;br/&gt;</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>03/09/2009</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>02/20/2011</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>0851367</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>William</FirstName>
<LastName>Hughes</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>C</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>William C Hughes</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>hugheswc@jmu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5405688069</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000250254</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>03/09/2009</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Brian</FirstName>
<LastName>Augustine</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>H</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Brian H Augustine</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>baugusti@highpoint.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>3368419405</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000186548</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>03/09/2009</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>James Madison University</Name>
<CityName>HARRISONBURG</CityName>
<ZipCode>228077000</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5405686872</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>MSC 5728</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[800 South Main Street]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Virginia</StateName>
<StateCode>VA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>00</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>VA00</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>879325355</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>JAMES MADISON UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>879325355</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[James Madison University]]></Name>
<CityName>HARRISONBURG</CityName>
<StateCode>VA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>228077000</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[MSC 5728]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Virginia</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>00</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>VA00</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<FoaInformation>
<Code>0106000</Code>
<Name>Materials Research</Name>
</FoaInformation>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7222</Code>
<Text>XC-Crosscutting Activities Pro</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>H433</Code>
<Text/>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>J103</Code>
<Text/>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>J243</Code>
<Text/>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7237</Code>
<Text>NANO NON-SOLIC SCI &amp; ENG AWD</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7736</Code>
<Text>DOD ASSURE PROGRAM</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9178</Code>
<Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9250</Code>
<Text>REU SITE-Res Exp for Ugrd Site</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>SMET</Code>
<Text>SCIENCE, MATH, ENG &amp; TECH EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0109</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0111</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0409</Code>
<Name>NSF Education &amp; Human Resource</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040106</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0410</Code>
<Name>NSF Education &amp; Human Resource</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040106</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0411</Code>
<Name>NSF Education &amp; Human Resource</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040106</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2009~126000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2010~44000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2011~85000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><span>The&nbsp;Interdisciplinary Materials Science REU Program at James Madison University supported 32 undergraduate students from 18 different institutions. These students worked in research labs under the direct, daily supervision of JMU faculty on a variety of projects. The primary goal was to provide undergraduate students the opportunity to participate in research in order to encourage them to pursue research careers including advanced degrees in STEM fields. We particularly concentrated on offering this opportunity to students who were early in their undergraduate careers or who came from other institutions at which they would not have had an opportunity to work on advanced research. Of the students who participated, 16 are still enrolled as undergraduates and most of these have expressed an interest in continuing on in science and engineering. Of the ones who have finished their bachelor&rsquo;s degrees, 5 are in graduate school, 1 in medical school, and 4 are working in scientific or engineering fields such as for PPG&rsquo;s solar cell research group or the NSWC at Dahlgren. The remaining 6 are unknown.</span></p> <p><span>The research projects that the students worked on have resulted in 15 different publications in scholarly journals with the students as either lead authors or co-authors. The student have also presented 34 talks or posters at regional and national scientific conferences such as the March Meeting of the American Physical Society, the Materials Research Society meeting, the National Meeting of the American Chemical Society, and&nbsp; the national meeting of the Geological Society of America. This included research on topics such as improving the adhesion of gold to acrylic surfaces, understanding the jamming transition in granular flows, developing a better understanding of the absorption of infrared (IR) light by thin aluminum oxide films, and using materials characterization methods to explain unique geological formations in the Shenandoah Valley, to name a few. All of these research projects are basic science that is foundational to deeper understanding of problems that may technical or societal. For example, the study of surface adhesion could lead to improved polymer devices such as flexible electronics while the study of IR absorption study could provide the basis for understanding loss mechanisms in photovoltaic devices.</span></p> <p><span>Using funding provided by other sources, undergraduate students from other countries were also invited to work alongside the domestic students funded by this grant. This allowed out domestic students to develop a better appreciation of the international nature of scientific research and undergraduate education. These international students came from universities in Brazil, Korea, UK, and South Africa and in some cases are planning to come back to the US for graduate studies based on their experience here.</span></p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 10/10/2012<br>      Modified by: William&nbsp;C&nbsp;Hughes</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Images (<span id="selectedPhoto0">1</span> of <span class="totalNumber"></span>)           </div> <div class="galControls" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2012/0851367/0851367_10027346_1349882869482_Untitled1--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2012/0851367/0851367_10027346_1349882869482_Untitled1--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Student Presentations"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2012/0851367/0851367_10027346_1349882869482_Untitled1--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Student Presentations"></a...]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The Interdisciplinary Materials Science REU Program at James Madison University supported 32 undergraduate students from 18 different institutions. These students worked in research labs under the direct, daily supervision of JMU faculty on a variety of projects. The primary goal was to provide undergraduate students the opportunity to participate in research in order to encourage them to pursue research careers including advanced degrees in STEM fields. We particularly concentrated on offering this opportunity to students who were early in their undergraduate careers or who came from other institutions at which they would not have had an opportunity to work on advanced research. Of the students who participated, 16 are still enrolled as undergraduates and most of these have expressed an interest in continuing on in science and engineering. Of the ones who have finished their bachelorÆs degrees, 5 are in graduate school, 1 in medical school, and 4 are working in scientific or engineering fields such as for PPGÆs solar cell research group or the NSWC at Dahlgren. The remaining 6 are unknown.  The research projects that the students worked on have resulted in 15 different publications in scholarly journals with the students as either lead authors or co-authors. The student have also presented 34 talks or posters at regional and national scientific conferences such as the March Meeting of the American Physical Society, the Materials Research Society meeting, the National Meeting of the American Chemical Society, and  the national meeting of the Geological Society of America. This included research on topics such as improving the adhesion of gold to acrylic surfaces, understanding the jamming transition in granular flows, developing a better understanding of the absorption of infrared (IR) light by thin aluminum oxide films, and using materials characterization methods to explain unique geological formations in the Shenandoah Valley, to name a few. All of these research projects are basic science that is foundational to deeper understanding of problems that may technical or societal. For example, the study of surface adhesion could lead to improved polymer devices such as flexible electronics while the study of IR absorption study could provide the basis for understanding loss mechanisms in photovoltaic devices.  Using funding provided by other sources, undergraduate students from other countries were also invited to work alongside the domestic students funded by this grant. This allowed out domestic students to develop a better appreciation of the international nature of scientific research and undergraduate education. These international students came from universities in Brazil, Korea, UK, and South Africa and in some cases are planning to come back to the US for graduate studies based on their experience here.          Last Modified: 10/10/2012       Submitted by: William C Hughes]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
