<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>REU Site: Biological Materials and Processes (BioMaP)</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>05/01/2009</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>04/30/2012</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>303403.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>303403</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07050000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>EEC</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Engineering Education and Centers</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Esther Bolding</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Proposal: 0851519&lt;br/&gt;PI Name: Narasimhan, Balaji&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This three year renewal REU site program at Iowa State University (ISU) will provide an opportunity for undergraduate students to do hands-on research focused on two research themes: 1) Biological Materials and Biological Processes. The students will be active members of interdisciplinary groups and will interact with faculty, post-docs, graduate students, and industry.  Some of the students will also participate in an international research experience at the Instituto Tecnologico y de Estudios Superiores de Monterrey (ITESM), Mexico, which will build on an existing partnership with ISU, and provide students with valuable skills in a global environment.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;In addition to the research experience, a variety of enrichment activities have been incorporated. These include: short courses, joint seminars/meetings, workshops, tours of research facilities, and field trips.  At the end of the program, the students will participate in a joint poster symposium together with students from other ISU undergraduate programs.  &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;A talented and diverse group of students will be recruited, with special efforts made to attract women and minorities.  The experience some students will get working in a global environment will evolve from dependent to independent status and will enable them to walk away with life-long skills that will impact their contributions to science and engineering and to society.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>04/06/2009</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/28/2010</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>0851519</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Balaji</FirstName>
<LastName>Narasimhan</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Balaji Narasimhan</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>nbalaji@iastate.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5152948019</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000286877</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/06/2009</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Monica</FirstName>
<LastName>Lamm</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>H</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Monica H Lamm</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>mhlamm@iastate.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5152946533</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000184232</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/06/2009</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Iowa State University</Name>
<CityName>AMES</CityName>
<ZipCode>500112207</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5152945225</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1138 Pearson</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Iowa</StateName>
<StateCode>IA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>IA04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>005309844</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>IOWA STATE UNIVERSITY OF SCIENCE AND TECHNOLOGY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>005309844</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Iowa State University]]></Name>
<CityName>AMES</CityName>
<StateCode>IA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>500112207</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[1138 Pearson]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Iowa</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>IA04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1360</Code>
<Text>EWFD-Eng Workforce Development</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>116E</Code>
<Text>RESEARCH EXP FOR UNDERGRADS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1360</Code>
<Text>HUMAN RESOURCES DEVELOPMENT</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9178</Code>
<Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9250</Code>
<Text>REU SITE-Res Exp for Ugrd Site</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>SMET</Code>
<Text>SCIENCE, MATH, ENG &amp; TECH EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0109</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0110</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2009~201910</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2010~101493</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The BioMaP Research Experiences for Undergraduates (REU) Program was offered at Iowa State University in the summers of 2009-11. A comprehensive and content-rich website (http://www.cbe.iastate.edu/research/undergraduate-research/) was developed that described the application process, research projects, contact information for faculty and staff, and other programmatic details. This NSF project funded 11 students each summer (33 in total) and matching funds from ISU were used to fund 13 additional students, bringing the total number of students funded by the program in three years to 46. Of these students, 43% were female and 17% were underrepresented minorities. The average GPA of the BioMaP students over three years was 3.80/4.00.</p> <p>The research performed by the students in the area of biological materials and processes has led to new high throughput methods for rapid screening of biomaterials, discovery of a new catalytic mechanism in glucoamylases, novel bioseparation methods for proteins, thermochemical processing methods for biomass, and new block copolymers for gene delivery. The BioMaP REU students produced seven refereed journal publications, five refereed conference proceedings, and 21 conference presentations. Several of the REU students won awards for research performed as part of the BioMaP REU.</p> <p>The participants experienced a substantial research experience in a cross-disciplinary area; indeed, many students split their time in laboratories of multiple PI&rsquo;s in departments such as cell biology, immunology, physics, and chemistry. This exposed the students to the excitement and the challenges of working at interfaces between fields. The students participated in workshops on oral communication and technical writing, graduate school, and bioethics, giving them life-long skills in these important areas. They also made oral presentations during research group meetings and submitted a final technical report. At the end of the program, the students presented a poster in a joint symposium with students from other summer research programs on campus.</p> <p>An external evaluation team conducted the formative and summative evaluation of the program. The assessment was carried out using three student/evaluator sessions, faculty interviews, and pretest/posttest scores. Overall, students expressed great satisfaction with the academic and social components of the program. Students were pleased with the interactions they had with faculty mentors and graduate students and with the opportunities for networking with other REU students. The students indicated that the REU experience had confirmed their career goals and helped them learn more about graduate school.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 07/30/2012<br>      Modified by: Monica&nbsp;H&nbsp;Lamm</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The BioMaP Research Experiences for Undergraduates (REU) Program was offered at Iowa State University in the summers of 2009-11. A comprehensive and content-rich website (http://www.cbe.iastate.edu/research/undergraduate-research/) was developed that described the application process, research projects, contact information for faculty and staff, and other programmatic details. This NSF project funded 11 students each summer (33 in total) and matching funds from ISU were used to fund 13 additional students, bringing the total number of students funded by the program in three years to 46. Of these students, 43% were female and 17% were underrepresented minorities. The average GPA of the BioMaP students over three years was 3.80/4.00.  The research performed by the students in the area of biological materials and processes has led to new high throughput methods for rapid screening of biomaterials, discovery of a new catalytic mechanism in glucoamylases, novel bioseparation methods for proteins, thermochemical processing methods for biomass, and new block copolymers for gene delivery. The BioMaP REU students produced seven refereed journal publications, five refereed conference proceedings, and 21 conference presentations. Several of the REU students won awards for research performed as part of the BioMaP REU.  The participants experienced a substantial research experience in a cross-disciplinary area; indeed, many students split their time in laboratories of multiple PIÆs in departments such as cell biology, immunology, physics, and chemistry. This exposed the students to the excitement and the challenges of working at interfaces between fields. The students participated in workshops on oral communication and technical writing, graduate school, and bioethics, giving them life-long skills in these important areas. They also made oral presentations during research group meetings and submitted a final technical report. At the end of the program, the students presented a poster in a joint symposium with students from other summer research programs on campus.  An external evaluation team conducted the formative and summative evaluation of the program. The assessment was carried out using three student/evaluator sessions, faculty interviews, and pretest/posttest scores. Overall, students expressed great satisfaction with the academic and social components of the program. Students were pleased with the interactions they had with faculty mentors and graduate students and with the opportunities for networking with other REU students. The students indicated that the REU experience had confirmed their career goals and helped them learn more about graduate school.       Last Modified: 07/30/2012       Submitted by: Monica H Lamm]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
