<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Towards Deep Tissue Imaging of Fluorescence Resonance Energy Transfer Parameters</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2009</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2015</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>344505.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>404505</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07020000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CBET</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Chem, Bioeng, Env, &amp; Transp Sys</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Leon Esterowitz</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>lesterow@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927942</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>0854249&lt;br/&gt;Webb&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Fluorescence resonance energy transfer (FRET) has proved to be of immense value in the study of chemical transport into cells and the underlying cause of disease due to, for example, protein misfolding (which may lead to Alzheimer's disease). The quenching of donor fluorescence by FRET transfer has been measured, and the intramolecular FRET parameters (lifetime and yield, and in the case of a flexible linker, the mean and variance of the linker distance) have been widely used. However, FRET imaging has been limited to in vitro or surface microscopy because of the deleterious effects of substantial scatter. The goal of this project is to demonstrate a method for imaging FRET parameters in highly scattering media, thereby providing the opportunity for deep tissue in vivo FRET studies. The new work planned is as follows:&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;- Development on an Approach to Image FRET Parameters with ODT: A fluorescence resonance energy transfer optical diffusion tomography (FRET-ODT) imaging approach will be developed. This will involve a solution for the intramolecular FRET parameters with both rigid and flexible linkers that are incorporated as unknown sources in a diffusion equation representation for the donor fluorescence. The sensitivity to the parameter space (modulation frequencies, source-detector arrangement, FRET parameters, signal to noise ratio) will be studied and software suitable for use with experimental data for FRET sources in a scattering medium will be developed. The merits of incorporating acceptor kinetics will also be investigated. In a similar way, intermolecular FRET sources will be implemented in an ODT framework.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;- FRET-ODT Experimental Studies: A model tissue experiment will be constructed to obtain data to evaluate the FRET-ODT imaging approach to be developed. Data allowing the influence of varying degrees of scatter, varying FRET chemical concentration, varying donor-acceptor distance and distance distribution, and multiple modulation frequencies, as well as the effect of an inhomogeneous background, will be obtained. As an in vivo FRET-ODT application, a mouse model for targeted drug delivery to cancer cells, with the subsequent drug entry and release, will be studied using a FRET model that incorporates information about the transport kinetics and which emulates the drug delivery process. Information from this study will aid in the development of targeted drugs that are selectively delivered to cancer cells, thereby preventing damage to healthy cells that usually occurs during chemotherapy (for example, leucopenia - a deficiency in white blood cells, alopecia - hair loss, constipation, and hypertension). This work will be done with the Low group in the Dept. of Chemistry at Purdue.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/17/2009</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/26/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>0854249</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Kevin</FirstName>
<LastName>Webb</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>J</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Kevin J Webb</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>webb@purdue.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>7654943373</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000449923</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/17/2009</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Purdue University</Name>
<CityName>West Lafayette</CityName>
<ZipCode>479072114</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>7654941055</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>Young Hall</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[155 S Grant Street]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Indiana</StateName>
<StateCode>IN</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>IN04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>072051394</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>PURDUE UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>072051394</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Purdue University]]></Name>
<CityName>West Lafayette</CityName>
<StateCode>IN</StateCode>
<ZipCode>479072114</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[Young Hall]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Indiana</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>IN04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<FoaInformation>
<Code>0000099</Code>
<Name>Other Applications NEC</Name>
</FoaInformation>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7236</Code>
<Text>BioP-Biophotonics</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>0000</Code>
<Text>UNASSIGNED</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>005E</Code>
<Text>Neuro-photonics</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>OTHR</Code>
<Text>OTHER RESEARCH OR EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0109</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0114</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2009~344505</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~60000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><strong>NSF 0854249: Outcomes</strong></p> <p><strong>Towards Deep Tissue Imaging of Fluorescence Resonance Energy Transfer&nbsp;</strong><strong>Parameters</strong></p> <p><strong>Kevin J. Webb, Purdue University</strong></p> <p>Photonics is revolutionizing medical research and healthcare delivery. Fluorescence (or F&ouml;rster) resonance energy transfer (FRET) is a non-radiative optical energy transfer process between donor and acceptor (DA) molecules spatially separated by a distance usually between 1-10 nanometers that can provide invaluable information for nanomedicine. Due to its strong distance dependence, intramolecular FRET can be used as a molecular ruler. Resolving the DA distance or distance distribution has been shown to be important in the study of protein folding, protein conformations, protein denaturation, and the action of molecular motors. Studying protein folding by FRET is important in understanding diseases like Alzheimer&rsquo;s disease, Parkinson&rsquo;s disease, Type-II diabetes, and some cancers, as research has shown protein misfolding to be one of their causes. However, the heavy scatter of light in tissue presented a challenge to extract FRET information. We found a means to achieve in vivo FRET imaging and developed the approach during this project. This is in principle permit in vivo molecular biology research that was not possible prior to this project.</p> <p>&nbsp;Our approach incorporated the intramolecular FRET parameters as unknown sources in a diffusion equation representation of tissue scatter with the donor fluorescence.&nbsp; The imaging method is called FRET-ODT (FRET - optical diffusion tomography). The sensitivity and accuracy of the method was investigated using tissue models. Evaluating, developing, and tuning optical imaging methods, such as ODT, requires readily available and realistic tissue-like phantoms that provide known, controlled shapes and optical parameters. There was therefore a need for anatomically realistic tissue models. A new method using 3D printing was used to fabricate reproducible heterogeneous solid phantoms in the shape of mice for optical imaging. &nbsp;We showed FRET parameters could be imaged in scattering models and in a mouse. Folate targeting can be used for targeted anti-cancer drug delivery in many human cancers, but the efficacy of the release and activation process was unknown. We imaged this kinetic process, and found the kinetic coefficients describing rate by measuring fluorescence. We were also able to image the mouse kidneys, showing the viability of optical imaging to access major organs. The experimental technique and the imaging method and software developed and demonstrated during this project will allow others to pursue applications of FRET-ODT.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 11/28/2015<br>      Modified by: Kevin&nbsp;J&nbsp;Webb</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ NSF 0854249: Outcomes  Towards Deep Tissue Imaging of Fluorescence Resonance Energy Transfer Parameters  Kevin J. Webb, Purdue University  Photonics is revolutionizing medical research and healthcare delivery. Fluorescence (or F&ouml;rster) resonance energy transfer (FRET) is a non-radiative optical energy transfer process between donor and acceptor (DA) molecules spatially separated by a distance usually between 1-10 nanometers that can provide invaluable information for nanomedicine. Due to its strong distance dependence, intramolecular FRET can be used as a molecular ruler. Resolving the DA distance or distance distribution has been shown to be important in the study of protein folding, protein conformations, protein denaturation, and the action of molecular motors. Studying protein folding by FRET is important in understanding diseases like AlzheimerÆs disease, ParkinsonÆs disease, Type-II diabetes, and some cancers, as research has shown protein misfolding to be one of their causes. However, the heavy scatter of light in tissue presented a challenge to extract FRET information. We found a means to achieve in vivo FRET imaging and developed the approach during this project. This is in principle permit in vivo molecular biology research that was not possible prior to this project.   Our approach incorporated the intramolecular FRET parameters as unknown sources in a diffusion equation representation of tissue scatter with the donor fluorescence.  The imaging method is called FRET-ODT (FRET - optical diffusion tomography). The sensitivity and accuracy of the method was investigated using tissue models. Evaluating, developing, and tuning optical imaging methods, such as ODT, requires readily available and realistic tissue-like phantoms that provide known, controlled shapes and optical parameters. There was therefore a need for anatomically realistic tissue models. A new method using 3D printing was used to fabricate reproducible heterogeneous solid phantoms in the shape of mice for optical imaging.  We showed FRET parameters could be imaged in scattering models and in a mouse. Folate targeting can be used for targeted anti-cancer drug delivery in many human cancers, but the efficacy of the release and activation process was unknown. We imaged this kinetic process, and found the kinetic coefficients describing rate by measuring fluorescence. We were also able to image the mouse kidneys, showing the viability of optical imaging to access major organs. The experimental technique and the imaging method and software developed and demonstrated during this project will allow others to pursue applications of FRET-ODT.                Last Modified: 11/28/2015       Submitted by: Kevin J Webb]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
