<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Molecules and Intense Light in a Photodynamical Test Tube</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2009</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2014</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>440000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>440000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03010000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>PHY</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Physics</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>John D. Gillaspy</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>jgillasp@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927173</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This project is an investigation of how molecules, the smallest particles of a substance, respond to very intense pulses of laser light. This is done to reveal the structure of molecules, and to understand how to actively force important molecules through processes that nature would normally not allow. The investigations will make use of a unique device, in which the number of molecules and the intensity of the light are precisely controlled. This innovative approach will allow the study of molecules in a reliable, exact, and accurate way --- beyond anything seen before in this field.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The molecules that are investigated are important building blocks of larger molecules. Such molecules are found, for instance, in the pharmaceutical industry, in biology, in environmental research, and also in outer space. On the human resources level, this project gives students in various phases of their education unique opportunities to work in a modern and professional research lab. They will work with state-of-the-art and highly specialized scientific equipment. Promoting scientific research, this gives students first hand experience which can help them decide whether a career in science or technology would be right for them.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/27/2009</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/11/2011</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>0855675</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Cornelis</FirstName>
<LastName>Uiterwaal</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>J</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Cornelis J Uiterwaal</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>cuiterwaal2@unl.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>4024729010</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000404938</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/27/2009</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</Name>
<CityName>Lincoln</CityName>
<ZipCode>685031435</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>4024723171</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>151 Prem S. Paul Research Center</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[2200 Vine St]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Nebraska</StateName>
<StateCode>NE</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NE01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>555456995</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>BOARD OF REGENTS OF THE UNIVERSITY OF NEBRASKA</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>068662618</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Nebraska-Lincoln]]></Name>
<CityName>Lincoln</CityName>
<StateCode>NE</StateCode>
<ZipCode>685031435</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[151 Prem S. Paul Research Center]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Nebraska</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NE01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<FoaInformation>
<Code>0000099</Code>
<Name>Other Applications NEC</Name>
</FoaInformation>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1291</Code>
<Text>ATOMIC &amp; MOLECULAR DYNAMICS</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>0000</Code>
<Text>UNASSIGNED</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>OTHR</Code>
<Text>OTHER RESEARCH OR EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0109</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0110</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0111</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2009~190000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2010~125000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2011~125000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Molecules are the smallest entities of a chemical substance. They are extremely small: about one thousandth of one millionth of a foot. The details of their structure completely determine the unique properties of each chemical substance. Molecules are made of atomic nuclei surrounded by electrons. The nuclei and the electrons attract each other through electric forces, the same forces that allow a rubbed rubber balloon to stick to a wall. In a molecule these electric binding forces are tremendously strong, and this gives molecules their stability. In the research project "Molecules and Intense Light in a Photodynamical Test Tube" we have investigated the structure of a variety of molecules. We did this by exposing molecules to&nbsp;very bright ("intense") light, about 100 million million times brighter than sunlight. We created this bright light by focusing very&nbsp;short pulses of laser light on the molecules. The extreme brightness is needed to give the light the power to stretch and squeeze the molecules, and they may then release one or more electrons, becoming what is called "ions". In fact, we can make the light so strong that it overcomes the electric forces that keep the molecule together, so that we may even "crack open" the molecules, causing them to break apart into fragments. After we applied the pulse we analyzed the ions and the fragments that were created. From this, we try to deduce the structure of the molecule.</p> <p>We can take this story one step further. When we expose molecules to our very short laser pulses, we make them do things they wouldn't normally do. For instance, when the pulses are short enough we may "take the molecule by surprise" and inhibit their fragmentation by not giving them the time needed to do so. They will then release an electron instead. This aspect of our work is related to&nbsp;the laser control of chemical reactions.&nbsp;</p> <p>We have investigated series of similar molecules, which only differ in one particular aspect. To give an example: One series we investigated are the four so-called "halobenzenes". The common&nbsp;core of these four molecules is a ring of six carbon atoms. They only differ in what kind of atom is attached to that ring. This could be either a fluorine atom, a chlorine atom, a bromine atom, or an iodine atom. These atoms are all closely related.</p> <p>We then investigated how they interacted with the bright light, and we did find different behavior when we compared the results. Some of them readily fell apart, while others were more robust, emitting just a few electrons instead.&nbsp;These different behaviors must be related to the different atoms&nbsp;attached to the molecular ring. Indeed, based on this experimental evidence we have been able to understand the effect of this one atom on the molecule as a whole.</p> <p>The laboratory in which the research took place has also served as an important training site. We created many learning opportunities for high school students and undergraduate students. All of them had direct, hands-on experience in our well-equipped, modern&nbsp;research lab. They have operated&nbsp;our&nbsp;state-of-the-art laser system, worked with vacuum equipment,&nbsp;handled&nbsp;the chemicals for our molecular targets. They have also worked with the computer control and automization of our equipment, and they have done data analysis and simulations using advanced software packages. In the summers of 2010, 2011, and 2012 four undergraduate students participated in our research who were funded by the NSF REU summer school "Research Experience for Undergraduates: Lasers and Optics".</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 07/08/2015<br>      Modified by: Cornelis&nbsp;J&nbsp;Uiterwaal</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Molecules are the smallest entities of a chemical substance. They are extremely small: about one thousandth of one millionth of a foot. The details of their structure completely determine the unique properties of each chemical substance. Molecules are made of atomic nuclei surrounded by electrons. The nuclei and the electrons attract each other through electric forces, the same forces that allow a rubbed rubber balloon to stick to a wall. In a molecule these electric binding forces are tremendously strong, and this gives molecules their stability. In the research project "Molecules and Intense Light in a Photodynamical Test Tube" we have investigated the structure of a variety of molecules. We did this by exposing molecules to very bright ("intense") light, about 100 million million times brighter than sunlight. We created this bright light by focusing very short pulses of laser light on the molecules. The extreme brightness is needed to give the light the power to stretch and squeeze the molecules, and they may then release one or more electrons, becoming what is called "ions". In fact, we can make the light so strong that it overcomes the electric forces that keep the molecule together, so that we may even "crack open" the molecules, causing them to break apart into fragments. After we applied the pulse we analyzed the ions and the fragments that were created. From this, we try to deduce the structure of the molecule.  We can take this story one step further. When we expose molecules to our very short laser pulses, we make them do things they wouldn't normally do. For instance, when the pulses are short enough we may "take the molecule by surprise" and inhibit their fragmentation by not giving them the time needed to do so. They will then release an electron instead. This aspect of our work is related to the laser control of chemical reactions.   We have investigated series of similar molecules, which only differ in one particular aspect. To give an example: One series we investigated are the four so-called "halobenzenes". The common core of these four molecules is a ring of six carbon atoms. They only differ in what kind of atom is attached to that ring. This could be either a fluorine atom, a chlorine atom, a bromine atom, or an iodine atom. These atoms are all closely related.  We then investigated how they interacted with the bright light, and we did find different behavior when we compared the results. Some of them readily fell apart, while others were more robust, emitting just a few electrons instead. These different behaviors must be related to the different atoms attached to the molecular ring. Indeed, based on this experimental evidence we have been able to understand the effect of this one atom on the molecule as a whole.  The laboratory in which the research took place has also served as an important training site. We created many learning opportunities for high school students and undergraduate students. All of them had direct, hands-on experience in our well-equipped, modern research lab. They have operated our state-of-the-art laser system, worked with vacuum equipment, handled the chemicals for our molecular targets. They have also worked with the computer control and automization of our equipment, and they have done data analysis and simulations using advanced software packages. In the summers of 2010, 2011, and 2012 four undergraduate students participated in our research who were funded by the NSF REU summer school "Research Experience for Undergraduates: Lasers and Optics".       Last Modified: 07/08/2015       Submitted by: Cornelis J Uiterwaal]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
