<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Urban Science, Technology, Engineering, and Mathematics Talent Expansion Program</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2009</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2015</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>1200000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>1200000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>11040200</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>EHR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DUE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Undergraduate Education</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Connie Della-Piana</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>cdellapi@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032925309</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This partnership encompasses three large urban commuting schools, two community colleges (City Colleges of Chicago Kennedy-King College and Olive-Harvey College) and the Chicago State University (CSU).  It is fostering an increase in the number of students persisting in science, technology, engineering and mathematics (STEM) courses and majors by focusing directly on the quality of student learning and engaging students in research projects early in their academic careers. The program: 1. enables students at community colleges to matriculate directly into the CSU baccalaureate STEM programs; 2. gives students support through programs that include facilitated learning, on-line tutoring, career counseling, seminars, development workshops, and faculty and peer mentoring programs; 3. puts early emphasis on developing student skills in mathematics and writing; and 4. uses CSU's local prairie garden for ecological and environmental field research as a base to expand opportunities for student research opportunities early in their undergraduate years. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Intellectual Merit:  Contributing to the intellectual merit of this project are: the strong emphasis on academic excellence through strengthening student skills in mathematics and writing; affording early research experiences on something that students can see is a part of their world; and the close attention to support through cohort class participation, faculty and peer workshops, group study, seminars, and hands-on instruction in mathematics and science. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Broader impacts: These institutions have long successful records of increasing diversity throughout their academic programs and have worked diligently with the public schools, community colleges and public institutions to do so.  The goals are to increase undergraduate research by 20% and transfer rates from community college to baccalaureate institutions by 25%. The results of the program are being widely disseminated.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/02/2009</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/15/2012</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.076</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>0856827</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Rachel</FirstName>
<LastName>Lindsey</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>W</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Rachel W Lindsey</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>rw-lindsey@csu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>7739952105</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000316055</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/02/2009</StartDate>
<EndDate>08/19/2011</EndDate>
<RoleCode>Former Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>LeRoy</FirstName>
<LastName>Jones II</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>LeRoy Jones II</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>ljones27@csu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>7739953296</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000314242</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/15/2012</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>LeRoy</FirstName>
<LastName>Jones II</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>LeRoy Jones II</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>ljones27@csu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>7739953296</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000314242</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/02/2009</StartDate>
<EndDate>08/19/2011</EndDate>
<RoleCode>Former Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Chicago State University</Name>
<CityName>Chicago</CityName>
<ZipCode>606281598</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>7739952400</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>9501 South King Drive</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Illinois</StateName>
<StateCode>IL</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>IL01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>108109182</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>CHICAGO STATE UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>108109182</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Chicago State University]]></Name>
<CityName>Chicago</CityName>
<StateCode>IL</StateCode>
<ZipCode>606281598</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[9501 South King Drive]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Illinois</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>IL01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<FoaInformation>
<Code>0116000</Code>
<Name>Human Subjects</Name>
</FoaInformation>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1796</Code>
<Text>STEP-STEM Talent Expansn Pgm</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9178</Code>
<Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>SMET</Code>
<Text>SCIENCE, MATH, ENG &amp; TECH EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0409</Code>
<Name>NSF Education &amp; Human Resource</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040106</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0412</Code>
<Name>NSF Education &amp; Human Resource</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040106</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2009~960000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2012~240000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The Urban STEM Talent Expansion Program (USTEP) was a collaborative effort between Chicago State University (CSU), Kennedy-King College (KKC) and Olive-Harvey College (OHC) to significantly increase the number of first and second year CSU and CCC college students who enter, pursue and graduate from science, technology, engineering and mathematics (STEM) programs.&nbsp; In order to achieve this vision, CSU, OHC and KKC implemented a student-centered academic support and research program to enhance undergraduate education and training at the intersection of the biological, physical sciences and mathematics for the purpose to prepare students to graduate, attend graduate study or careers in traditional and emerging fields that integrate the sciences. &nbsp;USTEP aimed to broaden undergraduate research capacity and experiences by utilizing CSU&rsquo;s local prairie garden for ecological and environmental field research, data collection, and material for laboratory experiments.</p> <p>The USTEP implemented five major research and education activities in support of the goals mentioned above.&nbsp; They included:</p> <p>1)&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; Mentoring - the USTEP project was designed to mentor motivated bright students in the philosophy, theories and technical aspects of STEM disciplines.&nbsp; USTEP mentors helped student participants discuss their academic needs; explore career options; and encourage participants to maintain high personal standards of effort as they develop academically in their STEM majors;</p> <p>2)&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; Research Experiences - USTEP mentors helped student participants prepare research projects in environmental and ecological research. &nbsp;This research helped to ground them in the STEM discipline, taught them valuable skills and techniques needed to conduct innovative research, and provided impressive experience for their resumes;</p> <p>3)&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; Workshops - specially designed study skills classes for STEM disciplines were offered to USTEP students throughout the academic year. &nbsp;Topics ranged from note-taking and test-taking skills in STEM courses to studying STEM problems and understanding STEM concepts;</p> <p>4)&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; Career Exploration - vocational information in the form of orientation workshops; seminars with STEM professionals; and regular programs established by university Career Placement Services (CPS) was provided for USTEP students. &nbsp;CPS also explored the students&rsquo; aptitude and interest in their majors, discussed academic requirements for certain fields, and informed students about internships and externships in the STEM disciplines; and</p> <p>5)&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; Research Conferences - USTEP students participated and presented at annual conferences and symposiums sponsored by discipline-specific STEM organizations.&nbsp; These conferences provided USTEP students with exposure to research and internships. &nbsp;It also provided them with the opportunity to make professional presentations and develop personal networking skills. &nbsp;Furthermore, it provided a venue for USTEP project participants to disseminate their research findings to the STEM community.</p> <p>During the life of the award, the following key outcomes were achieved:</p> <p>1)&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; Over 50% of the CCC USTEP students transferred to a four-year baccalaureate institution;</p> <p>2)&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; 100% of USTEP participants engaged in environmental and ecological research in CSU's Prairie Garden, and presented their research findings at local, state, national and/or international research conferences;</p> <p>3)&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; The Prairie Garden at CSU is now seen as a legitimate entity for research and teaching as evidenced by faculty expressing the desire to write proposals to broaden the use of the prairie g...]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The Urban STEM Talent Expansion Program (USTEP) was a collaborative effort between Chicago State University (CSU), Kennedy-King College (KKC) and Olive-Harvey College (OHC) to significantly increase the number of first and second year CSU and CCC college students who enter, pursue and graduate from science, technology, engineering and mathematics (STEM) programs.  In order to achieve this vision, CSU, OHC and KKC implemented a student-centered academic support and research program to enhance undergraduate education and training at the intersection of the biological, physical sciences and mathematics for the purpose to prepare students to graduate, attend graduate study or careers in traditional and emerging fields that integrate the sciences.  USTEP aimed to broaden undergraduate research capacity and experiences by utilizing CSUÆs local prairie garden for ecological and environmental field research, data collection, and material for laboratory experiments.  The USTEP implemented five major research and education activities in support of the goals mentioned above.  They included:  1)      Mentoring - the USTEP project was designed to mentor motivated bright students in the philosophy, theories and technical aspects of STEM disciplines.  USTEP mentors helped student participants discuss their academic needs; explore career options; and encourage participants to maintain high personal standards of effort as they develop academically in their STEM majors;  2)      Research Experiences - USTEP mentors helped student participants prepare research projects in environmental and ecological research.  This research helped to ground them in the STEM discipline, taught them valuable skills and techniques needed to conduct innovative research, and provided impressive experience for their resumes;  3)      Workshops - specially designed study skills classes for STEM disciplines were offered to USTEP students throughout the academic year.  Topics ranged from note-taking and test-taking skills in STEM courses to studying STEM problems and understanding STEM concepts;  4)      Career Exploration - vocational information in the form of orientation workshops; seminars with STEM professionals; and regular programs established by university Career Placement Services (CPS) was provided for USTEP students.  CPS also explored the studentsÆ aptitude and interest in their majors, discussed academic requirements for certain fields, and informed students about internships and externships in the STEM disciplines; and  5)      Research Conferences - USTEP students participated and presented at annual conferences and symposiums sponsored by discipline-specific STEM organizations.  These conferences provided USTEP students with exposure to research and internships.  It also provided them with the opportunity to make professional presentations and develop personal networking skills.  Furthermore, it provided a venue for USTEP project participants to disseminate their research findings to the STEM community.  During the life of the award, the following key outcomes were achieved:  1)      Over 50% of the CCC USTEP students transferred to a four-year baccalaureate institution;  2)      100% of USTEP participants engaged in environmental and ecological research in CSU's Prairie Garden, and presented their research findings at local, state, national and/or international research conferences;  3)      The Prairie Garden at CSU is now seen as a legitimate entity for research and teaching as evidenced by faculty expressing the desire to write proposals to broaden the use of the prairie garden;  4)      Community partnerships were established with the Museum of Natural History, City of Chicago Department of the Environment, The Art Institute, Purdue University, the Morton Arboretum, Kansas State University SU Agronomy Soil Testing Laboratory, the South East Environmental Taskforce, 'Trees R Beautiful' organization, Indiana Dunes National Park, Eden's Place, Chicago...]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
