<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Retention through Remediation : Enhancing Calculus I Success</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/15/2009</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>10/31/2016</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>1978337.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>1591508</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>11040200</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>EHR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DUE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Undergraduate Education</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>John Haddock</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>jhaddock@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922671</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>"Retention through Remediation: Enhancing Calculus I Success" is a Type 1-B STEP project.  Building on the success of a previous STEP 1-A award, this project is working in the new direction of improving students' mathematical background as a means of retaining STEM majors.  This bridge-type program is using a series of technology-based strategies for identifying new STEM students with weak pre-calculus/algebraic skills and providing them with a Personalized Study Program to strengthen their pre-calculus skills and position them for success in college mathematics.  The approach begins with using the results from a Calculus Readiness Assessment tool, which was developed during their STEP 1-A project, to determine which incoming students are mathematically at risk.  Then they follow-up with these students by a variety of technology-mediation methods including direct synchronous contact with an experienced instructor via conferencing software; videos of important pre-calculus topics; Applets to add interactivity, depth of understanding, and improve visualization of the concepts; and an online text, assessment, and homework delivered through an online course management system.  This program is taken during the summer prior to their first semester of college.  In the following fall semester, these students participate in the "Just-in-Time" program, which reinforces algebraic concepts, as they are needed in the Calculus I course.  The broader impact of this project includes their development of an effective, cost-efficient remediation program in pre-calculus available to large numbers of students who need it, prior to taking Calculus I, which is a  STEM-gateway course.  Their evaluation design is providing new knowledge about technology-based remediation of algebraically weak students during that summer prior to entering college and again in the first fall experience.  This project team is disseminating their strategy and set of software tools for successfully addressing the issue of attrition due to failure in first-year calculus, which is a widespread issue that impacts STEM graduation rates in institutions across the country.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project is impacting at least 600 of the incoming 3,100 STEM students in both the summer and fall interventions.  They are increasing their STEM graduation rates by at least 100 additional STEM graduates annually.  The project's External Advisory Board is providing expertise on how the project materials work within the context of other campuses, which is helping with the dissemination of project learning resources.  Presentations and publications are being developed to share this project's successes.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/07/2009</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/09/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.076</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>0856767</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>G.</FirstName>
<LastName>Allen</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>D</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>G. D Allen</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>dallen@math.tamu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>9798457950</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000334199</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/07/2009</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Donald</FirstName>
<LastName>Maxwell</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>A</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Donald A Maxwell</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>dmaxwell@civil.tamu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>9798457923</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000370232</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/07/2009</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Michael</FirstName>
<LastName>Pilant</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>S</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Michael S Pilant</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>mpilant@math.tamu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>9798455631</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000204996</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/07/2009</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Jeffrey</FirstName>
<LastName>Froyd</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>E</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Jeffrey E Froyd</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>froyd.1@osu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>9797774764</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000287199</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/07/2009</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Sandra</FirstName>
<LastName>Nite</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Sandra Nite</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>s-nite@tamu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>9798459503</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000513929</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/07/2009</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Texas A&amp;M Research Foundation</Name>
<CityName>College Station</CityName>
<ZipCode>778454375</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>9798626777</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>400 Harvey Mitchell Parkway, S</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[Suite 300]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Texas</StateName>
<StateCode>TX</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>17</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>TX17</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>078592789</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>TEXAS A &amp; M RESEARCH FOUNDATION</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>078592789</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Texas A&amp;M University]]></Name>
<CityName>College Station</CityName>
<StateCode>TX</StateCode>
<ZipCode>778454375</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[400 Harvey Mitchell Pkwy South]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Texas</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>17</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>TX17</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<FoaInformation>
<Code>0116000</Code>
<Name>Human Subjects</Name>
</FoaInformation>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1796</Code>
<Text>STEP-STEM Talent Expansn Pgm</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9178</Code>
<Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>SMET</Code>
<Text>SCIENCE, MATH, ENG &amp; TECH EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0409</Code>
<Name>NSF Education &amp; Human Resource</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040106</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0412</Code>
<Name>NSF Education &amp; Human Resource</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040106</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2009~1148887</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2012~442621</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The project has attempted an intervention for precollege students entering in the fall, but having relatively weak scores on their math placement examination (MPE).&nbsp; It is basically a crash course on pre-calculus topics, those specifically they did poorly on.&nbsp; These are precisely the topics that students have the most trouble with in Calculus I (engineering, math, physics, chemistry version). &nbsp;Each summer, we admitted about 200 students to this program, the personalized pre-calculus program, PPP. &nbsp;These students were platooned into groups of size up to 20, delivered for about three weeks at staggered intervals throughout the summer. &nbsp;Each session was conducted online by a live instructor, with total of about thirty contact hours.&nbsp; We prepared extensive videos, text materials, and online quizzes for the respective sessions, all prepared by experts at calculus teaching. These are currently available online for all to use without charge.&nbsp; Regarding the PPP sessions, students have told us overwhelmingly it was the live session that was the most helpful.&nbsp; In this context, a key point of our program was to select instructors with acknowledged excellence at both teaching and student relationships.&nbsp; The outcomes of our program numerous. Basically, students originally falling short in the MPE exam performed comparably with students meeting the MPE requirements as per their retake of this placement exam.</p> <p>In the third year of the grant, noting recruitment to the PPP program was the most difficult problem we faced, we enhanced our recruiting efforts &ndash; the true key for such programs.&nbsp; In addition, we created a bridging program. It was designed for students having completed Calculus I but with relatively low grades, i.e. C and B.&nbsp; This program was conducted for students entering Calculus II and was conducted in smallish sections the week prior to. &nbsp;As with the PPP, each session was conducted online with a skilled tutor.&nbsp; Ten total contact hours&nbsp; were required.&nbsp; We noted great completion (80%) of the program, and moreover students performed better than expected (statistically) that those not taking the bridging program. Normally more than 100 students enrolled.&nbsp; It seems that the low grade awakened many students to their need for some help going forward. &nbsp;This program was later extended to a bridge between Calculus II and Calculus III.&nbsp; This program has also been successful. &nbsp;&nbsp;Finally, for those students scoring very low on the MPE and simply agreeing to take pre-calculus in their first term, a pre-calculus bridging program, extensive in nature, for these students to take in their summer before matriculation.&nbsp;&nbsp; This program garners more than one-hundred students.&nbsp;</p> <p>The College of Engineering and other STEM departments are both delighted grateful for these interventions as they help increase STEM-student retention, a significant directive within the University, overall. &nbsp;The motto of the program is basically that it is far more productive to retain a STEM student than find a new one.</p> <p>As well, member of the project team(s) have disseminated all these outcomes and programs, have published numerous papers and given numerous presentations over the past six years.&nbsp; The programs as well have been imitated, the materials used, and the ideas of bridging have been duplicated nationwide.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 02/13/2017<br>      Modified by: G.&nbsp;D&nbsp;Allen</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The project has attempted an intervention for precollege students entering in the fall, but having relatively weak scores on their math placement examination (MPE).  It is basically a crash course on pre-calculus topics, those specifically they did poorly on.  These are precisely the topics that students have the most trouble with in Calculus I (engineering, math, physics, chemistry version).  Each summer, we admitted about 200 students to this program, the personalized pre-calculus program, PPP.  These students were platooned into groups of size up to 20, delivered for about three weeks at staggered intervals throughout the summer.  Each session was conducted online by a live instructor, with total of about thirty contact hours.  We prepared extensive videos, text materials, and online quizzes for the respective sessions, all prepared by experts at calculus teaching. These are currently available online for all to use without charge.  Regarding the PPP sessions, students have told us overwhelmingly it was the live session that was the most helpful.  In this context, a key point of our program was to select instructors with acknowledged excellence at both teaching and student relationships.  The outcomes of our program numerous. Basically, students originally falling short in the MPE exam performed comparably with students meeting the MPE requirements as per their retake of this placement exam.  In the third year of the grant, noting recruitment to the PPP program was the most difficult problem we faced, we enhanced our recruiting efforts &ndash; the true key for such programs.  In addition, we created a bridging program. It was designed for students having completed Calculus I but with relatively low grades, i.e. C and B.  This program was conducted for students entering Calculus II and was conducted in smallish sections the week prior to.  As with the PPP, each session was conducted online with a skilled tutor.  Ten total contact hours  were required.  We noted great completion (80%) of the program, and moreover students performed better than expected (statistically) that those not taking the bridging program. Normally more than 100 students enrolled.  It seems that the low grade awakened many students to their need for some help going forward.  This program was later extended to a bridge between Calculus II and Calculus III.  This program has also been successful.   Finally, for those students scoring very low on the MPE and simply agreeing to take pre-calculus in their first term, a pre-calculus bridging program, extensive in nature, for these students to take in their summer before matriculation.   This program garners more than one-hundred students.   The College of Engineering and other STEM departments are both delighted grateful for these interventions as they help increase STEM-student retention, a significant directive within the University, overall.  The motto of the program is basically that it is far more productive to retain a STEM student than find a new one.  As well, member of the project team(s) have disseminated all these outcomes and programs, have published numerous papers and given numerous presentations over the past six years.  The programs as well have been imitated, the materials used, and the ideas of bridging have been duplicated nationwide.       Last Modified: 02/13/2017       Submitted by: G. D Allen]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
