<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Multigraded Commutative Algebra</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/15/2005</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2009</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>100000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>100000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DMS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Tomek Bartoszynski</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This award supports the research of Maclagan to develop multigraded&lt;br/&gt;analogues of several fundamental properties of graded polynomial&lt;br/&gt;rings.  This is motivated by the many naturally multigraded objects&lt;br/&gt;arising in commutative algebra.  An important example is the Cox&lt;br/&gt;homogeneous coordinate ring of a simplicial toric variety, which&lt;br/&gt;allows algebro-geometric questions about sheaves on the toric variety&lt;br/&gt;to be studied using commutative algebra techniques.  Applications&lt;br/&gt;outside commutative algebra of Maclagan's research include those to&lt;br/&gt;algebraic geometry (explicit construction of multigraded Hilbert&lt;br/&gt;schemes, and projective normality of smooth toric varieties) and&lt;br/&gt;combinatorics (properties of matroids).  One of her projects allows&lt;br/&gt;concrete calculations of moduli spaces arising in the study of the&lt;br/&gt;McKay correspondence, which has been an active area of research for&lt;br/&gt;the last two decades.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This research lies in the intersection of commutative algebra and&lt;br/&gt;computational and combinatorial algebraic geometry, in the area of&lt;br/&gt;toric geometry.  The most classical version of these fields studies the&lt;br/&gt;geometry of solutions to polynomial equations in several variables.&lt;br/&gt;Such questions have been studied for hundreds of years, but continue&lt;br/&gt;to arise in applications such as robotics, statistics, and coding&lt;br/&gt;theory.  The particular aspects to be studied here have applications&lt;br/&gt;in optimization (integer programming through toric ideals) and&lt;br/&gt;theoretical physics (through the McKay correspondence).&lt;br/&gt;</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/12/2005</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/12/2005</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>0500386</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Diane</FirstName>
<LastName>Maclagan</LastName>
<EmailAddress>maclagan@math.rutgers.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>08/12/2005</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Rutgers University New Brunswick</Name>
<CityName>Piscataway</CityName>
<ZipCode>088543925</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>8489320150</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>33 Knightsbridge Road</StreetAddress>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New Jersey</StateName>
<StateCode>NJ</StateCode>
</Institution>
<FoaInformation>
<Code>0000099</Code>
<Name>Other Applications NEC</Name>
</FoaInformation>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1264</Code>
<Text>ALGEBRA,NUMBER THEORY,AND COM</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>0000</Code>
<Text>UNASSIGNED</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>OTHR</Code>
<Text>OTHER RESEARCH OR EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
</Award>
</rootTag>
