<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Research in Model Theory</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2005</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2011</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>0.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>226987</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DMS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Tomek Bartoszynski</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Baldwin proposes work on three topics in model theory: abstract&lt;br/&gt;elementary classes, generic expansions of fields, and the&lt;br/&gt;preservation of stability under expansion by naming predicates.&lt;br/&gt;The last two are in some sense dual.  The twenty year old search&lt;br/&gt;for a bad-field tries to construct a sufficiently generic subgroup&lt;br/&gt;of the complex numbers that omega stability is preserved.  Both&lt;br/&gt;refined model theoretic and algebraic tools are essential.  In the&lt;br/&gt;other direction Baldwin is exploring with Baizhanov, the most&lt;br/&gt;general conditions under which can hope to preserve stability when&lt;br/&gt;a subset is named.  Baldwin has been writing a monograph&lt;br/&gt;summarizing the current state of `Morley's theorem' for Abstract&lt;br/&gt;Elementary Classes.  This monograph, tries to clarify and organize&lt;br/&gt;the general work in this topic, underline the connections with&lt;br/&gt;both Zilber's work on complex geometry and the `Hrushovski&lt;br/&gt;construction, and lay the foundation for a more general stability&lt;br/&gt;theory in this context.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The general perspective of logic in understanding the foundations&lt;br/&gt;of various mathematical topics has provided in Baldwin's work&lt;br/&gt;links among fields as diverse as database theory (computer&lt;br/&gt;science), random graphs, abstract algebra and complex analysis. In&lt;br/&gt;many cases the role of logic is place limits on what can be proved&lt;br/&gt;and direct research into more productive endeavors.  Baldwin has&lt;br/&gt;served as a link between the logic and mathematics education&lt;br/&gt;communities for the last fifteen years.  He is currently director&lt;br/&gt;of the Office of Mathematics Education at UIC.  He aims to provide&lt;br/&gt;future teachers with a profound understanding of fundamental&lt;br/&gt;secondary school mathematics. A teacher with profound&lt;br/&gt;understanding of school mathematics is not only aware of the&lt;br/&gt;conceptual structure of secondary mathematics, but also&lt;br/&gt;understands the common strategies that students use to solve&lt;br/&gt;problems along with common student misconceptions.  A background&lt;br/&gt;in logic is invaluable in helping future teachers develop the&lt;br/&gt;ability to communicate mathematics clearly.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/27/2005</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/01/2010</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>0500841</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>John</FirstName>
<LastName>Baldwin</LastName>
<EmailAddress>jbaldwin@uic.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>06/27/2005</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Illinois at Chicago</Name>
<CityName>Chicago</CityName>
<ZipCode>606124305</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>3129962862</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>809 S. Marshfield Avenue</StreetAddress>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Illinois</StateName>
<StateCode>IL</StateCode>
</Institution>
<FoaInformation>
<Code>0000099</Code>
<Name>Other Applications NEC</Name>
</FoaInformation>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1268</Code>
<Text>FOUNDATIONS</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>0000</Code>
<Text>UNASSIGNED</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>OTHR</Code>
<Text>OTHER RESEARCH OR EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
</Award>
</rootTag>
