<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Study of Random Motion in Random Environment, and Random Matrix Theory</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2005</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2009</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>166001.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>166001</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03040200</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DMS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Tomek Bartoszynski</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>tbartosz@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924885</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This proposal deals with the long term behavior of RWRE (random walks in &lt;br/&gt;random environments). More precisely, one looks at random walks on the &lt;br/&gt;d-dimensional lattice, whose transition probabilities form a random field &lt;br/&gt;indexed by the vertices of the lattice. Not only is the RWRE providing a &lt;br/&gt;serious mathematical challenge, many of the results proved in this field, &lt;br/&gt;especially in the one dimensional case, stand in sharp contrast with the &lt;br/&gt;behavior of classical random walk. For example, in dimension 1, &lt;br/&gt;subdiffusive behavior and aging phenomena are present, whereas in high &lt;br/&gt;dimension one may construct RWRE's with nonzero (averaged) local drift &lt;br/&gt;pointing in one direction while the walk drifts away (with positive speed) &lt;br/&gt;in the opposite direction. Some of the mathematical challenge emanates &lt;br/&gt;from the fact that in the multidimensional case, conditioned on the &lt;br/&gt;transition probabilities random field, the RWRE is not reversible. This &lt;br/&gt;precludes the use of much of the available theory of homogenization, and &lt;br/&gt;requires the development of new techniques, most notably through the use &lt;br/&gt;of regeneration times and of renormalization ideas. In spite of rapid &lt;br/&gt;progress that was achieved in the last few years by several researchers &lt;br/&gt;including Bolthausen, Sznitman, Varadhan, Zerner, and the PI, many &lt;br/&gt;fundamental questions remain unanswered. Among these one notes the &lt;br/&gt;existence of 0-1 laws, laws of large numbers in full generality, &lt;br/&gt;transience and recurrence criteria, the relation between quenched and &lt;br/&gt;annealed large deviations behavior, the existence (or non-existence) of &lt;br/&gt;sub-diffusive behavior for high dimension, and the behavior of RWRE's in &lt;br/&gt;mixing (as opposed to i.i.d.) environments.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Random walks are arguably the stochastic processes most studied by &lt;br/&gt;mathematicians, having the widest range of applications in fields as &lt;br/&gt;diverse as the physical sciences, engineering, and the social sciences. &lt;br/&gt;Though the theory of random walks is by now well developed, this is not at &lt;br/&gt;all the case when one changes the medium in which the walk evolves to a &lt;br/&gt;random medium, thus obtaining a random walk in random environment (RWRE). &lt;br/&gt;Such RWRE's can be used to model many problems of motion in random media &lt;br/&gt;in the physical and engineering sciences, and are mathematically appealing &lt;br/&gt;because on the one hand the model is very simply stated, while on the &lt;br/&gt;other hand established tools for studying processes in random media are &lt;br/&gt;not applicable in the study of RWRE. The goal of the current proposal is &lt;br/&gt;to develop new basic probabilistic techniques that will allow to make &lt;br/&gt;provable predictions concerning the behavior of RWRE. It is expected that &lt;br/&gt;such techniques will be useful in the study of other processes, and link &lt;br/&gt;naturally to the study of trapping models and reinforced random walks. &lt;br/&gt;While not explicitly targeted in this proposal, trapping models have &lt;br/&gt;recently been used to study the environmental impact of nuclear waste, and &lt;br/&gt;RWRE's can naturally be used in this context to model the spread of &lt;br/&gt;contamination in a real environment, once the required mathematical &lt;br/&gt;background and tools are in place.&lt;br/&gt;</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/21/2005</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>04/06/2007</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>0503775</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Ofer</FirstName>
<LastName>Zeitouni</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Ofer Zeitouni</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>zeitouni@math.umn.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6126256522</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000110448</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/21/2005</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Minnesota-Twin Cities</Name>
<CityName>Minneapolis</CityName>
<CountyName>HENNEPIN</CountyName>
<ZipCode>554552070</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6126245599</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>200 OAK ST SE</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Minnesota</StateName>
<StateCode>MN</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MN05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>555917996</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>REGENTS OF THE UNIVERSITY OF MINNESOTA</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>117178941</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Minnesota-Twin Cities]]></Name>
<CityName>Minneapolis</CityName>
<CountyName>HENNEPIN</CountyName>
<StateCode>MN</StateCode>
<ZipCode>554552070</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[200 OAK ST SE]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Minnesota</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MN05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<FoaInformation>
<Code>0000099</Code>
<Name>Other Applications NEC</Name>
</FoaInformation>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1263</Code>
<Text>PROBABILITY</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>0000</Code>
<Text>UNASSIGNED</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>OTHR</Code>
<Text>OTHER RESEARCH OR EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0105</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>490100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0106</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>490100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0107</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>490100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2005~53960</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2006~55396</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2007~56645</FUND_OBLG>
</Award>
</rootTag>
