<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Novel Polymer Microgel Dispersions with an Inverse Thermoreversible Gelation</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>06/01/2005</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2009</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>0.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>300000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03070012</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DMR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Materials Research</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Andrew Lovinger</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The objective of this proposed project is to create dispersions of polymer microgels with &lt;br/&gt;an inverse thermo-reversible gelation.  They will be liquids at room temperature but become &lt;br/&gt;solids at an elevated temperature.  The central idea is to design and synthesize polymer microgels &lt;br/&gt;with environmentally responsive hydrophobic or hydrogen bonding that are sufficient to hold the &lt;br/&gt;microgel assembly together but not too strong to cause  flocculation.   In contrast to physically &lt;br/&gt;crosslinked gels such as gelatin, the building blocks of proposed dispersions are colloidal &lt;br/&gt;microgels.  With a temperature tunable interparticle potential, these microgels can self-assemble &lt;br/&gt;into various mesoscopic structures.  This proposed project consists of five aims. The first is to &lt;br/&gt;synthesize  microgels  with  two  interpenetrating  polymer  networks  (IPN).    One  network  is &lt;br/&gt;responsive to a temperature change and the other is not.  The balance between these two &lt;br/&gt;networks  provides  a  suitable  interparticle  potential,  resulting  in  an  inverse  thermoreversible &lt;br/&gt;gelation. The second is  to design and synthesize biodegradable  IPN microgels for the use in &lt;br/&gt;thermally  gelling  dispersions.  The  concept  of  thermally  gelling  microgel  dispersions  will  be &lt;br/&gt;extended  to  include  microgels  with  core-shell  structures  (Aim  3)  and  to  a  mixture  of  two &lt;br/&gt;different microgels  with hydrogen bonding (Aim 4).  The last  aim is to use the  IPN microgel &lt;br/&gt;dispersion as a model system to experimentally study dynamics of melting, the jamming phase &lt;br/&gt;diagram, and the interparticle forces.                                                                                                                    &lt;br/&gt;Intellectual merit: This proposed project is innovative because its designs combine the &lt;br/&gt;balances between different polymers, different structures and different inter-particle interactions. &lt;br/&gt;The polymer microgel synthesis will be correlated with accurate characterizations by UV-visible &lt;br/&gt;spectroscopy, static and  dynamic light scattering and rhelogical methods.  If successful, it  will &lt;br/&gt;lead to a new class of polymer microgel dispersions with an inverse thermoreversible gelation.  &lt;br/&gt;In contrast to all known dispersions including hard spheres or atomic systems, the  newly &lt;br/&gt;designed microgel dispersion with a single polymer concentration can change from a liquid to a &lt;br/&gt;gel by increasing temperature, or to a  crystal or to a  glass by  decreasing temperature.   This &lt;br/&gt;microgel dispersion can provide a model system to study the fundamental problems in melting &lt;br/&gt;and jamming processes that have not been fully explored due to limitations of current available &lt;br/&gt;colloidal systems. The proposed project will open an avenue to the development of injectable &lt;br/&gt;drug delivery liquids by  synthesizing biodegradable microgels as building blocks in the &lt;br/&gt;dispersions.                                                                                                                                                               &lt;br/&gt;Broader impacts:  The basic sciences established in this research will have impacts not &lt;br/&gt;only in polymer sciences but also in biomedical applications.  This program will integrate its &lt;br/&gt;undergraduate educational efforts with two existing programs that promote research experiences: &lt;br/&gt;the Texas Academy of Mathematics and Science (TAMS) and the Ronald F. McNair Post-&lt;br/&gt;baccalaureate Achievement Program at University of North Texas.  From this proposed inter-&lt;br/&gt;disciplinary project, both graduate and undergradaue students will gain valuable experimental &lt;br/&gt;and analytical skills in the rapidly growing fields of biopolymers and nanostructured materials.  &lt;br/&gt;</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>04/11/2005</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/23/2008</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>0507208</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Zhibing</FirstName>
<LastName>Hu</LastName>
<EmailAddress>zbhu@unt.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>04/11/2005</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of North Texas</Name>
<CityName>Denton</CityName>
<ZipCode>762035017</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>9405653940</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1155 Union Circle #305250</StreetAddress>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Texas</StateName>
<StateCode>TX</StateCode>
</Institution>
<FoaInformation>
<Code>0106000</Code>
<Name>Materials Research</Name>
</FoaInformation>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1773</Code>
<Text>POLYMERS</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9161</Code>
<Text>SINGLE DIVISION/UNIVERSITY</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>AMPP</Code>
<Text>ADVANCED MATERIALS &amp; PROCESSING PROGRAM</Text>
</ProgramReference>
</Award>
</rootTag>
