<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>NIRT:  Design of Biocompatible Nanoparticles for Probing Living Cellular Functions and Their Potential Environmental Impacts</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>06/15/2005</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>1114148.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>1713851</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07020000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CBET</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Chem, Bioeng, Env, &amp; Transp Sys</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Leon Esterowitz</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>lesterow@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927942</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>0507036&lt;br/&gt;Xu&lt;br/&gt;This proposal was received in response to Nanoscale Science and Engineering initiative, NSF 04-043, category NIRT.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The proposed work involves the design of nanoparticle probes to study the dynamics of "smart" membrane transport and the size change of membrane pores of living bacterial cells in real time. The model system to be used is the efflux pump (MexA-MexB-OprM) in P. aeruginosa because it extrudes a wide range of structurally and functionally unrelated substrates. The primary research goals are to (1) study the dependence of membrane transport kinetics on the size (1-80 nm), shape (sphere, rod, or triangle), surface charge (negative vs. positive), and properties (hydrophobic vs. hydrophilic) of nanoparticles, (2) study the interactions and assembly of efflux pump proteins in real time in response to the presence of synthesized nanoparticles with different sizes, shapes, surface charges, and properties, and (3) study the cytotoxicity and genotoxicity of the synthesized nanoparticles in vitro and in vivo to identify biocompatible and environmentally-friendly nanoparticles for real-time probing of membrane transport in living cells. This is an interdisciplinary research project in the areas of chemistry, material science and engineering, molecular and cellular biology, and protein engineering involving 4 PIs from Old Dominion University and Northwestern University: Xu (ODU, Chemistry and Biochemistry), Elsayed-Ali (ODU, Electrical and Computer Engineering), Osgood (ODU, Biological Sciences), and Van Duyne (Northwestern, Chemistry and Materials Science). An additional PI from CEA in France (Gillet, Protein Engineering) is also involved.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/03/2005</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>04/10/2017</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>0507036</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Richard</FirstName>
<LastName>Van Duyne</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Richard Van Duyne</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>vanduyne@northwestern.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>8474913516</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000190970</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/03/2005</StartDate>
<EndDate>04/23/2013</EndDate>
<RoleCode>Former Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Christopher</FirstName>
<LastName>Osgood</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>J</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Christopher J Osgood</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>cosgood@odu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>7576833605</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000199056</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/03/2005</StartDate>
<EndDate>04/23/2013</EndDate>
<RoleCode>Former Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Hani</FirstName>
<LastName>Elsayed-Ali</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>E</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Hani E Elsayed-Ali</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>helsayed@odu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>7576833748</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000304287</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/03/2005</StartDate>
<EndDate>04/23/2013</EndDate>
<RoleCode>Former Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Xiaohong Nancy</FirstName>
<LastName>Xu</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Xiaohong Nancy Xu</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>xhxu@odu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>7576835698</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000482085</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/03/2005</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Old Dominion University Research Foundation</Name>
<CityName>Norfolk</CityName>
<ZipCode>235082561</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>7576834293</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>4111 Monarch Way</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[Suite 204]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Virginia</StateName>
<StateCode>VA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>VA03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>077945947</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>OLD DOMINION UNIVERSITY RESEARCH FOUNDATION</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Old Dominion University]]></Name>
<CityName>Norfolk</CityName>
<StateCode>VA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>235290001</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[5115 Hampton Blvd]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Virginia</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>VA02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<FoaInformation>
<Code>0000099</Code>
<Name>Other Applications NEC</Name>
</FoaInformation>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1480</Code>
<Text>ERC-Eng Research Centers</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>5345</Code>
<Text>Engineering of Biomed Systems</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7236</Code>
<Text>BioP-Biophotonics</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7298</Code>
<Text>International Research Collab</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7680</Code>
<Text>EDA-Eng Diversity Activities</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>0000</Code>
<Text>UNASSIGNED</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>004E</Code>
<Text>BIOMEDICAL ENG AND DIAGNOSTICS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>005E</Code>
<Text>Neuro-photonics</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>014E</Code>
<Text>NANOBIOTECH AND NANOTOXICOLOGY</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1674</Code>
<Text>NANOSCALE: INTRDISCPL RESRCH T</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7218</Code>
<Text>RET SUPP-Res Exp for Tchr Supp</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7974</Code>
<Text>GRAD RESEARCH SUPPLEMENT</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9102</Code>
<Text>WOMEN, MINORITY, DISABLED, NEC</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9179</Code>
<Text>GRADUATE INVOLVEMENT</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9200</Code>
<Text>US CHINA COOP IN BASIC SCIENCE</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9251</Code>
<Text>REU SUPP-Res Exp for Ugrd Supp</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>OTHR</Code>
<Text>OTHER RESEARCH OR EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>SMET</Code>
<Text>SCIENCE, MATH, ENG &amp; TECH EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0105</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>490100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0106</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>490100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0107</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>490100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0108</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0109</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0110</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0112</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0114</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2005~1256494</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2006~33081</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2007~34176</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2008~35486</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2009~40738</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2010~40315</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2012~136626</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~136935</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><strong>Overview:</strong></p> <p>Nanomaterials possess unique physicochemical properties and promise a wide range of applications from smart sensing to nanomedicine.&nbsp; These unique properties may also incite toxicity and pose risks to environment and human.&nbsp; In this NIRT program, we have developed a set of new imaging tools, biocompatible photostable nanoparticle (NP) photonic probes (Fig.1), single-molecule-NP-optical-biosensors (SMNOBS) (Fig.2) and Photostable Optical Nanoscopy (PHOTON) (Fig.3); designed a mini-library of NPs as a model system (Fig.4) and<em> </em>ultrasensitive <em>in vivo</em> assays (early developing zebrafish embryos) (Fig.5) to systematically study physicochemical and organism dependent nanotoxicity in real-time at single NP resolution.&nbsp; We have achieved rational design of biocompatible and photostable imaging probes for probing living cellular function (membrane transport) and embryonic development.&nbsp;</p> <p>Membrane proteins in living cells can specifically recognize an array of structurally unrelated chemotoxics and assemble membrane transporters optimized for extruding them selectively out of the cells, which leads to multidrug resistance.&nbsp; These smart sensing and transport mechanisms occur at the nanoscale. Conventional methods use fluorophores or radioisotopes to study membrane transporters of ensemble cells and cannot study size-dependent function of single membrane transporters in single live cells.&nbsp; Fundamental understanding of underlying molecular mechanisms and machinery of such smart sensing and transport mechanism will transform current state of molecular sensing engineering, from design-based sensing to function-based sensing.&nbsp;&nbsp;</p> <p>Zebrafish possess unique features that are superior over other model organisms (e.g., mouse, rat) for assessing the effects of NPs on human. Notably, genetic phenotypes and drug-binding sites in zebrafish and human are highly similar. &nbsp;Fish are important aquatic species and renowned for their ability to bioconcentrate trace contaminants in the environment.&nbsp; Human consumption of fish suggests a direct impact to human health by potential releases of nanomaterials into environment. <strong>&nbsp;</strong>Further, the embryos are transparent and ex-utero, enabling direct visualization of embryonic development phenotypes, and study of real-time transport and effects of NPs <em>in vivo</em>.&nbsp;</p> <p><strong>The Intellectual Merit:</strong></p> <p><strong>Project 1:&nbsp;</strong>We have designed, synthesized and characterized a mini-library of NPs with various sizes, charges and chemical properties and developed a washing approach to prepare purified and stable (neither aggregated nor oxidized) NPs in desired medium (Fig.4).&nbsp; We have demonstrated that these NPs are photostable (non photodecomposed and non-blinking), and can serve as size-dependent optical image probes to study transport of single membrane transporters in single live cells in real time at nanometer resolution. Further, we have used these NPs as a model system to study dependence of membrane transport, biocompatibility and toxicity of NPs upon their sizes, chemical and surface properties (Fig.6).</p> <p><strong>Project 2:&nbsp;</strong>We have demonstrated, for the first time, that early developing zebrafish embryos can serve as ultrasensitive<em> in vivo</em> assays and model organisms to study biocompatibility and toxicity of NPs. &nbsp;We have systematically studied the size, charge and chemical dependent biocompatibility and toxicity of NPs upon the embryonic development (Fig.5).&nbsp; We can rationally design biocompatible Ag NPs by functionalizing their surfaces for imaging single live cells and developing embryos.</p> <p><strong>Project 3: </strong>We have genetically labeled multi-substrate membrane transporter using green fluorescence protein to create new bacterial strains and developed plasmonics-fluorescence energy-transfer spectroscopy to directly monitor the assembly of membrane transporter as it attempts to transport the NPs out of single live cells, and real-time measure its transport function and kinetics in single live cells (Fig.6).</p> <p><strong>The Broader Impacts:</strong></p> <p>This NIRT program provides new insights into (i) real-time assembly and function of multi-substrate transporter of single live cells at the molecular resolution; (ii) rational design of biocompatible and photostable NPs for imaging single live cells; (iii) dependence of optical properties, biocompatibility and toxicity of NPs upon their sizes, surface and chemical properties.&nbsp; This study leads to new knowledge that is essential to better understanding of single NP optics, the future design and assembly of smart molecular transport, and potential impacts of NPs on our environment.&nbsp; Such new knowledge significantly advance our understanding of an array of research fields (biology, chemistry, environment, materials science and engineering.)</p> <p>This NIRT program creates a new set of leading-edge optical imaging tools and assays; two new genetic-construct strains, an interdisciplinary educational environment for students; productive international collaborations; new institution infrastructure and collaboration activities. &nbsp;It broadens synergistic activities and participation of minority students by creating a new university-wide interdisciplinary nano/biotech course for students, a popular summer internship program for local high school students, and enhancing teaching and outreaching programs.</p> <p><strong>Facts &amp; Figures:</strong></p> <p>We have published 67 papers, 1 book, 5 chapters, 9 dissertations, 20 more papers and additional 2 dissertations are in preparation; presented 105 invited papers at national/international conferences and 31 invited seminars (public lectures); created one university-wide interdisciplinary course;&nbsp; One PI, 5 Co-PIs, 8 postdocs (5 women), 26 graduate (14 women, 4 minority), 23 undergraduate (12 women, 6 minority), 6 high-school students (2 girls), and two international visiting scholars participated in this NIRT program.&nbsp; For further information, visit <a href="http://www.odu.edu/~xhxu">www.odu.edu/~xhxu</a></p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 07/13/2018<br>      Modified by: Xiaohong Nancy&nbsp;Xu</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Images (<span id="selectedPhoto0">1</span> of <span class="totalNumber"></span>)           </div> <div class="galControls" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/0507036/0507036_10021401_1531447885020_Fig1Xu--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/0507036/0507036_10021401_1531447885020_Fig1Xu--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Rainbow-Colored Photostable Nanoparticle Plasmonic Imaging Probes"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/0507036/0507036_10021401_1531447885020_Fig1Xu--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Rainbow-Colored Photostable Nanoparticle Plasmonic Imaging Probes"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Fig. 1: Characterization of photostability of single plasmonic Ag NPs by dark-field optical microscopy and spectroscopy developed by the Xu lab shows that intensity and spectrum of single NPs remain unchanged under continuous illumination of halogen lamp over 12 h.  References therein</div> <div class="imageCredit">XuLab@ODU</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Xiaohong Nancy&nbsp;Xu</div> <div class="imageTitle">Rainbow-Colored Photostable Nanoparticle Plasmonic Imaging Probes</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/0507036/0507036_10021401_1531451208771_Fig3Xu--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/0507036/0507036_10021401_1531451208771_Fig3Xu--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Photostable Optical Nanoscopy (PHOTON): New Super-Resolution Imaging Tools"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/0507036/0507036_10021401_1531451208771_Fig3Xu--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Photostable Optical Nanoscopy (PHOTON): New Super-Resolution Imaging Tools"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Fig. 3: PHOTON overcome limitations (photobleaching, phototoxicity) of fluorescence-based imaging methods and achieve 1.2 nm resolution, mapping single binding sites of ligand-protein complex and real-time tracking same single live cells as they are undergoing apoptosis over hrs.</div> <div class="imageCredit">XuLab@ODU</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Xiaohong Nancy&nbsp;Xu</div> <div class="imageTitle">Photostable Optical Nanoscopy (PHOTON): New Super-Resolution Imaging Tools</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/0507036/0507036_10021401_1531453567752_Fig4Xu--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/0507036/0507036_10021401_1531453567752_Fig4Xu--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Design and Synthesis a Mini-Library of Purified &amp; Stable Ag Nanoparticles"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/0507036/0507036_10021401_1531453567752_Fig4Xu--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Design and Synthesis a Mini-Library of Purified &amp; Stable Ag Nanoparticles"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Fig. 4: Twelve representative colloidal Ag NPs that exhibit the rainbow colors, ranging from violet to red (full visible range), with peak wavelengths of absorption spectra of 393 to 738 nm, were synthesized using a rapid simple one-pot synthesis method, and characterized at single NP resolution.</div> <div class="imageCredit">XuLab@ODU</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Xiaohong Nancy&nbsp;Xu</div> <div class="imageTitle">Design and Synthesis a Mini-Library of Purified & Stable Ag Nanoparticles</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/0507036/0507036_10021401_1531469995588_Fig5Xu--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/0507036/0507036_10021401_1531469995588_Fig5Xu--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Early-Developing Zebrafish Embryos: Ultrasensitive In Vivo Assays for Study of NanoBiocompatibility &amp; NanoToxicity in Real-Time at Single NP Resolution"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/0507036/0507036_10021401_1531469995588_Fig5Xu--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Early-Developing Zebrafish Embryos: Ultrasensitive In Vivo Assays for Study of NanoBiocompatibility &amp; NanoToxicity in Real-Time at Single NP Resolution"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Fig. 5: Early-developing zebrafish embryos as ultrasensitive in vivo assays to systematically study physicochemical (size, charge & chemical) and organism (developmental-stage) dependent biocompatibility and toxicity of a mini library of purified and stable NPs in real-time at single NP resolution.</div> <div class="imageCredit">XuLab@ODU</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Xiaohong Nancy&nbsp;Xu</div> <div class="imageTitle">Early-Developing Zebrafish Embryos: Ultrasensitive In Vivo Assays for Study of NanoBiocompatibility & NanoToxicity in Real-Time at Single NP Resolution</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/0507036/0507036_10021401_1531470405174_Fig6Xu--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/0507036/0507036_10021401_1531470405174_Fig6Xu--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Real-time Dynamic Imaging of Functions of Single Membrane Transporter in Single Live Cells"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/0507036/0507036_10021401_1531470405174_Fig6Xu--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Real-time Dynamic Imaging of Functions of Single Membrane Transporter in Single Live Cells"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Fig.6: Using calibration approaches, we have developed size-dependent single NP optical rulers (size-dependent LSPR spectra of single NPs) for real-time imaging of size-dependent transport kinetics and sensing capability of single membrane transporter in single live cells.</div> <div class="imageCredit">XuLab@ODU</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Xiaohong Nancy&nbsp;Xu</div> <div class="imageTitle">Real-time Dynamic Imaging of Functions of Single Membrane Transporter in Single Live Cells</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/0507036/0507036_10021401_1531449816178_Fig2Xu--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/0507036/0507036_10021401_1531449816178_Fig2Xu--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Single Molecule Nanoparticle Optical Biosensors (SMNOBS)"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/0507036/0507036_10021401_1531449816178_Fig2Xu--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Single Molecule Nanoparticle Optical Biosensors (SMNOBS)"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Fig. 2: Ultrasmall Ag NPs (2.6 nm) are used to achieve high-dependent LSPR spectra of single NPs on their surface properties, and single molecule detection due to its larger surface-area-to-volume ratio.  It is indeed that The Smallest is the Most Beautiful (Sensitive)!  JACS, 130, 17095, 2008.</div> <div class="imageCredit">XuLab@ODU</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Xiaohong Nancy&nbsp;Xu</div> <div class="imageTitle">Single Molecule Nanoparticle Optical Biosensors (SMNOBS)</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Overview:  Nanomaterials possess unique physicochemical properties and promise a wide range of applications from smart sensing to nanomedicine.  These unique properties may also incite toxicity and pose risks to environment and human.  In this NIRT program, we have developed a set of new imaging tools, biocompatible photostable nanoparticle (NP) photonic probes (Fig.1), single-molecule-NP-optical-biosensors (SMNOBS) (Fig.2) and Photostable Optical Nanoscopy (PHOTON) (Fig.3); designed a mini-library of NPs as a model system (Fig.4) and ultrasensitive in vivo assays (early developing zebrafish embryos) (Fig.5) to systematically study physicochemical and organism dependent nanotoxicity in real-time at single NP resolution.  We have achieved rational design of biocompatible and photostable imaging probes for probing living cellular function (membrane transport) and embryonic development.   Membrane proteins in living cells can specifically recognize an array of structurally unrelated chemotoxics and assemble membrane transporters optimized for extruding them selectively out of the cells, which leads to multidrug resistance.  These smart sensing and transport mechanisms occur at the nanoscale. Conventional methods use fluorophores or radioisotopes to study membrane transporters of ensemble cells and cannot study size-dependent function of single membrane transporters in single live cells.  Fundamental understanding of underlying molecular mechanisms and machinery of such smart sensing and transport mechanism will transform current state of molecular sensing engineering, from design-based sensing to function-based sensing.    Zebrafish possess unique features that are superior over other model organisms (e.g., mouse, rat) for assessing the effects of NPs on human. Notably, genetic phenotypes and drug-binding sites in zebrafish and human are highly similar.  Fish are important aquatic species and renowned for their ability to bioconcentrate trace contaminants in the environment.  Human consumption of fish suggests a direct impact to human health by potential releases of nanomaterials into environment.  Further, the embryos are transparent and ex-utero, enabling direct visualization of embryonic development phenotypes, and study of real-time transport and effects of NPs in vivo.   The Intellectual Merit:  Project 1: We have designed, synthesized and characterized a mini-library of NPs with various sizes, charges and chemical properties and developed a washing approach to prepare purified and stable (neither aggregated nor oxidized) NPs in desired medium (Fig.4).  We have demonstrated that these NPs are photostable (non photodecomposed and non-blinking), and can serve as size-dependent optical image probes to study transport of single membrane transporters in single live cells in real time at nanometer resolution. Further, we have used these NPs as a model system to study dependence of membrane transport, biocompatibility and toxicity of NPs upon their sizes, chemical and surface properties (Fig.6).  Project 2: We have demonstrated, for the first time, that early developing zebrafish embryos can serve as ultrasensitive in vivo assays and model organisms to study biocompatibility and toxicity of NPs.  We have systematically studied the size, charge and chemical dependent biocompatibility and toxicity of NPs upon the embryonic development (Fig.5).  We can rationally design biocompatible Ag NPs by functionalizing their surfaces for imaging single live cells and developing embryos.  Project 3: We have genetically labeled multi-substrate membrane transporter using green fluorescence protein to create new bacterial strains and developed plasmonics-fluorescence energy-transfer spectroscopy to directly monitor the assembly of membrane transporter as it attempts to transport the NPs out of single live cells, and real-time measure its transport function and kinetics in single live cells (Fig.6).  The Broader Impacts:  This NIRT program provides new insights into (i) real-time assembly and function of multi-substrate transporter of single live cells at the molecular resolution; (ii) rational design of biocompatible and photostable NPs for imaging single live cells; (iii) dependence of optical properties, biocompatibility and toxicity of NPs upon their sizes, surface and chemical properties.  This study leads to new knowledge that is essential to better understanding of single NP optics, the future design and assembly of smart molecular transport, and potential impacts of NPs on our environment.  Such new knowledge significantly advance our understanding of an array of research fields (biology, chemistry, environment, materials science and engineering.)  This NIRT program creates a new set of leading-edge optical imaging tools and assays; two new genetic-construct strains, an interdisciplinary educational environment for students; productive international collaborations; new institution infrastructure and collaboration activities.  It broadens synergistic activities and participation of minority students by creating a new university-wide interdisciplinary nano/biotech course for students, a popular summer internship program for local high school students, and enhancing teaching and outreaching programs.  Facts &amp; Figures:  We have published 67 papers, 1 book, 5 chapters, 9 dissertations, 20 more papers and additional 2 dissertations are in preparation; presented 105 invited papers at national/international conferences and 31 invited seminars (public lectures); created one university-wide interdisciplinary course;  One PI, 5 Co-PIs, 8 postdocs (5 women), 26 graduate (14 women, 4 minority), 23 undergraduate (12 women, 6 minority), 6 high-school students (2 girls), and two international visiting scholars participated in this NIRT program.  For further information, visit www.odu.edu/~xhxu          Last Modified: 07/13/2018       Submitted by: Xiaohong Nancy Xu]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
