<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Inverse Homogenization for Microstructured Media</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2005</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2008</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardAmount>79887</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03040100</Code>
<Directorate>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Henry A. Warchall</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Abstract: DMS-0508901, Elena Cherkaev, University of Utah&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Title: Inverse Homogenization for Microstructured Media  &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The  project  develops a method of extracting information about the fine &lt;br/&gt;scale geometric structure of micro- or nano-structured material from &lt;br/&gt;effective acoustic or electromagnetic measurements. The technical &lt;br/&gt;difficulty of using sound or electromagnetic waves in sensing micro- or &lt;br/&gt;nano-structured media is the complexity and fine scale of &lt;br/&gt;the microgeometry. The length of the &lt;br/&gt;applied sound waves is much larger than the variations of the &lt;br/&gt;microstructure, so that only an effective or homogenized response of the  &lt;br/&gt;structure is present in measured data. The proposed "inverse &lt;br/&gt;homogenization" method derives microstructural parameters from effective &lt;br/&gt;measurements. The method is based on the Stieltjes analytic representation &lt;br/&gt;of the effective properties of a randomly microstructured medium, and a &lt;br/&gt;possibility to reconstruct the spectral function in this representation &lt;br/&gt;from the effective response of the homogenized material. The approach ties &lt;br/&gt;together properties of the medium&lt;br/&gt;on different scales: Complex permittivity on the coarse scale provides data &lt;br/&gt;for microscale inversion. Computationally, the problem is ill-posed and &lt;br/&gt;requires regularization to develop stable numerical algorithms. The recovered &lt;br/&gt;microstructural information can be used for characterizing other &lt;br/&gt;transport and physical properties of the medium, such as permeability, &lt;br/&gt;diffusion, thermal and hydraulic conductivity, etc.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The  project develops a novel approach to reconstruction of micro- and &lt;br/&gt;nano-structural information from measurements of effective properties of &lt;br/&gt;composite materials. It brings together results recently obtained in two &lt;br/&gt;different fields: homogenization, and inverse and imaging theory, which &lt;br/&gt;makes possible to formulate new applications for both research areas. The &lt;br/&gt;problem is to find a composite material's structure from its known &lt;br/&gt;response to the applied acoustic or electromagnetic field. When the &lt;br/&gt;wavelength of the applied field is much larger than the microstructural &lt;br/&gt;scale, then fine scale features of the structure cannot be resolved, and &lt;br/&gt;the microgeometry is  homogenized. The project develops an "inverse &lt;br/&gt;homogenization" method that utilizes acoustic or electromagnetic &lt;br/&gt;measurements over a range of frequency to recover information about &lt;br/&gt;the microstructural parameters of the medium.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The results of the proposed work are useful in designing artificial micro- &lt;br/&gt;and nano-structured composites. They also have applications to osteoporosis &lt;br/&gt;through ultrasound evaluation of bone structure and density and to &lt;br/&gt;noninvasive monitoring of blood clots and evaluation of their age and &lt;br/&gt;structure. &lt;br/&gt;</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/30/2005</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/30/2005</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>0508901</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Elena</FirstName>
<LastName>Cherkaev</LastName>
<EmailAddress>elena@math.utah.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>06/30/2005</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Utah</Name>
<CityName>SALT LAKE CITY</CityName>
<ZipCode>841128930</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>8015816903</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>75 S 2000 E</StreetAddress>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Utah</StateName>
<StateCode>UT</StateCode>
</Institution>
<FoaInformation>
<Code>0000099</Code>
<Name>Other Applications NEC</Name>
</FoaInformation>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1266</Code>
<Text>APPLIED MATHEMATICS</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>0000</Code>
<Text>UNASSIGNED</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7237</Code>
<Text>NANO NON-SOLIC SCI &amp; ENG AWD</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>OTHR</Code>
<Text>OTHER RESEARCH OR EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
</Award>
</rootTag>
