<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Collaborative Research: Midwest Geometry Conference 2005-2007</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>04/15/2005</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>03/31/2008</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>12000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>12000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03040200</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DMS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Christopher Stark</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Abstract&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Award:  DMS 0509068, 0508661, 0509714&lt;br/&gt;Principal Investigator:  Thomas P. Branson, Shihshu Walter Wei, &lt;br/&gt;Andrzej J. Derdzinski&lt;br/&gt;Institutions: University of Iowa, University of Oklahoma,&lt;br/&gt;Ohio State University&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The Midwest Geometry Conference has been meeting annually since&lt;br/&gt;1991.  Its goal is to present recent advances in differential&lt;br/&gt;geometry, geometric analysis, and integral geometry to geometers&lt;br/&gt;from the Midwest, including junior level researchers and some&lt;br/&gt;graduate students.  The main part of the program consists of&lt;br/&gt;several plenary lectures given by experts in specific sub-fields&lt;br/&gt;(who need not be Midwest-based); an opportunity is also provided&lt;br/&gt;for some of the participants to give contributed talks.  The&lt;br/&gt;current project provides for conferences in the spring of 2005,&lt;br/&gt;2006, and 2007 at the Ohio State University, the University of&lt;br/&gt;Oklahoma and, respectively, the University of Iowa.  The Ohio&lt;br/&gt;State conference, planned for April 29 to May 1, 2005, will focus&lt;br/&gt;on three topics: positively curved manifolds; Ricci flow,&lt;br/&gt;solitons and Einstein metrics; geometric group theory.  The lists&lt;br/&gt;of topics for the other two conferences are still tentative, and&lt;br/&gt;include: symmetric criticality; p-harmonic geometry; convexity,&lt;br/&gt;positively curved manifolds, and Ricci flow (Oklahoma, 2006), as&lt;br/&gt;well as: symmetries and overdetermined systems of PDEs; the&lt;br/&gt;AdS/CFT correspondence; nonlinear hyperbolic evolution equations;&lt;br/&gt;geometric scattering theory (Iowa, 2007).&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The Midwest Geometry Conference is dedicated to the exchange of&lt;br/&gt;ideas among members of the geometry community in the Midwest, as&lt;br/&gt;well as dissemination of important research advances and ideas,&lt;br/&gt;nationwide and worldwide, in differential geometry and related&lt;br/&gt;fields.  A key objective of the conference is the attempt to&lt;br/&gt;encourage researchers and potential researchers in the Midwest,&lt;br/&gt;especially those who work some distance from the large research&lt;br/&gt;centers, as well as young people, women, and members of&lt;br/&gt;underrepresented groups.  "Warm-up" sessions for graduate&lt;br/&gt;students and young researchers are planned for the days leading&lt;br/&gt;up to the conference.  At least one of the three or four focus&lt;br/&gt;topics at each conference is related to applications of geometry.&lt;br/&gt;Historically, such applications lie primarily in physics, with&lt;br/&gt;prominent examples provided by Einstein's general theory of&lt;br/&gt;relativity and the currently accepted Standard Model of&lt;br/&gt;elementary particles and their interactions.  Other well-known&lt;br/&gt;applications of differential geometry are in engineering, for&lt;br/&gt;example robotics.  A further example pertains to evolution&lt;br/&gt;equations, which are currently a subject of keen interest to&lt;br/&gt;differential geometers and, at the same time, have the applied&lt;br/&gt;aspect of describing how some materials, or the space itself,&lt;br/&gt;develop in time.  A very specific example of the latter kind is&lt;br/&gt;provided by the mean curvature flow.  The surface of a globule of&lt;br/&gt;molten plastic evolves, or adapts in time, to have the minimum&lt;br/&gt;possible curvature; this evolution is completely determined by&lt;br/&gt;the globule's curvature.  This fundamental observation provides&lt;br/&gt;an understanding of a wide range of flow problems, and allows an&lt;br/&gt;approach to predicting the flow.  This has immediate relevance to&lt;br/&gt;injection molding of materials, for example in the dashboards and&lt;br/&gt;bumpers of automobiles.  But the fundamental principles behind&lt;br/&gt;mean curvature flow have also provided a paradigm for problems&lt;br/&gt;like the Ricci flow, in which the metric properties of space&lt;br/&gt;itself are the quantities which are evolving.  Questions of the&lt;br/&gt;latter kind will be central to the coming meetings of the Midwest&lt;br/&gt;Geometry Conference.&lt;br/&gt;</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>04/11/2005</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>04/11/2005</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>0508661</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Shihshu Walter</FirstName>
<LastName>Wei</LastName>
<EmailAddress>wwei@ou.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>04/11/2005</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Oklahoma Norman Campus</Name>
<CityName>NORMAN</CityName>
<ZipCode>730199705</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>4053254757</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>201 Stephenson Parkway</StreetAddress>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Oklahoma</StateName>
<StateCode>OK</StateCode>
</Institution>
<FoaInformation>
<Code>0000099</Code>
<Name>Other Applications NEC</Name>
</FoaInformation>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1265</Code>
<Text>GEOMETRIC ANALYSIS</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>0000</Code>
<Text>UNASSIGNED</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7556</Code>
<Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>OTHR</Code>
<Text>OTHER RESEARCH OR EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0105</Code>
</Appropriation>
</Award>
</rootTag>
