<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>NER:    Exploratory Research in Molecular Communication between Nanomachines</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/15/2005</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2007</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>100000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>100000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>05010000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>CSE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CCF</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division of Computing and Communication Foundations</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Sankar Basu</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>sabasu@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927843</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>ABSTRACT&lt;br/&gt;Proposal ID: 0508506&lt;br/&gt;Title: NER: Exploratory Research in Molecular Communication between Nano-machines&lt;br/&gt;Institution: University of California at Irvine&lt;br/&gt;PI name: Tutsuya Suda&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project explores the possibility of molecular communication as a solution for communication between nanomachines.  Nanomachines are artificial or biological nano-scale devices that perform simple computation, sensing, or actuation. Molecular communication provides a mechanism for nanomachines to communicate over a short distance (adjacent nanomachines to tens of micrometers) using molecules as a communication carrier.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The class of molecular communication systems that the PI considers in the project consists of sender nanomachines, receiver nanomachines, carrier molecules, and the environment that these operate in.   Senders and receivers include biological (such as cells or bacteria) and biologically derived (such as molecular motors or sensors taken from biological systems) nanomachines that are capable of emitting and capturing molecules.  Carrier molecules are proteins, ions, or DNA.   The environment is the aqueous solution that is typically found within and between cells.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;In the project, the P.I. develops research ideas for molecular communication, designs a few possible molecular communication systems, evaluates the feasibility through simulations, empirical studies, collaborates with researchers in the field to identify promising options, and develops a full proposal to submit to NSF for the next year's competition.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Intellectual merits and broader impacts of the proposed projects are the following:&lt;br/&gt;Creation of new research area: Researchers have so far focused on understanding biological nanomachines and artificially creating counterparts of biological nanomachines. In this project, the P.I. investigates molecular communication as a solution for nano-scale communication between nanomachines. Using molecules as communication carriers is new, and creating such paradigm shifting research is intellectually challenging and rewarding.&lt;br/&gt;Interdisciplinary research: The project is interdisciplinary and involves biotechnology, nano technology and information technology. This is intellectually challenging and rewarding.&lt;br/&gt;Creation of new applications for bio and nano technologies: Communicating nanomachines enables a new set of applications. If multiple nanomachines communicate, they may cooperate and perform complex tasks such as nano-scale sensing, molecular computing, or nanomedicine. The proposed research enables creation of such important applications, and its impact is broad.&lt;br/&gt;Creation of new courses at the graduate program level: The project produces a broad impact on education by identifying a new area of science and technology.  The proposed research leads to the creation of new courses of the multidisciplinary nature at a graduate program level that provides a broad scope of nano scale science.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/15/2005</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/15/2005</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.070</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>0508506</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Tatsuya</FirstName>
<LastName>Suda</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Tatsuya Suda</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>suda@ics.uci.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>9498245474</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000165095</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/15/2005</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of California-Irvine</Name>
<CityName>Irvine</CityName>
<CountyName/>
<ZipCode>926977600</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>9498247295</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>160 Aldrich Hall</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>45</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CA45</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>046705849</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF CALIFORNIA, IRVINE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>071549000</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of California-Irvine]]></Name>
<CityName>Irvine</CityName>
<CountyName/>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>926977600</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[160 Aldrich Hall]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>45</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CA45</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<FoaInformation>
<Code>0000912</Code>
<Name>Computer Science</Name>
</FoaInformation>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1676</Code>
<Text>NANOSCALE:  EXPLORATORY RSRCH</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1676</Code>
<Text>NANOSCALE:  EXPLORATORY RSRCH</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9218</Code>
<Text>BASIC RESEARCH &amp; HUMAN RESORCS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>HPCC</Code>
<Text>HIGH PERFORMANCE COMPUTING &amp; COMM</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0105</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>490100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2005~100000</FUND_OBLG>
</Award>
</rootTag>
