<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>CSR-PDOS: Fast, Consistent Distributed File Systems through Operating System Speculation</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2005</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2009</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>599998.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>599998</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>05050000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>CSE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CNS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Computer and Network Systems</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Mohamed G. Gouda</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This project is investigating how generic support for speculative&lt;br/&gt;execution in a commodity operating system can improve the performance&lt;br/&gt;and consistency of remote data access.  Rather than block applications&lt;br/&gt;during a remote file system operation, the operating system&lt;br/&gt;checkpoints the state of the calling process, predicts the result of&lt;br/&gt;the remote operation, and speculatively resumes execution based upon&lt;br/&gt;the predicted results.  If the speculation proves correct, the&lt;br/&gt;checkpoint is discarded; if the speculation is incorrect, the calling&lt;br/&gt;process is restored to the checkpoint and the operation retried.  The&lt;br/&gt;operating system guarantees safe execution by preventing speculative&lt;br/&gt;processes from externalizing output until the speculations upon which&lt;br/&gt;that output depends have proven correct.  By tracking causal&lt;br/&gt;dependencies created through inter-process communication, the&lt;br/&gt;operating system allows multiple processes to safely share speculative&lt;br/&gt;state.  In addition to file systems, this project is exploring uses of&lt;br/&gt;speculation in diverse areas, including cyber-foraging, remote&lt;br/&gt;desktops, and software installation.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The major impact of this project lies in improving the performance,&lt;br/&gt;consistency guarantees, and safety of current distributed file&lt;br/&gt;systems.  The project is developing speculative versions of NFS, AFS&lt;br/&gt;and other distributed file systems that perform substantially better&lt;br/&gt;than current versions of these file systems.  At the same time, these&lt;br/&gt;versions provide stronger consistency and safety guarantees to&lt;br/&gt;applications.  The software artifacts developed as part of this&lt;br/&gt;project, including a modifed version of Linux that supports&lt;br/&gt;speculation, are being released to the open-source community.&lt;br/&gt;Additionally, educational initiatives are helping train the next&lt;br/&gt;generation of systems software developers.&lt;br/&gt;</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/15/2005</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/07/2007</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>0509093</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Peter</FirstName>
<LastName>Chen</LastName>
<EmailAddress>pmchen@umich.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>06/15/2005</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Jason</FirstName>
<LastName>Flinn</LastName>
<EmailAddress>jflinn@umich.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>06/15/2005</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Regents of the University of Michigan - Ann Arbor</Name>
<CityName>Ann Arbor</CityName>
<ZipCode>481091274</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>7347636438</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>3003 South State St. Room 1062</StreetAddress>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Michigan</StateName>
<StateCode>MI</StateCode>
</Institution>
<FoaInformation>
<Code>0000912</Code>
<Name>Computer Science</Name>
</FoaInformation>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7354</Code>
<Text>CSR-Computer Systems Research</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9218</Code>
<Text>BASIC RESEARCH &amp; HUMAN RESORCS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>HPCC</Code>
<Text>HIGH PERFORMANCE COMPUTING &amp; COMM</Text>
</ProgramReference>
</Award>
</rootTag>
