<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Collaborative research: A study of transient aseismic slip and non-volcanic tremor in southern Mexico with large aperture seismic and GPS arrays</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/15/2005</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>01/31/2011</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardAmount>165682</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>06030204</Code>
<Directorate>
<LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<LongName>Division Of Earth Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Eva E. Zanzerkia</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Intellectural merit: Funds are requested for a joint geodetic and seismic study of&lt;br/&gt;the Oaxaca-Guerrero segment of the Middle America subduction zone, one of the few places&lt;br/&gt;on earth where land-based GPS and seismic observations can be used to study both the&lt;br/&gt;locked, seismogenic area of a subduction interface and region of deeper transitional&lt;br/&gt;slip, where episodic tremor and slip may originate. The principal scientific goal is&lt;br/&gt;to better understand the recently discovered phenomenon of episodic slip transients&lt;br/&gt;and its role in either relieving or increasing strain accumulating along the seismogenic&lt;br/&gt;portion of a subduction interface. A pilot study during the past year shows that such&lt;br/&gt;transients are occurring as frequently as every 12-24 months in this region, that&lt;br/&gt;some transients (1998 and 2004) originate far outside the Guerrero seismic gap, and&lt;br/&gt;that the transients may be accompanied by non-volcanic seismic tremors.  Based on these&lt;br/&gt;previously unrecognized results, deployment for 24 months of an 8-station broadband&lt;br/&gt;seismic array and expansion of a regional continuous GPS array to include 4 critically&lt;br/&gt;located stations in a region where the transients appear to occur are planned. The&lt;br/&gt;new seismic array, which will span a&lt;br/&gt;broad gap between two dense seismic transects being installed as part of the already&lt;br/&gt;funded Caltech/UNAM Middle America Seismic Experiment, will allow detection and location&lt;br/&gt;of any episodic tremors in the study area. Continuous GPS measurements from the&lt;br/&gt;pre-existing GPS stations and nine new stations constructed by this group and&lt;br/&gt;collaborator Enrique Cabral of UNAM will provide critical complementary information&lt;br/&gt;about the source regions, magnitude, and timing of episodic slip. Data from an existing&lt;br/&gt;smaller-footprint 30-station continuous and campaign GPS array that DeMets and Cabral&lt;br/&gt;operate in Oaxaca above the Cocos-North America subduction interface will also be used&lt;br/&gt;to study in more detail deformation within a conspicuous seismic gap analogous to,&lt;br/&gt;but smaller than the well-known Guerrero seismic gap. The combined GPS and seismic&lt;br/&gt;arrays will be a powerful tool for studying subduction transients and non-volcanic&lt;br/&gt;tremor, and for imaging spatial and temporal variations in frictional coupling&lt;br/&gt;along the locked and transitional zones beneath our network. Brudzinski, who will be&lt;br/&gt;a new faculty member at Miami University of Ohio in August of 2005, will purchase the&lt;br/&gt;necessary seismic equipment with start-up funds from his faculty position and will&lt;br/&gt;have it prepared for a two-year deployment in early 2006. DeMets at UW-Madison will&lt;br/&gt;coordinate the GPS station installation with Dr. Cabral, as well as a modest expansion&lt;br/&gt;of the Oaxaca GPS network to improve coverage of the aforementioned seismic gap. The&lt;br/&gt;UW-Madison geophysics group has a long history of deploying seismic and GPS networks&lt;br/&gt;and will provide at no cost two expert technicians to help build and maintain the&lt;br/&gt;combined seismic and GPS network. Responsibilities for modeling of the geodetic and&lt;br/&gt;seismic observations will lie respectively with DeMets and Brudzinski.&lt;br/&gt;Broader impacts: Episodic tremor and slip are a newly observed phenomenon that appears&lt;br/&gt;to be related to many different aspects of earth science (seismology, tectonics,&lt;br/&gt;petrology, and geodynamics), with possible ramifications for understanding triggering&lt;br/&gt;of megathrust earthquakes. Students at Miami University will be offered a unique opportunity&lt;br/&gt;to participate in a field workshop course that will coincide with the initial seismic&lt;br/&gt;deployment, thereby exposing students to a geophysics field research. Broader impacts at&lt;br/&gt;UW-Madison will include education of Mexican graduate student Francisco Correa-Mora,&lt;br/&gt;who will do a substantial portion of his dissertation research on the mechanics of&lt;br/&gt;subduction along the Middle America trench. The availability of new continuous and&lt;br/&gt;campaign GPS and seismic data to the broader geophysical community will also&lt;br/&gt;extend the impact of this work beyond our group, particularly once future transient&lt;br/&gt;slip episodes and/or tremor sequences are recorded.&lt;br/&gt;</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>09/14/2005</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/26/2007</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>0510887</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Dennis</FirstName>
<LastName>DeMets</LastName>
<EmailAddress>chuck@geology.wisc.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>09/14/2005</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Wisconsin-Madison</Name>
<CityName>MADISON</CityName>
<ZipCode>537151218</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6082623822</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>21 North Park Street</StreetAddress>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Wisconsin</StateName>
<StateCode>WI</StateCode>
</Institution>
<FoaInformation>
<Code>0000099</Code>
<Name>Other Applications NEC</Name>
</FoaInformation>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1574</Code>
<Text>GEOPHYSICS</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>0000</Code>
<Text>UNASSIGNED</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1576</Code>
<Text>NATIONL EARTHQK HZRD REDCT PRG</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>OTHR</Code>
<Text>OTHER RESEARCH OR EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
</Award>
</rootTag>
