<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Structure and Dynamics of Block Ionomer Complexes</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2005</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2009</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount/>
<AwardAmount>345000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03070012</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DMR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Materials Research</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Andrew Lovinger</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>alovinge@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924933</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The major goal of this project is to explore two types of dispersed composite nanomaterials&lt;br/&gt;collectively called the block ionomers complexes or BIC. The first materials are synthesized by&lt;br/&gt;reacting dual hydrophilic block copolymers, containing ionic and water soluble nonionic&lt;br/&gt;segments, with oppositely charged polyions. Such materials form micelle-like aggregates with&lt;br/&gt;the polyion complex core and hydrophilic nonionic corona in aqueous media. The second&lt;br/&gt;materials are obtained by reacting micelles from block copolymers, containing ionic and water&lt;br/&gt;insoluble nonionic segments with the polyions of opposite charge. Such materials contain the&lt;br/&gt;micelles with hydrophobic cores as nucleating particles surrounded by insoluble polyion&lt;br/&gt;complex layer and a charged hydrophilic corona from the polyion present in excess.                                            &lt;br/&gt;The area of BIC has emerged a decade ago as a result of intersection of the studies on the selfassembly&lt;br/&gt;of polyelectrolyte complexes and ionic block copolymers in selective solvents. Several&lt;br/&gt;promising applications of BIC materials have been determined, including the delivery of DNA,&lt;br/&gt;therapeutic proteins, low molecular mass drugs and imaging agents. One fundamental property&lt;br/&gt;of regular polyelectrolyte complexes is the ability to participate in highly cooperative polyion&lt;br/&gt;interchange reactions with other polyelectrolyte components present in solution. Initial studies&lt;br/&gt;suggest that such reactions involving BIC can also proceed. Although these reactions are of great&lt;br/&gt;importance for the self-assembly and practical use of BIC no systematic studies in this area have&lt;br/&gt;been conducted. This proposal will address this deficiency using fluorescence technique to&lt;br/&gt;determine rates and directions of these reactions and understand the contribution of the core-shell&lt;br/&gt;architecture of BIC to their dynamic properties.                                                                                                     &lt;br/&gt;Novel materials will be synthesized and characterized, such as BIC obtained by reacting&lt;br/&gt;polyelectrolyte micelles having cross-linked ionic cores and nonionic water soluble corona or&lt;br/&gt;micelles having hydrophobic cores and polyion corona with various polyions, including DNA&lt;br/&gt;and proteins. The stability, size, charge and morphology of the BIC will be determined using a&lt;br/&gt;combination of physicochemical methods. In particular, the proposal will employ for&lt;br/&gt;characterization of BIC the Atomic Force Microscopy to determine the particle topography and&lt;br/&gt;Small Angle Neutron Scattering to determine the particle internal structure. A theoretical&lt;br/&gt;analysis of the BIC will be carried out in collaboration with scientists at Moscow State&lt;br/&gt;University. Overall the proposal will greatly advance experimental and theoretical understanding&lt;br/&gt;of BIC and develop new classes of BIC materials that can be useful in biomedical applications.                              &lt;br/&gt;The proposal will have broader impact by creating a favorable environment for collaboration&lt;br/&gt;between the material and biomedical scientists and will contribute to interdisciplinary training of&lt;br/&gt;students and scientists in the University of Nebraska and beyond. The results of the studies will&lt;br/&gt;be disseminated through scientific meetings and seminars within the Center for Drug Delivery&lt;br/&gt;and Nanomedicine, which will advance applications of polymer nanomaterials in drug and gene&lt;br/&gt;delivery. The integration of research and education will benefit from the course on Polymer&lt;br/&gt;Therapeutics taught by the PI and Co-PI, which incorporates recent scientific findings. The&lt;br/&gt;dissemination will be enhanced by the active use of Internet, such as online posting of the course&lt;br/&gt;and lectures. The scientific and technological understanding in the State of Nebraska will be&lt;br/&gt;enhanced by presentations to broad community groups such as MiniMedical School. These&lt;br/&gt;synergistic activities will demonstrate linkage between scientific discoveries and societal benefit&lt;br/&gt;by providing the examples of application of polymer materials including the new findings&lt;br/&gt;anticipated from this project.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>05/09/2005</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>04/28/2007</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>0513699</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Alexander</FirstName>
<LastName>Kabanov</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>V</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Alexander V Kabanov</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>kabanov@email.unc.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>9195373800</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000404859</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/09/2005</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Tatiana</FirstName>
<LastName>Bronich</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>K</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Tatiana K Bronich</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>tbronich@unmc.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>4025599351</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000404189</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/09/2005</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Nebraska Medical Center</Name>
<CityName>Omaha</CityName>
<CountyName/>
<ZipCode>681987835</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>4025597456</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>987835 Nebraska Medical Center</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Nebraska</StateName>
<StateCode>NE</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NE02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>168559177</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>BOARD OF REGENTS OF THE UNIVERSITY OF NEBRASKA</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>068662618</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Nebraska Medical Center]]></Name>
<CityName>Omaha</CityName>
<CountyName/>
<StateCode>NE</StateCode>
<ZipCode>681987835</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[987835 Nebraska Medical Center]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Nebraska</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NE02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<FoaInformation>
<Code>0106000</Code>
<Name>Materials Research</Name>
</FoaInformation>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1773</Code>
<Text>POLYMERS</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7237</Code>
<Text>NANO NON-SOLIC SCI &amp; ENG AWD</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9161</Code>
<Text>SINGLE DIVISION/UNIVERSITY</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>AMPP</Code>
<Text>ADVANCED MATERIALS &amp; PROCESSING PROGRAM</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0105</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>490100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0106</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>490100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0107</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>490100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2005~115000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2006~115000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2007~115000</FUND_OBLG>
</Award>
</rootTag>
