<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>SGER: Pervious/Impervious Pavement Comparative Site Base Study</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>06/01/2005</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>11/30/2006</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>49545</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07030000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Civil, Mechanical, &amp; Manufact Inn</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Richard J. Fragaszy</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Abstract &lt;br/&gt; Impervious surfaces, such as pavements and rooftops, are an ever-increasing part of the developed world. It has been established that these surfaces have many environmentally negative impacts. These impacts include nonpoint source pollution from runoff and an increase in the urban heat island effect. Pervious concrete is an alternative paving surface that may alleviate many of these environmental concerns, particularly those associated with erosion and the effects of stormwater runoff on soils and receiving waters. There is a widespread potential for the use of pervious concrete in roadways, parking lots and other paved areas, but this potential cannot be realized without more fundamental research into the material and its effect on the human, built and natural environment. This research is needed to facilitate the design and application of this practice. Limited laboratory research is being performed on the material environmental aspects of pervious concrete, and a number of field sites are available. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;An opportunity has arisen to perform comparative field research on a parking lot site that is partially pervious concrete and partially impervious pavement in collaboration with a large military installation in South Carolina. This proposed site is unique in that it represents a side-by-side comparison, specifically laid out to allow for a more controlled field research setting. This research proposal covers a baseline comparative assessment of physical, chemical, human dynamic, hydrologic and ecological characteristics and impacts of these two types of surfaces. The U.S. Army has taken the initiative to design the facility with this potential for comparative research in mind, giving the University of South Carolina and other researchers a great potential research opportunity at a greatly reduced cost. It is important to get an initial assessment of the site during construction and during the first year in order for more meaningful research results and opportunities in the future. The initial conditions are particularly important with respect to the standard concrete material property tests (traditionally performed at set times from the date of placement) and existing soil and neighboring conditions. This difficulty in this research is associated with the time constraints making it difficult for the research team to be able to rapidly mobilize once construction is underway in order to fully take advantage of this opportunity. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The intellectual merit of performing this baseline study includes providing for an opportunity for further scientific studies into the characteristics of pervious concrete and its ecological impacts. This research has very high practical implications, with the potential application of pervious concrete having a large impact on construction practices and their effect on the environment. Broader impacts also include the continued use of undergraduate and graduate students in this research at the University of South Carolina and with other researchers at the facility. A network for dissemination of research results has already been established within the industry and through the professional design community, and extends to the national level, in addition to other methods such as in research and design publications. The Army is also interested in showcasing this site over the years as a study site for both short-term and long-term impacts. The results from these comparisons will be used in sustainable design decisions both for the planned future expansions at this site and at other facilities potentially through out the world.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>06/03/2005</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>03/10/2006</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0514418</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Liv</FirstName>
      <LastName>Haselbach</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>lhaselbach@lamar.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>06/03/2005</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University South Carolina Research Foundation</Name>
      <CityName>COLUMBIA</CityName>
      <ZipCode>292080001</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>8037777093</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>1600 Hampton Street</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>South Carolina</StateName>
      <StateCode>SC</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0308000</Code>
      <Name>Industrial Technology</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1440</Code>
      <Text>ENVIRONMENTAL ENGINEERING</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1634</Code>
      <Text>GEOMECHANICS &amp; GEOMATERIALS</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1057</Code>
      <Text>CIS BASE RESEARCH</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9102</Code>
      <Text>WOMEN, MINORITY, DISABLED, NEC</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9237</Code>
      <Text>SMALL GRANTS-EXPLORATORY RSRCH</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>CVIS</Code>
      <Text>CIVIL INFRASTRUCTURE</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
