<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Financial Support: American Chemical Society (ACS) National Meeting; San Diego, CA; March 13-17, 2005</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>02/15/2005</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2005</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>2000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>05010000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division of Computing and Communication Foundations</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Eun K. Park</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The PI requests financial support for the Bionanotechnology section in Polymetric Materials, Sciences, and Engineering (PMSE) division at CUNY - Hunter College. &lt;br/&gt;The attendees: Hiroshi Matsui (CUNY), Kimberly Hamad-Schifferli (MIT), and Rajesh Naik (Air Force LabWright Patterson) are also presenting at this symposium.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Intellectual Merit&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The ACS National meeting is the largest meeting in the fields of Chemistry and related&lt;br/&gt;engineering. In the presentations being organized by Dr. Matsui's group, the topics are centered around bionanotechnology. Specifically, the group plans to explore biomaterials applications as they relate to computers, sensors and data storage, as well as relevant research applications such as tissue engineering and drug delivery.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The symposium as a whole, will have 3 sessions focused on nanomaterials in biology, the interface between biology and nanoscale systems, and biological polymers. This&lt;br/&gt;symposium will focus on how to utilize biological macromolecules as building blocks to&lt;br/&gt;synthesize inorganic nanomaterials, the interface between the biological world and&lt;br/&gt;nanoscale systems, and use of biological macromolecules as building blocks for&lt;br/&gt;polymers.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Broader Impact&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The goal of the symposium is to provide a forum for direct interaction between polymer, materials, and biological researchers in order to explore new interdisciplinary research activities in nanoscience.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The invited speakers include a diverse array of intellectual backgrounds, to include&lt;br/&gt;industrial, academic and government laboratories, male and female researchers, and&lt;br/&gt;established as well as young investigators.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>02/10/2005</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>02/10/2005</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0515171</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Hiroshi</FirstName>
      <LastName>Matsui</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>hmatsui@hunter.cuny.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>02/10/2005</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>CUNY Hunter College</Name>
      <CityName>New York</CityName>
      <ZipCode>100655024</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>2127724020</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>695 Park Avenue</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>New York</StateName>
      <StateCode>NY</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0000912</Code>
      <Name>Computer Science</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1705</Code>
      <Text>BIOLOGY &amp; INFORMATION TECHNOLO</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7286</Code>
      <Text>BIOCOMPUTATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9125</Code>
      <Text>BIOTECHNOLOGY TRAINING &amp; CAREER DEVLPMNT</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>BIOT</Code>
      <Text>BIOTECHNOLOGY</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
