<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>ISE/PIs-Aging Network Partners Conference to be Convened in Washington, DC, in the Fall of 2005</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>07/15/2005</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>03/31/2007</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>248197</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>11090000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Research On Learning</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Mary Ann Steiner</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The SPRY Foundation is requesting funding to organize a conference that will include principal investigators from ISE projects and representatives of the Aging Network to identify strategies to engage older adults in infromal lerning. The conference will present and critique existing programs, discuss new and sustainable models, and encourage the development of a network of ISE providers and organizations that serve older adults. Deliverables include a conference report with recommendations, the "Guide to Including Older Adults in Informal Science Education Programs", post-conference publications and presentations at the Association of Science and Technology Centers Annual Conference and the Annual Meeting of the Southeastern Association of Area Agencies in Aging. Addtionaly, pre-conference surveys will inform the planning process for this innovative meeting.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>07/26/2005</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>09/22/2006</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0517906</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Russell</FirstName>
      <LastName>Morgan</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>morganr@spry.org</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/26/2005</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>SPRY (Setting Priorities for Retirement Years) Foundation</Name>
      <CityName>Chevy Chase</CityName>
      <ZipCode>208155224</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>3016563405</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>3916 Rosemary Street</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Maryland</StateName>
      <StateCode>MD</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0000099</Code>
      <Name>Other Applications NEC</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
