<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Pan-American Advanced Studies Institute on Transmission Electron Microscopy in Materials Science; Santiago, Chile, January 2006</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2005</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>02/28/2007</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>0.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>94000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>01090000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>O/D</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Office Of The Director</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>OISE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Office Of Internatl Science &amp;Engineering</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Harold Stolberg</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This Pan-American Advanced Studies Institutes (PASI) award jointly supported by the NSF and Department of Energy (DOE), will take place at the University of Chile, January 2006, in Santiago, Chile.  The institute, organized by Dr. J. A. Eades, Lehigh University, will consist of lectures, discussions and laboratory demonstrations, to cover the principles, practice and applications of the advanced characterization techniques available through the transmission electron microscope. In the last decade there have been many advances, both in the hardware and in the way in which the data are used, that have made the transmission electron microscope more powerful and more valuable. The Institute will focus on these advances in the context of the established basic principles of the instrument.   The Institute will also dedicate substantial effort to the applications that are supported by these techniques, especifically in the areas of material science and geology, to promote the development of electron microscopy throughout the Americas. It will provide a unique opportunity, not only to learn about the latest advances in the field, but also to establish and develop future collaborations.  &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The Institute will involve approximately 48 participants from the United States and Latin America, including graduate students and junior and established investigators, and about 11 instructors (internationally recognized scientists, active in the field).  Recruitment of students will be done through notices and meetings of various professional societies and local microscopy societies in several countries in Latin America. The goal is to provide both structured opportunities and unstructured time to develop strong and continuing bonds among the participants. The lectures presented at the Institute will be made available to the participants and to anyone else by posting them on the Institute web site.  The web site used will either form part of the InterAmerican Committee of Societies for Electron Microscopy (CIASEM) web site, or be linked to it. CIASEM is the regional organization of the International Federation of Societies for Microscopy and is the umbrella organization for microscopy in the Americas.    &lt;br/&gt; &lt;br/&gt; &lt;br/&gt;</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>09/02/2005</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>09/06/2006</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>0517801</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>John</FirstName>
<LastName>Eades</LastName>
<EmailAddress>jae5@lehigh.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>09/02/2005</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Lehigh University</Name>
<CityName>Bethlehem</CityName>
<ZipCode>180153005</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6107583021</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>Alumni Building 27</StreetAddress>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Pennsylvania</StateName>
<StateCode>PA</StateCode>
</Institution>
<FoaInformation>
<Code>0000099</Code>
<Name>Other Applications NEC</Name>
</FoaInformation>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1253</Code>
<Text>OFFICE OF MULTIDISCIPLINARY AC</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1385</Code>
<Text>SSA-Special Studies &amp; Analysis</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7275</Code>
<Text>Cross-BIO Activities</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>T102</Code>
<Text/>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>0000</Code>
<Text>UNASSIGNED</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>5974</Code>
<Text>CHILE</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>5977</Code>
<Text>AMERICAS PROGRAM</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>OTHR</Code>
<Text>OTHER RESEARCH OR EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
</Award>
</rootTag>
