<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Bivalve Richness and Ecological Diversity of the End-Triassic Mass Extinction: Faunal Analyses from the West-Tethyan Lombardy, La Spezia and K?ssen Basins (Italy and Austria)</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/15/2005</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2008</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>50900.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>50900</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>06030207</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>GEO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>EAR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Earth Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>H. Richard Lane</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Late Triassic extinctions are known to have severely affected many invertebrate and&lt;br/&gt;vertebrate taxa from the marine and non-marine realms; however, the precise timing,&lt;br/&gt;magnitude, and ultimate cause(s) of the biotic crisis remain poorly understood. Recently&lt;br/&gt;published and unpublished high-resolution isotope stratigraphy coupled with preliminary&lt;br/&gt;bivalve collections reveals an abundance of ecologically significant bivalves near an&lt;br/&gt;initial negative excursion in -13C and now permits precise correlation between nearly all&lt;br/&gt;known Triassic-Jurassic boundary sections. To understand better which organisms were&lt;br/&gt;affected and the sequence of events in the late Triassic, I propose research involving an&lt;br/&gt;analysis of taxonomic richness and paleoecology of Triassic-Jurassic bivalve faunas of&lt;br/&gt;the Lombardy, La Spezia and Kossen Basins of the western Tethys By virtue of their&lt;br/&gt;abundance and richness in Triassic/Jurassic boundary beds within these key sections,&lt;br/&gt;bivalve mollusks provide an ideal group with which to test hypotheses surrounding the&lt;br/&gt;tempo and mode of extinction. Two related hypotheses will be investigated: (i) following&lt;br/&gt;a period of ecologic stability, the end-Triassic bivalve extinction was both severe and&lt;br/&gt;abrupt; and (ii) bivalves within the extinction and early survival interval exhibit an&lt;br/&gt;ecologic pattern of selective extinction and survival. To address these questions, I&lt;br/&gt;propose intensive field and institutional based research to: (i) revise and develop new&lt;br/&gt;taxonomic data on latest Triassic through earliest Jurassic bivalve fauna from the western&lt;br/&gt;Tethyan realm; and (ii) to develop high-resolution paleoecologic and paleoenvironmental&lt;br/&gt;data from identified stratigraphic sections spanning the Triassic/Jurassic boundary from&lt;br/&gt;five critical sections identified from the Lombardy, La Spezia and Kossen Basins of Italy&lt;br/&gt;and Austria. A taxonomic revision of west-Tethyan bivalves, which will involve&lt;br/&gt;extensive institutional-based research at major European repositories, has never been&lt;br/&gt;attempted and is long overdue. Paleoecologic analyses will entail bed-by-bed analyses of&lt;br/&gt;boundary intervals in which abundance, diversity, and trophic data will be collected from&lt;br/&gt;statistically large samples combined with taphonomic and sedimentologic data within a&lt;br/&gt;high-resolution biochronologic and chemostratigraphic framework. This work will&lt;br/&gt;involve substantial new collaborations with scientists from Italy, Austria and The&lt;br/&gt;Netherlands with expertise in micropaleontology, palynology, stable isotope&lt;br/&gt;geochemistry and regional geology, The research will also actively involve&lt;br/&gt;undergraduate students, both as assistants and as independent researchers and provide for&lt;br/&gt;their training and preparation for future graduate studies. The work proposed here will&lt;br/&gt;have broad significance for the interpretation of biotic patterns surrounding the end-&lt;br/&gt;Triassic mass extinction. The expected outcome of a revised taxonomy of&lt;br/&gt;Rhaetian/Hettangian bivalves of the Kossen Basin will, after more than 100 years, finally&lt;br/&gt;provide sound base-line taxonomic data from which to test hypotheses surrounding the&lt;br/&gt;timing, magnitude, and mode of the end-Triassic extinction.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>09/13/2005</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>09/13/2005</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.050</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>0518605</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Christopher</FirstName>
<LastName>McRoberts</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>A</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Christopher A McRoberts</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>christopher.mcroberts@cortland.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6077532925</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000201719</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/13/2005</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>SUNY College at Cortland</Name>
<CityName>Cortland</CityName>
<CountyName>CORTLAND</CountyName>
<ZipCode>130452000</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6077532511</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>Research Foundation for SUNY</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[PO Box 2000]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>22</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NY22</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>090190591</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>RESEARCH FOUNDATION FOR THE STATE UNIVERSITY OF NEW YORK, THE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>020657151</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[SUNY College at Cortland]]></Name>
<CityName>Cortland</CityName>
<CountyName>CORTLAND</CountyName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<ZipCode>130452000</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[Research Foundation for SUNY]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>22</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NY22</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<FoaInformation>
<Code>0000099</Code>
<Name>Other Applications NEC</Name>
</FoaInformation>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7459</Code>
<Text>Sedimentary Geo &amp; Paleobiology</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>0000</Code>
<Text>UNASSIGNED</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>OTHR</Code>
<Text>OTHER RESEARCH OR EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0105</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>490100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2005~50900</FUND_OBLG>
</Award>
</rootTag>
