<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Design and Synthesis of Molecular Scaffolds with Defined Ligand Arrays</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2005</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2008</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardAmount>495042</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03090003</Code>
<Directorate>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<LongName>Division Of Chemistry</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Tyrone D. Mitchell</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The Organic and Macromolecular Chemistry Program supports Professor Jacquelyn Gervay-Hague at the University of California-Davis whose research will take a dual approach to the design and synthesis of molecular scaffolds with defined ligand arrays. Rationally designed constructs will be decorated with polyvalent ligand displays that will be structurally defined using common biophysical methods including CD, NH/ND exchange, and computational chemistry. In complementary studies, combinatorial libraries will be generated as molecular probes to establish the design features that are important in the molecular recognition events under study. At a fundamental level, the proposed studies will provide insight into how multivalent interactions translate into macromolecular structure and function. These innovations may lead to the development of new tools for studying biological recognition events and identification of potential candidates for novel chemotherapeutic interventions.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The Organic and Macromolecular Chemistry Program supports Professor Jacquelyn Gervay-Hague whose research will extend the research group's investigations of the synthesis and structural characterization of conformationally defined carbohydrate-based ligand materials and structures. &lt;br/&gt;Students engaged in the research will develop diverse and multidimensional skills. Organic synthesis (solid-phase and combinatorial techniques), advanced NMR techniques, circular dichroism, and computational chemistry are regularly implemented in Professor Gervay-Hague's research endeavors. Students and postdoctoral researchers will also receive extensive training in biochemistry, since the targeted materials are designed with biological applications in mind. These combined skills will provide a strong foundation for careers in the pharmaceutical industry and in research-oriented academic institutions.&lt;br/&gt;</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/25/2005</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>04/16/2007</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>0518010</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Jacquelyn</FirstName>
<LastName>Gervay-Hague</LastName>
<EmailAddress>jgervayhague@ucdavis.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>08/25/2005</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of California-Davis</Name>
<CityName>Davis</CityName>
<ZipCode>956186134</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5307547700</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>OR/Sponsored Programs</StreetAddress>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
</Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1942</Code>
<Text>UNIMOLECULAR PROCESSES</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1944</Code>
<Text>BIMOLECULAR PROCESSES</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>0000</Code>
<Text>UNASSIGNED</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9161</Code>
<Text>SINGLE DIVISION/UNIVERSITY</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9179</Code>
<Text>GRADUATE INVOLVEMENT</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9183</Code>
<Text>GENERAL FOUNDATIONS OF BIOTECHNOLOGY</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>BIOT</Code>
<Text>BIOTECHNOLOGY</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>OTHR</Code>
<Text>OTHER RESEARCH OR EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
</Award>
</rootTag>
