<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Collaborative Research: Testing Potential of Paired Lakes on the NE Tibetan Plateau for Studying Interaction Between Hydrochemical Evolution and Environmental Change</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/15/2005</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2008</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>48501.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>48501</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>06030205</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>GEO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>EAR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Earth Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Enriqueta Barrera</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>ebarrera@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927780</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The evolution of the chemical composition of lake waters is determined by the inflow waters and&lt;br/&gt;subsequent evaporative concentration and the precipitation of minerals. In closed-basin lakes, evaporative&lt;br/&gt;concentration is mostly determined by changes in aridity, as a result of regional climate change. However,&lt;br/&gt;the interactions among lake water and groundwater chemistries, lake sediment geochemistry, and&lt;br/&gt;environmental change have not been studied over short or long time scales, and seldom using&lt;br/&gt;multidisciplinary approach.&lt;br/&gt;Intellectual merits. This pilot study is to investigate paired chemically-contrasting lakes (fresh and&lt;br/&gt;saline) in the arid northeastern Tibetan Plateau. These lakes are likely to be ideal sites for the study of&lt;br/&gt;water isotopic and elemental evolution, and the interactions of environmental change and lacustrine&lt;br/&gt;geochemical processes. The overarching objective of the proposed study is to understand hydrochemical&lt;br/&gt;evolution and how it interacts with various environmental controls at different time scales. The added&lt;br/&gt;bonus for undertaking such a study in this climate-sensitive region near the northern limit of the East&lt;br/&gt;Asian monsoon is to improve our ability to read the lacustrine sediment record of this region to better&lt;br/&gt;understand the past environmental changes. We propose to use a multidisciplinary approach to investigate&lt;br/&gt;at regional and watershed scales, the modern processes in these two lakes, history of solute and water flux&lt;br/&gt;from mineralogy and chemical and isotopic composition of authigenic and biogenic minerals, and from&lt;br/&gt;species assemblage of ostracodes and the history of climate and environmental change from such records&lt;br/&gt;of landscape processes as pollen, plant macrofossils, and environmental magnetism.&lt;br/&gt;The results from this project will provide insights into understanding the pathways and mechanisms of&lt;br/&gt;lake solute evolution and water flux and how they affect the sedimentary record of past environmental&lt;br/&gt;changes. This is the first study to employ a multidisciplinary approach to address the lake-climate&lt;br/&gt;interactions in Central Asia. A key feature of this project is in its use of paired limnologically- and&lt;br/&gt;chemically-contrasting lakes in order to unravel the interactions between lacustrine hydrologic and&lt;br/&gt;hydrochemical processes and environmental (and climatic) changes. The study of modern responses of&lt;br/&gt;the dilute lake (Keluke Lake) with a saline Lake (Toson Lake) will enable comprehensive and robust&lt;br/&gt;reconstructions of paleohydrochemistry. Also, the multiple techniques used in the proposed study will&lt;br/&gt;provide independent records of regional climate change, watershed stability and vegetation, as well as&lt;br/&gt;changes in lake chemistry. Integration of these records will allow us to focus on the complex interactions&lt;br/&gt;and feedbacks between these processes at different temporal scales (from present-day to interglacialglacial&lt;br/&gt;cycles).&lt;br/&gt;Broader impacts. Our interdisciplinary research will advance the understanding of complex interactions&lt;br/&gt;in these systems under different climate regimes. Understanding the lake and watershed responses to&lt;br/&gt;climate change of the past will contribute to our ability to predict the environmental consequences of&lt;br/&gt;climate (especially monsoon) variations and variability. Our approach of using contrasting&lt;br/&gt;hydrochemistries of paired fresh and saline lakes is not commonly employed but we believe is a very&lt;br/&gt;instructive one with a large pay-off. Understanding the hydrological dynamics will benefit the people in&lt;br/&gt;this remote arid part of China in adapting to the potential future changes in climate and hydrological&lt;br/&gt;cycles. The results will be compared with the response of lakes in the semi-arid northern Great Plains to&lt;br/&gt;climate and hydrololgic changes and shared with the state geological surveys and water commissions.&lt;br/&gt;Once past the pilot-stage, graduate and undergraduate students will be more fully involved in the project&lt;br/&gt;and will benefit from interacting with an international multidisciplinary research team. The project will&lt;br/&gt;facilitate collaborations, especially with our Chinese colleagues, who are having increased impacts in the&lt;br/&gt;international scene of science and technology.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/31/2005</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/31/2005</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.050</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>0519255</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Emi</FirstName>
<LastName>Ito</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Emi Ito</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>eito@umn.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6126247881</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000316082</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/31/2005</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Minnesota-Twin Cities</Name>
<CityName>Minneapolis</CityName>
<CountyName>HENNEPIN</CountyName>
<ZipCode>554552070</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6126245599</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>200 OAK ST SE</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Minnesota</StateName>
<StateCode>MN</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MN05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>555917996</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>REGENTS OF THE UNIVERSITY OF MINNESOTA</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>117178941</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Minnesota-Twin Cities]]></Name>
<CityName>Minneapolis</CityName>
<CountyName>HENNEPIN</CountyName>
<StateCode>MN</StateCode>
<ZipCode>554552070</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[200 OAK ST SE]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Minnesota</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MN05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<FoaInformation>
<Code>0000099</Code>
<Name>Other Applications NEC</Name>
</FoaInformation>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7295</Code>
<Text>Geobiology &amp; Low-Temp Geochem</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>0000</Code>
<Text>UNASSIGNED</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>OTHR</Code>
<Text>OTHER RESEARCH OR EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0105</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>490100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2005~48501</FUND_OBLG>
</Award>
</rootTag>
