<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>SBIR Phase II: Development of Smart Material Using Natural Fiber Reinforced Composite</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2005</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2009</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>604052</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07070000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Industrial Innovation &amp; Partnersh</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Cheryl F. Albus</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This Small Business Innovation Research (SBIR) Phase II project proposes to develop a suitable prototype based on the Active-Passive Natural Fiber Composite (APNFC0), the technical feasibility of which was demonstrated in the Phase I program. This innovative composite material concept is bio-based and hence environmentally friendly. The APNFC has excellent vibration and noise mitigation properties and can be used to control acoustic noise and structural vibrations in a wide variety of noisy environments. The unique design of this composite material will reduce noise transmission over a broad band of frequencies through a combination of absorption and dissipation phenomena. The prototype to be built during Phase II will consist of a thermoformed sandwiched material configuration where a polymer-based piezoelectric layer (PVdF) is formed between two passive layers composed of variable density natural fiber composite (VDNFC). This material will have an embedded control system with amplifiers and power supplies.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The commercial applications of the new technology include: home appliances, soundproof architectural doors, office furniture, operator cabins for agricultural and construction machinery, building materials, automobiles, and aircraft cabins. Collectively, these represent a multi-billion dollar market for parts and products to which the present core technology can be applied. The company has a focus commercialization plan with strategic partner support in the appliance application and the office and construction applications</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>07/29/2005</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>09/17/2007</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0521905</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Christopher</FirstName>
      <LastName>Whitmer</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>chris.whitmer.vsi@gmail.com</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/29/2005</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>VIBROACOUSTICS SOLUTIONS INC</Name>
      <CityName>BOONE</CityName>
      <ZipCode>500367003</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>5154508997</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>2205 229TH PLACE</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Iowa</StateName>
      <StateCode>IA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0308000</Code>
      <Name>Industrial Technology</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
