<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>MRI: Acquisition of a Scanning Laser Vibrometer for Smart-Structures Research</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/15/2005</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2006</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>199000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07030000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Civil, Mechanical, &amp; Manufact Inn</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Richard J. Fragaszy</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>ABSTRACT&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;ACQUISITION OF A SCANNING LASER VIBROMETER FOR&lt;br/&gt;SMART-STRUCTURES RESEARCH&lt;br/&gt;Ratneshwar Jha, Department of Mechanical and Aeronautical Engineering&lt;br/&gt;Goodarz Ahmadi, Department of Mechanical and Aeronautical Engineering&lt;br/&gt;Pier Marzocca, Department of Mechanical and Aeronautical Engineering&lt;br/&gt;Edward Sazonov, Department of Electrical and Computer Engineering&lt;br/&gt;Jubum Kim, Department of Civil and Environmental Engineering&lt;br/&gt;Clarkson University, Potsdam, NY&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;PROJECT SUMMARY&lt;br/&gt;Intellectual Merit&lt;br/&gt;The objective of this proposal is to acquire a high performance scanning laser vibrometer&lt;br/&gt;(SLV). The SLV will 1) provide new and unique experimental capabilities for smart-structures (and other structural) research, 2) enhance collaborative research across academic departments, 3) provide state-of-the-art instrumentation for training of graduate/undergraduate students, and 4) help recruitment of students from underrepresented groups. The SLV is based on the principle of the detection of the Doppler shift of coherent laser light that is scattered from a small area of the test object. Entire surfaces are rapidly scanned and automatically probed with flexible and&lt;br/&gt;interactively created scan grids. The SLV performs nonintrusive measurement of vibrations at a large number of grid points without adding mass or stiffness to the test structure. The observation of the mode shapes and spatial features of the vibration is not conveniently possible without a scanning laser vibrometer. The proposed SLV is a single, automated, turnkey system that offers all the advantages of a laser vibrometer integrated with the speed, ease of use, accuracy and comprehensive data processing and visualization of a dual-axis laser scanner.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Broader Impacts&lt;br/&gt;The SLV will add advanced experimental capabilities to modernize the Smart Structures&lt;br/&gt;Laboratory at Clarkson University, which serves many innovative, multidisciplinary research and education projects. The proposed research will have very significant impact on the design of aerospace, mechanical, and civil systems. The planned research will advance the knowledge of dynamics &amp; control of highly flexible structures such as Gossamer Spacecraft, inflatable unmanned aerial vehicles, and thin spinning disks for data storage devices. Health monitoring of civil infrastructures (bridges and buildings) and aircraft structures will also be investigated. The measurement features of a SLV are critical to the success of the planned innovative research activities. Presentations at technical conferences, journal papers, and web pages will be used to disseminate the research results widely. The SLV will enhance experiential project-based learning programs to attract women and minority students. Both graduate and undergraduate students will gain experience with state-of-the-art laser based vibrations measurement techniques. The SLV will positively impact outreach to the K-12 community of students and teachers through laboratory demonstrations and web site displays.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/10/2005</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>08/10/2005</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0521217</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Jubum</FirstName>
      <LastName>Kim</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>jkim@clarkson.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/10/2005</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Ratneshwar</FirstName>
      <LastName>Jha</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>rjha@clarkson.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/10/2005</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Edward</FirstName>
      <LastName>Sazonov</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>esazonov@clarkson.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/10/2005</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Pier</FirstName>
      <LastName>Marzocca</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>pmarzocc@clarkson.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/10/2005</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Goodarz</FirstName>
      <LastName>Ahmadi</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>ahmadi@clarkson.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/10/2005</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Clarkson University</Name>
      <CityName>Potsdam</CityName>
      <ZipCode>136761401</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>3152686475</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>8 Clarkson Avenue</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>New York</StateName>
      <StateCode>NY</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0308000</Code>
      <Name>Industrial Technology</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1189</Code>
      <Text>MAJOR RESEARCH INSTRUMENTATION</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1057</Code>
      <Text>CIS BASE RESEARCH</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>CVIS</Code>
      <Text>CIVIL INFRASTRUCTURE</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
