<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>MRI:  Development of a Deposition System for 3D Patterning of Molecular Materials in Vacuum</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2005</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2010</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>0.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>493414</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03070006</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DMR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Materials Research</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Charles E. Bouldin</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The proposed device is a standard vacuum flange compatible electrospray-based deposition unit ("MoleculeWriter"), capable of patterned deposition of molecular materials directly from solution in vacuum. The device utilizes the electrospray principle to inject molecular materials into high vacuum. Since electrospray generates an ionized molecular beam focusing and deflection by electromagnetic means becomes possible. This property will be used to generate a well-defined beam that can be directed to certain locations on the substrate, i.e. three-dimensional patterning becomes possible. Through computer control, arbitrary patterns can be generated. The materials that can be deposited with this system encompass a wide range of molecular entities as different in properties as luminescent polymers, proteins, functionalized nano-crystals, oligonucleotides, or supra-molecular species. The vacuum capability will enable fast solvent removal (i.e. prevent droplet related drying artifacts), precisely controlled, contamination-free deposition, and compatibility with established vacuum based deposition techniques (e.g. for metals and insulators) and surface preparation methods. Intersolubility issues will be dramatically reduced due to the vacuum environment, enabling the controlled deposition of three-dimensional multi-layered structures of materials soluble in the same solvent.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The proposed program will focus on the simulation and construction of a system of suitable ion-optics to focus and deflect an electrospray injected molecular ion beam, the building of a prototype of the patterning device, its optimization, and the demonstration of its capabilities on a variety of molecular materials. It is planned to initially commercialize the device as an add-on system to existing vacuum equipment.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The proposed work aims at the design and implementation of a device, which will be able to arrange nano-materials into well-defined three-dimensional structures on substrates. In order to utilize the special properties of nano-materials, methods need to be found to make structures from them, allowing the manufacture of nano-technology devices with practical uses, such as sensors or electronics. The proposed device will enable the patterning of nano-materials on a substrate in vacuum directly from a solution. The device will utilize the electrospray principle, to create a charged beam of the molecules separated from the solvent. The charges on the molecules can be used to focus and deflect the beam using electric and magnetic fields, so that the beam can be used to paint a defined pattern on a substrate in much the same way that an elctron beam paints a picture on a television screen. The proposed work will focus on the design and construction of a prototype of such a device, and its optimization and demonstration.&lt;br/&gt;</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/02/2005</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/11/2006</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>0521484</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Rudiger</FirstName>
<LastName>Schlaf</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Rudiger Schlaf</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>schlaf@eng.usf.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>8139748463</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000418793</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/02/2005</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>John</FirstName>
<LastName>Anthony</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>M</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>John M Anthony</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>anthony@elionsystems.com</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5122634617</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000150123</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/02/2005</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of South Florida</Name>
<CityName>Tampa</CityName>
<CountyName>HILLSBOROUGH</CountyName>
<ZipCode>336172008</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>8139742897</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>4019 E. Fowler Avenue</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2>Suite 100</StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Florida</StateName>
<StateCode>FL</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>14</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>FL14</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>069687242</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF SOUTH FLORIDA</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>069687242</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name>University of South Florida</Name>
<CityName>Tampa</CityName>
<CountyName>HILLSBOROUGH</CountyName>
<StateCode>FL</StateCode>
<ZipCode>336172008</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress>4019 E. Fowler Avenue</StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Florida</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>14</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>FL14</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<FoaInformation>
<Code>0106000</Code>
<Name>Materials Research</Name>
</FoaInformation>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1189</Code>
<Text>Major Research Instrumentation</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1712</Code>
<Text>DMR SHORT TERM SUPPORT</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1750</Code>
<Text>MPS DMR INSTRUMENTATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9161</Code>
<Text>SINGLE DIVISION/UNIVERSITY</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9251</Code>
<Text>REU SUPP-Res Exp for Ugrd Supp</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>AMPP</Code>
<Text>ADVANCED MATERIALS &amp; PROCESSING PROGRAM</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0105</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>490100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0106</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>490100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2005~481414</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2006~12000</FUND_OBLG>
</Award>
</rootTag>
