<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Processing and Evaluation of HA Nanocomposites</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/15/2005</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>01/31/2008</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>390000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>390000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CMMI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Civil, Mechanical, &amp; Manufact Inn</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>george hazelrigg</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This interdisciplinary project involves engineering faculty with nanomanufacturing and bioengineering backgrounds in an effort to gain fundamental understanding of the behavior of nanocrystalline ceramics for biomedical applications. The project's central focus is to develop nanocrystalline ceramic matrices with properties superior to those currently available and to test them in vitro for their utility as dental/maxillofacial implants. The main theme of the project is to fabricate nanocrystalline hydroxyapatite (n-HA) and tricalcium phosphate (TCP) nanocomposites in a graded structure. Such a structure is expected to make them more bio-active. The as- manufactured materials will be characterized in terms of phase content, microstructure, both short- and long-term mechanical reliability, and biocompatibility. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The project incorporates two vital technologies of the new millennium: biotechnology and nanotechnology. It is believed that the project will pervade many different strata of the society. While the targeted use will be in dentistry, the technology is broad enough for applications in other fields. This is particularly important in view 6fthe aging of the 'baby Boomer" population. From an educational viewpoint, the project will further enhance the pedagogical activities in the area of Biomaterials. The P .1. and the Co-P .1. are actively working with the local school districts, and undergraduate institutions (notably an HBCU) nearby. These activities include mentoring students during summer months through research activities and presenting guest lectures at schools.  A new teacher-training program is also contemplated. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/09/2005</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/09/2005</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>0522057</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Sarit</FirstName>
<LastName>Bhaduri</LastName>
<EmailAddress>sarit.bhaduri@utoledo.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>08/09/2005</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Martine</FirstName>
<LastName>LaBerge</LastName>
<EmailAddress>laberge@clemson.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>08/09/2005</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Clemson University</Name>
<CityName>CLEMSON</CityName>
<ZipCode>296345701</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>8646562424</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>230 Kappa Street</StreetAddress>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>South Carolina</StateName>
<StateCode>SC</StateCode>
</Institution>
<FoaInformation>
<Code>0308000</Code>
<Name>Industrial Technology</Name>
</FoaInformation>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1788</Code>
<Text>NANOMANUFACTURING</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9146</Code>
<Text>MANUFACTURING BASE RESEARCH</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>MANU</Code>
<Text>MANUFACTURING</Text>
</ProgramReference>
</Award>
</rootTag>
