<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Microbial Genome Sequencing: The Genome Sequence of Phytopthora Infestans</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>11/01/2005</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>10/31/2008</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>0.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>1898104</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>08070000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>BIO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>MCB</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Molecular and Cellular Bioscience</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Matthew Kane</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Phytophthora infestans, the cause of late blight of potato, is notorious as the agent of the Irish Potato Famine. Late blight remains a significant agricultural problem. Worldwide, P.infestans causes over $5 billion in annual losses in potato production alone, making it the single greatest pathogen threat to global food security. The goal of this project is to produce a high quality genome sequence of P. infestans and make it maximally useful to researchers working to control this pathogen. This will include identification of the genes, improvement of data to support genetic studies, tools for viewing and accessing the genome and genes, and development of education, training and outreach programs centered on this program and its findings. Importantly, all data generated will be promptly released in public databases.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;A genome sequence is the key resource to understanding the biology of an organism at the molecular level. Historically, the availability of a genome sequence of an organism has had an immediate and transforming effect on research into its biology, leading to an explosion of research and discovery. The extraordinary progress that has followed the release of the human and Arabidopsis genomes sequences are notable examples of this. With the P. infestans genome sequence in hand, it will be possible to: &lt;br/&gt;o  Prepare a list of the genes of the organism&lt;br/&gt;o  Study the function of its genes, and do so in a the context of a complete gene set&lt;br/&gt;o  Compare this genome to the genomes of related sequenced organisms to find genes and other elements conserved through evolution and to look for critical differences&lt;br/&gt;o  Identify gene targets for potential fungicides or other control agents&lt;br/&gt;o  Better understand key aspects of pathogenicity, including plant infection, host specificity and reproduction.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The remarkable historical and contemporary impact of P. infestans offers unique opportunities in outreach and training. Outreach activities will include organizing a series of workshops on "forensic pathogen DNA from the Irish potato famine" in partnership with high schools and museums, integrating P.infestans economics into online teaching curricula, and developing a mobile exhibit on the potato famine pathogen. In addition, results from the sequencing project will be incorporated into classes at the undergraduate and graduate levels.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project is being supported through a collaboration of the National Science Foundation and the National Research Initiative of the Cooperative Research, Education, and Extension Service of the Department of Agriculture.  &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>09/15/2005</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/24/2008</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>0523670</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>William</FirstName>
<LastName>Fry</LastName>
<EmailAddress>wef1@cornell.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>09/15/2005</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Howard</FirstName>
<LastName>Judelson</LastName>
<EmailAddress>howard.judelson@ucr.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>09/15/2005</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Jean</FirstName>
<LastName>Ristaino</LastName>
<EmailAddress>Jean_Ristaino@ncsu.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>09/15/2005</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Harris</FirstName>
<LastName>Nusbaum</LastName>
<EmailAddress>chad@genome.wi.mit.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>09/15/2005</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Sophien</FirstName>
<LastName>Kamoun</LastName>
<EmailAddress>sophien.kamoun@tsl.ac.uk</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>09/15/2005</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Massachusetts Institute of Technology</Name>
<CityName>Cambridge</CityName>
<ZipCode>021394301</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6172531000</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>77 MASSACHUSETTS AVE</StreetAddress>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
<StateCode>MA</StateCode>
</Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1629</Code>
<Text>BE: NON-ANNOUNCEMENT RESEARCH</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7187</Code>
<Text>MICROBIAL GENOME SEQUENCING</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1228</Code>
<Text>MINORITY INVOLVEMENT -- BIO</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1629</Code>
<Text>BE: Non-Announcement Research</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7187</Code>
<Text>MICROBIAL GENOME SEQUENCING</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7218</Code>
<Text>RET SUPP-Res Exp for Tchr Supp</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9109</Code>
<Text>AGRICULTURAL BIOTECHNOLOGY</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9178</Code>
<Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9183</Code>
<Text>GENERAL FOUNDATIONS OF BIOTECHNOLOGY</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9251</Code>
<Text>REU SUPP-Res Exp for Ugrd Supp</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>BIOT</Code>
<Text>BIOTECHNOLOGY</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>SMET</Code>
<Text>SCIENCE, MATH, ENG &amp; TECH EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
</Award>
</rootTag>
