<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Collaborative Research:  Zooplankton in the Redoxcline of the Cariaco Basin: Impact on Biogeochemical Cycling</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2006</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2011</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>0.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>339204</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>06040301</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>GEO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>OCE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Ocean Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>David Garrison</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>&lt;br/&gt;The CARIACO (CArbon Retention In A Colored Ocean) Program is a time-series programs, with the central goal to better understand seasonal to decadal time-scales of processes governing ocean biogeochemistry.  The CARIACO site is situated in the tropics on a productive continental margin off Venezuela, the basin is anoxic, and the site is strongly connected to paleoclimate investigations.  Thus, CARIACO has the additional goal of relating modern oceanographic processes with the production, transformation, and preservation of particulate matter in the sediment record. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Zooplankton composition, behavior, and physiological rates are important components of the biological pump.  Recent findings from the Cariaco Basin and other regions with pelagic redoxclines (suboxic and anoxic interfaces) suggest that they are active regions of biogeochemical cycling, in which C may be directly transferred from bacterial production to zooplankton grazers. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The goals of this project are to determine the vertical and horizontal distributions of zooplankton in relation to the redoxcline during two seasons using discrete-depth net samples and a vertical-profiling laser-line scan camera system. Anaerobic and aerobic respiration and metabolites, excretion, and egestion rates will be experimentally determined for vertical migrators and resident species nearsurface and at suboxic and anoxic depths to determine whether zooplankton differ in their release of metabolic and egested products, due to differences in their metabolism and/or composition of food resources. Grazing experiments, in combination with lipid biomarkers and stable isotopic compositions, will be used to assess in situ diet and long-term feeding history of zooplankton. Fecal pellet composition will be compared with pellets in sediment traps. Time-series zooplankton samples also will be analyzed to obtain temporal information on zooplankton community dynamics and allow a seasonal estimate of the zooplankton contribution to elemental fluxes. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Intellectual Merit. One of the grand challenges of oceanography is to understand the processes that control the transformation and fate of organic carbon in marine systems. Meeting this challenge is hindered by a lack of basic information about factors that govern the response of biological activity to environmental forcing and climate change. In particular, the role of the marine biosphere in the global carbon cycle remains poorly constrained, in part due to uncertainties about biological controls on the quality and quantity of carbon export. This project will contribute to our knowledge of the role of mesozooplankton in biogeochemical cycles, especially in relation to how processes may be modified in regions with anoxic or suboxic layers and strong redox gradients, and will help to correctly understand the links between water column processes and climate history as recorded in the varved sediments of the Cariaco Basin. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Broader Impacts.   The zooplankton time-series will provide information on patterns of marine biodiversity and ecological interactions from a poorly known region. The CARIACO Program has an ongoing impact in technology transfer and human resource development in Venezuela. This project will help train personnel in Venezuela and will support several graduate students. The lead investigators and students will develop materials on the project for dissemination through the NSF-Center for Ocean Science Education Excellence (COSEE) located at USF.  &lt;br/&gt;</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>09/14/2005</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>11/07/2005</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.050</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>0526545</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Kendra</FirstName>
<LastName>Daly</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>L</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Kendra L Daly</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>kdaly@mail.usf.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>7275531041</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000111546</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/14/2005</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of South Florida</Name>
<CityName>Tampa</CityName>
<CountyName>HILLSBOROUGH</CountyName>
<ZipCode>336172008</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>8139742897</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>4019 E. Fowler Avenue</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2>Suite 100</StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Florida</StateName>
<StateCode>FL</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>14</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>FL14</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>069687242</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF SOUTH FLORIDA</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>069687242</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name>University of South Florida</Name>
<CityName>Tampa</CityName>
<CountyName>HILLSBOROUGH</CountyName>
<StateCode>FL</StateCode>
<ZipCode>336172008</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress>4019 E. Fowler Avenue</StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Florida</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>14</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>FL14</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<FoaInformation>
<Code>0204000</Code>
<Name>Oceanography</Name>
</FoaInformation>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1650</Code>
<Text>BIOLOGICAL OCEANOGRAPHY</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1389</Code>
<Text>CARBON CYCLE RESEARCH</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>EGCH</Code>
<Text>ENVIRONMENT AND GLOBAL CHANGE</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0105</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>490100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2005~339204</FUND_OBLG>
</Award>
</rootTag>
