<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Visualizing and Exploring High-dimensional Data</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2006</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2010</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>0.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>325419</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>05020000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>CSE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>IIS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Information &amp; Intelligent Systems</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Maria Zemankova</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The aim of this project is to develop new methods for interactively exploring relationships within large high-dimensional data sets, such as those typical of high-throughput scientific experiments. The resulting tools will provide an aid to scientists prior to applying traditional offline data-analysis techniques such as clustering, segmentation, and classification. Scientists will be able to explore hypotheses and incorporate their own knowledge to drive traditional unsupervised data-mining algorithms in sensible and more promising directions. The visualization tools will assist scientist in many disciplines, including biologists in studying gene function, medical doctors in comprehending disease susceptibility, chemists in developing candidate drugs, and high-energy physics in analyzing the data generated by particle accelerators. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;A key component of the novel approach is the ability to interactively explore parameter spaces and combine attributes of high-dimensional data points. The visualization tool will provide two alternate views of the data sets: a dissimilarity-matrix view that offers insights into the size, compactness, separation, and relative proximity of clusters, and a point-cloud view that provides a 3-D projection of the high-dimensional source data that best preserve the distance between points. This dual-view approach excels in communicating the flow and migrations of points from one cluster to another as parameters are tuned. It also allows the user to probe and interact with the data, including such tasks as hand clustering the data, and examining particular points. The resulting visualization tools will support dynamic cluster formation and migration as the contributions of various data set features are interactively modified. The project provides an excellent interdisciplinary education and research environment, and the collaborative nature of the project also enhances the potential for results dissemination. The project Web site (http://cs.unc.edu/~tynia/HiDimViewer/index.html) provides access to publications and visualization tools.  &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/17/2006</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/19/2009</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>0534580</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Leonard</FirstName>
<LastName>McMillan</LastName>
<EmailAddress>mcmillan@cs.unc.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>08/17/2006</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Wei</FirstName>
<LastName>Wang</LastName>
<EmailAddress>weiwang@cs.ucla.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>08/17/2006</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill</Name>
<CityName>CHAPEL HILL</CityName>
<ZipCode>275991350</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>9199663411</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>104 AIRPORT DR STE 2200</StreetAddress>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>North Carolina</StateName>
<StateCode>NC</StateCode>
</Institution>
<FoaInformation>
<Code>0104000</Code>
<Name>Information Systems</Name>
</FoaInformation>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>6855</Code>
<Text>INFORMATION &amp; KNOWLEDGE MANAGE</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7364</Code>
<Text>Info Integration &amp; Informatics</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>6855</Code>
<Text>INFORMATION &amp; KNOWLEDGE MANAGE</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7496</Code>
<Text>COLLABORATIVE SYSTEMS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9216</Code>
<Text>ADVANCED SOFTWARE TECH &amp; ALGOR</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9218</Code>
<Text>BASIC RESEARCH &amp; HUMAN RESORCS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9251</Code>
<Text>REU SUPP-Res Exp for Ugrd Supp</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>HPCC</Code>
<Text>HIGH PERFORMANCE COMPUTING &amp; COMM</Text>
</ProgramReference>
</Award>
</rootTag>
