<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Addition of Low-Field FT-NMR and FT-IR Spectroscopy for the Enhancement of the Chemistry Laboratory Curriculum</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>02/01/2006</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>01/31/2009</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>89528.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>89528</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>11040200</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>EHR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DUE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Undergraduate Education</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Bert Holmes</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>&lt;br/&gt;Chemistry (12)&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Spectroscopic analysis of compounds, critical for the comprehension of how molecular structure determines the chemical properties of matter, is used extensively in chemistry. The Chemistry faculty are adapting experiments from multiple sources and are enhancing the chemistry program curricula to include hands-on spectroscopic instrumentation, namely nuclear magnetic resonance, NMR (1H and 13C), and infrared spectroscopy, FT-IR. The inclusion of spectroscopy at all levels of chemistry classes encourages students to learn proper handling of scientific instruments for data collection early in their academic careers, developing analytical, problem solving, and critical thinking skills necessary for transfer to four-year institutions. The general chemistry and the non-major students learn to identify functional groups, differentiate between structural isomers, and determine product structures. Students in organic chemistry use these instruments for structure characterization of synthesized products, stereochemistry determination from coupling constants, and identification of unknown organic compounds. Above all, our students are developing the skills to relate theoretical concepts to practical observations with the inclusion of spectroscopy in the laboratory curriculum. Spectroscopy workshops for high school science teachers are being held to provide them with professional development and continuing education opportunities. This encourages chemistry teachers to incorporate topics on spectroscopy into the high school curriculum.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>01/23/2006</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>01/23/2006</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>0535624</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Sumita</FirstName>
<LastName>Singh</LastName>
<EmailAddress>ssingh@everettcc.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>01/23/2006</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Karl</FirstName>
<LastName>Bailey</LastName>
<EmailAddress>kbailey@everettcc.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>01/23/2006</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Anne</FirstName>
<LastName>Brackett</LastName>
<EmailAddress>abrackett@everettcc.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>01/23/2006</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Everett Community College</Name>
<CityName>Everett</CityName>
<ZipCode>982011390</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>4253889389</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>2000 Tower</StreetAddress>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Washington</StateName>
<StateCode>WA</StateCode>
</Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7494</Code>
<Text>CCLI-Type 1 (Exploratory)</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9178</Code>
<Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>SMET</Code>
<Text>SCIENCE, MATH, ENG &amp; TECH EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
</Award>
</rootTag>
