<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Finite Element Simulation of Laboratory Experiments for Enhanced Learning</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>02/01/2006</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>01/31/2010</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>129995.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>129995</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>11040200</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>EHR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DUE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Undergraduate Education</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Don Millard</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Engineering - Chemical (53)&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This proposal is answering several questions regarding the use of simulated laboratory experiments and learning.  By developing finite element models of chemical engineering laboratory experiments, the PIs are investigating discovery versus tutorial use of the simulations and examining the impact on student learning.  In the tutorial mode, the students execute a prescribed set of simulations and are given explanations of the results they are observing.  In the discovery mode, the students are using the simulations, generating computer-experiment results that they are analyzing in a pre-lab study, similar to how they treat laboratory experimental results.  Students are playing with the model and discovering what is happening in the experimental system.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;FEMLABTM is being used in model development, allowing modeling of multiple physical processes that are occurring simultaneously.  Teams of seniors are developing some of the models as part of their senior thesis project.  This is allowing the PIs to investigate the importance of students constructing their own simulations, versus using previously developed models.  The PIs are gaining insight into how and where to introduce finite element modeling into the undergraduate curriculum.  Additionally they are learning whether or not computer simulation is an appropriate replacement for hands on laboratory experience.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The project is evaluating enhanced student learning using a pre- and post-lab test developed specifically for each experiment.  Course evaluations, interviews and surveys of students is providing qualitative evaluation.  Results are being disseminated though ASEE and FIE conference publications.&lt;br/&gt;</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>02/03/2006</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>02/03/2006</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>0536342</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>David</FirstName>
<LastName>DiBiasio</LastName>
<EmailAddress>dibiasio@wpi.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>02/03/2006</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>William</FirstName>
<LastName>Clark</LastName>
<EmailAddress>wmclark@wpi.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>02/03/2006</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Worcester Polytechnic Institute</Name>
<CityName>WORCESTER</CityName>
<ZipCode>016092247</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5088315000</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>100 INSTITUTE RD</StreetAddress>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
<StateCode>MA</StateCode>
</Institution>
<FoaInformation>
<Code>0116000</Code>
<Name>Human Subjects</Name>
</FoaInformation>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7494</Code>
<Text>CCLI-Type 1 (Exploratory)</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9178</Code>
<Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>SMET</Code>
<Text>SCIENCE, MATH, ENG &amp; TECH EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
</Award>
</rootTag>
