<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>STTR Phase I: Robust Organic Light-Emitting Diodes (OLED) Displays using Self-Assembled MonoLayers</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>01/01/2006</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2007</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>97620</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07070000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Industrial Innovation &amp; Partnersh</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>William Haines</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The Small Business Technology Transfer (STTR) Phase I project will demonstrate the feasibility of using self-assembled mono-layers to dramatically improve the cost performance of OLED displays. The OLED industry is interested in p-i-n structured OLEDs because they can be fully printed in open-air conditions on flexible barrier substrates through the use of air-stable printable electrodes; however, these displays suffer from slow switching speeds and shortened lifetimes. The intellectual merit of this proposal is focused on stabilizing the p-i-n junction architecture for OLED devices using self-assembled mono-layers (SAM). This effort will focus on developing the materials and processes for depositing the SAM layer that specifically overcomes the weaknesses of current p-i-n displays caused by the mobility of the dopants responsible for the p and n-type doping, and to dramatically improve the efficiency, lifetime, switching speed, and printability of LEP devices onto flexible substrates. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The broader impact of this proposal will be the creation of a significant technology and print-based manufacturing platform that will accelerate the use of OLED displays and photovoltaics in the low cost, large-area optoelectronic markets. Such technology is expected to provide low cost, flexible displays and could have a direct impact on other printable electronics, such as organic transistors and memory, where low cost manufacturing of high efficiency devices are paramount for commercial success.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>11/10/2005</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>12/14/2006</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0539802</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Jian Ping</FirstName>
      <LastName>Chen</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>jianpc@add-vision.com</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>11/10/2005</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Add-vision, Incorporated</Name>
      <CityName>Scotts Valley</CityName>
      <ZipCode>950664945</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>8314388192</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>1600 Green Hills Rd. Suite #100</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>California</StateName>
      <StateCode>CA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0110000</Code>
      <Name>Technology Transfer</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
