<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>SGER: Volume Comparisons</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2005</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>02/28/2007</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>55000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>05010000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division of Computing and Communication Foundations</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Lawrence Rosenblum</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Volume data is a vital part of many types of scientific and medical inquiry. Volume visualization has provided tools to help scientists examine volume data: methods exist for display of massive datasets and to display moderate datasets interactively using commodity hardware. Synthetic appearance methods to provide fake lighting and stylized (e.g. non-photorealistic) rendering methods help make complex shapes easier to comprehend. However, all of these advances focus on tools to help a scientist examine a single volumetric dataset.&lt;br/&gt;There is a need for tools that explicitly help scientists make visual comparisons among volume datasets. For example, a scientist may need to find differences between two specimens or to look for trends in a sequence of volumes. The need for such tools will grow as the throughput of data generation increases: the proliferation of scanning means more specimens will be scanned; noninvasive imaging techniques allow for series of scans over the development of an animal; and grid-based supercomputing allows for large numbers of independent simulations to be run.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>09/08/2005</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>03/15/2006</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0540653</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Michael</FirstName>
      <LastName>Gleicher</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>gleicher@cs.wisc.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>09/08/2005</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Wisconsin-Madison</Name>
      <CityName>MADISON</CityName>
      <ZipCode>537151218</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>6082623822</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>21 North Park Street</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Wisconsin</StateName>
      <StateCode>WI</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0000912</Code>
      <Name>Computer Science</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
