<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Seismic Indicators of Time-Varying Deep Deformation along the Central San Andreas Fault</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2006</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2008</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>55474.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>55474</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>06030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>GEO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>EAR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Earth Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Kaye Shedlock</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>0544730&lt;br/&gt;Nadeau&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Seismic Indicators of Time-Varying Deep Deformation along the Central San Andreas Fault&lt;br/&gt;Understanding the time-varying deformation field of plate bounding fault zones at great depth&lt;br/&gt;is important for understanding active tectonics, fault-fault interactions and the occurrence of&lt;br/&gt;large earthquakes. However, measurements of large-scale time-varying deep deformation along&lt;br/&gt;vertical strike-slip plate boundaries such as the San Andreas Fault have been difficult to obtain,&lt;br/&gt;due to the limited extent, coverage and sampling frequency of geodetic measurements and the&lt;br/&gt;fundamental trade-offs and assumptions required to infer deep deformation on vertical faults from measurements of surface motion.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;To more clearly understand the role of deep transient deformation along the San Andreas&lt;br/&gt;Fault (SAF) plate boundary in central California, data from new seismic indicators of deep fault&lt;br/&gt;zone deformation are analyzed and compared to geodetic measurements of deformation and&lt;br/&gt;moderate to large earthquake occurrence. The new seismic indicators are of two types: 1)&lt;br/&gt;characteristically repeating microearthquakes (used to inferred deep-fault aseismic slip&lt;br/&gt;information) and 2) deep non-volcanic tremor activity (indicators of episodic slow-slip events in&lt;br/&gt;the deep sub-seismogenic lithosphere).&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project will produce a large-scale catalog of tremor activity along 175&lt;br/&gt;km of the central SAF that does not currently exist and that will likely be of use for related&lt;br/&gt;research. The proposed activity will also comprise a component of a graduate student's Ph.D.&lt;br/&gt;dissertation and will be a major component of an undergraduates senior thesis. Results will be&lt;br/&gt;disseminated to the public through K-12 tours and annual public open houses of the Berkeley&lt;br/&gt;Seismological Lab and to the scientific community scientific community at meetings and in&lt;br/&gt;publication . Results will also be incorporated into an upper-division undergraduate course on&lt;br/&gt;California Earthquakes (eps 130). Two undergraduates are also participating in the preliminary&lt;br/&gt;and ongoing research through an independent research course (eps 199). Project activities will&lt;br/&gt;benefit society through public education, education and training of students and by providing&lt;br/&gt;information on the complex processes occurring along the SAF plate boundary and the timevarying&lt;br/&gt;aspects of slip-deficit accumulation in the region, all of which are critical inputs for the&lt;br/&gt;accurate assessment of the seismic hazard posed by the active tectonics of this region.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>03/29/2006</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>03/29/2006</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>0544730</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Robert</FirstName>
<LastName>Nadeau</LastName>
<EmailAddress>nadeau@seismo.berkeley.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>03/29/2006</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of California-Berkeley</Name>
<CityName>BERKELEY</CityName>
<ZipCode>947101749</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5106433891</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>Sponsored Projects Office</StreetAddress>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
</Institution>
<FoaInformation>
<Code>0000099</Code>
<Name>Other Applications NEC</Name>
</FoaInformation>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>017F</Code>
<Text>EARTHSCOPE-SCIENCE UTILIZATION</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>0000</Code>
<Text>UNASSIGNED</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>OTHR</Code>
<Text>OTHER RESEARCH OR EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
</Award>
</rootTag>
