<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>CAREER: Time-Dependent Multi-Scale Frameworks for Mechano-Thermo-Hygro-Visco and Damage Behaviors of Composite Materials and Structures</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>01/01/2006</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>09/30/2011</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>0.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>406000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CMMI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Civil, Mechanical, &amp; Manufact Inn</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Yick Hsuan</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>CAREER: Time-dependent Multi-scale Frameworks for Mechano-thermo-hygro-visco and Damage Behaviors of Composite Materials and Structures&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;PI: Anastasia Muliana (Texas A&amp;M University)&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Long-term mechanical performance and durability of fiber reinforced polymer (FRP) composite structures are strongly influenced by the evolution of their microstructure.  A multi-scale analysis framework of composite structures that recognize microstructural deterioration due to coupled time-stress-temperature-moisture effects are needed in conjunction with experimental works for microstructural characterization to understand and predict material/structural behaviors.  The proposed CAREER program aims to develop a method for linking the evolution of composite constituent (fiber-matrix-interphase) to the overall viscoelastic and damage behaviors of FRP structures and to effectively model and characterize the microstructural properties.  The research plan consists of (1) An analytical/computational formulation phase to develop a multi-scale material and structural modeling framework.  The framework is based on a synthesis of three major components: numerical algorithms of time-dependent constitutive models with hygrothermal, stress, and damage effects at the constituent (matrix-interphase) levels, hierarchical micromechanical constitutive models for several composite reinforcements, and layered structural elements that incorporate through-thickness material variability and transverse shear deformations.  The framework is implemented in a general three-dimensional (3D) nonlinear finite element (FE) code.  (2) Experimental phase to characterize in-situ microstructural properties and verify the proposed multi-scale framework.  Macro scale testing includes axial and shear creep tests on FRP specimens with Digital image correlation (DIC) to record full field surface displacements.  Micro scale testing includes creep indentation and scratch tests on fiber, matrix and interphase regions.  While major progress has been made in multi-scale material constitutive modeling, the proposed research plan is significant and unique because it provides an overall microstructural-global material and structural framework that couples time, mechanical, hygrothermal, and damage behaviors from the micro-level  (micron scale) to the nonlinear response at the structural level (meters scale).  The outcome of this research will enhance understanding of microstructural behaviors of heterogeneous materials that strongly influence the global responses of composite structures.  This will benefit both civil and aerospace infrastructures, such as aircraft structural components, bridges, tunnels, fluid conveying pipes, and many others.  The research and education plans are integrated so that the education initiatives draw upon the research results.  The interdisciplinary nature of the CAREER Plan will overreach and impact students in the mechanical, civil, aerospace, and petroleum engineering departments.  The educational plan focuses on strengthening solid mechanics curriculum at Texas A&amp;M by developing graduate course in Computational Inelasticity and preparing undergraduate and graduate students who can contribute to nonlinear mechanics of heterogeneous systems both as engineers and researchers.  To enhance student learning in material and structural behaviors, visualization and animations that are correlated with real testing using DIC technique will be developed.  A summer research program that targets high-school teachers will be established to disseminate research in the evolution of microstructural materials to public.  In addition, collaborations with industry will be initiated to apply the research finding in the analyses of oil drilling and aircraft structures.&lt;br/&gt;</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>11/14/2005</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/05/2010</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>0546528</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Anastasia</FirstName>
<LastName>Muliana</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>H</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Anastasia H Muliana</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>amuliana@tamu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>9794583579</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000494327</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>11/14/2005</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Texas A&amp;M Engineering Experiment Station</Name>
<CityName>College Station</CityName>
<ZipCode>778454645</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>9798626777</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>400 Harvey Mitchell Pkwy S</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[Suite 300]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Texas</StateName>
<StateCode>TX</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>17</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>TX17</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>847205572</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>TEXAS A&amp;M ENGINEERING EXPERIMENT STATION</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>042915991</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Texas A&amp;M Engineering Experiment Station]]></Name>
<CityName>College Station</CityName>
<StateCode>TX</StateCode>
<ZipCode>778454645</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[400 Harvey Mitchell Pkwy S]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Texas</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>17</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>TX17</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1635</Code>
<Text>STRUCTURAL MATERIALS AND MECH</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1675</Code>
<Text>NANOSCALE: SCIENCE &amp; ENGIN CTR</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>025E</Code>
<Text>INFRASTRUCTURE MATERIALS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>036E</Code>
<Text>CIVIL INFRASTRUCTURE</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1045</Code>
<Text>CAREER-Faculty Erly Career Dev</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>116E</Code>
<Text>RESEARCH EXP FOR UNDERGRADS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9102</Code>
<Text>WOMEN, MINORITY, DISABLED, NEC</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9161</Code>
<Text>SINGLE DIVISION/UNIVERSITY</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9178</Code>
<Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9231</Code>
<Text>SUPPL FOR UNDERGRAD RES ASSIST</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9251</Code>
<Text>REU SUPP-Res Exp for Ugrd Supp</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>AMPP</Code>
<Text>ADVANCED MATERIALS &amp; PROCESSING PROGRAM</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0105</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>490100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0110</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2006~400000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2010~6000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Research Outcome for the General Public</p> <p>Principal Investigator: Anastasia Muliana</p> <p>Organization: Texas Engineering Experiment Station (TEES)</p> <p>Title: CAREER <em>Time-dependent Multi-scale Frameworks for Mechano-thermo-hygro-visco and Damage Behaviors of Composite Materials and Structures</em></p> <p>Award ID: 0546528</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p><span style="text-decoration: underline;">Intellectual Merit</span>:</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>This NSF CAREER project introduces a model to predict the overall time-dependent performance of several structures and/or structural components made of fiber reinforced polymer layered composites subject to coupled mechanical and hygrothermal external stimuli. The use of layered fiber reinforced polymer composites makes it possible to build lighter bridge-decks, aircraft fuselages, transmission towers, large wind-turbine blades, ship decks, and many others. The composites used in these applications often experience complex mechanical loading and hostile environmental conditions, which cause degradation in the structures. The response of polymeric based composite changes over time due to the existence of soft polymers and continuous changes in the environmental conditions, i.e. high temperatures during summer and low temperatures in winter in addition to changes in the humidity, intensify the deterioration of the microstructures which cause material damages and structural collapses. Thus, it is necessary to bridge the microstructural response of the composites to the overall performance of the composites structures. This can be achieved through the development of a multi-scale model of composite structures that include time-stress-temperature-moisture effects and damage behaviors (Fig. 1). In order to support the development of the multi-scale framework, experimental data on the performance of composites at different environmental conditions are needed.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>This project has successfully developed the predictive model for the performance of composite structures subject to mechanical loading and hostile environmental conditions at multiple time and length scales. Figure 2 illustrates time-dependent deformations (short- and long-term responses) from the experiment and multi-scale prediction of layered composites, commonly used in bridge decks, at several isothermal temperatures. Another example is on predicting time-dependent response of aircraft fuselage made of fiber reinforced polymer and aluminum layered composites, termed as fiber metal laminates. The time-dependent deformations from the multi-scale have been verified by comparing their results with available experimental data on fiber metal laminates reported in the literature. Figure 3 shows the overall field deformation of an aircraft fuselage, made of fiber metal laminate having glass fiber epoxy composite and aluminum layers, which was generated from the multi-scale model. The multi-scale model has also been used to analyze response of other composite systems such as polymeric based functionally graded materials and foam core sandwich composites at different isothermal temperatures and moisture contents. Furthermore, predictions of time-dependent delamination or separation between layers in the layered composites, such as separation between composite skins and foam core of sandwich composites undergoing diffusion of a fluid, have been made.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p><span style="text-decoration: underline;">Broader Impact</span>:</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>The research on the development of a multi-scale model for predicting time-stress-temperature-moisture dependent response of polymeric based composites have been disseminated through several publications: 26 peer reviewed journals, 9 conference proceedings, 3 PhD dissertations, and 6 master theses. The PI has involved 3 PhD, 6 Master, and 2 Undergraduate students in this NSF CAREER project. The stu...]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Research Outcome for the General Public  Principal Investigator: Anastasia Muliana  Organization: Texas Engineering Experiment Station (TEES)  Title: CAREER Time-dependent Multi-scale Frameworks for Mechano-thermo-hygro-visco and Damage Behaviors of Composite Materials and Structures  Award ID: 0546528        Intellectual Merit:     This NSF CAREER project introduces a model to predict the overall time-dependent performance of several structures and/or structural components made of fiber reinforced polymer layered composites subject to coupled mechanical and hygrothermal external stimuli. The use of layered fiber reinforced polymer composites makes it possible to build lighter bridge-decks, aircraft fuselages, transmission towers, large wind-turbine blades, ship decks, and many others. The composites used in these applications often experience complex mechanical loading and hostile environmental conditions, which cause degradation in the structures. The response of polymeric based composite changes over time due to the existence of soft polymers and continuous changes in the environmental conditions, i.e. high temperatures during summer and low temperatures in winter in addition to changes in the humidity, intensify the deterioration of the microstructures which cause material damages and structural collapses. Thus, it is necessary to bridge the microstructural response of the composites to the overall performance of the composites structures. This can be achieved through the development of a multi-scale model of composite structures that include time-stress-temperature-moisture effects and damage behaviors (Fig. 1). In order to support the development of the multi-scale framework, experimental data on the performance of composites at different environmental conditions are needed.     This project has successfully developed the predictive model for the performance of composite structures subject to mechanical loading and hostile environmental conditions at multiple time and length scales. Figure 2 illustrates time-dependent deformations (short- and long-term responses) from the experiment and multi-scale prediction of layered composites, commonly used in bridge decks, at several isothermal temperatures. Another example is on predicting time-dependent response of aircraft fuselage made of fiber reinforced polymer and aluminum layered composites, termed as fiber metal laminates. The time-dependent deformations from the multi-scale have been verified by comparing their results with available experimental data on fiber metal laminates reported in the literature. Figure 3 shows the overall field deformation of an aircraft fuselage, made of fiber metal laminate having glass fiber epoxy composite and aluminum layers, which was generated from the multi-scale model. The multi-scale model has also been used to analyze response of other composite systems such as polymeric based functionally graded materials and foam core sandwich composites at different isothermal temperatures and moisture contents. Furthermore, predictions of time-dependent delamination or separation between layers in the layered composites, such as separation between composite skins and foam core of sandwich composites undergoing diffusion of a fluid, have been made.     Broader Impact:     The research on the development of a multi-scale model for predicting time-stress-temperature-moisture dependent response of polymeric based composites have been disseminated through several publications: 26 peer reviewed journals, 9 conference proceedings, 3 PhD dissertations, and 6 master theses. The PI has involved 3 PhD, 6 Master, and 2 Undergraduate students in this NSF CAREER project. The students have been trained in conducting experiments on composites, analyzing overall time-dependent responses of composite structures subject to combined mechanical, thermal, and moisture stimuli, developing models for predicting deformations of polymers and composites, formulating multi-sc...]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
