<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>CAREER: machine learning approches for articulatory inversion</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>01/15/2006</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>11/30/2007</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>500001.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>200001</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>05020000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>CSE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>IIS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Information &amp; Intelligent Systems</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Tatiana Korelsky</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Articulatory inversion is the problem of recovering the sequence of&lt;br/&gt;vocal tract shapes that produce a given acoustic utterance. &lt;br/&gt;Articulatory representations are useful for automatic speech&lt;br/&gt;recognition, speech production research, language therapy, and&lt;br/&gt;language learning. Articulatory inversion is a hard problem because&lt;br/&gt;different vocal tract shapes can produce the same acoustics, yet the&lt;br/&gt;articulatory trajectory must obey the mechanical constraints of the&lt;br/&gt;human vocal tract. Other examples of inversion problems over a&lt;br/&gt;sequence, which share the multivalued nature of the mappings and the&lt;br/&gt;existence of constraints, are: the recovery of facial gestures&lt;br/&gt;associated with a speech utterance; the inverse kinematics of a robot&lt;br/&gt;arm; and the recovery of 3D motion from video.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project approaches articulatory inversion from a machine learning&lt;br/&gt;standpoint, based on a framework introduced by the PI. The&lt;br/&gt;low-dimensional manifold in articulatory-acoustic space is represented&lt;br/&gt;in a probabilistic way by a density model estimated from data&lt;br/&gt;(recorded using a microphone and electromagnetic articulography). &lt;br/&gt;Multivalued mappings are explicitly represented by the modes of&lt;br/&gt;conditional distributions of this density, and the articulatory&lt;br/&gt;trajectory is disambiguated using a continuity constraint.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The project introduces new problems in dimensionality reduction,&lt;br/&gt;density estimation and regularization (such as multivalued regression&lt;br/&gt;and graph-learning from noisy data), and new models and algorithms. &lt;br/&gt;The expected results of this work are: performing basic research in&lt;br/&gt;machine learning, and introducing mapping inversion problems to&lt;br/&gt;research and education; improving articulatory inversion (for which&lt;br/&gt;code will be made freely available); and advocating data-driven&lt;br/&gt;approaches in speech production research and education.&lt;br/&gt;</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>12/23/2005</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>11/20/2006</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>0546857</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Miguel</FirstName>
<LastName>Carreira-Perpinan</LastName>
<EmailAddress>mcarreira-perpinan@ucmerced.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>12/23/2005</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Oregon Health &amp; Science University</Name>
<CityName>Portland</CityName>
<ZipCode>972393098</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5034947784</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>3181 S W Sam Jackson Park Rd</StreetAddress>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Oregon</StateName>
<StateCode>OR</StateCode>
</Institution>
<FoaInformation>
<Code>0104000</Code>
<Name>Information Systems</Name>
</FoaInformation>
<FoaInformation>
<Code>0116000</Code>
<Name>Human Subjects</Name>
</FoaInformation>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7274</Code>
<Text>HUMAN LANGUAGE &amp; COMMUNICATION</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7495</Code>
<Text>Robust Intelligence</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1045</Code>
<Text>CAREER-Faculty Erly Career Dev</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9218</Code>
<Text>BASIC RESEARCH &amp; HUMAN RESORCS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>HPCC</Code>
<Text>HIGH PERFORMANCE COMPUTING &amp; COMM</Text>
</ProgramReference>
</Award>
</rootTag>
