<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Collaborative Research: Development of the Automated Dissolved Inorganic Carbon Analyzer (AMICA) for Seawater DIC Analyses</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>10/01/2006</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>09/30/2011</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardAmount>285074</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>06040104</Code>
<Directorate>
<LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<LongName>Division Of Ocean Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Kandace S. Binkley</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Collection of high quality DIC data will be required for studies of ocean carbon cycling and studies of marine metabolic processes. The PI's propose to develop the next generation of DIC analyzer, capable of producing high quality data for all types of natural waters. The instrument design uses a commercially available infrared analyzer and improved approaches to the extraction, manipulation of samples, and the measurement of CO2. The system builds upon a proof of concept system first built by Gernot Friederich at MBARI. The instrument is referred to as the Automated Dissolved Inorganic Carbon Analyzer. Key elements of the instrument design are: highly precise and accurate DIC analyses; reliability and efficiency of the analysis; ease of use; good sample throughput; robustness of design for use at sea and in laboratory; low cost; capability of analyzing a range of sample type; capability of analyzing a range of sample volumes, suitable for analyzing sediment porewater to oceanic samples, broad analytical range and; easily modified for different applications. Development of the instrument for broad community use requires significant technical and intellectual resources.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Broader Impacts&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;High quality DIC data are at the core of a number of U.S. and international research programs (U.S. Carbon Cycle Science Program; international SOLAS and IMBER, etc.).If successful, this proposal could have wide ranging, positive impact on the ocean research community. Accurate measurements of dissolved inorganic carbon in the ocean is a prerequisite for addressing one of the most important questions in current carbon and climate research, i.e. what is the fate of the CO2 that we emit into the atmosphere as a result of fossil fuel burning and land-use change. In addition, funding is provided for a post doc and grad student.&lt;br/&gt;</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>09/21/2006</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/21/2010</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>0549750</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Nicholas</FirstName>
<LastName>Bates</LastName>
<EmailAddress>nick.bates@bios.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>09/21/2006</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Bermuda Institute of Ocean Sciences (BIOS), Inc.</Name>
<CityName>St. George's    GE01</CityName>
<ZipCode/>
<PhoneNumber>4412971880</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>17 Biological Station</StreetAddress>
<CountryName>Bermuda</CountryName>
<StateName/>
<StateCode/>
</Institution>
<FoaInformation>
<Code>0204000</Code>
<Name>Oceanography</Name>
</FoaInformation>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1680</Code>
<Text>OCEAN TECH &amp; INTERDISC COORDIN</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>0000</Code>
<Text>UNASSIGNED</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>OTHR</Code>
<Text>OTHER RESEARCH OR EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
</Award>
</rootTag>
