<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Collaborative Research: Seeds and Slaves: Technological Change, Plantation Efficiency, and Southern Economic Development</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>03/01/2006</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>02/28/2010</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>76605</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>04050000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Divn Of Social and Economic Sciences</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Nancy A. Lutz</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This research project will call into question five standard lessons about the development of American&lt;br/&gt;agriculture, and more specifically of plantation agriculture in the slave South:&lt;br/&gt;1. Little biological change occurred in the antebellum South, or indeed anywhere in American&lt;br/&gt;agriculture before the advent of hybrid corn in the 1930s.&lt;br/&gt;2. Biological learning, when it did occur, was exclusively associated with land-augmenting (yieldincreasing)&lt;br/&gt;technological change rather than labor-saving technological change.&lt;br/&gt;3. The antebellum cotton economy grew almost exclusively through territorial expansion.&lt;br/&gt;4. The slave South was 'uninventive' and technologically stagnant.&lt;br/&gt;5. The productivity differentials that did exist across plantations and regions were primarily&lt;br/&gt;associated with labor organization and scale.&lt;br/&gt;The analysis, based on archival plantation records, will demonstrate that each of these lessons must be&lt;br/&gt;fundamentally rethought. In preliminary work, the authors have collected a sample of over 400,000&lt;br/&gt;observations on the daily cotton picking performance of individual slaves over the 1811-62 period.&lt;br/&gt;Analysis of this sample at the plantation level shows that the average amount of cotton picked per slave in&lt;br/&gt;a day increased by over 2.2 percent per annum. Thus, in the 50 years preceding the Civil War, picking&lt;br/&gt;efficiency tripled. Given that picking was the peak-load labor requirement, this change relaxed the key&lt;br/&gt;binding constraint and allowed planters to reallocate labor and land to higher value uses. The&lt;br/&gt;introduction, local refinement, and diffusion of new cultivars (the so-called Mexican cottons) is the&lt;br/&gt;leading explanation of this labor-saving technological change.&lt;br/&gt;The current sample has been collected from the most accessible sources. It contains key gaps--&lt;br/&gt;e.g., coverage is disproportionately weighted to the Mississippi Valley and the late antebellum period.&lt;br/&gt;Funding will allow tapping known archival records to roughly double the sample and increase its&lt;br/&gt;coverage of the pre-1840 period and of the important cotton belt in Alabama, Georgia, and South&lt;br/&gt;Carolina. In addition to picking records, the authors will collect information on slave demographics, seed&lt;br/&gt;varieties, management activities, and other cultural practices. Pushing the sample back in time and&lt;br/&gt;increasing its geographic coverage will substantially improve its usefulness for understanding the&lt;br/&gt;diffusion of the new biological technology (improved seeds) and its relationship to increased picking&lt;br/&gt;efficiency. Funding will facilitate assembling the data from specific plantations into a larger panel dataset&lt;br/&gt;including the micro data for several thousand individual African-American slaves. Such a panel dataset&lt;br/&gt;will allow the improved analysis of productivity growth controlling for labor force composition and other&lt;br/&gt;factors, the measurement of differences in picking performance across age and gender categories, and the&lt;br/&gt;fuller re-evaluation of standard conclusions about the relationship between plantation scale, labor&lt;br/&gt;organization, and efficiency.&lt;br/&gt;The intellectual merit of this proposal is the creation and analysis of a large new panel dataset&lt;br/&gt;that will improve our understanding of the dynamics of American economic development by directing&lt;br/&gt;attention to a hitherto neglected issue--the rapid productivity growth of slave labor in cotton cultivation.&lt;br/&gt;The new evidence will shed light on many of the most contentious issues in American history associated&lt;br/&gt;with the competitive performance and labor organization of this nation's 'peculiar institution.'&lt;br/&gt;The broader significance of this research will be the reinterpretation of the sources of American&lt;br/&gt;economic growth by highlighting the role of biological technologies. Such technologies had enormous&lt;br/&gt;impacts on both land and labor productivity that are at odds with the conventional views inspired by the&lt;br/&gt;pioneering work of Zvi Griliches on hybrid corn. The findings will also challenge standard views about&lt;br/&gt;the 'uninventive South' that influence the way American history is understood and taught. Finally, the&lt;br/&gt;research will illuminate the working lives of individual African-American slaves who have heretofore&lt;br/&gt;labored in anonymity.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>01/24/2006</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>01/31/2007</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0550913</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Paul</FirstName>
      <LastName>Rhode</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>prhode@email.unc.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>01/24/2006</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>National Bureau of Economic Research Inc</Name>
      <CityName>Cambridge</CityName>
      <ZipCode>021385398</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>6178683900</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>1050 Massachusetts Avenue</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
      <StateCode>MA</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
