<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Some Variants of the Kakeya Problem</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>06/15/2006</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2010</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardAmount>84537</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Bruce P. Palka</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>(1) This project will focus on certain geometric questions from classical &lt;br/&gt;analysis which have their origins in the well-known Kakeya problem: find &lt;br/&gt;the minimum dimension of a subset of d-dimensional space which contains a &lt;br/&gt;line segment in each direction. Of particular interest to the p.i. are &lt;br/&gt;estimates from below for the Hausdorff dimension of sets which have large &lt;br/&gt;intersections with certain collections of lines, planes, or spheres (or, in higher &lt;br/&gt;dimensions, with certain collections of k-planes or hyperspheres). A theme of this work &lt;br/&gt;will be to explore the scope and limitations of a particular method, due &lt;br/&gt;to the p.i., for treating the averaging operators which arise in the study of &lt;br/&gt;these problems. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;(2) This project is concerned with the structure of certain complicated &lt;br/&gt;subsets of higher dimensional spaces. The study of these sets, while of &lt;br/&gt;compelling intrinsic interest, should properly be viewed as a test of our &lt;br/&gt;current understanding of certain objects called averaging operators. The &lt;br/&gt;relevant averaging operators here are of two kinds: spherical averaging &lt;br/&gt;operators and Radon transforms. Spherical averaging operators are basic to &lt;br/&gt;our understanding of the propagation of waves through fluid media such as &lt;br/&gt;the ocean or the atmosphere. The Radon transform and its relatives are &lt;br/&gt;essential, for example, in problems of tomography such as those which &lt;br/&gt;arise in the field of medical imaging. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/07/2006</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/07/2006</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>0552041</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Daniel</FirstName>
<LastName>Oberlin</LastName>
<EmailAddress>oberlin@math.fsu.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>06/07/2006</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Florida State University</Name>
<CityName>TALLAHASSEE</CityName>
<ZipCode>323064166</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>8506445260</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>874 Traditions Way, 3rd Floor</StreetAddress>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Florida</StateName>
<StateCode>FL</StateCode>
</Institution>
<FoaInformation>
<Code>0000099</Code>
<Name>Other Applications NEC</Name>
</FoaInformation>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1281</Code>
<Text>ANALYSIS PROGRAM</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>0000</Code>
<Text>UNASSIGNED</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>OTHR</Code>
<Text>OTHER RESEARCH OR EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
</Award>
</rootTag>
