<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Autothermal Reforming of Greenhouse Gases - SGER</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>02/01/2006</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2007</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>0.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>77797</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07020000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CBET</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Chem, Bioeng, Env, &amp; Transp Sys</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Maria Burka</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>ABSTRACT&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;PI: Marco J. Castaldi &lt;br/&gt;Institution:  Columbia University&lt;br/&gt;Proposal Number: 0553648&lt;br/&gt;Title: Autothermal Reforming of Greenhouse Gases-SGER&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This Small Grant for Exploratory Research (SGER) effort for autothermal dry reforming of greenhouse gases to high value chemicals will accomplish two major goals.  The first is targeted toward understanding the reaction mechanisms occurring on precious metal-based formulations, specifically platinum (Pt) and rhodium (Rh).  The second major goal is to investigate and understand the mechanism of carbon formation and the operating parameters that prevent and promote formation and deposition on the surface.  Other goals tied to this SGER effort will be to obtain preliminary insight into long term activity changes and to disseminate the knowledge and understanding obtained to a broad spectrum of students, industry professionals and other researchers.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The intellectual merit of developing an understanding of the reaction mechanisms to convert greenhouse gases into chemicals will be proven by determining the kinetic parameters and reaction mechanisms governing autothermal reforming of carbon dioxide (CO2) and methane (CH4) to synthesis gas and high value chemicals, such as ethylene.  Thermal Gravimetric Analysis (TGA) will be employed to obtain kinetic rate data, reaction orders, turnover frequencies and reaction mechanisms to further the knowledge base of greenhouse gas reforming. TGA data coupled with pre- and post-test surface analyses, such as BET, XRD and TPD, will provide a clearer understanding of the important reactions, both primary and secondary, thus enabling better reactor design in the future. One primary outcome of this effort, in addition to the ones stated above, will be to provide reliable data to enable effective reactor design for greenhouse gas conversion to useful chemicals. It is anticipated the results of this SGER effort will provide the foundations for future research in chemical reactor design and exploration in a more efficient, directed manner.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The broader impact of this project is to instill in a broad spectrum of students, middle school to graduate level, the concept of catalysis and its potential to positively affect the environment.&lt;br/&gt;This will be achieved through three main routes of dissemination: &lt;br/&gt;1) Environmental Catalysis course development at the undergraduate and graduate levels, &lt;br/&gt;2) Site visits to applicable industry, &lt;br/&gt;3) Curriculum development for middle and high school students. &lt;br/&gt;The courses will involve industry professionals participating in the selection of material as well as giving lectures to the students. The courses will have an experimental component which will be done in the PIs laboratory and allot time for site visits to catalyst companies. The site visits will provide an opportunity for students to interact with industry leaders and get valuable feedback on the research. Lastly the curriculum development for middle and high school students will be accomplished through the existing GK12 program at Columbia University with the participation of the PI, a graduate student and middle and high school teachers. Modules and lesson plans will be assembled to expose the students to concepts in catalysis and how it has already been used to positively affect the environment, such as the three-way automobile catalytic converter. It is anticipated that emphasizing the environmental aspects of catalytic processes will further encourage the students to learn more on their own initiative.  &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>01/18/2006</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>03/08/2007</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>0553648</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Marco</FirstName>
<LastName>Castaldi</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>J</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Marco J Castaldi</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>mcastaldi@ccny.cuny.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2126505418</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000627742</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>01/18/2006</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Columbia University</Name>
<CityName>NEW YORK</CityName>
<CountyName>NEW YORK</CountyName>
<ZipCode>100276902</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2128546851</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>2960 Broadway</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>10</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NY10</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>049179401</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>TRUSTEES OF COLUMBIA UNIVERSITY IN THE CITY OF NEW YORK, THE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>049179401</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Columbia University]]></Name>
<CityName>NEW YORK</CityName>
<CountyName>NEW YORK</CountyName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<ZipCode>100276902</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[2960 Broadway]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>10</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NY10</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<FoaInformation>
<Code>0308000</Code>
<Name>Industrial Technology</Name>
</FoaInformation>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1403</Code>
<Text>Proc Sys, Reac Eng &amp; Mol Therm</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>0000</Code>
<Text>UNASSIGNED</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>047E</Code>
<Text>REACTION ENGINEERING</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7237</Code>
<Text>NANO NON-SOLIC SCI &amp; ENG AWD</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9178</Code>
<Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9231</Code>
<Text>SUPPL FOR UNDERGRAD RES ASSIST</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9237</Code>
<Text>SMALL GRANTS-EXPLORATORY RSRCH</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>OTHR</Code>
<Text>OTHER RESEARCH OR EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>SMET</Code>
<Text>SCIENCE, MATH, ENG &amp; TECH EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0106</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>490100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0107</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>490100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2006~71802</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2007~5995</FUND_OBLG>
</Award>
</rootTag>
