<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Molecule-based Magnets Based on Dinuclear Metal Tetracarboxlates</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/15/2006</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2010</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>0.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>512425</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03090005</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CHE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Chemistry</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Timothy Patten</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Dr. Joel Miller, Chemistry Department, University of Utah, is supported by the Inorganic, Bioinorganic, and Organometallic Chemistry Program of the Chemistry Division for the study of organic- and molecule based magnets (mbms) that consist of two interpenetrating lattices, one being composed of a mixed valent, cationic ruthenium carboxylate and the other an anionic hexacyano- or thiocyanatometalate. The broad goals of the research are to understand the fundamental science that governs behavior in organic-based magnets, to identify new magnetic phenomena, and to make organic-based magnets with enhanced and controllable critical temperatures and coercive fields. Initially, mbms based on S = 3/2 mixed-valent ruthenium(II/III) carboxylates will be studied. The goal is to understand the magnetic consequences of the interpenetrating lattices for these systems. The project will be extended to anionic S = 2 Ru(III) and S = 3/2 Ru(II/III) sulfate and carbonates, to Fe and Os analogues, and to less common oxidation states of these metals. The ultimate objective is the development of new magnetically ordered materials with combination of properties not observed for classical magnets.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This research will provide a fundamental understanding of magnetic behavior in molecular and supramolecular organic magnets, as well as provide more temperature-stable, higher field magnets. Soluble molecular magnets will advance thin film magneto-optical applications. Collaborations with international chemists and physicists will provide a strong interdisciplinary training for students.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/10/2006</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/15/2007</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>0553573</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Joel</FirstName>
<LastName>Miller</LastName>
<EmailAddress>jsmiller@chem.utah.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>08/10/2006</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Utah</Name>
<CityName>SALT LAKE CITY</CityName>
<ZipCode>841128930</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>8015816903</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>75 S 2000 E</StreetAddress>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Utah</StateName>
<StateCode>UT</StateCode>
</Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1968</Code>
<Text>PHYSICAL INORGANIC</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7237</Code>
<Text>NANO NON-SOLIC SCI &amp; ENG AWD</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9146</Code>
<Text>MANUFACTURING BASE RESEARCH</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9161</Code>
<Text>SINGLE DIVISION/UNIVERSITY</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>AMPP</Code>
<Text>ADVANCED MATERIALS &amp; PROCESSING PROGRAM</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>MANU</Code>
<Text>MANUFACTURING</Text>
</ProgramReference>
</Award>
</rootTag>
