<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>FRG: Collaborative Research:  Arithmetic and equidistribution on homogeneous spaces</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>06/01/2006</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>11/30/2008</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>285000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>285000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03040200</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DMS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Tomek Bartoszynski</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>In recent years, it has become clear that many interesting problems,&lt;br/&gt;in particular problems in arithmetic, quantum chaos and the theory of&lt;br/&gt;L-functions, may be profitably reduced to questions concerning&lt;br/&gt;equidistribution of points or measures on homogeneous spaces. These &lt;br/&gt;questions regarding equidistribution can be approached from many&lt;br/&gt;angles. Two theories which have proved to be particularly well-suited&lt;br/&gt;to study such questions are the spectral theory of automorphic forms,&lt;br/&gt;which is closely related to the theory of L-functions, and the theory &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;of dynamical systems, particularly the study of unipotent and more&lt;br/&gt;general flows on these homogeneous spaces. Recently there has been&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;considerable progress involving tools such as special value formulae&lt;br/&gt;for L-functions, and (partial) classification results for measures&lt;br/&gt;invariant under higher rank torus actions. Particularly exciting is &lt;br/&gt;the possibility, already realized in some instances, of combining&lt;br/&gt;these techniques. The purpose of the proposed FRG is to investigate&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;further this circle of ideas, which we believe has the potential to&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;impact many other problems related to the above. The result of these&lt;br/&gt;investigations will be a deeper understanding of the dynamics of group&lt;br/&gt;actions on homogeneous spaces, of the analytic theory of automorphic &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;forms, and the (sometimes unexpected) applications to problems of&lt;br/&gt;arithmetic nature.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The present project is concerned with a surprising link between two&lt;br/&gt;classical fields of mathematics of quite disparate origin: number&lt;br/&gt;theory and dynamics. The study of number theory began thousands of &lt;br/&gt;years ago, motivated, in significant part, by questions about prime&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;numbers.  On the other hand, ergodic theory and dynamics are&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;mathematical fields of more recent provenance, which arose from&lt;br/&gt;studying the long-term evolution of complicated deterministic&lt;br/&gt;processes -- such as planetary motion. It is a striking fact (which &lt;br/&gt;has only recently begun to be heavily exploited) that, in certain&lt;br/&gt;contexts, ideas from ergodic theory interact very deeply with classical&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;problems in number theory.  This project will enhance our&lt;br/&gt;understanding of this inter-relation and how we can combine knowledge&lt;br/&gt;from both of these fruitful disciplines effectively.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>04/26/2006</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>04/26/2006</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>0554365</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Akshay</FirstName>
<LastName>Venkatesh</LastName>
<EmailAddress>akshay@math.ias.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>04/26/2006</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>New York University</Name>
<CityName>NEW YORK</CityName>
<ZipCode>100121019</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2129982121</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>70 WASHINGTON SQUARE S</StreetAddress>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
</Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1264</Code>
<Text>ALGEBRA,NUMBER THEORY,AND COM</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>0000</Code>
<Text>UNASSIGNED</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1616</Code>
<Text>FOCUSED RESEARCH GROUPS IN MATH SCIENCES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>OTHR</Code>
<Text>OTHER RESEARCH OR EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
</Award>
</rootTag>
