<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Project I.D.:    Instrument Development for Exploring the Professional Growth Continuum</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2006</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>01/31/2011</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardAmount>286311</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>11090000</Code>
<Directorate>
<LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<LongName>Division Of Research On Learning</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>David A. Hanych</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>"Project I.D." is identifying pivotal experiences of career science teachers that have promoted their advancement along the teacher professional continuum.  The goal of the project is to develop an instrument that informs researchers about professional development opportunities that successful, empowered science teachers recall as having impacted their teaching and their overall sense of professionalism.&lt;br/&gt; &lt;br/&gt;The project is using a methodology in which teachers draw behavior over time (BOT) graphs while telling their stories of empowerment.  An earlier study of 15 teachers identified three distinct phases of professional growth during the careers of teachers.  "Project I.D." continues this investigation during year one with a new group of 50 teachers, half of which are drawn from the Texas Regional Collaboratives for Excellence in Science Teaching.  The remaining teachers roughly approximate the makeup of science teachers statewide.  &lt;br/&gt; &lt;br/&gt;During year two the 50 teachers meet in small regional focus groups of ten teachers each.  These focus groups identify pivotal career experiences and assist in the early development of an instrument.  The project is designing an instrument that collects similar data more efficiently through the use of technology.  During year two, the project is administering this instrument to a group of 50 teachers and then to a larger group of teachers (250+).  In year three, the project is administering the instrument to still larger groups of teachers. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/18/2006</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/26/2008</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>0554468</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Mary</FirstName>
<LastName>Hobbs</LastName>
<EmailAddress>maryhobbs@mail.utexas.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>07/18/2006</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>James</FirstName>
<LastName>Barufaldi</LastName>
<EmailAddress>jamesb@mail.utexas.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>07/18/2006</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Texas at Austin</Name>
<CityName>Austin</CityName>
<ZipCode>787595316</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5124716424</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>3925 W Braker Lane, Ste 3.340</StreetAddress>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Texas</StateName>
<StateCode>TX</StateCode>
</Institution>
<FoaInformation>
<Code>0000099</Code>
<Name>Other Applications NEC</Name>
</FoaInformation>
<FoaInformation>
<Code>0116000</Code>
<Name>Human Subjects</Name>
</FoaInformation>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7271</Code>
<Text>TEACHER PROFESSIONAL CONTINUUM</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9177</Code>
<Text>ELEMENTARY/SECONDARY EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>SMET</Code>
<Text>SCIENCE, MATH, ENG &amp; TECH EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
</Award>
</rootTag>
