<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Self-Aligned Nanomanufacturing of Carbon Nanotubes for Nanoelectronics</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>06/01/2006</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2009</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>175000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>175000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CMMI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Civil, Mechanical, &amp; Manufact Inn</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>george hazelrigg</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The research goal of this project is to develop a methodology that can achieve self-aligned growth of carbon nanotubes (CNTs) in a controllable manner at lower temperature. The specific objectives are to: 1) develop theoretical models for self-aligned CNT growth; 2) develop a method of nanoscale light enhancement and local heating at the apex of tip-shaped electrodes; 3) achieve CNT growth between two metallic electrodes under laser irradiation; 4) use an electrical field to control CNT growth direction; 5) achieve selective growth of semiconducting and metallic CNTs; and 6) demonstrate practical applications of the CNT nanomanufacturing method(s) developed. This project will advance discovery and understanding while promoting teaching, training, and learning through the integration of the proposed research with educational activities for both graduate and undergraduate students. The project activities will be integrated into an existing course (Introduction to Nanotechnology) for graduate and senior undergraduate students. The students enrolled in this course will have an opportunity to visit the research facility and participate in discussions of the experimental results. This approach will strengthen students understanding of basic theories in nanoscale science and engineering. This project will engage a diverse group of students as a way of encouraging underrepresented groups to continue on for postgraduate study. &lt;br/&gt;The successful completion of this project will lay a foundation for future nanoelectronics manufacturing. The proposed process is compatible with current manufacturing processes used in microelectronics and can be used to integrate CNT devices and interconnections as key components in integrated circuits fabricated using current semiconductor manufacturing infrastructures. The integration of CNT devices will improve the integration density, circuit functionality, power consumption and circuit speed, with minimum additional capital investment. The success of this project has the potential to transfer CNT-based nanoelectronics to a viable industry.&lt;br/&gt;</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>05/22/2006</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/22/2006</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>0555884</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Yongfeng</FirstName>
<LastName>Lu</LastName>
<EmailAddress>ylu2@unl.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>05/22/2006</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</Name>
<CityName>Lincoln</CityName>
<ZipCode>685031435</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>4024723171</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>151 Prem S. Paul Research Center</StreetAddress>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Nebraska</StateName>
<StateCode>NE</StateCode>
</Institution>
<FoaInformation>
<Code>0308000</Code>
<Name>Industrial Technology</Name>
</FoaInformation>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1788</Code>
<Text>NANOMANUFACTURING</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>084E</Code>
<Text>NANOMANUFACTURING</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9146</Code>
<Text>MANUFACTURING BASE RESEARCH</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>MANU</Code>
<Text>MANUFACTURING</Text>
</ProgramReference>
</Award>
</rootTag>
