<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Quantization, Symmetric Spaces, and Symplectic Reduction</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2006</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2010</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardAmount>106419</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Bruce P. Palka</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>     This proposal studies two issues within the area of &lt;br/&gt;quantization theory. The first issue, building on the PI's &lt;br/&gt;earlier work, is the holomorphic quantization of symmetric &lt;br/&gt;spaces. Attention will be given mainly to the noncompact case, &lt;br/&gt;where singularities arise that one does not see in the compact &lt;br/&gt;case. Building on work of the PI with J. Mitchell and work of B. &lt;br/&gt;Krotz, G. Olafsson, and R. Stanton, the PI intends to find &lt;br/&gt;appropriate ways to cancel out these singularities. He intends to &lt;br/&gt;develop inversion and isometry formulas for the Segal-Bargmann &lt;br/&gt;transform on noncompact symmetric spaces, with the goal of making &lt;br/&gt;these formulas as parallel as possible to the results in the dual &lt;br/&gt;compact case. The PI hopes to combine the approach used in his &lt;br/&gt;work with Mitchell with the shift-operator method of Krotz, &lt;br/&gt;Olafsson, and Stanton. The second issue concerns the relationship &lt;br/&gt;of quantization to reduction. In work with W. Kirwin, the PI will &lt;br/&gt;investigate the unitarity (or lack thereof) of the Guillemin-&lt;br/&gt;Sternberg map between the "first quantize then reduce" space and &lt;br/&gt;the "first reduce and then quantize space." We hope to &lt;br/&gt;demonstrate that this map is not unitary, even to leading order &lt;br/&gt;in Planck's constant, but that inclusion of the half-form &lt;br/&gt;correction yields leading-order unitarity.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;     This proposal concerns quantization, namely, the &lt;br/&gt;construction of a quantum-mechanical theory corresponding to a &lt;br/&gt;given classical theory. In modern physics, the relevant theories &lt;br/&gt;to be quantized often have interesting geometric properties &lt;br/&gt;involving various sorts of symmetries. This proposal attempts to &lt;br/&gt;understand how this geometry manifests itself in the quantum &lt;br/&gt;theory. The first part of the proposal is an attempt to extend a &lt;br/&gt;standard tool in quantum theory, the Segal-Bargmann transform &lt;br/&gt;(closely related to the ubiquitous concept of coherent states), &lt;br/&gt;to more geometrically interesting situations where nice &lt;br/&gt;symmetries are present. The PI's earlier work in this area has &lt;br/&gt;already been applied in several different ways by workers in loop &lt;br/&gt;quantum gravity. The second part of the proposal concerns the way &lt;br/&gt;symmetries interact with quantum mechanics. Most modern physical &lt;br/&gt;theories (e.g., gravity, electromagnetism, relativity) use &lt;br/&gt;symmetry in an essential way. The PI's work addresses the subtle &lt;br/&gt;but important question of whether imposing the symmetries before &lt;br/&gt;quantizing gives the same result as imposing them after &lt;br/&gt;quantizing.&lt;br/&gt;</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/13/2006</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/13/2006</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>0555862</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Brian</FirstName>
<LastName>Hall</LastName>
<EmailAddress>bhall@nd.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>07/13/2006</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Notre Dame</Name>
<CityName>NOTRE DAME</CityName>
<ZipCode>465565708</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5746317432</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>940 Grace Hall</StreetAddress>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Indiana</StateName>
<StateCode>IN</StateCode>
</Institution>
<FoaInformation>
<Code>0000099</Code>
<Name>Other Applications NEC</Name>
</FoaInformation>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1281</Code>
<Text>ANALYSIS PROGRAM</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>0000</Code>
<Text>UNASSIGNED</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>OTHR</Code>
<Text>OTHER RESEARCH OR EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
</Award>
</rootTag>
