<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>High-Index-Contrast Waveguides for Enhanced Optoelectronic Devices and Integration</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/15/2006</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2010</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardAmount>288000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07010000</Code>
<Directorate>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<LongName>Div Of Electrical, Commun &amp; Cyber Sys</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>John Zavada</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>High-Index-Contrast Waveguides for &lt;br/&gt;Enhanced Optoelectronic Devices and Integration&lt;br/&gt;Douglas C. Hall, University of Notre Dame&lt;br/&gt;0601702&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Abstract&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The intellectual merit of this project lies in the further characterization and exploitation of a newly-discovered method for confining light in low-loss, small geometry and tightly-curved compound semiconductor waveguides.  With beneficial insulating, defect passivation, roughness-smoothing, and optical properties, the native oxides grown directly on etched aluminum gallium arsenide through an oxygen-enhanced wet thermal oxidation process yield a unique high-index-contrast waveguide structure to greatly enhance the performance of semiconductor lasers. Very high quality ring resonator devices will be realized for compact, wavelength-tunable components. Sub-micron aperture diode lasers with low drive current requirements and enhanced output beam quality and polarization properties will be developed.  The possibility for improving diode laser reliability and cost by passivating the cleaved facet mirrors through controlled oxidation will be investigated.  Low-bend-loss waveguides having 10-100 micron curvature radii will be pursued to demonstrate a new path towards very dense photonic integrated circuits.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Broader impacts of this project include: advancing discovery and understanding in photonics through the pioneering of new planar integration techniques for compact, high-performance, active optoelectronic devices (lasers, amplifiers, detectors, etc.) to offer functionality which greatly exceeds today's passive silicon-based technology; the societal and economic benefits of making ultra-high-speed multi-wavelength optical communications more affordable to accelerate deployment of fiber-to-the-X for yet un-reached education, health, public service and consumer markets; and enriching the educational experiences of broad constituencies through the effective and continued integration of research activities with teaching and mentoring. Educational activities include the PI's participation in a growing "RET@ND" community outreach effort at Notre Dame (enabling area school teachers to have a summer research experience through which they can enliven their classrooms with the science of light propagation and semiconductor devices), summer Research Experience for Undergraduates (REU) programs administered by the Notre Dame Center for Nano Science and Technology, incorporating research devices into special-project modules in the PI's Photonics Teaching Laboratory course, and outreach to underrepresented minorities through participation in programs sponsored by the Minority Engineering Program (MEP) at the University of Notre Dame.&lt;br/&gt;</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/23/2006</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/13/2009</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>0601702</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Douglas</FirstName>
<LastName>Hall</LastName>
<EmailAddress>dhall@nd.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>08/23/2006</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Notre Dame</Name>
<CityName>NOTRE DAME</CityName>
<ZipCode>465565708</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5746317432</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>940 Grace Hall</StreetAddress>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Indiana</StateName>
<StateCode>IN</StateCode>
</Institution>
<FoaInformation>
<Code>0206000</Code>
<Name>Telecommunications</Name>
</FoaInformation>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1517</Code>
<Text>ELECT, PHOTONICS, &amp; MAG DEVICE</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>0000</Code>
<Text>UNASSIGNED</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>103E</Code>
<Text>Energy efficient electronics</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9251</Code>
<Text>RES EXPER FOR UNDERGRAD-SUPPLT</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>OTHR</Code>
<Text>OTHER RESEARCH OR EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
</Award>
</rootTag>
