<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Conformal Mapping</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>06/15/2006</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2009</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardAmount>121289</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03040100</Code>
<Directorate>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Joe W. Jenkins</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The Loewner differential equation was introduced in 1923 to study &lt;br/&gt;extremal problems for conformal maps in the unit disc. Schramm's &lt;br/&gt;recent discovery of the stochastic Loewner evolution SLE, the &lt;br/&gt;Loewner equation driven by one-dimensional Brownian motion, has &lt;br/&gt;opened up a new area of investigations involving conformal mappings, &lt;br/&gt;probability theory and mathematical physics. It has led to the &lt;br/&gt;discovery of new results in percolation and random walks, for &lt;br/&gt;example, as well as the discovery mathematical proofs of results &lt;br/&gt;known to the theoretical physics community. The Loewner equation is &lt;br/&gt;also related to an algorithm for numerical conformal mapping &lt;br/&gt;discovered by Marshall and K\"uhnau. The Loewner equation has as &lt;br/&gt;input an arbitrary continuous function and produces a continuous &lt;br/&gt;family of conformal mappings. Marshall plans to investigate &lt;br/&gt;properties of the solutions of Loewner's equation under various &lt;br/&gt;assumptions on the smoothness of the driving function, and &lt;br/&gt;conversely to investigate how smoothness of the boundaries of the &lt;br/&gt;associated regions implies smoothness of the driving function. This &lt;br/&gt;is a classical problem where progress has been made only recently. &lt;br/&gt;Marshall will analyze convergence and error-estimates for the &lt;br/&gt;numerical mapping method called ``zipper'', closely related to &lt;br/&gt;Loewner's equation, and improve the speed of convergence using &lt;br/&gt;``generational'' techniques.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The main theme of Marshall's research program is to study conformal &lt;br/&gt;mappings generated by the Loewner differential equation, and related &lt;br/&gt;topics. Conformal mappings have been used as a tool in science and &lt;br/&gt;engineering for many years. They are often used to change &lt;br/&gt;coordinates from a complicated region to a simpler region like a &lt;br/&gt;disc. Physical processes are modeled by partial differential &lt;br/&gt;equations. A partial differential equation on the complicated two &lt;br/&gt;dimensional region can be changed by a conformal map to a similar &lt;br/&gt;equation on the disc, a setting where it is easier to solve. &lt;br/&gt;Classically, this method was used for problems related to Laplace's &lt;br/&gt;equation, such as electrostatics and two dimensional fluid flow. &lt;br/&gt;Numerous non-classical applications have been developed in the last &lt;br/&gt;three decades such as electro-magnetics, vibrating membranes and &lt;br/&gt;acoustics, transverse vibrations and buckling of plates, elasticity, &lt;br/&gt;and heat transfer. Fundamental research in conformal mapping and &lt;br/&gt;conformal field theory are important directions in mathematics and &lt;br/&gt;physics respectively. The fusion of Loewner's differential equation &lt;br/&gt;and probability forms a bridge between these two areas. This project &lt;br/&gt;is likely to increase the understanding of solutions to Loewner's &lt;br/&gt;equation, as foundational work, which should increase its usefulness &lt;br/&gt;in understanding stochastic processes. Broader impacts include the &lt;br/&gt;continued improvement and dissemination of the conformal mapping &lt;br/&gt;computer codes, which have been used by a number of investigators &lt;br/&gt;not in mathematics, as well as mathematicians. Greater speed and new &lt;br/&gt;knowledge of convergence should lead to wider applicability and use &lt;br/&gt;of this algorithm. Broader impacts also include helping to cement a &lt;br/&gt;stronger relationship between modern complex analysis and &lt;br/&gt;mathematical physics, which should benefit both.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/16/2006</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/16/2006</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>0602509</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Donald</FirstName>
<LastName>Marshall</LastName>
<EmailAddress>marshall@math.washington.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>06/16/2006</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Washington</Name>
<CityName>Seattle</CityName>
<ZipCode>981950001</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2065434043</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>4333 Brooklyn Ave NE</StreetAddress>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Washington</StateName>
<StateCode>WA</StateCode>
</Institution>
<FoaInformation>
<Code>0000099</Code>
<Name>Other Applications NEC</Name>
</FoaInformation>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1281</Code>
<Text>ANALYSIS PROGRAM</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>0000</Code>
<Text>UNASSIGNED</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>OTHR</Code>
<Text>OTHER RESEARCH OR EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
</Award>
</rootTag>
