<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Planning Grant for Regional Center of Excellence in Automation and Process Technology</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>05/01/2006</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>04/30/2007</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>71600</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>11040100</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Undergraduate Education</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Russell L. Pimmel</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The project is developing a plan for an ATE Regional Center of Excellence in Automation and Process Technology in the Willamette Valley, Oregon. The ultimate goal of the center is to create an educated worker with the skills and understandings to thrive in today's computerized manufacturing environment. The planning effort is developing and formalizing institutional alliances among regional community colleges, four-year institutions, secondary schools, corporations, industrial councils, and government agencies. It is identifying common, portable skill competencies for process technicians in the four targeted manufacturing sectors, and it is reviewing and evaluating existing educational materials to be packaged into an integrated and modular advanced manufacturing curriculum that is interdisciplinary, competency-based, and occupationally verified. Finally, it is defining career pathways that identify clear educational steps on career paths matched to labor market demand and facilitate student transitions between high school, community college, and four-year institutions. Formative evaluation efforts are focusing on the development of collaborative partnerships, while summative efforts are examining the success in identifying common, portable skills, in reviewing and evaluating existing educational materials, and in defining career pathways that are matched to labor market demand. Dissemination is being carried out through the Professional and Technical Education Deans' Network and the Oregon Association of Career and Technical Education. The broader impacts include a supportive relationship with the Governor's Manufacturing Workforce Committee that is recommending an expansion of community college manufacturing programs and support for regional public-private centers of excellence. The planned Regional Center of Excellence would enhance the connection of community colleges to economic development efforts throughout the state. The project has a special focus on improving the involvement of underrepresented and underserved populations.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>04/28/2006</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>04/28/2006</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0603494</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Ronald</FirstName>
      <LastName>Jantzi</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>janr@chemeketa.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>04/28/2006</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Michael</FirstName>
      <LastName>Dalton</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>michael.dalton@oregonstate.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>04/28/2006</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Tim</FirstName>
      <LastName>Brower</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>browert@oit.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>04/28/2006</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Fred</FirstName>
      <LastName>Haynes</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>haynesf@linnbenton.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>04/28/2006</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Linn Benton Community College</Name>
      <CityName>Albany</CityName>
      <ZipCode>973213755</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>5419174999</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>6500 S W Pacific Blvd</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Oregon</StateName>
      <StateCode>OR</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
