<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Iterated Monodromy Groups</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2006</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2009</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>96155.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>96155</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03040200</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DMS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Joanna Kania-Bartoszynska</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>jkaniaba@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924881</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>&lt;br/&gt;Iterated monodromy groups&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;{First abstract.} The project explores new connections&lt;br/&gt;between geometric group theory and dynamical systems via the&lt;br/&gt;notion of the iterated monodromy group of a self-covering. It&lt;br/&gt;relates a very active branch of geometric group theory (automata&lt;br/&gt;groups and groups acting on rooted trees) with symbolic and&lt;br/&gt;holomorphic dynamics.  Before introduction of iterated monodromy&lt;br/&gt;groups, groups generated by finite automata were mainly isolated&lt;br/&gt;exotic (counter) examples. It is clear now that such groups appear&lt;br/&gt;naturally in connection with iterations of self-coverings of&lt;br/&gt;topological spaces (in particular iterations of post-critically&lt;br/&gt;finite rational functions). This opens new perspectives of&lt;br/&gt;application of holomorphic dynamics to group theory. On the other&lt;br/&gt;hand, computational effectiveness of automata groups helps to&lt;br/&gt;study deeper the combinatorics and symbolic dynamics of&lt;br/&gt;self-coverings. For example, if the self-covering is expanding,&lt;br/&gt;then its Julia set is uniquely determined by the iterated&lt;br/&gt;monodromy group. The project suggests further investigation of the&lt;br/&gt;connections between dynamical systems and automata groups. We&lt;br/&gt;hope, in particular, to get new results in the theory of groups&lt;br/&gt;acting on rooted trees, groups generated by automata, theory of&lt;br/&gt;growth of groups, find new applications of geometric group theory&lt;br/&gt;to combinatorics of iterations of rational functions and&lt;br/&gt;polynomials.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;{Second abstract.} The project brings together two branches&lt;br/&gt;of Mathematics, which where not so close before: geometric group&lt;br/&gt;theory and holomorphic dynamics. Geometric groups theory is a part&lt;br/&gt;of algebra which studies large-scale properties of groups of&lt;br/&gt;symmetries. Holomorphic dynamics studies iterations of rational&lt;br/&gt;and polynomial functions and is a source of complex and beautiful&lt;br/&gt;fractal structures such as Mandelbrot and Julia sets. Iterated&lt;br/&gt;monodromy groups, introduced by the investigator, are naturally&lt;br/&gt;associated with rational iterations and are groups encoding in a&lt;br/&gt;compact symbolic form all the complex topological behavior of the&lt;br/&gt;iterations and geometry of their Julia sets. The construction of&lt;br/&gt;the iterated monodromy group is very natural, but groups obtained&lt;br/&gt;in this way are very exotic from the point of view of classical&lt;br/&gt;group theory. Difference between classical groups and iterated&lt;br/&gt;monodromy groups resembles in some way the difference between the&lt;br/&gt;``smooth'' geometric shapes of the classical geometry and fractal&lt;br/&gt;``wild'' shapes of holomorphic dynamics. Algebraic properties of&lt;br/&gt;iterated monodromy groups remain to be rather mysterious and a&lt;br/&gt;part of the project is to understand them better. We are also&lt;br/&gt;hoping that this new connection between group theory and dynamical&lt;br/&gt;systems will be fruitful for both parts of mathematics, that we&lt;br/&gt;will be able to use group theory to obtain new results in&lt;br/&gt;holomorphic dynamics and to apply holomorphic dynamics to study&lt;br/&gt;new classes of groups.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/13/2006</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/13/2006</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>0605019</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Volodymyr</FirstName>
<LastName>Nekrashevych</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Volodymyr Nekrashevych</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>nekrash@math.tamu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>9798450905</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000491784</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/13/2006</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Texas A&amp;M Research Foundation</Name>
<CityName>College Station</CityName>
<ZipCode>778454375</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>9798626777</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>400 Harvey Mitchell Parkway, S</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[Suite 300]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Texas</StateName>
<StateCode>TX</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>17</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>TX17</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>078592789</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>TEXAS A &amp; M RESEARCH FOUNDATION</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>078592789</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Texas A&amp;M University]]></Name>
<CityName>College Station</CityName>
<StateCode>TX</StateCode>
<ZipCode>778454375</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[400 Harvey Mitchell Pkwy South]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Texas</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>17</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>TX17</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<FoaInformation>
<Code>0000099</Code>
<Name>Other Applications NEC</Name>
</FoaInformation>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1267</Code>
<Text>TOPOLOGY</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>0000</Code>
<Text>UNASSIGNED</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>OTHR</Code>
<Text>OTHER RESEARCH OR EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0106</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>490100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2006~96155</FUND_OBLG>
</Award>
</rootTag>
