<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>PRECISION MEASUREMENT OF STELLAR SIZES AND CIRCUMSTELLAR MATERIAL WITH 10 MICRON INTERFEROMETRY AND NARROW FREQUENCY BANDWIDTHS</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/15/2006</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2007</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>143735.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>143735</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03020415</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>AST</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Astronomical Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Michael M. Briley</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>ABSTRACT&lt;br/&gt;The Berkeley Infrared Spatial Interferometer is a unique system of three 1.65-meter&lt;br/&gt;telescopes located at the Mt. Wilson Observatory. Its baselines range from 4 to&lt;br/&gt;approximately 75 meters and it is capable of 20 milliarcsecond resolution. The system&lt;br/&gt;uses heterodyne detection with a bandwidth of 0.2/cm and the resulting signals can be&lt;br/&gt;filters to obtain arbitrarily narrow spectral widths. The recent addition of a third telescope&lt;br/&gt;has allowed phase closure measurements to an accuracy of 1 degree, which allows nearly&lt;br/&gt;complete Fourier analysis of intensity patterns, including asymmetries.&lt;br/&gt;An observing program of evolved late-type stars will be continued using the&lt;br/&gt;interferometer. The sizes of such stars and select associated features (surrounding dust&lt;br/&gt;distributions and asymmetries, water vapor envelopes, etc.) will be directly measured.&lt;br/&gt;The narrow bandwidth capability will allow the atomic and molecular spectral lines of&lt;br/&gt;surrounding gas to be avoided or selected yielding, among other characteristics, reliable&lt;br/&gt;and realistic stellar sizes. The observations will follow the changes in size of prominent&lt;br/&gt;Mira variable stars as a function of phase and examine possible departures from&lt;br/&gt;sphericity of Miras and red giants. Previous studies with the interferometer have shown&lt;br/&gt;movements of dust clouds surrounding late-type stars as well as deviations of the clouds&lt;br/&gt;from spherical symmetry. Studies of these variations will be continued to provide&lt;br/&gt;information on the motion of dust clouds around stars, and from this and Doppler&lt;br/&gt;measurements, also a determination of distances.&lt;br/&gt;The work here will provide training for young scientists (a postdoctoral research&lt;br/&gt;associate) and students (2 graduate students as well as undergraduates) who will have&lt;br/&gt;hands-on opportunities to learn optics, electronics, computer control systems, data&lt;br/&gt;analysis, and scientific interpretation. Interferometry and instrumentation are two areas of&lt;br/&gt;high priority for the astronomical community and the education of the next generation of&lt;br/&gt;instrument builders is critical the field's continued success.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/17/2006</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/17/2006</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>0606839</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Charles</FirstName>
<LastName>Townes</LastName>
<EmailAddress>cht@ssl.berkeley.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>07/17/2006</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of California-Berkeley</Name>
<CityName>BERKELEY</CityName>
<ZipCode>947101749</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5106433891</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>Sponsored Projects Office</StreetAddress>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
</Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1215</Code>
<Text>STELLAR ASTRONOMY &amp; ASTROPHYSC</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>0000</Code>
<Text>UNASSIGNED</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1207</Code>
<Text>OBSERVATIONAL ASTRONOMY</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>OTHR</Code>
<Text>OTHER RESEARCH OR EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
</Award>
</rootTag>
