<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Fundamental Stellar Parameters from the CHARA Array</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/15/2006</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2010</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>706158.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>706158</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03020400</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>AST</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Astronomical Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Donald M. Terndrup</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>&lt;br/&gt;This award supports the Georgia State University's Center for High Angular Resolution&lt;br/&gt;Astronomy (CHARA). The CHARA Array consists of six 1-m aperture telescopes&lt;br/&gt;operating in the optical/near infrared and arranged in a Y configuration which provides&lt;br/&gt;15 baselines from 33 to 331 meters in length. In terms of the number and aperture size of&lt;br/&gt;its telescopes and the length of its baselines, the CHARA Array is among the most&lt;br/&gt;powerful facilities of its type in the world.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Built with funds provided by Georgia State University (GSU), the NSF, the W.M. Keck&lt;br/&gt;Foundation, and the David and Lucile Packard Foundation, the CHARA Array has&lt;br/&gt;undertaken several extensive observational programs with a broad impact on stellar&lt;br/&gt;astrophysics. These include measuring the oblateness and other physical parameters&lt;br/&gt;(including gravity darkening) for the rapidly rotating stars Regulus, Alderamin, and&lt;br/&gt;Vega; checking the Baade-Wesselink method for calibrating the Cepheid periodluminosity&lt;br/&gt;relation; detecting the circumstellar envelopes of Delta Cephei and Polaris&lt;br/&gt;(two Cepheid variables) and showing that emission from these envelopes must be&lt;br/&gt;modeled to avoid biases in the Baade-Wesselink method; discovering that solar&lt;br/&gt;metallicity M dwarfs are larger than similar mass but lower metallicity M dwarfs which&lt;br/&gt;implies an additional opacity source not included in current models; and measuring the&lt;br/&gt;angular separation between the components of the binary star 12 Persei to an accuracy of&lt;br/&gt;0.05% their separation thereby improving the accuracy of their derived masses.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;During the award period, several science programs will be carried out which continue to&lt;br/&gt;capitalize on CHARA's unique capabilities. These include the measurement of stellar&lt;br/&gt;angular diameters of brighter stars to better than 1% accuracy. This will allow the critical&lt;br/&gt;testing of stellar atmosphere codes (including effective temperatures and brightness&lt;br/&gt;profiles) at temperatures from M to B. Evolved stars will be included as well to&lt;br/&gt;characterize the scale heights of their atmospheres. Pulsations of more Cepheid variables&lt;br/&gt;will be measured to further calibrate the Baade-Wesselink method. The properties of&lt;br/&gt;disks surrounding Be stars will also be characterized. With regard to binaries, CHARA's&lt;br/&gt;high angular resolution will be used to resolve spectroscopic binaries, which will in turn&lt;br/&gt;allow high quality measurements of stellar mass, luminosity, and radius for stars across&lt;br/&gt;the Hertzsprung-Russell Diagram. Known extrasolar planetary systems will also be&lt;br/&gt;inspected to ensure face-on binaries are not contaminating the samples.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The training of the next generation of scientific and technical experts in interferometry&lt;br/&gt;will also continue. CHARA is enhancing scientific awareness through the incorporation&lt;br/&gt;of its results into the large undergraduate courses taught at Georgia State. Thousands of&lt;br/&gt;public visitors to Mt. Wilson will also have the opportunity to interactively learn the&lt;br/&gt;principles of interferometry through a display at the CHARA Exhibit Hall on Mt. Wilson&lt;br/&gt;(which also houses the 20-foot Michelson Stellar Interferometer used at the 100-inch&lt;br/&gt;telescope).</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/10/2006</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/12/2008</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>0606958</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Harold</FirstName>
<LastName>McAlister</LastName>
<EmailAddress>hal@chara.gsu.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>07/10/2006</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>William</FirstName>
<LastName>Bagnuolo</LastName>
<EmailAddress>bagnuolo@chara.gsu.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>07/10/2006</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Stephen</FirstName>
<LastName>Ridgway</LastName>
<EmailAddress>sridgway@noao.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>07/10/2006</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Theo</FirstName>
<LastName>ten Brummelaar</LastName>
<EmailAddress>theo@chara-array.org</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>07/10/2006</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Douglas</FirstName>
<LastName>Gies</LastName>
<EmailAddress>gies@chara.gsu.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>07/10/2006</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Georgia State University Research Foundation, Inc.</Name>
<CityName>Atlanta</CityName>
<ZipCode>303032921</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>4044133570</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>58 Edgewood Avenue</StreetAddress>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Georgia</StateName>
<StateCode>GA</StateCode>
</Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1215</Code>
<Text>STELLAR ASTRONOMY &amp; ASTROPHYSC</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>0000</Code>
<Text>UNASSIGNED</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1207</Code>
<Text>OBSERVATIONAL ASTRONOMY</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>OTHR</Code>
<Text>OTHER RESEARCH OR EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
</Award>
</rootTag>
