<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Support for the 8th International Workshop on Discrete Event Systems-WODES '06.  The workshop will be held on July 10-12, 2006 in Ann Arbor on the campus of University of Michigan</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>06/01/2006</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2007</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>10000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>10000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07010000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>ECCS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Electrical, Commun &amp; Cyber Sys</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Radhakisan Baheti</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>B Project Summary&lt;br/&gt;Support is sought from NSF to help with the organization of the 8th International Workshop on Discrete&lt;br/&gt;Event Systems - WODES06, to be held in Ann Arbor on the campus of the University of Michigan, July 10-&lt;br/&gt;12, 2006. WODES is a bi-annual series of conferences entirely devoted to the field of discrete event systems.&lt;br/&gt;It is attended by 100-150 researchers (primarily from academia), with considerable international diversity.&lt;br/&gt;All past seven editions of WODES have been held in Europe, every other year since 1992. WODES conferences&lt;br/&gt;are not financially sponsored by any technical organization. In the past, host institutions have been&lt;br/&gt;sponsoring the conference.&lt;br/&gt;WODES06 is the first edition ofWODES to be held in the US. It will provide researchers from different&lt;br/&gt;fields (control theoreticians and control engineers, software engineers and computer scientists, operations&lt;br/&gt;research specialists) with an opportunity to exchange information and new ideas, and to discuss new developments&lt;br/&gt;on the theory and applications of discrete event systems. The conference will be particularly&lt;br/&gt;attractive to US students in these fields who have not been able to attend WODES in the past. It offers&lt;br/&gt;a unique opportunity for them to get exposed to the latest research trends in the multidisciplinary area of&lt;br/&gt;discrete event systems. The organizers of the conference intend to offer reduced registration rates to student&lt;br/&gt;attendees in order to encourage their participation. Moreover, the organizers are making a special effort&lt;br/&gt;to solicit participation of industrial researchers at the conference through industrial sponsorship, invited&lt;br/&gt;sessions, and software demonstrations.&lt;br/&gt;Broader Impacts: WODES06 will have broad educational impact on the US graduate student community&lt;br/&gt;in control engineering, embedded systems, software systems, and operations research as well as broad&lt;br/&gt;impact in bringing together theoreticians and practitioners with interest in modeling, analysis, verification,&lt;br/&gt;diagnosis, control, optimization, and simulation of discrete event systems.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/05/2006</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/05/2006</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>0607076</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Dawn</FirstName>
<LastName>Tilbury</LastName>
<EmailAddress>tilbury@umich.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>07/05/2006</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Stephane</FirstName>
<LastName>Lafortune</LastName>
<EmailAddress>stephane@umich.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>07/05/2006</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Regents of the University of Michigan - Ann Arbor</Name>
<CityName>Ann Arbor</CityName>
<ZipCode>481091274</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>7347636438</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>3003 South State St. Room 1062</StreetAddress>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Michigan</StateName>
<StateCode>MI</StateCode>
</Institution>
<FoaInformation>
<Code>0112000</Code>
<Name>System Theory</Name>
</FoaInformation>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7607</Code>
<Text>EPCN-Energy-Power-Ctrl-Netwrks</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>0000</Code>
<Text>UNASSIGNED</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>093E</Code>
<Text>System fab/packaging &amp; assembly</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7238</Code>
<Text>ENG ITR CORE ACTIVITIES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>OTHR</Code>
<Text>OTHER RESEARCH OR EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
</Award>
</rootTag>
