<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>NIRT: Nuclear hyperpolarization for organic and inorganic semiconductor nanostructures</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2006</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2011</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardAmount>1100000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07010000</Code>
<Directorate>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<LongName>Div Of Electrical, Commun &amp; Cyber Sys</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>John Zavada</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This work will use optical pumping (OP) and spin-injection (SI) methods to&lt;br/&gt;generate massively athermal nuclear spin polarizations for exploitation in nanostructured&lt;br/&gt;semiconductor devices. The proposed research aims to develop a fundamental&lt;br/&gt;understanding of the electron-nuclear cross relaxation in a host of materials engineered to&lt;br/&gt;exhibit structural features ranging from bulk to mesoscale to quantum dots. In the course&lt;br/&gt;of these studies, new phenomenology in the form of nuclear spin hyperpolarization in&lt;br/&gt;novel inorganic and polymeric semiconductor structures is anticipated as well as the&lt;br/&gt;development of new analytical tools for the measurement of nuclear polarization. This&lt;br/&gt;work will use the newly developed understanding of OP and SI to design new application&lt;br/&gt;experiments and devices.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The intellectual merit of the proposed work lies in the assertion that measurement&lt;br/&gt;and observation are of intrinsic and fundamental value in developing an understanding of&lt;br/&gt;the natural world. A more complete understanding of nuclear hyperpolarization could&lt;br/&gt;potentially overcome limitations in current analytical spectroscopic methods (i.e., NMR,&lt;br/&gt;MRI) by providing the mechanism for greatly enhanced signals as well as assist in the&lt;br/&gt;creation of spintronics and quantum computing devices.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The proposed research is expected to have a broad educational outcome because it&lt;br/&gt;will offer students a unique inter-disciplinary scientific education and exposure to teams&lt;br/&gt;of diverse and complimentary backgrounds. Undergraduate students from both CCNY&lt;br/&gt;and UC Berkeley will be involved in the research and will spend summers visiting the&lt;br/&gt;alternate campus to broaden their scientific horizons. This research will also be used to&lt;br/&gt;inspire freshmen during a pivotal point of their undergraduate education through a series&lt;br/&gt;of seminar discussion courses. Long-distance seminars and group meetings between the&lt;br/&gt;CCNY and UC Berkeley groups will be used to ensure the synergistic nature of the&lt;br/&gt;consortium.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/15/2006</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/15/2006</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>0608763</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Jeffrey</FirstName>
<LastName>Reimer</LastName>
<EmailAddress>reimer@berkeley.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>06/15/2006</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Maria</FirstName>
<LastName>Tamargo</LastName>
<EmailAddress>mtamargo@ccny.cuny.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>06/15/2006</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Rachel</FirstName>
<LastName>Segalman</LastName>
<EmailAddress>segalman@engineering.ucsb.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>06/15/2006</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Carlos</FirstName>
<LastName>Meriles</LastName>
<EmailAddress>cmeriles@ccny.cuny.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>06/15/2006</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>CUNY City College</Name>
<CityName>New York</CityName>
<ZipCode>100319101</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2126505418</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>Convent Ave at 138th St</StreetAddress>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
</Institution>
<FoaInformation>
<Code>0206000</Code>
<Name>Telecommunications</Name>
</FoaInformation>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1674</Code>
<Text>NANOSCALE: INTRDISCPL RESRCH T</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>0000</Code>
<Text>UNASSIGNED</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>101E</Code>
<Text>Printed and flexible electronics</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1674</Code>
<Text>NANOSCALE: INTRDISCPL RESRCH T</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>OTHR</Code>
<Text>OTHER RESEARCH OR EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
</Award>
</rootTag>
