<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Dissertation Research - Molecular Phylogeny of Cuphea P. Browne (Lythraceae) in North America: Evolution of Floral Morphology, Chromosome Number, and Seed Oil Composition</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>06/15/2006</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2008</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardAmount>9486</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>08010206</Code>
<Directorate>
<LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<LongName>Division Of Environmental Biology</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Richard M. McCourt</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Pollinator specialization is believed to drive plant diversification and evolutionary radiation. Recently, ecologists have criticized the concept that a flower's shape is directly related to a specific pollinator because flowers may receive visits from several kinds of pollinators. Species of the genus Cuphea in North America are ideal plants to test diversification theories because they exhibit a wide range of floral morphology, pollination syndromes, and chromosome numbers and occur in different habitats. Cuphea species are also of interest due to the great variation in their seed oils which have worldwide importance as ingredients in livestock feed, detergents, cosmetics and biodiesel fuel.  A molecular phylogeny of North American Cuphea will provide a framework that will enable the investigators to analyze evolutionary patterns in floral morphology, pollination syndromes, chromosome numbers, and test the influence of ecology on seed oil composition.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This study will identify closely related species that may be of interest to agricultural researchers and provide insights into the nature of genetic variation in Cuphea. This project will build collaborations between Saint Louis University, the Missouri Botanical Garden, and the University of Georgia and provide training for the graduate co-PI and several undergraduates in taxonomy, molecular phylogenetics, and biochemical analysis.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>05/26/2006</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/26/2006</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>0608248</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Janet</FirstName>
<LastName>Barber</LastName>
<EmailAddress>barberjc@slu.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>05/26/2006</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Saint Louis University</Name>
<CityName>St Louis</CityName>
<ZipCode>631032006</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>3149773925</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>221 N. Grand Blvd.</StreetAddress>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Missouri</StateName>
<StateCode>MO</StateCode>
</Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1171</Code>
<Text>PHYLOGENETIC SYSTEMATICS</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1171</Code>
<Text>PHYLOGENETIC SYSTEMATICS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9169</Code>
<Text>BIODIVERSITY AND ECOSYSTEM DYNAMICS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>EGCH</Code>
<Text>ENVIRONMENT AND GLOBAL CHANGE</Text>
</ProgramReference>
</Award>
</rootTag>
