<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Future Directions in Karst Research: A Workshop Proposal</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2006</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2007</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>23375</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>06030109</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Earth Sciences</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>L. Douglas James</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>Martin&lt;br/&gt;0608945&lt;br/&gt;Intellectual Merit The Karst Waters Institute plans to sponsor an interdisciplinary&lt;br/&gt;workshop on Research Directions in Karst Research. This workshop is designed to&lt;br/&gt;bring together biologists, biogeochemists, microbial ecologists, hydrogeologists, and&lt;br/&gt;geomorphologists who have an interest in advancing all aspects of karst science. The&lt;br/&gt;workshop will in part assess the current state of knowledge, but its primary function will&lt;br/&gt;be to identify gaps in that knowledge and to describe (and write down) a road map for&lt;br/&gt;closing those gaps. The workshop discussions will include questions from disciplines&lt;br/&gt;outside of karst science (e.g. paleoclimate, microbiology) that can be addressed in karst&lt;br/&gt;areas. The workshop is not intended to be a meeting at which only recent scientific&lt;br/&gt;findings are discussed; instead, the workshop will be tightly structured leading to&lt;br/&gt;identification of the critical science questions to be investigated over the coming decade.&lt;br/&gt;The workshop is tentatively planned for three days in Fall of 2006 with tightly&lt;br/&gt;orchestrated logistics. Following a short introductory plenary session, the participants&lt;br/&gt;will be broken into disciplinary groups to discuss the important current science questions&lt;br/&gt;within their specialties. Three plenary sessions will be interspersed with the disciplinary&lt;br/&gt;break-out sessions throughout the workshop to allow cross-disciplinary discussions and&lt;br/&gt;integration of topical science questions. At the end of the workshop and while still on&lt;br/&gt;location at the workshop venue, the key participants (disciplinary leaders and workshop&lt;br/&gt;conveners) will write the initial draft of a report outlining the state of the science in karst&lt;br/&gt;research and focus on what questions should be investigated over the next 10 years. The&lt;br/&gt;final draft of the report will be completed by the workshop conveners within several&lt;br/&gt;months of the meeting&lt;br/&gt;Broader Impacts The workshop should positively impact the human resources of a&lt;br/&gt;variety of disciplines including karst science, hydrology, microbiology, and ecology. The&lt;br/&gt;funding requested here will be used to offset travel and per diem expenses incurred by the&lt;br/&gt;participants, with the primary support going to students, junior faculty and disciplinary&lt;br/&gt;group leaders. Efforts will be made to include under-represented groups in the workshop.&lt;br/&gt;The workshop will be advertised in several professional outlets including web resources,&lt;br/&gt;EOS, Geotimes, GSA Today, and Bulletin of the Ecological Society of America to assure&lt;br/&gt;broad interdisciplinary participation. Additional funding is being requested from other&lt;br/&gt;agencies and KWI has allocated $10,000 toward the workshop for travel support,&lt;br/&gt;advertising, publication costs and other incidental expenses.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>06/16/2006</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>06/16/2006</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0608945</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Jonathan</FirstName>
      <LastName>Martin</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>jbmartin@ufl.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>06/16/2006</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Karst Water Institute</Name>
      <CityName>Charles Town</CityName>
      <ZipCode>254140490</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>7028950451</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>P.O Box 490</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>West Virginia</StateName>
      <StateCode>WV</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0000099</Code>
      <Name>Other Applications NEC</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
