<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Finite Element Approximation of Partial Differential Equations</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2006</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2010</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>189878</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03040000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Junping Wang</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The first area of proposed research involves the study of compatible&lt;br/&gt;discretization schemes for partial differential equations, an approach that&lt;br/&gt;attempts to produce numerical approximations that inherit or mimic&lt;br/&gt;fundamental properties of a partial differential equation, such as&lt;br/&gt;conservation and symmetries. Several problems, modeling phenomena in&lt;br/&gt;elasticity and fluids, will be studied from this point of view. The new&lt;br/&gt;approach taken is based on the construction of piecewise polynomial exact&lt;br/&gt;elasticity sequences, which are closely related to the development of stable&lt;br/&gt;mixed finite element schemes. Other work in this area includes a new &lt;br/&gt;approach to the construction of hierarchical bases for scalar and vector-valued &lt;br/&gt;finite element spaces in arbitrary space dimensions, and exact sequence &lt;br/&gt;properties of rectangular and quadrilateral finite elements and their applications to the&lt;br/&gt;stability of mixed finite element approximation. The second area of &lt;br/&gt;study is the approximation properties of several types of finite element spaces &lt;br/&gt;defined on irregular hexahedral elements obtained by trilinear mappings from a&lt;br/&gt;reference cube. Such spaces are used to approximate three-dimensional vector&lt;br/&gt;functions and arise naturally in many applications, including the &lt;br/&gt;approximation of Maxwell's equations and the use of mixed and least squares finite element&lt;br/&gt;methods for second order elliptic equations. Although it is often implicitly&lt;br/&gt;assumed that approximation results known for regular hexahedrons extend to&lt;br/&gt;these spaces, in fact this is not the case. The research is to determine&lt;br/&gt;precisely what is needed for optimal order approximation and construct&lt;br/&gt;families of finite element spaces that have this property. The third &lt;br/&gt;area of research is to study convergence rates for discontinuous Galerkin &lt;br/&gt;methods for linear hyperbolic problems. Although optimal order convergence rates are&lt;br/&gt;often seen in practice, the theory guarantees such rates only for uniform&lt;br/&gt;meshes, while a lower rate is known to be the best possible on specially&lt;br/&gt;constructed meshes. The proposed research is to classify the type of meshes&lt;br/&gt;for which the optimal convergence rate is achieved.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Mathematical modeling of physical and biological processes using partial&lt;br/&gt;differential equations has become the standard method of studying a host of&lt;br/&gt;important problems. Such models capture in a concise and precise way the&lt;br/&gt;fundamental features of the process being modeled. Unfortunately, the&lt;br/&gt;resulting equations rarely have solutions that can be expressed by simple&lt;br/&gt;mathematical formulas. Hence, the development of reliable and efficient&lt;br/&gt;numerical approximation schemes are necessary to make this method into a&lt;br/&gt;practical approach and is central to progress in many areas of science and&lt;br/&gt;engineering. Part of this development involves the investigation of the&lt;br/&gt;theoretical underpinnings of numerical methods. Such investigation can lead&lt;br/&gt;to a greater understanding of existing methods and to the development of new&lt;br/&gt;methods with desirable properties. Thus, such study has the potential to&lt;br/&gt;improve the accuracy of, or even make possible, essential computer &lt;br/&gt;simulations performed by scientists and engineers. This project is concerned with the&lt;br/&gt;study of numerical methods for approximating equations modeling phenomena in&lt;br/&gt;elasticity and fluid flow. One central theme is to develop approximation&lt;br/&gt;schemes that preserve discrete versions of some of the fundamental &lt;br/&gt;properties of the mathematical model, in order to more accurately capture the &lt;br/&gt;fundamental features of the underlying process being modeled.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>06/14/2006</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>06/14/2006</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0609755</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Richard</FirstName>
      <LastName>Falk</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>falk@math.rutgers.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>06/14/2006</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Rutgers University New Brunswick</Name>
      <CityName>Piscataway</CityName>
      <ZipCode>088543925</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>8489320150</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>33 Knightsbridge Road</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>New Jersey</StateName>
      <StateCode>NJ</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0000099</Code>
      <Name>Other Applications NEC</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>1271</Code>
      <Text>COMPUTATIONAL MATHEMATICS</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>0000</Code>
      <Text>UNASSIGNED</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>9263</Code>
      <Text>COMPUTATIONAL SCIENCE &amp; ENGING</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>OTHR</Code>
      <Text>OTHER RESEARCH OR EDUCATION</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
