<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Locally Optimal Preconditioned Eigenvalue Solvers</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/15/2006</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2010</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardAmount>249542</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Junping Wang</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The area of preconditioned iterative solvers for eigenvalue &lt;br/&gt;computations is rapidly developing. Software implementations of &lt;br/&gt;several preconditioned eigensolvers, in particular, the locally &lt;br/&gt;optimal block preconditioned conjugate gradient (LOBPCG) method &lt;br/&gt;developed by the principal investigator (PI) earlier, are being &lt;br/&gt;written. The recent progress opens new opportunities to develop &lt;br/&gt;efficient preconditioned iterative solvers for interior eigenvalues &lt;br/&gt;and singular value computations.  The use of preconditioned &lt;br/&gt;eigensolvers in applications raises new area-specific important &lt;br/&gt;issues, both practical and theoretical, which need to be resolved. The &lt;br/&gt;proposed research addresses these issues based on the success of the &lt;br/&gt;previous work of the PI. The PI expects to advance the theory of some &lt;br/&gt;known methods, to discover new locally optimal algorithms, and to be &lt;br/&gt;able to provide specific recommendations concerning the choice of &lt;br/&gt;methods. The following specific and interrelated research projects are&lt;br/&gt;proposed: reducing the LOBPCG costs for large block sizes; developing &lt;br/&gt;efficient preconditioned solvers for interior eigenvalues and singular &lt;br/&gt;value computations; finite element method error analysis for &lt;br/&gt;eigenproblems resulting from partial differential equations with &lt;br/&gt;highly discontinuous coefficients. The projects form a balanced mix of &lt;br/&gt;theoretical research and code development. Numerical simulations are &lt;br/&gt;to be performed on modern parallel computing systems, such as the IBM &lt;br/&gt;BlueGene/L supercomputer.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The ideas behind the proposed research are original, and build on &lt;br/&gt;prior work. The project addresses mathematically difficult and &lt;br/&gt;practically important problems. The broader impact resulting from the &lt;br/&gt;proposed activity is twofold: Ph.D. education and advances in &lt;br/&gt;software.  Funds are requested in the proposal to support Ph.D. &lt;br/&gt;students. Improvement of the software currently used and development &lt;br/&gt;of new codes for scientists and engineers creates potential advances, &lt;br/&gt;e.g., in analyzing extremely large data sets, which is important for &lt;br/&gt;national security.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/10/2006</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/26/2008</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>0612751</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Andrew</FirstName>
<LastName>Knyazev</LastName>
<EmailAddress>Andrew.Knyazev@ucdenver.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>08/10/2006</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Colorado at Denver-Downtown Campus</Name>
<CityName>Aurora</CityName>
<ZipCode>800452571</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>3037240090</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>F428, AMC Bldg 500</StreetAddress>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Colorado</StateName>
<StateCode>CO</StateCode>
</Institution>
<FoaInformation>
<Code>0000099</Code>
<Name>Other Applications NEC</Name>
</FoaInformation>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1271</Code>
<Text>COMPUTATIONAL MATHEMATICS</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>0000</Code>
<Text>UNASSIGNED</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9263</Code>
<Text>COMPUTATIONAL SCIENCE &amp; ENGING</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>OTHR</Code>
<Text>OTHER RESEARCH OR EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
</Award>
</rootTag>
