<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Collaborative Research: Proposal for Establishing an Industry/University Cooperative Research Center for Precision Forming</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>04/15/2006</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>03/31/2013</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>400000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>629212</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07070000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>IIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Industrial Innovation &amp; Partnersh</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Rathindra DasGupta</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The Ohio State University and the University of Michigan have established a multi-university Industry/University Cooperative Research Center (I/UCRC) for Precision Forming.    The mission of the I/UCRC is to serve as a center of excellence for the creation and dissemination of a systematic body of knowledge in precision forming and fabrication of lightweight-high strength materials of interest in this century, and ultimately to impact the next-generation products and production systems with precision, responsiveness and near-zero waste.  The objectives of this I/UCRC are to explore, conduct research and to bring about innovation and practical solutions by focusing on industrially relevant research needs; foster collaborative and interdisciplinary research projects between industrial and academic engineers and scientists; and promote intra-university research activities and prepare the next generation of engineering graduates for the metal forming industry.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>04/14/2006</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/23/2010</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>0613007</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Taylan</FirstName>
<LastName>Altan</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Taylan Altan</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>altan.1@osu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6142925063</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000469689</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/14/2006</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Ohio State University Research Foundation -DO NOT USE</Name>
<CityName>Columbus</CityName>
<ZipCode>432101016</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6146888734</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1960 KENNY RD</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Ohio</StateName>
<StateCode>OH</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>OH03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>071650709</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>OHIO STATE UNIVERSITY RESEARCH FOUNDATION, THE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Ohio State University]]></Name>
<CityName>Columbus</CityName>
<StateCode>OH</StateCode>
<ZipCode>432101016</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[Office of Sponsored Programs]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Ohio</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>OH03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<FoaInformation>
<Code>0400000</Code>
<Name>Industry University - Co-op</Name>
</FoaInformation>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>5761</Code>
<Text>IUCRC-Indust-Univ Coop Res Ctr</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7609</Code>
<Text>IUCRC FUNDAMENTAL RESEARCH</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>0000</Code>
<Text>UNASSIGNED</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1049</Code>
<Text>INDUSTRY-UNIV COOPERATIVE RSCH PROJECTS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>122E</Code>
<Text>CENTERS: OTHER INDUSTRY-UNIV</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>129E</Code>
<Text>CENTERS: MANUFACTURING &amp; PROC</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>5761</Code>
<Text>INDUSTRY/UNIV COOP RES CENTERS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>OTHR</Code>
<Text>OTHER RESEARCH OR EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0106</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>490100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0107</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>490100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0108</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0109</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0110</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2006~80000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2007~205000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2008~59918</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2009~154914</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2010~129380</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The outcomes of the award can be summarized as follows:</p> <p>1. Cup Draw Test was developed to evaluate lubricants for forming galvannealed steeel, AHSS and aluminum. 'Good' lubricants were identified to form galvannealed draw quality steel, which are used in manufacturing outer body. This test is accepted by many companies for use in industry.</p> <p>2. An inverse methodology to obtain flow stress data of materials using the dome test was developed. Work is in progress to develop a "quasi" standard for obtaining strain-stress data under biaxial conditions for sheet materials.</p> <p>3. The capability to simulate the hot stamping was using Finite Element Analysis was developed. This would enable to optimize process parameters in real life industrial environment at much lesser cost.</p> <p>4. The phenomenon of springback in different AHSS materials was understood using experiments and simulations. This would be useful in predicting and overcoming springback issues in the industrial world.</p> <p>5. An idea to improve punch and die life in blanking by having variable punch-die clearance was developed and proved experimentally. The life of the punch increased almost three times when the variable clearance was selected.</p> <p>6. The use of servo press in forming high strength steels has been investigated to improve formability, reduce springback and increase productivity in industrial applications.</p> <p>Overall, contributions have been made in the area of forming low formability, high strength, light-weight materials used in the automotive industry to serve their need to acheive better fuel efficiency.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 05/29/2013<br>      Modified by: Taylan&nbsp;Altan</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The outcomes of the award can be summarized as follows:  1. Cup Draw Test was developed to evaluate lubricants for forming galvannealed steeel, AHSS and aluminum. 'Good' lubricants were identified to form galvannealed draw quality steel, which are used in manufacturing outer body. This test is accepted by many companies for use in industry.  2. An inverse methodology to obtain flow stress data of materials using the dome test was developed. Work is in progress to develop a "quasi" standard for obtaining strain-stress data under biaxial conditions for sheet materials.  3. The capability to simulate the hot stamping was using Finite Element Analysis was developed. This would enable to optimize process parameters in real life industrial environment at much lesser cost.  4. The phenomenon of springback in different AHSS materials was understood using experiments and simulations. This would be useful in predicting and overcoming springback issues in the industrial world.  5. An idea to improve punch and die life in blanking by having variable punch-die clearance was developed and proved experimentally. The life of the punch increased almost three times when the variable clearance was selected.  6. The use of servo press in forming high strength steels has been investigated to improve formability, reduce springback and increase productivity in industrial applications.  Overall, contributions have been made in the area of forming low formability, high strength, light-weight materials used in the automotive industry to serve their need to acheive better fuel efficiency.       Last Modified: 05/29/2013       Submitted by: Taylan Altan]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
