<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>High Impact Design Requirements for Software Intensive Systems: The Challenge of New Computing Environments</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/15/2006</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2008</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>96771.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>96771</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>05010000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>CSE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CCF</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division of Computing and Communication Foundations</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Sol Greenspan</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>NSF Proposal 0613606&lt;br/&gt;PI: Kalle Lyytinen&lt;br/&gt;Case Western Reserve University&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;High Impact Design Requirements for Software Intensive Systems-  The Challenge of New Computing Environments&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project is aimed at building up a robust community of design researchers around requirements capture and management with heterogeneous backgrounds.  The aim is to organize workshops and conduct fact finding studies to bring new paradigms, theories concepts, approaches into the development of a strong intellectual&lt;br/&gt;foundation for software design for new computing environments. The theme of the workshop is formulating principles, foundations and guidance for identifying, soliciting, deriving and managing design requirements. These issues are discussed around a number of research streams including human computer interaction, software design and architectures, formal specification and verification, business models and enterprise architectures, industrial and media design. The workshop seeks to find differences and commonalities across&lt;br/&gt;communities and to analyze how new computing environments challenge the design practice in each. The aim is to build up a research vision of requirements identification, capture, verification and management&lt;br/&gt;that addresses challenges of designing software intensive systems in the 21st century that are characterized increasingly by industrial, media and business design.  The following issues will be addressed: 1) what is the changing scope of requirements in software intensive systems, 2) how can we adjust and expand current design principles to capture broadened concerns for usability, security, business value across a set of applications.  &lt;br/&gt;The workshop seeks to identify challenges faced by designers and takeholders in specifying requirements for high impact designs, and to outline features of design approaches that can address these challenges from a multi-disciplinary perspective. The workshop is expected to produce a special issue in requirements engineering journal and a book on new design practices which approaches the concerns from multiple disciplinary practices.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>09/08/2006</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>09/08/2006</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>0613606</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Kalle</FirstName>
<LastName>Lyytinen</LastName>
<EmailAddress>kalle@po.cwru.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>09/08/2006</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Case Western Reserve University</Name>
<CityName>CLEVELAND</CityName>
<ZipCode>441064901</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2163684510</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>Nord Hall, Suite 615</StreetAddress>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Ohio</StateName>
<StateCode>OH</StateCode>
</Institution>
<FoaInformation>
<Code>0000912</Code>
<Name>Computer Science</Name>
</FoaInformation>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7372</Code>
<Text>ITR-SCIENCE OF DESIGN</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7372</Code>
<Text>ITR-SCIENCE OF DESIGN</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9218</Code>
<Text>BASIC RESEARCH &amp; HUMAN RESORCS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>HPCC</Code>
<Text>HIGH PERFORMANCE COMPUTING &amp; COMM</Text>
</ProgramReference>
</Award>
</rootTag>
