<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Doctoral Dissertation in DRMS:    Choice Sets and Consumer Selection of Health Plans</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2006</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2007</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardAmount>11139</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>04050100</Code>
<Directorate>
<LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<LongName>Divn Of Social and Economic Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Robert E. O'Connor</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This project studies consumers' response to an increasing number of options among valued goods and services. Conventional economic theory predicts that more options increase the probability of consumers finding and choosing a product that well matches their preferences.  The literature on bounded rationality, however, suggests otherwise. Research involving low-cost consumer goods documents that as the number of options increase, consumers show a greater propensity to a) refuse to make a choice  ("choice deferral"), despite having options they would have selected  in more restricted sets, and b) make errors in their decision making ("choice pathologies"). Although suggestive, these recent studies leave important questions unanswered. Are choice deferral and associated pathologies evident for high-stakes choices?  How is the magnitude of these effects related to  the number of choices?  Does bounded rationality reflect that consumers' cognitive capacities have been exceeded or simply reflect consumers' uncertainty about their preferences? This project addresses these questions, applied to contemporary choices among health insurance plans.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The answers are relevant to contemporary health care reform in the United States. Increasing consumer choice is the hallmark of recent policy changes, ranging from the Medicare Modernization Act to consumer-directed health plans in the private sector.  Medicare beneficiaries now have (depending on their place of residence) upwards of 10 options if they wish to enroll in a managed care plan under Medicare Part C and upwards of 50 prescription drug plans as part of Medicare Part D.  Anecdotal reports of consumer confusion about Medicare C and D, combined with low take-up rates for Part D benefits,  demonstrate the potential relevance of cognitive constraints.  &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Using mixed methods, we test whether larger choice sets are associated with  (1) consumers deferring choice of health plans, foregoing options that would have been selected in a smaller choice set, (2) consumers failing to disenroll from poorly performing plans (leaving them vulnerable and muting market signals), and (3) consumers who do choose  making more errors in selecting among plans. We will use experimental techniques to identity whether choice deferral and associated pathologies exist for health plans and explore why they exist. We then analyze survey data to identify the prevalence and magnitude of these effects in real-world choices involving health plans.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/13/2006</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/13/2006</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>0615538</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Mark</FirstName>
<LastName>Schlesinger</LastName>
<EmailAddress>mark.schlesinger@yale.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>07/13/2006</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Brian</FirstName>
<LastName>Elbel</LastName>
<EmailAddress>Brian.Elbel@nyu.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>07/13/2006</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Yale University</Name>
<CityName>New Haven</CityName>
<ZipCode>065208327</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2037854689</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>Office of Sponsored Projects</StreetAddress>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Connecticut</StateName>
<StateCode>CT</StateCode>
</Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1321</Code>
<Text>DECISION RISK &amp; MANAGEMENT SCI</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9179</Code>
<Text>GRADUATE INVOLVEMENT</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>SMET</Code>
<Text>SCIENCE, MATH, ENG &amp; TECH EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
</Award>
</rootTag>
