<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>NMR Determination of Biomolecular Structural Dynamics Using Residual Dipolar Couplings Measured in Multiple Alignment Media</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2006</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2011</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>946211.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>946211</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>08070400</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>BIO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>MCB</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Molecular and Cellular Bioscience</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Kamal Shukla</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The goal of this project is the development of residual dipolar coupling (RDC)-based NMR methods for the determination of biomolecular structure and dynamics.  This approach will be based on the measurement of multiple sets of RDCs under conditions of different anisotropic solvent environments.  Novel methods for modulating the nature of the anisotropic solvent environment will be developed in order to improve the efficiency of data acquisition.  In particular, these studies will focus on the exploitation of the interference observed between aligning forces for composite, mechanically ordered media such as bacteriophage Pf1 particles embedded within a strained polyacrylamide gel matrix.  The DIDC approach to the interpretation of RDCs, demonstrated by the PI for backbone amide N-H bonds, will be extended to the determination of side-chain conformation and dynamics.  Furthermore, these multi-alignment RDC-based approaches will be adapted for application to the protein Neisseria meningitidis heme oxygenase, for which dynamics have been implicated as necessary for its function.  These studies will serve as a test case for the ability to characterize in detail the structural dynamics of a moderately sized protein (24 kDa) using RDC-based methods.  It is anticipated that these studies will lay a foundation for future NMR investigations and provide novel insights into the relationship between protein structural dynamics and function.  &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This research will provide powerful tools for the characterization of mobility and structure of biomolecular systems and thus will have a far reaching impact on the ability to characterize the mechanical aspects of biomolecular function at atomic resolution.  This project will also broadly impact undergraduate teaching and research in biomolecular NMR spectroscopy, a technique often inaccessible to undergraduates due to the expense and geographical concentration of high field NMR instrumentation.  In order to increase undergraduate research opportunities in biomolecular NMR, one undergraduate summer research position has been established, primarily intended for students outside of the Johns Hopkins community.  Sustained efforts are being made to stimulate collaboration and facilitate training of local biophysical and biochemical researchers such that they can employ state of the art biomolecular NMR spectroscopic techniques to advantage&lt;br/&gt;</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/08/2006</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/17/2010</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.074</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>0615786</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Joel</FirstName>
<LastName>Tolman</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>R</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Joel R Tolman</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>tolman@jhu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>4105168022</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000189505</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/08/2006</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Johns Hopkins University</Name>
<CityName>Baltimore</CityName>
<ZipCode>212182686</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>4439971898</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1101 E 33rd St</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[Suite B001]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Maryland</StateName>
<StateCode>MD</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MD07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>001910777</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>JOHNS HOPKINS UNIVERSITY, THE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>001910777</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Johns Hopkins University]]></Name>
<CityName>Baltimore</CityName>
<StateCode>MD</StateCode>
<ZipCode>212182686</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[1101 E 33rd St]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Maryland</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MD07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1144</Code>
<Text>Molecular Biophysics</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1164</Code>
<Text>MOLECULAR BIOPHYSICS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7465</Code>
<Text>NANOSCALE BIO CORE</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9183</Code>
<Text>GENERAL FOUNDATIONS OF BIOTECHNOLOGY</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>BIOT</Code>
<Text>BIOTECHNOLOGY</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0106</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>490100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0107</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>490100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0108</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0109</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0110</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2006~177994</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2007~183763</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2008~189240</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2009~194762</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2010~200452</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The research was focused on the development of novel methods for probing protein structure and dynamics using high field Nuclear Magnetic Resonance (NMR) spectroscopy.&nbsp; Normally much potentially useful information is lost when working with proteins dissolved in aqueous solution due to random molecular tumbling.&nbsp; It has been show that some of this information can be retrieved by introducing a slight degree of alignment relative to the NMR magnetic field.&nbsp; Depending on exactly how the alignment of the protein molecules is introduced, different and potentially complementary information can be retrieved.&nbsp; Indeed, the goal of this research was to explore different mechanisms by which the alignment of the protein molecules can be better controlled by the experimentalist, thus enabling a fuller description of the structural and dynamic properties of the protein to be obtained.&nbsp;</p> <p>We have shown that it is straightforward to obtain three independent sets of measurements for a given protein but that it is much more difficult to obtain four or five independent sets with state of the art techniques.&nbsp; This allows very powerful information about the orientation of individual bonds to be obtained, however our ability to independently establish the extent of mobility of those bonds remains limited.&nbsp; Future research is needed to develop methods which allow more data to be measured reliably.&nbsp; We have also shown that these techniques can be applied to the side-chains of proteins and that they can readily allow determination of regions of high mobility.&nbsp; For the protein ubiquitin, there was a clear correlation between side-chains which were surface accessible and which had high mobility.&nbsp; We expect that these tools will be very useful for studying proteins which require motion for their function such as allosteric proteins.&nbsp; In addition to the training of several undergraduate and graduate students in high resolution NMR techniques, these results pave the way for future studies of protein structure and flexibility by NMR spectroscopy.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 12/29/2011<br>      Modified by: Joel&nbsp;R&nbsp;Tolman</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The research was focused on the development of novel methods for probing protein structure and dynamics using high field Nuclear Magnetic Resonance (NMR) spectroscopy.  Normally much potentially useful information is lost when working with proteins dissolved in aqueous solution due to random molecular tumbling.  It has been show that some of this information can be retrieved by introducing a slight degree of alignment relative to the NMR magnetic field.  Depending on exactly how the alignment of the protein molecules is introduced, different and potentially complementary information can be retrieved.  Indeed, the goal of this research was to explore different mechanisms by which the alignment of the protein molecules can be better controlled by the experimentalist, thus enabling a fuller description of the structural and dynamic properties of the protein to be obtained.   We have shown that it is straightforward to obtain three independent sets of measurements for a given protein but that it is much more difficult to obtain four or five independent sets with state of the art techniques.  This allows very powerful information about the orientation of individual bonds to be obtained, however our ability to independently establish the extent of mobility of those bonds remains limited.  Future research is needed to develop methods which allow more data to be measured reliably.  We have also shown that these techniques can be applied to the side-chains of proteins and that they can readily allow determination of regions of high mobility.  For the protein ubiquitin, there was a clear correlation between side-chains which were surface accessible and which had high mobility.  We expect that these tools will be very useful for studying proteins which require motion for their function such as allosteric proteins.  In addition to the training of several undergraduate and graduate students in high resolution NMR techniques, these results pave the way for future studies of protein structure and flexibility by NMR spectroscopy.       Last Modified: 12/29/2011       Submitted by: Joel R Tolman]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
