<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>2006 ACES Workshop:   Simulating and Forecasting Earthquakes and Tsunamis with Information Technology; Maui, Hawaii; April 2006</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>03/01/2006</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>02/28/2007</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardAmount>15000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>06030204</Code>
<Directorate>
<LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<LongName>Division Of Earth Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Eva Zanzerkia</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The ACES workshop in April 2006, will bring together US researchers with international scientific colleagues from the Asia-Pacific Rim countries. ACES is the APEC Cooperation for Earthquake Simulation (ACES), an international collaboration of scientists that has been meeting since February 1999. The purpose of the April 2006 workshop will be to review recent progress in several key areas of science and technology and to formulate joint plans for future progress. Topics of interest will include earthquake and tsunami forecasting; enabling technologies and computational methods, including web services and grid computing; modeling and simulation advances; and the use of new types of satellite measurements, for example Synthetic Aperture Radar Interferometry (InSAR). ACES activities and meetings involve students and academia from all of the participating countries.  Many of the results are also communicated to the broader public through press releases and news stories. The work will advance our understanding of earthquake processes, and therefore improve our ability to mitigate damage and loss of life from these events. Effective partnerships have been built at the individual researcher level, through the coordination of National Programs through ACES. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>03/01/2006</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>03/01/2006</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>0616985</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>John</FirstName>
<LastName>Rundle</LastName>
<EmailAddress>jbrundle@ucdavis.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>03/01/2006</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Andrea</FirstName>
<LastName>Donnellan</LastName>
<EmailAddress>donnellan@jpl.nasa.gov</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>03/01/2006</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Southern California</Name>
<CityName>Los Angeles</CityName>
<ZipCode>900890001</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2137407762</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>University Park</StreetAddress>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
</Institution>
<FoaInformation>
<Code>0000099</Code>
<Name>Other Applications NEC</Name>
</FoaInformation>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1574</Code>
<Text>GEOPHYSICS</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>0000</Code>
<Text>UNASSIGNED</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>OTHR</Code>
<Text>OTHER RESEARCH OR EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
</Award>
</rootTag>
