<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>The Chemistry of N-Confused Porphyrin: Metalation and Model Complexes</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2006</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2010</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>306000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>306000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03090005</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CHE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Chemistry</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Timothy Patten</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Professor Christopher J. Ziegler of the University of Akron is supported by the Inorganic, Bioinorganic and Organometallic Chemistry Program to explore the syntheses and characterization of N-confused porphyrins. These novel ligands are isomers of the porphyrin ligands that are found in the active sites of many proteins.  In N-confused porphyrins, one of the pyrrole rings has been inverted.  These macrocycles are known to stabilize unique oxidation states and coordination environments about their metal centers.  Biologically relevant molecules (peptide systems), chromophore assemblies, and heterobimetallic constructs can be coupled to the N-confused porphyrin via the functionalization of the peripheral nitrogen.  With these modified ligands, small molecule reactivities (binding to CO and NO) will be studied.  This research may be applied to biological and catalytic systems and the planned studies should provide excellent training for underprivileged high school students (sponsored through the American Chemical Society's Project SEED Program) as well as undergraduate and graduate students.  Prof. Ziegler has been instrumental in developing the infrastructure of the Department of Chemistry at the University of Akron (through grants from the NSF-Major Research Instrumentation (MRI) Program); this research utilizes the recently required chemical instrumentation.&lt;br/&gt;</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/22/2006</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/02/2008</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>0616416</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Christopher</FirstName>
<LastName>Ziegler</LastName>
<EmailAddress>ziegler@uakron.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>07/22/2006</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Akron</Name>
<CityName>Akron</CityName>
<ZipCode>443250001</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>3309722760</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>302 Buchtel Common</StreetAddress>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Ohio</StateName>
<StateCode>OH</StateCode>
</Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1966</Code>
<Text>SYNTHETIC INORGANIC</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9161</Code>
<Text>SINGLE DIVISION/UNIVERSITY</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9177</Code>
<Text>ELEMENTARY/SECONDARY EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9178</Code>
<Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9179</Code>
<Text>GRADUATE INVOLVEMENT</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9183</Code>
<Text>GENERAL FOUNDATIONS OF BIOTECHNOLOGY</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>AMPP</Code>
<Text>ADVANCED MATERIALS &amp; PROCESSING PROGRAM</Text>
</ProgramReference>
</Award>
</rootTag>
