<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>MRI: Acquisition of Raman Micro-Spectroscopy System for Advanced Interdisciplinary Materials Research, Education and Training</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2006</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2007</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>210076.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>210076</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03070006</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DMR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Materials Research</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Charles E. Bouldin</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Technical Abstract:&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;NCAT will acquire a high-resolution Raman micro-spectroscopy system with three significant competitive advantages over traditional spectroscopic techniques (lack of need for sample preparation, faster and higher-resolution probing, and non-invasiveness). The instrument will have the following technical features: full automation for confocal Raman analysis, high stability BX41 confocal microscope for most of the routine Raman measurements and most importantly, sufficient resolution for strain measurements in thin films and silicon substrates. The system will be equipped with laser excitation kits, motorized mapping piezo-stages, a heating stage (room temperature to 1500 degrees C capable), the ability to add corrosive gases in chamber, a HJY catalysis cell to allow for in-situ Raman measurements on catalysts and other material under working conditions, and a macro chamber for 90 degree and 180 degree excitation that allows measurements with minimized sample background (stray light, fluorescence, and thermal emission) and polarization studies. The proposed micro-Raman will add to our intellectual capital through interdisciplinary learning, discovery, engagement and operational excellence in the areas of (i) advanced ceramics, (ii) nanocomposites, (iii) tribological coatings, (iv) fuel cell materials, (v) magnetic thin films (vi) semiconductor and photovoltaic materials (vii) piezomaterials, (viii) nanofilled polymers and polymeric sensors, (ix) nanocatalysts, and (x) carbon nanotube growth.  This system is highly critical to many research and educational activities at NCAT, which has produced a high number of underrepresented minority PhD students. NCAT has acquired and deployed the most strategic pieces of major equipment. We are now at the stage where acquisition of micro-Raman lies directly on the critical path to our interdisciplinary research goals.  Research using this equipment will lead to significant advances in the understanding of various advanced materials including nanomaterials.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Lay Abstract:&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Micro-Raman spectroscopy is a sophisticated materials analysis tool. This state-of-the-art system will add a new dimension and capability to NCAT's major research program in advanced materials and nanotechnology. In addition to directly supporting research projects, this equipment will be used for the education and training of undergraduate and graduate students, as well as for our outreach programs. Innovations in materials development require complex interplay of various characterization techniques. Our research team at NCAT (supported by various funding agencies, including the National Science Foundation, Department of Defense, Department of Energy, NASA, and others) is nationally recognized for producing outstanding African-American baccalaureate, masters, as well as doctoral degree-holding engineers. The research and educational outcome of the proposed equipment acquisition will be a significantly improvement in the infrastructure for NCAT and further promote advanced materials engineering as a unifying research and education discipline. It will result in increased competitiveness of the NCAT engineering and science programs and better conditions for the faculty development, and for attraction and recruitment of talented undergraduate and graduate students especially from the underrepresented groups. The availability of proposed equipment for training and education will contribute to shortening of the learning curve of the existing MS and PhD students, and adding a new dimension to our curricula. As part of the courses and research programs we will invite leading scientists in the area of micro-Raman spectroscopy to address our scientists and students. Also, NCAT will include this equipment on tours it routinely organizes for local high schools.&lt;br/&gt;</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/23/2006</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/23/2006</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>0619192</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Jagannathan</FirstName>
<LastName>Sankar</LastName>
<EmailAddress>sankar@ncat.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>08/23/2006</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>North Carolina Agricultural &amp; Technical State University</Name>
<CityName>Greensboro</CityName>
<ZipCode>274110001</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>3363347995</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1601 E. Market Street</StreetAddress>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>North Carolina</StateName>
<StateCode>NC</StateCode>
</Institution>
<FoaInformation>
<Code>0106000</Code>
<Name>Materials Research</Name>
</FoaInformation>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1189</Code>
<Text>Major Research Instrumentation</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9161</Code>
<Text>SINGLE DIVISION/UNIVERSITY</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>AMPP</Code>
<Text>ADVANCED MATERIALS &amp; PROCESSING PROGRAM</Text>
</ProgramReference>
</Award>
</rootTag>
