<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>MRI:  Acquisition of an Instrument for Nanoscale Manipulation and Experimental Characterization</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2006</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2010</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardAmount>326700</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<LongName>Div Of Civil, Mechanical, &amp; Manufact Inn</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Charalabos C. Doumanidis</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This Major Research Instrumentation (MRI) grant provides funding to acquire a state-of-the-art nanomanipulation and visualization system for scientific research and training in prototyping, characterization, and performance evaluation of functional nanostructures and micro/nanoscale devices and systems. This system will provide nanometer-resolution, scanning electron microscope (SEM)-compatible manipulation capability, enabling a number of critical nanoscale experimental investigations in support of ongoing research in each of the following areas: 1) Nanoscale tensile testing of nanostructures and nanocomposites; 2) Characterization of high power lateral RF MEMS switches and PZT nanofibers; 3) Development of 6-DOF design methodologies for novel nano/microscale manipulation; 4) Bottom-up prototyping and experimental characterization of microchemical systems; 5) Nano-rheological characterization of complex fluids; 6) Prototyping/characterization of photonic crystal-based nano-sensor technology; 7) Nanoscale characterization of the interactions of living cells with their microenvironment; 8) Nanometer resolution mapping of electromechanical property evolution during material aging; and 9) The development of colloidal probe-based techniques for sensor applications.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Efforts in these research areas will greatly benefit from the controllable three-dimensional nanoscale manipulation with simultaneous visualization capabilities provided by this system. The broader impact of this effort will be the enhanced understanding of critical nanoscale phenomena developed as a result of the direct experimental characterization enabled by the instrumentation funded by this grant. The research projects directly impacted by this capability span many key emerging nano/microtechnology areas, including: nanomaterials development/characterization, nano/micro sensors and actuators, and micro-chemical and micro-micromechanical systems. In addition, this system will promote interdisciplinary collaborations among an increasing number of faculty, senior research personnel, and graduate and undergraduate students working in these research areas, and will strongly complement undergraduate and graduate educational initiatives in Nanotechnology at our Institute.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/07/2006</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>03/11/2010</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>0619762</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Yong</FirstName>
<LastName>Shi</LastName>
<EmailAddress>yshi2@stevens.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>07/07/2006</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Zhenqi</FirstName>
<LastName>Zhu</LastName>
<EmailAddress>zzhu2@stevens.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>07/07/2006</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Frank</FirstName>
<LastName>Fisher</LastName>
<EmailAddress>ffisher@stevens.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>07/07/2006</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Henry</FirstName>
<LastName>Du</LastName>
<EmailAddress>hdu@stevens.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>07/07/2006</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Stevens Institute of Technology</Name>
<CityName>HOBOKEN</CityName>
<ZipCode>070305991</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2012168762</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>CASTLE POINT ON HUDSON</StreetAddress>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New Jersey</StateName>
<StateCode>NJ</StateCode>
</Institution>
<FoaInformation>
<Code>0308000</Code>
<Name>Industrial Technology</Name>
</FoaInformation>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1189</Code>
<Text>MAJOR RESEARCH INSTRUMENTATION</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9146</Code>
<Text>MANUFACTURING BASE RESEARCH</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>MANU</Code>
<Text>MANUFACTURING</Text>
</ProgramReference>
</Award>
</rootTag>
