<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>CAREER: Development of an Integrated Research and Education Program in Nanobiomechanical Analysis of Skeletal Fragility</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>01/10/2006</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>04/30/2012</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>344789.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>348789</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07020000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CBET</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Chem, Bioeng, Env, &amp; Transp Sys</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Athanassios Sambanis</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>0449188&lt;br/&gt;Akkus&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This CAREER development project will establish the foundation for integration of research and education at the Department of Bioengineering of the University &lt;br/&gt;of Toledo towards developing cures for alleviating skeletal fragility.  The proposal seeks to attain the following specific objectives: (1) to understand the molecular and supramolecular level deformation and fracture mechanisms in healthy bone, (2) to determine whether bone's mechanical function can be improved by modulating the size and the geometry of mineral nanocrystals, (3) to integrate this nanobiomechanical perspective with the existing undergraduate- and graduate-level biomechanics curricula, and (4) to realize the participation of undergraduates and high-school students from under-served populations in these research activities. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>03/27/2006</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>11/29/2010</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>0620061</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Ozan</FirstName>
<LastName>Akkus</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Ozan Akkus</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>ozan.akkus@case.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>7654967517</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000270559</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>03/27/2006</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Purdue University</Name>
<CityName>West Lafayette</CityName>
<ZipCode>479072114</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>7654941055</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>Young Hall</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[155 S Grant Street]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Indiana</StateName>
<StateCode>IN</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>IN04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>072051394</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>PURDUE UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>072051394</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Purdue University]]></Name>
<CityName>West Lafayette</CityName>
<StateCode>IN</StateCode>
<ZipCode>479072114</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[Young Hall]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Indiana</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>IN04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>5342</Code>
<Text>Disability &amp; Rehab Engineering</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>5345</Code>
<Text>Engineering of Biomed Systems</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>0000</Code>
<Text>UNASSIGNED</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>004E</Code>
<Text>BIOMEDICAL ENG AND DIAGNOSTICS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1045</Code>
<Text>CAREER-Faculty Erly Career Dev</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7237</Code>
<Text>NANO NON-SOLIC SCI &amp; ENG AWD</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9251</Code>
<Text>REU SUPP-Res Exp for Ugrd Supp</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>OTHR</Code>
<Text>OTHER RESEARCH OR EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0105</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>490100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0106</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>490100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0107</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>490100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0108</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0109</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0110</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2005~24789</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2006~80001</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2007~79996</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2008~86193</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2009~73810</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2010~4000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The project aimed to develop and integrated outreach, research and teaching program on nanobiomechanics. The research activities focused on the involvement of mineral nanocrystals in skeletal fragility.</p> <p>Broader Impact: On the training facet, 23 undergraduates (8 females), 3 MS students (1 female), 1 PhD student and two postdoctoral fellows were associated with this project. Of the 23 undergraduates, 4 of them decided to pursue doctoral studies. Five middle school students (4 females) from underrepresented minority populations participated in STEM activities in biomedical sciences related projects. The interactive models which were created by undergraduate students were displayed in a science museum and in an audiology clinic. The PI have developed graduate classes on mechanics of tissues and proteins.</p> <p>Intellectual Merit: The activities resulted in 3 MS theses, 1 dissertation, 12 peer-reviewed manuscripts and more than several dozen conference presentations. The first merit was the identification of peptides which could modulate the crystallinity (size and shape) of mineral nanocrystals in bone. We have continued to prove that such crystallinity is a predictor of monotonic and fatigue fragility in aging human bone. The second merit was the first report of nanovoids forming in bone as precursors of failure. We have continued to identify that these nanovoids are associated with separation of mineral organic interface. The third merit was the demonstration of calcium efflux from the regions of bone sustaining pre-damage nanovoids. The fourth merit of the studies were the demonstration of bone as a mechanochemical transducer. Specifically, cells which are co-localized with the damaged regions of bone responded to the damage related calcium efflux. The studies have laid the foundation for the very important hypothesis that bone cells may detect damaged regions of bone and target such regions for repair under the effect of the calcium release from the damaged regions. The fundamental basic science insight gained from these studies lays the foundation to treat skeletal fragility.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 04/07/2014<br>      Modified by: Ozan&nbsp;Akkus</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Images (<span id="selectedPhoto0">1</span> of <span class="totalNumber"></span>)           </div> <div class="galControls" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2014/0620061/0620061_10022040_1396910273776_FinalOutcomeFig1--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2014/0620061/0620061_10022040_1396910273776_FinalOutcomeFig1--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Interactive model of Sarcomere"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2014/0620061/0620061_10022040_1396910273776_FinalOutcomeFig1--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Interactive model of Sarcomere"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">The model was constructed  by graduate students (http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=tZWxbe8BPPY) and it was on display at Medical Marvels exhibition at Science Central, a childrenÆs museum at Fort Wayne IN.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Ozan Akkus Ph.D.</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Public Domain</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Ozan&nbsp;Akkus</div> <div class="imageTitle">Interactive model of Sarcomere</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2014/0620061/0620061_10022040_1396910454283_FinalOutcomeFig2--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2014/0620061/0620061_10022040_1396910454283_FinalOutcomeFig2--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Examples of the undergraduate projects."><img sr...]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The project aimed to develop and integrated outreach, research and teaching program on nanobiomechanics. The research activities focused on the involvement of mineral nanocrystals in skeletal fragility.  Broader Impact: On the training facet, 23 undergraduates (8 females), 3 MS students (1 female), 1 PhD student and two postdoctoral fellows were associated with this project. Of the 23 undergraduates, 4 of them decided to pursue doctoral studies. Five middle school students (4 females) from underrepresented minority populations participated in STEM activities in biomedical sciences related projects. The interactive models which were created by undergraduate students were displayed in a science museum and in an audiology clinic. The PI have developed graduate classes on mechanics of tissues and proteins.  Intellectual Merit: The activities resulted in 3 MS theses, 1 dissertation, 12 peer-reviewed manuscripts and more than several dozen conference presentations. The first merit was the identification of peptides which could modulate the crystallinity (size and shape) of mineral nanocrystals in bone. We have continued to prove that such crystallinity is a predictor of monotonic and fatigue fragility in aging human bone. The second merit was the first report of nanovoids forming in bone as precursors of failure. We have continued to identify that these nanovoids are associated with separation of mineral organic interface. The third merit was the demonstration of calcium efflux from the regions of bone sustaining pre-damage nanovoids. The fourth merit of the studies were the demonstration of bone as a mechanochemical transducer. Specifically, cells which are co-localized with the damaged regions of bone responded to the damage related calcium efflux. The studies have laid the foundation for the very important hypothesis that bone cells may detect damaged regions of bone and target such regions for repair under the effect of the calcium release from the damaged regions. The fundamental basic science insight gained from these studies lays the foundation to treat skeletal fragility.          Last Modified: 04/07/2014       Submitted by: Ozan Akkus]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
