<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Free boundary problems and Viscosity solutions.</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>02/01/2006</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2008</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>59617.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>59617</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03040100</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DMS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Joe W. Jenkins</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>&lt;br/&gt;Proposal DMS-0401436&lt;br/&gt;PIs: David Jerison and Christina Kim (MIT)&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Title: Free boundary problems and viscosity solutions&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;ABSTRACT&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The main focus of this project is on problems in nonlinear differential&lt;br/&gt;equations in which the boundary is unknown and has to be determined: a&lt;br/&gt;so-called 'free boundary'. The PI is interested in the free boundary&lt;br/&gt;problems with nonlocal structure, where velocities of the free boundaries&lt;br/&gt;depend on global characteristics of the solutions. The goal is to gain a&lt;br/&gt;better understanding of the following aspects of such problems: the&lt;br/&gt;existence and uniqueness of solutions in global time; asymptotic behavior&lt;br/&gt;of the free boundary as time reaches zero or infinity; waiting time&lt;br/&gt;phenomena; and the regularity properties of the free boundaries. The PI&lt;br/&gt;employs the notion of viscosity solutions to address the behavior of&lt;br/&gt;aformentioned free boundary problems. This approach has been succesfully&lt;br/&gt;used to study nonlinear PDEs and local laws of motions such as 'motion by&lt;br/&gt;mean curvature'. The great advantage of this approach is its seamless&lt;br/&gt;handling of topological transitions such as pinch-off. The key-step of the&lt;br/&gt;theory of viscosity solutions is to establish a comparison principle. This&lt;br/&gt;property leads, in turn, to the existence of solutions and allows for the&lt;br/&gt;further study of their properties. Techniques coming from quantitative&lt;br/&gt;versions of the comparison principle and harmonic analysis are employed to&lt;br/&gt;study further properties of solutions.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The classical Stefan problem of melting ice is an example of the free&lt;br/&gt;boundary problems. In the Stefan problem, one is modeling the evolution of&lt;br/&gt;the polar ice caps, and the question of interest is the location, as a&lt;br/&gt;function of time, of the interface between water and ice. The particular&lt;br/&gt;problems to which the methods of the present proposal apply also include:&lt;br/&gt;the&lt;br/&gt;Hele-Shaw problem which models fluid motion in a narrow cell between&lt;br/&gt;two parallel plates; flame fronts; and the interface between oil and&lt;br/&gt;water in a flow. This is an area where modeling and computation are far&lt;br/&gt;ahead of mathematical analysis. The main obstacle for developing a&lt;br/&gt;well-defined notion for general motion of interfaces is that initially&lt;br/&gt;smooth boundaries moving under smooth velocities may develop singularities&lt;br/&gt;in finite time. The hitting and splitting of interfaces in flame&lt;br/&gt;propagation is an example. It is natural to wonder whether the&lt;br/&gt;continuation of the solutions is uniquely determined after pinch-off, or&lt;br/&gt;whether additional constitutive information might be required at the&lt;br/&gt;singular time. The impact of the singularity to the other part of the free&lt;br/&gt;boundary is another interesting question.  The PI plans to investigate&lt;br/&gt;these questions in local and global perspectives.&lt;br/&gt;</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>03/29/2006</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>03/29/2006</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>0627896</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Inwon</FirstName>
<LastName>Kim</LastName>
<EmailAddress>ikim@math.ucla.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>03/29/2006</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of California-Los Angeles</Name>
<CityName>LOS ANGELES</CityName>
<ZipCode>900951406</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>3107940102</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>10889 Wilshire Boulevard</StreetAddress>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
</Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1281</Code>
<Text>ANALYSIS PROGRAM</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>0000</Code>
<Text>UNASSIGNED</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>OTHR</Code>
<Text>OTHER RESEARCH OR EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
</Award>
</rootTag>
