<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>ACS Tribology Symposium: "Chemical Foundations of Friction and Wear"</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2006</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>01/31/2007</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>5000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>5000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CMMI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Civil, Mechanical, &amp; Manufact Inn</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Clark Cooper</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>ACS Tribology Symposium: "Chemical Foundations of Friction and Wear"&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Abstract&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt; Within the last decade, the tribological community has seen a resurgence of interest in the basic origins of friction, lubrication, and wear.   These renewed efforts have been prompted by a number of distinct factors related to both opportunity and need.  Opportunities for more detailed research have been provided through advances in computational methods and power, the development and refinement of instrumentation, and the synthesis and fabrication of novel materials.  The need for a greater understanding of tribological fundamentals has been driven largely by technological applications requiring more stringent control of the tribological interface.  Examples of this need are prevalent in the microelectronics, aerospace, and biotechnology industries.  Equipped with the tools to model, design, synthesize, and measure the tribological interface with greater precision, scientists and engineers within the community have begun mapping out an understanding of tribological phenomena on an atomic and molecular (chemical) scale. NSF support of the ACS Chemical Foundations of Friction and Wear Symposium will bring together a diverse group of scientists from academia and industry to share their recent advances in the field, having a blend of applied and fundamental, experimental and theoretical work.  The opportunity provided through this support will allow the exchange of the most recent results and will impact society through advancing the fundamental understanding of a topic of widespread importance.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt; &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/03/2006</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/03/2006</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>0629303</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Scott</FirstName>
<LastName>Perry</LastName>
<EmailAddress>ssp@ufl.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>07/03/2006</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Houston</Name>
<CityName>Houston</CityName>
<ZipCode>772042015</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>7137435773</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>4800 Calhoun Boulevard</StreetAddress>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Texas</StateName>
<StateCode>TX</StateCode>
</Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1633</Code>
<Text>MATERIALS AND SURFACE ENG</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1057</Code>
<Text>CIS BASE RESEARCH</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1444</Code>
<Text>SURFACE ENGINEERING</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>CVIS</Code>
<Text>CIVIL INFRASTRUCTURE</Text>
</ProgramReference>
</Award>
</rootTag>
