<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Learning About Environmental Research in a Context of Climate Change: An International Scholastic Interchange</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2006</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2007</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>63286</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>06090100</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Polar Programs</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Anna Kerttula de Echave</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>ABSTRACT&lt;br/&gt;ARC-0632333&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This proposal as a very innovative project to create an international research interchange of 12 students from three indigenous communities - Barrow, Alaska (Inupiat); Ixtlan de Juarez, Oaxaca, Mexico; and San Juan Nuevo Parangaricutiro, Michoacan, Mexico- to participate in environmental research project conducted in Mexico and on the North Slope of Alaska. The project will start in Barrow, Alaska where the students from Mexico will join their Alaskan Native hosts and be integrated into 4 teams of on-going environmental research in Barrow. These research experiences will be supported by regular classroom discussions and assessments. The following month, the same students will travel to Mexico for a parallel experience in Michoacan and Oaxaca. The goal of the project is to expose all three sets of students to three distinct eco-zones and three cultural contexts to foster collaboration and cross-cultural and environmental understanding between these three groups. The project is supported by Ilisagvik College and the students will receive 4 university credits in introductory environmental science and 2 credits in IT.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>07/21/2006</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>07/21/2006</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0632333</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Barbara</FirstName>
      <LastName>Bodenhorn</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>bb106@cam.ac.uk</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/21/2006</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Laura</FirstName>
      <LastName>Barraza</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>lbarraza@oikos.unam.mx</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/21/2006</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Barrow Arctic Science Consortium (BASC)</Name>
      <CityName>Barrow</CityName>
      <ZipCode>997230577</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>9078524881</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>PO Box 577</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Alaska</StateName>
      <StateCode>AK</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
