<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Improving Quantitative Reasoning and Inquiry-Based Learning in the Undergraduate Biology Curriculum</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>02/01/2007</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>01/31/2010</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>163458.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>163458</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>11040200</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>EHR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DUE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Undergraduate Education</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Mary Lee S. Ledbetter</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Life Science Biological (61) By increasing the emphasis on quantitative reasoning and inquiry-based activities in life science laboratory courses, faculty at the University of St. Thomas (UST) and North Hennepin Community College (NHCC) are encouraging more students to consider doing research.  A first year introductory biology laboratory and a mid-level plant biology laboratory are being revised by faculty collaborating at these schools. Digital microscopy and quantitative analysis of gas exchange are being brought into the introductory laboratory curriculum. The addition of these technologies and the associated curricular changes are targeting four specific objectives:&lt;br/&gt;- better integration of math skills and higher order thinking skills in biology.&lt;br/&gt;- improving and expanding inquiry-based laboratories to create better links with ongoing research projects.&lt;br/&gt;- students working with organisms to understand the relationship of structure to function leading to greater understanding of biological diversity.&lt;br/&gt;- use of technology in small groups to promote cooperative learning and a sense of community within each laboratory.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Intellectual Merit: Student gains are being assessed using attitudinal surveys, comparisons of student performance on laboratory examinations before and after the implementation of new technology-enhanced laboratory exercises, and tests of scientific and quantitative reasoning pre- and post-semester.  Results are being examined to detect effects of curricular changes on different populations of students.  &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Broader Impacts: Curricular use of research technology is intended to challenge students toward higher order thinking, and, as a result, to increase student enthusiasm and engagement in lower division life science labs. This collaboration between a university and community college helps acquaint more students from diverse backgrounds with people who work together to carry out science research endeavors.&lt;br/&gt;</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>01/26/2007</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>01/26/2007</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>0633017</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Susan</FirstName>
<LastName>Chaplin</LastName>
<EmailAddress>sbchaplin@stthomas.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>01/26/2007</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Amy</FirstName>
<LastName>Verhoeven</LastName>
<EmailAddress>asverhoeven@stthomas.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>01/26/2007</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Doreen</FirstName>
<LastName>Schroeder</LastName>
<EmailAddress>djschroeder@stthomas.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>01/26/2007</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Tinna</FirstName>
<LastName>Ross</LastName>
<EmailAddress>tross@nhcc.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>01/26/2007</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of St. Thomas</Name>
<CityName>St. Paul</CityName>
<ZipCode>551051096</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6519626038</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>2115 Summit Avenue</StreetAddress>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Minnesota</StateName>
<StateCode>MN</StateCode>
</Institution>
<FoaInformation>
<Code>0116000</Code>
<Name>Human Subjects</Name>
</FoaInformation>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1536</Code>
<Text>S-STEM-Schlr Sci Tech Eng&amp;Math</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7494</Code>
<Text>CCLI-Type 1 (Exploratory)</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9178</Code>
<Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>SMET</Code>
<Text>SCIENCE, MATH, ENG &amp; TECH EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
</Award>
</rootTag>
