<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>A Biomathematical Learning Enhancement Network for Diversity (BLEND)</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/15/2006</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2009</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardAmount>240000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03040100</Code>
<Directorate>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Mary Ann Horn</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Although biology and mathematics programs at Historically Minority Universities (HMUs) have consistently produced high numbers of STEM baccalaureate degrees, more innovative programs are needed to increase the number of undergraduates who go on to earn the Ph.D.  The challenge is to bring together a critical mass of interdisciplinary research collaborations and partnerships that address basic root origins of achievement gaps for underrepresented minorities in mathematics and biology.  The Biomathematics Learning Enhancement Network for Diversity (BLEND) project at North Carolina A&amp;T State University was conceptualized by an interdepartmental alliance of faculty who are early adopters of transformational change required to prepare students for graduate study at the interface of biology and mathematics.  The BLEND project will supply both a physical and virtual intellectual setting where students may find a sense of identification, belonging, responsibility, and most importantly, achievement that prepares them for roles of leadership and service in biomathematical research careers.  The overall goal of the BLEND project is to produce undergraduate students outstandingly prepared for the interdisciplinary nature of biomathematical research.  To accomplish this goal, the BLEND project will (1) link research and classroom experiences, (2) provide joint-mentoring at the interface of mathematics and biology, and (3) broaden the appeal to biomathematics training and research.  Our Core Genomics Research Cluster will provide a natural opportunity for students to explore, learn, and engage problems in biology from a mathematical and computational perspective while gaining deeper insight into genomics research.  The central theme of the research projects is high-throughput data collection methods in genome sequencing and protein structure prediction.  Research activities will focus on abiotic plant stress tolerance strategies and identification of stress-relevant genes and pathways.  Students will emerge from these research activities with a coherent picture of links between molecular, biochemical, and physiological mechanisms that enable higher plants to cope with abiotic stress conditions such as drought, salinity, and temperature extremes.  These research activities are context-driven and purposed to provide an innovative learning culture that connects undergraduates with insightful interactions between biology and mathematics.  This project will advance a forward-thinking model for motivating underrepresented minorities to pursue professions at the interface of mathematics and biology. &lt;br/&gt;</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>09/12/2006</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>09/12/2006</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>0634598</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Mary</FirstName>
<LastName>Smith</LastName>
<EmailAddress>smithma@ncat.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>09/12/2006</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Gregory</FirstName>
<LastName>Goins</LastName>
<EmailAddress>gdgoins@ncat.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>09/12/2006</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Vinaya</FirstName>
<LastName>Kelkar</LastName>
<EmailAddress>vakelkar@ncat.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>09/12/2006</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Mingxiang</FirstName>
<LastName>Chen</LastName>
<EmailAddress>chen@ncat.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>09/12/2006</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Dominic</FirstName>
<LastName>Clemence</LastName>
<EmailAddress>clemence@ncat.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>09/12/2006</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>North Carolina Agricultural &amp; Technical State University</Name>
<CityName>Greensboro</CityName>
<ZipCode>274110001</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>3363347995</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1601 E. Market Street</StreetAddress>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>North Carolina</StateName>
<StateCode>NC</StateCode>
</Institution>
<FoaInformation>
<Code>0116000</Code>
<Name>Human Subjects</Name>
</FoaInformation>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1253</Code>
<Text>OFFICE OF MULTIDISCIPLINARY AC</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7229</Code>
<Text>MATHEMATICAL SCIENCES</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1228</Code>
<Text>MINORITY INVOLVEMENT -- BIO</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7303</Code>
<Text>MATH SCI PRIORITY AREA: INTERDISCIPLINAR</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7317</Code>
<Text>INTERDISC TRNG IN BIO &amp; MATH</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9178</Code>
<Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9183</Code>
<Text>GENERAL FOUNDATIONS OF BIOTECHNOLOGY</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>BIOT</Code>
<Text>BIOTECHNOLOGY</Text>
</ProgramReference>
</Award>
</rootTag>
