<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Theory and Methodology for the Design and Evaluation of High-Performance LDPC Codes</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>10/01/2006</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>09/30/2010</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>672474.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>672474</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>05010000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>CSE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CCF</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division of Computing and Communication Foundations</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>John Cozzens</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The project addresses some of the currently most important basic research challenges in error&lt;br/&gt;control coding theory. The bulk of current theory on efficient decoding methods is asymptotic in nature, and thus does not yield useful predictions for the shorter and intermediate blocklengths needed for delaysensitive applications (e.g., high-speed communications, streaming and peer-to-peer networks). A closely related goal is to gain a deeper understanding the so-called "error floor" behavior exhibited by certain classes of low-density parity check (LDPC) codes. These error floors seriously limit their usefulness for very low bit error rate (BER) applications (e.g., high-speed communications, data storage). A current major bottleneck is the lack of systematic and reliable methods to explore this deep BER regime, and we propose to address this challenge through a combination of combinatorial and geometric analysis, hardware-based emulation,&lt;br/&gt;and fast stochastic simulation.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Intellectual merit: Lack of finite-length analysis and the existence of error floors is a key bottleneck slowing down the deployment of high performance codes in a range of very important applications. Addressing this challenge requires a range of deep and fundamental scientific questions, drawing on ideas from polyhedral combinatorics, graph theory, dynamical systems and probability theory. Hardware implementation of message passing algorithms for high performance applications is in itself challenging. The research uses the development of high performance iterative decoders as a design driver for developing a novel emulation-simulation based design approach. This paradigm is novel and poses many fundamental challenges,&lt;br/&gt;including the development of fast simulation techniques for gathering error statistics, stochastic&lt;br/&gt;adaptive algorithms that exploit error statistics in order to design better codes, and investigation of systematic techniques for efficiently mapping code designs onto a field-programmable gate array (FPGA) platform.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Broader impact: Message-passing algorithms on graphs play a fundamental role across of a broad spectrum of scientific and engineering disciplines. The range of applications covers areas as diverse as communication systems, image processing, bioinformatics, statistical physics, and natural language processing, among many others. Consequently, our research, with its explicit goal of gaining a deeper understanding of message passing algorithms, has the potential for broad impact and dissemination across a variety of areas. In addition, our project has a significant educational and outreach component. Graduate students at Berkeley will be trained in both algorithmic and VLSI design techniques while participating in this research. Students coming our of this program will have a unique skill set that spans both theory and implementation,&lt;br/&gt;thereby constituting an invaluable addition to the nation's technical workforce. We are also very active in promoting undergraduate research and in facilitating research experiences for students from historically underrepresented communities. The overall thrust of this project has many well defined subprojects, which makes it very well-suited to such outreach activity at the  undergraduate level.&lt;br/&gt;1&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>09/18/2006</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>09/18/2006</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>0635372</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Venkatachalam</FirstName>
<LastName>Anantharam</LastName>
<EmailAddress>ananth@eecs.berkeley.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>09/18/2006</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Borivoje</FirstName>
<LastName>Nikolic</LastName>
<EmailAddress>bora@eecs.berkeley.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>09/18/2006</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Martin</FirstName>
<LastName>Wainwright</LastName>
<EmailAddress>wainwrig@eecs.berkeley.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>09/18/2006</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of California-Berkeley</Name>
<CityName>BERKELEY</CityName>
<ZipCode>947101749</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5106433891</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>Sponsored Projects Office</StreetAddress>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
</Institution>
<FoaInformation>
<Code>0000912</Code>
<Name>Computer Science</Name>
</FoaInformation>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7351</Code>
<Text>THEORETICAL FOUNDATIONS (TF)</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9218</Code>
<Text>BASIC RESEARCH &amp; HUMAN RESORCS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>HPCC</Code>
<Text>HIGH PERFORMANCE COMPUTING &amp; COMM</Text>
</ProgramReference>
</Award>
</rootTag>
