<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Renewal of the South American Meridional B-field Array (SAMBA): An American-Chilean magnetometer chain</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2007</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2014</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>792520.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>807520</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>06090300</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>GEO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>OPP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Office of Polar Programs (OPP)</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Vladimir Papitashvili</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>vpapita@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927425</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The proposed work is the continued operation of a latitudinally extended magnetometer chain in Chile and Antarctica (SAMBA =  South American Meridional B-field Array).  Previous work has brought the twelve stations into full operation and has brought it to the attention of the scientific community. The next five years of operation will address key science objectives, further the international collaborations already begun, further develop the data distribution system, and to maintain and develop the magnetometer network  The primary science objectives are: (1) the quantitative determination of the effect solar wind dynamic pressure enhancements have on the asymmetric ring current, (2) a more reliable automated determination of field-line resonances (FLR), (3) the investigation of constraints on models used to determine equatorial mass density from FLRs, (4) the remote monitoring of the inner magnetospheric mass density during storms, and (5) auroral conjugate observations of substorms in conjunction with NASA's THEMIS mission (THEMIS = Time History of Events and Macroscale Interactions during Substorms).</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/17/2007</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>09/04/2013</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.078</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>0636939</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Lawrence</FirstName>
<LastName>Lyons</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>R</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Lawrence R Lyons</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>larry@atmos.ucla.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>3102067876</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000449978</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/17/2007</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Mark</FirstName>
<LastName>Moldwin</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>B</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Mark B Moldwin</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>mmoldwin@umich.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>7347807334</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000324989</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/17/2007</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Eftyhia</FirstName>
<LastName>Zesta</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Eftyhia Zesta</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>ezesta@atmos.ucla.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>3102062710</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000420727</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/17/2007</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Athanasios</FirstName>
<LastName>Boudouridis</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Athanasios Boudouridis</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>thanasis@spacescience.org</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>7209745877</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000068466</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/17/2007</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of California-Los Angeles</Name>
<CityName>LOS ANGELES</CityName>
<ZipCode>900951406</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>3107940102</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>10889 Wilshire Boulevard</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[Suite 700]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>33</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CA33</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>092530369</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF CALIFORNIA, LOS ANGELES</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>071549000</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of California-Los Angeles]]></Name>
<CityName>LOS ANGELES</CityName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>900951406</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[10889 Wilshire Boulevard]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>33</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CA33</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<FoaInformation>
<Code>0311000</Code>
<Name>Polar Programs-Related</Name>
</FoaInformation>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>5115</Code>
<Text>ANT Astrophys &amp; Geospace Sci</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>5750</Code>
<Text>MAGNETOSPHERIC PHYSICS</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>0000</Code>
<Text>UNASSIGNED</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>4444</Code>
<Text>INTERDISCIPLINARY PROPOSALS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>OTHR</Code>
<Text>OTHER RESEARCH OR EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0107</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>490100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0108</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0109</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0110</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0111</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>02XX</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2007~170212</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2008~145006</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2009~168680</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2010~151279</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2011~157343</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2013~15000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><ol> <li>SAMBA is a US-Chilean collaboration project that included 12 magnetometer stations along the coast of Chile and in Antarctica. During the period of operations, SAMBA supported 4 senior and mid-career researchers, graduated 1 PhD student and 2 MS students in the US, and 2 MS students in Chile. SAMBA also supported 2 Chilean undergraduate students that are currently studying for their PhD at UCLA, and is currently scientifically supporting one PhD student in Greece. SAMBA produced more than 15 peer-reviewed publications and over 50 conference presentations. SAMBA is a voting member of ULTIMA, has and continues to distribute large amounts of data to the community, either directly or via two large data portals.</li> <li>SAMBA held two collaborative project workshops. The first took place at the beginning of the project, in May 2008 at UCLA with the purpose to launch scientific collaboration between the US and Chilean teams. The second took place in Punta Arenas, Chile, at the INACH institute, November 3-5, 2013. It was attended by approximately 20 young students, postdocs, researchers, and engineers from both the US and Chile. The meeting was singularly successful, brought together old and newer members of the team, local operators, the PI team, the Chilean leadership of the project and UCLA engineers. Activities from the past 5 years were reviewed, but most importantly new collaborations and future plans were formed.</li> <li>The new magnetometer data archive web site for SAMBA and AMBER networks, <a href="http://magnetometers.bc.edu">http://magnetometers.bc.edu</a>, has been functioning well and during the past year all of the MEASURE magnetometer chain data have been added to the data base. Real-time magnetograms and dynamic spectra are currently displayed in the website.</li> <li>The effect of solar wind dynamic pressure enhancements on the partial ring current (PRC) was studied comprehensively via case studies, statistical studies, and modeling in a series of 4 publications. SAMBA station observations were augmented by a global set of ground stations and the Tsyganenko storm-time model (TS04) was used to model the ground responses to dynamic pressure enhancements during the various phases of a storm. We found that a pressure enhancement impact intensify the pre-existing PRC as well as R1 and R2 field aligned currents nearly instantaneously, the cumulative effect of all those currents manifested as different responses at ground stations at different latitudes and local times. </li> <li>Global ULF wave activity is intense not only during typical Coronal Mass Ejection (CME) storms that exhibit large reduction in the Dst index, but also during High Speed Stream (HSS)/Corotating Interaction Region (CIR) disturbances which may produce only moderate Dst reduction but drive strong coupling to the magnetosphere. <em>Yizengaw et al.</em> [2013] showed &nbsp;that Pc5 waves may occur within the magnetosphere and ionosphere during such CIR storms in response to similar strong wave activity in the upstream solar wind. They also showed that Pc5 waves may penetrate to the equatorial ionosphere and modulate the equatorial electrojet (EEJ) there as well as the ionospheric density. Figure 1 shows filtered time series (white lines), dynamic spectra and magnitudes of the total electron content (TEC) and equatorial vertical ExB drift (which is directly proportional to the EEJ strength and calculated from ground magnetometer observations) observed at the same equatorial location. The time period shown is 3-hr during the CIR when wave power was high throughout the magnetosphere and ionosphere. Large 2-4 mHz Pc5 waves are present in both the TEC and vertical drift and were also recorded by widely spaced ground and spacebased magnetometers. Yizengaw et al. (2013) concluded that the source of the TEC oscillations was the global magnetospheric Pc5 wave, which was in turn directly drive...]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ SAMBA is a US-Chilean collaboration project that included 12 magnetometer stations along the coast of Chile and in Antarctica. During the period of operations, SAMBA supported 4 senior and mid-career researchers, graduated 1 PhD student and 2 MS students in the US, and 2 MS students in Chile. SAMBA also supported 2 Chilean undergraduate students that are currently studying for their PhD at UCLA, and is currently scientifically supporting one PhD student in Greece. SAMBA produced more than 15 peer-reviewed publications and over 50 conference presentations. SAMBA is a voting member of ULTIMA, has and continues to distribute large amounts of data to the community, either directly or via two large data portals. SAMBA held two collaborative project workshops. The first took place at the beginning of the project, in May 2008 at UCLA with the purpose to launch scientific collaboration between the US and Chilean teams. The second took place in Punta Arenas, Chile, at the INACH institute, November 3-5, 2013. It was attended by approximately 20 young students, postdocs, researchers, and engineers from both the US and Chile. The meeting was singularly successful, brought together old and newer members of the team, local operators, the PI team, the Chilean leadership of the project and UCLA engineers. Activities from the past 5 years were reviewed, but most importantly new collaborations and future plans were formed. The new magnetometer data archive web site for SAMBA and AMBER networks, http://magnetometers.bc.edu, has been functioning well and during the past year all of the MEASURE magnetometer chain data have been added to the data base. Real-time magnetograms and dynamic spectra are currently displayed in the website. The effect of solar wind dynamic pressure enhancements on the partial ring current (PRC) was studied comprehensively via case studies, statistical studies, and modeling in a series of 4 publications. SAMBA station observations were augmented by a global set of ground stations and the Tsyganenko storm-time model (TS04) was used to model the ground responses to dynamic pressure enhancements during the various phases of a storm. We found that a pressure enhancement impact intensify the pre-existing PRC as well as R1 and R2 field aligned currents nearly instantaneously, the cumulative effect of all those currents manifested as different responses at ground stations at different latitudes and local times.  Global ULF wave activity is intense not only during typical Coronal Mass Ejection (CME) storms that exhibit large reduction in the Dst index, but also during High Speed Stream (HSS)/Corotating Interaction Region (CIR) disturbances which may produce only moderate Dst reduction but drive strong coupling to the magnetosphere. Yizengaw et al. [2013] showed  that Pc5 waves may occur within the magnetosphere and ionosphere during such CIR storms in response to similar strong wave activity in the upstream solar wind. They also showed that Pc5 waves may penetrate to the equatorial ionosphere and modulate the equatorial electrojet (EEJ) there as well as the ionospheric density. Figure 1 shows filtered time series (white lines), dynamic spectra and magnitudes of the total electron content (TEC) and equatorial vertical ExB drift (which is directly proportional to the EEJ strength and calculated from ground magnetometer observations) observed at the same equatorial location. The time period shown is 3-hr during the CIR when wave power was high throughout the magnetosphere and ionosphere. Large 2-4 mHz Pc5 waves are present in both the TEC and vertical drift and were also recorded by widely spaced ground and spacebased magnetometers. Yizengaw et al. (2013) concluded that the source of the TEC oscillations was the global magnetospheric Pc5 wave, which was in turn directly driven by upstream waves. Five stations from SAMBA, merged with McMAC and CARISMA in the north, were used to remotely sense the plasmasphere in L values from 1.5 to ...]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
