<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>EMSW21-MCTP: Center for Mentoring Undergraduate Research in Mathematics</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>10/01/2006</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>09/30/2011</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>1262854.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>1262854</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DMS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Bruce P. Palka</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The Brigham Young University (BYU) Mentoring through Critical Transition Points project will target two critical transition phases:  undergraduate students making a transition to graduate school in the mathematical sciences; and younger mathematics faculty members making a transition to becoming successful and contributing members of their institutions.  &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project will create and operate a year-round Center for Mentoring Undergraduate Research in Mathematics.  The center will promote undergraduate research projects in mathematics (including interdisciplinary topics) during the academic year, patterned after a successful existing model program at BYU.  This model consists of: (1) training faculty members as mentors for undergraduate research projects; (2) having these faculty members mentor undergraduate students in research groups who work together as a team on one research project during the academic year; (3) advising faculty members at other institutions on how to establish consistent funding to support undergraduate research at their own institution; and (4) preparing undergraduate students to succeed in graduate studies in mathematics.  Each year, this center will administer mini-grants to about 45 undergraduate students working in 15 groups during the academic year at various institutions across the U.S.  Included in these mini-grants will be workshops to train the faculty mentors in mentoring skills, in helping their mentored students succeed in graduate school, and in setting up consistently funded undergraduate research groups at their own institution.  There will be an emphasis on mentoring women (both students and faculty) and participants from undergraduate institutions.&lt;br/&gt;</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>09/08/2006</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>09/08/2006</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>0636648</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Tyler</FirstName>
<LastName>Jarvis</LastName>
<EmailAddress>jarvis@math.byu.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>09/08/2006</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Michael</FirstName>
<LastName>Dorff</LastName>
<EmailAddress>mdorff@mathematics.byu.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>09/08/2006</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Denise</FirstName>
<LastName>Halverson</LastName>
<EmailAddress>halverson@math.byu.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>09/08/2006</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Jeffrey</FirstName>
<LastName>Humpherys</LastName>
<EmailAddress>jhumpherys@gmail.com</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>09/08/2006</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Brigham Young University</Name>
<CityName>Provo</CityName>
<ZipCode>846021231</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>8014223360</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>A-285 ASB</StreetAddress>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Utah</StateName>
<StateCode>UT</StateCode>
</Institution>
<FoaInformation>
<Code>0000099</Code>
<Name>Other Applications NEC</Name>
</FoaInformation>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7335</Code>
<Text>WORKFORCE IN THE MATHEMAT SCI</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>0000</Code>
<Text>UNASSIGNED</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7302</Code>
<Text>MENTOR THR CRIT TRANS PTS IN THE MAT SCI</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>OTHR</Code>
<Text>OTHER RESEARCH OR EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
</Award>
</rootTag>
