<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Fourth U.S.-Japan Young Researchers Exchange Program on New Instrumentation for Nanoscale Structures</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2006</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>02/28/2009</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>76788</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07030000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Civil, Mechanical, &amp; Manufact Inn</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Glaucio H. Paulino</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>US-Japan exchanges&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This proposal is to secure support for an exchange of young researchers, from the United&lt;br/&gt;States and Japan, working in the area of nanotechnology. This is the fourth such exchange&lt;br/&gt;between the two countries and will primarily focus on new instrumentation for nanoscale&lt;br/&gt;structures. It is scheduled for 2007, with 14 young researchers from Japan visiting the&lt;br/&gt;U.S. in March with a reciprocal visit by 14 young U.S. researchers to occur in the summer&lt;br/&gt;or fall of the same year. During the 7 to 10 day visits, the participants will travel to&lt;br/&gt;leading research centers to investigate current research in each others countries. The&lt;br/&gt;objectives of this exchange program are to develop and strengthen connections between&lt;br/&gt;young U.S. and Japanese researchers (primarily at the assistant professor level), in the&lt;br/&gt;discipline of nanotechnology and, specifically, nanomanufacturing.&lt;br/&gt;The intellectual merit lies in the exchange of scientific and technical information, in&lt;br/&gt;the emerging, fast growing and ever-important field of nanotechnology. The broader impact&lt;br/&gt;lies in continuing and future intellectual exchanges and the promise of continuing a&lt;br/&gt;mutually beneficial collaborative relationship between these two technology leading&lt;br/&gt;countries</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>08/10/2006</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>08/10/2006</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0638833</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Robert</FirstName>
      <LastName>Hocken</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>hocken@uncc.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>08/10/2006</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of North Carolina at Charlotte</Name>
      <CityName>CHARLOTTE</CityName>
      <ZipCode>282230001</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>7046871888</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>9201 University City Boulevard</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>North Carolina</StateName>
      <StateCode>NC</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
