<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Continuing, GK-12: From Aquifers to Estuaries Tracing a Drop of Water via an Interactive Program Linking UT Scientists with K-12 Students and Teachers</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2007</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2011</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>1796988.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>1833937</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>11010000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>EHR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DGE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Graduate Education</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Sonia Ortega</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>sortega@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032925198</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>PROPOSAL #: 0638740&lt;br/&gt;PRINCIPAL INVESTIGATOR: Kenneth Dunton&lt;br/&gt;INSTITUTION: University of Texas at Austin&lt;br/&gt;TITLE:  Continuing, GK-12: From Aquifers to Estuaries  Tracing a Drop of Water via an Interactive Program Linking UT Scientists with K-12 Students and Teachers&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The continuing GK-12 project, From Aquifers to Estuaries  Tracing a Drop of Water via an Interactive Program Linking UT Scientists with K-12 Students and Teachers, between the University of Texas at Austin and three K-12 urban school districts, targets students in grades 5-8 in the disciplines of physics, chemistry, biology, mathematics and marine, geological and environmental sciences.  The theme of the project "Tracing a Drop of Water" has linked the program with efforts to increase teacher content knowledge in under-performing schools and provides fellows with an example of how scientists can excite students about science while still having a career in research. &lt;br/&gt;The intellectual merit of the program established a partnership between scientists and the K-12 community by focusing on interdisciplinary environmental and watershed sciences.  There will be creative links between mathematics, science, social science and technology in order to address important social issues in inland and coastal watersheds.  The broader impacts of this program not only strives to increase students STEM knowledge in grades 5-8 but also encourages students to think about STEM career options.  The K-12 schools involved in this project are high-needs schools with typically over two-thirds of the students from underrepresented groups.  Also, the overall theme of water is critical to all people.  The sustained program aims to change the culture of K-12 outreach in the university research community and to serve as a model for other institutions of higher learning. &lt;br/&gt;</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>04/06/2007</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>03/11/2011</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.076</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>0638740</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Kenneth</FirstName>
<LastName>Dunton</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>H</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Kenneth H Dunton</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>ken.dunton@mail.utexas.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>3617496744</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000176703</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/06/2007</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Michael</FirstName>
<LastName>Marder</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>P</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Michael P Marder</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>marder@chaos.ph.utexas.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5124713612</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000308752</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/06/2007</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Jay</FirstName>
<LastName>Banner</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>L</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Jay L Banner</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>banner@mail.utexas.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5124715016</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000162591</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/06/2007</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Jill</FirstName>
<LastName>Marshall</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Jill Marshall</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>marshall@austin.utexas.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5122329685</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000372938</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/06/2007</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Christopher</FirstName>
<LastName>Bell</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>J</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Christopher J Bell</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>cjbell@jsg.utexas.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5124715209</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000241680</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/06/2007</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Texas at Austin</Name>
<CityName>Austin</CityName>
<ZipCode>787595316</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5124716424</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>3925 W Braker Lane, Ste 3.340</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Texas</StateName>
<StateCode>TX</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>10</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>TX10</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>170230239</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF TEXAS AT AUSTIN</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>042000273</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Texas at Austin]]></Name>
<CityName>Austin</CityName>
<StateCode>TX</StateCode>
<ZipCode>787595316</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[3925 W Braker Lane, Ste 3.340]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Texas</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>10</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>TX10</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<FoaInformation>
<Code>0000099</Code>
<Name>Other Applications NEC</Name>
</FoaInformation>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7179</Code>
<Text>GRAD TEACHING FELLOWS IN K-12</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7179</Code>
<Text>GRAD TEACHING FELLOWS IN K-12</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9179</Code>
<Text>GRADUATE INVOLVEMENT</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>SMET</Code>
<Text>SCIENCE, MATH, ENG &amp; TECH EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0107</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>490100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0407</Code>
<Name>NSF,Education &amp; Human Resource</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>490106</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0408</Code>
<Name>NSF Education &amp; Human Resource</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040106</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0410</Code>
<Name>NSF Education &amp; Human Resource</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040106</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2007~599834</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2008~1197154</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2010~36949</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><span style="white-space: pre;"> </span>The University of Texas at Austin project &ldquo;GK-12: From Aquifers to Estuaries Tracing a Drop of Water via an Interactive Program Linking UT Scientists with K-12 Students and Teachers&rdquo; paired science graduate student Fellows with K-12 teachers from school districts in Austin, Port Aransas, Corpus Christi, Aransas Pass and Rockport to expose students to hands-on science. Through partnering with local school districts, the project strengthened the connection between K-12 schools and The University of Texas at Austin. Students participated in inquiry-based science lessons and field activities led by graduate Fellows. Activities covered varied scientific topics including marine science, environmental science, biology, physics, and math while also highlighting local watersheds to show how human activities contribute to water issues facing the world and local communities. The project concentrated on schools with a large proportion of underrepresented student groups (i.e. minority or economically disadvantaged students), providing opportunities previously unavailable and creating meaningful learning opportunities for students.&nbsp; With the guidance of their graduate Fellows, K-12 students made important links between math, science, and human impacts on natural systems.</p> <p>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; In addition to increasing scientific and mathematic knowledge, the project also focused on exposing K-12 students to careers involving science or math.&nbsp; Students observed what it takes to become a scientist and examined new science related career options. We improved student&rsquo;s scientific content knowledge during the course of the program as shown by tracking standardized testing scores. Standardized test scores increased in all participating districts with the exception of two districts, whose scores remained unchanged. Superintendents and principals of participating districts have stated that they felt increased science standardized test scores were a direct result of their district&rsquo;s participation in the project.</p> <p><span style="white-space: pre;"> </span>&nbsp;As well as exposing students to scientific career options and increasing knowledge related to the natural world around them, the project also positively influenced student&rsquo;s enthusiasm towards science. On project evaluations and questionnaires, teachers mentioned that students looked forward to having a scientist in the classroom and were enthusiastic and engaged during the Fellow&rsquo;s lessons. &nbsp;Overall, a greater percentage of students exposed to a graduate Fellow valued science and science classroom experiences following their participation in the program than classrooms without a graduate Fellow (Figure 1).</p> <p><span style="white-space: pre;"> </span>Both teachers and graduate Fellows agreed that the program was beneficial to their own skill sets as well as those of their students. Graduate Fellows stated that the program greatly improved their communication skills, which is helpful in building their future careers. Fellows also stated that the GK-12 program experience helped them identify possible career options. A majority of the Fellows that participated in the project stated that it was of value to them (Figure 2). The one Fellow who rated the program poorly did so due to the time commitment of the project as well as the fact that the teaching objectives and the Fellow&rsquo;s own scientific research objectives were not aligned. Many of the teachers said their participation in the project increased their scientific knowledge and provided classroom resources not only during their participation but also for years to come. Teachers also reported increased confidence in teaching science as a result of participating in the program (Figure 3). Based on this information, we can conclude ...]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[  The University of Texas at Austin project "GK-12: From Aquifers to Estuaries Tracing a Drop of Water via an Interactive Program Linking UT Scientists with K-12 Students and Teachers" paired science graduate student Fellows with K-12 teachers from school districts in Austin, Port Aransas, Corpus Christi, Aransas Pass and Rockport to expose students to hands-on science. Through partnering with local school districts, the project strengthened the connection between K-12 schools and The University of Texas at Austin. Students participated in inquiry-based science lessons and field activities led by graduate Fellows. Activities covered varied scientific topics including marine science, environmental science, biology, physics, and math while also highlighting local watersheds to show how human activities contribute to water issues facing the world and local communities. The project concentrated on schools with a large proportion of underrepresented student groups (i.e. minority or economically disadvantaged students), providing opportunities previously unavailable and creating meaningful learning opportunities for students.  With the guidance of their graduate Fellows, K-12 students made important links between math, science, and human impacts on natural systems.              In addition to increasing scientific and mathematic knowledge, the project also focused on exposing K-12 students to careers involving science or math.  Students observed what it takes to become a scientist and examined new science related career options. We improved studentÆs scientific content knowledge during the course of the program as shown by tracking standardized testing scores. Standardized test scores increased in all participating districts with the exception of two districts, whose scores remained unchanged. Superintendents and principals of participating districts have stated that they felt increased science standardized test scores were a direct result of their districtÆs participation in the project.    As well as exposing students to scientific career options and increasing knowledge related to the natural world around them, the project also positively influenced studentÆs enthusiasm towards science. On project evaluations and questionnaires, teachers mentioned that students looked forward to having a scientist in the classroom and were enthusiastic and engaged during the FellowÆs lessons.  Overall, a greater percentage of students exposed to a graduate Fellow valued science and science classroom experiences following their participation in the program than classrooms without a graduate Fellow (Figure 1).   Both teachers and graduate Fellows agreed that the program was beneficial to their own skill sets as well as those of their students. Graduate Fellows stated that the program greatly improved their communication skills, which is helpful in building their future careers. Fellows also stated that the GK-12 program experience helped them identify possible career options. A majority of the Fellows that participated in the project stated that it was of value to them (Figure 2). The one Fellow who rated the program poorly did so due to the time commitment of the project as well as the fact that the teaching objectives and the FellowÆs own scientific research objectives were not aligned. Many of the teachers said their participation in the project increased their scientific knowledge and provided classroom resources not only during their participation but also for years to come. Teachers also reported increased confidence in teaching science as a result of participating in the program (Figure 3). Based on this information, we can conclude that the program had a positive impact on K-12 students, graduate Fellows and teachers.                    Last Modified: 02/27/2012       Submitted by: Kenneth H Dunton]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
