<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>InSTEP II: Expansion of the Integrate Science Teaching Enhancement Partnership</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>03/01/2007</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>02/28/2015</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>1711058.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>1711058</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>11010000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>EHR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DGE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Graduate Education</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Laura Regassa</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>PROPOSAL #: 0638702&lt;br/&gt;PRINCIPAL INVESTIGATOR: Richard Tankersley&lt;br/&gt;INSTITUTION: Florida Institute of Technology&lt;br/&gt;TITLE: INSTEP II:  Expansion of the Integrated Science Teaching Enhancement Partnership &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The continuing GK-12 project, INSTEP, between Florida Institute of Technology and Brevard County, builds upon the experiences and successes of the Track 1 program.  This project matches graduate students with high school (grades 9-11) Integrated Science (IS) teachers to enhance the curriculum and develop new hands-on activities.  The teams which include graduate students and teachers participate in workshops and seminars focusing on students learning styles, inquiry-based teaching methods, pedagogy, and national and state curriculum standards.  The intellectual merit of the project concentrates on having graduate fellows, teachers and university faculty design and pilot standards-based modules that link core IS content areas  Earth science, biology, chemistry and physics.  Many activities use the new mobile laboratory purchased by Florida Tech which allows schools to use resources and conduct hands-on experiments at local field sites.  The overarching theme of the project is "ocean discovery" which takes advantage of Florida's extensive coastline and also makes students aware of ocean-related issues therefore stimulating interest in science.  This thematic approach helps demonstrate the interconnectedness of science disciplines and the role the ocean plays in environmental and chemical cycles and physical and biological processes.  The broader impacts of the project are reflected in the continued benefits to fellows, teachers and K-12 students: fellows gain valuable teaching, communication and classroom management skills; teachers improve their understanding and mastery of science, become more knowledgeable of current trends in their disciplines, increase their comfort with inquiry-based instruction and gain a greater appreciation for the interdisciplinary nature of the IS curriculum; the high school students are provided the opportunity to interact with scientists and career role models and develop a deeper appreciation for the scientific process and the relevance of science to local issues.  &lt;br/&gt;</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>12/26/2006</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>03/18/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>0638702</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>John</FirstName>
<LastName>Windsor</LastName>
<EmailAddress>jwindsor@fit.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>12/26/2006</StartDate>
<EndDate>07/26/2012</EndDate>
<RoleCode>Former Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>John</FirstName>
<LastName>Windsor</LastName>
<EmailAddress>jwindsor@fit.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>03/18/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Richard</FirstName>
<LastName>Tankersley</LastName>
<EmailAddress>rtankers@uncc.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>12/26/2006</StartDate>
<EndDate>07/26/2012</EndDate>
<RoleCode>Former Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Florida Institute of Technology</Name>
<CityName>MELBOURNE</CityName>
<ZipCode>329016975</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>3216748000</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>150 W UNIVERSITY BLVD</StreetAddress>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Florida</StateName>
<StateCode>FL</StateCode>
</Institution>
<FoaInformation>
<Code>0000099</Code>
<Name>Other Applications NEC</Name>
</FoaInformation>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7179</Code>
<Text>GRAD TEACHING FELLOWS IN K-12</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7179</Code>
<Text>GRAD TEACHING FELLOWS IN K-12</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9179</Code>
<Text>GRADUATE INVOLVEMENT</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>SMET</Code>
<Text>SCIENCE, MATH, ENG &amp; TECH EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
</Award>
</rootTag>
