<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>STTR Phase I: Superhydrophobic Corrosion Resistant Coatings</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>01/01/2007</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2008</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>149033</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07070000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Industrial Innovation &amp; Partnersh</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Cheryl F. Albus</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This Small Business Technology Transfer (STTR) Phase I project will demonstrate improved corrosion resistance of iron and aluminum alloys by coating the alloys with a durable superhydrophobic coating. The corrosion of metal has a major effect on the economy of industrial nations. The costs associated with corrosion are in the billions of dollars annually. The superhydrophobic coating is a highly water repellent coating that is composed of hydrophobic chemicals and nano-sized particles. The coating is applied onto the metal surface to create a hydrophobic surface that is nanotextured. The presence of water plays an integral role in most metal corrosion processes and the nanotextured hydrophobic thin film prevents liquid water from wetting/adhering to the metal surface. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;In addition to the use of the superhydrophobic coating for metal corrosion protection, the use of a primer layer that is applied underneath the superhydrophobic coating is examined. The primer layers to be investigated are known to have metal adhesion and anti-corrosion properties. The anti-corrosion properties of the superhydrophobic coatings will be evaluated using electrochemical techniques.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>10/27/2006</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>12/26/2007</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0638146</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Laurie</FirstName>
      <LastName>Lawin</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>llawin@isurtec.com</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>10/27/2006</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Innovative Surface Technologies, Inc.</Name>
      <CityName>St. Paul</CityName>
      <ZipCode>551148612</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>6512099757</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>1000 Westgate Drive</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Minnesota</StateName>
      <StateCode>MN</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0110000</Code>
      <Name>Technology Transfer</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
    <FoaInformation>
      <Code>0308000</Code>
      <Name>Industrial Technology</Name>
    </FoaInformation>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
