<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Gordon Conference: 2006 Molecular Basis of Microbial One-Carbon Metabolism Gordon Research Conference; Oxford, United Kingdom; August 6-11, 2006</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2006</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2007</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>7000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>08070400</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Molecular and Cellular Bioscience</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Nara Gavini</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This Gordon Research Conference on "Molecular Basis of Microbial One-Carbon Metabolism" focuses on one-carbon compounds, which play a central role in microbial metabolism and are central in pathways of energy metabolism and carbon fixation. Several areas are of direct relevance to the National Science Foundation and especially the Molecular and Metabolic Biochemistry programs. Many of the invited speakers from the USA are NSF funded and all of the talks will describe research at the forefront of biology. The Program covers speakers with diverse research interests and backgrounds, but are linked by their interests in solving key problems related to one-carbon metabolism. The speakers also are diverse with respect to the career stage, gender, and ethnicity, with representation of underrepresented minority participants and speakers. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Broader Impacts&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The wide variety of disciplines brought to the study of C-1 metabolism make the field an excellent one in which to train young researchers. NSF support for this conference will allow more participants including students and postdocs to attend the GRC, facilitating interaction between junior and established scientists.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>07/28/2006</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>07/28/2006</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0639200</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Stephen</FirstName>
      <LastName>Ragsdale</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>sragsdal@umich.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/28/2006</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Nancy</FirstName>
      <LastName>Gray</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>nsf@grc.org</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>07/28/2006</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Gordon Research Conferences</Name>
      <CityName>West Kingston</CityName>
      <ZipCode>028921502</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>4017834011</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>512 Liberty Lane</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Rhode Island</StateName>
      <StateCode>RI</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
