<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>SGER / Collaborative Research : Multiscale Modeling: Finding Strengths, Avoiding Weaknesses</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2006</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>01/31/2009</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>0.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>99996</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CMMI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Civil, Mechanical, &amp; Manufact Inn</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>george hazelrigg</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This Small Grant for Exploratory Research (SGER) is to investigate the limitations of multiscaling modeling.  Multiscaling modeling is a new approach that promises significant advances in an array of disciplines ranging from physics to engineering.  By connecting what happens at different physical scales, through the use of a variety of aggregation approaches, new advances have been made.  At this stage of its development, however, there are only a few general principles to guide our understanding about when this form of modeling should be, or should not be, used.   By applying recent advances in our understanding of aggregation processes, this research will develop new guidelines to understand when multiscaling modeling is appropriate, when the usual notions of multiscaling must be modified, and when using this approach is not appropriate. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This research will have an effect not only on modeling within engineering, but also on questions coming from physics and mathematics.  By providing guidelines about the appropriate use of this technique, this research can be expected to facilitate the research efforts of the growing number of other researchers who are involved in this type of modeling, it is expected to eventually add to the efficiency of engineering processes that are based on multiscaling, and it is expected to identify new explanations for observed behavior within the class of engineering problems that will be emphasized. This project also is designed to expose graduate and undergraduate students to a new approach for the analysis of models.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/19/2006</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/05/2008</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>0640826</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Abhijit</FirstName>
<LastName>Chandra</LastName>
<EmailAddress>achandra@iastate.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>07/19/2006</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Iowa State University</Name>
<CityName>AMES</CityName>
<ZipCode>500112207</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5152945225</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1138 Pearson</StreetAddress>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Iowa</StateName>
<StateCode>IA</StateCode>
</Institution>
<FoaInformation>
<Code>0308000</Code>
<Name>Industrial Technology</Name>
</FoaInformation>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1468</Code>
<Text>Manufacturing Machines &amp; Equip</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>082E</Code>
<Text>MFG MACHINES &amp; METROLOGY</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>083E</Code>
<Text>MATERIAL TRANSFORMATION PROC</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9146</Code>
<Text>MANUFACTURING BASE RESEARCH</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9237</Code>
<Text>SMALL GRANTS-EXPLORATORY RSRCH</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>MANU</Code>
<Text>MANUFACTURING</Text>
</ProgramReference>
</Award>
</rootTag>
