<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Remote Sensing of Tornadoes and Storms with Mobile W-band Polarimetric and X-band Spaced-Antenna and Phased-Array Doppler Radar</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>01/15/2007</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2010</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardAmount>773328</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>06020105</Code>
<Directorate>
<LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<LongName>Div Atmospheric &amp; Geospace Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Chungu Lu</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Under this research effort, the Principal Investigator will continue a collaboration of research on severe storms with the University of Oklahoma (OU) through the use of two existing polarimetric mobile Doppler radar systems developed by UMass and through the development, test, and evaluation of an X-band pulse compression Doppler radar transceiver that will enable compatibility with phased-array technology already under development at UMass. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The project includes operation of two mobile radar systems (a W-band polarimetric Doppler radar and an X-band dual-polarized Doppler radar with spaced-antenna capability).  Additionally associated signal processing algorithms for use with spaced antennas and phased array antennas will be developed and evaluated &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Under prior support UMass has developed a dual-polarized spaced-antenna (DPSA) to estimate transverse (cross-beam) velocities in addition to the standard Doppler (radial) velocities.  The objective is to retrieve 2-D velocity vectors from a common point.  This antenna was fielded for the first time during Spring 2005 and data analysis is currently underway.  Under this award, the PI will continue these efforts in wind field retrieval techniques and extend them towards rapid diagnosis of tornadoes and other severe storm features using electronically-scanned antennas.  The research will make use of existing infrastructure at the University of Massachusetts and will position the program to take advantage of future technology developments occurring within the NSF-sponsored Engineering Research Center for Collaborative Adaptive Sensing of the Atmosphere (CASA). &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Specific research efforts will focus on the following objectives:  (1) Continue analysis of transverse wind estimates using spaced-antenna approaches performed in 2005.  (2) Maintain and operate the UMass W-band and X-band mobile Doppler radars for tornado and severe storm research on the Great Plains.  (3) Implement a pulse-compression transceiver to improve spatial resolution, to provide frequency and phase agility with existing antennas, and to support dual-polarized phased-array antennas under development by CASA. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The intellectual merit of the research is to develop and improve techniques for radar remote sensing of severe weather phenomena such as tornadoes and to develop affordable technology to do so. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The broader impacts are to improve understanding of the kinematics and dynamics of severe convective storms and their formation, ultimately leading to improved predictions of such severe weather events.  In addition, the project includes strong involvement of engineering graduate students from UMass working directly with graduate students in meteorology from OU. &lt;br/&gt;</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>12/11/2006</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>02/05/2009</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>0641201</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Paul</FirstName>
<LastName>Siqueira</LastName>
<EmailAddress>siqueira@ecs.umass.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>12/11/2006</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Stephen</FirstName>
<LastName>Frasier</LastName>
<EmailAddress>frasier@umass.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>12/11/2006</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Massachusetts Amherst</Name>
<CityName>Hadley</CityName>
<ZipCode>010359450</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>4135450698</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>Research Administration Building</StreetAddress>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
<StateCode>MA</StateCode>
</Institution>
<FoaInformation>
<Code>0000099</Code>
<Name>Other Applications NEC</Name>
</FoaInformation>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1525</Code>
<Text>PHYSICAL &amp; DYNAMIC METEOROLOGY</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>0000</Code>
<Text>UNASSIGNED</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>OTHR</Code>
<Text>OTHER RESEARCH OR EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
</Award>
</rootTag>
