<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>The Microevolution of Craniofacial Development in Threespine Stickleback</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>06/01/2007</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2011</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>449944.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>473944</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>08090100</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>BIO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>IOS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Integrative Organismal Systems</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Steven Klein</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>sklein@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927122</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Biologists have made great progress in understanding the genetic basis of simple traits, from the study of induced mutations in model organisms. However, most traits are complex, and their development is directed by many genes that are influenced by environmental conditions. The Cresko laboratory will examine natural populations of threespine stickleback fish to understand the developmental genetic basis of variation in complex head and jaw traits. These structures vary tremendously among individuals, populations and species. Despite this diversity, the development of head and jaw structures occurs through conserved genetic interactions and will prove highly informative about the proper development of similar structures in other vertebrates such as humans. This research will provide a much better understanding of the genetic basis of complex traits, be they characters important for stickleback, or the most common types of human diseases that afflict tens of millions of people. Dr. Cresko's group has an outstanding of outreach to elementary students and also of undergraduate training. They are also active contributors to the resources of the research community.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>05/18/2007</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>04/23/2010</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.074</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>0642264</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>John</FirstName>
<LastName>Postlethwait</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>H</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>John H Postlethwait</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>jpostle@oregon.uoregon.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5413464538</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000288575</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/18/2007</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Charles</FirstName>
<LastName>Kimmel</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>B</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Charles B Kimmel</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>kimmel@uoneuro.uoregon.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5413464519</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000305043</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/18/2007</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Patrick</FirstName>
<LastName>Phillips</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>C</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Patrick C Phillips</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>pphil@uoregon.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5413460916</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000446690</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/18/2007</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>William</FirstName>
<LastName>Cresko</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>A</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>William A Cresko</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>wcresko@uoregon.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5413464779</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000208135</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/18/2007</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Oregon Eugene</Name>
<CityName>Eugene</CityName>
<ZipCode>974035219</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5413465131</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>5219 UNIVERSITY OF OREGON</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Oregon</StateName>
<StateCode>OR</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>OR04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>079289626</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF OREGON</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>049793995</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Oregon Eugene]]></Name>
<CityName>Eugene</CityName>
<StateCode>OR</StateCode>
<ZipCode>974035219</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[5219 UNIVERSITY OF OREGON]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Oregon</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>OR04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<FoaInformation>
<Code>0000099</Code>
<Name>Other Applications NEC</Name>
</FoaInformation>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1080</Code>
<Text>Evolution of Develp Mechanism</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1228</Code>
<Text>MINORITY INVOLVEMENT -- BIO</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9178</Code>
<Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9183</Code>
<Text>GENERAL FOUNDATIONS OF BIOTECHNOLOGY</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9251</Code>
<Text>REU SUPP-Res Exp for Ugrd Supp</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>BIOT</Code>
<Text>BIOTECHNOLOGY</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>SMET</Code>
<Text>SCIENCE, MATH, ENG &amp; TECH EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0107</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>490100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0108</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0109</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0110</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2007~149982</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2008~161979</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2009~149983</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2010~12000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><span>A surprising biological discovery is that even distantly related species use a conserved set of genes during the formation of their bodies. Despite this conservation, organisms are fantastically diverse. Where does variation for the amazing diversity of attributes, such as size, shape or coloration, reside in this conserved genome of organisms? The development of head and jaw structures in fishes provides an excellent opportunity to address this question. The long term objective of this project was to study the genes and development of marked head and jaw differences across populations of threespine stickleback fish that have changed rapidly as they have adapted to novel environmental conditions. For this project we developed a variety of new laboratory and computer tools and approaches to finely dissect genetic variation in the development of stickleback head and jaw bones.&nbsp;</span></p> <p><span><span> </span>We had three major goals. The first goal was to produce a set of genetically heterogenous laboratory lines of stickleback that varied in head bone and jaw attributes that could be studied to map genes for this variation. We developed stickleback specific protocols to degrade the genetic material of sperm without damaging the cells themselves. We then used these sperm to activate stickleback eggs without contributing any genetic material. These activated embryos, containing only the mother&rsquo;s genome, were then restored to their normal two genome copies using manipulations of very young embryos. Using these techniques we produced the first clonal laboratory lines of threespine stickleback. The second goal was to define the spectrum of genetic effects contributing to variation in head bones and jaws. We developed advanced DNA sequencing technologies to rapidly and efficiently isolate causative genomic regions contributing to head and jaw variation. We also produced a detailed growth series to determine how the cartilage and bone cells that make the head and jaws have changed their behaviors, allowing us to link genetic differences to developmental changes. Our last aim was to examine how gene activity modifications in cartilage and bone cells relate to the DNA sequence and developmental differences. Using the newly completed stickleback genome sequence, we produced the first high quality resources for assaying the difference in gene expression of all of the genes in the stickleback genome. This genome sequence was particularly useful for our project as it was produced from a single fish from one the lines that we produced in fulfillment of this project. We developed several new approaches based on microarray and new sequencing platforms, to examine the complete suite of genes expressed in small numbers of bone and cartilage cells at the beginning of head and jaw development that we isolated using a very precise laser-capture micro-dissection microscope.&nbsp;</span></p> <p><span><span> </span>The completion of our project has led to the publication of nearly a dozen scientific papers that have been well received by the scientific community. Support from this grant has also produced benefits to other researchers, as well as increases in student training and expanded scientific education of the broader public. Our research has produced advanced genomic laboratory protocols, and highly efficient computer programs for the analysis of vast amounts of data, both of which are freely available and widely used. To help the community use these resources, we have taught several short courses in places such as Puerto Rico and the National Evolutionary Synthesis Center (NESCent) in Raleigh, NC.<strong> </strong>We have also been describing our research to a wider audience by presenting several public outreach seminars across the U.S., and particularly in Oregon communities. One of our lectures on Genomics and Human Health was attended by nearly 500 members of ...]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ A surprising biological discovery is that even distantly related species use a conserved set of genes during the formation of their bodies. Despite this conservation, organisms are fantastically diverse. Where does variation for the amazing diversity of attributes, such as size, shape or coloration, reside in this conserved genome of organisms? The development of head and jaw structures in fishes provides an excellent opportunity to address this question. The long term objective of this project was to study the genes and development of marked head and jaw differences across populations of threespine stickleback fish that have changed rapidly as they have adapted to novel environmental conditions. For this project we developed a variety of new laboratory and computer tools and approaches to finely dissect genetic variation in the development of stickleback head and jaw bones.    We had three major goals. The first goal was to produce a set of genetically heterogenous laboratory lines of stickleback that varied in head bone and jaw attributes that could be studied to map genes for this variation. We developed stickleback specific protocols to degrade the genetic material of sperm without damaging the cells themselves. We then used these sperm to activate stickleback eggs without contributing any genetic material. These activated embryos, containing only the motherÆs genome, were then restored to their normal two genome copies using manipulations of very young embryos. Using these techniques we produced the first clonal laboratory lines of threespine stickleback. The second goal was to define the spectrum of genetic effects contributing to variation in head bones and jaws. We developed advanced DNA sequencing technologies to rapidly and efficiently isolate causative genomic regions contributing to head and jaw variation. We also produced a detailed growth series to determine how the cartilage and bone cells that make the head and jaws have changed their behaviors, allowing us to link genetic differences to developmental changes. Our last aim was to examine how gene activity modifications in cartilage and bone cells relate to the DNA sequence and developmental differences. Using the newly completed stickleback genome sequence, we produced the first high quality resources for assaying the difference in gene expression of all of the genes in the stickleback genome. This genome sequence was particularly useful for our project as it was produced from a single fish from one the lines that we produced in fulfillment of this project. We developed several new approaches based on microarray and new sequencing platforms, to examine the complete suite of genes expressed in small numbers of bone and cartilage cells at the beginning of head and jaw development that we isolated using a very precise laser-capture micro-dissection microscope.    The completion of our project has led to the publication of nearly a dozen scientific papers that have been well received by the scientific community. Support from this grant has also produced benefits to other researchers, as well as increases in student training and expanded scientific education of the broader public. Our research has produced advanced genomic laboratory protocols, and highly efficient computer programs for the analysis of vast amounts of data, both of which are freely available and widely used. To help the community use these resources, we have taught several short courses in places such as Puerto Rico and the National Evolutionary Synthesis Center (NESCent) in Raleigh, NC. We have also been describing our research to a wider audience by presenting several public outreach seminars across the U.S., and particularly in Oregon communities. One of our lectures on Genomics and Human Health was attended by nearly 500 members of the Eugene community, and another on the same topic was given to 150 medical professionals at the Lane County Medical Board. Finally, this project has supported the ...]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
