<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>CAREER: Data Intensive Grid Computing on Active Storage Clusters</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>05/01/2007</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>04/30/2013</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>398245.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>537894</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>05050000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>CSE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CNS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Computer and Network Systems</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Marilyn McClure</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>mmcclure@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032925197</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Clusters and grids have achieved great successes in executing computation intensive workloads. However, executing data intensive workloads has proven to be much more difficult: data services are a serious bottleneck in large computing systems. To address this problem, cluster and grid computing systems must closely integrate computation with data storage. &lt;br/&gt;A variety of new system structures are being developed according to this principle. &lt;br/&gt;To provide scalable computation and storage, a cluster constructed from active storage units can serve as a combined archival file system and batch computing system. Distributed data structures built on active storage can guide data and computation placement in a coordinated manner. A new cluster programming language allows distributed data structures to be efficiently harnessed by large workloads. The result of this project will be a dramatic increase in the capacity of clusters and grids to process data intensive scientific workloads. This project will serve as an exciting environment for class projects in operating systems and distributed systems classes, and the software developed will be distributed as "courseware" for use by other educators.  This work will have an impact on a wide variety of scientific disciplines, but will work particularly closely with active users in astrophysics, bioinformatics, biometrics, and molecular dynamics. The software created by this project will be disseminated in open source form for use by the broader community.In addition, this software will also be used as a vehicle for making live astrophysics data accessible to high school students and teachers through the Notre Dame Extended Research Community. &lt;br/&gt;</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>03/13/2007</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/19/2011</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.070</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>0643229</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Douglas</FirstName>
<LastName>Thain</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Douglas Thain</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>dthain@nd.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5746316845</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000341714</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>03/13/2007</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Notre Dame</Name>
<CityName>NOTRE DAME</CityName>
<ZipCode>465565708</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5746317432</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>940 Grace Hall</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Indiana</StateName>
<StateCode>IN</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>IN02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>824910376</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF NOTRE DAME DU LAC</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>048994727</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Notre Dame]]></Name>
<CityName>NOTRE DAME</CityName>
<StateCode>IN</StateCode>
<ZipCode>465565708</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[940 Grace Hall]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Indiana</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>IN02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<FoaInformation>
<Code>0000912</Code>
<Name>Computer Science</Name>
</FoaInformation>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>4090</Code>
<Text>ADVANCED NET INFRA &amp; RSCH</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7354</Code>
<Text>CSR-Computer Systems Research</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>8010</Code>
<Text>Computing in the Cloud</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1045</Code>
<Text>CAREER-Faculty Erly Career Dev</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1187</Code>
<Text>PECASE- eligible</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7354</Code>
<Text>COMPUTER SYSTEMS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9178</Code>
<Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9218</Code>
<Text>BASIC RESEARCH &amp; HUMAN RESORCS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9251</Code>
<Text>REU SUPP-Res Exp for Ugrd Supp</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>HPCC</Code>
<Text>HIGH PERFORMANCE COMPUTING &amp; COMM</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0107</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>490100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0108</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0109</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0110</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0111</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2007~171813</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2008~59626</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2009~75875</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2010~214580</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2011~16000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>This CAREER project explored the design and implementation of systems software used to harness clusters, clouds, and grids for large scale data intensive scientific workloads.</p> <p><strong>Intellectual Merit:</strong> We analyzed a variety of existing scientific applications in order to discern the underlying computational patterns. &nbsp;These patterns were used to guide the design of frameworks of 'abstractions' that could be used to scale those applications up to hundreds or thousands of machines drawn from clusters, clouds, and grids. &nbsp;Through detailed performance studies, we observed that these abstractions made it much more tractable to design applications that had predictable performance at a wide variety of scales, making it possible to reliably select the appropriate resources on which to execute the applications. &nbsp;We also observed that similar techniques were effective at harnessing multi-core computers, and hierarchical clusters of multi-core computers.</p> <p><strong>Broader Impact:</strong> Using the techniques developed in this work, we created open source software and deployed it in collaboration with researchers in a variety of high impact applications. &nbsp;This software has been used by active researchers in biometrics, bioinformatics, economics, molecular dynamics, geographic image analysis, and high energy physics to run experiments at scales not previously possible. &nbsp; &nbsp;Multiple workshops were held on campus and at venues around the country to train the community in the use of this software. &nbsp;Graduate and undergraduate students carried out the bulk of the project work, gaining experience in software development, experimental work, and scientific communication. &nbsp;Techniques developed in this project were integrated into the curriculum at the University of Notre Dame in order to train undergraduates in advanced techniques in distributed computing.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <dl class="clearing"><dd> <div class="tinyMCEContent"> <p>&nbsp;</p> </div> </dd></dl> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 08/03/2013<br>      Modified by: Douglas&nbsp;Thain</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ This CAREER project explored the design and implementation of systems software used to harness clusters, clouds, and grids for large scale data intensive scientific workloads.  Intellectual Merit: We analyzed a variety of existing scientific applications in order to discern the underlying computational patterns.  These patterns were used to guide the design of frameworks of 'abstractions' that could be used to scale those applications up to hundreds or thousands of machines drawn from clusters, clouds, and grids.  Through detailed performance studies, we observed that these abstractions made it much more tractable to design applications that had predictable performance at a wide variety of scales, making it possible to reliably select the appropriate resources on which to execute the applications.  We also observed that similar techniques were effective at harnessing multi-core computers, and hierarchical clusters of multi-core computers.  Broader Impact: Using the techniques developed in this work, we created open source software and deployed it in collaboration with researchers in a variety of high impact applications.  This software has been used by active researchers in biometrics, bioinformatics, economics, molecular dynamics, geographic image analysis, and high energy physics to run experiments at scales not previously possible.    Multiple workshops were held on campus and at venues around the country to train the community in the use of this software.  Graduate and undergraduate students carried out the bulk of the project work, gaining experience in software development, experimental work, and scientific communication.  Techniques developed in this project were integrated into the curriculum at the University of Notre Dame in order to train undergraduates in advanced techniques in distributed computing.                    Last Modified: 08/03/2013       Submitted by: Douglas Thain]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
