<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>CAREER: QoS Maps for Large-Scale, High-mobility Wireless Networks</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>01/01/2007</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2012</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>319611.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>399944</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>05050000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>CSE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CNS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Computer and Network Systems</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Thyagarajan Nandagopal</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>tnandago@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924550</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The wireless networks of the next 10 years are expected to consist of a plethora of microprocessor-sensor devices embedded in clothes, shoes, cars, buses, as well as the traditional portable handhelds, and laptops. Since information is expected to flow through thousands to millions of wireless devices themselves in these networks (rather than a few gateways), it is essential that an aggregate view of the essential qualities of the mobile network be built and made available. Quality-of-Service (QoS) decisions (regarding energy consumption, delay and throughput) will play a prominent role in making intelligent decisions in these large-scale networks.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The major research contribution of this project is the development of methodologies for tracking and disseminating QoS metrics in mobile, wireless networks of microprocessor-sensor devices by building QoS maps in the joint memories of the nodes over relevant time scales. QoS potential functions are constructed over space by the nodes via path integration methods, and distributed via information exchange during node encounters. Novel concepts, such as the coherence time of QoS metrics, enable the application of signal processing methods to the refinement of QoS maps.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project opens the way to building the first-generation large-scale networks of small, mobile, microprocessor-sensor devices in civilian settings, which will transform the way our society operates, utilizing a plethora of sensors and supporting semantic devices that translate this information to useful actions. This project integrates the traditionally separate signal processing and networking techniques in graduate coursework, and develops an early career focus program for minority undergraduate students.&lt;br/&gt;</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>12/20/2006</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>01/14/2011</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.070</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>0643946</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Volkan</FirstName>
<LastName>Rodoplu</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Volkan Rodoplu</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>vrodoplu@ece.ucsb.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>8052943150</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000202496</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>12/20/2006</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of California-Santa Barbara</Name>
<CityName>Santa Barbara</CityName>
<ZipCode>931062050</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>8058934188</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>Office of Research</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[Rm 3227 Cheadle Hall]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>24</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CA24</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>094878394</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF CALIFORNIA, SANTA BARBARA</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>071549000</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of California-Santa Barbara]]></Name>
<CityName>Santa Barbara</CityName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>931062050</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[Office of Research]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>24</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CA24</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<FoaInformation>
<Code>0000912</Code>
<Name>Computer Science</Name>
</FoaInformation>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>4090</Code>
<Text>ADVANCED NET INFRA &amp; RSCH</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7363</Code>
<Text>Networking Technology and Syst</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1045</Code>
<Text>CAREER-Faculty Erly Career Dev</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7363</Code>
<Text>RES IN NETWORKING TECH &amp; SYS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9218</Code>
<Text>BASIC RESEARCH &amp; HUMAN RESORCS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>HPCC</Code>
<Text>HIGH PERFORMANCE COMPUTING &amp; COMM</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0107</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>490100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0108</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0109</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0111</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2007~79288</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2008~79773</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2009~160434</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2011~80449</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The goal of this project was to develop a novel method to conceptualize the delivery of Quality of Service (QoS) in mobile wireless networks, and to develop algorithms and protocols to enable QoS delivery. Mobile wireless networks are made up of a large number of mobile terminals (a.k.a. users or nodes) in which devices can communicate directly with each other, without the help of a base station. When there is no gateway that connects such a network into the wired domain, such a network is called an &ldquo;ad hoc&rdquo; network; otherwise, it is called a &ldquo;hybrid&rdquo; network. Our main emphasis in this project has been on hybrid networks in which data or voice travels from the source of origin, through multiple mobile terminals, eventually to a gateway. Such hybrid networks can be considered as extensions of cellular networks.</p> <p>QoS refers to the set of network metrics such as end-to-end delay (important for voice communication), end-to-end energy consumption (important for battery-limited mobile devices), and packet error rate (important for successful delivery of data). These metrics are the network designer&rsquo;s measures that roughly translate to the user&rsquo;s experience of voice and data reception. The traditional methods of delivering QoS in mobile networks conceived of the path through which data travels as a sequence of nodes. The problem with this approach was that links between nodes break frequently due to mobility; hence, end-to-end QoS delivery through mobile networks becomes a challenge, and in many cases delivering QoS within acceptable ranges becomes impossible.</p> <p>Our breakthrough insight was that the path that data travels should not be considered as the sequence of nodes, but rather as a sequence of patches of space. All that is needed for data to cross a patch of space is that at least an intermediate node that can carry the data be present on that patch, at the moment of delivery. In high-density areas, such as cities, there is a high likelihood that some node will be there to carry the data, through space, to the ultimate gateway.</p> <p>Our results obtained via sophisticated, realistic simulation of such networks, showed that when paths are conceptualized as spatial paths, and routing algorithms are designed according to this new notion, the end-to-end QoS metrics show much more stability than what can be obtained via the traditional node-centric routing protocols. To this end, we have successfully designed protocols to enable Voice over IP (VoIP) traffic to be delivered end-to-end while meeting the stringent voice delay constraints. As a side result, we have also collected end-to-end VoIP delay measurements, and found that an exponentially decaying model gives a very good fit for modeling end-to-end VoIP traffic.</p> <p>In the second part of the project, we have expanded the scope of our work to issues of trustworthiness and reliability in networks. Often, the presence or absence of a route is a measure of reliability. Furthermore, it is important to understand whether data are traveling through a trustworthy region or whether it can be compromised. By using our framework, we have shown that trustworthiness and reliability can be successfully delivered in such network scenarios.</p> <p>Through the course of the project, we have developed several novel methods that are important in their own right: First, we have created spatial QoS maps that show, instantaneously, what QoS can be delivered on a terrain at that moment in space. Second, we have utilized the fact that nodes are mobile, to enable the nodes to exchange the QoS information that they collect piecemeal, in their encounters with other nodes. We have introduced two novel concepts into the networking literature: The spreading period is the time that it takes for a token of information to spread throughout a network. The coherence time of a QoS metric is the time fo...]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The goal of this project was to develop a novel method to conceptualize the delivery of Quality of Service (QoS) in mobile wireless networks, and to develop algorithms and protocols to enable QoS delivery. Mobile wireless networks are made up of a large number of mobile terminals (a.k.a. users or nodes) in which devices can communicate directly with each other, without the help of a base station. When there is no gateway that connects such a network into the wired domain, such a network is called an "ad hoc" network; otherwise, it is called a "hybrid" network. Our main emphasis in this project has been on hybrid networks in which data or voice travels from the source of origin, through multiple mobile terminals, eventually to a gateway. Such hybrid networks can be considered as extensions of cellular networks.  QoS refers to the set of network metrics such as end-to-end delay (important for voice communication), end-to-end energy consumption (important for battery-limited mobile devices), and packet error rate (important for successful delivery of data). These metrics are the network designerÆs measures that roughly translate to the userÆs experience of voice and data reception. The traditional methods of delivering QoS in mobile networks conceived of the path through which data travels as a sequence of nodes. The problem with this approach was that links between nodes break frequently due to mobility; hence, end-to-end QoS delivery through mobile networks becomes a challenge, and in many cases delivering QoS within acceptable ranges becomes impossible.  Our breakthrough insight was that the path that data travels should not be considered as the sequence of nodes, but rather as a sequence of patches of space. All that is needed for data to cross a patch of space is that at least an intermediate node that can carry the data be present on that patch, at the moment of delivery. In high-density areas, such as cities, there is a high likelihood that some node will be there to carry the data, through space, to the ultimate gateway.  Our results obtained via sophisticated, realistic simulation of such networks, showed that when paths are conceptualized as spatial paths, and routing algorithms are designed according to this new notion, the end-to-end QoS metrics show much more stability than what can be obtained via the traditional node-centric routing protocols. To this end, we have successfully designed protocols to enable Voice over IP (VoIP) traffic to be delivered end-to-end while meeting the stringent voice delay constraints. As a side result, we have also collected end-to-end VoIP delay measurements, and found that an exponentially decaying model gives a very good fit for modeling end-to-end VoIP traffic.  In the second part of the project, we have expanded the scope of our work to issues of trustworthiness and reliability in networks. Often, the presence or absence of a route is a measure of reliability. Furthermore, it is important to understand whether data are traveling through a trustworthy region or whether it can be compromised. By using our framework, we have shown that trustworthiness and reliability can be successfully delivered in such network scenarios.  Through the course of the project, we have developed several novel methods that are important in their own right: First, we have created spatial QoS maps that show, instantaneously, what QoS can be delivered on a terrain at that moment in space. Second, we have utilized the fact that nodes are mobile, to enable the nodes to exchange the QoS information that they collect piecemeal, in their encounters with other nodes. We have introduced two novel concepts into the networking literature: The spreading period is the time that it takes for a token of information to spread throughout a network. The coherence time of a QoS metric is the time for which the spatial QoS metric remains roughly the same. We have demonstrated that if the spreading period is much less than the...]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
