<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>CAREER:    Economic Theory, Testing of Theories</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2007</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2013</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>400000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>400000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>04050000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>SBE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>SES</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Divn Of Social and Economic Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Georgia Kosmopoulou</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>gkosmopo@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032920000</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This CAREER project is a collection of several studies; two main of them are: Testing Probabilistic Theories and Repeated Games with Private Monitoring. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Perhaps surprisingly, it is not easy to come up with "good" empirical tests, which would reveal if potential experts know the actual data generating processes, without making hard to validate assumptions on the process itself; examples include weather forecasts or forecasts of financial analysts. Several authors, beginning with Foster and Vohra, show that some natural tests (such as calibration) or classes of tests (such as tests that must give a verdict in a fixed finite time), that control for type I error have completely no power of controlling for type II error. Referring to the ideas introduced by Dekel and Feinberg, a good test that controls for both types of errors can be constructed. Yet, it is conjectured that this and other good tests have to use counterfactual predictions in the way that is rare in statistics. Testing Probabilistic Theories seeks to identify properties of good tests, circumstances that allow for good empirical testing, as well as implementability of good tests, or strategies for passing ignorantly well-known empirical tests, in concrete settings (such as weather forecasting, or financial analysis).&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Repeated Games with Private Monitoring attempts to determine the range of possible equilibrium outcomes for repeated games with imperfect private monitoring, and if possible, to provide "simple" and "robust" equilibria.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The CAREER project also includes ongoing studies on law and economics, mechanism design, decision theory and communication. For example, the study on law and economics compares different forms of arbitration (such as that in the Major League Baseball) from a welfare perspective.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The Broader Impacts&lt;br/&gt;Testing Probabilistic Theories makes a contribution not only to economics, but also to other disciplines, including the philosophy of science. The results may have impact on demarcation criteria commonly used in science; for example, they cast some doubts on the celebrated falsifiability criteria of Popper. The results also seem to have a number of potential concrete applications (such as testing weather forecasts, and possibly recommendations of financial analysts). &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The literature on repeated games traditionally has implications regarding collusive behavior in oligopoly markets and antitrust regulations, and the objective of welfare analysis of arbitration is to provide some insight on which form of arbitration should be used in public services such as police and fire protection, buyers and sellers in commercial contracts, baseball players and club owners, and divorce settlements.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;It is an essential objective of this CAREER project to combine research with teaching. Summer reading groups on topics related to the ongoing studies are organized for graduate students who wish to specialize in economic theory, with the objective of facilitating the transition from coursework to independent research. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Interested undergraduate students are offered the opportunity of working as research assistants, e.g. collecting narrative evidence on evaluation schemes in industries producing probabilistic forecasts or collecting similar evidence regarding arbitration, and simultaneously, writing their senior dissertations and independent papers on the same or related topics.&lt;br/&gt;</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>02/20/2007</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/13/2010</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.075</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>0644930</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Wojciech</FirstName>
<LastName>Olszewski</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Wojciech Olszewski</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>wo@northwestern.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>8474918482</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000190176</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>02/20/2007</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Northwestern University</Name>
<CityName>Chicago</CityName>
<ZipCode>606114579</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>3125037955</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>750 N. Lake Shore Drive</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[Rubloff 7th Floor]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Illinois</StateName>
<StateCode>IL</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>IL07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>160079455</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>NORTHWESTERN UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>005436803</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Northwestern University]]></Name>
<CityName>Chicago</CityName>
<StateCode>IL</StateCode>
<ZipCode>606114579</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[750 N. Lake Shore Drive]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Illinois</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>IL07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1320</Code>
<Text>Economics</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>0000</Code>
<Text>UNASSIGNED</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1045</Code>
<Text>CAREER-Faculty Erly Career Dev</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1187</Code>
<Text>PECASE- eligible</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>OTHR</Code>
<Text>OTHER RESEARCH OR EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0107</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>490100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0108</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0109</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0110</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2007~88877</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2008~79910</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2009~80001</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2010~151212</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><span style="font-family: Times New Roman; font-size: small;"> </span></p> <p style="margin: 0in 0in 0pt; line-height: normal; mso-layout-grid-align: none;">This CAREER proposal comprised several theoretical projects, two main of them were: (1) testing probabilistic forecasts or theories; and (2) dynamic models with private monitoring.<span style="font-size: small;"> </span></p> <p style="margin: 0in 0in 0pt; line-height: normal; mso-layout-grid-align: none;"><span style="font-size: small;"><br /></span></p> <p style="margin: 0in 0in 0pt; line-height: normal; mso-layout-grid-align: none;"><span><span style="mso-spacerun: yes;">&nbsp;</span>(1) Probabilistic hypotheses are in use throughout the science, and in numerous&nbsp;</span><span>everyday activities, such as weather forecasting or stock market analysis. Statistics is centered on testing these hypotheses. It (implicitly) assumes that the hypotheses being tested were born out of thin air, and were completely unlinked to the testing methods. In particular the hypothesis generating entity had no incentives of its own. The research conducted within this proposal is about testing hypotheses delivered by self-interested strategic experts, anticipating these tests.</span></p> <p style="margin: 0in 0in 0pt; line-height: normal; mso-layout-grid-align: none;"><span><br /></span></p> <p style="margin: 0in 0in 0pt; line-height: normal; mso-layout-grid-align: none;"><span>This project resulted in a number of findings regarding the philosophy of science, and suggestions regarding testing methods; in particular: </span><span>(1) the celebrated</span></p> <p style="margin: 0in 0in 0pt; line-height: normal; mso-layout-grid-align: none;"><span style="font-size: small;">&nbsp;</span></p> <p style="margin: 0in 0in 0pt; line-height: normal; mso-layout-grid-align: none;"><span>falsifiability of Popper has no power to distinguish scientific theories from worthless theories when theories can be produced by strategic experts; (2) the premise of accepting theories only because they explain existing data is vulnerable to manipulation of strategic but ignorant &ldquo;experts;&rdquo; (3) the maxim that testable theories should not be rejected until found inconsistent with the data </span><span>is immune to this kind of manipulation; (4) forecasts regarding the future, which cannot be tested with currently existed data, may be an essential component in evaluating theories; in particular, experts should not be judged based on the forecasts they make &ldquo;day by day&rdquo; but on complete theories they deliver.</span></p> <p style="margin: 0in 0in 0pt; line-height: normal; mso-layout-grid-align: none;"><span style="font-size: small;">&nbsp;</span></p> <p style="margin: 0in 0in 0pt; line-height: normal; mso-layout-grid-align: none;"><span>An essential component of this part of the proposal was to advise graduate, and especially undergraduate students in conducting research on compensation schemes in the industries in which experts make probabilistic forecasts.<span style="mso-spacerun: yes;">&nbsp; </span>Several Northwestern students conducted research on this and related topics, including an undergraduate who wrote an awarded honors thesis. <span style="mso-spacerun: yes;">&nbsp;</span></span></p> <p style="margin: 0in 0in 0pt; line-height: normal; mso-layout-grid-align: none;"><span><span style="mso-spacerun: yes;"><br /></span></span></p> <p style="margin: 0in 0in 0pt; line-height: normal; mso-layout-grid-align: none;"><span>(2) Monitoring is essential in economic activity, and especially in longer, dynamic interactions. People who are not monitored by others often have lower incentives for providing effort. In practice, monitoring is typically subjective and private, or at least contains such a component in it; for example, even if you work as hard as you can, you may not be sure that your effort is appreciated by your supervisor. <spa...]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[   This CAREER proposal comprised several theoretical projects, two main of them were: (1) testing probabilistic forecasts or theories; and (2) dynamic models with private monitoring.     (1) Probabilistic hypotheses are in use throughout the science, and in numerous everyday activities, such as weather forecasting or stock market analysis. Statistics is centered on testing these hypotheses. It (implicitly) assumes that the hypotheses being tested were born out of thin air, and were completely unlinked to the testing methods. In particular the hypothesis generating entity had no incentives of its own. The research conducted within this proposal is about testing hypotheses delivered by self-interested strategic experts, anticipating these tests.   This project resulted in a number of findings regarding the philosophy of science, and suggestions regarding testing methods; in particular: (1) the celebrated   falsifiability of Popper has no power to distinguish scientific theories from worthless theories when theories can be produced by strategic experts; (2) the premise of accepting theories only because they explain existing data is vulnerable to manipulation of strategic but ignorant "experts;" (3) the maxim that testable theories should not be rejected until found inconsistent with the data is immune to this kind of manipulation; (4) forecasts regarding the future, which cannot be tested with currently existed data, may be an essential component in evaluating theories; in particular, experts should not be judged based on the forecasts they make "day by day" but on complete theories they deliver.   An essential component of this part of the proposal was to advise graduate, and especially undergraduate students in conducting research on compensation schemes in the industries in which experts make probabilistic forecasts.  Several Northwestern students conducted research on this and related topics, including an undergraduate who wrote an awarded honors thesis.     (2) Monitoring is essential in economic activity, and especially in longer, dynamic interactions. People who are not monitored by others often have lower incentives for providing effort. In practice, monitoring is typically subjective and private, or at least contains such a component in it; for example, even if you work as hard as you can, you may not be sure that your effort is appreciated by your supervisor.     Dynamic economic models, such as repeated games, have been (for long time) disregarding a private component of monitoring, assuming it to be public; that is, assuming that you know precisely what your supervisor thinks about you. There were several reasons for doing it. For example, it has not occur until the nineties that adding even a small dose of private monitoring to a public monitoring model can dramatically change its predictions; more importantly, the analysis of private monitoring models is very complicated.      The part of the proposal devoted to private monitoring was focused more on tools for economic analysis, rather than studying phenomena observed in practice. The objective was to see whether public monitoring models deliver similar outcomes as corresponding models with private monitoring, and to deliver tools for studying of private monitoring explicitly.   A substantial progress has been achieved regarding the former task. The research of this project, and follow-up research inspired by the methods developed within this project, show that the outcomes of public and private monitoring models are not as different as it might have initially appeared, and generate the same outcomes in a large class of repeated games. Despite some progress made within this project, the latter task basically remains an open problem.      As mentioned earlier, several other projects on various topics have been conducted within this CAREER proposal. For example, the project on arbitration compares two, most commonly used in practice, forms of arbitration from the we...]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
