<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>CAREER: The Grammar Matrix: Computational Linguistic Typology</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>03/15/2007</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>02/28/2013</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>474229.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>474229</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>04040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>SBE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>BCS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Behavioral and Cognitive Sci</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>William Badecker</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>wbadecke@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032925069</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Linguists investigate the structure of natural languages by building models called grammars which associate strings of words with their semantic representations.  As natural languages are quite complex in their structure, there are great benefits to building these models as computer software, both in managing the complex interactions of subparts of the model and in automating the testing of the model against large collections of natural language text.  However, such computerized models are expensive and difficult to build, so most linguistic hypothesis testing takes place off-line.  At the same time, there are great similarities among languages, suggesting that existing work on computerized models for a few well-studied languages can be leveraged to jump start the creation of models for other languages.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;With this CAREER award, Dr. Emily Bender aims to develop a grammar customization system that combines a cross-linguistic core grammar with a series of 'libraries' specifying alternate ways of realizing different linguistic subsystems that vary across languages (e.g., the expression of tense and aspect, coordination, or negation).  This system will allow linguists to easily customize a small working grammar for a particular language, which they can then use as a test-bed for further linguistic investigation.  The process of building the system itself will involve an unprecedented exploration of computational linguistic typology, exploring precise analyses of diverse linguistic phenomena across a sample of languages which show the boundaries of variation.  The broader impacts of this project include the potential for quicker, more precise documentation of endangered languages and cheaper development of natural language technology (including machine translation, grammar checkers and computer-assisted language learning programs) in under-resourced languages. This project is cofunded by the Linguistics Program in the Behavioral &amp; Cognitive Sciences Division of the Social, Behavioral &amp; Economic Sciences Directorate and the Robust Intelligence Cluster in the Information &amp; Intelligent Systems Division of the Computer &amp; Information Science &amp; Engineering Directorate.&lt;br/&gt;</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>03/09/2007</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>01/20/2011</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.075</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>0644097</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Emily</FirstName>
<LastName>Bender</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>M</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Emily M Bender</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>ebender@u.washington.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2065436914</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000429660</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>03/09/2007</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Washington</Name>
<CityName>Seattle</CityName>
<ZipCode>981950001</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2065434043</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>4333 Brooklyn Ave NE</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Washington</StateName>
<StateCode>WA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>WA07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>605799469</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF WASHINGTON</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>042803536</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Washington]]></Name>
<CityName>Seattle</CityName>
<StateCode>WA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>981950001</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[4333 Brooklyn Ave NE]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Washington</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>WA07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1311</Code>
<Text>Linguistics</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7495</Code>
<Text>Robust Intelligence</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>0000</Code>
<Text>UNASSIGNED</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1045</Code>
<Text>CAREER-Faculty Erly Career Dev</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1187</Code>
<Text>PECASE- eligible</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7495</Code>
<Text>ROBUST INTELLIGENCE</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>OTHR</Code>
<Text>OTHER RESEARCH OR EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0107</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>490100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0108</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0109</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0110</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0111</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2007~87119</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2008~90937</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2009~94704</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2010~98658</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2011~102811</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The Grammar Matrix began as a starter-kit for creating computational grammars of natural languages. &nbsp;It was initially developed by abstracting out those parts of a large computational grammar for English that appeared likely to be cross-linguistically useful. The goal of the project, from the beginning, has been to facilitate the rapid development of computational grammars for both linguistic research and practical applications, while promoting consistency across grammars for interoperability with downstream processing and comparative typological linguistic research. In other words, by helping to create grammars of different languages that produce comparable meaning representations and that use similar rules to do so, we further the scientific goals of comparing the grammars of different languages and the engineering goals of the development of multilingual applications, including machine translation as well as monolingual systems (e.g., for grammar checking or dialog systems) that can be ported from resource-rich languages to resource-poor languages by switching out the grammar.</p> <p>This project has extended the initial Grammar Matrix beyond the initial core grammar to include a series of libraries of analyses of linguistic phenomena which vary across languages. Through the grant period, the Grammar Matrix customization system went from a simple proof&shy;-of&shy;-concept to a rich resource that continues to be actively used and developed. &nbsp;One measure of the degree of complexity it has attained is in the way users interact with the system. Where initially the customization system could be filled out relatively quickly, it now supports so much grammar development that users include it in the iterative develop&shy;-and-&shy;test cycle typical of grammar engineering. That is, they develop an initial version of the grammar, try parsing some sentences and then return to the customization system to extend their grammar. In addition to dozens of small grammars developed in the context of course work, the Grammar Matrix has been used as the basis of larger linguistically and/or practically oriented grammars for Bulgarian, Danish, Dutch, German, Hausa, Mandarin, Norwegian, Portuguese, Spanish, Turkish, and Wambaya.</p> <p>The more phenomena we add to the customization system, the more extensive the grammar fragments it can produce, and thus the more useful it is to grammar engineers. These increasing benefits span all of the initial goals of the Grammar Matrix project: to cut down on development time, to standardize (to the extent possible) semantic representations across grammars for different languages, and to lower the bar to entry to grammar engineering. &nbsp;By basing the libraries we develop on surveys of the literature in linguistic typology, we ensure that the resulting resource is as cross-&shy;linguistically applicable as possible, and not tailored only to well&shy; studied languages. This, together with the lowering the barrier to entry, is what makes it likely that the Grammar Matrix will be useful in the context of language documentation (the subject of a follow-&shy;on project, AGGREGATION; BCS-1160274).</p> <p>The Grammar Matrix project has also established the value and practicality of grammar customization as an approach to grammar engineering, providing the basis for two important further innovations. First, in the CLIMB project, started by Grammar Matrix collaborator Antske Fokkens, the notion of grammar customization is applied to the development of individual grammars. Second, the customization system as a whole can be seen as an algorithm for mapping from relatively simple linguistic descriptions to working, elaborated grammar fragments which relate linguistic strings to semantic representations, in both parsing and generation. This opens up very interesting possibilities for the automatic creation of such grammars: The grammars themsel...]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The Grammar Matrix began as a starter-kit for creating computational grammars of natural languages.  It was initially developed by abstracting out those parts of a large computational grammar for English that appeared likely to be cross-linguistically useful. The goal of the project, from the beginning, has been to facilitate the rapid development of computational grammars for both linguistic research and practical applications, while promoting consistency across grammars for interoperability with downstream processing and comparative typological linguistic research. In other words, by helping to create grammars of different languages that produce comparable meaning representations and that use similar rules to do so, we further the scientific goals of comparing the grammars of different languages and the engineering goals of the development of multilingual applications, including machine translation as well as monolingual systems (e.g., for grammar checking or dialog systems) that can be ported from resource-rich languages to resource-poor languages by switching out the grammar.  This project has extended the initial Grammar Matrix beyond the initial core grammar to include a series of libraries of analyses of linguistic phenomena which vary across languages. Through the grant period, the Grammar Matrix customization system went from a simple proof&shy;-of&shy;-concept to a rich resource that continues to be actively used and developed.  One measure of the degree of complexity it has attained is in the way users interact with the system. Where initially the customization system could be filled out relatively quickly, it now supports so much grammar development that users include it in the iterative develop&shy;-and-&shy;test cycle typical of grammar engineering. That is, they develop an initial version of the grammar, try parsing some sentences and then return to the customization system to extend their grammar. In addition to dozens of small grammars developed in the context of course work, the Grammar Matrix has been used as the basis of larger linguistically and/or practically oriented grammars for Bulgarian, Danish, Dutch, German, Hausa, Mandarin, Norwegian, Portuguese, Spanish, Turkish, and Wambaya.  The more phenomena we add to the customization system, the more extensive the grammar fragments it can produce, and thus the more useful it is to grammar engineers. These increasing benefits span all of the initial goals of the Grammar Matrix project: to cut down on development time, to standardize (to the extent possible) semantic representations across grammars for different languages, and to lower the bar to entry to grammar engineering.  By basing the libraries we develop on surveys of the literature in linguistic typology, we ensure that the resulting resource is as cross-&shy;linguistically applicable as possible, and not tailored only to well&shy; studied languages. This, together with the lowering the barrier to entry, is what makes it likely that the Grammar Matrix will be useful in the context of language documentation (the subject of a follow-&shy;on project, AGGREGATION; BCS-1160274).  The Grammar Matrix project has also established the value and practicality of grammar customization as an approach to grammar engineering, providing the basis for two important further innovations. First, in the CLIMB project, started by Grammar Matrix collaborator Antske Fokkens, the notion of grammar customization is applied to the development of individual grammars. Second, the customization system as a whole can be seen as an algorithm for mapping from relatively simple linguistic descriptions to working, elaborated grammar fragments which relate linguistic strings to semantic representations, in both parsing and generation. This opens up very interesting possibilities for the automatic creation of such grammars: The grammars themselves are too complex to be the target of machine learning, but the choices files are much more a...]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
