<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>CAREER: Strongly Correlated Quantum Phenomena in Low-Dimensional Systems</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2007</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2015</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>400000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>480000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03070000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DMR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Materials Research</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Daryl Hess</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>dhess@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924942</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>TECHNICAL SUMMARY:&lt;br/&gt;This CAREER award supports theoretical research and education on strongly correlated quantum phenomena in low-dimensional systems. The research plan employs a common set of theoretical techniques to explore strongly correlated physics in three such systems which have drawn the attention of the scientific community and have been the focus of cutting-edge experimental investigations: 1) carbon nanotubes, 2) trapped atomic systems and 3) fractional quantum Hall systems. These systems address complementary aspects of low-dimensional systems and have both fundamental and technological value. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The major focus of this research program will in three specific arenas:&lt;br/&gt;i) Luttinger-liquid physics and spin-charge separation: Probes and characteristic signatures of the Luttinger-liquid physics, which is characteristic of one dimension, will be explored in nanotubes and trapped atomic systems with emphasis on spin-charge (density) separation. Novel physics, only recently observed in solid state systems, will be explored in the trapped atomic clusters by exploiting the unprecedented level of tuning capability that is possible.&lt;br/&gt;ii) Quantum dot physics in nanotubes: Short nanotubes placed between tunnel contacts have displayed quantum dot behavior, which could be exploited for quantum-device applications. The quantum states of such nanotubes will be characterized, and schemes will be proposed for realizing quantum entanglement in coupled tubes.&lt;br/&gt;iii) Measurement of fractional statistics: The prospect of detecting fractional statistics in quantum Hall systems will be investigated. The intent is to identify experimental consequences that may be described for measurements and analyses which will permit identification of clear-cut signatures of fractional quantum numbers.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The education component consists of interconnected plans for education and outreach that span high school to graduate level education, seek to enhance participation of underrepresented groups, and include an international dimension.  Included in this activity are workshops for women faculty, researchers, and students; interaction with Wellesley to share and develop educational resources for undergraduates; outreach to local high schools that is stimulated by the PI's collaboration on outreach activities with the Bangalore Association for Scientific Education in India; and specific contributions to "discovery-style" experimental units in a sweeping revitalization of laboratory courses.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;NON-TECHNICAL SUMMARY:&lt;br/&gt;This CAREER award supports theoretical research and education into the unusual physics that underlies the complex behaviors of very small electronic systems and electrons that are confined to planes or lines. The award also supports education, particularly as it relates to the new area of nanotechnology, through the involvement of students in the research and a range of outreach efforts at both the local and international level. The research effort investigates electronic structure of small assemblies of atoms, including carbon nanotubes which have a rapidly growing role in nanotechnology. Theoretical techniques will be developed and used to describe the incompletely-understood electronic properties of materials when employed in extremely miniaturized devices. These will necessarily employ quantum theory governing the dynamics of such small systems and build on and extend the recent advances in applying the theoretical techniques to small nanoscale structures. The research has both theoretical and technological value. It is designed to engage directly issues encountered in ultra-small experimental systems that are now receiving intense scrutiny by researchers in experimental physics and technology-focused investigations. From the technological perspective, these studies of quantum physics in small confined materials will be supportive of work towards building nanoscale devices and realizing future technological advances put forth by the newly emerging field of quantum information science.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/06/2007</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/19/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>0644022</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Smitha</FirstName>
<LastName>Vishveshwara</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Smitha Vishveshwara</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>smivish@illinois.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2173332187</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000208535</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/06/2007</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign</Name>
<CityName>Champaign</CityName>
<ZipCode>618207406</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2173332187</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1901 South First Street</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[Suite A]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Illinois</StateName>
<StateCode>IL</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>13</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>IL13</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>041544081</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF ILLINOIS</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>041544081</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign]]></Name>
<CityName>Champaign</CityName>
<StateCode>IL</StateCode>
<ZipCode>618207406</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[1901 South First Street]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Illinois</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>13</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>IL13</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<FoaInformation>
<Code>0106000</Code>
<Name>Materials Research</Name>
</FoaInformation>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1253</Code>
<Text>OFFICE OF MULTIDISCIPLINARY AC</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1765</Code>
<Text>CONDENSED MATTER &amp; MAT THEORY</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1045</Code>
<Text>CAREER-Faculty Erly Career Dev</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1187</Code>
<Text>PECASE- eligible</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>6863</Code>
<Text>SEBML-MOORE'S LAW</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7203</Code>
<Text>QUANTUM INFORMATION SCIENCE</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7237</Code>
<Text>NANO NON-SOLIC SCI &amp; ENG AWD</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7574</Code>
<Text>CYBER INFRA FOR MATERIALS RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7799</Code>
<Text>ACI FELLOWS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9161</Code>
<Text>SINGLE DIVISION/UNIVERSITY</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>AMPP</Code>
<Text>ADVANCED MATERIALS &amp; PROCESSING PROGRAM</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0107</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>490100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0109</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0110</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0111</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2007~160000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2009~80000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2010~120000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2011~120000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>In physical systems and materials in which constituent particles are strongly correlated, interactions give rise to collective behavior markedly different from that of the individual particles, particularly in low dimensions. A major goal of condensed matter physics, from both fundamental and applied perspectives, lies in understanding the phases, the observable &lsquo;quasiparticles&rsquo;, and the dynamics in such systems.</p> <p>This CAREER project addressed this goal theoretically in a diverse range of settings, including two-dimensional quantum Hall systems, optical lattices and other cold atomic physics, and one-dimensional systems, such as etched nanowires, superconducting wires and carbon nanotubes. <br /><br /><strong>Intellectual Merit:</strong> Exploring the spectrum of behavior resulting from strong correlations and low-dimensions led to insights on several different fronts. Specific thrusts included the following.&nbsp; i) The co-existence of different phases of matter, characteristic signatures, and novel dynamics were analyzed in cold atomic optical lattice systems. ii) As a striking hallmark of strong correlations, &lsquo;fractionalization&rsquo; and related fractional quantum statistics were studied in the context of thin mesoscopic rings and quantum Hall settings, accompanied by proposals for their detection in realistic experiments. iii) At the nanoscale, carbon nanotubes in the presence of applied fields were investigated, including an analysis of quantum dot physics, with an eye towards application to quantum information science. iv) Of&nbsp; late, in systems exhibiting &lsquo;topological order&rsquo;, the notion of the &lsquo;Majorana fermion&rsquo; has come to the limelight as an exotic quantum entity and for the purpose of quantum computation. The stability of such entities in superconducting wires was established in a range of physical setting, such as in the presence of quasiperiodic and disordered potential landscapes. v) As a new frontier, the interplay of non-equilibrium dynamics, low-dimensionality and topological order formed a significant part of the project.</p> <p>Together, these studies revealed the diversity and richness exhibited by strongly correlated low-dimensional systems, made connections with experimental studies, and proposed potential applications.<br /><br /><strong>Broader Impact:</strong> Several of the theoretical findings are of immediate experimental relevance and are accompanied by proposals for viable experiments in solid state and cold atomic systems. A set of studies have addressed open issues in the fertile and active area of research related to topological systems and Majorana fermions. Other related studies involved the realm of nanophysics and are directly applicable to nanoscience based technologies. Findings on the topological and nanophysics fronts would be relevant to developments in quantum information science and quantum computing.</p> <p>The training of students and junior researchers involved multiple aspects. In addition to acquiring theoretical techniques in quantum condensed matter physics, graduate students worked closely with experimental groups. Graduate students were mentored not only by the PI but also postdoctoral researchers in the department and collaborators. The project contributed to the thesis work of four graduate students and to undergraduate reading courses.</p> <p>The PI developed an advanced graduate special topics course covering several topics of this project and has also used the course material for guided graduate study.&nbsp; An international liaison, with Prof. Diptiman Sen, led to PI and student exchanges with the Indian Institute of Science, Bangalore, India. Another liaison and extensive collaboration, with Prof. Courtney Lannert, established connections with Wellesley College, a liberal-arts college for women. <br />&nbsp;<br />The PIs was heavily involved in outreach a...]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ In physical systems and materials in which constituent particles are strongly correlated, interactions give rise to collective behavior markedly different from that of the individual particles, particularly in low dimensions. A major goal of condensed matter physics, from both fundamental and applied perspectives, lies in understanding the phases, the observable æquasiparticlesÆ, and the dynamics in such systems.  This CAREER project addressed this goal theoretically in a diverse range of settings, including two-dimensional quantum Hall systems, optical lattices and other cold atomic physics, and one-dimensional systems, such as etched nanowires, superconducting wires and carbon nanotubes.   Intellectual Merit: Exploring the spectrum of behavior resulting from strong correlations and low-dimensions led to insights on several different fronts. Specific thrusts included the following.  i) The co-existence of different phases of matter, characteristic signatures, and novel dynamics were analyzed in cold atomic optical lattice systems. ii) As a striking hallmark of strong correlations, æfractionalizationÆ and related fractional quantum statistics were studied in the context of thin mesoscopic rings and quantum Hall settings, accompanied by proposals for their detection in realistic experiments. iii) At the nanoscale, carbon nanotubes in the presence of applied fields were investigated, including an analysis of quantum dot physics, with an eye towards application to quantum information science. iv) Of  late, in systems exhibiting ætopological orderÆ, the notion of the æMajorana fermionÆ has come to the limelight as an exotic quantum entity and for the purpose of quantum computation. The stability of such entities in superconducting wires was established in a range of physical setting, such as in the presence of quasiperiodic and disordered potential landscapes. v) As a new frontier, the interplay of non-equilibrium dynamics, low-dimensionality and topological order formed a significant part of the project.  Together, these studies revealed the diversity and richness exhibited by strongly correlated low-dimensional systems, made connections with experimental studies, and proposed potential applications.  Broader Impact: Several of the theoretical findings are of immediate experimental relevance and are accompanied by proposals for viable experiments in solid state and cold atomic systems. A set of studies have addressed open issues in the fertile and active area of research related to topological systems and Majorana fermions. Other related studies involved the realm of nanophysics and are directly applicable to nanoscience based technologies. Findings on the topological and nanophysics fronts would be relevant to developments in quantum information science and quantum computing.  The training of students and junior researchers involved multiple aspects. In addition to acquiring theoretical techniques in quantum condensed matter physics, graduate students worked closely with experimental groups. Graduate students were mentored not only by the PI but also postdoctoral researchers in the department and collaborators. The project contributed to the thesis work of four graduate students and to undergraduate reading courses.  The PI developed an advanced graduate special topics course covering several topics of this project and has also used the course material for guided graduate study.  An international liaison, with Prof. Diptiman Sen, led to PI and student exchanges with the Indian Institute of Science, Bangalore, India. Another liaison and extensive collaboration, with Prof. Courtney Lannert, established connections with Wellesley College, a liberal-arts college for women.    The PIs was heavily involved in outreach as a part of the activities concerning this project. She was very active in Women in Physics groups and related mentoring.  For two years, she taught a general education course for majors across campus entitled Physics ...]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
