<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>CAREER:   Child-Mother Secure Base Relationship Processes and Social Competence in Early Childhood: A Cross-Cultural Perspective</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2007</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2013</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>409993.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>409993</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>04040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>SBE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>BCS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Behavioral and Cognitive Sci</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>david moore</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Child-mother relationships provide an important context for children to learn about their environment and about how to interact with peers and other adults. Thus, the study of child-parent relationships is a key to understanding all socialization processes of children. The basis for the formation and maintenance of child-mother relationships are everyday interactions. This program of research will explore the relation between those interactions and children's competence in other contexts such as preschool settings. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Research on these issues is scant, despite the fact that the preschool years are likely to be a time when child-mother relationships are consolidated, with implications for children's adaptation to social exchanges with others, and for children's socialization outcomes in general. Findings may have important implications for prevention and intervention issues in families from the populations studied. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project has two objectives. The first is to investigate child-mother relationships processes in the domains of behavior and mental representation during early childhood (3.5 to 5 years of age). Further, we will study the relations between child-mother relationships and children's social competence (i.e., social exchanges with peers and other adults). To accomplish this, observations of maternal and child behavior at home and in playgrounds will be conducted. Narratives regarding child-mother relationships will also be obtained from mothers and children, as well as an assessment of mother-child joint interaction regarding attachment related issues. Finally, data on children's behavior during social interactions with peers and adults will be obtained from preschool teachers. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The second objective of the research is to investigate and compare the relationship processes mentioned above and their ability to predict social competence in samples of dyads from two different cultural contexts. Information will be collected from both U.S. and Colombian children. Although the tendency to form relationships with primary caregivers is characteristic of all humans, child-mother relationships are context sensitive. We will compare the data from both samples to determine common as well as sample specific patterns of association among the variables.&lt;br/&gt;</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/31/2007</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/05/2011</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.075</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>0645530</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>German</FirstName>
<LastName>Posada</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>E</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>German E Posada</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>gposada@purdue.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>7654941029</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000455133</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/31/2007</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Purdue University</Name>
<CityName>West Lafayette</CityName>
<ZipCode>479072114</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>7654941055</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>Young Hall</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[155 S Grant Street]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Indiana</StateName>
<StateCode>IN</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>IN04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>072051394</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>PURDUE UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>072051394</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Purdue University]]></Name>
<CityName>West Lafayette</CityName>
<StateCode>IN</StateCode>
<ZipCode>479072114</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[Young Hall]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Indiana</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>IN04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<FoaInformation>
<Code>0116000</Code>
<Name>Human Subjects</Name>
</FoaInformation>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1698</Code>
<Text>DS -Developmental Sciences</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>0000</Code>
<Text>UNASSIGNED</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1045</Code>
<Text>CAREER-Faculty Erly Career Dev</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1187</Code>
<Text>PECASE- eligible</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>OTHR</Code>
<Text>OTHER RESEARCH OR EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0107</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>490100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0108</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0109</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0110</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0111</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2007~124749</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2008~114316</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2009~94551</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2010~42441</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2011~33936</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>This study investigated mother-child relationships during the preschool years, from the time children are 3.5 years old until they are 5 years old. &nbsp;The quality of those relationships has been found to play an important role in child development.&nbsp; There were two general goals for the study.&nbsp; The first main goal was to investigate the relations between the quality of maternal care (sensitivity) during mother-child interactions and children&rsquo;s quality of attachment to mother (security).&nbsp; Attachment security was assessed at the levels of both behavior and narratives (representations).&nbsp; In addition, we were interested in studying the associations between security and the quality of children&rsquo;s social exchanges with peers and other adults in preschool settings (social competence, aggression, and withdrawal).&nbsp; The second main goal was to investigate and compare the issues mentioned above in samples from two different cultural contexts. &nbsp;Thus, similar information was collected in a U.S. sample and a sample from Colombia.&nbsp; To achieve those goals, we conducted extensive observations of mother-child interactions at home and in playgrounds, collected narratives from children about attachment-related events, and gathered information from preschool teachers about children&rsquo;s behavior.</p> <p>Analysis of the information collected indicated that maternal sensitivity and child attachment security are significantly stable from 3.5 to 5 years of age. &nbsp;Also, results showed that sensitivity is significantly related to child security at both points in time, when children are 3.5 and 5 years of age. &nbsp;Children of mothers described as sensitive are more securely attached than children of mothers described as insensitive.&nbsp; Furthermore, changes in maternal sensitivity from 3.5 to 5 years of age were significantly associated with corresponding changes in child attachment security. &nbsp;That is, when mothers became more sensitive, their children became more secure and vice versa. &nbsp;Thus, continuous quality of care remains significantly related to children&rsquo;s attachment security.&nbsp; All those results were found for both the U.S. and the Colombian samples.</p> <p>As narratives (representations) about attachment are concerned, results showed initial evidence of a significant association between attachment behavior and attachment narratives, when children were 3.5 years old. &nbsp;This was so in samples from both countries. &nbsp;However, analyses indicated that the association between attachment behavior and narratives&nbsp; was not significant at 5 years of age in either sample. &nbsp;Thus, more research is needed on the topic to account for the differences at both points in time.&nbsp;</p> <p>Findings about the relations between attachment security and social competence, aggression, and withdrawal showed that attachment security was not significantly related to social competence and aggression at 3.5 years of age in either samples; child withdrawal was significantly related to attachment behavior in the Colombian, but was not in the U.S. sample. &nbsp;However, when children were 5 years old, attachment behavior was significantly associated with social competence and aggression, but not with withdrawal in both samples.&nbsp; As attachment narratives are concerned, results indicated that they were related to social competence and withdrawal in both samples, but not to child aggression, when children were 3.5 years old. &nbsp;At 5 years of age, attachment narratives were only related to withdrawal in the U.S. sample.&nbsp; Overall these findings call for further exploration of attachment behavior and narratives to explain the different associations found with children&rsquo;s social competence, aggression, and withdrawal at different ages and in both samples.</p> <p>On the whole, the findings highlight the continuous relevance of maternal quality of care in children&rsquo;s attachment security outcomes during the preschool years in different cultural groups.&nbsp; Results indicate that processes involved in maintaining stability and/or promoting change in child security (i.e., mother-child interactions) seem to be similar in different cultural contexts during the preschool years.&nbsp; Also, the results pose further questions and hopefully stimulate more research on the interplay between attachment behavior and attachment narrative representations as children grow up; it is important to investigate how specifically mothers (and other caregivers) contribute both behaviorally and verbally to the organization of children's attachment behavior and narratives. &nbsp;Finally, analyses showed that although mother-child attachment relationships seem to be implicated in children&rsquo;s outcomes concerned with social competence, aggression and withdrawal in preschool settings, the associations are complex and vary depending on whether you consider attachment behavior or attachment narratives.&nbsp; Last, findings point to the usefulness of observational methodologies in naturalistic settings when studying parent-child attachment relationships.&nbsp; Those methodologies are important to investigate the phenomenon during the preschool years, when language is expanding and its correspondence with attachment behavior is not well-known.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 10/13/2017<br>      Modified by: German&nbsp;E&nbsp;Posada</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ This study investigated mother-child relationships during the preschool years, from the time children are 3.5 years old until they are 5 years old.  The quality of those relationships has been found to play an important role in child development.  There were two general goals for the study.  The first main goal was to investigate the relations between the quality of maternal care (sensitivity) during mother-child interactions and children?s quality of attachment to mother (security).  Attachment security was assessed at the levels of both behavior and narratives (representations).  In addition, we were interested in studying the associations between security and the quality of children?s social exchanges with peers and other adults in preschool settings (social competence, aggression, and withdrawal).  The second main goal was to investigate and compare the issues mentioned above in samples from two different cultural contexts.  Thus, similar information was collected in a U.S. sample and a sample from Colombia.  To achieve those goals, we conducted extensive observations of mother-child interactions at home and in playgrounds, collected narratives from children about attachment-related events, and gathered information from preschool teachers about children?s behavior.  Analysis of the information collected indicated that maternal sensitivity and child attachment security are significantly stable from 3.5 to 5 years of age.  Also, results showed that sensitivity is significantly related to child security at both points in time, when children are 3.5 and 5 years of age.  Children of mothers described as sensitive are more securely attached than children of mothers described as insensitive.  Furthermore, changes in maternal sensitivity from 3.5 to 5 years of age were significantly associated with corresponding changes in child attachment security.  That is, when mothers became more sensitive, their children became more secure and vice versa.  Thus, continuous quality of care remains significantly related to children?s attachment security.  All those results were found for both the U.S. and the Colombian samples.  As narratives (representations) about attachment are concerned, results showed initial evidence of a significant association between attachment behavior and attachment narratives, when children were 3.5 years old.  This was so in samples from both countries.  However, analyses indicated that the association between attachment behavior and narratives  was not significant at 5 years of age in either sample.  Thus, more research is needed on the topic to account for the differences at both points in time.   Findings about the relations between attachment security and social competence, aggression, and withdrawal showed that attachment security was not significantly related to social competence and aggression at 3.5 years of age in either samples; child withdrawal was significantly related to attachment behavior in the Colombian, but was not in the U.S. sample.  However, when children were 5 years old, attachment behavior was significantly associated with social competence and aggression, but not with withdrawal in both samples.  As attachment narratives are concerned, results indicated that they were related to social competence and withdrawal in both samples, but not to child aggression, when children were 3.5 years old.  At 5 years of age, attachment narratives were only related to withdrawal in the U.S. sample.  Overall these findings call for further exploration of attachment behavior and narratives to explain the different associations found with children?s social competence, aggression, and withdrawal at different ages and in both samples.  On the whole, the findings highlight the continuous relevance of maternal quality of care in children?s attachment security outcomes during the preschool years in different cultural groups.  Results indicate that processes involved in maintaining stability and/or promoting change in child security (i.e., mother-child interactions) seem to be similar in different cultural contexts during the preschool years.  Also, the results pose further questions and hopefully stimulate more research on the interplay between attachment behavior and attachment narrative representations as children grow up; it is important to investigate how specifically mothers (and other caregivers) contribute both behaviorally and verbally to the organization of children's attachment behavior and narratives.  Finally, analyses showed that although mother-child attachment relationships seem to be implicated in children?s outcomes concerned with social competence, aggression and withdrawal in preschool settings, the associations are complex and vary depending on whether you consider attachment behavior or attachment narratives.  Last, findings point to the usefulness of observational methodologies in naturalistic settings when studying parent-child attachment relationships.  Those methodologies are important to investigate the phenomenon during the preschool years, when language is expanding and its correspondence with attachment behavior is not well-known.          Last Modified: 10/13/2017       Submitted by: German E Posada]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
