<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Standard Research - California Delta: The Engineered Heart of a Modern State Formation</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>01/01/2008</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2011</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardAmount>160410</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>04050300</Code>
<Directorate>
<LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<LongName>Divn Of Social and Economic Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Frederick M Kronz</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Synopsis: Research in STS is focusing on the relationship between nature, technology and society in modern techno-scientific states. In these states, nature and society are integrated in complex socio-technical networks: massive and distributed systems of dams, earthworks, drainage, water conveyance, power grids, sanitary engineering and so on. Social, natural, and technological elements are engineered together and are deeply interconnected. The California Delta is a prime example of a large socio-technical network that is crucial to the stability of a modern state. Understanding such networks is central to the purpose of STS, but preliminary research indicates that modeling social, natural, and technological elements independently of one another has resulted in partial understandings, that while perfectly adequate for particular purposes, can actually hinder broad understanding of the Delta as a whole, and thus its prospects for sustainability (the meaning of which is contested). This research seeks a broad understanding of the development of the Delta, and also of how it is now assembled, which is a necessary complement to more focused research. The aim is a historical sociological case study, with three key objectives. First, situate the Delta in the broad historical context of western civilization, with a focus on science and the governance of nature. Second, target critical moments in the history of the Delta that explain major outcomes in each case. Third, survey the current configuration of the network with the aim of contributing insight to the contested discussion of network sustainability today. Each of these objectives will be accomplished through an overarching analysis of the formation of the modern state of California as an ongoing process of engineering nature, society and technology together through the co-productions of science and government.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Intellectual Merit: The research foresees a significant contribution to the literature in STS through the publication of a book and a number of articles. Substantial intellectual merit lies in the theoretical insights developed by bringing together explanatory schemes in socio-technical network analysis, neo-institutional analyses in organizational sociology, and historical/cultural sociology of state formation. Engaging these literatures, the research seeks to develop a theoretical approach to socio-technical networks that avoids replacing technological and natural determinism with social determinism. In this context the research elaborates the distinction between agency and causality so that all elements in the network can cause outcomes, but only human actors and their artifacts are granted agency. In so doing the research seeks to reconcile some of the differences between the actor-network and social construction of technology approaches. The concept of ?material culture? distinguishes material technology from material nature, and will be used to integrate socio-technical network research with an account of the material dimensions of modern state formation. These theoretical contributions will inform, and be informed by, a new empirical analysis of the historical development, current configuration, and future prospects of the California Delta. The core intellectual merit of the project is its contribution to research in STS that integrates theoretical formulation and explanation with fine-grained empirical case study analysis.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Broad Impacts: Broad impacts will be made in the area of education and training. A course will be designed, ?STS 180, Special Topics,? on socio-technical networks, with a focus on the California Delta based on the research. This course will be part of the newly formed STS undergraduate major at the University of California, Davis. The research dataset (hypertext format) will be placed on the web for students to use in their own research. Understanding how the California Delta developed, and its contemporary condition and prospects for sustainability, will have broad impact and benefits for society. The research will have policy relevance for all levels of government. Envisioning a book, this research aims to have a broad impact on public understanding of science and technology in society. As well as the public at large, the research will be of interest to numerous constituencies of California, such as environmentalists, scientists, engineers (the categories are not of course exclusive), business people and farmers, among others. Finally, broad impact lies in the contribution the research makes to discussions about the meaning and possibility of large-scale socio-technical network sustainability in the twenty-first century, and the relationship of such to the viability and stability of the state. &lt;br/&gt;</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/15/2007</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/20/2009</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>0646982</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Patrick</FirstName>
<LastName>Carroll</LastName>
<EmailAddress>pcarroll@ucdavis.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>08/15/2007</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of California-Davis</Name>
<CityName>Davis</CityName>
<ZipCode>956186134</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5307547700</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>OR/Sponsored Programs</StreetAddress>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
</Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7603</Code>
<Text>SCIENCE, TECH &amp; SOCIETY</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>0000</Code>
<Text>UNASSIGNED</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>OTHR</Code>
<Text>OTHER RESEARCH OR EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
</Award>
</rootTag>
