<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>REU Site: Multiscale High Rate Phenomena</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>05/01/2007</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>11/30/2010</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>300000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>07050000</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Div Of Engineering Education and Centers</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Esther Bolding</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>EEC-0647924&lt;br/&gt;Philip M. Gullett&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The award provides support for a three-year REU Site at Mississippi State University. This program will engage 10 undergraduate students each year for three years in research focused on multiscale high rate phenomena starting from the atomic scale using molecular dynamics simulations to very large scale crash finite element simulations. The need for understanding high rate phenomena is important in the weapons community, space programs, and automotive/vehicular industry. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The objectives of this REU program are: 1) engage undergraduates in meaningful contributions to state-of-the-art research in multiscale modeling of high rate phenomena; 2) foster excitement and diversity of research in a subject of national importance; 3) encourage undergraduates to pursue graduate degrees in math, physics, and engineering; 4) communicate the importance of quality research, publishing, and collaboration; 5) facilitate collaborations among faculty in the area of Solid Mechanics; and 6) enhance instructional experiences of the graduate student mentors. Also, the participants will visit local engineering research facilities, take part in various social activities, and be provided technical training and exposure to professional development topics weekly.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Recruitment efforts will focus on students from underrepresented groups at various universities and community colleges, such as, Tuskegee University, Clark-Atlanta University, Jackson State University, Mississippi Delta Community College, and Jones County Junior College. This REU program will attract and encourage undergraduate students to pursue advanced degrees in the fields of math, physics, and engineering. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>02/27/2007</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>05/01/2009</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0647924</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Tommy</FirstName>
      <LastName>Stevenson</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>Tstevenson@aaeo.msstate.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>02/27/2007</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Philip</FirstName>
      <LastName>Gullett</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>pmgullett@cee.msstate.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>02/27/2007</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>Mississippi State University</Name>
      <CityName>MISSISSIPPI STATE</CityName>
      <ZipCode>397629662</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>6623257404</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>PO Box 6156</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Mississippi</StateName>
      <StateCode>MS</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
