<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>SGER: Algorithmic Issues at the Nano Scale</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>10/01/2006</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>09/30/2008</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>130000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>130000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>05010000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>CSE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CCF</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division of Computing and Communication Foundations</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Mitra Basu</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Project Summary&lt;br/&gt;Self-assembly is the process by which small "components" follow simple&lt;br/&gt;combination rules to form intricate structures. DNA Self-assembly is widely&lt;br/&gt;believed to be a key tool for nano-technology, nano-robotics, and molecular&lt;br/&gt;computation. DNA self-assembly in particular, and nano-technology in general,&lt;br/&gt;offer significant algorithmic challenges. This project will explore two&lt;br/&gt;exciting directions in this field:&lt;br/&gt;1. Error correction at the nano scale.&lt;br/&gt;2. Models and algorithms for molecular machines.&lt;br/&gt;Intellectual merit: Error correction at the nano scale appears to require&lt;br/&gt;tools and techniques that are significantly different from those required for&lt;br/&gt;error correcting codes. For instance, errors and error correction mechanisms&lt;br/&gt;are bound by thermodynamic laws at the nano scale, as well as by the constraint&lt;br/&gt;that any "computation" required to correct an error must be carried&lt;br/&gt;out using the same underlying error prone physical mechanism. While specific&lt;br/&gt;error correction mechanisms are now known in certain cases, a general&lt;br/&gt;understanding has been elusive.&lt;br/&gt;Many experimental groups have developed rudimentary (but very promising)&lt;br/&gt;DNA based molecular machines. Modeling of these machines is in a preliminary&lt;br/&gt;stage. Exploratory research in modeling these machines is likely to&lt;br/&gt;lead to interesting and challenging algorithmic questions.&lt;br/&gt;Broad impact: Error correction at the nano scale will facilitate sophisticated&lt;br/&gt;tasks such as counting, growing crystals of pre-specified sizes (no&lt;br/&gt;larger, no smaller), shape recognition etc. with great precision using inherently&lt;br/&gt;error-prone DNA self-assembly (or other technologies). This would be&lt;br/&gt;a new engineering primitive, somewhat like the engine and the semiconductor,&lt;br/&gt;with important immediate as well as unforeseen uses. Also, molecular&lt;br/&gt;machines may act as sensors, signal carriers, actuators, or drug delivery&lt;br/&gt;mechanisms. Undoubtedly, much of the hard work in achieving these goals&lt;br/&gt;will be done (and is being done) by experimentalists. But the PI believes&lt;br/&gt;that algorithmic techniques will also play an important supporting role.&lt;br/&gt;The PI will organize an informal reading seminar where students will&lt;br/&gt;explore this area in depth. The PI hopes that this seminar will provide a&lt;br/&gt;valuable educational experience. The PI also plans to write an article in a&lt;br/&gt;book intended for scientifically literate readers who are not experts in this&lt;br/&gt;field; the article will highlight algorithmic issues at the nano scale.&lt;br/&gt;1</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>09/18/2006</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>09/18/2006</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>0650058</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Ashish</FirstName>
<LastName>Goel</LastName>
<EmailAddress>ashishg@stanford.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>09/18/2006</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Stanford University</Name>
<CityName>Stanford</CityName>
<ZipCode>943052004</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6507232300</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>450 Jane Stanford Way</StreetAddress>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
</Institution>
<FoaInformation>
<Code>0000912</Code>
<Name>Computer Science</Name>
</FoaInformation>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7353</Code>
<Text>EMERGING MODELS &amp; TECHNOLOGIES</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9218</Code>
<Text>BASIC RESEARCH &amp; HUMAN RESORCS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9237</Code>
<Text>SMALL GRANTS-EXPLORATORY RSRCH</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>HPCC</Code>
<Text>HIGH PERFORMANCE COMPUTING &amp; COMM</Text>
</ProgramReference>
</Award>
</rootTag>
