<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Sum Frequency Generation Imaging of Patterns on Surfaces</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>05/01/2007</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>04/30/2011</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>374145</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Continuing grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>03090006</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Division Of Chemistry</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Zeev Rosenzweig</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>The Analytical and Surface Chemistry (ASC) program of the Division of Chemistry will support the research program of Prof. Steven Baldelli of the University of Houston. Prof. Baldelli's' research program focuses on the development of sum frequency generation (SFG) microscopy with the capability to investigate chemically patterned surfaces at the molecular level based on the vibrational spectroscopy of the adsorbates. SFG is surface sensitive technique that has been used previously to obtain the structure and orientation of molecules when adsorbed to surfaces. Dr. Baldelli and his students will convert this spectroscopic method to a powerful imaging tool characterized with 20 psec temporal resolution and 1 micron spatial resolution. This will enable the group to obtain a detailed chemical map of the surface with information on adsorbate bonding, local electric fields, chemical reactivity, and speciation across the surface. Samples such as polymers, thin films and coatings could be analyzed in great detail using SFG microscopy. It will also be possible to obtain molecular information from biological samples like cell surfaces and tissues. The study will provide an excellent educational opportunity for trainees desiring work at the interface of chemistry and material science.</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>04/04/2007</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>03/24/2009</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>0650779</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Steven</FirstName>
      <LastName>Baldelli</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>sbaldelli@uh.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>04/04/2007</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Houston</Name>
      <CityName>Houston</CityName>
      <ZipCode>772042015</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>7137435773</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>4800 Calhoun Boulevard</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Texas</StateName>
      <StateCode>TX</StateCode>
    </Institution>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
