<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>International Research Experience for Students (IRES) with LeTourneau Engineering Global Solutions</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2007</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2011</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>139998.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>139998</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>01090000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>O/D</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Office Of The Director</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>OISE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Office Of Internatl Science &amp;Engineering</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>DeAndra Beck</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This international research experience for students is an integral component of the LeTourneau Engineering Global Solutions (LEGS) ongoing initiative to design, create and test a highquality above-knee (AK) prosthetic device for high-ambulation patients in Kenya and Bangladesh. This program employs well-established engineering and science principles in device design to improve amputee mobility and quality of life in developing countries. The initial prototype of the LEGS limb is currently undergoing testing in hospitals with established programs for amputees: the Bethany Crippled Children's Hospital (BCCH) in Kenya and the Mulumghat Christian Hospital (MCH) in Bangladesh. Both Kenya and Bangladesh have high numbers of lower limb amputees due to trauma and war; yet do not have access to prosthetic devices that allow an articulated gait for AK amputees, much less affordable options. In addition, their rehabilitation programs are limited by caregiver training, patient poverty and access to transportation.&lt;br/&gt;Juniors accepted into the LEGS project are mentored by seniors and faculty as they gain skills in collaborative research and receive training in intercultural skills. Assigned to either Kenya or Bangladesh, the students focus on the cultural and community issues at each site as well as supporting the broader team effort with their research. Components of the LEGS limb are modified and rehabilitation and assessment/follow-up protocols are developed as team members determine the needed field protocols for each international visit. Each team member is assigned specific research objectives. As seniors they travel to Kenya or Bangladesh to collaborate with national professionals in implementation, to respond to feedback, to realize the ongoing implementation of their research and to witness firsthand the resulting improvements in the lifestyles of AK amputees. In the process, the LEGS team, consisting of engineering and pre-health science students, develops skills in international collaboration while personally experiencing the cultural and economic impact of doing field research in Kenya or Bangladesh. Through face-to-face communication overseas and via email, they interact with national health and prosthetics &amp; orthotics (P&amp;O) professionals to (1) enhance the LEGS trans-femoral prosthetic device and (2) enable the development of culturally viable rehabilitation and follow-up protocols. &lt;br/&gt;Future engineers and scientists are gaining experience in international research by collaborating with international professionals. These international and cross-disciplinary collaborations foster new skills, give student participants a global perspective and provide opportunities for future partnerships and international networking. Women, Hispanic and Asian students are an integral part of the LEGS team. Through this initiative, long-term collaborative international scientific relationships will develop. &lt;br/&gt;</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/03/2007</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/03/2007</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.079</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>0651132</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Roger</FirstName>
<LastName>Gonzalez</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>V</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Roger V Gonzalez</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>rvgonzalez@utep.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>9157475909</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000372979</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/03/2007</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Karen</FirstName>
<LastName>Rispin</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>L</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Karen L Rispin</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>KarenRispin@letu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>9032333957</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000213078</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/03/2007</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>LeTourneau University</Name>
<CityName>Longview</CityName>
<ZipCode>756077001</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>9032333100</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>P O BOX 7001</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Texas</StateName>
<StateCode>TX</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>TX01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>010473718</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>LETOURNEAU UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>010473718</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[LeTourneau University]]></Name>
<CityName>Longview</CityName>
<StateCode>TX</StateCode>
<ZipCode>756077001</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[P O BOX 7001]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Texas</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>TX01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<FoaInformation>
<Code>0116000</Code>
<Name>Human Subjects</Name>
</FoaInformation>
<FoaInformation>
<Code>0510400</Code>
<Name>Physically Disadvantaged</Name>
</FoaInformation>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7316</Code>
<Text>EAPSI</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>5976</Code>
<Text>AFRICA, NEAR EAST, &amp; SO ASIA</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>5991</Code>
<Text>KENYA</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7343</Code>
<Text>BANGLADESH</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9149</Code>
<Text>SUPPORT SYS &amp; EDUC FOR ADV MANUFACTURING</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>MANU</Code>
<Text>MANUFACTURING</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0107</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>490100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2007~139998</FUND_OBLG>
</Award>
</rootTag>
