<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Topics in Reaction-Diffusion and Fluid Mechanics</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>06/01/2008</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2011</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>132000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>132000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DMS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Bruce P. Palka</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Topics in Reaction-Diffusion and Fluid Mechanics&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Abstract of Proposed Research&lt;br/&gt;Alexander Kiselev&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt; The investigator intends to study a variety of mathematical questions that arise in the modeling of fluid flows and the interaction of flows and diffusion processes. They involve issues in dynamical systems, spectral theory and the existence and regularity of solutions of certain partial differential equations. One problem is to understand the enhancement of diffusion by fluid flow by studying certain advection-diffusion partial differential equations. The PI will investigate the link between the geometric and dynamical properties of flows and their efficiency in enhancing diffusion. Another topic is the existence and properties of the dissipative quasi-geostrophic and Navier-Stokes equations. A particular interest is the derivation of some new inequalities for the solutions of these equations and the investigation of the effects of nonlinear terms in the partial differential equations of fluid mechanics.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The equations to be studied model important physical processes yet their mathematical properties are not well understood at present. They include issues in combustion, atmospheric and ocean modeling, aerodynamics and astrophysics as well as many biological models including morphogenesis. It is hoped the results will lead to better understanding of  fundamental issues in science and engineering ranging from  front formation and propagation to turbulence.&lt;br/&gt;</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>10/10/2007</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>03/04/2010</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>0653813</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Alexander</FirstName>
<LastName>Kiselev</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Alexander Kiselev</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>kiselev@math.duke.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>9196602839</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000656921</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>10/10/2007</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Wisconsin-Madison</Name>
<CityName>MADISON</CityName>
<ZipCode>537151218</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6082623822</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>21 North Park Street</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[Suite 6401]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Wisconsin</StateName>
<StateCode>WI</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>WI02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>161202122</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF WISCONSIN SYSTEM</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>041188822</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Wisconsin-Madison]]></Name>
<CityName>MADISON</CityName>
<StateCode>WI</StateCode>
<ZipCode>537151218</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[21 North Park Street]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Wisconsin</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>WI02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<FoaInformation>
<Code>0000099</Code>
<Name>Other Applications NEC</Name>
</FoaInformation>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1281</Code>
<Text>ANALYSIS PROGRAM</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>0000</Code>
<Text>UNASSIGNED</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>OTHR</Code>
<Text>OTHER RESEARCH OR EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0108</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0109</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0110</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2008~42442</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2009~43978</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2010~45580</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Research supported by this award focused on properties of solutions of the fundamental equations of fluid dynamics and on mixing by fluid flows. In the first direction, new tools have been developed that allow to investigate and predict behavior of solutions to the class of equations called "active scalars".&nbsp;These equations describe a wide range of phenomena in science and nature, including from traffic flow, evolution of temperature field in atmosphere, and any two dimensional flow of non viscous incompressible fluid. Although many of these equations are classical and well studied, their solutions can exhibit very complex behaviors, and many key questions about them remain open. The new technique allows to estimate and predict the behavior of solutions of these equations in a novel way, yielding more precise bounds and wealth of new information. &nbsp;</p> <p>In the secong direction, the research focused on enhancement of diffusive mixing due to fluid flow. Mixing by fluid flow is a process that is important in many processes in engineering and nature. Examples include internal combustion engines, distribution of ozone in the atmosphere, and food processing. The research focused on identification of charateristics of flows that make them most efficient in mixing. The results can have applications in other areas of science dealing with convergence to equilibrium, which will be a subject of subsequent investigation.</p> <p>The project led to development of a graduate course in fluid mechanics. One graduate student is about to defend a PhD on subjects inspired by research supported by this award. Several undergraduate students completed research projects on topics derived from this research as well. &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 06/27/2011<br>      Modified by: Alexander&nbsp;Kiselev</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Research supported by this award focused on properties of solutions of the fundamental equations of fluid dynamics and on mixing by fluid flows. In the first direction, new tools have been developed that allow to investigate and predict behavior of solutions to the class of equations called "active scalars". These equations describe a wide range of phenomena in science and nature, including from traffic flow, evolution of temperature field in atmosphere, and any two dimensional flow of non viscous incompressible fluid. Although many of these equations are classical and well studied, their solutions can exhibit very complex behaviors, and many key questions about them remain open. The new technique allows to estimate and predict the behavior of solutions of these equations in a novel way, yielding more precise bounds and wealth of new information.    In the secong direction, the research focused on enhancement of diffusive mixing due to fluid flow. Mixing by fluid flow is a process that is important in many processes in engineering and nature. Examples include internal combustion engines, distribution of ozone in the atmosphere, and food processing. The research focused on identification of charateristics of flows that make them most efficient in mixing. The results can have applications in other areas of science dealing with convergence to equilibrium, which will be a subject of subsequent investigation.  The project led to development of a graduate course in fluid mechanics. One graduate student is about to defend a PhD on subjects inspired by research supported by this award. Several undergraduate students completed research projects on topics derived from this research as well.               Last Modified: 06/27/2011       Submitted by: Alexander Kiselev]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
