<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Multivariable Operator Theory and Applications</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2013</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>299999.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>299999</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DMS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Edward Taylor</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>A holomorphic function of a single variable can easily be applied to matrices whose spectra lie in the domain of the function, and this has developed into a very successful and important theory. The Principal Investigator proposes to study functions of several variables applied to matrices. The theory immediately splits into the commutative and noncommutative cases. In the former, the project will investigate when functions of several variables preserve the natural order structure on matrices, and what happens when the size of the matrices becomes infinite (the operator case). Conversely, the Principal Investigator proposes to use tools from operator theory to understand functions of several variables, such as characterizing asymptotic expansions of functions in the Pick class (this is called the Hamburger problem in one variable). In the noncommutative case, he will investigate how noncommutative holomorphic functions can be obtained as limits of noncommutative polynomials. The description of noncommutative holomorphic functions will be in terms of operator theoretic realizations. He will also work on applying analytic techniques to improve ultrasound imaging.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Virtually all imaging devices today function by collecting either electromagnetic or acoustic waves and using the energy carried by these waves to determine pixel values in order to build up what is basically an "energy" picture.  However, waves also carry information, and this can also be used to determine the pixel values in an image. Various studies have shown that these "information" images often reveal features that are completely missed by conventional, energy images. This project will study how to improve these images, using various different measures of information-theoretic entropy, both to render them sharper, and to enable their calculation in real time. These techniques will have applications in medical imaging and also in security scanning. The Principal Investigator will also conduct basic research in areas of pure mathematics related to control theory and signal processing.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>04/02/2013</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>04/29/2015</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1300280</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>John</FirstName>
<LastName>McCarthy</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>E</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>John E McCarthy</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>mccarthy@math.wustl.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>3149356753</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000449017</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/02/2013</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Washington University</Name>
<CityName>Saint Louis</CityName>
<ZipCode>631304862</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>3147474134</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>CAMPUS BOX 1054</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[1 Brookings Drive]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Missouri</StateName>
<StateCode>MO</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MO01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>068552207</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>WASHINGTON UNIVERSITY, THE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>068552207</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Washington University]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>MO</StateCode>
<ZipCode>631304899</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Missouri</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MO01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1281</Code>
<Text>ANALYSIS PROGRAM</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0113</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0114</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0115</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2013~70136</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~113135</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2015~116728</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The project was primarily in pure mathematics, but insights gained from pure mathematical research allowed the PI also to contribute to two other areas, analysis of ultrasound and understanding the spread of Alzheimer's disease.</p> <p>&nbsp;Pure Mathematics</p> <p>A problem with roots in both pure mathematics and engineering is to understand functions of matrices.</p> <p>Matrices are square arrays of numbers, and given two matrices X and Yone can add them, X+Y, or multiply them, XY. Crucially, although additions is commutative (i.e. X+Y = Y+X), multiplication is not: XY and YX can be different. So if one tries to extend the function p(x,y) = x<sup>2</sup> + 4 xy to matrices,there are many distinct choices---such as X<sup>2</sup> + 4 XY, and &nbsp;X<sup>2</sup> + 3XY + YX, etc.</p> <p>The problem becomes even more complicated if one moves beyond polynomials, to functions like the square root of xy.</p> <p>The recently invented field of non-commutative function theory studies functions of matrices. Over the course of the grant, the PI published seven papers with co-authors on non-commutative functions.  One of theseestablished a representation theorem for bounded non-commutative functions, and this paper won the G. de B. Robinson award from the Canadian Mathematical society. Another paper proved an implicit function theorem, which allows one to show under certain circumstances matrices that satisfy some algebraic relation must commute with each other.</p> <p>Ultrasound</p> <p>Ultrasound analysis has traditionally relied on examining the energy of the reflected signal. The PI and co-author Mike Hughes realized that the waves also carry information that can be measured using various forms of entropy. During the project, the PI and co-authors published one theoretical paper on the underpinnings of the technique, and three on applications, both in medical ultrasound, and in identifying guns from the sounds of the gunshots.</p> <p>Alzheimer's Disease</p> <p>During the project, the PI worked with several neuroscientists to improve the understanding of amyloid and tau deposition in the brain by mathematically analyzing brain scans. One of the co-authored papers was featured in the Wall Street Journal (5/11/16).</p> <p>Pure mathematicians bring different insights and techniques to bear on medical problems than applied mathematicians or statisticians. The support of the NSF for pure mathematicians is vital not only for the health of pure mathematics, but also to allow collaborations such as those described above.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 07/31/2017<br>      Modified by: John&nbsp;E&nbsp;Mccarthy</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The project was primarily in pure mathematics, but insights gained from pure mathematical research allowed the PI also to contribute to two other areas, analysis of ultrasound and understanding the spread of Alzheimer's disease.   Pure Mathematics  A problem with roots in both pure mathematics and engineering is to understand functions of matrices.  Matrices are square arrays of numbers, and given two matrices X and Yone can add them, X+Y, or multiply them, XY. Crucially, although additions is commutative (i.e. X+Y = Y+X), multiplication is not: XY and YX can be different. So if one tries to extend the function p(x,y) = x2 + 4 xy to matrices,there are many distinct choices---such as X2 + 4 XY, and  X2 + 3XY + YX, etc.  The problem becomes even more complicated if one moves beyond polynomials, to functions like the square root of xy.  The recently invented field of non-commutative function theory studies functions of matrices. Over the course of the grant, the PI published seven papers with co-authors on non-commutative functions.  One of theseestablished a representation theorem for bounded non-commutative functions, and this paper won the G. de B. Robinson award from the Canadian Mathematical society. Another paper proved an implicit function theorem, which allows one to show under certain circumstances matrices that satisfy some algebraic relation must commute with each other.  Ultrasound  Ultrasound analysis has traditionally relied on examining the energy of the reflected signal. The PI and co-author Mike Hughes realized that the waves also carry information that can be measured using various forms of entropy. During the project, the PI and co-authors published one theoretical paper on the underpinnings of the technique, and three on applications, both in medical ultrasound, and in identifying guns from the sounds of the gunshots.  Alzheimer's Disease  During the project, the PI worked with several neuroscientists to improve the understanding of amyloid and tau deposition in the brain by mathematically analyzing brain scans. One of the co-authored papers was featured in the Wall Street Journal (5/11/16).  Pure mathematicians bring different insights and techniques to bear on medical problems than applied mathematicians or statisticians. The support of the NSF for pure mathematicians is vital not only for the health of pure mathematics, but also to allow collaborations such as those described above.                            Last Modified: 07/31/2017       Submitted by: John E Mccarthy]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
