<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Role of structure in chemical functionalization of oxide-free silicon surfaces and nanoparticles</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/15/2013</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>383654.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>393654</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03090000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CHE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Chemistry</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Tingyu Li</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>tli@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924949</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The Chemical Structure, Dynamics, and Mechanisms - B Program of the Division of Chemistry supports Professor Yves J. Chabal from the University of Texas at Dallas to develop a fundamental understanding and control of the chemistry involved in making and modifying model hydrogen-terminated Si surfaces to investigate the correlation between their optoelectronic properties and chemical bonding. While hydrogen-terminated silicon surfaces have played a critical role in microelectronics because of their simple synthesis, superior chemical stability and excellent electrical properties, their transformative use critically depends on the ability to chemically modify them without oxidizing the Si substrate, since interfacial oxides typically have poor electrical properties. By controlling the quality of the chemical and physical structure of modified H/Si surfaces, it is then possible to address fundamental questions such as the nature of interfacial defect states and the origin of photoluminescence of Si nanoparticles. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This work will provide the fundamental knowledge for applications such as silicon-based chemical- and bio-sensors, fuel and photovoltaic cells, catalysis, selective atomic layer deposition, ultra-shallow doping, and single electron devices. Thus, this interdisciplinary approach is of interest to the chemical, biomedical, energy and semiconductor processing industries and provides students with the opportunity to learn about different fields and to connect to industrial projects and international collaborators. The program will also incorporate "Surface Chemical Functionalization" into two courses and several modules for Materials Research Society tutorials, a Research Experience for Undergraduates program, as well as graduate student seminars.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>09/06/2013</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/15/2015</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1300180</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Yves</FirstName>
<LastName>Chabal</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>J</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Yves J Chabal</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>chabal@utdallas.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>9728835751</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000203589</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/06/2013</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Texas at Dallas</Name>
<CityName>Richardson</CityName>
<ZipCode>750803021</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>9728832313</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>800 W. Campbell Rd., AD15</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Texas</StateName>
<StateCode>TX</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>32</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>TX32</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>800188161</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF TEXAS AT DALLAS</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>042000273</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Texas at Dallas]]></Name>
<CityName>Richardson</CityName>
<StateCode>TX</StateCode>
<ZipCode>750803021</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[800 W Campbell Rd, RL10]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Texas</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>32</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>TX32</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>9102</Code>
<Text>Chem Struct,Dynmcs&amp;Mechansms B</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>6879</Code>
<Text>STRUCTURE, DYNAMIC &amp; MECHANISM</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9161</Code>
<Text>SINGLE DIVISION/UNIVERSITY</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>AMPP</Code>
<Text>ADVANCED MATERIALS &amp; PROCESSING PROGRAM</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0113</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0115</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2013~383654</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2015~10000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The properties of all devices are critically dependent on the quality of the interfaces between the different materials used to fabricate these devices. This is particularly true for silicon (Si) that is the basic, most important material for microelectronics and solar cells. While in some cases it is best to carefully oxidize the surface to passivate it and minimize nefarious electronic defect states, there are many applications that require the removal of the oxide. This is typically achieved by etching in hydrofluoric acid, which leaves a layer of hydrogen on the surface. These hydrogen-terminated silicon surfaces not only play a critical role in microelectronics but are also the gateway to the best and most reliable functionalization chemistries because of their simple synthesis, superior chemical stability and excellent electrical properties. The motivation for this work was therefore the realization that the transformative use of these surfaces critically depends on the ability <em>to chemically modify them without oxidizing the Si substrate</em>. By controlling the quality of the chemical and physical structure of modified H/Si surfaces, it is then possible to address fundamental questions such as the nature of interfacial defect states and the origin of photoluminescence of Si nanoparticles.</p> <p>During the grant period, a fundamental understanding of both oxidized and oxide-free silicon surfaces was developed, which has made it possible to contribute to applications such Si-based chemical- and bio-sensors, photovoltaic cells, catalysis, selective atomic layer deposition, ultra-shallow doping, and single electron devices.</p> <p>For instance, the controlled deposition of ultra-thin (~ 1nanometer) films was examined with a relatively novel technique called atomic layer deposition, using <em>in situ</em> spectroscopy. The ability to deposit these films at low temperatures (&lt;200<sup>o</sup>C), particularly silicon oxide and silicon nitride, is critical for future microelectronic devices. With home-made reactors that incorporate IR spectroscopy, new gas molecules were tested and processes developed for atomic layer deposition, often working in collaboration with industry (e.g. EMD Performance Materials, Versum Materials and more recently Lam Research).</p> <p>Another critical issue for the microelectronics industry was also addressed: selective deposition. In collaboration with Intel, we have sought ways to selectively deposit on silicon oxide and silicon nitride. The surface composition of both dielectrics was determined after mild etching in hydrofluoric acid and it was demonstrated that different organic molecules could be attached on each surface following the identical treatment. This discovery provided the basis for subsequent selective deposition using ALD.</p> <p>Using knowledge derived about surface chemical modification, gold nanoparticles were isolated on Si with an organic insulating layer to produce &ldquo;single-electron devices&rdquo; using a scanning tunneling microscope (STM) tip with a collaborator in France. Such devices are able to handle one electron at a time and therefore constitute the ultimate in miniaturization. These are the first such systems demonstrated on a silicon substrate.</p> <p>Teaming up with Zyvex Labs, a method for atomic scale manufacturing was developed based on the use of an STM tip to remove H from a Si surface with atomic precision and selectively grow Si pillars or an aluminum oxide (Al<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub>) mask. The UT Dallas contribution was to explore the epitaxial growth of Si pillars and the selective deposition of Al<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub>.</p> <p>Finally, a contribution to graphene-based electronics was provided by devising an efficient way to clean graphene that has been transferred from a metal substrate and by proposing an effective geometry for metal contacts. These advances are important for graphene-based electronics.</p> <p>The interdisciplinary approach developed at UT Dallas is of great interest to the chemical, biomedical, energy and semiconductor processing industries and provides students with a unique opportunity to learn about different fields and to connect to industrial projects and international collaborators. The PI developed lectures on &ldquo;surface chemical functionalization&rdquo; for two courses, and several modules for MRS tutorials, a REU program and graduate student seminars. The PI also supported and contributed to an outreach program &ldquo;Young Women in Science and Engineering Investigators&rdquo;, created in 2012, that provides a year-long research experience with a circle of four mentors (graduate student, professor, industry, and teacher) to teams of high school girls (primarily Hispanic and African American) from low socio-economic backgrounds.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 11/13/2017<br>      Modified by: Yves&nbsp;J&nbsp;Chabal</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The properties of all devices are critically dependent on the quality of the interfaces between the different materials used to fabricate these devices. This is particularly true for silicon (Si) that is the basic, most important material for microelectronics and solar cells. While in some cases it is best to carefully oxidize the surface to passivate it and minimize nefarious electronic defect states, there are many applications that require the removal of the oxide. This is typically achieved by etching in hydrofluoric acid, which leaves a layer of hydrogen on the surface. These hydrogen-terminated silicon surfaces not only play a critical role in microelectronics but are also the gateway to the best and most reliable functionalization chemistries because of their simple synthesis, superior chemical stability and excellent electrical properties. The motivation for this work was therefore the realization that the transformative use of these surfaces critically depends on the ability to chemically modify them without oxidizing the Si substrate. By controlling the quality of the chemical and physical structure of modified H/Si surfaces, it is then possible to address fundamental questions such as the nature of interfacial defect states and the origin of photoluminescence of Si nanoparticles.  During the grant period, a fundamental understanding of both oxidized and oxide-free silicon surfaces was developed, which has made it possible to contribute to applications such Si-based chemical- and bio-sensors, photovoltaic cells, catalysis, selective atomic layer deposition, ultra-shallow doping, and single electron devices.  For instance, the controlled deposition of ultra-thin (~ 1nanometer) films was examined with a relatively novel technique called atomic layer deposition, using in situ spectroscopy. The ability to deposit these films at low temperatures (&lt;200oC), particularly silicon oxide and silicon nitride, is critical for future microelectronic devices. With home-made reactors that incorporate IR spectroscopy, new gas molecules were tested and processes developed for atomic layer deposition, often working in collaboration with industry (e.g. EMD Performance Materials, Versum Materials and more recently Lam Research).  Another critical issue for the microelectronics industry was also addressed: selective deposition. In collaboration with Intel, we have sought ways to selectively deposit on silicon oxide and silicon nitride. The surface composition of both dielectrics was determined after mild etching in hydrofluoric acid and it was demonstrated that different organic molecules could be attached on each surface following the identical treatment. This discovery provided the basis for subsequent selective deposition using ALD.  Using knowledge derived about surface chemical modification, gold nanoparticles were isolated on Si with an organic insulating layer to produce "single-electron devices" using a scanning tunneling microscope (STM) tip with a collaborator in France. Such devices are able to handle one electron at a time and therefore constitute the ultimate in miniaturization. These are the first such systems demonstrated on a silicon substrate.  Teaming up with Zyvex Labs, a method for atomic scale manufacturing was developed based on the use of an STM tip to remove H from a Si surface with atomic precision and selectively grow Si pillars or an aluminum oxide (Al2O3) mask. The UT Dallas contribution was to explore the epitaxial growth of Si pillars and the selective deposition of Al2O3.  Finally, a contribution to graphene-based electronics was provided by devising an efficient way to clean graphene that has been transferred from a metal substrate and by proposing an effective geometry for metal contacts. These advances are important for graphene-based electronics.  The interdisciplinary approach developed at UT Dallas is of great interest to the chemical, biomedical, energy and semiconductor processing industries and provides students with a unique opportunity to learn about different fields and to connect to industrial projects and international collaborators. The PI developed lectures on "surface chemical functionalization" for two courses, and several modules for MRS tutorials, a REU program and graduate student seminars. The PI also supported and contributed to an outreach program "Young Women in Science and Engineering Investigators", created in 2012, that provides a year-long research experience with a circle of four mentors (graduate student, professor, industry, and teacher) to teams of high school girls (primarily Hispanic and African American) from low socio-economic backgrounds.          Last Modified: 11/13/2017       Submitted by: Yves J Chabal]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
