<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Ultrafast Dynamics of Electronic Excited States: Photocatalysis and Photomagnetism</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>10/01/2013</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>09/30/2016</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>420000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>420000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03090000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CHE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Chemistry</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Colby Foss</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>cfoss@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032925327</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>In this project funded by the Chemical Structure, Dynamics, and Mechanisms Program-A (CSDM-A) and the Chemical Instrumentation Program of Division of Chemistry, Professor Kevin J. Kubarych of the University of Michigan and his graduate and undergraduate students are addressing the fundamental relationships between structure, dynamics and function in molecules that, powered by light, are poised to dramatically reshape approaches to transforming carbon dioxide and to storing information. In both classes of system, photocatalysts for reduction of carbon dioxide, and photomagnets, the key chemical starting point involves molecules that have absorbed light, carrying out their initial functional steps in excited electronic states. Using novel experimental techniques based on ultrafast two-dimensional infrared (2D-IR) spectroscopy and related methods, Professor Kubarych and his group will obtain the level of detailed dynamical information on the active excited states that is presently only possible on ground state molecules. By employing novel pulse sequences that combine different spectral ranges such as the visible and infrared, including multiple laser sources permitting access to timescales ranging from femtoseconds to seconds, Professor Kubarych's team will be able to disentangle complex photocycles and identify transient intermediate species using the powerful resolution of 2D-IR spectroscopy. With the addition of low-temperature capabilities, the group will gain access to the cooperative ultrafast dynamics of photoswitchable magnetic molecules and materials, which they will examine using novel hybrid electronic/vibrational spectroscopy methods. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The long term goal of this research project is to address the clear societal need to develop new approaches for energy conversion, storage, as well as the removal of greenhouse gases. Results of this project will guide development of new chemical systems as well as macromolecular constructs by elucidating the fundamental design principles. Professor Kubarych will leverage the widespread interest in energy, technology, and climate change to appeal to the next generation of women and minority scientists by developing hands-on demonstrations of dye-sensitized solar cells for middle and high school students in the southeast Michigan area. To dramatically broaden his reach, he will produce videos and a web resource describing basic challenges in solar energy conversion, highlighting the role of physical chemistry in the development of new solutions.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>09/16/2013</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>09/16/2013</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1300239</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Kevin</FirstName>
<LastName>Kubarych</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>J</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Kevin J Kubarych</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>kubarych@umich.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>7347647528</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000119852</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/16/2013</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Regents of the University of Michigan - Ann Arbor</Name>
<CityName>Ann Arbor</CityName>
<ZipCode>481091274</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>7347636438</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>3003 South State St. Room 1062</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Michigan</StateName>
<StateCode>MI</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>12</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MI12</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>073133571</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>REGENTS OF THE UNIVERSITY OF MICHIGAN</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>073133571</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Michigan Ann Arbor]]></Name>
<CityName>Ann Arbor</CityName>
<StateCode>MI</StateCode>
<ZipCode>481091055</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[930 N. University Ave.]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Michigan</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>12</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MI12</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1938</Code>
<Text>Chemical Instrumentation</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>9101</Code>
<Text>Chem Struct,Dynmcs&amp;Mechansms A</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8607</Code>
<Text>Solar Energy Capture&amp;Conver</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8650</Code>
<Text>Sustainable Chemistry</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0113</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2013~420000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Using extremely short bursts of laser light, this project dissected structure and dynamics of a chemical reaction that uses light to reverse combustion, effectively converting carbon dioxide into usable chemical raw materials. Catalysts speed up slow chemical reactions, and photocatalysts achieve this feat using power from light. Graduate students working in the research group used the distinct molecular vibrations of the most successful CO<sub>2</sub> reduction photocatalyst to essentially record the fastest molecular motions of the catalyst, as well as the immediate molecular surroundings in the solution environment. For the first time, these vibrational snapshots enabled measurements of the photocatalyst in its active state following visible light absorption, enabling a direct comparison to the same molecule fully relaxed before excitation. The main finding is that the molecule&rsquo;s fluctuations appear to slow following excitation, due to a reduced coupling to the surroundings. After a study changing both the chemical structure as well as the type of liquid solvent it is dissolved in, the team learned that the time scales for the dynamical fluctuations are dictated by a property of the liquid that relates to its tendency to infiltrate the catalyst and stick to the central metal atom (which is an atom of the metal element rhenium).&nbsp;</p> <p><span> </span>These first investigations led the team to add more ingredients needed for the photocatalytic reduction of CO<sub>2</sub>. To transform CO<sub>2</sub> into other chemically useful materials (such as carbon monoxide or formate), requires a source of electrons. In the lab, researchers typically use amine bases (ammonia is one such base), and the best choice is triethanolamine. When the catalyst has absorbed visible light, it stays in a state that is especially prone to accepting an electron from triethanolamine, thus enabling the photocatalytic cycle to progress. The team performed the first experiments using vibrational snapshots of the catalyst dissolved in a series of triethanolamine solutions (with other liquids serving as the main solvent). They observed a remarkable slowdown in the dynamical fluctuations for specific mixtures of triethanolamine and some of the solvents. This finding shows that in some solution environments, the triethanolamine prefers to sit right next to the catalyst rather than be out in the solution. With the electron donating molecule so close to the catalyst, the time needed to transfer the electron to the catalyst is greatly reduced since the two do not need to randomly diffuse around to encounter each other. Other researchers in this field have not previously considered this possibility, and the findings provide some guidance about how future catalytic systems can be engineered to have increased efficiency and reliability.&nbsp;</p> <p><span><span> </span>To test the idea that the catalyst in some sense &ldquo;attracts&rdquo; some molecules at the expense of others, the team added another molecule to the solution with the rhenium catalyst. This molecule, a salt of sodium and thiocyanate, gives a particularly strong vibrational signal, so the researchers could test whether or not it was close to the catalyst by exciting the vibrations of the catalyst, and timing how long the energy arrived at the presumably nearby thiocyanate solute. The process is similar to a radio transmitter and receiver: the closer the radio is to the broadcasting tower, the stronger the radio signal will be. They found that even at low concentration of thiocyanate, where one would not expect many to be found near the catalyst, the time for energy transfer was very fast. This fast energy transfer &ldquo;call and response&rdquo; indicates that the two are essentially touching each other in solution, offering further support for the picture of preferential interaction.&nbsp;</span></p> <p><span> </span>Understating fundamental details of chemical reactions is essentially in order to design rationally the next generation of CO<sub>2</sub> reducing catalysts. By exposing the relatively strong interactions between various actors in the complex mechanism, new approaches based on using surfaces, materials, and alternative linking strategies should enable more robust and efficient conversion of CO<sub>2</sub>, a potent greenhouse gas, into useful chemicals to make new products needed by society and industry.&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 01/30/2017<br>      Modified by: Kevin&nbsp;J&nbsp;Kubarych</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Using extremely short bursts of laser light, this project dissected structure and dynamics of a chemical reaction that uses light to reverse combustion, effectively converting carbon dioxide into usable chemical raw materials. Catalysts speed up slow chemical reactions, and photocatalysts achieve this feat using power from light. Graduate students working in the research group used the distinct molecular vibrations of the most successful CO2 reduction photocatalyst to essentially record the fastest molecular motions of the catalyst, as well as the immediate molecular surroundings in the solution environment. For the first time, these vibrational snapshots enabled measurements of the photocatalyst in its active state following visible light absorption, enabling a direct comparison to the same molecule fully relaxed before excitation. The main finding is that the molecule?s fluctuations appear to slow following excitation, due to a reduced coupling to the surroundings. After a study changing both the chemical structure as well as the type of liquid solvent it is dissolved in, the team learned that the time scales for the dynamical fluctuations are dictated by a property of the liquid that relates to its tendency to infiltrate the catalyst and stick to the central metal atom (which is an atom of the metal element rhenium).    These first investigations led the team to add more ingredients needed for the photocatalytic reduction of CO2. To transform CO2 into other chemically useful materials (such as carbon monoxide or formate), requires a source of electrons. In the lab, researchers typically use amine bases (ammonia is one such base), and the best choice is triethanolamine. When the catalyst has absorbed visible light, it stays in a state that is especially prone to accepting an electron from triethanolamine, thus enabling the photocatalytic cycle to progress. The team performed the first experiments using vibrational snapshots of the catalyst dissolved in a series of triethanolamine solutions (with other liquids serving as the main solvent). They observed a remarkable slowdown in the dynamical fluctuations for specific mixtures of triethanolamine and some of the solvents. This finding shows that in some solution environments, the triethanolamine prefers to sit right next to the catalyst rather than be out in the solution. With the electron donating molecule so close to the catalyst, the time needed to transfer the electron to the catalyst is greatly reduced since the two do not need to randomly diffuse around to encounter each other. Other researchers in this field have not previously considered this possibility, and the findings provide some guidance about how future catalytic systems can be engineered to have increased efficiency and reliability.    To test the idea that the catalyst in some sense "attracts" some molecules at the expense of others, the team added another molecule to the solution with the rhenium catalyst. This molecule, a salt of sodium and thiocyanate, gives a particularly strong vibrational signal, so the researchers could test whether or not it was close to the catalyst by exciting the vibrations of the catalyst, and timing how long the energy arrived at the presumably nearby thiocyanate solute. The process is similar to a radio transmitter and receiver: the closer the radio is to the broadcasting tower, the stronger the radio signal will be. They found that even at low concentration of thiocyanate, where one would not expect many to be found near the catalyst, the time for energy transfer was very fast. This fast energy transfer "call and response" indicates that the two are essentially touching each other in solution, offering further support for the picture of preferential interaction.    Understating fundamental details of chemical reactions is essentially in order to design rationally the next generation of CO2 reducing catalysts. By exposing the relatively strong interactions between various actors in the complex mechanism, new approaches based on using surfaces, materials, and alternative linking strategies should enable more robust and efficient conversion of CO2, a potent greenhouse gas, into useful chemicals to make new products needed by society and industry.           Last Modified: 01/30/2017       Submitted by: Kevin J Kubarych]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
