<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Collaborative Research: Tailoring Energy Flow in Magnetic Oscillator Arrays</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>06/01/2013</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2016</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>250000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>250000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CMMI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Civil, Mechanical, &amp; Manufact Inn</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Jordan Berg</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>jberg@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032925365</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This project seeks to develop an integrated research and educational collaboration to examine the fundamental behavior of large arrays of coupled nonlinear oscillators.  Through a combined series of theoretical and experimental investigations, we will investigate how alterations in the coupling (via magnetic interactions)  can tailor bandgaps, bifurcations, the localization of energy, and a new phenomena called a passively reconfiguring bandgap.  Research studies build from theory to micro/macro experimental demonstrations with a focus on tuning the magnetic interactions to create desired phenomena.  The Principle Investigators believe the passively reconfiguring bandgaps, where a response threshold could be used to completely reconfigure the bandgap structure, offers a fundamentally new capability for avoiding catastrophic failures. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The fundamental nature of the research investigations is expected to improve engineering practice with specific examples of how to exploit nonlinearity to achieve  desirable energy flow behaviors in oscillator arrays.  The avoidance of catastrophic failures from mechanical or acoustic overloads is a specific application area for this research. Educational and outreach efforts will leverage the PIs successful involvement in existing programs, the Pratt Fellows program at Duke University and the NSF funded Southeast Alliance for Graduate Education and the Professoriate (SEAGEP) program at the University of Florida, to attract underrepresented students to participate in engineering research and pursue advanced degrees.  Summertime graduate student exchanges are planned to broaden the perspectives of everyone involved and enhance the project collaboration and impact.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>05/21/2013</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/21/2013</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1300658</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>David</FirstName>
<LastName>Arnold</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>P</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>David P Arnold</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>darnold@ufl.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>3523924931</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000267630</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/21/2013</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Florida</Name>
<CityName>GAINESVILLE</CityName>
<ZipCode>326112002</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>3523923516</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1 UNIVERSITY OF FLORIDA</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Florida</StateName>
<StateCode>FL</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>FL03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>969663814</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF FLORIDA</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>159621697</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Florida]]></Name>
<CityName>Gainesville</CityName>
<StateCode>FL</StateCode>
<ZipCode>326116200</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[213 Larsen Hall]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Florida</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>FL03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7478</Code>
<Text>DYNAMICAL SYSTEMS</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>034E</Code>
<Text>Dynamical systems</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>035E</Code>
<Text>NOISE, ACOUSTICS, VIBRATIONS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8024</Code>
<Text>Complex Systems</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0113</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2013~250000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Mechanical oscillators serve as the basic building blocks for a variety of dynamic devices and systems including energy harvesters, mechanical resonators, vibration dampers. There has been a growing interest in wave energy propagation behaviors that can be realized using periodic arrays of coupled oscillators. Of specic interest are frequency bandgaps that can be tailored by tuning parameters of the oscillator arrays. A frequency bandgap is a region in a systems frequency response where wave propagation (acoustic, electrical signal, vibrational, etc.) is attenuated, but around which propagation of the wave input occurs.</p> <p>This collaborative research effort between Duke University and University of Florida explored ways to leverage arrays nonlinearly coupled oscillators, defined as magneto-mechanical lattices, to enable unique dynamic energy propoagation behaviors. This effort relied on multidisciplinary expertise in nonlinear dynamics and vibration, magnetic systems, and microfabrication. Using a combination of theory and experiements, we showed how magnetic coupling can be used to enable reconfiguring bandgaps, energy localization, and internal resonances. &nbsp;Experimental demonstrators were built and tested at both the macroscale and microscale. &nbsp;The results demonstrate controllable modication of the bandgap response and the ability to actively tune the response via an external magnetic field. Overall, these research results have broad application in energy conversion systems, acoustic devices, and shock/vibration control. This work also established a cross-disciplinary collaboration between Duke University and University of Florida.&nbsp;Summertime graduate student exchanges enabled students from Duke to spend time at University of Florida in order to broaden the perspectives and enhance the project impact.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 02/24/2017<br>      Modified by: David&nbsp;P&nbsp;Arnold</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Image         </div> <div class="galControls onePhoto" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation onePhoto" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1300658/1300658_10247076_1487968847379_graphic--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1300658/1300658_10247076_1487968847379_graphic--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Microfabricated Magneto-mechanical Lattices"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1300658/1300658_10247076_1487968847379_graphic--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Microfabricated Magneto-mechanical Lattices"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Photographs of various magnetically coupled oscillator array testbeds microfabricated from silicon substrates making use of nickel-iron (NiFe) for inter-oscillator magnetic coupling.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Robin E. Carroll, University of Florida</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">David&nbsp;P&nbsp;Arnold</div> <div class="imageTitle">Microfabricated Magneto-mechanical Lattices</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Mechanical oscillators serve as the basic building blocks for a variety of dynamic devices and systems including energy harvesters, mechanical resonators, vibration dampers. There has been a growing interest in wave energy propagation behaviors that can be realized using periodic arrays of coupled oscillators. Of specic interest are frequency bandgaps that can be tailored by tuning parameters of the oscillator arrays. A frequency bandgap is a region in a systems frequency response where wave propagation (acoustic, electrical signal, vibrational, etc.) is attenuated, but around which propagation of the wave input occurs.  This collaborative research effort between Duke University and University of Florida explored ways to leverage arrays nonlinearly coupled oscillators, defined as magneto-mechanical lattices, to enable unique dynamic energy propoagation behaviors. This effort relied on multidisciplinary expertise in nonlinear dynamics and vibration, magnetic systems, and microfabrication. Using a combination of theory and experiements, we showed how magnetic coupling can be used to enable reconfiguring bandgaps, energy localization, and internal resonances.  Experimental demonstrators were built and tested at both the macroscale and microscale.  The results demonstrate controllable modication of the bandgap response and the ability to actively tune the response via an external magnetic field. Overall, these research results have broad application in energy conversion systems, acoustic devices, and shock/vibration control. This work also established a cross-disciplinary collaboration between Duke University and University of Florida. Summertime graduate student exchanges enabled students from Duke to spend time at University of Florida in order to broaden the perspectives and enhance the project impact.       Last Modified: 02/24/2017       Submitted by: David P Arnold]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
