<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Combinatorial Representation Theory</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2013</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2016</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>94719.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>94719</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DMS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Tomek Bartoszynski</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>tbartosz@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924885</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This proposal brings together a set of problems aimed at integrating three seemingly different areas in combinatorial representation theory: centralizer algebras, Kronecker products and subalgebras of the symmetric group algebra. A fundamental open problem in combinatorial representation theory is to describe the multiplicities in the decomposition of the tensor product of two irreducible representations of the symmetric group. These multiplicities are called the Kronecker coefficients. The problem of finding a combinatorial interpretation for these coefficients has been open for nearly a hundred years and is one of the main problems in combinatorial representation theory. In a new development the PI and collaborators have established a new connection of this problem to the partition algebra, a centralizer algebra of the symmetric group.  The PI will use this new connection to study several outstanding open problems related to the Kronecker coefficients. The PI will also continue her contributions to combinatorial algebras, which are algebras that can be described via combinatorial methods, e.g., the descent and peak algebras. The significance of the descent algebras arise from their applications to noncommutative and quasi-symmetric functions, and from their connections to the ring of representations of the symmetric group. In this project, the PI proposes to investigate new combinatorial algebras and to use centralizer algebras to better understand the existing combinatorial algebras.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This research is in the general area of algebraic combinatorics. Algebraic objects are often complex and difficult to understand. Combinatorics help make abstract algebraic objects more concrete so that they become more accessible and can be more easily used in other fields. This is achieved through efficient algorithms and elementary models which give insight into the properties of algebraic objects. The proposed projects tackle deep and important problems that will advance the understanding of many fields, including quantum information theory, complexity theory, and algorithms. The results will have applications that would span many fields from physics and chemistry to computer science. In addition, the proposed research is of broad interest in mathematics to those studying symmetric functions, Lie theory, quantum groups, algebraic geometry, low dimensional topology and mathematical physics.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>09/03/2013</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>09/03/2013</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1300512</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Rosa</FirstName>
<LastName>Orellana</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>C</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Rosa C Orellana</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>Rosa.C.Orellana@Dartmouth.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6036462430</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000486366</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/03/2013</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Dartmouth College</Name>
<CityName>HANOVER</CityName>
<ZipCode>037551421</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6036463007</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>OFFICE OF SPONSORED PROJECTS</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[11 ROPE FERRY RD #6210]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New Hampshire</StateName>
<StateCode>NH</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NH02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>041027822</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>TRUSTEES OF DARTMOUTH COLLEGE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>041027822</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Dartmouth College]]></Name>
<CityName>Hanover</CityName>
<StateCode>NH</StateCode>
<ZipCode>037553546</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[6188 Kemeny Hall]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New Hampshire</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NH02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7970</Code>
<Text>Combinatorics</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EPSCoR Co-Funding</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0113</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2013~94719</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Objects arising in algebra are often viewed as complicated and mysterious.&nbsp; In combinatorial representation theory we seek to find simpler ways to represent these objects in order to understand and organize them.&nbsp; The easier representations are often then used to model physical phenomena. This proposal explored several projects related to tensor products of representations.&nbsp; The tensor decomposition problem is an important and difficult problem that shows up in many fields, including algebraic combinatorics, complexity theory, and statistics, and has applications in medicine, computer vision, chemistry, and fast matrix multiplication. Essentially, it is the problem of recovering individual signals from a mixture of signals.</p> <p>This award provided funding for the PI&rsquo;s investigation in combinatorial representation theory.&nbsp;&nbsp;In particular, the research centered around a fundamental unsolved problem in combinatorial representation theory that asks for a description of the multiplicities, called Kronecker coefficients, in the decomposition of the tensor product of two irreducible representations of the symmetric group.&nbsp; The PI investigated problems on the following topics: (1) Kronecker coefficients, (2) centralizer and diagram algebras, and (3) symmetric functions.</p> <p>In 1901, Schur discovered the Schur-Weyl duality that is considered one of the most profound and important results in representation theory as it links the most important groups in mathematics, the symmetric group and the general linear group. This duality has many beautiful consequences.&nbsp; In the 1990s, Jones discovered a new Schur-Weyl duality between the symmetric group and what has become known as the partition algebra, which was introduced by Martin. The projects in this proposal generalized two important consequences of the classical Schur-Weyl duality to this newer Schur-Weyl duality between the symmetric group and the partition algebra.&nbsp; The first consequence links tensor products and induced representations and the second consequence provides a link to symmetric functions via a Frobenius type formula.</p> <p>The main result of the investigation was the discovery of new bases of symmetric functions that specialize to characters of the symmetric group.&nbsp; One of the new basis has as structure coefficients the stable Kronecker coefficients. &nbsp;</p> <p>The Kronecker product has been linked to quantum physics and to theoretical computer science. Thus, the results will have a broader impact once they become mainstream.&nbsp;&nbsp; In addition, the PI has involved undergraduates in her research program and started programs for grade school children, middle and high school students to excite and hence increase the number of students wanting to study STEM related subjects.&nbsp;&nbsp; Additionally, the PI has been involved in the mentoring of female mathematicians through a number activities and workshops. &nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 11/21/2016<br>      Modified by: Rosa&nbsp;C&nbsp;Orellana</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Objects arising in algebra are often viewed as complicated and mysterious.  In combinatorial representation theory we seek to find simpler ways to represent these objects in order to understand and organize them.  The easier representations are often then used to model physical phenomena. This proposal explored several projects related to tensor products of representations.  The tensor decomposition problem is an important and difficult problem that shows up in many fields, including algebraic combinatorics, complexity theory, and statistics, and has applications in medicine, computer vision, chemistry, and fast matrix multiplication. Essentially, it is the problem of recovering individual signals from a mixture of signals.  This award provided funding for the PI?s investigation in combinatorial representation theory.  In particular, the research centered around a fundamental unsolved problem in combinatorial representation theory that asks for a description of the multiplicities, called Kronecker coefficients, in the decomposition of the tensor product of two irreducible representations of the symmetric group.  The PI investigated problems on the following topics: (1) Kronecker coefficients, (2) centralizer and diagram algebras, and (3) symmetric functions.  In 1901, Schur discovered the Schur-Weyl duality that is considered one of the most profound and important results in representation theory as it links the most important groups in mathematics, the symmetric group and the general linear group. This duality has many beautiful consequences.  In the 1990s, Jones discovered a new Schur-Weyl duality between the symmetric group and what has become known as the partition algebra, which was introduced by Martin. The projects in this proposal generalized two important consequences of the classical Schur-Weyl duality to this newer Schur-Weyl duality between the symmetric group and the partition algebra.  The first consequence links tensor products and induced representations and the second consequence provides a link to symmetric functions via a Frobenius type formula.  The main result of the investigation was the discovery of new bases of symmetric functions that specialize to characters of the symmetric group.  One of the new basis has as structure coefficients the stable Kronecker coefficients.    The Kronecker product has been linked to quantum physics and to theoretical computer science. Thus, the results will have a broader impact once they become mainstream.   In addition, the PI has involved undergraduates in her research program and started programs for grade school children, middle and high school students to excite and hence increase the number of students wanting to study STEM related subjects.   Additionally, the PI has been involved in the mentoring of female mathematicians through a number activities and workshops.         Last Modified: 11/21/2016       Submitted by: Rosa C Orellana]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
