<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Collaborative Research: Nexus of Simulation, Sensing and Actuation for Aerodynamic Vibration Reduction of Wind Turbine Blades</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>05/01/2013</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>10/31/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>138531.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>148531</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CMMI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Civil, Mechanical, &amp; Manufact Inn</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Yick Hsuan</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The objective of this collaborative research project is to advance the smart blade system through innovations in areas of advanced computational models of fluid-structure interactions, sensors and actuators.  Wind energy, an important source of clean and renewable energy, is becoming a major component of the U.S. energy portfolio.  The interest in large capacity wind turbines as an economical way to harvest wind energy has significantly increased in recent years.  Wind turbine blades are over 100m in length and the trend of increasing the size of the blades continues.  However, increases in the size of wind turbine blades means that aerodynamic vibrations need to be managed to prevent catastrophic failures.  The collaborative project team takes an innovative perspective to advance the smart turbine blade technology. The hypothesis of this research is that aerodynamic vibrations in wind turbine blades can be effectively mitigated with bio-inspired strategies for flow sensing, surface morphological change and fluid-structure interactions.  The specific goals of this research project are 1) to understand blade vibration dynamics with advanced modeling of fluid-structure interactions; 2) to study the mechanism of bio-sensing for flow turbulence determination and to implement a feasible sensor design strategy; and 3) to understand and emulate the functions of "smart fins" and "smart denticles" for aerodynamic vibration reductions. A systematic approach will be undertaken by combining modeling, sensing and actuation strategies. The smart blade system performance will also be validated via simulation-based virtual testing and reduced-scale model experiments. All of these aim to advance the state of art in the smart wind turbine blades.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project presents a great opportunity to advance smart blade technologies, which include intelligent components for blade vibration reduction.  A unique bio-inspired strategy will be pursued to prevent catastrophic failures of wind turbine blades by effectively mitigating the aerodynamic vibrations.  The strategy will also improve the operational efficiency of the wind energy system.   All of these advances will have important impacts on the safe and efficient production of wind energy.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>02/27/2013</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/03/2015</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1300149</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Xiong</FirstName>
<LastName>Yu</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Xiong Yu</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>xxy21@po.cwru.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2163686247</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000288471</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>02/27/2013</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Case Western Reserve University</Name>
<CityName>CLEVELAND</CityName>
<ZipCode>441064901</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2163684510</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>Nord Hall, Suite 615</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[10900 Euclid Avenue]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Ohio</StateName>
<StateCode>OH</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>11</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>OH11</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>077758407</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>CASE WESTERN RESERVE UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>077758407</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Case Western Reserve University]]></Name>
<CityName>Cleveland</CityName>
<StateCode>OH</StateCode>
<ZipCode>441064901</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[10900 Euclid Avenue]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Ohio</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>11</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>OH11</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1635</Code>
<Text>STRUCTURAL MATERIALS AND MECH</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1637</Code>
<Text>Structural and Architectural E</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1639</Code>
<Text>SENSORS AND SENSING SYSTEMS</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>025E</Code>
<Text>INFRASTRUCTURE MATERIALS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>032E</Code>
<Text>SENSORS AND ACTUATORS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>033E</Code>
<Text>Smart and responsive structures</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>036E</Code>
<Text>CIVIL INFRASTRUCTURE</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>039E</Code>
<Text>STRUCTURAL SYSTEMS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>040E</Code>
<Text>Haz mitigation of structural sys</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>099E</Code>
<Text>High voltage switching &amp; conversion</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>116E</Code>
<Text>RESEARCH EXP FOR UNDERGRADS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8022</Code>
<Text>Sustainable Infrastructure Materials</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9178</Code>
<Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9231</Code>
<Text>SUPPL FOR UNDERGRAD RES ASSIST</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9251</Code>
<Text>REU SUPP-Res Exp for Ugrd Supp</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0113</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0115</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2013~138531</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2015~10000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Wind energy is one of the most promising green energy sources as it is renewable, sustainable, and worldwide availability. &nbsp;&nbsp;This study assessed the potential of improving the energy production by wind turbine with smart blade technologies.&nbsp; Two innovative wind turbine blades, extensible blade and bio-inspired blade are studied. The extensible &lsquo;smart&rsquo; blade will be extended at low wind speed to harvest more wind energy; on the other hand, it will be retracted to its original shape at high wind speed to protect the blade from damages.&nbsp; Analyses showed that the extensible can increase the energy output by 30% compared with conventional blade under the wind condition in Lake Erie area.&nbsp; This study also investigated a bio-inspired blade inspired from the leading-edge tubercles on the humpback whale flippers and its potential to improving wind energy output. &nbsp;&nbsp;The performance of different blades is tested in a wind tunnel. &nbsp;The result shows that the blade with tubercles features higher performance in increasing the maximum power coefficient. Additionally, the tubercles can delay the stall significantly comparing to the reference blade. &nbsp;Computational simulations were conducted and results validated the results from experiments.</p> <p>This study engaged students to participate innovative interdisciplinary research.&nbsp; The outcome of this project will lead to new strategies to increase wind energy production.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 02/01/2018<br>      Modified by: Xiong&nbsp;Yu</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Wind energy is one of the most promising green energy sources as it is renewable, sustainable, and worldwide availability.   This study assessed the potential of improving the energy production by wind turbine with smart blade technologies.  Two innovative wind turbine blades, extensible blade and bio-inspired blade are studied. The extensible ?smart? blade will be extended at low wind speed to harvest more wind energy; on the other hand, it will be retracted to its original shape at high wind speed to protect the blade from damages.  Analyses showed that the extensible can increase the energy output by 30% compared with conventional blade under the wind condition in Lake Erie area.  This study also investigated a bio-inspired blade inspired from the leading-edge tubercles on the humpback whale flippers and its potential to improving wind energy output.   The performance of different blades is tested in a wind tunnel.  The result shows that the blade with tubercles features higher performance in increasing the maximum power coefficient. Additionally, the tubercles can delay the stall significantly comparing to the reference blade.  Computational simulations were conducted and results validated the results from experiments.  This study engaged students to participate innovative interdisciplinary research.  The outcome of this project will lead to new strategies to increase wind energy production.          Last Modified: 02/01/2018       Submitted by: Xiong Yu]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
