<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Biologically-Inspired Silicification of Fine-Grained Soils</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>03/01/2013</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>02/28/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>387652.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>387652</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CMMI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Civil, Mechanical, &amp; Manufact Inn</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Richard Fragaszy</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Many organisms mineralize tissues to produce structures that serve diverse functions such as skeletal support and protective composite layers.  These structures are formed through biomineralization processes that have low metabolic cost to the organism.  Of particular interest is the process of biosilicification -- the ability of organisms to direct the nucleation and growth of mechanically efficient silica skeletal materials.  Advances in biosilicification research present an opportunity for cross-fertilization between the seemingly disparate disciplines of biomineralization and geotechnical engineering to advance ground improvement technology.  The goals of this project are to:  1) Uncover new pathways for silica polymerization in fine-grained soil, 2) Use insights from biosilicification research to develop new processes for forming amorphous silica cements at natural pH levels using environmentally benign chemical materials, and 3) Reduce the life cycle impacts associated with ground improvement.  To achieve the project goals, laboratory experiments will be conducted to model the geotechnical construction practices of subgrade stabilization using wet and dry soil mixing.  Lime and cement stabilized samples will be used as control treatments.  Soil materials that consist of pure clay minerals, mixtures of the clay minerals, mine tailings, and natural soils will be silicified with a polycation and sodium silicate.  Adsorption and silicification-caused changes in soil geochemical properties will be assessed by x-ray diffraction, zeta potential, surface area, cation exchange capacity and pH.  Changes in geotechnical index properties due to treatment will be determined and used to optimize the experiments.  Strength of silicified soil will be measured by unconfined compression, consolidated undrained triaxial compression tests.  Consolidation and creep tests will be used to evaluate strength and compressibility changes.  The potential for the silicification process to reduce the volume changes associated with expansive soil will be determined.  Pilot scale field tests will guide development of field implementation methods and to improve treatment effectiveness.  &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Findings from this project will benefit society by reducing the life cycle environmental impacts of geotechnical construction, and training of the next generation of geotechnical engineers.  Current ground treatment processes can possess relatively high embodied energy, and they rely on resources that cannot be renewed on human time scales.  There can also be impacts to soil and groundwater and significant releases of CO2 to the atmosphere.  The silicification process offers the potential for using reduced amounts of environmentally friendly input materials to achieve engineering performance that is comparable to or better than current technologies.  By reducing the environmental impact, this new process has the potential to lower the cost of infrastructure projects.  The findings also have the potential to benefit the resource recovery industries in managing fine-grained tailings. Graduate students will receive interdisciplinary training and will have the unique opportunity to develop expertise in the rapidly growing areas of applied biogeochemistry and biologically inspired materials.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>02/12/2013</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>02/12/2013</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1301124</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Patricia</FirstName>
<LastName>Dove</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>M</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Patricia M Dove</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>dove@vt.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5402312444</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000242497</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>02/12/2013</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Joseph</FirstName>
<LastName>Dove</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>E</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Joseph E Dove</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>jedove@vt.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5402312307</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000246669</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>02/12/2013</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University</Name>
<CityName>BLACKSBURG</CityName>
<ZipCode>240610001</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5402315281</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>Sponsored Programs 0170</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[300 Turner Street NW, Suite 4200]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Virginia</StateName>
<StateCode>VA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>09</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>VA09</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>003137015</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>VIRGINIA POLYTECHNIC INSTITUTE AND STATE UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>003137015</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>VA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>240600001</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Virginia</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>09</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>VA09</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1634</Code>
<Text>GEOMECHANICS &amp; GEOMATERIALS</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1057</Code>
<Text>CIS BASE RESEARCH</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>172E</Code>
<Text>Geomechanics</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>CVIS</Code>
<Text>CIVIL INFRASTRUCTURE</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0113</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2013~387652</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Over the last decade, the engineering and scientific communities have made advances in developing new materials that draw upon a rapidly expanding understanding of biological materials and processes. &nbsp;Of particular interest is the ability of organisms to produce materials that serve diverse functions such as vision, navigation, and protection.&nbsp; These materials are the result of natural selection that is, in itself, the result of "tuning" mechanical efficiency in response to environmental conditions.&nbsp; &nbsp;Scientists, engineers, and businesses are highly motivated to harness insights from Nature to produce new industrial materials.&nbsp; The goal is to produce lighter, stiffer, stronger materials using smaller inputs of energy and component chemicals. This goal holds the promise of translating into improved economic and environmental sustainability for the producer and society.</p> <p>Civil engineers often need to increase the strength of the soils underlying roads, buildings, bridges and other infrastructure.&nbsp; Current strengthening methods typically use Portland cement to react with moisture in the soil to produce cementing compounds.&nbsp; Quicklime and hydrated lime are also extensively used instead of or in conjunction with Portland cement. &nbsp;While a great deal of expertise and equipment has developed over the years for applying these technologies, drawbacks to the current state of practice include: 1) production of Portland cement and lime requires 4.8 MJ/kg and 5.3 MJ/kg of embodied energy, respectively; 2) environmental costs of production that includes release of 0.93 kgCO<sub>2</sub>/kg and 0.76 kgCO<sub>2</sub>/kg, respectively; 3) potential harmful effects on soil, groundwater and buried structures due to high concentrations of caustic and/or other materials in the subsurface; and 4) inconsistent improvement of certain soils.</p> <p>The primary intellectual merit of this project is in using insights into how some marine organisms incorporate dilute concentrations of silica in the oceans into their skeletons.&nbsp; It is known that these organisms use complex chemical reactions that cannot currently be duplicated at the scale of a construction project. Therefore, a method was developed in this research in which the surface chemistry of natural clay soils was modified with various commercially-available water soluble polymers.&nbsp; After this pretreatment, the soils were blended with a silica solution and compacted.&nbsp; A method to determine the quantities of the components needed for treatment was developed.</p> <p>Results indicate that this method improves the strength and compressibility for most of the fine-grained soils used.&nbsp; Strength gains are comparable to other more traditional methods of improving soils for construction.&nbsp; As an additional benefit, the tendency for certain fine-grained soils to undergo volume change that is damaging to structures is also reduced. &nbsp;At this stage of development, this new method is most readily applied to the problem of stabilizing subgrades underlying roadways, airports and other structures.</p> <p>In addition to the project results, the broader outcomes of this project included: introducing the need for improving the ground underlying infrastructure to middle school students; creating a collection of clay mineral images for geoscience and engineering teaching that has been downloaded 835 times (as of August 2017); submission of two journal manuscripts; and the multidisciplinary graduate training of five US students and one international student. &nbsp;All students are now in professional practice.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 08/15/2017<br>      Modified by: Joseph&nbsp;E&nbsp;Dove</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Over the last decade, the engineering and scientific communities have made advances in developing new materials that draw upon a rapidly expanding understanding of biological materials and processes.  Of particular interest is the ability of organisms to produce materials that serve diverse functions such as vision, navigation, and protection.  These materials are the result of natural selection that is, in itself, the result of "tuning" mechanical efficiency in response to environmental conditions.   Scientists, engineers, and businesses are highly motivated to harness insights from Nature to produce new industrial materials.  The goal is to produce lighter, stiffer, stronger materials using smaller inputs of energy and component chemicals. This goal holds the promise of translating into improved economic and environmental sustainability for the producer and society.  Civil engineers often need to increase the strength of the soils underlying roads, buildings, bridges and other infrastructure.  Current strengthening methods typically use Portland cement to react with moisture in the soil to produce cementing compounds.  Quicklime and hydrated lime are also extensively used instead of or in conjunction with Portland cement.  While a great deal of expertise and equipment has developed over the years for applying these technologies, drawbacks to the current state of practice include: 1) production of Portland cement and lime requires 4.8 MJ/kg and 5.3 MJ/kg of embodied energy, respectively; 2) environmental costs of production that includes release of 0.93 kgCO2/kg and 0.76 kgCO2/kg, respectively; 3) potential harmful effects on soil, groundwater and buried structures due to high concentrations of caustic and/or other materials in the subsurface; and 4) inconsistent improvement of certain soils.  The primary intellectual merit of this project is in using insights into how some marine organisms incorporate dilute concentrations of silica in the oceans into their skeletons.  It is known that these organisms use complex chemical reactions that cannot currently be duplicated at the scale of a construction project. Therefore, a method was developed in this research in which the surface chemistry of natural clay soils was modified with various commercially-available water soluble polymers.  After this pretreatment, the soils were blended with a silica solution and compacted.  A method to determine the quantities of the components needed for treatment was developed.  Results indicate that this method improves the strength and compressibility for most of the fine-grained soils used.  Strength gains are comparable to other more traditional methods of improving soils for construction.  As an additional benefit, the tendency for certain fine-grained soils to undergo volume change that is damaging to structures is also reduced.  At this stage of development, this new method is most readily applied to the problem of stabilizing subgrades underlying roadways, airports and other structures.  In addition to the project results, the broader outcomes of this project included: introducing the need for improving the ground underlying infrastructure to middle school students; creating a collection of clay mineral images for geoscience and engineering teaching that has been downloaded 835 times (as of August 2017); submission of two journal manuscripts; and the multidisciplinary graduate training of five US students and one international student.  All students are now in professional practice.       Last Modified: 08/15/2017       Submitted by: Joseph E Dove]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
