<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Tunable VUV pump and tunable VUV probe experiments on the photodissociation dynamics of atmospheric molecules using slice velocity imaging for detection</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/15/2013</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>360000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>376834</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03090000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CHE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Chemistry</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Colby Foss</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>cfoss@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032925327</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>With this award, funded by the Chemical Structure, Dynamics, and Mechanisms - A Program in the Division of Chemistry, Prof. William M. Jackson from the University of California, Davis will characterize the photochemical channels of molecules important in planetary atmospheres, comets, and the interstellar medium in the spectral region between 190.8 and 73.8 nm. The initial studies will be done with the nitrogen, oxygen, nitric oxide, and carbon monoxide molecules. The first three molecules are important for the chemistry of the upper atmosphere, while the last, carbon monoxide is the second most abundant molecule in the interstellar medium and is important in the early development of solar systems. A unique apparatus has been developed with two tunable VUV lasers based on resonance enhanced four wave mixing that has a bandwidth of 0.4 wavenumbers and is tunable between 190.8 and 73.8 nm. One of these tunable lasers can be used to excite the molecule to a particular energy state characterized by the electronic, vibrational, and rotational energy in the molecule and the other can be used to ionize the product atoms that are formed in the dissociation. These lasers are connected to a slice imaging apparatus that can determine the mass as well as the velocity and angular distributions of the product atoms. This information provides critical information about how the specific internal energy of an excited molecule affects the conservation of spin and the fine structure distributions of the product atoms and it provides a critical test for the best theoretical calculations for excited state potential energy curves as well as the dissociation process that occurs on these curves.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Simple molecules such as nitrogen, oxygen, nitric oxide, and carbon monoxide only absorb high-energy solar light. This light cannot be seen by the naked eye and it will not travel in air. Yet this light from the sun determines how long molecules such as nitrogen, oxygen and NO can exist in the earth's and other planets atmospheres. It provides the energy for the chemical reactions occurring in these regions as well as those that occurred during the early years of planet formation in this and other solar systems. To truly understand the chemical reactions that do occur in the atmosphere, it is important to understand how this solar light forms the reactive atoms and fragments. These reactive species, in turn, undergo chemical reactions with stable trace species such as carbon dioxide that help determine the climate here on earth. Solar light with different amounts of energy can form nitrogen and oxygen atoms from nitrogen and oxygen molecules that can react differently with both the trace species such as carbon dioxide as well as with the oxygen and nitrogen molecules themselves. The work that will be performed on this grant will provide the information about how the energy of the atoms that is formed changes with the solar energy of the solar light that is absorbed. This information can then be put in the models that are used to predict the future behavior of trace components in our atmosphere as well as the atmospheres of other planets and astronomical bodies.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>09/08/2013</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/01/2015</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1301501</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>William</FirstName>
<LastName>Jackson</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>M</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>William M Jackson</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>wmjackson@ucdavis.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>9167526310</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000352158</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/08/2013</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of California-Davis</Name>
<CityName>Davis</CityName>
<ZipCode>956186134</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5307547700</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>OR/Sponsored Programs</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[1850 Research Park Dr., Ste 300]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CA03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>047120084</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF CALIFORNIA, DAVIS</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>071549000</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of California- Davis]]></Name>
<CityName>Davis</CityName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>956165271</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[One Shields Ave]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CA03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>9101</Code>
<Text>Chem Struct,Dynmcs&amp;Mechansms A</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1524</Code>
<Text>ATMOSPHERIC CHEMISTRY</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9162</Code>
<Text>MULTI DIVISION/UNIVERSITY</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>AMPP</Code>
<Text>ADVANCED MATERIALS &amp; PROCESSING PROGRAM</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0113</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0115</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2013~360000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2015~16834</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>&nbsp; &nbsp;The main goal of this research is to unravel the key photochemical sinks of important molecules in planetary&nbsp;atmospheres in our and other solar systems, protostellar envelopes, circumstellar disk and the interstellar medium in the most important wavelengths between 80 and 100 nm. This kind of information will allow us trace the detailed molecular history of our universe and the improve the chemical models in these regions. The principle molecules under study this year were N<sub>2</sub>, CO&nbsp;and CO<sub>2</sub>. A unique apparatus, Fig. 1, was built that uses a laser with a wavelength between&nbsp; 80-100 nm to excite isolated molecules in a molecular beam to a state with an energy defined by the laser wavelength with an accuracy of 4 parts in a million.&nbsp; The atoms or molecules that are formed can be selectively ionized using a second laser and a time-of-flight mass spectrometer equipped with an imaging detector (TOF-MS-ID) that measures the mass and kinetic energies of the product. For the N<sub>2</sub>&nbsp;molecule the branching ratios for the reactions that form N(<sup>4</sup>S<sub>3/2</sub>),&nbsp;N(<sup>2</sup>D<sub>5/2</sub>,<sub>3/2</sub>) and/or N(<sup>2</sup>P<sub>1/2,3/2</sub>) have been determined at well-defined energies between 12.45-14.5 eV. Similar, experiments have been performed for CO. These results have been used to explain why the&nbsp;<sup>15</sup>N isotope of N<sub>2</sub>&nbsp;is 7 times more enriched in terrestrial planets relative to the sun than the&nbsp; rare isotopes of <sup>17</sup>O&nbsp;and <sup>18</sup>O.</p> <p>&nbsp; The spin correlated branching ratios of the O(<sup>3</sup>P<sub>2,1,0</sub>)&nbsp;atoms formed with CO (&atilde; <sup>3</sup>&Pi;; v) and CO(X <sup>1</sup>&Sigma;<sup>+</sup><sub>u</sub>&nbsp;; v) in the photodissociation of CO<sub>2</sub> have been determined using the apparatus. Product distributions in the dissociation CO<sub>2</sub> in the 13.540 -13.678 eV regions show CO(X<sup>1</sup>&Sigma;<sup>+</sup>; v") + O(<sup>1</sup>D) or O(<sup>1</sup>S); CO(a<sup>3</sup>&Pi;; v') + O(<sup>3</sup>P<sub>2,1,0</sub>) or O(<sup>1</sup>D); CO(a' <sup>3</sup>&Sigma;<sup>+</sup>; v') + O(<sup>3</sup>P<sub>2,1,0</sub>); CO(d' <sup>3</sup>&Delta;; v') + O(<sup>3</sup>P<sub>2,1,0</sub>); and CO(e <sup>3</sup>&Sigma;<sup>-</sup>; v') + O(<sup>3</sup>P<sub>2,1,0</sub>). At lower excitation energies in the 11.94-12.20 eV range the photoproducts observed by breaking the C-O bond in CO<sub>2</sub> lead to the formation of CO(X<sup>1</sup>&Sigma;<sup>+</sup>; v"= 0-18) + O(<sup>1</sup>D) or CO(X<sup>1</sup>&Sigma;<sup>+</sup>; v" 0-9) + O(<sup>1</sup>S). In this same energy range, we have shown that photodissociation &nbsp;of CO<sub>2</sub> produces C(<sup>3</sup>P<sub>2,1,0</sub>) + O<sub>2</sub>(X<sup>3</sup>&Sigma;<sub>g</sub><sup>-</sup>). &nbsp;This work has been published and the reprints will be loaded along with this report.</p> <p>&nbsp;&nbsp; In addition to the published work the PI has unpublished work on the spin-orbit states of N<sub>2</sub>, CO, and CO<sub>2</sub>. The work on N<sub>2</sub> shows the relative production of N(<sup>2</sup>D<sub>3/2</sub>)/ N(<sup>2</sup>D<sub>5/2</sub>) can be measured from the photofragment excitation spectrum (PHOFEX) obtained by tuning the&nbsp; detection laser while dissociating the N<sub>2</sub> molecule from the c<sub>3</sub><sup>1</sup>&Pi;,&nbsp;v'= 0, J' =1, with the photolysis laser. The work on CO covers the photodissociation of this molecule from 92.46 nm to the ionization potential at 88.50 nm and it shows how C(<sup>3</sup>P<sub>0</sub>) and C(<sup>3</sup>P<sub>0</sub>) and O(<sup>1</sup>D<sub>2</sub>) are produced. This extends earlier work done on this molecule. Two other noteworthy observations have been that are &nbsp;to be published are the observation of the production of the triplet dissociation channels of CO<sub>2</sub> by ionizing the CO(a<sup>3</sup>&Pi;; v') with the detection laser. The higher excited states of the triple CO molecule relax via emission to this state in tens of ns that provides us with a probe of all of these triplet states. dissociation channels This is the first example to our knowledge that this type of information of excited states of a molecular fragment can be detected in this manner. The second observation is the production of C + O<sub>2</sub> in the 13.540 -13.678 eV energy region, thus proving that molecular oxygen is produce on the ground and excited states. This has profound implications since it means that there are a variety ways that molecular oxygen will be produce in the early history of the Earth that have profound implications on the origin of life.</p> <p>&nbsp;&nbsp; All of the work that has been described in the publications and to date in the unpublished work has been performed by exciting allowed transitions from the ground electronic state to excited states. While photons have been used to accomplish these feats, the same states will be excited over a much larger energy range by electrons with energies above the threshold energies for a particular group of products. This means that even in regions where the high energy light cannot penetrate the processes described can still occur if high energy electrons are present. These high energy electrons will appear everywhere because will be formed as cosmic rays are slowed down in matter.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 11/23/2017<br>      Modified by: William&nbsp;M&nbsp;Jackson</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Images (<span id="selectedPhoto0">1</span> of <span class="totalNumber"></span>)           </div> <div class="galControls" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1301501/1301501_10276792_1511397852284_revisedapparatuswithequations--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1301501/1301501_10276792_1511397852284_revisedapparatuswithequations--rgov-800width.jpg" title="VUV Pump and VUV Probe Apparatus"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1301501/1301501_10276792_1511397852284_revisedapparatuswithequations--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="VUV Pump and VUV Probe Apparatus"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">UC Davis Vacuum Ultraviolet laser apparatus. The VUV lasers are produced by resonant enhanced four-wave mixing in a rare gas. The detector is a Time of flight (TOF) mass spectrometer equipped with a slice imaging detector.</div> <div class="imageCredit">William M. Jackson</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">William&nbsp;M&nbsp;Jackson</div> <div class="imageTitle">VUV Pump and VUV Probe Apparatus</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1301501/1301501_10276792_1511410363830_Fig.3--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1301501/1301501_10276792_1511410363830_Fig.3--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Probing the forbidden O singlet D channel as a function of wavelength from 88.34-92.68 nm"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1301501/1301501_10276792_1511410363830_Fig.3--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Probing the forbidden O singlet D channel as a function of wavelength from 88.34-92.68 nm"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Fig. a, probing the C triplet J = 0 spin-orbit state, Fig. b, probing the C triplet J =2 spin-orbit state and Fig. c. PHOFEX spectrum of CO sitting on the C triplet J = 0 line, while tuning the photolysis laser. The squares in Figs. a and b are obtained from the images.</div> <div class="imageCredit">William M. Jackson</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">William&nbsp;M&nbsp;Jackson</div> <div class="imageTitle">Probing the forbidden O singlet D channel as a function of wavelength from 88.34-92.68 nm</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1301501/1301501_10276792_1511411755206_Fig.5--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1301501/1301501_10276792_1511411755206_Fig.5--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Formation of C from the photodissociation CO2 in the 11.686-12.145 eV"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1301501/1301501_10276792_1511411755206_Fig.5--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Formation of C from the photodissociation CO2 in the 11.686-12.145 eV"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Formation of the C(triplet P, J = 2) atom produced in the photodissociation of CO2. The threshold energy for the production of this atom is 11.44 eV. This work proved that the C atoms are produced on the ground state surface.</div> <div class="imageCredit">William M. Jackson</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">William&nbsp;M&nbsp;Jackson</div> <div class="imageTitle">Formation of C from the photodissociation CO2 in the 11.686-12.145 eV</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1301501/1301501_10276792_1511412926829_Fig.2--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1301501/1301501_10276792_1511412926829_Fig.2--rgov-800width.jpg" title="PHOFEX spectra of the spin orbit states of the excited D states of N atoms and the ground quartet S state."><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1301501/1301501_10276792_1511412926829_Fig.2--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="PHOFEX spectra of the spin orbit states of the excited D states of N atoms and the ground quartet S state."></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">T figure shows the PHOFEX spectra for nitrogen atoms produced when the the nitrogen molecule is excited to the c3 singlet pi Rydberg state at 104,141.4 cm-1.</div> <div class="imageCredit">William M. Jackson</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">William&nbsp;M&nbsp;Jackson</div> <div class="imageTitle">PHOFEX spectra of the spin orbit states of the excited D states of N atoms and the ground quartet S state.</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1301501/1301501_10276792_1511418795356_Fig.8--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1301501/1301501_10276792_1511418795356_Fig.8--rgov-800width.jpg" title="First detection of the a triplet pi state of CO produced in the photodissociation of carbon dioxide at 13.68 eV"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1301501/1301501_10276792_1511418795356_Fig.8--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="First detection of the a triplet pi state of CO produced in the photodissociation of carbon dioxide at 13.68 eV"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">This TKER spectrum shows evidence for production of C atoms and oxygen molecules from the photodissociation of carbon dioxide  at high energies. Similar observations  have been made at 13.568 and 13.605 eV.</div> <div class="imageCredit">William M. Jackson</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">William&nbsp;M&nbsp;Jackson</div> <div class="imageTitle">First detection of the a triplet pi state of CO produced in the photodissociation of carbon dioxide at 13.68 eV</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1301501/1301501_10276792_1511419213134_Fig.9--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1301501/1301501_10276792_1511419213134_Fig.9--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Production of molecular oxygen at high energies from the photodissociation of CO2."><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1301501/1301501_10276792_1511419213134_Fig.9--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Production of molecular oxygen at high energies from the photodissociation of CO2."></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">This figure shows that molecular oxygen can be produced at high energies of 13.68 eV.</div> <div class="imageCredit">William M. Jackson</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">William&nbsp;M&nbsp;Jackson</div> <div class="imageTitle">Production of molecular oxygen at high energies from the photodissociation of CO2.</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[    The main goal of this research is to unravel the key photochemical sinks of important molecules in planetary atmospheres in our and other solar systems, protostellar envelopes, circumstellar disk and the interstellar medium in the most important wavelengths between 80 and 100 nm. This kind of information will allow us trace the detailed molecular history of our universe and the improve the chemical models in these regions. The principle molecules under study this year were N2, CO and CO2. A unique apparatus, Fig. 1, was built that uses a laser with a wavelength between  80-100 nm to excite isolated molecules in a molecular beam to a state with an energy defined by the laser wavelength with an accuracy of 4 parts in a million.  The atoms or molecules that are formed can be selectively ionized using a second laser and a time-of-flight mass spectrometer equipped with an imaging detector (TOF-MS-ID) that measures the mass and kinetic energies of the product. For the N2 molecule the branching ratios for the reactions that form N(4S3/2), N(2D5/2,3/2) and/or N(2P1/2,3/2) have been determined at well-defined energies between 12.45-14.5 eV. Similar, experiments have been performed for CO. These results have been used to explain why the 15N isotope of N2 is 7 times more enriched in terrestrial planets relative to the sun than the  rare isotopes of 17O and 18O.    The spin correlated branching ratios of the O(3P2,1,0) atoms formed with CO (&atilde; 3&Pi;; v) and CO(X 1&Sigma;+u ; v) in the photodissociation of CO2 have been determined using the apparatus. Product distributions in the dissociation CO2 in the 13.540 -13.678 eV regions show CO(X1&Sigma;+; v") + O(1D) or O(1S); CO(a3&Pi;; v') + O(3P2,1,0) or O(1D); CO(a' 3&Sigma;+; v') + O(3P2,1,0); CO(d' 3&Delta;; v') + O(3P2,1,0); and CO(e 3&Sigma;-; v') + O(3P2,1,0). At lower excitation energies in the 11.94-12.20 eV range the photoproducts observed by breaking the C-O bond in CO2 lead to the formation of CO(X1&Sigma;+; v"= 0-18) + O(1D) or CO(X1&Sigma;+; v" 0-9) + O(1S). In this same energy range, we have shown that photodissociation  of CO2 produces C(3P2,1,0) + O2(X3&Sigma;g-).  This work has been published and the reprints will be loaded along with this report.     In addition to the published work the PI has unpublished work on the spin-orbit states of N2, CO, and CO2. The work on N2 shows the relative production of N(2D3/2)/ N(2D5/2) can be measured from the photofragment excitation spectrum (PHOFEX) obtained by tuning the  detection laser while dissociating the N2 molecule from the c31&Pi;, v'= 0, J' =1, with the photolysis laser. The work on CO covers the photodissociation of this molecule from 92.46 nm to the ionization potential at 88.50 nm and it shows how C(3P0) and C(3P0) and O(1D2) are produced. This extends earlier work done on this molecule. Two other noteworthy observations have been that are  to be published are the observation of the production of the triplet dissociation channels of CO2 by ionizing the CO(a3&Pi;; v') with the detection laser. The higher excited states of the triple CO molecule relax via emission to this state in tens of ns that provides us with a probe of all of these triplet states. dissociation channels This is the first example to our knowledge that this type of information of excited states of a molecular fragment can be detected in this manner. The second observation is the production of C + O2 in the 13.540 -13.678 eV energy region, thus proving that molecular oxygen is produce on the ground and excited states. This has profound implications since it means that there are a variety ways that molecular oxygen will be produce in the early history of the Earth that have profound implications on the origin of life.     All of the work that has been described in the publications and to date in the unpublished work has been performed by exciting allowed transitions from the ground electronic state to excited states. While photons have been used to accomplish these feats, the same states will be excited over a much larger energy range by electrons with energies above the threshold energies for a particular group of products. This means that even in regions where the high energy light cannot penetrate the processes described can still occur if high energy electrons are present. These high energy electrons will appear everywhere because will be formed as cosmic rays are slowed down in matter.          Last Modified: 11/23/2017       Submitted by: William M Jackson]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
