<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>SusChEM: Mechanistic examination and design of multifunctional heterogeneous photocatalysts for artificial photosynthesis</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2013</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>315000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>315000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03090000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CHE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Chemistry</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>George Janini</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>gjanini@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032928840</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The Chemical Catalysis Program (CAT) of the NSF Division of Chemistry supports Professor Phillip Christopher of the University of California, Riverside in efforts to elucidate the elementary mechanisms that control performance for the solar driven artificial photosynthesis (AP) reaction, CO2 + H2O conversion to fuels. Specifically, the kinetics associated with H2O splitting, CO2 methanation and H2O formation will be studied on metal loaded semiconductors (Rh, Ru and Ni deposited on TiO2 and GaN:ZnO) as a function of catalyst characteristics and process variables. Catalytically active sites will be engineered to optimize AP performance and nano-scale mass transfer control will be utilized to manipulate concentrations of reaction intermediate at active sites. The effect of adding a thermal stimulus to the reacting system will be explored, which is hypothesized to significantly enhance reaction rates. The overall objective is to identify materials and conditions that maximize the rates of H2O splitting and CO2 methanation while minimizing H2O formation to facilitate the overall AP process through a unique reaction pathway that exploits thermo- and photo-catalytic steps.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Global reliance on unsustainable fossil resources for energy and chemical industries has resulted in the release of massive quantities of CO2 and H2O into the atmosphere. The development of strategies that harness solar energy for direct CO2 and H2O conversion to fuels and chemicals (artificial photosynthesis, AP) are the most appealing solutions for environmental and energy sustainability. Professor Christopher and coworkers will combine fundamental insights into the reaction mechanism with nano-scale reaction engineering to design more efficient AP catalysts.  Students from UC Riverside, Riverside community college and local middle schools will significantly benefit from hands on education in this multidisciplinary research effort.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>04/15/2013</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>09/04/2013</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1301019</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Phillip</FirstName>
<LastName>Christopher</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>N</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Phillip N Christopher</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>pchristopher@ucsb.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>9518277959</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000600255</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/15/2013</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of California-Riverside</Name>
<CityName>RIVERSIDE</CityName>
<ZipCode>925210217</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>9518275535</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>Research &amp; Economic Development</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[245 University Office Building]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>44</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CA44</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>627797426</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>REGENTS OF THE UNIVERSITY OF CALIFORNIA AT RIVERSIDE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>071549000</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of California-Riverside]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>925210001</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>41</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CA41</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>6884</Code>
<Text>Chemical Catalysis</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>6884</Code>
<Text>CHEMICAL CATALYSIS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8248</Code>
<Text>SusChEM</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8650</Code>
<Text>Sustainable Chemistry</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0113</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2013~315000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Intellectual Merit</p> <p>The development of viable CO<sub>2</sub>&nbsp;conversion technologies is at its infancy, both in terms of fundamental science and applied engineering. As with many technologies, the fundamental science, demonstrating the potential promise of a technology, must be advanced before significant engineering efforts to realize this promise can be justified. The primary intellectual outputs of this project were detailed fundamental insights that will guide the design of optimized heterogeneous catalysts for thermal driven CO<sub>2</sub>&nbsp;conversion and photocatalysts for the conversion of solar energy into viable fuels.</p> <p>Experimental and theoretical analysis executed in this project added significant knowledge to the field regarding catalyst characteristics that control reactivity and selectivity in the conversion of CO<sub>2</sub>&nbsp;to higher value products (CO for example) through thermal driven heterogeneous catalytic processes. Specifically, the influence of active metal structure (from nanometer sized metal clusters to single metal atoms), composition (including most late transition metals) and support composition and structure on CO<sub>2</sub>&nbsp;conversion selectivity were elucidated and reported. In addition, characterization approaches for supported metal catalysts were developed, including a quantitative active site differentiation and counting methodology and combined in-situ infrared spectroscopy and electron microscopy approach for studying the reconstruction of supported metal catalysts.&nbsp;</p> <p>Another intellectual contribution that emerged from these studies is the importance of considering the thermocatalytic properties of co-catalysts used in photocatalysis. Co-catalysts in photocatalysis have long been considered to act as charge carrier syncs, but not often has the importance of the thermocatalytic characteristics of these structures been a major focus. We made efforts to demonstrate that the inherent thermocatalytic properties of co-catalysts are perhaps their most important characteristic.</p> <p>Broader Impact</p> <p>The fundamental insights elucidated in this project are expected to facilitate the development and design of catalytic CO<sub>2</sub>&nbsp;conversion technologies by guiding the identification of optimal catalytic materials. Furthermore, the developed methodologies for characterizing heterogeneous supported metal catalysts are expected to be useful for the understanding and design of a range of heterogeneous catalysts, from those used in applications ranging from automotive catalysis to commodity chemical production.</p> <p>This project has provided many opportunities for training and professional development of students. Part of the broader impact of this proposal was aimed at creating a program to give undergraduate students at a local community college, Riverside Community College (RCC), summer long immersion research experiences. Throughout this project, 6 undergraduate students spent a significant amount of time on the project. The work of these students has resulted in multiple publications. All 6 undergrads have excelled in their studies, with 5 out of 6 graduating from undergraduate school and 3 continuing into PhD programs. The remaining student is expected to follow a similar path. In addition, 2 PhD students and 1 MS student were involed in the research associated with this project. Collectively, these graduate students published high-level papers, delivered presentations at national meetings and had opportunities to train undergraduate students. This project has provided opportunities for the training and development of multiple undergraduate and graduate students through hands on research, mentoring opportunities, publications and presentations at national conferences.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 09/29/2017<br>      Modified by: Phillip&nbsp;N&nbsp;Christopher</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Intellectual Merit  The development of viable CO2 conversion technologies is at its infancy, both in terms of fundamental science and applied engineering. As with many technologies, the fundamental science, demonstrating the potential promise of a technology, must be advanced before significant engineering efforts to realize this promise can be justified. The primary intellectual outputs of this project were detailed fundamental insights that will guide the design of optimized heterogeneous catalysts for thermal driven CO2 conversion and photocatalysts for the conversion of solar energy into viable fuels.  Experimental and theoretical analysis executed in this project added significant knowledge to the field regarding catalyst characteristics that control reactivity and selectivity in the conversion of CO2 to higher value products (CO for example) through thermal driven heterogeneous catalytic processes. Specifically, the influence of active metal structure (from nanometer sized metal clusters to single metal atoms), composition (including most late transition metals) and support composition and structure on CO2 conversion selectivity were elucidated and reported. In addition, characterization approaches for supported metal catalysts were developed, including a quantitative active site differentiation and counting methodology and combined in-situ infrared spectroscopy and electron microscopy approach for studying the reconstruction of supported metal catalysts.   Another intellectual contribution that emerged from these studies is the importance of considering the thermocatalytic properties of co-catalysts used in photocatalysis. Co-catalysts in photocatalysis have long been considered to act as charge carrier syncs, but not often has the importance of the thermocatalytic characteristics of these structures been a major focus. We made efforts to demonstrate that the inherent thermocatalytic properties of co-catalysts are perhaps their most important characteristic.  Broader Impact  The fundamental insights elucidated in this project are expected to facilitate the development and design of catalytic CO2 conversion technologies by guiding the identification of optimal catalytic materials. Furthermore, the developed methodologies for characterizing heterogeneous supported metal catalysts are expected to be useful for the understanding and design of a range of heterogeneous catalysts, from those used in applications ranging from automotive catalysis to commodity chemical production.  This project has provided many opportunities for training and professional development of students. Part of the broader impact of this proposal was aimed at creating a program to give undergraduate students at a local community college, Riverside Community College (RCC), summer long immersion research experiences. Throughout this project, 6 undergraduate students spent a significant amount of time on the project. The work of these students has resulted in multiple publications. All 6 undergrads have excelled in their studies, with 5 out of 6 graduating from undergraduate school and 3 continuing into PhD programs. The remaining student is expected to follow a similar path. In addition, 2 PhD students and 1 MS student were involed in the research associated with this project. Collectively, these graduate students published high-level papers, delivered presentations at national meetings and had opportunities to train undergraduate students. This project has provided opportunities for the training and development of multiple undergraduate and graduate students through hands on research, mentoring opportunities, publications and presentations at national conferences.          Last Modified: 09/29/2017       Submitted by: Phillip N Christopher]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
