<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>RUI: Collaborative Research: An Experimental Study of Relativistic, Stochastic Heating of Electrons During the Irradiation of Wavelength-scale Plasmas by a Strong-Laser Field</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2013</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>255000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>255000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03010000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>PHY</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Physics</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Vyacheslav (Slava) Lukin</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>vlukin@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927382</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Collaborative Research: An Experimental Study of Relativistic, Stochastic Heating of Electrons During the Irradiation of Wavelength-scale Plasmas by a Strong-Laser Field&lt;br/&gt;A renewal proposal from PIs T. Ditmire (University of Texas) and T. Donnelly (Harvey Mudd College)&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Scientific Merit&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This grant supports a collaboration between Prof. Ditmire at the University of Texas at Austin (UT) and Prof. Donnelly at Harvey Mudd College (HMC), an undergraduate institution. We will investigate mechanisms by which high-intensity laser pulses deposit energy into matter.  While the nature of intense laser interactions with atoms, molecules, and solids has been studied for many years, exactly how intense laser pulses interact with objects that are of a spatial scale comparable to the light's wavelength (less than a millionth of a meter) is largely unexplored.  We will focus a 20 TW laser - a laser with nearly ten times the power of that on the entire US electrical grid - onto wavelength-scale targets and study the resulting electron and ions energies to study the mechanisms by which laser energy is absorbed by the target.   The scientific merit of this work rests in filling this gap in our knowledge of physics, and in developing improved x-ray and neutron sources.  &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Broader Impact&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The broader scientific impacts of this research rest in advancing the understanding of high-intensity laser interactions with a class of targets not previously well explored.  Application of these studies may aid in the development of improved x-ray sources for radiography and time-resolved diffraction, or compact neutron sources for imaging other systems.  The broader educational impact of this work is found in the training that both graduate and undergraduate students will receive.  Our work represents a unique collaboration in which an undergraduate group is directly and critically involved in strong-field-physics research, a field which is prohibitively resource intensive for an undergraduate research program to pursue alone.  The undergraduates funded by this grant will have the opportunity to do research at HMC, travel to UT in the summers to participate in research using equipment they have developed, and travel to conferences to present their work to the scientific community.  Our collaboration will continue to be an effective way to motivate undergraduates to seek advanced degrees in science.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>09/03/2013</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/18/2015</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1301823</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Thomas</FirstName>
<LastName>Donnelly</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>D</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Thomas D Donnelly</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>tom_donnelly@hmc.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>9096071843</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000476045</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/03/2013</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Harvey Mudd College</Name>
<CityName>CLAREMONT</CityName>
<ZipCode>917115901</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>9096218121</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>301 Platt Boulevard</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>27</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CA27</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>066691130</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>HARVEY MUDD COLLEGE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>066691130</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Harvey Mudd College]]></Name>
<CityName>Claremont</CityName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>917115901</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[301 Platt Blvd.]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>27</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CA27</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1242</Code>
<Text>PLASMA PHYSICS</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1062</Code>
<Text>BASIC PLASMA SCIENCE &amp; ENGINEERING</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9178</Code>
<Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9229</Code>
<Text>RES IN UNDERGRAD INST-RESEARCH</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0113</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0114</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0115</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2013~85000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~85000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2015~85000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The goal of this project is for the University of Texas at Austin (UT)/Harvey Mudd College collaboration to study the absorption of extremely-intense laser light by micron-scale targets.&nbsp; Specifically, we will carry out experiments to determine if these targets absorb energy through the process of multi-pass stochastic heating, an absorption mechanism that has been theorized as dominating the electron heating process but which has never been experimentally studied.</p> <p>At Harvey Mudd College, we have developed new target deposition techniques, a target-etching technique to overcome microsphere-microsphere bonding problems, and improved our model of target ablation to include Monte Carlo methods.&nbsp; Our evaporative and spin-coating techniques for depositing microspheres on a silicon substrate further improves our ability to cover macroscopic target areas with hexagonally close-pack arrangements of microspheres.&nbsp; This, in turn, improves the consistency with which we place microspheres into the focus of the high-power laser, and also improves the number of microsphere targets we can expect to hit with each high-power laser shot.</p> <p>We have also developed an oxygen-etching technique that overcomes the problem of microspheres bonding together as they form hexagonally-close-packed layers on our silicon surfaces.&nbsp; As the microspheres self-assemble in our deposition, they, unfortunately, tend to bond together and can therefore be ablated in clumps instead of as single spheres.&nbsp; To overcome this interspecies bonding, we have developed an oxygen etching technique that eats away at these bonds so that microspheres can be ablated as individual targets.</p> <p>We have also improved our model which describes how the ablating laser removes spheres from the silicon surface on which they have been deposited.&nbsp; Our model now uses Monte Carlo techniques to give a more accurate representation of of the timing delay between the firing of the ablation laser and the high-power laser.&nbsp; We have further improved the model&rsquo;s sophistication such that it no longer has any free parameters and does a very good job of reproducing our time of flight data.</p> <p>Finally, of the 12 Havey Mudd College undergraduates who have worked on this project (each one for multiple years) 7 are now pursuing PhDs in physics or physics-related fields. &nbsp;The other 5 are either working in high-tech (e.g., for a quantum computer start up company) or are still at Harvey Mudd College. &nbsp;Funding for this porject has provided opportunities to fill the STEM pipeline in the US. &nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 09/02/2017<br>      Modified by: Thomas&nbsp;D&nbsp;Donnelly</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Image         </div> <div class="galControls onePhoto" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation onePhoto" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1301823/1301823_10274181_1504369221305_Donnelly_Flier--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1301823/1301823_10274181_1504369221305_Donnelly_Flier--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Our Experiment"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1301823/1301823_10274181_1504369221305_Donnelly_Flier--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Our Experiment"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Microspheres are ejected from a silicon surface by a heating laser and then interact with UT Austin's high-power GHOST laser.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Tom Donnelly</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Public Domain</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Thomas&nbsp;D&nbsp;Donnelly</div> <div class="imageTitle">Our Experiment</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The goal of this project is for the University of Texas at Austin (UT)/Harvey Mudd College collaboration to study the absorption of extremely-intense laser light by micron-scale targets.  Specifically, we will carry out experiments to determine if these targets absorb energy through the process of multi-pass stochastic heating, an absorption mechanism that has been theorized as dominating the electron heating process but which has never been experimentally studied.  At Harvey Mudd College, we have developed new target deposition techniques, a target-etching technique to overcome microsphere-microsphere bonding problems, and improved our model of target ablation to include Monte Carlo methods.  Our evaporative and spin-coating techniques for depositing microspheres on a silicon substrate further improves our ability to cover macroscopic target areas with hexagonally close-pack arrangements of microspheres.  This, in turn, improves the consistency with which we place microspheres into the focus of the high-power laser, and also improves the number of microsphere targets we can expect to hit with each high-power laser shot.  We have also developed an oxygen-etching technique that overcomes the problem of microspheres bonding together as they form hexagonally-close-packed layers on our silicon surfaces.  As the microspheres self-assemble in our deposition, they, unfortunately, tend to bond together and can therefore be ablated in clumps instead of as single spheres.  To overcome this interspecies bonding, we have developed an oxygen etching technique that eats away at these bonds so that microspheres can be ablated as individual targets.  We have also improved our model which describes how the ablating laser removes spheres from the silicon surface on which they have been deposited.  Our model now uses Monte Carlo techniques to give a more accurate representation of of the timing delay between the firing of the ablation laser and the high-power laser.  We have further improved the model?s sophistication such that it no longer has any free parameters and does a very good job of reproducing our time of flight data.  Finally, of the 12 Havey Mudd College undergraduates who have worked on this project (each one for multiple years) 7 are now pursuing PhDs in physics or physics-related fields.  The other 5 are either working in high-tech (e.g., for a quantum computer start up company) or are still at Harvey Mudd College.  Funding for this porject has provided opportunities to fill the STEM pipeline in the US.               Last Modified: 09/02/2017       Submitted by: Thomas D Donnelly]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
