<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>RET: in Engineering and Computer Science:Energizing Engineering Education (E3):  An RET site at the University of New Mexico investigating energy research  and engineering practice</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>04/15/2013</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>03/31/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>509543.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>509543</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07050000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>EEC</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Engineering Education and Centers</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Mary Poats</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This award provides funding for a three year continuing award to support a Research Experiences for Teachers (RET) in Engineering and Computer Science Site program at the University of New Mexico (UNM) entitled, "Energizing Engineering Education (E3): An RET site at the University of New Mexico investigating energy research and engineering practice", under the direction of Dr. Charles Fleddermann. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The E3 RET site program will advance pre-college education by creating enduring partnerships between New Mexico's under-represented minority (URM)-serving secondary schools, tribal community college and UNM faculty, students and staff.  A total of 40 teachers and community college faculty over three years from New Mexico (NM) Mathematics, Engineering, Science Achievement (MESA), Albuquerque Public Schools, Bernalillo Public Schools, Cibola County Schools and the Southwestern Indiana Polytechnic Institute (SIPI), will participate in a seven-week summer program where as part of interdisciplinary teams, they will plan, conduct, analyze and interpret potentially tranformative energy research at the materials, device and systems levels. Research topics include solar, wind and hydropower, biofuels, fuel cells, nuclear power, batteries, smart grid and solid-state lighting. The E3 program will be seated in three University Research Centers: the Center for Emerging Energy Technologies (CEET), the Center for Micro-Engineered Materials (CNEM), and the Center for High Technology Materials (CHTM).  In addition, faculty and graduate student mentors from four NSF Engineering Research Centers will be collaborating with RET participants.  RET participants will also collaborate with the College of Education co-PI, Dr. Vanessa Svihla, to develop activities and instructional approaches that model and transfer their RET experience to the classroom. Scheduled interactions throughout the academic year, continued UNM research in the teachers' classrooms, the E3 website and UNM outreach visits will sustain these RET partnerships.   &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;As one of the nation's first "minority-majority" states, New Mexico's students represent the future of the U.S. workforce. The UNM E3 RET site will work to attract these students to STEM majors and careers through the educational enrichment and mentoring of their teachers.  By focusing on energy research the E3 RET site will enlist teachers and students in the real-world quest for clean, sustainable energy, which will not only address the nation's critical need, but will brighten the economic outlook of New Mexico.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>04/08/2013</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>02/18/2015</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1301373</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Charles</FirstName>
<LastName>Fleddermann</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>B</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Charles B Fleddermann</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>cbf@unm.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5052775521</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000419835</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/08/2013</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Vanessa</FirstName>
<LastName>Svihla</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Vanessa Svihla</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>vsvihla@unm.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5052774186</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000608108</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/08/2013</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of New Mexico</Name>
<CityName>Albuquerque</CityName>
<ZipCode>871310001</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5052774186</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1700 Lomas Blvd. NE, Suite 2200</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New Mexico</StateName>
<StateCode>NM</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NM01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>868853094</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF NEW MEXICO, THE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>784121725</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of New Mexico]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>NM</StateCode>
<ZipCode>871310001</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New Mexico</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NM01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1359</Code>
<Text>RES EXP FOR TEACHERS(RET)-SITE</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EPSCoR Co-Funding</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>115E</Code>
<Text>RESEARCH EXP FOR TEACHERS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1359</Code>
<Text>RET SITE-Res Exp for Tchr Site</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9177</Code>
<Text>ELEMENTARY/SECONDARY EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0113</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0115</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2013~329783</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2015~179760</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The Energizing Engineering Education (E<sup>3</sup>) Research Experience for Teachers program at the University of New Mexico provided 29 New Mexican teachers with 51 lab experiences over five years. Counting only the years immediately following the teachers&rsquo; summer lab experiences, the program directly impacted 6,836 students, 75.8% of whom come from populations traditionally underrepresented in STEM and 61.3% of whom were economically disadvantaged.</p> <p>The actual number of students is much higher, because, as teachers noted in surveys, the E3 program had a lasting impact on the way they taught. Elementary, middle and high school teachers worked with faculty and graduate student mentors investigating solar cells, nuclear energy, light emitting diodes, batteries, and other energy-related topics in labs in the School of Engineering and Sandia National Laboratories. They attended energy and ethics-related seminars, went on field trips and participated in intensive workshops on project-based learning led by co-PI Vanessa Svihla.&nbsp;&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;To bring their experiences back to their students, teachers made videos of their lab mentors sharing stories about how they navigated challenges to become engineers. Teachers presented posters and Pecha Kucha presentations about their lab experiences. The teachers created 49 lessons and 62 activities to engage their students in engineering projects. Examples include designing and programming a hydroponic, LED-lit experimental greenhouse in their school, choosing the best configuration of solar panels for a community of tiny houses for Americorp Vista volunteers, and using real data to predict what happens to a high-altitude balloon during its flight and then checking predictions against actual on-board videos.&nbsp;&nbsp;(<a href="https://sites.google.com/site/unmret2014/">https://sites.google.com/site/unmret2014/</a>;&nbsp;<a href="https://www.teachengineering.org/curriculum/browse?q=1301373">https://www.teachengineering.org/curriculum/browse?q=1301373</a>).</p> <p>Three teachers won several awards, and several received a number of grants; all attribute these successes to the teaching strategies and information gained through the E<sup>3</sup>program.&nbsp;&nbsp;A few credit project-based learning with increasing their students' test scores compared to other students in their schools.&nbsp;&nbsp;All of the teachers were very glad to receive funds to buy badly needed supplies for their classrooms. Another benefit of the program was a richer relationship between UNM and the community. The School of Engineering Outreach Manager notified the RET teachers of professional development opportunities, campus tours, conducted outreach at the teachers&rsquo; schools, recruited UNM students to be science fair judges and recruited high school students for research internships and engineering camps.</p> <p>&nbsp;Evaluation of the E<sup>3</sup>program resulted in 4 publications: (1)&nbsp;Teachers completed a pre and post survey of their understanding of STEM practices. The teachers all learned about social norms and the realities of lab work and expressed concern over translating complex research experiences into classroom experiences. Those who participated for more than one summer increasingly agreed that their students should be responsible for coming up with their own questions and ways to investigate those questions&nbsp;(Livingston, Collins, Kooser, &amp; Svihla, 2014). This finding suggests that teachers may benefit from repeated participation in RET programs, especially in a time when many teachers feel deprofessionalized. This is echoed in results from the E<sup>3</sup>evaluation, in which a teacher explained,&nbsp;"My RET program has given me the skills, resources, and opportunities that I so DESPERATELY needed to head BACK into my classroom ready to change the world, one student at a time! It is a refreshing change to be valued and treated with such respect. I am not the same teacher I was when I walked onto the campus of UNM to begin my RET program three years ago" &nbsp;&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;(2) We tested an approach to supporting teachers to design technology-enhanced learning experiences. We first engaged the teachers in an hour-long 3D printing conceptual design challenge. When contrasted with a group who had not had this experience, our RET teachers designed much richer, more generative tasks for their own students&nbsp;(Svihla, Gines, Yang, Collins, &amp; Steinbrecher, 2015).</p> <p>(3) Students who viewed what they were learning as important to their futures and who reported having opportunities to draw their own conclusions were significantly more likely to express interest in becoming an engineer. Most students could describe normative differences between science and engineering, but very few envisioned an active role for themselves&nbsp;(Svihla, 2016).</p> <p>&nbsp;(4) Based on a metasynthesis of recent K12 engineering education research, there has been an increase in the overall rigor of research methods used and an increase in the use of qualitative methods, which provide critical information about how specific interventions support learning. Although many papers argue for diversification, very few studies tackle issues of equity and inclusion, suggesting an opportunity for RET programs that work with diverse populations (Svihla, Marshall, Liu, &amp; Winter, 2017).</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 05/15/2018<br>      Modified by: Charles&nbsp;B&nbsp;Fleddermann</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Images (<span id="selectedPhoto0">1</span> of <span class="totalNumber"></span>)           </div> <div class="galControls" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1301373/1301373_10240008_1525386996380_UNMRETPIandteachers2015--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1301373/1301373_10240008_1525386996380_UNMRETPIandteachers2015--rgov-800width.jpg" title="UNM RET PI and teachers 2015"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1301373/1301373_10240008_1525386996380_UNMRETPIandteachers2015--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="UNM RET PI and teachers 2015"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">PI Chuck Fleddermann (left) and teachers from the 3rd year of the Energizing Engineering Education Research Experiences for Teachers program at the University of New Mexico</div> <div class="imageCredit">Kimberly Delker, UNM</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Royalty-free (unrestricted use)</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Charles&nbsp;B&nbsp;Fleddermann</div> <div class="imageTitle">UNM RET PI and teachers 2015</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1301373/1301373_10240008_1525387119470_UNMRETteachersatCHTM--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1301373/1301373_10240008_1525387119470_UNMRETteachersatCHTM--rgov-800width.jpg" title="UNM RET teachers at CHTM"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1301373/1301373_10240008_1525387119470_UNMRETteachersatCHTM--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="UNM RET teachers at CHTM"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Several teachers from the Energizing Engineering Education Research Experiences for Teachers program at the University of New Mexico suit up for a cleanroom project at the Center for High Technology Materials.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Stefi Weisburd, UNM</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Royalty-free (unrestricted use)</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Charles&nbsp;B&nbsp;Fleddermann</div> <div class="imageTitle">UNM RET teachers at CHTM</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1301373/1301373_10240008_1525387990255_Mammoliroof--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1301373/1301373_10240008_1525387990255_Mammoliroof--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Teachers with Dr. Mammoli on the ME roof"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1301373/1301373_10240008_1525387990255_Mammoliroof--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Teachers with Dr. Mammoli on the ME roof"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Teachers learn about the solar thermal system on the roof of the UNM mechanical engineering building with Dr. Andrea Mammoli.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Stefi Weisburd, UNM</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Royalty-free (unrestricted use)</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Charles&nbsp;B&nbsp;Fleddermann</div> <div class="imageTitle">Teachers with Dr. Mammoli on the ME roof</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1301373/1301373_10240008_1525725903227_Screenshot2018-05-0713.52.47--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1301373/1301373_10240008_1525725903227_Screenshot2018-05-0713.52.47--rgov-800width.jpg" title="UNM RET Jodie Guillen"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1301373/1301373_10240008_1525725903227_Screenshot2018-05-0713.52.47--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="UNM RET Jodie Guillen"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">UNM RET Jodie Guillen taking a selfie with teachers at an energy workshop. She spoke about the RET and led teachers through her RET lesson plan. Five former RETs attended the DOE workshop, an example of the continued relationship between UNM and the teachers.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Stefi  Weisburd, UNM</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Charles&nbsp;B&nbsp;Fleddermann</div> <div class="imageTitle">UNM RET Jodie Guillen</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1301373/1301373_10240008_1526408938647_Screenshot2018-05-1512.21.53--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1301373/1301373_10240008_1526408938647_Screenshot2018-05-1512.21.53--rgov-800width.jpg" title="UNM RET teachers in labs"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1301373/1301373_10240008_1526408938647_Screenshot2018-05-1512.21.53--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="UNM RET teachers in labs"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Several UNM RET teachers in their labs at UNM with mentors and high school students.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Stefi Weisburd, UNM</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Royalty-free (unrestricted use)</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Charles&nbsp;B&nbsp;Fleddermann</div> <div class="imageTitle">UNM RET teachers in labs</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The Energizing Engineering Education (E3) Research Experience for Teachers program at the University of New Mexico provided 29 New Mexican teachers with 51 lab experiences over five years. Counting only the years immediately following the teachers? summer lab experiences, the program directly impacted 6,836 students, 75.8% of whom come from populations traditionally underrepresented in STEM and 61.3% of whom were economically disadvantaged.  The actual number of students is much higher, because, as teachers noted in surveys, the E3 program had a lasting impact on the way they taught. Elementary, middle and high school teachers worked with faculty and graduate student mentors investigating solar cells, nuclear energy, light emitting diodes, batteries, and other energy-related topics in labs in the School of Engineering and Sandia National Laboratories. They attended energy and ethics-related seminars, went on field trips and participated in intensive workshops on project-based learning led by co-PI Vanessa Svihla.     To bring their experiences back to their students, teachers made videos of their lab mentors sharing stories about how they navigated challenges to become engineers. Teachers presented posters and Pecha Kucha presentations about their lab experiences. The teachers created 49 lessons and 62 activities to engage their students in engineering projects. Examples include designing and programming a hydroponic, LED-lit experimental greenhouse in their school, choosing the best configuration of solar panels for a community of tiny houses for Americorp Vista volunteers, and using real data to predict what happens to a high-altitude balloon during its flight and then checking predictions against actual on-board videos.  (https://sites.google.com/site/unmret2014/; https://www.teachengineering.org/curriculum/browse?q=1301373).  Three teachers won several awards, and several received a number of grants; all attribute these successes to the teaching strategies and information gained through the E3program.  A few credit project-based learning with increasing their students' test scores compared to other students in their schools.  All of the teachers were very glad to receive funds to buy badly needed supplies for their classrooms. Another benefit of the program was a richer relationship between UNM and the community. The School of Engineering Outreach Manager notified the RET teachers of professional development opportunities, campus tours, conducted outreach at the teachers? schools, recruited UNM students to be science fair judges and recruited high school students for research internships and engineering camps.   Evaluation of the E3program resulted in 4 publications: (1) Teachers completed a pre and post survey of their understanding of STEM practices. The teachers all learned about social norms and the realities of lab work and expressed concern over translating complex research experiences into classroom experiences. Those who participated for more than one summer increasingly agreed that their students should be responsible for coming up with their own questions and ways to investigate those questions (Livingston, Collins, Kooser, &amp; Svihla, 2014). This finding suggests that teachers may benefit from repeated participation in RET programs, especially in a time when many teachers feel deprofessionalized. This is echoed in results from the E3evaluation, in which a teacher explained, "My RET program has given me the skills, resources, and opportunities that I so DESPERATELY needed to head BACK into my classroom ready to change the world, one student at a time! It is a refreshing change to be valued and treated with such respect. I am not the same teacher I was when I walked onto the campus of UNM to begin my RET program three years ago"      (2) We tested an approach to supporting teachers to design technology-enhanced learning experiences. We first engaged the teachers in an hour-long 3D printing conceptual design challenge. When contrasted with a group who had not had this experience, our RET teachers designed much richer, more generative tasks for their own students (Svihla, Gines, Yang, Collins, &amp; Steinbrecher, 2015).  (3) Students who viewed what they were learning as important to their futures and who reported having opportunities to draw their own conclusions were significantly more likely to express interest in becoming an engineer. Most students could describe normative differences between science and engineering, but very few envisioned an active role for themselves (Svihla, 2016).   (4) Based on a metasynthesis of recent K12 engineering education research, there has been an increase in the overall rigor of research methods used and an increase in the use of qualitative methods, which provide critical information about how specific interventions support learning. Although many papers argue for diversification, very few studies tackle issues of equity and inclusion, suggesting an opportunity for RET programs that work with diverse populations (Svihla, Marshall, Liu, &amp; Winter, 2017).          Last Modified: 05/15/2018       Submitted by: Charles B Fleddermann]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
