<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Collaborative Research: Tunable Nanoscale Ferroelectric Photonic Crystals: Materials and Fabrication, Photonic Crystal Structures, and Devices</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2013</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>309999.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>317999</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07010000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>ECCS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Electrical, Commun &amp; Cyber Sys</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Mahmoud Fallahi</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Objective: This program uses new advances in ultrathin ferroelectric-film fabrication, nano-poling, and simulation methods for nonlinear-optical devices, to realize new tunable photonic-crystal devices.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Intellectual Merit: This photonics program will investigate a new class of tunable second-order optical susceptibility nano-photonic device, by nano-structuring ferroelectric thin-film photonic crystals to tailor their optical response. The main challenges are ultrahigh-resolution poling, electrode-structure design, and thin-film device implementation. Key elements are nano-fabrication methods, design and testing of the tunable crystals, and two model-device fabrications. Its transformative aspect arises from its nanometer scale, providing unprecedented control of phase matching due to light confinement.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Broader Impacts: This program involves photonic devices, an area with broad impact for sensors in medical and biological science, data transmission and processing, and metrology. The research will be integrated into the education mission of Columbia and the University at Albany to foster an interdisciplinary examination of artificial nonlinear metamaterials and to enable the two groups with a strong history of interactions to collaborate. This work will involve students interaction and travel to their partner universities. The program will recruit diverse student collaborators. Recruitment will be done via five yearly outreach talks to undergrads at Columbia and Albany and participation in Undergraduate Research Opportunities Program at Columbia. The project will enable students to collaborate with the Nanocenter at Brookhaven National Laboratory, which one of the PIs was the founding director, and with the Ion-Beam Facility at Albany. This program involves overseas research collaboration with University of Bonn (Soergel) and University College London (Panoiu).&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project is jointly funded by the Electronics, Photonics, and Magnetic Devices Program (EPMD) in the Division of Electrical, Communications and Cyber Systems (ECCS) and by the Electronic and Photonic Materials Program (EPM) in the Division of Materials Research (DMR).</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/13/2013</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/07/2015</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1302488</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Richard</FirstName>
<LastName>Osgood</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>M</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME>Jr.</PI_SUFX_NAME>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Richard M Osgood</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>osgood@columbia.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2128544462</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000148502</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/13/2013</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Columbia University</Name>
<CityName>NEW YORK</CityName>
<ZipCode>100276902</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2128546851</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>2960 Broadway</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>10</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NY10</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>049179401</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>TRUSTEES OF COLUMBIA UNIVERSITY IN THE CITY OF NEW YORK, THE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>049179401</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Columbia University]]></Name>
<CityName>New York</CityName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<ZipCode>100276623</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[500 West 120th Street, 1300 Mudd]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>10</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NY10</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1253</Code>
<Text>OFFICE OF MULTIDISCIPLINARY AC</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1517</Code>
<Text>EPMD-ElectrnPhoton&amp;MagnDevices</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1775</Code>
<Text>ELECTRONIC/PHOTONIC MATERIALS</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>094E</Code>
<Text>Optoelectronic devices</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>095E</Code>
<Text>Photonic integration</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7237</Code>
<Text>NANO NON-SOLIC SCI &amp; ENG AWD</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9251</Code>
<Text>REU SUPP-Res Exp for Ugrd Supp</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0113</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0115</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2013~309999</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2015~8000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p class="western"><span style="color: #000000;"><span style="font-family: &quot;Times New Roman&quot;, serif;"><span>This project investigated the materials and device issues in a class of tunable &chi;</span></span></span><span style="color: #000000;"><sup><span style="font-family: &quot;Times New Roman&quot;, serif;"><span>(2)</span></span></sup></span><span style="color: #000000;"><span style="font-family: &quot;Times New Roman&quot;, serif;"><span> nanophotonic devices, based on a new form of single-crystal ferroelectric materials. These materials are used in many types of voltage-controlled integrated optical devices including those for the modulation and frequency change of an input optical beam. These devices will have lower electrical power and be spatially efficient. To achieve these devices requires ultrahigh resolution in patterning the crystal domains. In particular, our research has focussed on the development of the materials technologies and the advancement in nanomaterials patterning and device realization.  Extensive collaborations with domestic and international groups in universities and national labs have been demonstrated, thus enhancing the education of PhD, MS, and undergraduate students.</span></span></span><span style="color: #000000;"><span style="font-family: &quot;Times New Roman&quot;, serif;"><span><em> </em></span></span></span></p> <p class="western"><span style="font-family: &quot;Times New Roman&quot;, serif;"><span> We have conducted a series of in-depth experiments to analyze the effects of sample thickness, surface character, and ion implantation on poling quality. For example, we have examined the effect of sample thickness on poling voltage and coercive field. We have demonstrated a linear relationship between poling voltage and sample thickness (down to 25 &mu;m). We have also conducted a thorough study of the relationship between poled domain width and sample thickness using cross-sectional optical microscopy and scanning electron microscopy (SEM). We have found that domain broadening decreases with decreasing thickness by a factor of ~8 nm/&mu;m. We also observed that the sample Z- cut surface shows consistently wider domain widths than the Z+ surface. Currently, we are exploring the materials physics of such surface dependence of domain width, including the preferential nucleation sites and domain-wall propagation activity.</span></span></p> <p><span style="font-family: &quot;Times New Roman&quot;, serif;"><span> In our work, we have also used the key materials probes of micro-Raman spectroscopy, atomic force microscopy (AFM), and scanning electron microscopy (SEM) to verify the effects of surface conditions on the poling activity. It was found that the existence of extrinsic micro defects on the sample surface can modify the crystallinity, further inhibiting the initiation of the poling activity. Using Micro-Raman spectroscopy, we have also demonstrated a thickness-dependent Raman intensity contrast between poled and unpoled domains for 7 prominent LNO Raman modes.</span></span></p> <p class="western"><span style="font-family: &quot;Times New Roman&quot;, serif;"><span> Finally, we have conducted a parallel study using a novel ion-patterning method to achieve high-resolution poling. Our results show that the distributions of the implanted ions significantly affect the poling kinetics, showing the promise of pattern irradiation as an alternative for producing well controlled nanometric ferroelectric domains. </span></span><span style="color: #000000;"><span style="font-family: &quot;Times New Roman&quot;, serif;"><span>We </span></span></span><span style="color: #000000;"><span style="font-family: &quot;Times New Roman&quot;, serif;"><span>demonstrated</span></span></span><span style="color: #000000;"><span style="font-family: &quot;Times New Roman&quot;, serif;"><span> excellent etch quality and are now exploring (using Raman microscopy) the extent if any of lattice damage. </span></span></span></p> <p class="western"><span style="color: #00000a;"><span style="font-family: &quot;Times New Roman&quot;, serif;"><span> Dissemination of the results of this program to the public has been carried out via major publications and talks at high profile optical conferences. In addition, a key aspect of this program was to emphasize the learning and training which could be had involvement with other labs and in fact we had </span></span></span><span style="color: #00000a;"><span style="font-family: &quot;Times New Roman&quot;, serif;"><span>extensive collaborations and interactions between students and research scientists from Columbia, SUNY Albany, Pacific Northwest National Laboratory (PNNL), Brookhaven National Laboratory (BNL), and the United State Military Academy (USMA) at West Point. </span></span></span><span style="font-family: &quot;Times New Roman&quot;, serif;"><span>Finally we have recently initiated several collaborations, which are based on the achievements of our materials capabilities developed on this program. Thus we have first used our Raman methods to observed l</span></span><span style="color: #000000;"><span style="font-family: &quot;Times New Roman&quot;, serif;"><span>arge magneto-optic enhancement in ultra-thin liquid-phase-epitaxy iron garnet films. This work was a collaborative project with Prof Miguel Levy at Michigan Tech in Holton. MI. Second, </span></span></span><span style="font-family: &quot;Times New Roman&quot;, serif;"><span>we have initiated a collaboration with the Kymissis Group at Columbia, and have begun to fabricate lithium niobate thin-film bulk acoustic wave resonators (FBARs) for radio frequency (RF) filtering, specifically multi-frequency and wideband filtering.</span></span></p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 09/29/2016<br>      Modified by: Richard&nbsp;M&nbsp;Osgood</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[This project investigated the materials and device issues in a class of tunable &chi;(2) nanophotonic devices, based on a new form of single-crystal ferroelectric materials. These materials are used in many types of voltage-controlled integrated optical devices including those for the modulation and frequency change of an input optical beam. These devices will have lower electrical power and be spatially efficient. To achieve these devices requires ultrahigh resolution in patterning the crystal domains. In particular, our research has focussed on the development of the materials technologies and the advancement in nanomaterials patterning and device realization.  Extensive collaborations with domestic and international groups in universities and national labs have been demonstrated, thus enhancing the education of PhD, MS, and undergraduate students.   We have conducted a series of in-depth experiments to analyze the effects of sample thickness, surface character, and ion implantation on poling quality. For example, we have examined the effect of sample thickness on poling voltage and coercive field. We have demonstrated a linear relationship between poling voltage and sample thickness (down to 25 &mu;m). We have also conducted a thorough study of the relationship between poled domain width and sample thickness using cross-sectional optical microscopy and scanning electron microscopy (SEM). We have found that domain broadening decreases with decreasing thickness by a factor of ~8 nm/&mu;m. We also observed that the sample Z- cut surface shows consistently wider domain widths than the Z+ surface. Currently, we are exploring the materials physics of such surface dependence of domain width, including the preferential nucleation sites and domain-wall propagation activity.   In our work, we have also used the key materials probes of micro-Raman spectroscopy, atomic force microscopy (AFM), and scanning electron microscopy (SEM) to verify the effects of surface conditions on the poling activity. It was found that the existence of extrinsic micro defects on the sample surface can modify the crystallinity, further inhibiting the initiation of the poling activity. Using Micro-Raman spectroscopy, we have also demonstrated a thickness-dependent Raman intensity contrast between poled and unpoled domains for 7 prominent LNO Raman modes.  Finally, we have conducted a parallel study using a novel ion-patterning method to achieve high-resolution poling. Our results show that the distributions of the implanted ions significantly affect the poling kinetics, showing the promise of pattern irradiation as an alternative for producing well controlled nanometric ferroelectric domains. We demonstrated excellent etch quality and are now exploring (using Raman microscopy) the extent if any of lattice damage.   Dissemination of the results of this program to the public has been carried out via major publications and talks at high profile optical conferences. In addition, a key aspect of this program was to emphasize the learning and training which could be had involvement with other labs and in fact we had extensive collaborations and interactions between students and research scientists from Columbia, SUNY Albany, Pacific Northwest National Laboratory (PNNL), Brookhaven National Laboratory (BNL), and the United State Military Academy (USMA) at West Point. Finally we have recently initiated several collaborations, which are based on the achievements of our materials capabilities developed on this program. Thus we have first used our Raman methods to observed large magneto-optic enhancement in ultra-thin liquid-phase-epitaxy iron garnet films. This work was a collaborative project with Prof Miguel Levy at Michigan Tech in Holton. MI. Second, we have initiated a collaboration with the Kymissis Group at Columbia, and have begun to fabricate lithium niobate thin-film bulk acoustic wave resonators (FBARs) for radio frequency (RF) filtering, specifically multi-frequency and wideband filtering.          Last Modified: 09/29/2016       Submitted by: Richard M Osgood]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
