<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>RI: Medium: Collaborative Research: Decision-Making on Uncertain Spatial-Temporal Fields: Modeling, Planning and Control with Applications to Adaptive Sampling</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>06/01/2013</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>199117.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>199117</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>05020000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>CSE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>IIS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Information &amp; Intelligent Systems</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Reid Simmons</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Inland bodies of freshwater are a resource that is critical for the Nation's health and safety.  This project is developing a new spatio-temporal field representation suitable for modeling, planning and control under uncertainty in order to improve monitoring of such water systems. The project's focus is on a reconfigurable aquatic sensor-actuator network designed to capture data from coupled physical, chemical, and biological processes that occur across space and time-scales.  The key advantages of this sensor-actuator network in its application to this domain include synoptic volume coverage, adaptive sampling, flexible control and robustness to component failure.  The research objective is to build models of dynamic processes for which high resolution sampling is necessary at special locations. Toward this end, this project is contributing new methods, data-structures, algorithms, and implementations validated by field testing a heterogeneous system consisting of stationary and mobile (robotic) underwater node. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project provides unique interdisciplinary opportunities for education of both graduate and undergraduate students via new course work that blends projects and research topics directly into courses and newly developed seminars. It provides a multi-disciplinary experience for students while developing their engineering skills. Relevant components of computer science, computer engineering, and mechanical engineering are integrated together by using the project's aquatic platform and experimental scenarios as a focal point. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The project advances the state-of-the-art for such systems because it integrates low-level dynamic processes with high-level planning and distributed optimization. The research represents a change in the scale of robotic aquatic sampling away from immense bodies of water in oceanographic research, toward bodies of water that have a more immediate affect on our well-being as they are sources and stores of drinking water. The impact of datasets which lead to better understanding of managed and natural inlets, differing topography including dam walls and man-made structures, regions of turbulence, and seasonal algal growth are immense.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/10/2013</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/13/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.070</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1302302</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Srikanth</FirstName>
<LastName>Saripalli</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Srikanth Saripalli</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>ssaripalli@tamu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>4802344395</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000537575</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/10/2013</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Arizona State University</Name>
<CityName>TEMPE</CityName>
<ZipCode>852816011</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>4809655479</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>ORSPA</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[660 South Mill Avenue, Suite 310]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Arizona</StateName>
<StateCode>AZ</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>09</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>AZ09</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>943360412</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>ARIZONA STATE UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>806345658</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Arizona State University]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>AZ</StateCode>
<ZipCode>852816011</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Arizona</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>09</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>AZ09</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7495</Code>
<Text>Robust Intelligence</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7495</Code>
<Text>ROBUST INTELLIGENCE</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7924</Code>
<Text>MEDIUM PROJECT</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0113</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0114</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0115</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0116</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2013~64886</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~59261</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2015~39833</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2016~35137</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Accurate monitoring of inland bodies such as rivers, lakes is essential for determing the viability of using them for everyday purposes. In this project, we have been able to demonstrate adaptive sampling techniques that can be used to determine the undelying spatio-temporal fields present in these water bodies (for example the variation of &nbsp;pH in a lake at different times of the year). We used both commerically off the self underwater vehicles (AUVs) as well as custom built Remotely Operated Vehicles (ROVs) to evaluate emprically sampling strategies in various lakes around Phoenix.&nbsp;</p> <p><span>A critical problem in planning sampling paths for autonomous underwater vehicles (AUVs) is correctly balancing two issues. First, obtaining an accurate scalar field estimation and second, efficiently utilizing the stored energy capacity of the sampling vehicle. &nbsp;Our goal was to experimentally evaluate various sampling path strategies based on how well each strategy estimates scalar fields at various sampling densities, and how much relative energy consumption each sampling strategy takes. &nbsp;We have experimentally demonstrated that a systematic spiral sampling path strategy is optimal for high-variance scalar fields for all sampling densities and low-variance scalar fields when sampling is sparse. In addition, our experiments show that the random spiral sampling path strategy is found to be optimal for low-variance scalar fields when sampling is dense.</span></p> <p><span>Broader Impacts: By demonstrating adaptive sampling strategies and the effectiveness of them (depending on what one can measure) we believe that water/city planner's can make effective decisions regarding inland water bodies that are used for drinking water. For example how does one determine the change in pH of a lake over a year..</span></p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 04/07/2018<br>      Modified by: Srikanth&nbsp;Saripalli</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Image         </div> <div class="galControls onePhoto" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation onePhoto" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1302302/1302302_10250987_1523156968326_iver--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1302302/1302302_10250987_1523156968326_iver--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Autonomous Underwater Vehicle"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1302302/1302302_10250987_1523156968326_iver--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Autonomous Underwater Vehicle"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">AUV used for Adaptive Sampling</div> <div class="imageCredit">Srikanth Saripalli</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Creative Commons</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Srikanth&nbsp;Saripalli</div> <div class="imageTitle">Autonomous Underwater Vehicle</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Accurate monitoring of inland bodies such as rivers, lakes is essential for determing the viability of using them for everyday purposes. In this project, we have been able to demonstrate adaptive sampling techniques that can be used to determine the undelying spatio-temporal fields present in these water bodies (for example the variation of  pH in a lake at different times of the year). We used both commerically off the self underwater vehicles (AUVs) as well as custom built Remotely Operated Vehicles (ROVs) to evaluate emprically sampling strategies in various lakes around Phoenix.   A critical problem in planning sampling paths for autonomous underwater vehicles (AUVs) is correctly balancing two issues. First, obtaining an accurate scalar field estimation and second, efficiently utilizing the stored energy capacity of the sampling vehicle.  Our goal was to experimentally evaluate various sampling path strategies based on how well each strategy estimates scalar fields at various sampling densities, and how much relative energy consumption each sampling strategy takes.  We have experimentally demonstrated that a systematic spiral sampling path strategy is optimal for high-variance scalar fields for all sampling densities and low-variance scalar fields when sampling is sparse. In addition, our experiments show that the random spiral sampling path strategy is found to be optimal for low-variance scalar fields when sampling is dense.  Broader Impacts: By demonstrating adaptive sampling strategies and the effectiveness of them (depending on what one can measure) we believe that water/city planner's can make effective decisions regarding inland water bodies that are used for drinking water. For example how does one determine the change in pH of a lake over a year..             Last Modified: 04/07/2018       Submitted by: Srikanth Saripalli]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
