<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Capacity Building for Information Assurance and Cyber Security</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2014</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>322410.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>322410</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>11010000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>EHR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DGE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Graduate Education</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Victor Piotrowski</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>vpiotrow@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032925141</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This capacity building project seeks to foster high quality education and research in Cybersecurity. The University of South Alabama (USA) has been designated as a Center of Academic Excellence in Information Assurance (IA) Education by the National Security Agency and is an active participants in the CyberCorps®: Scholarship for Service (SFS) program. USA currently offers a full range of Cybersecurity courses at the graduate and undergraduate level. This project aims to increase the number of students interested in pursuing cybersecurity education, to provide key resource to further ongoing Cybersecurity research, and to increase the expertise of faculty and students. The project is providing broader impact and dissemination through local colloquia and research groups on campus and through two regional workshops that brings faculty from up to ten local community and junior colleges, fostering development of Cybersecurity focus throughout the region. The NSF's CyberCorps® SFS program funds projects that address cybersecurity education and workforce development. The Scholarship Track provides funding to award scholarships to students in cybersecurity. In return for their scholarships, recipients will work after graduation for a Federal, State, Local, or Tribal Government organization in a position related to cybersecurity for a period equal to the length of the scholarship. The Capacity Track seeks innovative proposals leading to an increase in the ability of the United States higher education enterprise to produce cybersecurity professionals. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The project will expand the current cybersecurity program by three key activities: 1) developing a virtual lab facility that supports hands-on Cybersecurity curriculum development for ten cybersecurity courses and will provide computational resources for ten faculty conducting Cybersecurity research; 2) implementing a professional development program for faculty to remain current in Cybersecurity research advancements; and 3) sponsoring K-12 STEM field trips and summer camps that brings high school junior and seniors from local partner schools to the USA campus for cybersecurity focused field trips.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/05/2014</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>04/20/2017</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.076</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1303384</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Jeffrey</FirstName>
<LastName>McDonald</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>T</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Jeffrey T McDonald</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>jtmcdonald@southalabama.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2514606111</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000605183</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/05/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Todd</FirstName>
<LastName>Andel</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>R</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Todd R Andel</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>tandel@southalabama.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2514606701</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000605224</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/05/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Harvey</FirstName>
<LastName>Barnett</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>L</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME>Jr.</PI_SUFX_NAME>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Harvey L Barnett</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>hlbarnett@southalabama.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2514606111</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000605225</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/05/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Rebecca</FirstName>
<LastName>Bace</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>G</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Rebecca G Bace</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>Infomom@sprintmail.com</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2514606333</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000619182</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/05/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate>04/20/2017</EndDate>
<RoleCode>Former Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>William</FirstName>
<LastName>Glisson</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>B</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>William B Glisson</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>glisson@shsu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>9362941579</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000671420</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/20/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of South Alabama</Name>
<CityName>Mobile</CityName>
<ZipCode>366880002</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2514606333</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>307 University Boulevard</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Alabama</StateName>
<StateCode>AL</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>AL01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>172750234</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF SOUTH ALABAMA</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>172750234</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[USA - School of Computing]]></Name>
<CityName>Mobile</CityName>
<StateCode>AL</StateCode>
<ZipCode>366880002</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[2101 Shelby Hall]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Alabama</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>AL01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1668</Code>
<Text>CYBERCORPS: SCHLAR FOR SER</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7254</Code>
<Text>CYBER SECURITY ACT PROPOSALS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7434</Code>
<Text>CNCI</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9178</Code>
<Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9179</Code>
<Text>GRADUATE INVOLVEMENT</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>SMET</Code>
<Text>SCIENCE, MATH, ENG &amp; TECH EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0414</Code>
<Name>NSF Education &amp; Human Resource</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040106</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~322410</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>This capacity building grant has extended the capacity for information assurance (IA) and cybersecurity research, education, and outreach at the University of South Alabama (USA) within its School of Computing (SoC) and Center for Forensics, Information Technology, Security (CFITS). It has strengthened existing IA-focused educational programs and fostered collaborative outreach in the community among various stakeholders in the southeast region. The project achieved three major goals related to building IA capacity at USA: 1) development of a K-12 IA awareness program and GenCyber outreach activity, 2) support for a faculty/student IA professional development program, and 3) development of a virtual IA lab research facility. The project has resulted in increasing the number of students interested in pursuing cybersecurity education, provided key resources to further ongoing Cybersecurity research, and increased the expertise of faculty and students pursuing cybersecurity education. Achievement of its goals have contributed to the educational mission and outcomes of the School of Computing at USA, which offers 4 undergraduate degree programs, 2 master's program specializations, and a doctoral degree program.</p> <p>In terms of the K-12 IA awareness program, capacity building resulted in over ten funded field trips from local partner schools that are part of the CFITS Partner School program and support for GenCyber summer camps that are now fully supported by the National Security Agency. USA developed virtual-lab hands-on-learning-activities (HOLLAs) geared toward 10-12th grade students with grant funds allowing for travel costs to be paid to partner schools that participated in the outreach activities. HOLLA units developed during the grant period supported in-school field trips of 20-30 students from local partner schools such as Davidson High School, a Title I CFITS partner school, and the Alabama School of Math and Science (ASMS), a statewide magnet school located in Mobile, AL. HOLLA material targeted approximately 60 minute long presentations that are now part of a general program of IA awareness reaching high school juniors and seniors. Investigators developed security related HOLLAs on topics including PKI, steganography, cyber ethics, digital logic, forensics, and cryptography. Over 170 students and 15 high school teachers attended funded HOLLA events over the course of the grant period. Investigators also leveraged the capacity grant to spearhead USA's participation in the NSA GenCyber camp program in 2015 which resulted in three succesfully hosted camps from 2015-2017. As a result, 152 students that were incoming 9th graders of the Engineering Pathways Integrated Curriculum (EPIC) program at a local Title I high school participated in the USA GenCyber program. The camps provided 5 days of cyber security related activities that included lecture, hands-on projects, group activities, team-based games, and realworld scenario exercises. Each camp day covered a breadth of subject matter, including programming, secure coding, forensics, cryptography, robotics, and cyber physical systems. Demographics of the campers included 47% female, 37% African-American, 10% Asian, and 7% Hispanic.</p> <p>The professional development program enhanced IA research and education activities within SoC by supporting travel to present research and participate in 18 various cybersecurity venues such as Blackhat, DEF CON, MALCON, NII Shonan Seminars, Dagstuhl Seminar, ACSAC, and HOST. The development program targeted promotion of selected strategic research domains within SoC including cyber physical systems, systems protection and exploitation, forensics, reverse engineering, and cyber competitions: these venues allowed 5 doctoral students and 4 IA faculty to dissemenate research and expand their current research knowledge through interaction at key cyber IA event and direct publication of 11 peer-reviewed conference and workshop papers. Dissemination occurred after events through monthly guest lectures in the CFITS Colloquium, which brings together over 60 faculty, students, and industry professionals to hear IA-relevant presentations, as well as presentations in two different research groups within SoC. Further dissemination involved curriculum integration in 3 courses in the SoC curriculum using lessons learned and enhanced laboratory activities that include courses in Secure Software Engineering, Surreptitious Software, and Network Security. In addition, the capacity grant funded six different undergraduate and graduate assistants in conducting cybersecurity research during the execution, resulting in follow on Master's and Doctoral research work for each participant.</p> <p>Finally, the capacity grant provided virtual lab equipment to support effective and scalable research/education facilities for faculty and students at USA.&nbsp; The server environment provided direct support for five gradate student research projects, learning activities for K-12 STEM outreach, and support for IA curriculum and hands-on activities. As an enduring capability, the system provides the ability to target pre-HOLLA K-12 instruction topic areas such as number systems, simple ciphers, and digital logic for students on off-site campus locations in the southeast region. Custom virtual machines developed through the grant period help provide easy access to tools, OS, applications, and supporting learning material for the CFITS Partner School program.&nbsp; In addition, the virtual facilities provide support for training in cyber competitions for over 50 members of USA's DayZero cyber competition student organization.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 11/26/2017<br>      Modified by: Jeffrey&nbsp;T&nbsp;Mcdonald</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Image         </div> <div class="galControls onePhoto" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation onePhoto" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1303384/1303384_10328866_1511209605326_USAVirtualLab--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1303384/1303384_10328866_1511209605326_USAVirtualLab--rgov-800width.jpg" title="USA IA/Cybersecurity Virtual Lab Facilities"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1303384/1303384_10328866_1511209605326_USAVirtualLab--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="USA IA/Cybersecurity Virtual Lab Facilities"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">The USA virtual lab facility provides support for IA curriculum outreach activities with K-12 partner schools and support for cybersecurity curriculum and research within the School of Computing.</div> <div class="imageCredit">J.T. McDonald</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Jeffrey&nbsp;T&nbsp;Mcdonald</div> <div class="imageTitle">USA IA/Cybersecurity Virtual Lab Facilities</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ This capacity building grant has extended the capacity for information assurance (IA) and cybersecurity research, education, and outreach at the University of South Alabama (USA) within its School of Computing (SoC) and Center for Forensics, Information Technology, Security (CFITS). It has strengthened existing IA-focused educational programs and fostered collaborative outreach in the community among various stakeholders in the southeast region. The project achieved three major goals related to building IA capacity at USA: 1) development of a K-12 IA awareness program and GenCyber outreach activity, 2) support for a faculty/student IA professional development program, and 3) development of a virtual IA lab research facility. The project has resulted in increasing the number of students interested in pursuing cybersecurity education, provided key resources to further ongoing Cybersecurity research, and increased the expertise of faculty and students pursuing cybersecurity education. Achievement of its goals have contributed to the educational mission and outcomes of the School of Computing at USA, which offers 4 undergraduate degree programs, 2 master's program specializations, and a doctoral degree program.  In terms of the K-12 IA awareness program, capacity building resulted in over ten funded field trips from local partner schools that are part of the CFITS Partner School program and support for GenCyber summer camps that are now fully supported by the National Security Agency. USA developed virtual-lab hands-on-learning-activities (HOLLAs) geared toward 10-12th grade students with grant funds allowing for travel costs to be paid to partner schools that participated in the outreach activities. HOLLA units developed during the grant period supported in-school field trips of 20-30 students from local partner schools such as Davidson High School, a Title I CFITS partner school, and the Alabama School of Math and Science (ASMS), a statewide magnet school located in Mobile, AL. HOLLA material targeted approximately 60 minute long presentations that are now part of a general program of IA awareness reaching high school juniors and seniors. Investigators developed security related HOLLAs on topics including PKI, steganography, cyber ethics, digital logic, forensics, and cryptography. Over 170 students and 15 high school teachers attended funded HOLLA events over the course of the grant period. Investigators also leveraged the capacity grant to spearhead USA's participation in the NSA GenCyber camp program in 2015 which resulted in three succesfully hosted camps from 2015-2017. As a result, 152 students that were incoming 9th graders of the Engineering Pathways Integrated Curriculum (EPIC) program at a local Title I high school participated in the USA GenCyber program. The camps provided 5 days of cyber security related activities that included lecture, hands-on projects, group activities, team-based games, and realworld scenario exercises. Each camp day covered a breadth of subject matter, including programming, secure coding, forensics, cryptography, robotics, and cyber physical systems. Demographics of the campers included 47% female, 37% African-American, 10% Asian, and 7% Hispanic.  The professional development program enhanced IA research and education activities within SoC by supporting travel to present research and participate in 18 various cybersecurity venues such as Blackhat, DEF CON, MALCON, NII Shonan Seminars, Dagstuhl Seminar, ACSAC, and HOST. The development program targeted promotion of selected strategic research domains within SoC including cyber physical systems, systems protection and exploitation, forensics, reverse engineering, and cyber competitions: these venues allowed 5 doctoral students and 4 IA faculty to dissemenate research and expand their current research knowledge through interaction at key cyber IA event and direct publication of 11 peer-reviewed conference and workshop papers. Dissemination occurred after events through monthly guest lectures in the CFITS Colloquium, which brings together over 60 faculty, students, and industry professionals to hear IA-relevant presentations, as well as presentations in two different research groups within SoC. Further dissemination involved curriculum integration in 3 courses in the SoC curriculum using lessons learned and enhanced laboratory activities that include courses in Secure Software Engineering, Surreptitious Software, and Network Security. In addition, the capacity grant funded six different undergraduate and graduate assistants in conducting cybersecurity research during the execution, resulting in follow on Master's and Doctoral research work for each participant.  Finally, the capacity grant provided virtual lab equipment to support effective and scalable research/education facilities for faculty and students at USA.  The server environment provided direct support for five gradate student research projects, learning activities for K-12 STEM outreach, and support for IA curriculum and hands-on activities. As an enduring capability, the system provides the ability to target pre-HOLLA K-12 instruction topic areas such as number systems, simple ciphers, and digital logic for students on off-site campus locations in the southeast region. Custom virtual machines developed through the grant period help provide easy access to tools, OS, applications, and supporting learning material for the CFITS Partner School program.  In addition, the virtual facilities provide support for training in cyber competitions for over 50 members of USA's DayZero cyber competition student organization.       Last Modified: 11/26/2017       Submitted by: Jeffrey T Mcdonald]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
