<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>International Collaboration in Chemistry: Measuring the effects of surfactants on cloud microphysics</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2013</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>502000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>502000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03090000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CHE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Chemistry</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Anne-Marie Schmoltner</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>aschmolt@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924716</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The Environmental Chemical Sciences Program supports Professor Ronald C. Cohen of the University of California, Berkeley, in collaboration with the research group of Barbara Noziere of the University of Lyon, France to advance understanding of cloud droplets by studying whether surfactants affect droplet growth rates. In the Earth's atmosphere, cloud droplets are formed exclusively by the condensation of water vapor onto micron-size aerosol particles. The research will develop new ideas and approaches to understanding cloud droplet growth especially with respect to the key question of how mixtures of organic chemicals in aerosol and on water droplets affect droplet growth rates. In Lyon, the focus of the research will be on the characterization of surfactants found in ambient aerosol. At Berkeley the focus will be on determining parameters that affect droplet growth and evaporation and understanding how model surfactants as well as the surfactants extracted from ambient aerosol by the Lyon group affect the evaporation and growth. To accomplish these goals, novel analytical and spectroscopic methods will be developed, including optical traps, fluorescence anisotropy decay, Raman thermometry and cavity enhanced Raman scattering, to investigate the effect of atmospheric surfactants on cloud droplet formation and growth.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project will develop and apply the next generation of laboratory experiments to study the fundamental chemistry of cloud droplet growth. In the Earth's atmosphere, cloud droplets are formed exclusively by the condensation of water vapor onto micron-size aerosol particles.  The Cohen group at Berkeley and the Noziere group at Lyon have separately pioneered new approaches to studying droplet growth over the last few years. Fusion of the experimental skills and knowledge of the two teams, a goal of this project, is expected to lead to unique advances in our understanding of the chemical link between aerosol and clouds, especially at the crucial step of cloud droplet growth. This project is expected to result in significant advances in our understanding of the scientific basis for policy decisions regarding air quality and climate. The results will be communicated both in the scientific literature, to a more general audience through various media and directly to regulators and policy makers in California with whom the PI meets informally at meetings aimed at planning for climate change in the local region</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/29/2013</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/29/2013</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1303763</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Ronald</FirstName>
<LastName>Cohen</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>C</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Ronald C Cohen</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>rccohen@berkeley.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5106422735</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000184195</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/29/2013</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of California-Berkeley</Name>
<CityName>BERKELEY</CityName>
<ZipCode>947101749</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5106433891</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>Sponsored Projects Office</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[1608 Fourth Street, Suite 220]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>13</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CA13</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>124726725</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>REGENTS OF THE UNIVERSITY OF CALIFORNIA, THE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>071549000</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of California-Berkeley]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>947201460</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>13</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CA13</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>6882</Code>
<Text>Environmental Chemical Science</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1524</Code>
<Text>ATMOSPHERIC CHEMISTRY</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>6882</Code>
<Text>ENVIRONMENTAL CHEMICAL SCIENCE</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0113</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2013~502000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>International Collaboration in Chemistry: Measuring the effects of surfactants on cloud microphysics</p> <p>&nbsp;PI Ronald C. Cohen, UC Berkeley</p> <p>&nbsp;Award ID:&nbsp;AGS - 1303763</p> <p>This project aimed to use laboratory and field experiments to understand the role of surfactants (molecules that are similar to the ones that make up soaps) in the formation of cloud droplets. As cloud droplets from, impurities in the droplet such as surfactants can affect the rate of droplet growth, the number of droplets and the ultimate size of the droplets. Understanding the effects of surfactants is needed to describe the properties of clouds and their propensity to rain. Along with these scientific objectives, the project also aimed to build collaborative relationships with French partners in the research. Our partners were Barbara Noziere (CNRS-Lyon), Ann-Marie Delort (University of Clermont) and their graduate students, most notable Violaine Gerard (CNRS-Lyon).</p> <p>To achieve these objectives, at Berkeley, we built a new tool, an aerosol optical trap, that allows us to hold a single micron sized cloud drop in air for hours while we study how it grows or shrinks. The new tool allows us to measure the size change of the droplet with incredible precision (better than 1%). For comparison the width of human hair is in the range 20-180 microns. The droplets are created with pure water, with salt, since salt is frequently found in atmospheric aerosol and with commercially available surfactants that mimic the properties of the more unusual surfactants found in nature. We observed an unexpected effect of surfactants. Our hypothesis had been that surfactants would slow droplet growth and result in smaller cloud droplets. Instead, we found that droplets containing surfactants had a larger change in size with a change in relative humidity than droplets without surfactants that contained salt only. Droplets containing salt only behaved as predicted based on theoretical considerations that guided our thinking prior to the experiments. Our French collaborators visited for extended periods to work on these experiments with us. We also went to sea on the Marine Aerosol Cruise aboard the Endeavor, where we collected sea water and aerosol to examine the role of sea spray in seeding the atmosphere with surfactants.</p> <p>In Lyon, we collaborated on methods development for extracting and characterizing trace amounts of surfactants from aerosol, assembled a cloud water collector and deployed it in Pallas, Finland, and then characterized surfactant distributions in cloud droplets and aerosol from Pallas and from the Marine Aerosol Cruise.</p> <p>Findings from this research have been published or submitted for publication.&nbsp;</p> <p>Broader impacts of the research effort include: the mentoring and training of undergraduate, PhD students, and postdoctoral fellows. The lead postdoc on this project used this research a springboard to a faculty position at the University of Georgia (Athens, GA). In addition, the PI and his postdocs and graduate students have visited many local classrooms to talk about the research and high school students have come to visit our laboratories. Finally, a deeper understanding of the chemistry of clouds is fundamentally interesting and will improve our ability to make predictions of the behavior of clouds. These improved predictions will useful to weather forecasting and efforts to understand climate.</p> <p><strong>&nbsp;</strong></p> <p><strong>&nbsp;</strong></p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 12/11/2017<br>      Modified by: Ronald&nbsp;C&nbsp;Cohen</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ International Collaboration in Chemistry: Measuring the effects of surfactants on cloud microphysics   PI Ronald C. Cohen, UC Berkeley   Award ID: AGS - 1303763  This project aimed to use laboratory and field experiments to understand the role of surfactants (molecules that are similar to the ones that make up soaps) in the formation of cloud droplets. As cloud droplets from, impurities in the droplet such as surfactants can affect the rate of droplet growth, the number of droplets and the ultimate size of the droplets. Understanding the effects of surfactants is needed to describe the properties of clouds and their propensity to rain. Along with these scientific objectives, the project also aimed to build collaborative relationships with French partners in the research. Our partners were Barbara Noziere (CNRS-Lyon), Ann-Marie Delort (University of Clermont) and their graduate students, most notable Violaine Gerard (CNRS-Lyon).  To achieve these objectives, at Berkeley, we built a new tool, an aerosol optical trap, that allows us to hold a single micron sized cloud drop in air for hours while we study how it grows or shrinks. The new tool allows us to measure the size change of the droplet with incredible precision (better than 1%). For comparison the width of human hair is in the range 20-180 microns. The droplets are created with pure water, with salt, since salt is frequently found in atmospheric aerosol and with commercially available surfactants that mimic the properties of the more unusual surfactants found in nature. We observed an unexpected effect of surfactants. Our hypothesis had been that surfactants would slow droplet growth and result in smaller cloud droplets. Instead, we found that droplets containing surfactants had a larger change in size with a change in relative humidity than droplets without surfactants that contained salt only. Droplets containing salt only behaved as predicted based on theoretical considerations that guided our thinking prior to the experiments. Our French collaborators visited for extended periods to work on these experiments with us. We also went to sea on the Marine Aerosol Cruise aboard the Endeavor, where we collected sea water and aerosol to examine the role of sea spray in seeding the atmosphere with surfactants.  In Lyon, we collaborated on methods development for extracting and characterizing trace amounts of surfactants from aerosol, assembled a cloud water collector and deployed it in Pallas, Finland, and then characterized surfactant distributions in cloud droplets and aerosol from Pallas and from the Marine Aerosol Cruise.  Findings from this research have been published or submitted for publication.   Broader impacts of the research effort include: the mentoring and training of undergraduate, PhD students, and postdoctoral fellows. The lead postdoc on this project used this research a springboard to a faculty position at the University of Georgia (Athens, GA). In addition, the PI and his postdocs and graduate students have visited many local classrooms to talk about the research and high school students have come to visit our laboratories. Finally, a deeper understanding of the chemistry of clouds is fundamentally interesting and will improve our ability to make predictions of the behavior of clouds. These improved predictions will useful to weather forecasting and efforts to understand climate.                Last Modified: 12/11/2017       Submitted by: Ronald C Cohen]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
