<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>New generation of high-power widely-tunable mid-IR lasers using novel collinear orthogonally-polarized two-color semiconductor VECSEL</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>04/15/2013</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>09/30/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>359328.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>359328</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07010000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>ECCS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Electrical, Commun &amp; Cyber Sys</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Dominique Dagenais</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>ddagenai@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922980</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Objective: The objective of this research is to study and develop a novel high-power (watt-level), widely tunable, compact 3.5-4 micron laser source. The approach is based on a novel intra-cavity collinear type-II difference frequency generation (DFG) in a two-chip T-cavity vertical external-cavity surface-emitting laser (VECSEL). Wavelength tuning of each chip around the gain maxima will result in high power wide wavelength tuning in the mid-IR band. The proposed high quality factor doubly-resonant laser cavity will open doors to a new class of high power semiconductor-based mid- to far-IR lasers and will have a transformative effect in various fields of science. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Intellectual Merit: The proposed research is to develop a new class of high-power, compact, widely-tunable mid-IR laser sources. Significant research and technical advancement will be made in areas such as: semiconductor laser and cavity design, nonlinear optical materials, thermal management, and difference frequency conversion. The proposed intra-cavity DFG in a two-color doubly-resonant VECSEL cavity will open doors to a new class of high power semiconductor-based mid- to far-IR lasers.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Broader Impact: The proposed mid-IR source will have significant future scientific impact on various fields of science and engineering and multi-disciplinary education and outreach. In addition to the application-rich mid-IR, the proposed concept can be extended to the untapped spectral regions in the far-IR providing even more research opportunities in the future. The interdisciplinary nature of the proposed research will provide powerful and unique educational opportunities for graduate and undergraduate and underrepresented minority students.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>04/08/2013</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/22/2018</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1303476</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Chris</FirstName>
<LastName>Hessenius</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Chris Hessenius</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>CHessenius@optics.arizona.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>7143510268</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000646927</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/30/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Mahmoud</FirstName>
<LastName>Fallahi</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Mahmoud Fallahi</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>mahmoud.fallahi@optics.arizona.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5206218260</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000070938</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/08/2013</StartDate>
<EndDate>07/30/2014</EndDate>
<RoleCode>Former Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Arizona</Name>
<CityName>Tucson</CityName>
<ZipCode>857194824</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5206266000</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>888 N Euclid Ave</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Arizona</StateName>
<StateCode>AZ</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>AZ03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>806345617</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF ARIZONA</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>072459266</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Arizona]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>AZ</StateCode>
<ZipCode>857210001</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Arizona</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>AZ03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1517</Code>
<Text>EPMD-ElectrnPhoton&amp;MagnDevices</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>091E</Code>
<Text>Light generation &amp; detection</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0113</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2013~359328</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><strong><span style="text-decoration: underline;">Final Report</span></strong></p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>Broad wavelength coverage high power lasers in the mid-infrared (mid-IR) spectral region are needed for numerous applications such as: chemical and environmental monitoring, medical diagnostics, atmospheric transmission, military and security applications. The main goals of the project were:</p> <ul> <li>Theoretical investigation of difference frequency generation (DFG) in high-Q VECSEL cavity with orthogonal polarization &ndash; We demonstrated two-color outputs in our modified t-cavity configuration and made advances in the modeling of the device to optimize performance of the mid-IR DFG outputs.</li> </ul> <ul> <li>Design optimization and growth of 920nm and 1180-nm vertical external cavity surface emitting laser (VECSEL) structure with large gain bandwidth. &ndash; During the project we designed a new VECSEL structure that lased near the desired 920nm wavelength. This pushed the boundary of high-power GaAs quantum well structures. We were able to achieve output powers near 10W with excellent mode profile.</li> </ul> <ul> <li>Design and demonstration of tunable two-color multi-watts power 920 and 1180 nm VECSEL in a T-cavity configuration. &ndash; We combined the new 920nm wafer structure with our existing 1180nm devices in order to create the two-color laser system with sufficient separation to achieve the desired outputs in the 3.5-4um mid-IR range.</li> </ul> <ul> <li>Study and selection of NLO crystals with high transparency and high conversion efficiency. &ndash; We considered many nonlinear crystals for use in the intracavity conversion and ultimately decided to use AGS due to its high transparency and ability to phase match to the desired wavelengths. This was the first demonstration using this crystal for intracavity DFG in VECSEL lasers.</li> </ul> <ul> <li>Demonstration of high power, tunable, mid-IR difference frequency generation in the 3.5-4 um band. &ndash; While we were not able to reach a wavelength less than 4um, we did achieve outputs at 4.2um, 5.5um, and also demonstrated tuning of more than 1.3um from 9.3-10.6um.</li> </ul> <p>The results of this research led to significant advances in the fields of nonlinear optics, semiconductor lasers, and laser cavity design. We believe there is the opportunity for significant improvements with the t-cavity design.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 12/31/2018<br>      Modified by: Chris&nbsp;Hessenius</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Final Report     Broad wavelength coverage high power lasers in the mid-infrared (mid-IR) spectral region are needed for numerous applications such as: chemical and environmental monitoring, medical diagnostics, atmospheric transmission, military and security applications. The main goals of the project were:  Theoretical investigation of difference frequency generation (DFG) in high-Q VECSEL cavity with orthogonal polarization &ndash; We demonstrated two-color outputs in our modified t-cavity configuration and made advances in the modeling of the device to optimize performance of the mid-IR DFG outputs.   Design optimization and growth of 920nm and 1180-nm vertical external cavity surface emitting laser (VECSEL) structure with large gain bandwidth. &ndash; During the project we designed a new VECSEL structure that lased near the desired 920nm wavelength. This pushed the boundary of high-power GaAs quantum well structures. We were able to achieve output powers near 10W with excellent mode profile.   Design and demonstration of tunable two-color multi-watts power 920 and 1180 nm VECSEL in a T-cavity configuration. &ndash; We combined the new 920nm wafer structure with our existing 1180nm devices in order to create the two-color laser system with sufficient separation to achieve the desired outputs in the 3.5-4um mid-IR range.   Study and selection of NLO crystals with high transparency and high conversion efficiency. &ndash; We considered many nonlinear crystals for use in the intracavity conversion and ultimately decided to use AGS due to its high transparency and ability to phase match to the desired wavelengths. This was the first demonstration using this crystal for intracavity DFG in VECSEL lasers.   Demonstration of high power, tunable, mid-IR difference frequency generation in the 3.5-4 um band. &ndash; While we were not able to reach a wavelength less than 4um, we did achieve outputs at 4.2um, 5.5um, and also demonstrated tuning of more than 1.3um from 9.3-10.6um.   The results of this research led to significant advances in the fields of nonlinear optics, semiconductor lasers, and laser cavity design. We believe there is the opportunity for significant improvements with the t-cavity design.          Last Modified: 12/31/2018       Submitted by: Chris Hessenius]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
