<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Spin Injection and Relaxation in Organic Semiconductors</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2013</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>405000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>405000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03070000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DMR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Materials Research</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Miriam Deutsch</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>mdeutsch@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032925360</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Technical Description: Research on organic spintronics has gained momentum in the past few years. An important advantage of organic materials is the intrinsically long spin-lifetime because of the small atomic numbers, resulting in less spin-orbit interaction. Strong organic magnetoresistance response as high as 300% has recently been reported. The roles of spin injection and carrier recombination in organic light emitting diodes have also been extensively observed. While the potential is high, there remain challenging fundamental issues, including the mechanisms governing spin injection and spin flip. It is well recognized that interfaces are critical in organic spintronics. The knowledge gap in understanding of the fundamental processes in organic spintronics must be bridged to realize its potential.&lt;br/&gt;The goal of this project is to investigate spin injection and relaxation dynamics to understand the underlying fundamental mechanisms important for the development of organic spintronics. The spin injection efficiency is investigated for the interface between various inorganic substrates and organic materials, and the spin relaxation dynamics are studied in organic semiconductor thin films. The primary tool for the investigation is spin-resolved photoemission spectroscopy, supported by other surface analytical techniques including ultraviolet and x-ray photoemission spectroscopy, inverse photoemission spectroscopy, scanning tunneling microscopy, atomic force microscopy, and magnetic force microscopy. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Non-Technical Description: The project is on fundamental materials research of spin injection and relaxation in organic semiconductors. Success of the project can enhance the understanding of the nature of spin-related phenomena in molecular system, with potential impact on organic spintronics for future information technologies. The impact also comes from training of the next generation of scientists in a fast advancing field with international experience and leadership. A major focus of the project is educating and training scientists in an interdisciplinary field including organic electronic materials, surface and interface analysis, ultrafast dynamics, and spintronics. A strong emphasis of the program is on increasing participation of women through programs including University of Rochester Women in Science and Engineering and Pre-College Experience in Physics for high-school students.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project is co-funded by the Electronic and Photonic Materials Program (EPM) and the Condensed Matter Physics Program (CMP).</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/10/2013</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/01/2015</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1303742</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Yongli</FirstName>
<LastName>Gao</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Yongli Gao</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>ygao@pas.rochester.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5852758574</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000294273</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/10/2013</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Rochester</Name>
<CityName>Rochester</CityName>
<ZipCode>146270140</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5852754031</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>518 HYLAN, RC BOX 270140</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>25</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NY25</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>041294109</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF ROCHESTER</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>041294109</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Rochester]]></Name>
<CityName>Rochester</CityName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<ZipCode>146270171</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[518 Hylan]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>25</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NY25</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1710</Code>
<Text>CONDENSED MATTER PHYSICS</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1775</Code>
<Text>ELECTRONIC/PHOTONIC MATERIALS</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>6863</Code>
<Text>SEBML-MOORE'S LAW</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0113</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0114</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0115</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2013~143995</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~128286</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2015~132719</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><strong><span style="font-family: Times New Roman; font-size: small;">Intellectual Merit: </span></strong><span style="font-family: Times New Roman; font-size: small;">Research on organic spintronics has gain momentum in the past decade. An important advantage of organic materials is the intrinsically long spin-lifetime because of the small atomic numbers resulting in less spin-orbit interaction. </span><span><span style="font-family: Times New Roman; font-size: small;">&nbsp;</span></span><span style="font-family: Times New Roman; font-size: small;">The progress in organic spintronics indicates that it represents a major opportunity.</span><span><span style="font-family: Times New Roman; font-size: small;">&nbsp; </span></span><span style="font-family: Times New Roman; font-size: small;">While the potential is high, there remain challenging fundamental issues, including the mechanisms governing spin injection and spin flip.</span><span><span style="font-family: Times New Roman; font-size: small;">&nbsp; </span></span><span style="font-family: Times New Roman; font-size: small;">It is well recognized that interfaces are critical in organic spintronics.</span><span><span style="font-family: Times New Roman; font-size: small;">&nbsp; </span></span><span style="font-family: Times New Roman; font-size: small;">The knowledge gap in understanding of the fundamental processes in organic spintronics must be bridged to realize its potential.</span></p> <p><span style="font-family: Times New Roman; font-size: small;">&nbsp;</span></p> <p><span style="font-family: Times; font-size: small;">The goal of this proposal is to investigate spin injection and relaxation dynamics to understand the underlying fundamental mechanisms important for the development of organic spintronics.</span><span><span style="font-family: Times; font-size: small;">&nbsp; </span></span><span><span style="font-family: Times; font-size: small;">The </span></span><span style="font-family: Times; font-size: small;">spin injection efficiency is investigated for interface between various inorganic ferromagnetic substrates and organic materials, and the spin relaxation dynamics is studied in organic semiconductor thin films. The primary tool for the investigation is photoemission spectroscopy, supported by other techniques including inverse photoemission spectroscopy, scanning tunneling microscopy, atomic force microscopy, magnetic force microscopy, and density functional theory.</span><span><span style="font-family: Times; font-size: small;">&nbsp; </span></span></p> <p><span style="font-family: Times; font-size: small;">&nbsp;</span></p> <p><span style="font-family: Times; font-size: small;">Our study on the interface of ferromagnetic metal with high mobility organic semiconductor sets up the basis for effective spin transport in organic semiconductors.</span><span><span style="font-family: Times; font-size: small;">&nbsp; </span></span><span style="font-family: Times; font-size: small;">Although the spin relaxation lifetime in organic semiconductors is orders of magnitude longer than that in inorganic ones, the spin diffusion length is still low (~10 nm) as it is proportional to the square root of the mobility.</span><span><span style="font-family: Times; font-size: small;">&nbsp; </span></span><span style="font-family: Times; font-size: small;">Our results indicate that the injection of spin carried by charge carriers is strongly influenced by interface energy level alignment and reactions, and proper design insertion layers is important for improving spin injection.</span><span><span style="font-family: Times; font-size: small;">&nbsp; </span></span><span style="font-family: Times; font-size: small;">We have 40 papers and 3 book chapters published.</span><span><span style="font-family: Times; font-size: small;">&nbsp; </span></span><span style="font-family: Times; font-size: small;">We have 34 presentations in national/international conferences, including 14 invited talks.</span></p> <p><span style="font-family: Times; font-size: small;">&nbsp;</span></p> <p><strong><span>Broader Impact: </span></strong><span>The proposed research aims at fundamental issues of spin injection and relaxation in organic semiconductors.<span>&nbsp; </span>The results of the experiments enhance the understanding of the nature of spin-related phenomena in molecular system, especially on the advances of organic spintronic devices.<span>&nbsp;&nbsp; </span>The knowledge has a strong impact on organic spintronics for future information technologies.<span>&nbsp; </span>The impact also comes from training of the next generation of scientists in a fast advancing field with international experience and leadership.<span>&nbsp; </span>A major focus of the program is educating and training scientists in an interdisciplinary field including organic electronic materials, surface and interface analysis, ultrafast dynamics, and spintronics.<span>&nbsp; </span>A strong emphasis of the program is on increasing participation of women through programs including University of Rochester Women in Science and Engineering (WISE) and Pre-College Experience in Physics (PREP) for high school women.</span><strong>&nbsp;</strong><em></em></p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 05/29/2017<br>      Modified by: Yongli&nbsp;Gao</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Intellectual Merit: Research on organic spintronics has gain momentum in the past decade. An important advantage of organic materials is the intrinsically long spin-lifetime because of the small atomic numbers resulting in less spin-orbit interaction.  The progress in organic spintronics indicates that it represents a major opportunity.  While the potential is high, there remain challenging fundamental issues, including the mechanisms governing spin injection and spin flip.  It is well recognized that interfaces are critical in organic spintronics.  The knowledge gap in understanding of the fundamental processes in organic spintronics must be bridged to realize its potential.     The goal of this proposal is to investigate spin injection and relaxation dynamics to understand the underlying fundamental mechanisms important for the development of organic spintronics.  The spin injection efficiency is investigated for interface between various inorganic ferromagnetic substrates and organic materials, and the spin relaxation dynamics is studied in organic semiconductor thin films. The primary tool for the investigation is photoemission spectroscopy, supported by other techniques including inverse photoemission spectroscopy, scanning tunneling microscopy, atomic force microscopy, magnetic force microscopy, and density functional theory.       Our study on the interface of ferromagnetic metal with high mobility organic semiconductor sets up the basis for effective spin transport in organic semiconductors.  Although the spin relaxation lifetime in organic semiconductors is orders of magnitude longer than that in inorganic ones, the spin diffusion length is still low (~10 nm) as it is proportional to the square root of the mobility.  Our results indicate that the injection of spin carried by charge carriers is strongly influenced by interface energy level alignment and reactions, and proper design insertion layers is important for improving spin injection.  We have 40 papers and 3 book chapters published.  We have 34 presentations in national/international conferences, including 14 invited talks.     Broader Impact: The proposed research aims at fundamental issues of spin injection and relaxation in organic semiconductors.  The results of the experiments enhance the understanding of the nature of spin-related phenomena in molecular system, especially on the advances of organic spintronic devices.   The knowledge has a strong impact on organic spintronics for future information technologies.  The impact also comes from training of the next generation of scientists in a fast advancing field with international experience and leadership.  A major focus of the program is educating and training scientists in an interdisciplinary field including organic electronic materials, surface and interface analysis, ultrafast dynamics, and spintronics.  A strong emphasis of the program is on increasing participation of women through programs including University of Rochester Women in Science and Engineering (WISE) and Pre-College Experience in Physics (PREP) for high school women.           Last Modified: 05/29/2017       Submitted by: Yongli Gao]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
