<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Erdos Centennial</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>04/01/2013</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>03/31/2014</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>15000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>15000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DMS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Qing Xiang</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The Alfred Renyi Institute of Mathematics, together with the Hungarian Academy of Sciences, the Eotvos Lorand University and the Janos Bolyai Mathematical Society are organizing a conference in the summer of 2013 to celebrate the 100th birthday of Paul Erdos, one of the most influential mathematicians of the 20th century. The conference will be held July 1-5, 2013, in Budapest, Hungary, in the historical building of the Hungarian Academy of Sciences. There will be only invited talks by outstanding mathematicians who will create a scientic program with intellectual merit on a par with Erdos's incredible research achievements. Invited speakers who have accepted our invitation include several winners of the Fields Medal, Wolf Prize, Nevanlinna Prize, and other major prizes. One of our underlying goals, in addition to honoring Paul Erdos, is to bring together these exceptional researchers and study the relationships between their work and Erdos's work. We are confident that the meeting will inspire new insights and further collaborations from these "mathematical giants". There is no doubt that Erdos's work will continue to be the source of beautiful developments in mathematics and in other fields.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>03/26/2013</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>03/26/2013</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1303796</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Gabor</FirstName>
<LastName>Sarkozy</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>N</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Gabor N Sarkozy</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>gsarkozy@cs.wpi.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5088315408</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000261097</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>03/26/2013</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Worcester Polytechnic Institute</Name>
<CityName>WORCESTER</CityName>
<ZipCode>016092247</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5088315000</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>100 INSTITUTE RD</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
<StateCode>MA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MA02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>041508581</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>WORCESTER POLYTECHNIC INSTITUTE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>041508581</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Worcester Polytechnic Institute]]></Name>
<CityName>Worcester</CityName>
<StateCode>MA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>016092280</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[100 Institute Road]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MA02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7970</Code>
<Text>Combinatorics</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7556</Code>
<Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0113</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2013~15000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The legendary mathematician Paul Erdos was born on the 26th of March 1913. The Alfred Renyi Institute of Mathematics, together with the Hungarian<br />Academy of Sciences, the Eotvos Lorand University and the<br />Janos Bolyai Mathematical Society organized a conference in the<br />summer of 2013 to celebrate this occasion. The conference was held<br />July 1-5, 2013 in Budapest, Hungary, in the historical building of the Hungarian Academy of Sciences.</p> <p>The main goal of the organizers of the conference was to bring<br />together those mathematicians from all around the world who have<br />contributed to the important topics and theories of mathematics related to Erdos' work&nbsp;and therefore present an overview of the state of the<br />art of these areas (the contributions were also collected and<br />published as a volume of the Bolyai Society Mathematical Series by<br />Springer).</p> <p>There were only invited talks by outstanding mathematicians who<br />created a scientific program on a par with Erdos' incredible<br />research achievements. The plenary lectures invited speakers inculeded&nbsp;distinguished mathematicians and<br />computer scientists including several winners of the Fields Medal<br />and Wolf Prize, and other major prizes. Apart from them, there were<br />about 100 other lectures, all invited by the organizing committee or<br />of the special session organizers. The conference also had a poster<br />section for contributed papers.</p> <p>Let us take this opportunity to thank the NSF again for making this truly special conference possible.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 02/19/2014<br>      Modified by: Gabor&nbsp;N&nbsp;Sarkozy</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The legendary mathematician Paul Erdos was born on the 26th of March 1913. The Alfred Renyi Institute of Mathematics, together with the Hungarian Academy of Sciences, the Eotvos Lorand University and the Janos Bolyai Mathematical Society organized a conference in the summer of 2013 to celebrate this occasion. The conference was held July 1-5, 2013 in Budapest, Hungary, in the historical building of the Hungarian Academy of Sciences.  The main goal of the organizers of the conference was to bring together those mathematicians from all around the world who have contributed to the important topics and theories of mathematics related to Erdos' work and therefore present an overview of the state of the art of these areas (the contributions were also collected and published as a volume of the Bolyai Society Mathematical Series by Springer).  There were only invited talks by outstanding mathematicians who created a scientific program on a par with Erdos' incredible research achievements. The plenary lectures invited speakers inculeded distinguished mathematicians and computer scientists including several winners of the Fields Medal and Wolf Prize, and other major prizes. Apart from them, there were about 100 other lectures, all invited by the organizing committee or of the special session organizers. The conference also had a poster section for contributed papers.  Let us take this opportunity to thank the NSF again for making this truly special conference possible.       Last Modified: 02/19/2014       Submitted by: Gabor N Sarkozy]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
