<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Workshop on Multilevel Computational Methods and Optimization</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>05/15/2013</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>04/30/2014</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>20000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>20000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DMS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Junping Wang</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>jwang@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924488</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This grant supports travel of US researchers to attend the workshop on "Mutilevel methods and Optimization" from April 29 to May 2, 2013, at the Weizmann Institute of Science in Rehovot, Israel. The planned talks and panel discussions will cover classical problems such as partial differential equations, together with modern tasks such as web search and data mining.  Speakers and participants in the workshop come from a variety of disciplines, including physics, biology, chemistry, economics, environment and earth sciences, computer science and engineering. A special two-hour panel "Challenges in Multilevel Computation: where should we be directing our efforts and our graduate students?" is planned for the second day.  &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Multilevel solution methods for simulation and optimization problems over very large number of variables is central and important to virtually all disciplines in the sciences and engineering. These methodologies are very powerful because they exploit the fact that most computational problems have multiple scales. This notion of multiple scales may take on many different guises, including time and space, pixels, particles, proteins, or web-pages. This multiplicity and disparity of scales is an essential source of computational complexity. The multilevel algorithms address the problem under consideration at a hierarchy of scales, typically treating each with a method that is local to that particular scale.  The proposed workshop will bring together junior researchers and world-class experts, mainly from North America, Western Europe, and Israel, to exhibit and discuss their recent research on multilevel computational methods for simulation and optimization in a wide variety of topics and applications.  Together, the diverse backgrounds of the participants in the workshop and the planned activities are expected to expose new research directions in multilevel computational methods and to identify the most pressing challenges in this diverse field.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>05/13/2013</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/13/2013</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1303442</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>James</FirstName>
<LastName>Brannick</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>J</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>James J Brannick</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>brannick@psu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>8148637327</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000445849</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/13/2013</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Pennsylvania State Univ University Park</Name>
<CityName>University Park</CityName>
<ZipCode>168021503</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>8148651372</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>201 Old Main</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Pennsylvania</StateName>
<StateCode>PA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>PA05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>003403953</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>PENNSYLVANIA STATE UNIVERSITY, THE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>003403953</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Pennsylvania State Univ University Park]]></Name>
<CityName>University Park</CityName>
<StateCode>PA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>168021503</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[201 Old Main]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Pennsylvania</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>PA05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1271</Code>
<Text>COMPUTATIONAL MATHEMATICS</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7556</Code>
<Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9263</Code>
<Text>COMPUTATIONAL SCIENCE &amp; ENGING</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0113</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2013~20000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The Weizmann Workshop on Multilevel Compuational Methods and Optimization was held at the Weizmann Institute of Science from April 30 - May 2, 2013. &nbsp;The workshop brought together world-class experts, students, and junior researchers, mainly from North America, Western Europe, and Israel, to exhibit and discuss their recent research on multilevel computational methods for optimization in a wide variety of topics and applications. The program included talks on classical problems such as partial differential equations, together with modern tasks such as web search and data mining. Attendees came from diverse disciplines, including physics, biology, chemistry, economics, environment and earth sciences, computer science and engineering. &nbsp;The workshop also included a panel discusssion <span>&ldquo;Challenges in Multilevel Computation: where should we be directing out efforts &ndash; and our graduate students?&rdquo; &nbsp;</span>The panel was led by Irad Yavneh (Technion) and included four panelists Achi Brandt (Weizmann), Tony Chan (Hong Kong University), Uli Rude (University of Erlangen), and Jinchao Xu (Penn State University).</p> <p>The requested NSF funding&nbsp;supported travel of junior researchers from the United States including students, postdocs, and women. It gave them the opportunity to participate in the workshop, which provided them with a general review and an introduction to the state of the art topics in multilevel scientific computing.&nbsp; Given the extensive list of participants and the active social program, the workshop also provided an excellent venue for networking. &nbsp;Several of the speakers that were supported by the requested funds also submitted papers to the workshop's proceedings ``Special Issue on Multilevel Computational Methods" that will be published in The Journal of Numerical Mathematics: Theory, Methods and&nbsp; Applications.</p> <p>A &nbsp;webpage for the workshop was also developed:</p> <p>&nbsp;http://www.wisdom.weizmann.ac.il/April2013/WeizmannProjectProgramme.html</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 05/17/2014<br>      Modified by: James&nbsp;J&nbsp;Brannick</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The Weizmann Workshop on Multilevel Compuational Methods and Optimization was held at the Weizmann Institute of Science from April 30 - May 2, 2013.  The workshop brought together world-class experts, students, and junior researchers, mainly from North America, Western Europe, and Israel, to exhibit and discuss their recent research on multilevel computational methods for optimization in a wide variety of topics and applications. The program included talks on classical problems such as partial differential equations, together with modern tasks such as web search and data mining. Attendees came from diverse disciplines, including physics, biology, chemistry, economics, environment and earth sciences, computer science and engineering.  The workshop also included a panel discusssion "Challenges in Multilevel Computation: where should we be directing out efforts &ndash; and our graduate students?"  The panel was led by Irad Yavneh (Technion) and included four panelists Achi Brandt (Weizmann), Tony Chan (Hong Kong University), Uli Rude (University of Erlangen), and Jinchao Xu (Penn State University).  The requested NSF funding supported travel of junior researchers from the United States including students, postdocs, and women. It gave them the opportunity to participate in the workshop, which provided them with a general review and an introduction to the state of the art topics in multilevel scientific computing.  Given the extensive list of participants and the active social program, the workshop also provided an excellent venue for networking.  Several of the speakers that were supported by the requested funds also submitted papers to the workshop's proceedings ``Special Issue on Multilevel Computational Methods" that will be published in The Journal of Numerical Mathematics: Theory, Methods and  Applications.  A  webpage for the workshop was also developed:   http://www.wisdom.weizmann.ac.il/April2013/WeizmannProjectProgramme.html       Last Modified: 05/17/2014       Submitted by: James J Brannick]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
