<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Collaborative Research: Digitization TCN: The Macroalgal Herbarium Consortium: Accessing 150 Years of Specimen Data to Understand Changes in the Marine/Aquatic Environment</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2013</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>315518.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>315518</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>08080000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>BIO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DBI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Biological Infrastructure</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Reed Beaman</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>rsbeaman@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927163</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This award will support investigators from a consortium of 50 herbaria at universities, botanical gardens, and natural history museums across the U.S. to digitize their collections of macroalgae.  When they have finished, high resolution images and information about when and where each specimen was collected will be openly accessible for more than a million specimens through the consortium's web portal and the iDigBio web resource.  Macroalgae are the foundation of marine, estuarine and freshwater benthic ecosystems providing food, substrata and protection for a myriad of other aquatic organisms. Many macroalgal species are sensitive to environmental change.  The data provided through the portal will allow researchers and the public at large determine how macroalgal biodiversity and our aquatic ecosystems have changed over the past 150 years as a result of climate change, bioinvasions, and a wide range of human activity. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;A number of macroalgal species, including kelp, nori, and others are grown extensively via aquaculture or harvested from the wild for human food and for extraction of colloids used in cosmetics, food products, and pharmaceuticals. The consortium's web portal will provide opportunities for the public to learn about the economic and ecological importance of macroalgae.  Tools will be provided for citizen scientists to contribute to the project by helping transcribe some of the ancillary details from specimen labels into the database.  Interactive exhibits and educational modules will be developed by the education departments of the museums in the consortium where hundreds of thousands of visitors will experience them each year.  The project will also provide integrative training in collections and informatics research for undergraduate and graduate students through participation in the digitization effort and through internships at one of the museums.  This award is made as part of the National Resource for Digitization of Biological Collections through the Advancing Digitization of Biological Collections program and all data resulting from this award will be available through the national resource (iDigBio.org).</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/20/2013</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/20/2013</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.074</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1303909</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Brent</FirstName>
<LastName>Mishler</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Brent Mishler</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>bmishler@berkeley.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5106426810</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000461444</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/20/2013</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of California-Berkeley</Name>
<CityName>BERKELEY</CityName>
<ZipCode>947101749</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5106433891</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>Sponsored Projects Office</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[1608 Fourth Street, Suite 220]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>13</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CA13</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>124726725</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>REGENTS OF THE UNIVERSITY OF CALIFORNIA, THE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>071549000</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of California-Berkeley]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>947202465</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>13</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CA13</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>6895</Code>
<Text>Digitization</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>6895</Code>
<Text>DIGITIZATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0113</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2013~315518</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>&nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp;&nbsp;Macroalgae are a diverse group of aquatic organisms that occur in four divisions (phyla) spanning two kingdoms. They are the foundation of many marine, estuarine, and freshwater benthic ecosystems and provide food, substrata, and protection for a myriad of other aquatic organisms. Many macroalgae are sensitive to environmental change, and as a consequence, community structure can be altered by the loss or gain of species in response to bioinvasions, climate change, and a wide range of human activities. Through their effect on other organisms, disturbances in macroalgal community structure can be amplified to impact entire ecosystems. &nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; The overall goal of the collaboration was to&nbsp;digitize most of the macroalgal herbarium specimens in the US and to make the data easily accessible in a way that will (a) facilitate research to document ecological changes in marine, estuarine and freshwater environments; (b) inform environmental managers and regulatory agencies; and&nbsp;(c) engage the public and promote an appreciation of the importance of macroalgae and natural history collections.</p> <p>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; The UC Berkeley portion of the project was able to complete imaging, databasing, and georeferencing of all of its own macroalgae specimens. In addition, all macroalgae specimens of several other, smaller institutions&nbsp;(San Diego Natural History Museum, Hopkins Marine Station, Humboldt State University, University of California, Davis, University of Utah, and University of California, Irvine) were also digitized.&nbsp; All have been made available at the Macroalgal Herbarium Consortium Portal:&nbsp;http://macroalgae.org/portal/index.php</p> <p>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; Many of the digitization tasks were carried out by undergraduate students hired for the project at UC Berkeley. It will provided them with an enriched educational experience, skills for using state-of-the-art bioinformatics tools, and an appreciation of the value of their contribution to an important national effort.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 12/29/2017<br>      Modified by: Brent&nbsp;Mishler</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[             Macroalgae are a diverse group of aquatic organisms that occur in four divisions (phyla) spanning two kingdoms. They are the foundation of many marine, estuarine, and freshwater benthic ecosystems and provide food, substrata, and protection for a myriad of other aquatic organisms. Many macroalgae are sensitive to environmental change, and as a consequence, community structure can be altered by the loss or gain of species in response to bioinvasions, climate change, and a wide range of human activities. Through their effect on other organisms, disturbances in macroalgal community structure can be amplified to impact entire ecosystems.                The overall goal of the collaboration was to digitize most of the macroalgal herbarium specimens in the US and to make the data easily accessible in a way that will (a) facilitate research to document ecological changes in marine, estuarine and freshwater environments; (b) inform environmental managers and regulatory agencies; and (c) engage the public and promote an appreciation of the importance of macroalgae and natural history collections.              The UC Berkeley portion of the project was able to complete imaging, databasing, and georeferencing of all of its own macroalgae specimens. In addition, all macroalgae specimens of several other, smaller institutions (San Diego Natural History Museum, Hopkins Marine Station, Humboldt State University, University of California, Davis, University of Utah, and University of California, Irvine) were also digitized.  All have been made available at the Macroalgal Herbarium Consortium Portal: http://macroalgae.org/portal/index.php              Many of the digitization tasks were carried out by undergraduate students hired for the project at UC Berkeley. It will provided them with an enriched educational experience, skills for using state-of-the-art bioinformatics tools, and an appreciation of the value of their contribution to an important national effort.          Last Modified: 12/29/2017       Submitted by: Brent Mishler]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
