<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>CAREER:Teaching Mixed Methods, International Research, and Comparative Perspectives through a Study of Childbearing and Childrearing under China's Fertility Limitation Policies</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2012</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2015</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>151408.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>151408</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>04040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>SBE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>BCS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Behavioral and Cognitive Sci</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Jeffrey Mantz</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>jmantz@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927783</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Anthropologist Dr. Vanessa L. Fong, of Harvard University, will continue her unique longitudinal study of the childbearing and childrearing practices of the first generation of young adults born as singletons under China's one-child policy. Fong's research addresses three focal questions:1) What factors cause childbearing preferences and outcomes associated with low fertility? 2) What factors cause son or daughter preference and skewed sex ratios at birth? And 3) What effects do discrepancies between childbearing preferences and outcomes have on childrearing goals and practices? &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Fong will administer surveys to the approximately 1,600 Dalian young adults who previously responded to a survey conducted in 1999, when they were adolescents. She also will interview and conduct participant observation among 100 of them. Unlike single-wave and single-method studies that have difficulty addressing issues of causality, this mixed-method, longitudinal approach will permit understanding cause and effect in the lives of the same individuals and families over time. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This research is important because it will help social scientists to understand the social dynamics of childbearing and childrearing at a time when issues of population pressure and population ageing are increasingly pressing worldwide. The research also will help to bridge the divide between qualitative humanistic and quantitative scientific approaches to social research, using their complementary strengths to shed light on these pressing social problems. Because the researcher will engage students in her research and develop new educational programs, this award also supports expanded opportunities for interdisciplinary training for a new generation of social science researchers.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>02/07/2013</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/30/2013</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.075</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1303404</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Vanessa</FirstName>
<LastName>Fong</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>L</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Vanessa L Fong</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>vfong@amherst.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>4135425563</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000056027</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>02/07/2013</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Amherst College</Name>
<CityName>Amherst</CityName>
<ZipCode>010025000</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>4135422804</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>Controller's Office</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[P.O. Box 5000]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
<StateCode>MA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MA02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>066985367</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>AMHERST COLLEGE, TRUSTEES OF</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>066985367</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Amherst College]]></Name>
<CityName>Amherst</CityName>
<StateCode>MA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>010025000</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[155 S. Pleasant St.]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MA02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1390</Code>
<Text>Cultural Anthropology</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>0000</Code>
<Text>UNASSIGNED</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1045</Code>
<Text>CAREER-Faculty Erly Career Dev</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1187</Code>
<Text>PECASE- eligible</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1390</Code>
<Text>CULTURAL ANTHROPOLOGY</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9178</Code>
<Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9179</Code>
<Text>GRADUATE INVOLVEMENT</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>OTHR</Code>
<Text>OTHER RESEARCH OR EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0111</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0113</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2011~102321</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2013~49087</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Using surveys, interviews, and participant observation among a cohort of young adults born in China between 1979 and 1986, right after China&rsquo;s one-child policy began, this project continued a longitudinal study of childbearing and childrearing among the first generation of young adults born as singletons under that policy.</p> <p><strong>Project Outcomes</strong></p> <p><strong>Intellectual Merit</strong></p> <p>Unlike single-wave and single-method studies that have difficulty addressing issues of causality, this mixed-method, longitudinal approach permits understanding cause and effect in the lives of the same individuals and families over time.&nbsp; We found that most of the cohort we studied delayed marriage and childbearing to their 30s, due to their high aspirations for continual educational attainment and career advancement. Our research participants entered the job market during the first decade of the twenty-first century, when competition for middle-class work had reached unprecedented intensity due to the competitiveness, parental investment, diploma inflation, and high aspirations and educational attainment among China&rsquo;s first generation of only-children, who had to compete against a whole generation of fellow singletons who were almost all raised with similarly high aspirations and parental investment. Though most of their parents had no more than a middle school diploma, most of the &nbsp;singletons we studied ended up with college degrees. They have been very upwardly mobile and hope and expect their own children to be even more upwardly mobile. They also experienced far less gender inequality than their parents did, and have become even more gender egalitarian as adults than they were as adolescents. Many of them have gone abroad, and many more hope to go abroad or send their children abroad. &nbsp;All of these factors caused them to delay marriage and childbearing, which could halt their upwardly mobile trajectories by compelling them to invest in their children&rsquo;s education instead of their own educational and professional development. Those who did have children during our study faced tremendous pressure to invest unaffordably high amounts of time, attention, and money into their children&rsquo;s education from the moment their children were born, as standards for parental investment have increased even when compared to the intense parental investment these young adults experienced, which was far greater than what their parents experienced. These factors have made it likely that the generation born under China&rsquo;s one-child policy will themselves have below-replacement fertility even though China&rsquo;s policy now allows only-children to have two children.</p> <p><strong>Broader Impacts. </strong></p> <p>This research is important because it will help social scientists to understand the social dynamics of childbearing and childrearing at a time when issues of population pressure and population ageing are increasingly pressing worldwide. The research has also helped to bridge the divide between qualitative and quantitative scientific approaches to social research, using their complementary strengths to shed light on these pressing social problems. &nbsp;By engaging students in &nbsp;research and develop new educational programs, this award also supports expanded opportunities for interdisciplinary training for a new generation of social science researchers.</p> <p>Data from this research was used for graduate and undergraduate student projects, undergraduate senior honors theses, and a doctoral dissertation. Participation in the research project helped these students learn to design research questions, transcribe and translate interview data, conduct qualitative &nbsp;and quantitative analyses, and write papers and theses based on these analyses.&nbsp;Students have co-authored many articles with the PI based on data from this...]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Using surveys, interviews, and participant observation among a cohort of young adults born in China between 1979 and 1986, right after ChinaÆs one-child policy began, this project continued a longitudinal study of childbearing and childrearing among the first generation of young adults born as singletons under that policy.  Project Outcomes  Intellectual Merit  Unlike single-wave and single-method studies that have difficulty addressing issues of causality, this mixed-method, longitudinal approach permits understanding cause and effect in the lives of the same individuals and families over time.  We found that most of the cohort we studied delayed marriage and childbearing to their 30s, due to their high aspirations for continual educational attainment and career advancement. Our research participants entered the job market during the first decade of the twenty-first century, when competition for middle-class work had reached unprecedented intensity due to the competitiveness, parental investment, diploma inflation, and high aspirations and educational attainment among ChinaÆs first generation of only-children, who had to compete against a whole generation of fellow singletons who were almost all raised with similarly high aspirations and parental investment. Though most of their parents had no more than a middle school diploma, most of the  singletons we studied ended up with college degrees. They have been very upwardly mobile and hope and expect their own children to be even more upwardly mobile. They also experienced far less gender inequality than their parents did, and have become even more gender egalitarian as adults than they were as adolescents. Many of them have gone abroad, and many more hope to go abroad or send their children abroad.  All of these factors caused them to delay marriage and childbearing, which could halt their upwardly mobile trajectories by compelling them to invest in their childrenÆs education instead of their own educational and professional development. Those who did have children during our study faced tremendous pressure to invest unaffordably high amounts of time, attention, and money into their childrenÆs education from the moment their children were born, as standards for parental investment have increased even when compared to the intense parental investment these young adults experienced, which was far greater than what their parents experienced. These factors have made it likely that the generation born under ChinaÆs one-child policy will themselves have below-replacement fertility even though ChinaÆs policy now allows only-children to have two children.  Broader Impacts.   This research is important because it will help social scientists to understand the social dynamics of childbearing and childrearing at a time when issues of population pressure and population ageing are increasingly pressing worldwide. The research has also helped to bridge the divide between qualitative and quantitative scientific approaches to social research, using their complementary strengths to shed light on these pressing social problems.  By engaging students in  research and develop new educational programs, this award also supports expanded opportunities for interdisciplinary training for a new generation of social science researchers.  Data from this research was used for graduate and undergraduate student projects, undergraduate senior honors theses, and a doctoral dissertation. Participation in the research project helped these students learn to design research questions, transcribe and translate interview data, conduct qualitative  and quantitative analyses, and write papers and theses based on these analyses. Students have co-authored many articles with the PI based on data from this project.                   Last Modified: 08/14/2015       Submitted by: Vanessa L Fong]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
