<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>PostDoctoral Research Fellowship</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2013</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>150000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>150000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Fellowship Award</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DMS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Victor Roytburd</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>vroytbur@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032928584</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This award is made as part of the FY 2013 Mathematical Sciences Postdoctoral Research Fellowships Program. Each of the fellowships supports a research and training project at a host institution in the mathematical sciences, including applications to other disciplines, under the mentorship of a sponsoring scientist. . The title of the project for this fellowship to Theodore Johnson-Freyd is "Combinatorial and Topological Constructions of Batalin-Vilkovisky Quantum Field Theories." The host institution for the fellowship is Northwestern University, and the sponsoring scientist is Dr. Kevin Costello.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>03/27/2013</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>03/27/2013</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1304054</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Theodore</FirstName>
<LastName>Johnson-Freyd</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>P</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Theodore P Johnson-Freyd</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress/>
<PI_PHON>5419150578</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000629414</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>03/27/2013</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Johnson-Freyd, Theodore P</Name>
<CityName>BERKELEY</CityName>
<ZipCode>947203840</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber/>
<StreetAddress/>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>13</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CA13</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM/>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME/>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Northwestern University]]></Name>
<CityName>Evanston</CityName>
<StateCode>IL</StateCode>
<ZipCode>602082730</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Illinois</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>09</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>IL09</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7335</Code>
<Text>WORKFORCE IN THE MATHEMAT SCI</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9219</Code>
<Text>POSTDOCTORAL FELLOWSHIPS IN MATH SCIENCE</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0113</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2013~150000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>This project expanded the mathematical understanding of quantum gauge systems. Major results of the project included:</p> <ul> <li>The construction of topolical sigma models with Poisson target.</li> <li>The definition of ideals in derived algebra, and the subsquent definition of coisotropic structures in derived geometry as a type of Poisson ideals; the construction of Poisson topological sigma models with coisotropic boundary conditions.</li> <li>The identification of the quantization problem for Poisson topological sigma models with, on the one hand, the quantization problem for Poisson algebras and, on the other hand, the problem of providing a graph-level homotopy Poincare duality structure to the spacetime manifold.</li> <li>The discovery of an explicit obstruction to graph-level Poincare duality for the simplest manifold: the one-dimensional circle.</li> <li>The higher category theory necessary to define anomalous quantum field theories. The requisite notion involves "lax" natural transformations between functors of higher categories.</li> <li>The discovery that topological gauge theories with solvable gauge groups cannot exist in a non-derived universe.</li> <li>The description of 8-fold periodicity of (1+1)-dimensional fermionic systems in terms of supergeometric Hamiltonian reduction.</li> </ul> <p>These results contribute to an ongoing shift in theoretical physics from the infinite-dimensional manifolds and partial differential equations formerly used in path-integral quantization to a more homotopical and algebrogeometric picture.&nbsp;Quantum field theory has motivated great advances in low-dimensional, differential, and symplectic topology in spite of the inadequate mathematical foundations provided by path-integral quantization. The overarching intellectual merit of this project is that the shift to homotopical and algebrogeometric techniques help provide a much firmer foundation for physical methods.</p> <p>This project, by&nbsp;integrating ideas from physics and mathematics, is by nature interdisciplinary. This interdisciplinarity contributes to myriad broader impacts of the project: the mathematics of quantum field theory, and specifically of quantum gauge systems and of topological field theory, has direct applications to the study of condensed matter systems, quantum information, and high-energy physics, and is actively used in the engineering applications of these areas. Furthermore, the PI worked with undergraduate and graduate students as an instructor, mentor, and academic adviser; such contact helps not just to disseminate mathematical physics ideas, but to create future ideas.</p> <ul> </ul><br> <p>            Last Modified: 09/27/2017<br>      Modified by: Theodore&nbsp;P&nbsp;Johnson-Freyd</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ This project expanded the mathematical understanding of quantum gauge systems. Major results of the project included:  The construction of topolical sigma models with Poisson target. The definition of ideals in derived algebra, and the subsquent definition of coisotropic structures in derived geometry as a type of Poisson ideals; the construction of Poisson topological sigma models with coisotropic boundary conditions. The identification of the quantization problem for Poisson topological sigma models with, on the one hand, the quantization problem for Poisson algebras and, on the other hand, the problem of providing a graph-level homotopy Poincare duality structure to the spacetime manifold. The discovery of an explicit obstruction to graph-level Poincare duality for the simplest manifold: the one-dimensional circle. The higher category theory necessary to define anomalous quantum field theories. The requisite notion involves "lax" natural transformations between functors of higher categories. The discovery that topological gauge theories with solvable gauge groups cannot exist in a non-derived universe. The description of 8-fold periodicity of (1+1)-dimensional fermionic systems in terms of supergeometric Hamiltonian reduction.   These results contribute to an ongoing shift in theoretical physics from the infinite-dimensional manifolds and partial differential equations formerly used in path-integral quantization to a more homotopical and algebrogeometric picture. Quantum field theory has motivated great advances in low-dimensional, differential, and symplectic topology in spite of the inadequate mathematical foundations provided by path-integral quantization. The overarching intellectual merit of this project is that the shift to homotopical and algebrogeometric techniques help provide a much firmer foundation for physical methods.  This project, by integrating ideas from physics and mathematics, is by nature interdisciplinary. This interdisciplinarity contributes to myriad broader impacts of the project: the mathematics of quantum field theory, and specifically of quantum gauge systems and of topological field theory, has direct applications to the study of condensed matter systems, quantum information, and high-energy physics, and is actively used in the engineering applications of these areas. Furthermore, the PI worked with undergraduate and graduate students as an instructor, mentor, and academic adviser; such contact helps not just to disseminate mathematical physics ideas, but to create future ideas.         Last Modified: 09/27/2017       Submitted by: Theodore P Johnson-Freyd]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
