<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>RUI: Fluctuations and Phase Transitions in Iron Pnictide Superconductors</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>05/01/2013</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>04/30/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>185000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>185000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03070000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DMR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Materials Research</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Tomasz Durakiewicz</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>tdurakie@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924892</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>****Technical Abstract****&lt;br/&gt;This award supports experimental low-temperature physics research at an undergraduate institution. The scaling analysis of voltage vs. current curves has been an invaluable tool in the study of the normal-superconducting phase transition. However, recent work has shown that the conventional application of this tool is too flexible to uniquely determine the critical parameters, and that extrinsic effects can obscure or destroy the phase transition. With these caveats known, we have successfully applied this technique to study the hole-doped cuprate YBa2Cu3O7 and the electron-doped cuprate Pr2-xCexCuO4. This project will use the same technique to examine the phase transition in the new iron pnictide-122 superconductors (SrFe2As2 and BaFe2As2) both in a magnetic field and in zero magnetic field. This work will lead to an understanding of the model that governs the phase transition in this material and the differences and similarities of the phase transition between iron pnictide superconductors and other superconductors. This project will also train undergraduate students in experimental and low-temperature physics in preparation for graduate work or industry careers. In addition, to encourage broader education in science, this project will contribute to an existing outreach program with local public schools and submit video demonstrations to YouTube.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;****Non-Technical Abstract****&lt;br/&gt;This award supports experimental low-temperature physics research at an undergraduate institution. "High-Temperature" superconductors, discovered more than a quarter of a century ago, still hold great promise and great challenges. The promise lies in the hope of eventually making superconductors with much higher transition temperatures, and the challenges lie in the fact that we do not, even 25 years later, fully understand how or why these materials superconduct. Superconductors made from iron and arsenic, discovered in 2008, are the latest in an array of unusual materials to display superconductivity. This individual investigator award supports a project that will study how iron- and arsenic-based materials become superconducting, comparing them to copper-oxygen based superconductors and conventional, single element superconductors, all in the hopes of understanding the underlying mechanism that creates superconductivity in these materials. The proposed studies will add to the knowledge of high-temperature superconductors and help fulfill the promise of attaining higher transition temperatures. This project will also train undergraduate students in state-of-the-art sample growth, characterization, and measurement techniques. This project will also contribute to broader educational goals by fostering science outreach to local schools and promoting the research via online video demonstrations.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>05/13/2013</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/13/2013</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1305637</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Matthew</FirstName>
<LastName>Sullivan</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>C</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Matthew C Sullivan</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>mcsullivan@ithaca.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6072743964</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000241488</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/13/2013</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Ithaca College</Name>
<CityName>Ithaca</CityName>
<ZipCode>148507000</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6072741206</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>953 Danby Road</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>23</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NY23</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>041340159</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>ITHACA COLLEGE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>041340159</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Ithaca College]]></Name>
<CityName>Ithaca</CityName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<ZipCode>148507000</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>23</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NY23</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1710</Code>
<Text>CONDENSED MATTER PHYSICS</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9229</Code>
<Text>RES IN UNDERGRAD INST-RESEARCH</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0113</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2013~185000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The project studied the mechanism underlying the normal-superconducting phase transition in cobalt-doped BaFe2As2 superconductors.&nbsp; This grant supported the growth of cobalt-doped BaFe2As2 crystals and careful current vs. voltage measurements of the crystals at temperatures very near the normal-superconducting transition temperature.&nbsp; These measurements were conducted in both zero magnetic field and in low magnetic fields. &nbsp;&nbsp;To date, the research is inconclusive in its attempt to determine whether the electrons in the iron-based superconductors behaved like conventional superconductors or like the well-studied cuprate superconductors, and the mechanism for superconductivity in the iron-based superconductors remains a mystery.&nbsp;&nbsp; The Principal Investigators of this project will continue to analyze the measurements after the conclusion of the grant.</p> <p>This vast majority of this research was conducted at a primarily undergraduate institution.&nbsp; This project successfully trained ten undergraduate physics students in modern crystal growth, vacuum technology, and low-temperature experimental physics.&nbsp; Three students wrote their senior thesis based on research conducted related to this grant, and two of those students are now in Ph.D. programs for physics and materials science.&nbsp; In addition, five undergraduate students presented their research at national conferences of the American Physical Society, winning three awards for &ldquo;Best Undergraduate Research and Presentation.&rdquo;</p> <p>Finally, this project has worked to spread the knowledge of superconductors to audiences outside academia.&nbsp; This project supported a local outreach program run by the Principal Investigator.&nbsp; During the grant, the Principal Investigator visited five different schools, some of them multiple times, and presented the interactive outreach program &ldquo;Temperature and Heat&rdquo; to move than 500 local students from grades three to eight.&nbsp; In addition, the project supported training four different undergraduate students in the production of outreach videos.&nbsp; Ithaca College students produced five different outreach videos, all hosted on YouTube, which have a combined total of more than 400,000 views.&nbsp; These videos have successfully brought the science and technology of superconductivity to a global audience.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 08/22/2017<br>      Modified by: Matthew&nbsp;C&nbsp;Sullivan</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Image         </div> <div class="galControls onePhoto" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation onePhoto" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1305637/1305637_10245097_1503322781537_3pi_Movie_image--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1305637/1305637_10245097_1503322781537_3pi_Movie_image--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Outreach Video: 3-pi Mobius Strip Track"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1305637/1305637_10245097_1503322781537_3pi_Movie_image--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Outreach Video: 3-pi Mobius Strip Track"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">This video shows the outreach video we created to highlight the levitation and suspension properties of superconductors.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Ithaca College Physics</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Public Domain</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Matthew&nbsp;C&nbsp;Sullivan</div> <div class="imageTitle">Outreach Video: 3-pi Mobius Strip Track</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The project studied the mechanism underlying the normal-superconducting phase transition in cobalt-doped BaFe2As2 superconductors.  This grant supported the growth of cobalt-doped BaFe2As2 crystals and careful current vs. voltage measurements of the crystals at temperatures very near the normal-superconducting transition temperature.  These measurements were conducted in both zero magnetic field and in low magnetic fields.   To date, the research is inconclusive in its attempt to determine whether the electrons in the iron-based superconductors behaved like conventional superconductors or like the well-studied cuprate superconductors, and the mechanism for superconductivity in the iron-based superconductors remains a mystery.   The Principal Investigators of this project will continue to analyze the measurements after the conclusion of the grant.  This vast majority of this research was conducted at a primarily undergraduate institution.  This project successfully trained ten undergraduate physics students in modern crystal growth, vacuum technology, and low-temperature experimental physics.  Three students wrote their senior thesis based on research conducted related to this grant, and two of those students are now in Ph.D. programs for physics and materials science.  In addition, five undergraduate students presented their research at national conferences of the American Physical Society, winning three awards for "Best Undergraduate Research and Presentation."  Finally, this project has worked to spread the knowledge of superconductors to audiences outside academia.  This project supported a local outreach program run by the Principal Investigator.  During the grant, the Principal Investigator visited five different schools, some of them multiple times, and presented the interactive outreach program "Temperature and Heat" to move than 500 local students from grades three to eight.  In addition, the project supported training four different undergraduate students in the production of outreach videos.  Ithaca College students produced five different outreach videos, all hosted on YouTube, which have a combined total of more than 400,000 views.  These videos have successfully brought the science and technology of superconductivity to a global audience.       Last Modified: 08/22/2017       Submitted by: Matthew C Sullivan]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
