<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>CHIP SCALE MAGNETIC SENSOR ARRAYS BASED ON MAGNETOVISCOUS EFFECT OF FERROFLUIDS</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>05/15/2013</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>04/30/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>330000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>330000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07010000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>ECCS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Electrical, Commun &amp; Cyber Sys</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Usha Varshney</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>uvarshne@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032925385</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This project will investigate the design and implementation of a novel magnetometer array capable of picoTesla magnetic field sensitivity at room temperature. The principle of operation of the magnetic sensor is based on the sensitive monitoring of the magnetoviscous effects in ferrofluids using micromachined, shear mode, bulk acoustic wave resonators. The uniqueness is in the exploitation of, hitherto unexplored, response of a ferrofluid atop a high-frequency shear wave resonator to externally applied magnetic field that is sensitively monitored through the at-resonance impedance characteristics of the resonator. Ferrofluids consist of ~10 nm sized ferri- or ferro-magnetic nanoparticles suspended in a carrier liquid. Interaction of the ferrofluid nanoparticles with the surface of the resonator is considered to result in the formation of a dense magnetic double layer at the interface with a high magnetic susceptibility. Application of external magnetic fields results in changes in magnetoviscosity of the magnetic double layer at the resonator-ferrofluid interface and can be accurately monitored using micromachined quartz resonators. High frequency micromachined quartz resonators are highly sensitive to small changes in the viscoelastic loading at the resonator surface and can be used for the quantification of the magnetoviscous effect and is the working principle of the magnetometer proposed here.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Intellectual Merit: The proposed work aims at exploring the interaction of high frequency shear waves and magnetic fields on the spontaneous organization of ferromagnetic nanoparticles suspended in a fluid medium focusing specifically on the immediate layers adjacent to the resonator surface. The proposed experiments and model development will attempt to explore the interfacial origins of the phenomenon of magnetoviscosity. Combining real-time viscoelastic measurements with magnetic flux concentrator structures will provide the designs for realizing high-sensitivity magnetic sensors capable of vector measurements of magnetic field and a greater understanding of the magneto-rheological effects. Current experimental techniques on ferrofluids employ shear rates that are five orders of magnitude lower and preclude such interfacial investigations on ferrofluids. This work will demonstrate high-sensitivity, chip-scale, magnetometer arrays capable of resolving pico-Tesla magnetic field vectors.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Broader Impact: This project will explore the basic interaction of acoustic waves, magnetic fields, and ferromagnetic nanoparticles in a fluid. A deeper understanding of this phenomenon will provide the tools for understanding the role of thermal energy, dipole interaction energy, and hydrodynamic forces on nanoparticles. This work will elucidate the relationship between the observed rheological properties of the ferrofluids and the agglomeration characteristics of the nanoparticles at ferrofluid-resonator interface. The successful development of the integrated sensors in this proposal has the potential to revolutionize the biomagnetic field detection and imaging. The potential impact of this technology on life science research and functional brain imaging, in particular, is immeasurable because it creates an opportunity to produce an array of portable devices operating at room temperature that are currently unavailable. In addition to supporting graduate student training the proposed work includes the creation of demonstration models using ferrofluids to demonstrate magnetic fields, dipoles and nanoparticle concepts to K-5 students.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>05/09/2013</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/09/2013</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1305653</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Srinivas</FirstName>
<LastName>Tadigadapa</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Srinivas Tadigadapa</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>srinivas@ece.neu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6173737529</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000330855</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/09/2013</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Pennsylvania State Univ University Park</Name>
<CityName>University Park</CityName>
<ZipCode>168021503</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>8148651372</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>201 Old Main</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Pennsylvania</StateName>
<StateCode>PA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>PA05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>003403953</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>PENNSYLVANIA STATE UNIVERSITY, THE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>003403953</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Pennsylvania State Univ University Park]]></Name>
<CityName>University Park</CityName>
<StateCode>PA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>168021503</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[201 Old Main]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Pennsylvania</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>PA05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1517</Code>
<Text>EPMD-ElectrnPhoton&amp;MagnDevices</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>108E</Code>
<Text>Bioelectronics</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0113</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2013~330000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>In this work we explored a novel concept for magnetic sensing that is based upon the sensitive monitoring of the magnetoviscous effects in ferrofluids using micromachined, shear mode, bulk acoustic wave resonators. The uniqueness of the work is in the exploitation of, hitherto unexplored, response of a ferrofluid atop a high-frequency shear wave resonator to externally applied magnetic field that was sensitively monitored through the at-resonance impedance characteristics of the resonator.<em> </em>We have previously shown that the high frequency micromachined quartz resonators are highly sensitive to small changes in the viscoelastic loading on the resonator surface and can be used for highly sensitive quantification of the magnetoviscous effect and is the working principle of the magnetometer investigated here. For improved sensitivity, the in-plane sensed magnetic flux density was concentrated using a high relative permeability thin film of Metglas<sup>&reg;</sup> (Fe<sub>85</sub>B<sub>5</sub>Si<sub>10</sub>) deposited on the resonator electrode. Furthermore, by patterning the Metglas<sup>&reg;</sup> film in a bow-tie shape and aligned at the center of the &micro;QCR electrode, both 2D vector sensing as well as improvement in the sensitivity was achieved. Using these improvements, a minimum detectable field of 1.5 nT/&radic;Hz at 1 Hz was experimentally demonstrated. Although the magnetometer concept worked well, the oil base of the ferrofluid was found to continuously evaporate with time and resulted in sensor drift that was difficult to compensate. Thus, we made a change in the approach to the project and explored two new concepts of micromachined magnetometers.</p> <p>In the first modified approach, we explored a mechanism for magnetic field sensing based on magnetoflexoelastic effect. The magnetic sensor consists of a micromachined quartz bulk acoustic wave (BAW) resonator coated with a thin film of Fe<sub>85</sub>B<sub>5</sub>Si<sub>10 </sub>and configured as a unimorph plate fixed at one end. Externally applied magnetic field strains the magnetostrictive layer which is elastically coupled to the quartz BAW resonator. The resulting out-of-plane bending of the laminate plate structure causes the resonance frequency to shift and consequently changes the at-resonance admittance characteristics of the resonator. This effect where out-of-plane flexure of a quartz resonator results in a frequency shift due to coupling of the induced strain and strain gradients through third order elastic coefficients can be defined as the flexoelastic effect or the force-frequency effect . When the flexure in the plate resonator structure is induced magnetostrictively, the effect can be termed as magnetoflexoelastic effect. Frequency shifts are proportionally correlated to the applied magnetic flux density. High quality factor 7.5 um thick, AT-cut quartz plate resonator with 500 nm thick magnetostrictive Metglas<sup>&reg;</sup> layer forming a laminate heterostructure was fabricated and demonstrated as a magnetic sensor. Experimental results showed a minimum detectable magnetic flux density of ~79 nT modulated at 10 Hz. Further optimization of the device structure can achieve sensitivities into the picoTesla range and operating at room temperature. As opposed to the ME laminates these sensors are an order of magnitude smaller in size and can be fabricated in large arrays using microfabrication techniques.</p> <p>In a second alternative approach, a novel magnetometer consisting of chip-scale whispering gallery mode resonators with high<em>-Q</em> factors (&gt;10<sup>6</sup>) realized using MEMs fabrication techniques was demonstrated. A permanent magnet is elastically coupled to a whispering gallery mode borosilicate microbubble. Magnetic force from applied external magnetic fields induces deformation in the microbubble which can be sensitively monitored through changes in the optical resonance characteristics. We calculated the force and simulate the deformation in the microbubble. The effect of different permanent magnet orientations and microbubble shell thickness was experimentally investigated and modelled. We experimentally demonstrated a large sensitivity of 1.9 GHz/mT on a microbubble with 1.1 &micro;m shell thickness. Operating at minimum gain on the photodiode and assuming a perfectly stable laser and environmental noise compensation on the WGM the limit if detection of this setup can be as low as 100 pT/&radic;Hz. A photodetector operating off a DC battery may offer even lower noise, pushing the noise floor lower.</p> <p>In summary, the project explored three new concepts of micromachined magnetometers. One student was fully supported through this project and three additional graduate Ph.D. students were partially supported through this grant. A total of five peer reviewed journal papers and seven peer reviewed conference papers have been published. Two further peer reviewed journal publications are currently in preparation.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 08/17/2017<br>      Modified by: Srinivas&nbsp;Tadigadapa</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Images (<span id="selectedPhoto0">1</span> of <span class="totalNumber"></span>)           </div> <div class="galControls" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1305653/1305653_10244487_1503010224566_MagnetoviscousSensor--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1305653/1305653_10244487_1503010224566_MagnetoviscousSensor--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Magnetoviscous Ferrofluid Magnetometer"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1305653/1305653_10244487_1503010224566_MagnetoviscousSensor--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Magnetoviscous Ferrofluid Magnetometer"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">(a)Schematic illustration of a magnetoviscous ferrofluid magnetometer. (b) Obtained Experimental Response, (c) Sensitivity Graph</div> <div class="imageCredit">Gokhan Hatipoglu, Srinivas Tadigadapa</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Srinivas&nbsp;Tadigadapa</div> <div class="imageTitle">Magnetoviscous Ferrofluid Magnetometer</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1305653/1305653_10244487_1503010417872_APLFig1--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1305653/1305653_10244487_1503010417872_APLFig1--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Magnetoflexoelastic Magnetometer"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1305653/1305653_10244487_1503010417872_APLFig1--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Magnetoflexoelastic Magnetometer"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">(a) Oblique schematic view of the micromachined quartz resonator with a circular inverted mesa design. (b) Shows the top view and sectional view drawn along the dotted line AA?. Various structural parameters are also labeled. (c) SEM photograph of the fabricated micromachined quartz resonator with u</div> <div class="imageCredit">Applied Physics Letters</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Srinivas&nbsp;Tadigadapa</div> <div class="imageTitle">Magnetoflexoelastic Magnetometer</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ In this work we explored a novel concept for magnetic sensing that is based upon the sensitive monitoring of the magnetoviscous effects in ferrofluids using micromachined, shear mode, bulk acoustic wave resonators. The uniqueness of the work is in the exploitation of, hitherto unexplored, response of a ferrofluid atop a high-frequency shear wave resonator to externally applied magnetic field that was sensitively monitored through the at-resonance impedance characteristics of the resonator. We have previously shown that the high frequency micromachined quartz resonators are highly sensitive to small changes in the viscoelastic loading on the resonator surface and can be used for highly sensitive quantification of the magnetoviscous effect and is the working principle of the magnetometer investigated here. For improved sensitivity, the in-plane sensed magnetic flux density was concentrated using a high relative permeability thin film of Metglas&reg; (Fe85B5Si10) deposited on the resonator electrode. Furthermore, by patterning the Metglas&reg; film in a bow-tie shape and aligned at the center of the &micro;QCR electrode, both 2D vector sensing as well as improvement in the sensitivity was achieved. Using these improvements, a minimum detectable field of 1.5 nT/&radic;Hz at 1 Hz was experimentally demonstrated. Although the magnetometer concept worked well, the oil base of the ferrofluid was found to continuously evaporate with time and resulted in sensor drift that was difficult to compensate. Thus, we made a change in the approach to the project and explored two new concepts of micromachined magnetometers.  In the first modified approach, we explored a mechanism for magnetic field sensing based on magnetoflexoelastic effect. The magnetic sensor consists of a micromachined quartz bulk acoustic wave (BAW) resonator coated with a thin film of Fe85B5Si10 and configured as a unimorph plate fixed at one end. Externally applied magnetic field strains the magnetostrictive layer which is elastically coupled to the quartz BAW resonator. The resulting out-of-plane bending of the laminate plate structure causes the resonance frequency to shift and consequently changes the at-resonance admittance characteristics of the resonator. This effect where out-of-plane flexure of a quartz resonator results in a frequency shift due to coupling of the induced strain and strain gradients through third order elastic coefficients can be defined as the flexoelastic effect or the force-frequency effect . When the flexure in the plate resonator structure is induced magnetostrictively, the effect can be termed as magnetoflexoelastic effect. Frequency shifts are proportionally correlated to the applied magnetic flux density. High quality factor 7.5 um thick, AT-cut quartz plate resonator with 500 nm thick magnetostrictive Metglas&reg; layer forming a laminate heterostructure was fabricated and demonstrated as a magnetic sensor. Experimental results showed a minimum detectable magnetic flux density of ~79 nT modulated at 10 Hz. Further optimization of the device structure can achieve sensitivities into the picoTesla range and operating at room temperature. As opposed to the ME laminates these sensors are an order of magnitude smaller in size and can be fabricated in large arrays using microfabrication techniques.  In a second alternative approach, a novel magnetometer consisting of chip-scale whispering gallery mode resonators with high-Q factors (&gt;106) realized using MEMs fabrication techniques was demonstrated. A permanent magnet is elastically coupled to a whispering gallery mode borosilicate microbubble. Magnetic force from applied external magnetic fields induces deformation in the microbubble which can be sensitively monitored through changes in the optical resonance characteristics. We calculated the force and simulate the deformation in the microbubble. The effect of different permanent magnet orientations and microbubble shell thickness was experimentally investigated and modelled. We experimentally demonstrated a large sensitivity of 1.9 GHz/mT on a microbubble with 1.1 &micro;m shell thickness. Operating at minimum gain on the photodiode and assuming a perfectly stable laser and environmental noise compensation on the WGM the limit if detection of this setup can be as low as 100 pT/&radic;Hz. A photodetector operating off a DC battery may offer even lower noise, pushing the noise floor lower.  In summary, the project explored three new concepts of micromachined magnetometers. One student was fully supported through this project and three additional graduate Ph.D. students were partially supported through this grant. A total of five peer reviewed journal papers and seven peer reviewed conference papers have been published. Two further peer reviewed journal publications are currently in preparation.          Last Modified: 08/17/2017       Submitted by: Srinivas Tadigadapa]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
