<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Electronic and Atomistic Effects in Nanostructures</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2013</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>560000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>615000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03070000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DMR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Materials Research</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Germano Iannacchione</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>giannacc@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032920000</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>****Technical Abstract****&lt;br/&gt;This project is a study of the atomic-scale structure and behavior of composite systems that are prepared by atomic deposition, artificial layering, and thermal processing of metals on the most important electronic substrate materials, including silicon, germanium, and silicon carbide, that are flat, stepped, or decorated by atomic wires. The deposited metals, amounting to few atomic layers thick, tend to self-organize into nanoscale features, such as atomic wires, stripes, mesas, pyramids, or even ultrasmooth films, because of quantum confinement and boundary effects. These nanostructures often exhibit unusual properties that are not intuitively connected to the behavior of the metals in the bulk form. The underlying nanoscale science is a key basis for developing new material and device configurations relevant to technological and industrial advances. The research will focus on the connections between the stability, shapes, and sizes of the nanostructures and the electronic structure and chemical properties of the system, with the intent to derive a general understanding and design rules for guiding system fabrication and functionalization. The experimental tools will include angle-resolved photoemission spectroscopy and x-ray diffraction, and much of the work will be performed at national synchrotron-radiation facilities. This research bridges basic science and applications, and provides opportunities for education and training of students, postdoctoral research associates, and visiting scholars in the use of modern tools for materials synthesis and characterization. The experiences will position them well for careers in scientific research, education, technology, and industry.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;****Non-Technical Abstract****&lt;br/&gt;This project is a study of the atomic-scale structure and behavior of composite systems prepared by atomic deposition, artificial layering, and controlled heat treatment of metals on the most common electronic substrate materials including silicon, germanium, and silicon carbide. The deposited metals, amounting to few atomic layers thick, tend to naturally develop nanoscale features such as atomic wires, stripes, mesas, pyramids, or even ultrasmooth films. These nanostructures often exhibit unusual properties that are not observed in the bulk form of these materials. The underlying nanoscale science is a key basis for developing new materials and device configurations for industry. The research will focus on the connections between the stability, shapes, and sizes of the nanostructures and the electronic structure and chemical properties of the system, with the intent to derive a general understanding and design rules to guide the development of new functional materials. The experiments will be performed at national synchrotron radiation facilities, which provide intense x-rays for probing the systems of interest. This research bridges basic science and applications, and provides opportunities for education and training of students, postdoctoral research associates, and visiting scholars in the use of modern tools for materials synthesis and characterization. The experiences will position them well for careers in scientific research, education, technology, and industry.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/21/2013</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/09/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1305583</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Tai</FirstName>
<LastName>Chiang</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>C</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Tai C Chiang</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>tcchiang@illinois.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2173332593</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000462954</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/21/2013</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Thomas</FirstName>
<LastName>Miller</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>J</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Thomas J Miller</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>tamille1@facstaff.wisc.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6088772342</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000390173</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/21/2013</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign</Name>
<CityName>Champaign</CityName>
<ZipCode>618207406</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2173332187</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1901 South First Street</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[Suite A]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Illinois</StateName>
<StateCode>IL</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>13</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>IL13</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>041544081</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF ILLINOIS</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>041544081</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign]]></Name>
<CityName>Urbana</CityName>
<StateCode>IL</StateCode>
<ZipCode>618013003</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[1110 West Green Street]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Illinois</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>13</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>IL13</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1710</Code>
<Text>CONDENSED MATTER PHYSICS</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7237</Code>
<Text>NANO NON-SOLIC SCI &amp; ENG AWD</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7644</Code>
<Text>ENERGY FOR SUSTAINABILITY</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0113</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0114</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0115</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0116</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2013~180000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~185000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2015~130000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2016~120000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Understanding the physics and chemistry of surfaces and interfaces is critical to a wide range of scientific and technological issues in connection with working in the quantum, nano, and meso regimes. This project is a study of the electronic structure, morphology, stability, and atomistic behavior of selected surface-based nanoscale systems prepared by deposition, artificial layering, self-assembly, and self-organization. The systems of interest include various elemental and alloy films prepared on surfaces that are smooth, stepped, or modulated by nanowire arrays. The systems are chosen for their broad scientific and technological relevance. Specifically, stepped and modulated surfaces provide opportunities of property tuning by controlling the Fermi surface topology. The primary tools for the proposed work include angle-resolved photoemission spectroscopy (ARPES) and x-ray diffraction and scattering (XRD). Many of the experiments are carried out at national facilities. Generally, electrons confined in nanoscale systems form discrete states, or quantum well states, with energies and wave functions dependent sensitively on the physical dimensions and boundary conditions. As a result, the electronic properties including the total energy, charge and spin distributions, density of states, and electronic transport can exhibit substantial quantum variations as a function of system size and environment. The lattice structure in turn responds to these variations, possibly leading to structural distortions, symmetry-breaking transformations, and novel configurations. These electron-lattice coupling effects are strongly enhanced at the nanoscale partly because of quantum coherence and interference. Additionally, as the solid-vacuum boundaries are often soft, the atoms and the accompanying electrons may readily morph or diffuse to adopt new configurations corresponding to the local minima in a complex multi-dimensional free-energy landscape. Such electronically driven transformations are enhanced at elevated temperatures, where fluctuation, entropy, and kinetic effects come into play. The system may undergo atomic reorganization and structural evolution with details that are difficult to predict based on the known bulk behavior alone. These effects and phenomena, of central importance to nano and mesoscale science and technology, are the focus of our research. Our work has focused on several selected model systems that are particularly well suited for establishing the general scientific principles as outlined above. The specific results have been published in open journals and covered in public lectures.&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 08/05/2017<br>      Modified by: Tai&nbsp;C&nbsp;Chiang</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Image         </div> <div class="galControls onePhoto" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation onePhoto" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1305583/1305583_10253483_1501971779289_graphics--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1305583/1305583_10253483_1501971779289_graphics--rgov-800width.jpg" title="graphics"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1305583/1305583_10253483_1501971779289_graphics--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="graphics"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Growth by molecular beam epitaxy (MBE) of Si on Ag(111) results in a two-dimensional film with (?3 × ?3) surface structure at near monolayer (ML) coverage. The same (?3 × ?3) pattern persists for coverages of Si up to several MLs. The atomic structure of the resulting Si film has posed an intriguing</div> <div class="imageCredit">Han-De Chen, Ko-Hsiang Chie, Cho-Ying Lin, Tai-Chang Chiang, and Deng-Sung Lin, J. Phys. Chem. C, 2016, 120 (5), pp 2698?2702</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Tai&nbsp;C&nbsp;Chiang</div> <div class="imageTitle">graphics</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Understanding the physics and chemistry of surfaces and interfaces is critical to a wide range of scientific and technological issues in connection with working in the quantum, nano, and meso regimes. This project is a study of the electronic structure, morphology, stability, and atomistic behavior of selected surface-based nanoscale systems prepared by deposition, artificial layering, self-assembly, and self-organization. The systems of interest include various elemental and alloy films prepared on surfaces that are smooth, stepped, or modulated by nanowire arrays. The systems are chosen for their broad scientific and technological relevance. Specifically, stepped and modulated surfaces provide opportunities of property tuning by controlling the Fermi surface topology. The primary tools for the proposed work include angle-resolved photoemission spectroscopy (ARPES) and x-ray diffraction and scattering (XRD). Many of the experiments are carried out at national facilities. Generally, electrons confined in nanoscale systems form discrete states, or quantum well states, with energies and wave functions dependent sensitively on the physical dimensions and boundary conditions. As a result, the electronic properties including the total energy, charge and spin distributions, density of states, and electronic transport can exhibit substantial quantum variations as a function of system size and environment. The lattice structure in turn responds to these variations, possibly leading to structural distortions, symmetry-breaking transformations, and novel configurations. These electron-lattice coupling effects are strongly enhanced at the nanoscale partly because of quantum coherence and interference. Additionally, as the solid-vacuum boundaries are often soft, the atoms and the accompanying electrons may readily morph or diffuse to adopt new configurations corresponding to the local minima in a complex multi-dimensional free-energy landscape. Such electronically driven transformations are enhanced at elevated temperatures, where fluctuation, entropy, and kinetic effects come into play. The system may undergo atomic reorganization and structural evolution with details that are difficult to predict based on the known bulk behavior alone. These effects and phenomena, of central importance to nano and mesoscale science and technology, are the focus of our research. Our work has focused on several selected model systems that are particularly well suited for establishing the general scientific principles as outlined above. The specific results have been published in open journals and covered in public lectures.        Last Modified: 08/05/2017       Submitted by: Tai C Chiang]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
