<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Moduli spaces, Extremality and Global Invariants</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>04/15/2013</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>03/31/2014</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>110000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>110000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DMS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Joanna Kania-Bartoszynska</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>jkaniaba@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924881</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The spring 2013 semester of the Centre des Recherches Mathematiques (CRM) theme year "Moduli Spaces, Extremality and Global Invariants" is organized around five sets of focused activities staged between April 30 and July 12, 2013 at the CRM on the campus of the Universite de Montreal: 1) J-holomorphic Curves in Symplectic Geometry, Topology and Dynamics, April 30-May 11, 2013: workshop, two mini-courses, Aisenstadt Chair lectures given by Helmut Hofer (IAS); 2) The Topology of 3-dimensional Manifolds, May 6-17, 2013: workshop, three mini-courses given by Ian Agol (Berkeley), Tao Li (Boston College), and Juan Souto (University of British Columbia)), Aisenstadt Chair lectures given by David Gabai (Princeton); 3) Extremal Kahler Metrics, May 26-June 1, 2013: workshop, Aisenstadt Chair lectures Gang Tian (Princeton and Peking); 4) Moduli Spaces and their Invariants in Mathematical Physics, June 3-14, 2013: workshop; 5) Low-dimensional Topology after Floer, July 8-12, 2013: workshop.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The semester will present the state of the art in a number of currently active areas of research in geometry and topology. Beyond providing a vehicle for communicating the most significant new research results, one of the principal objectives is to stimulate new ideas through cross-fertilization between the different domains represented. We will also focus our energies on providing an environment in which young researchers can immerse themselves in contemporary research trends. The junior participants will interact with not only the leaders in their fields, but also with the brightest students, postdoctoral fellows and junior faculty worldwide. Information on registration, accommodations, financial support, and scheduling can be found at&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;http://www.crm.umontreal.ca/Geometry2012/index.php/</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>04/04/2013</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>04/04/2013</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1305448</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Alan</FirstName>
<LastName>Reid</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>W</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Alan W Reid</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>alan.reid@rice.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>7133484829</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000280989</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/04/2013</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Claude</FirstName>
<LastName>LeBrun</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Claude LeBrun</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>claude@math.sunysb.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5166212903</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000375046</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/04/2013</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Denis</FirstName>
<LastName>Auroux</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Denis Auroux</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>auroux@math.harvard.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6174955487</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000544461</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/04/2013</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Steven</FirstName>
<LastName>Boyer</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Steven Boyer</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>steven.boyer@uqam.ca</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5149873000</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000631173</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/04/2013</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Texas at Austin</Name>
<CityName>Austin</CityName>
<ZipCode>787595316</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5124716424</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>3925 W Braker Lane, Ste 3.340</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Texas</StateName>
<StateCode>TX</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>10</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>TX10</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>170230239</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF TEXAS AT AUSTIN</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>042000273</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Texas at Austin]]></Name>
<CityName>Austin</CityName>
<StateCode>TX</StateCode>
<ZipCode>787595316</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[3925 W Braker Lane, Ste 3.340]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Texas</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>10</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>TX10</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1267</Code>
<Text>TOPOLOGY</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7556</Code>
<Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0113</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2013~110000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>This award was to help support young american mathematicans to travel to particpate in workshops, and summer schools attached to a special semester (Moduli Spaces, Extremality and Global Invariants) in Montreal.&nbsp;&nbsp;</p> <p>As well as support from NSF, funding for the semester's activities is provided by the CRM through its thematic program. CIRGET, the geometry-topology lab of the CRM, has also contributed significant financial and organizational resources to the events. The SMS summer school is funded by the Canadian Mathematical Institutes (CRM, Fields, PIMS) together with the MSRI. It also receives the support of the Simons Foundation, the ISM, the UdeM, as well as that of the Canadian Mathematical Society.</p> <p>The&nbsp; title for this special semester, reflects the theme of the study of the geometry of certain spaces, how these spaces relate to each other, invariants of these spaces and how these spaces arise in physics. The events that took place were:</p> <p>&nbsp;J-holomorphic Curves in Symplectic Geometry, Topology and Dynamics, April 30--May 11, 2013: workshop, two mini-courses.</p> <p>&nbsp;The Topology of 3-dimensional Manifolds, May 6--17, 2013: workshop, three mini-courses.</p> <p>Extremal Kahler Metrics, May 26--June 1, 2013: workshop.</p> <p>Moduli Spaces and their Invariants in Mathematical Physics, June 3--14, 2013: workshop.</p> <p>The Physics and Mathematics of Link Homologies}, June 28--July 5, 2013: SMS summer school.</p> <p>&nbsp;Low-dimensional Topology after Floer, July 8--12, 2013: workshop.</p> <p>The workshops and summer schools featured distinguished lecture series (the Aisenstadt Chairs), as well as talks by junior and mid career mathematicians.</p> <p>Beyond presenting the latest results, the program&nbsp; provided an ideal opportunity for interaction between the different domains represented and created an environment for young researchers to immerse themselves in contemporary research trends. Thus&nbsp; junior participants&nbsp; interacted with not only the leaders in their fields, but also with the brightest students, postdoctoral fellows and junior faculty worldwide. These contacts will serve them throughout their careers.</p> <p>Intellectual Merit:&nbsp; The areas of focus continue to be focal points of research in 21st century mathematics.&nbsp; The workshop sought to bring students, postdocs and senior people in the field to help disseminate new results and techniques.</p> <p>Broader Impact: The areas of focus have connections to many discplines: for example to physics, biology and computer science to name a few.&nbsp; The talks and interaction held at the workshops set the platform to train and prepare future generations to build on these connections.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 05/24/2014<br>      Modified by: Alan&nbsp;W&nbsp;Reid</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ This award was to help support young american mathematicans to travel to particpate in workshops, and summer schools attached to a special semester (Moduli Spaces, Extremality and Global Invariants) in Montreal.    As well as support from NSF, funding for the semester's activities is provided by the CRM through its thematic program. CIRGET, the geometry-topology lab of the CRM, has also contributed significant financial and organizational resources to the events. The SMS summer school is funded by the Canadian Mathematical Institutes (CRM, Fields, PIMS) together with the MSRI. It also receives the support of the Simons Foundation, the ISM, the UdeM, as well as that of the Canadian Mathematical Society.  The  title for this special semester, reflects the theme of the study of the geometry of certain spaces, how these spaces relate to each other, invariants of these spaces and how these spaces arise in physics. The events that took place were:   J-holomorphic Curves in Symplectic Geometry, Topology and Dynamics, April 30--May 11, 2013: workshop, two mini-courses.   The Topology of 3-dimensional Manifolds, May 6--17, 2013: workshop, three mini-courses.  Extremal Kahler Metrics, May 26--June 1, 2013: workshop.  Moduli Spaces and their Invariants in Mathematical Physics, June 3--14, 2013: workshop.  The Physics and Mathematics of Link Homologies}, June 28--July 5, 2013: SMS summer school.   Low-dimensional Topology after Floer, July 8--12, 2013: workshop.  The workshops and summer schools featured distinguished lecture series (the Aisenstadt Chairs), as well as talks by junior and mid career mathematicians.  Beyond presenting the latest results, the program  provided an ideal opportunity for interaction between the different domains represented and created an environment for young researchers to immerse themselves in contemporary research trends. Thus  junior participants  interacted with not only the leaders in their fields, but also with the brightest students, postdoctoral fellows and junior faculty worldwide. These contacts will serve them throughout their careers.  Intellectual Merit:  The areas of focus continue to be focal points of research in 21st century mathematics.  The workshop sought to bring students, postdocs and senior people in the field to help disseminate new results and techniques.  Broader Impact: The areas of focus have connections to many discplines: for example to physics, biology and computer science to name a few.  The talks and interaction held at the workshops set the platform to train and prepare future generations to build on these connections.       Last Modified: 05/24/2014       Submitted by: Alan W Reid]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
