<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Bacterial Photosynthetic Pathways Probed by Two-Dimensional Electronic Spectroscopy</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2013</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2016</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>420000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>420000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03010000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>PHY</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Physics</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Krastan Blagoev</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>kblagoev@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924666</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>With this award the PI will employ two-dimensional electronic spectroscopy (2DES) to investigate the underlying physical mechanisms governing the directional ultrafast transfer of energy between the antennae and reaction centers of photosynthetic purple bacteria. The program of research will both push the capabilities of 2DES as a powerful and quantitative method for studying natural photosynthetic systems, and use 2DES to address open questions about photosynthesis in purple bacteria. Specifically, this research aims to answer the following questions: 1) What are the roles of vibrational and electronic coherence in energy transfer and charge separation in purple bacteria? 2) How do purple bacteria remodel their energy-landscape to regulate energy transfer under high and low light conditions? This research aims to extend the capabilities of 2DES spectroscopy to perform the first 2DES experiments on single crystals of photosynthetic complexes as well as the first 2DES experiments on whole cells. Improvements in the capabilities of 2DES, and its ability to provide feedback to theoretical modeling of energy transfer and charge separation in purple bacteria as a model system will ultimately pave the way for a better understanding of the more complex plant photosystems. Understanding the role of coherence in photosynthetic energy transfer and charge separation may drive the development of new theoretical models of these processes. The award also aims to promote a positive image of science through public education, and in particular to encourage women and minorities to enter careers in science through outreach activities and mentored undergraduate research.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project is being jointly supported by the Physics of Living Systems program in the Division of Physics and the Molecular Biophysics Program in the Division of Molecular and Cellular Biosciences.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/06/2013</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/14/2015</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1305450</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Jennifer</FirstName>
<LastName>Ogilvie</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>P</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Jennifer P Ogilvie</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>jogilvie@umich.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>7347641817</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000330322</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/06/2013</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Regents of the University of Michigan - Ann Arbor</Name>
<CityName>Ann Arbor</CityName>
<ZipCode>481091274</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>7347636438</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>3003 South State St. Room 1062</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Michigan</StateName>
<StateCode>MI</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>12</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MI12</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>073133571</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>REGENTS OF THE UNIVERSITY OF MICHIGAN</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>073133571</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Michigan, Department of Physics and Biophysics]]></Name>
<CityName>Ann Arbor</CityName>
<StateCode>MI</StateCode>
<ZipCode>481091040</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[450 Church St]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Michigan</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>12</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MI12</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7246</Code>
<Text>PHYSICS OF LIVING SYSTEMS</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7275</Code>
<Text>Cross-BIO Activities</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7237</Code>
<Text>NANO NON-SOLIC SCI &amp; ENG AWD</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7246</Code>
<Text>PHYSICS OF LIVING SYSTEMS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8007</Code>
<Text>BioMaPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9183</Code>
<Text>GENERAL FOUNDATIONS OF BIOTECHNOLOGY</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0113</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0114</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0115</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2013~240000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~40000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2015~140000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>&nbsp;</p> <p>Photosynthetic organisms employ an elaborate architecture of antenna arrays to gather solar energy and transfer it to photochemical reaction centers for conversion to stable charge separation. The processes of photosynthetic energy transfer and charge separation occur with near unit quantum efficiency. Underlying this stunning efficiency is the energy landscape that provides ultrafast directional transfer of energy from antennae to reaction centers, and directional electron transfer within reaction centers. Understanding the design principles of natural photosynthesis could enable us to design the next generation of artificial light-harvesting materials. Two-dimensional electronic spectroscopy (2DES) has proven to be a powerful tool for studying photosynthetic energy transfer and charge separation. With ultrafast time resolution, it reveals coupling between the components of photosynthetic systems, allowing the elucidation of energy transfer pathways and mechanisms. Previous 2DES studies of photosynthetic antennae complexes have revealed puzzling long-lived coherent dynamics. The physical origin and possible functional relevance of these coherences continues to be hotly debated. Supported by this project we have performed the first 2DES studies of charge separation in the bacterial reaction center (BRC). Our 2DES data has enabled us to refine excitonic models of the system and to distinguish between proposed charge separation mechanisms. We have also observed coherent dynamics in the BRC, as well as in monomer photosynthetic pigments and have determined the physical origin of the coherent dynamics. Work is ongoing to use models developed by optimizing fits to our 2DES data to assess the functional relevance of the coherent processes in the BRC.</p> <p>Supported by this project we have also developed a rapid and high signal-to-noise approach for the characterization of coherent dynamics, which we call two-color rapid acquisition coherence spectroscopy (T-RACS). We have demonstrated the method in a study of chlorophyll a and have shown that the T-RACS approach can selectively detect particular coherences and distinguish between ground and excited state coherence.</p> <p>Two-dimensional electronic spectroscopy is now being used worldwide in a broad range of research. The technical barriers to implementing 2DES have thus far limited the number of groups employing the method. We have extensively reviewed the different experimental implementations of 2DES, describing each method, how it has been used, and the advantages and disadvantages of the approach in comparison to other implementations. Our work provides a guide for researchers entering the field to enable them to make the best choice of implementation for their application.&nbsp;</p> <p>The broader impacts of this project include enhancing our experimental and theoretical tools for understanding energy transfer and charge separation in natural and artificial systems. Our measurements provide new data that can guide the improvement of theoretical modeling of energy transfer and charge separation in bacterial photosystems, ultimately paving the way for a better understanding of plant photosystems and artificial light-harvesting materials. <strong>&nbsp;</strong></p> <p>This project supported the extensive training of graduate and undergraduate students, teaching them a wide range of skills, from the design of optical experiments, the hardware interfacing required for data acquisition, to data-taking and analysis, and scientific communication. The project also supported the PI and her graduate students to host the 2015 APS Conference for Undergraduate Women in Physics (CUWiP) at the University of Michigan. Our three-day meeting hosted 134 undergraduate women from the Midwest and beyond, educating them about career opportunities and research in Physics and helping strengthen the network of women in Physics in the US. The PI has also served on the CUWiP National Organizing Committee and the Site Selection Committee for the 2016 meetings. The PI and her group have been active in other outreach activities, including lab tours to economically disadvantaged students, a day of science for K-6 Girl Scouts and Physics Demo Day at a local middle school.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 09/18/2017<br>      Modified by: Jennifer&nbsp;P&nbsp;Ogilvie</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Image         </div> <div class="galControls onePhoto" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation onePhoto" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1305450/1305450_10264611_1505761854069_2015CUWiP--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1305450/1305450_10264611_1505761854069_2015CUWiP--rgov-800width.jpg" title="CUWiP at The University of Michigan"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1305450/1305450_10264611_1505761854069_2015CUWiP--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="CUWiP at The University of Michigan"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Attendees of the 2015 APS Conference for Undergraduate Women in Physics (CUWiP) at the University of Michigan.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Jessica Micallef</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Public Domain</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Jennifer&nbsp;P&nbsp;Ogilvie</div> <div class="imageTitle">CUWiP at The University of Michigan</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[    Photosynthetic organisms employ an elaborate architecture of antenna arrays to gather solar energy and transfer it to photochemical reaction centers for conversion to stable charge separation. The processes of photosynthetic energy transfer and charge separation occur with near unit quantum efficiency. Underlying this stunning efficiency is the energy landscape that provides ultrafast directional transfer of energy from antennae to reaction centers, and directional electron transfer within reaction centers. Understanding the design principles of natural photosynthesis could enable us to design the next generation of artificial light-harvesting materials. Two-dimensional electronic spectroscopy (2DES) has proven to be a powerful tool for studying photosynthetic energy transfer and charge separation. With ultrafast time resolution, it reveals coupling between the components of photosynthetic systems, allowing the elucidation of energy transfer pathways and mechanisms. Previous 2DES studies of photosynthetic antennae complexes have revealed puzzling long-lived coherent dynamics. The physical origin and possible functional relevance of these coherences continues to be hotly debated. Supported by this project we have performed the first 2DES studies of charge separation in the bacterial reaction center (BRC). Our 2DES data has enabled us to refine excitonic models of the system and to distinguish between proposed charge separation mechanisms. We have also observed coherent dynamics in the BRC, as well as in monomer photosynthetic pigments and have determined the physical origin of the coherent dynamics. Work is ongoing to use models developed by optimizing fits to our 2DES data to assess the functional relevance of the coherent processes in the BRC.  Supported by this project we have also developed a rapid and high signal-to-noise approach for the characterization of coherent dynamics, which we call two-color rapid acquisition coherence spectroscopy (T-RACS). We have demonstrated the method in a study of chlorophyll a and have shown that the T-RACS approach can selectively detect particular coherences and distinguish between ground and excited state coherence.  Two-dimensional electronic spectroscopy is now being used worldwide in a broad range of research. The technical barriers to implementing 2DES have thus far limited the number of groups employing the method. We have extensively reviewed the different experimental implementations of 2DES, describing each method, how it has been used, and the advantages and disadvantages of the approach in comparison to other implementations. Our work provides a guide for researchers entering the field to enable them to make the best choice of implementation for their application.   The broader impacts of this project include enhancing our experimental and theoretical tools for understanding energy transfer and charge separation in natural and artificial systems. Our measurements provide new data that can guide the improvement of theoretical modeling of energy transfer and charge separation in bacterial photosystems, ultimately paving the way for a better understanding of plant photosystems and artificial light-harvesting materials.    This project supported the extensive training of graduate and undergraduate students, teaching them a wide range of skills, from the design of optical experiments, the hardware interfacing required for data acquisition, to data-taking and analysis, and scientific communication. The project also supported the PI and her graduate students to host the 2015 APS Conference for Undergraduate Women in Physics (CUWiP) at the University of Michigan. Our three-day meeting hosted 134 undergraduate women from the Midwest and beyond, educating them about career opportunities and research in Physics and helping strengthen the network of women in Physics in the US. The PI has also served on the CUWiP National Organizing Committee and the Site Selection Committee for the 2016 meetings. The PI and her group have been active in other outreach activities, including lab tours to economically disadvantaged students, a day of science for K-6 Girl Scouts and Physics Demo Day at a local middle school.             Last Modified: 09/18/2017       Submitted by: Jennifer P Ogilvie]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
