<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>The Michigan AGEP Alliance for Transformation (MAA): Mentoring and Community Building to Accelerate Successful Progression into the Professoriate</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/15/2013</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>02/28/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>652321.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>652321</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>11060000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>EHR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>HRD</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Human Resource Development</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Mark Leddy</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>mleddy@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924655</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The Michigan AGEP Alliance for Transformation (MAA) was created in response to the NSF's Alliances for Graduate Education and the Professoriate (AGEP) program solicitation (NSF 12-554) for the AGEP-Transformation (AGEP-T) track.  The AGEP-T track targets strategic alliances of institutions and organizations to develop, implement, and study innovative evidence-based models and standards for STEM graduate education, postdoctoral training, and academic STEM career preparation that eliminate or mitigate negative factors and promote positive practices for underrepresented.  The Michigan AGEP Alliance for Transformation (MAA): Mentoring and Community Building to Accelerate Successful Progression into the Professoriate represents a collaboration between the University of Michigan, Michigan State University, Michigan Technological University, Wayne State University, and Western Michigan University.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The long-term vision and planned outcome of MAA is to increase the success U.S. citizens who are underrepresented minority (URM) graduate students and postdoctoral scholars in all fields of STEM through graduate study, postdoctoral training and the professoriate.  This vision and outcome is being addressed by pursuing the following three overarching goals of the MAA:&lt;br/&gt;1) Adapting two existing models, one for fostering multidisciplinary learning communities with diverse students and the other for improving faculty mentoring of URM graduate students and postdoctoral fellows, to the needs of the five MAA campuses; &lt;br/&gt;2) Studying their effects on the academic identity and career progress of U.S. citizens who are URM graduate students and postdoctoral fellows in STEM programs; and &lt;br/&gt;3) Implementing more widely on campuses those models that lead to improved academic outcomes and widespread institutional change.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The objectives for this project are:&lt;br/&gt;Objective 1: Designing, adapting and implementing evidence-based mentoring initiatives, on all five campuses, that are focused on improved mentoring for U.S. URM graduate students and postdoctoral fellows in all fields of STEM.  &lt;br/&gt;Objective 2: Designing, adapting and implementing evidence-based initiatives to promote interdisciplinary learning communities, on all five campuses, that are focused on improved mentoring for U.S. URM STEM graduate students and postdoctoral fellows.  &lt;br/&gt;Objective 3: Conducting research about the ways in which improved mentoring and improved sense of community are linked to a sense of academic identity, and the ways in which academic identity is linked to important academic and career outcomes, for U.S. URM graduate students and postdoctoral fellows in all STEM fields.&lt;br/&gt;Objective 4: Conducting research about the ways in which departmental and university variables moderate the relations among mentoring, community, academic identity and academic outcomes for U.S. citizens who are URM graduate students and postdoctoral fellows in all STEM disciplines.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The primary activities that contribute to the model for the alliance include: &lt;br/&gt;1. Designing, adapting and implementing the University of Michigan's Mentoring Others Results in Excellence (MORE) model as a foundation for improving mentoring of U.S. URM graduate students and postdoctoral fellows in STEM.  This includes training facilitators who run faculty mentoring workshops, conducting mentoring workshops, training advanced level students for intergenerational mentoring, and developing/distributing individualized mentoring agreements to faculty and STEM programs.&lt;br/&gt;2. Designing, adapting and implementing the Michigan State University's interdisciplinary learning community model as a foundation for improving the sense of belonging, peer support and academic identify of U.S. URM graduate students and postdoctoral fellows in STEM.  This includes training facilitators, conducting institution-specific community meetings, and holding MAA-wide community meetings for graduate students, postdoctoral fellows and faculty.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The MAA includes a social science research study that will explore the mechanisms that help explain the under-representation and attrition of URM students in STEM, as well as the contextual and individual factors that can promote academic persistence and success in those fields.  The research team predicts that racial/ethnic stigma experiences in students' academic contexts lead to dis-identification from the academic discipline, which then leads to lower academic performance and completion.  They also predict that contextual-level resources, such as high-quality mentoring, moderate these relationships.  Examples of specific study hypotheses being tested include:&lt;br/&gt;1. Students reporting more negative department diversity climates (stigma experiences) will report lower sense of belonging (affective indicator of academic identity) in their academic departments than students reporting positive diversity climates.&lt;br/&gt;2. Students reporting having higher quality mentoring relationships with their faculty advisors will report more positive academic identity outcomes (higher perceived preparation, higher sense of belonging, higher curricular/professional involvement) than students reporting lower quality mentoring relationships.&lt;br/&gt;3. Quality mentoring will moderate the association between stigma (e.g., reported negative department climate) and academic identity (e.g., reported sense of belonging), such that the negative association of negative department diversity climate with sense of belonging will be stronger for students reporting lower quality mentoring relative to those reporting higher quality mentoring.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>09/11/2013</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/25/2017</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.076</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1305932</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Carol</FirstName>
<LastName>Fierke</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>A</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Carol A Fierke</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>fierke@umich.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>7349362678</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000384500</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/18/2015</StartDate>
<EndDate>08/25/2017</EndDate>
<RoleCode>Former Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Tabbye</FirstName>
<LastName>Chavous</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>M</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Tabbye M Chavous</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>tchavous@umich.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>7347641817</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000257189</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/18/2015</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Janet</FirstName>
<LastName>Weiss</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Janet Weiss</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>janetw@umich.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>7347641817</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000198968</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/11/2013</StartDate>
<EndDate>09/18/2015</EndDate>
<RoleCode>Former Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Regents of the University of Michigan - Ann Arbor</Name>
<CityName>Ann Arbor</CityName>
<ZipCode>481091274</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>7347636438</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>3003 South State St. Room 1062</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Michigan</StateName>
<StateCode>MI</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>12</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MI12</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>073133571</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>REGENTS OF THE UNIVERSITY OF MICHIGAN</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>073133571</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Michigan Ann Arbor]]></Name>
<CityName>Ann Arbor</CityName>
<StateCode>MI</StateCode>
<ZipCode>481091070</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[915 E. Washington St.]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Michigan</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>12</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MI12</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1515</Code>
<Text>AGEP</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1515</Code>
<Text>MINORITY GRADUATE EDUC ACTIVIT</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8212</Code>
<Text>Broaden Particip STEM Resrch</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0413</Code>
<Name>NSF Education &amp; Human Resource</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040106</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0414</Code>
<Name>NSF Education &amp; Human Resource</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040106</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0415</Code>
<Name>NSF Education &amp; Human Resource</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040106</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2013~248523</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~246798</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2015~157000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The Michigan AGEP Alliance (MAA), made up of the University of Michigan, Michigan State University, Michigan Technological University, Wayne State University and Western Michigan, developed models and programming for 1) fostering multidisciplinary learning communities among historically underrepresented racial/ethnic minority (URM) students in Science, Technology, Engineering, and Mathematics (STEM) fields and 2) supporting improved faculty mentoring for URM graduate students and URM postdoctoral fellows in STEM.&nbsp; Each campus adapted and implemented these models in ways that aligned with the needs of their respective campuses. After implementation, each campus identified those models that most effectively led to improved academic outcomes for program participants. Improved academic outcomes referred to increasing the success of URM graduate students and postdoctoral scholars in STEM fields through completion of graduate study, postdoctoral training, and movement into the professoriate.&nbsp; The project addressed 4 objectives:</p> <p>For <strong>Objective 1</strong>, the MAA campuses designed, adapted and implemented evidence-based mentoring initiatives focused on improved mentoring for URM graduate students and postdoctoral fellows. The project used the University of Michigan campus; "Mentoring Others Results in Excellence (MORE) program as a model and collected evidence of its effectiveness, including increased participation in MORE workshops by STEM faculty-student mentoring dyads and positive evaluations of faculty-student and department workshops offered by MORE.</p> <p>For <strong>Objective 2</strong>, the MAA campuses designed, adapted and implemented evidence-based programming to promote interdisciplinary learning communities among URM graduate students and postdoctoral fellows. The project used the Michigan State University Interdisciplinary Learning Community (ILC) program as a model and collected evidence of its effectiveness. Outcomes included increased graduate student/postdoctoral participation in ILC activities (community scholar gatherings, research symposia, writing workshops) and student-reported positive impacts on their professional development and research career interests.</p> <p>For <strong>Objectives 3-4</strong>, the University of Michigan (U-M) research team conducted a multi-method research study, including longitudinal surveys of URM  ((N=507) and non-URM (N=589) doctoral students from AGEP-eligible STEM fields across MAA institutions and interview data from a subsample of U-M students (N=32). The research addressed Objective 3 through examining how campus and department context experiences (including climate and mentoring) affected URM students' academic identity outcomes (e.g., sense of belonging, academic efficacy, intellectual interest and engagement, academic effort), and subsequent impacts on students' academic and career interest outcomes. The research addressed Objective 4 by examining  individual student and department/institutional factors that interacted with mentoring,  climate, and academic identity to affect academic outcomes for URM  students.</p> <p>The research findings demonstrated that URM students, compared to non-URM students, were less positive in reports of department climate (negative race and gender equity climates, more frequent microaggressions and incivility), of quality mentoring relationships (those characterized by high expectations and critical feedback), and URM students were more likely to have to seek mentors outside of their department.</p> <p>Climate and mentoring experiences influenced academic identity and achievement outcomes across all examined racial/ethnic student groups and across MAA institutions. However, for URM students in particular, negative department climate experiences related to more negative academic identity outcomes, more academic struggles, and less interest in research and faculty careers. In contrast, experiencing positive department climates and quality mentoring experiences (characterized by high expectations and critical feedback) related to more positive academic identity outcomes, less academic struggles, and more interest in research and faculty careers.</p> <p>Having opportunities to connect with mentors of the same race within their department/discipline also related to increased interest in faculty careers among URM students. URM students with stronger connections to their racial/cultural identities and who reported more support from their cultural communities showed more positive academic identity outcomes generally and were more academically resilient in the face of negative climate and mentoring experiences, compared to students with weaker racial/cultural community connections.</p> <p>Taken together, project findings highlight how academic identity is relevant to all students and is affected by students' experienced climates and mentoring. However, URM students experienced more contextual risks (negative climate, mentoring challenges) that could undermine their academic identity than did non-URM students. The findings also show how contextual risks (experiences of negative climates, low quality mentoring) and resources (mentoring, student cultural identity, sense of community) uniquely influence URM students' academic identity and persistence interests/intentions in STEM. The project design and findings inform and contribute to both practice and theory/research on enhancing diversity, equity, and inclusion and success in STEM.</p> <p>One overall project implication is that curricular and co-curricular efforts to enhance URM students&rsquo; STEM success should include approaches that address and improve the department climate and mentoring culture. This includes increasing faculty diversity - including URM faculty - along with supports for developing effective mentoring practices for all faculty. Also, URM students may benefit when they are able to connect their personal and cultural identities to their academic and disciplinary contexts. As such, programmatic efforts should include practices and structures that acknowledge, affirm, and support a sense of community around students&rsquo; racial/cultural identities.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 06/26/2018<br>      Modified by: Tabbye&nbsp;M&nbsp;Chavous</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The Michigan AGEP Alliance (MAA), made up of the University of Michigan, Michigan State University, Michigan Technological University, Wayne State University and Western Michigan, developed models and programming for 1) fostering multidisciplinary learning communities among historically underrepresented racial/ethnic minority (URM) students in Science, Technology, Engineering, and Mathematics (STEM) fields and 2) supporting improved faculty mentoring for URM graduate students and URM postdoctoral fellows in STEM.  Each campus adapted and implemented these models in ways that aligned with the needs of their respective campuses. After implementation, each campus identified those models that most effectively led to improved academic outcomes for program participants. Improved academic outcomes referred to increasing the success of URM graduate students and postdoctoral scholars in STEM fields through completion of graduate study, postdoctoral training, and movement into the professoriate.  The project addressed 4 objectives:  For Objective 1, the MAA campuses designed, adapted and implemented evidence-based mentoring initiatives focused on improved mentoring for URM graduate students and postdoctoral fellows. The project used the University of Michigan campus; "Mentoring Others Results in Excellence (MORE) program as a model and collected evidence of its effectiveness, including increased participation in MORE workshops by STEM faculty-student mentoring dyads and positive evaluations of faculty-student and department workshops offered by MORE.  For Objective 2, the MAA campuses designed, adapted and implemented evidence-based programming to promote interdisciplinary learning communities among URM graduate students and postdoctoral fellows. The project used the Michigan State University Interdisciplinary Learning Community (ILC) program as a model and collected evidence of its effectiveness. Outcomes included increased graduate student/postdoctoral participation in ILC activities (community scholar gatherings, research symposia, writing workshops) and student-reported positive impacts on their professional development and research career interests.  For Objectives 3-4, the University of Michigan (U-M) research team conducted a multi-method research study, including longitudinal surveys of URM  ((N=507) and non-URM (N=589) doctoral students from AGEP-eligible STEM fields across MAA institutions and interview data from a subsample of U-M students (N=32). The research addressed Objective 3 through examining how campus and department context experiences (including climate and mentoring) affected URM students' academic identity outcomes (e.g., sense of belonging, academic efficacy, intellectual interest and engagement, academic effort), and subsequent impacts on students' academic and career interest outcomes. The research addressed Objective 4 by examining  individual student and department/institutional factors that interacted with mentoring,  climate, and academic identity to affect academic outcomes for URM  students.  The research findings demonstrated that URM students, compared to non-URM students, were less positive in reports of department climate (negative race and gender equity climates, more frequent microaggressions and incivility), of quality mentoring relationships (those characterized by high expectations and critical feedback), and URM students were more likely to have to seek mentors outside of their department.  Climate and mentoring experiences influenced academic identity and achievement outcomes across all examined racial/ethnic student groups and across MAA institutions. However, for URM students in particular, negative department climate experiences related to more negative academic identity outcomes, more academic struggles, and less interest in research and faculty careers. In contrast, experiencing positive department climates and quality mentoring experiences (characterized by high expectations and critical feedback) related to more positive academic identity outcomes, less academic struggles, and more interest in research and faculty careers.  Having opportunities to connect with mentors of the same race within their department/discipline also related to increased interest in faculty careers among URM students. URM students with stronger connections to their racial/cultural identities and who reported more support from their cultural communities showed more positive academic identity outcomes generally and were more academically resilient in the face of negative climate and mentoring experiences, compared to students with weaker racial/cultural community connections.  Taken together, project findings highlight how academic identity is relevant to all students and is affected by students' experienced climates and mentoring. However, URM students experienced more contextual risks (negative climate, mentoring challenges) that could undermine their academic identity than did non-URM students. The findings also show how contextual risks (experiences of negative climates, low quality mentoring) and resources (mentoring, student cultural identity, sense of community) uniquely influence URM students' academic identity and persistence interests/intentions in STEM. The project design and findings inform and contribute to both practice and theory/research on enhancing diversity, equity, and inclusion and success in STEM.  One overall project implication is that curricular and co-curricular efforts to enhance URM students? STEM success should include approaches that address and improve the department climate and mentoring culture. This includes increasing faculty diversity - including URM faculty - along with supports for developing effective mentoring practices for all faculty. Also, URM students may benefit when they are able to connect their personal and cultural identities to their academic and disciplinary contexts. As such, programmatic efforts should include practices and structures that acknowledge, affirm, and support a sense of community around students? racial/cultural identities.          Last Modified: 06/26/2018       Submitted by: Tabbye M Chavous]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
