<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Strong Correlations in Environmental Condensed Matter</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2013</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2016</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>275000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>275000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03070000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DMR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Materials Research</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Daryl Hess</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>dhess@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924942</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>TECHNICAL SUMMARY&lt;br/&gt;This award supports theoretical and computational research, and education on materials and systems relevant to the environment and where strong correlations play an important role. The PI aims to address problems of fundamental importance that bear on the quest for a sustainable future.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The research is centered on three problems that arise in the context of the environment:  modeling actinide compounds and complexes in the environment, exploring a new approach to harvest solar energy, and developing statistical methods to describe anisotropic and inhomogeneous fluid flows known as "macroturbulence." Each focus system is characterized by strong correlations, with the latter two involving systems that are driven far from equilibrium.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Actinides compounds and complexes will be modeled in ways that account for strong correlations between the f-electrons, with the goal of developing the ability to make first-principles predictions of properties of actinides such as uranium and plutonium in the nuclear fuel cycle and as waste products in the environment. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;High-frequency rectification at junctions of doped Mott insulators will be studied analytically and through numerical simulation. Diodes made of these materials may be able to operate up to optical frequencies, enabling nanoscale rectenna designs that could directly convert the electromagnetic field of sunlight to direct current. The conversion mechanism represents a mechanism that is fundamentally differs from the mechanism underlying traditional solar cell technology.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Macroturbulent Jets in anisotropic and inhomogenous fluid flows will be described statistically by methods that forgo standard approaches based upon accumulation of statistics during numerical simulation. Instead the flow statistics will be captured directly by non-equilibrium statistical mechanics through approximations that are inspired by quantum many-body theory, and that can be systematically improved.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The research provides an interdisciplinary environmental context for training students and postdocs. The project will provide a cross-disciplinary learning experience for students at various levels, enhancing human resources for theoretical and computational condensed matter physics by training students and postdocs in cutting-edge methods of quantum many-body and non-equilibrium statistical physics in problems with potential impact on sustatinability. The PI will continue to draw the community's interest to solving problems that would lead to contributions to a sustainable future through the organization of workshops and conferences, and writing pedagogical articles.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;NONTECHNICAL SUMMARY&lt;br/&gt;This award supports theoretical and computational research, and education on materials and systems relevant to the environment. The PI aims to address problems of fundamental import that bear on the quest for a sustainable future. The research will focus on three problems:  1.) developing a computational method of improved accuracy for chemical compounds involving uranium and other atoms classified as actinides in the periodic table, 2.) investigating a key component, a diode, that can operate at sufficiently high frequency to enable a way to harvest energy from sunlight that operates on different fundamental principles than a solar cell and is potentially more efficient, 3.)  adapting statistical methods used to describe systems of many interacting electrons to understand the fundamental principles that underlie weather and climate. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The research provides an interdisciplinary environmental context for training students and postdocs. The project will provide a cross-disciplinary learning experience for students at various levels, enhancing human resources for theoretical and computational condensed matter physics by training students and postdocs in cutting-edge methods of quantum many-body and non-equilibrium statistical physics in problems with potential impact on sustainability. The PI will continue to draw the community's interest to solving problems that would lead to contributions to a sustainable future through the organization of workshops and conferences, and writing pedagogical articles.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>09/09/2013</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>04/23/2015</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1306806</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>John</FirstName>
<LastName>Marston</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>B</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>John B Marston</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>marston@brown.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>4018632061</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000437734</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/09/2013</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Brown University</Name>
<CityName>Providence</CityName>
<ZipCode>029129002</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>4018632777</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>BOX 1929</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[350 Eddy Street]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Rhode Island</StateName>
<StateCode>RI</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>RI01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>001785542</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>BROWN UNIVERSITY IN PROVIDENCE IN THE STATE OF RHODE ISLAND AND PROVIDENCE PLANTATIONS</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>001785542</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Brown University]]></Name>
<CityName>Providence</CityName>
<StateCode>RI</StateCode>
<ZipCode>029129093</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[Office of Sponsored Projects]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Rhode Island</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>RI01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1765</Code>
<Text>CONDENSED MATTER &amp; MAT THEORY</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1303</Code>
<Text>CLIMATE MODELING &amp; PREDICTION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7644</Code>
<Text>ENERGY FOR SUSTAINABILITY</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0113</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0115</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2013~180000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2015~95000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><div class="page" title="Page 20"> <div class="layoutArea"> <div class="column"> <p><span>Theoretical and computational research, and education and outreach, were conducted on materials and systems with many degrees of freedom.&nbsp; The research program addressed problems of fundamental import that also contribute to national competitiveness and to the quest for a sustainable future. Three systems were studied:&nbsp; (1)&nbsp; Junctions of metal-oxide materials, recently shown to rectify, were simulated using computational models.&nbsp; Such diodes may be able to operate up to extremely high frequencies, creating a new class of electronic devices. (2) Compounds of uranium were modeled to predict their behavior in compounds such as those found in high-level nuclear wastes.&nbsp; (3) Anisotropic and inhomogeneous turbulence in fluid flows was described statistically by methods that forgo standard approaches based upon accumulation of statistics during numerical simulation. Instead the flow statistics were captured directly in ways that can be systematically improved with a view to applications in both climate modeling and in engineering.</span></p> <p><span>&nbsp;</span></p> <p><span>The research program was aligned with several areas of national interest: Competitiveness, national security, and the need to move towards a sustainable future. &nbsp; The project educated graduate and undergraduate students, thereby enhancing human resources for theoretical and computational condensed matter physics.&nbsp; Graduate students, and several undergraduates, were trained in leading methods of quantum many-body and non-equilibrium statistical physics. Such multidisciplinary training is increasingly important to newcomers seeking to understand and/or control condensed matter with engineering or environmental application. &nbsp;Computer code that was developed was made available to the wider community of researchers, and to the public, including the Mac OS X app "GCM" that has been downloaded over 2,500 times. &nbsp;</span></p> <div><span><br /></span></div> <p>&nbsp;</p> </div> </div> </div><br> <p>            Last Modified: 11/27/2016<br>      Modified by: John&nbsp;B&nbsp;Marston</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Images (<span id="selectedPhoto0">1</span> of <span class="totalNumber"></span>)           </div> <div class="galControls" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2016/1306806/1306806_10277603_1480267512186_TachoclineVorticity--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2016/1306806/1306806_10277603_1480267512186_TachoclineVorticity--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Fluid flow in model of solar interior"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2016/1306806/1306806_10277603_1480267512186_TachoclineVorticity--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Fluid flow in model of solar interior"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Snapshot of the fluid flow during a  quiescent intervals in an idealized model of the solar tachocline.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Brad Marston</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">John&nbsp;B&nbsp;Marston</div> <div class="imageTitle">Fluid flow in model of solar interior</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2016/1306806/1306806_10277603_1480267802313_AbbyPlummer--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2016/1306806/1306806_10277603_1480267802313_AbbyPlummer--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Abigail Plummer"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2016/1306806/1306806_10277603_1480267802313_AbbyPlummer--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Abigail Plummer"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Ms. Abigail Plummer conduced her senior thesis research on the solar tachocline under Prof. Marston's direction.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Abigail Plummer</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">John&nbsp;B&nbsp;Marston</div> <div class="imageTitle">Abigail Plummer</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2016/1306806/1306806_10277603_1480267955116_LewisSilletto--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2016/1306806/1306806_10277603_1480267955116_LewisSilletto--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Lewis Silletto"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2016/1306806/1306806_10277603_1480267955116_LewisSilletto--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Lewis Silletto"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Mr. Lewis Silletto is an undergraduate developing a smartphone app that tracks slight changes in atmospheric pressure. Statistics so collected from many phones will be compared to simulations of atmospheric boundary layer turbulence.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Lewis Silletto</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">John&nbsp;B&nbsp;Marston</div> <div class="imageTitle">Lewis Silletto</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[    Theoretical and computational research, and education and outreach, were conducted on materials and systems with many degrees of freedom.  The research program addressed problems of fundamental import that also contribute to national competitiveness and to the quest for a sustainable future. Three systems were studied:  (1)  Junctions of metal-oxide materials, recently shown to rectify, were simulated using computational models.  Such diodes may be able to operate up to extremely high frequencies, creating a new class of electronic devices. (2) Compounds of uranium were modeled to predict their behavior in compounds such as those found in high-level nuclear wastes.  (3) Anisotropic and inhomogeneous turbulence in fluid flows was described statistically by methods that forgo standard approaches based upon accumulation of statistics during numerical simulation. Instead the flow statistics were captured directly in ways that can be systematically improved with a view to applications in both climate modeling and in engineering.     The research program was aligned with several areas of national interest: Competitiveness, national security, and the need to move towards a sustainable future.   The project educated graduate and undergraduate students, thereby enhancing human resources for theoretical and computational condensed matter physics.  Graduate students, and several undergraduates, were trained in leading methods of quantum many-body and non-equilibrium statistical physics. Such multidisciplinary training is increasingly important to newcomers seeking to understand and/or control condensed matter with engineering or environmental application.  Computer code that was developed was made available to the wider community of researchers, and to the public, including the Mac OS X app "GCM" that has been downloaded over 2,500 times.                 Last Modified: 11/27/2016       Submitted by: John B Marston]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
