<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Stochastic Systems with Complex Interactions and Random Environments</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2013</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>313681.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>313681</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DMS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Tomek Bartoszynski</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>tbartosz@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924885</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This  project studies mathematical models of random paths in random environments and percolation models that describe random growth.  The goal is to describe  typical large scale behavior and to quantify deviations from the typical behavior.  The emphasis is on finding universal principles  that apply to classes of models that share fundamental characteristics.  There are two main directions of research.  (i) The study of the combinatorics, probability distributions and large deviations of 1+1 dimensional exactly solvable models in the Kardar-Parisi-Zhang universality class.  Outcomes of this research include rigorous verification of fluctuation exponents conjectured in the physics literature, new connections between combinatorics and models from probability and statistical physics, and better understanding of the integrable structures underlying exact solvability.   (ii)  The study of more general models of random paths and growing clusters  with probabilistic tools. This work will lead to variational descriptions of limiting free energies and limit shapes, and the identification of structures in these models that enable us to study their universal fluctuation properties. The grand goal is to establish some universal properties for models beyond the narrow set of explicitly solvable cases. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project investigates mathematical models that describe complex interactions, growth,  and motion of particles in an irregular environment.   These mathematical systems incorporate randomness to model irregularity and unpredictability.  The goal is to discover general mathematical laws that govern such systems.    These systems appear quite different at microscopic and macroscopic  scales.  So it is important to understand how different rules for small-scale evolution lead to different large-scale systemwide behavior.  Real-world phenomena that such mathematical studies can illuminate include the motion of vehicles,  packets in a communication network,  fluid particles in a tube, wetting transitions where fluid spreads in a porous medium, epidemics advancing in a population,  or the fluctuations of a polymer chain in a fluid.  Over the long term understanding complex interactions has profound implications for science and engineering and thereby for society. Models of the kind described in the proposal are intensely and concurrently studied by mathematicians, natural scientists, social scientists, and engineers.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>05/29/2013</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>04/30/2015</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1306777</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Timo</FirstName>
<LastName>Seppalainen</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Timo Seppalainen</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>seppalai@math.wisc.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6082633624</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000384142</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/29/2013</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Wisconsin-Madison</Name>
<CityName>MADISON</CityName>
<ZipCode>537151218</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6082623822</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>21 North Park Street</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[Suite 6401]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Wisconsin</StateName>
<StateCode>WI</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>WI02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>161202122</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF WISCONSIN SYSTEM</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>041188822</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Wisconsin-Madison]]></Name>
<CityName>Madison</CityName>
<StateCode>WI</StateCode>
<ZipCode>537151218</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[21 North Park St, STE 6401]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Wisconsin</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>WI02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1263</Code>
<Text>PROBABILITY</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0113</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0114</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0115</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2013~119233</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~96816</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2015~97632</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The goal of this project is the discovery of general mathematical laws that govern the behavior of complex systems. Mathematical models of such systems are stochastic, that is, they incorporate randomness to model irregularity and unpredictability. Examples of such systems include the motion of a particle in a varying environment or in a complicated network, the growth of a crystal structure, the spread of a contagion, or the mutual interaction of a large population of agents.&nbsp;</p> <p>This project studies the abstract mathematics of such complex systems. Throughout the sciences and engineering, human capacity to comprehend, control and manipulate nature and man-made systems relies on mathematics. Thus the study of fundamental mathematical principles can provide insight that in the future aids the understanding of concrete real-world systems.&nbsp;</p> <p>The main innovations of the current project include new mathematical formulas that capture the limiting form of large spreading clusters that grow by random addition of microscopic particles. &nbsp;The hope is that these formulas lead to understanding of the properties of such limit shapes that have remained mysterious for 50 years. &nbsp;These formulas have led to better understating of the routes in space through which such growing clusters advance. &nbsp;Several important discoveries that describe long-term behavior of models of random evolutions were also made. These mathematical results confirm predictions that have been made earlier in physics.&nbsp;</p> <p>The broader impacts of the project include the development of educational materials on the mathematics of complex systems, available to the public, and the training of junior scientists who have gone on to employment in academia and industry. A textbook on large deviation theory co-authored by the Principal Investigator was published in 2015. Books in progress on interacting particle systems and growth models, along with videos of the Principal Investigator&rsquo;s lectures, are available on the PI&rsquo;s website. &nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 09/03/2017<br>      Modified by: Timo&nbsp;Seppalainen</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The goal of this project is the discovery of general mathematical laws that govern the behavior of complex systems. Mathematical models of such systems are stochastic, that is, they incorporate randomness to model irregularity and unpredictability. Examples of such systems include the motion of a particle in a varying environment or in a complicated network, the growth of a crystal structure, the spread of a contagion, or the mutual interaction of a large population of agents.   This project studies the abstract mathematics of such complex systems. Throughout the sciences and engineering, human capacity to comprehend, control and manipulate nature and man-made systems relies on mathematics. Thus the study of fundamental mathematical principles can provide insight that in the future aids the understanding of concrete real-world systems.   The main innovations of the current project include new mathematical formulas that capture the limiting form of large spreading clusters that grow by random addition of microscopic particles.  The hope is that these formulas lead to understanding of the properties of such limit shapes that have remained mysterious for 50 years.  These formulas have led to better understating of the routes in space through which such growing clusters advance.  Several important discoveries that describe long-term behavior of models of random evolutions were also made. These mathematical results confirm predictions that have been made earlier in physics.   The broader impacts of the project include the development of educational materials on the mathematics of complex systems, available to the public, and the training of junior scientists who have gone on to employment in academia and industry. A textbook on large deviation theory co-authored by the Principal Investigator was published in 2015. Books in progress on interacting particle systems and growth models, along with videos of the Principal Investigator?s lectures, are available on the PI?s website.         Last Modified: 09/03/2017       Submitted by: Timo Seppalainen]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
