<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Study of the Electro-weak Structure of the Nucleon</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2013</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2016</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>497895.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>497895</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03010000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>PHY</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Physics</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Bogdan Mihaila</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>bmihaila@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032928235</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This award supports a three-year research program focusing on the study of the electro-weak structure of the nucleon using the electron beam at Jefferson Lab (JLab) as a probe. The medium-energy nuclear experimental program conducted by the PIs aims to obtain information which will help to answer the questions: "What is the internal landscape of the nucleon?" and "What are the key ingredients of a New Standard Model of particle physics?".  The research program builds on the PIs previous work on the QWEAK and DVCS experiments and one of its highlights will be data taking on one of the first experiments of the JLab 12 GeV era. The goal of DVCS experiments is ultimately to provide a simultaneous spatial and momentum mapping of the internal structure of the proton.  Roche is a co-spokesperson of two experiments dedicated to the study of GPDs in Hall A at JLab, one of which is scheduled to take data as early as 2014. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Another aspect of the program is precision measurement of interactions which can be reliably predicted by the Standard Model, for example the measurement of the rate of parity violation in electron scattering.  The PIs will continue their data acquisition and analysis software work up to publication of the results of the completed QWEAK experiment and prepare for the next generation of such experiments at JLab: the MOLLER experiment.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The broader impacts of the program are twofold: training the next generation of scientists and raising the profile of minority scientists. The research proposed by the PIs is performed in part by two graduate students. In addition, the PIs will carry out projects in which undergraduate students can meaningfully participate. Finally, this award supports the research of a woman physicist whose residence on campus and mentoring activities serve to support and encourage graduate and undergraduate women in physics.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/24/2013</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/10/2015</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1306376</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Julie</FirstName>
<LastName>Roche</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Julie Roche</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>rochej@ohio.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>7405931982</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000243248</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/24/2013</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Paul</FirstName>
<LastName>King</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>M</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME>II</PI_SUFX_NAME>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Paul M King</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>kingp1@ohio.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>7405931974</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000315720</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/24/2013</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Ohio University</Name>
<CityName>ATHENS</CityName>
<ZipCode>457012979</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>7405932857</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>108 CUTLER HL</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Ohio</StateName>
<StateCode>OH</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>15</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>OH15</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>041077983</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>OHIO UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>041077983</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Ohio University]]></Name>
<CityName>Athens</CityName>
<StateCode>OH</StateCode>
<ZipCode>457012979</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[206 Edwards Accelerator Lab]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Ohio</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>15</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>OH15</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1232</Code>
<Text>Nuclear &amp; Hadron Quantum Chrom</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7621</Code>
<Text>PHYSICS-BROADEN PARTICIPATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0113</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0114</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0115</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2013~195095</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~151400</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2015~151400</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>This award supported a three-year research program focusing on the internal structure of the nucleon using electrons as probe. The medium-energy nuclear experimental group directed by the PIs aims at answering the following overarching questions formulated by the Nuclear Science Advisory Committee (DOE-NSF): "What is the internal landscape of the nucleon?" and "What are the key ingredients of a New Standard Model of particle physics?". The research is mainly performed at the Thomas Jefferson National Accelerator Facility (JLab) in Virginia.</p> <p><br />For the duration of this award, the main focus of the group was to take data for experiment E12-06-114 at JLab. PI Roche is one of the spoke-person for that experiment. The goal of the experiment is to study the internal structure of the nucleon in a novel formalism that allows the simultaneous mapping of the position and momentum distribution of the nucleon constituents.This approach can be compared to a tomography. &nbsp;E12-04-116 was chosen as one of the first experiment to take data at the recently upgraded JLab facility because it was recognized for its potential scientific high impact. The PIs, their students and collaborators performed that experiment, providing a concrete and demanding target of performance to the accelerator scientists commissioning the new electron beam at JLab.<br />Another important focus of the group supported by this award was to further their exploration of the limitations of the widely successful Standard Model of Particle Physics. To this aim, the PIs and their students furthered the analysis of the QWEAK experiment and formulated plans for the upcoming MOLLER experiment, both experiments conducted at JLab.</p> <p><br />The broader impacts of this award were three-fold: &ldquo;training the next generation of scientists&rdquo;, &ldquo;broadening the participation of under-represented groups&rdquo;, and&ldquo;enhancing infrastructure for research&rdquo;. The PIs work with two graduate students and at least two undergraduate summer interns each year. &nbsp;Of those ten students, two were female, three were from underrepresented minorities, two were age-atypical and five were first generation students. &nbsp;Collectively these numbers testify of the emphasis the PIs put on accessibility, which results on the broadening of participation. In the same spirit, the PIs take part to regular meetings with the community at larger for example taking part to the &ldquo;Adopt a Physicist&rdquo; online program that fosters exchanges with middle and high school students. &nbsp;Finally the PIs are part of executive committees of relevant professional associations like the Ohio Region section of the American Physical Society and the JLab user group.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 10/07/2016<br>      Modified by: Julie&nbsp;Roche</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ This award supported a three-year research program focusing on the internal structure of the nucleon using electrons as probe. The medium-energy nuclear experimental group directed by the PIs aims at answering the following overarching questions formulated by the Nuclear Science Advisory Committee (DOE-NSF): "What is the internal landscape of the nucleon?" and "What are the key ingredients of a New Standard Model of particle physics?". The research is mainly performed at the Thomas Jefferson National Accelerator Facility (JLab) in Virginia.   For the duration of this award, the main focus of the group was to take data for experiment E12-06-114 at JLab. PI Roche is one of the spoke-person for that experiment. The goal of the experiment is to study the internal structure of the nucleon in a novel formalism that allows the simultaneous mapping of the position and momentum distribution of the nucleon constituents.This approach can be compared to a tomography.  E12-04-116 was chosen as one of the first experiment to take data at the recently upgraded JLab facility because it was recognized for its potential scientific high impact. The PIs, their students and collaborators performed that experiment, providing a concrete and demanding target of performance to the accelerator scientists commissioning the new electron beam at JLab. Another important focus of the group supported by this award was to further their exploration of the limitations of the widely successful Standard Model of Particle Physics. To this aim, the PIs and their students furthered the analysis of the QWEAK experiment and formulated plans for the upcoming MOLLER experiment, both experiments conducted at JLab.   The broader impacts of this award were three-fold: "training the next generation of scientists", "broadening the participation of under-represented groups", and"enhancing infrastructure for research". The PIs work with two graduate students and at least two undergraduate summer interns each year.  Of those ten students, two were female, three were from underrepresented minorities, two were age-atypical and five were first generation students.  Collectively these numbers testify of the emphasis the PIs put on accessibility, which results on the broadening of participation. In the same spirit, the PIs take part to regular meetings with the community at larger for example taking part to the "Adopt a Physicist" online program that fosters exchanges with middle and high school students.  Finally the PIs are part of executive committees of relevant professional associations like the Ohio Region section of the American Physical Society and the JLab user group.          Last Modified: 10/07/2016       Submitted by: Julie Roche]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
