<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>CDS&amp;E:A large-scale data discovery framework for understanding intermittent, performance-critical phenomena in simulations of offshore wind turbines</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2013</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>500005.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>500005</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07020000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CBET</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Chem, Bioeng, Env, &amp; Transp Sys</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Ron Joslin</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>rjoslin@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927030</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>CBET 1306869&lt;br/&gt;S. Sarkar (PI), S. Baden (co-PI) and Y. Bazilevs (co-PI)&lt;br/&gt;UC San Diego&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Large scale simulation data sets that describe spatial and temporal variation of physical phenomena over a multitude of scales often contain characteristic flow features that are infrequent but critical to understanding the natural phenomenon or engineered system in question. The research will lead to a novel data discovery framework, to flexibly  identify, extract and interrogate features of interest in space-time, leading to both a reduction in size of stored data sets and identification of time periods where high-fidelity simulation of the system is necessary. The data discovery framework will provide algorithmic and data structure optimizations to enable the user to flexibly query the data over space and time. It will be implemented on Gordon, a new data-intensive platform with non-volatile storage - flash memory. The proposed research will bring together investigators with expertise in computer science, fluid mechanics and structural mechanics to advance computational and data-enabled science and engineering.&lt;br/&gt; &lt;br/&gt;The motivating engineering application is offshore wind turbines. The wind turbine simulations proposed here are ambitious and will couple computation of flow-structure interaction at the temporal resolution of seconds with simulations of realistic atmospheric turbulence. Such simulations of a full-scale wind turbine are unprecedented and will be enabled by a computational framework that brings together the following components: advanced large eddy simulation for atmospheric flow, isogeometric analysis for fluid-structure interaction, and a finite element method with weak boundary conditions for the blade aerodynamics. Atmospheric conditions in a marine boundary layer, particularly under conditions of stable stratification, lead to intermittent bursts of wind shear and pressure that can have an unusually large effect on the rotor blade structural response. Quantification and understanding of such large-impact events using the data discovery framework will enable better and more cost-effective blade design, better operational performance, and more accurate wind resource forecasting. There will also be better understanding of extreme atmospheric events that lead to wind turbine blade failure. The data discovery framework to be developed here will have broad impact since it can be employed in any field involving multi-scale, time-dependent data containing dynamically important objects of lower-order complexity. Some examples are cardiovascular imaging and modeling, hurricane prediction, epidemiological modeling, and cloud dynamics.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/13/2013</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/13/2013</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1306869</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Scott</FirstName>
<LastName>Baden</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>B</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Scott B Baden</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>baden@ucsd.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>8585348861</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000099064</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/13/2013</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Sutanu</FirstName>
<LastName>Sarkar</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Sutanu Sarkar</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>ssarkar@ucsd.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>8585348243</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000269164</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/13/2013</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Yuri</FirstName>
<LastName>Bazilevs</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Yuri Bazilevs</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>yuri_bazilevs@brown.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>4018631859</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000516027</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/13/2013</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of California-San Diego</Name>
<CityName>La Jolla</CityName>
<ZipCode>920930934</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>8585344896</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>Office of Contract &amp; Grant Admin</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[9500 Gilman Drive, 0934]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>49</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CA49</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>804355790</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF CALIFORNIA, SAN DIEGO</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>071549000</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of California-San Diego]]></Name>
<CityName>La Jolla</CityName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>920930934</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[9500 Gilman Drive MC 0934]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>49</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CA49</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7644</Code>
<Text>EchemS-Electrochemical Systems</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>8084</Code>
<Text>CDS&amp;E</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>6892</Code>
<Text>CI REUSE</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7433</Code>
<Text>CyberInfra Frmwrk 21st (CIF21)</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8084</Code>
<Text>CDS&amp;E</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0113</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2013~500005</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The atmospheric boundary layer (ABL) &nbsp;has turbulent fluctuations of wind along with extreme, coherent gusts that interact with wind turbines. These &nbsp;atmospheric flow features occur occasionally, but have an unusually large effect on the rotor blade structural response, exhibit strong interactions with turbine wakes, and substantially affect the intermittency of extracted wind power. Quantification and understanding of such large-impact events will lead to better and more cost-effective blade design, better operational performance, and more accurate wind resource forecasting.&nbsp;</p> <p><br />&nbsp;We have developed an advanced &nbsp; computational model that can predict the flow and structural response of wind turbines operating in the ABL. &nbsp;The modeling framework allows geometrically complex turbines &nbsp;at full scale that operate in an ABL with realistic turbulence including offshore sites. The model is able to handle &nbsp;different local atmospheric conditions and can predict the flow in the challenging case of strong surface cooling when there are rapid changes in &nbsp;the speed and direction of wind. &nbsp;An efficient data discovery method is used to identify large-amplitude coherent flow features in the massive &nbsp;simulation database. Numerical methods for &nbsp;flow structure interaction (FSI) have been developed to accurately predict the structural response of the wind turbine blades during these episodes of rapidly varying wind shear. &nbsp;We have deployed the computational model on large-scale computing platforms to successfully simulate the time variation of power and torque of two back-to-back 5 megawatt wind turbines in a cooled ABL.&nbsp;</p> <p><br />Wind energy is &nbsp;a key component in the &nbsp; energy portfolio of the United States. By bringing a new level of accuracy to simulation-based engineering, the research of this project can &nbsp;help technological innovation in the energy sector. &nbsp;Two graduate students have received multidisciplinary training spanning fluid mechanics, structural mechanics, and computational science and engineering while working on this project.&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 05/18/2018<br>      Modified by: Sutanu&nbsp;Sarkar</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The atmospheric boundary layer (ABL)  has turbulent fluctuations of wind along with extreme, coherent gusts that interact with wind turbines. These  atmospheric flow features occur occasionally, but have an unusually large effect on the rotor blade structural response, exhibit strong interactions with turbine wakes, and substantially affect the intermittency of extracted wind power. Quantification and understanding of such large-impact events will lead to better and more cost-effective blade design, better operational performance, and more accurate wind resource forecasting.     We have developed an advanced   computational model that can predict the flow and structural response of wind turbines operating in the ABL.  The modeling framework allows geometrically complex turbines  at full scale that operate in an ABL with realistic turbulence including offshore sites. The model is able to handle  different local atmospheric conditions and can predict the flow in the challenging case of strong surface cooling when there are rapid changes in  the speed and direction of wind.  An efficient data discovery method is used to identify large-amplitude coherent flow features in the massive  simulation database. Numerical methods for  flow structure interaction (FSI) have been developed to accurately predict the structural response of the wind turbine blades during these episodes of rapidly varying wind shear.  We have deployed the computational model on large-scale computing platforms to successfully simulate the time variation of power and torque of two back-to-back 5 megawatt wind turbines in a cooled ABL.    Wind energy is  a key component in the   energy portfolio of the United States. By bringing a new level of accuracy to simulation-based engineering, the research of this project can  help technological innovation in the energy sector.  Two graduate students have received multidisciplinary training spanning fluid mechanics, structural mechanics, and computational science and engineering while working on this project.        Last Modified: 05/18/2018       Submitted by: Sutanu Sarkar]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
