<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>NSF Postdoctoral Fellowship in Biology FY 2013</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>10/01/2013</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>09/30/2015</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>140000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>156777</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Fellowship Award</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>08080000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>BIO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DBI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Biological Infrastructure</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Daniel Marenda</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>dmarenda@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922157</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This Postdoctoral Research Fellowship award to Dr. Benjamin Parker is supported by both the Directorate for Biological Sciences and the Office of International Science and Engineering at the National Science Foundation. During the 24-month fellowship, Dr. Parker will work on a project titled, "Variation in the outcome of an insect-symbiont association: a role for host genotype" under the sponsorship of Professor H Charles Godfray at the University of Oxford in Oxford, England. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Animals host complex communities of microbes that play an important role in health and disease. In recent years, scientists have determined that there is a great deal of variation in the types of microbes that inhabit different individuals, and in what effect these microbes have on their hosts. The goal of this research is to use a simple model system to learn about the ecological and evolutionary forces generating variation in animal-microbe interactions. Pea aphids host a species of bacteria that protects them from a natural fungal pathogen. Recent work has shown that some aphids are better protected from this fungus by bacteria than others. This project will combine next-generation sequencing and immunological techniques to determine the role that hosts are playing in shaping their associations with beneficial bacteria, and why hosts differ in these associations. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;By learning about this simple animal-microbe system, this work will contribute to a broader understanding of how ecology and evolution shape associations with microbes in more complex individuals. In addition, aphids are invasive agricultural pests, and fungal pathogens are used as a way of controlling aphid populations. Developing an understanding of how crop pests resist biocontrol agents is important to agricultural management. This project will also involve the development of a series of classroom exercises that use aphids to expose students to natural history. The exercises will have students set up and monitor natural communities of aphids, which are found commonly throughout the US, and will explore how pathogens and predators influence populations. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award provides a unique opportunity for a US scientist to collaborate with foreign scientists, and utilize the unique facilities, expertise and experimental conditions available abroad.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>05/17/2013</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/11/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.074</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1306387</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Benjamin</FirstName>
<LastName>Parker</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>J</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Benjamin J Parker</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress/>
<PI_PHON>7734255002</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000631483</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/17/2013</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Parker                  Benjamin       J</Name>
<CityName>Atlanta</CityName>
<ZipCode>303071715</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber/>
<StreetAddress/>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Georgia</StateName>
<StateCode>GA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>GA05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM/>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME/>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Parker                  Benjamin       J]]></Name>
<CityName>Atlanta</CityName>
<StateCode>GA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>303071715</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Georgia</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>GA05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>5956</Code>
<Text>IRFP-Inter Res Fellowship Prog</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>8049</Code>
<Text>Biology Postdoctoral Research</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>5946</Code>
<Text>UNITED KINGDOM</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>5956</Code>
<Text>IRFP</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7137</Code>
<Text>POSTDOCTORAL FELLOWSHIPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8210</Code>
<Text>Intl Bio Postdoc Res Fellowshp</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0113</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0114</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2013~140000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~16777</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Animals host communities of microbes that play an important role in health and disease. Determining how these associations evolve in natural populations is a difficult challenge. Genetic variation provides the raw material for evolution to act, and biologists therefore study natural variation to learn how organisms are evolving. In addition, by comparing what genes differ between individuals, researchers can uncover molecular mechanisms underlying traits. This project used a tractable model system (pea aphids and their bacterial partners<em>,&nbsp;</em>which benefit aphids by protecting them from pathogens) to better understand the patterns and mechanisms underlying genetic variation in a simple animal-microbe association.</p> <p>This work demonstrated that strains of the symbiotic bacterium <em>Regiella insecticola</em> differ in whether they protect aphids against a fungal infection. By using next-generation genome sequencing, it was found that <em>Regiella </em>genotypes differ in hundreds of genes and potentially protect their hosts by competing with fungal pathogens for soluble iron. It was further shown that <em>Regiella</em> may be coevolving with fungal pathogens in natural populations. In parallel, it was demonstrated that host aphid genotypes differ in whether they can accept and maintain&nbsp;<em>Regiella&nbsp;</em>infections. It was also found that an aphid&rsquo;s genotype determines whether it benefits from hosting microbes, and if harboring bacteria harms a host&rsquo;s fitness. Molecular techniques were used to show that aphids influence the phenotypic effects of hosting microbes by actively controlling bacterial densities, but do not appear to be influencing symbiont gene expression.</p> <p>Together, this work suggests that variation in animal-microbe associations can be driven by both host and bacterial genetic mechanisms. Natural selection is likely balancing the costs and benefits of symbiont infection for animal hosts in different environments by acting on immune system genes that determine bacterial densities. This project has furthered our understanding of an important model for symbiosis research, and has identified candidate mechanisms for future research on the molecular underpinnings of animal-microbe interactions. More broadly, this work has contributed to an emerging view of the microbiota as a complex trait under host control, shaped by natural selection, that has important influences on animal health and disease.</p> <p>Studying this model animal-microbe system has contributed to a more general understanding of how animal-microbe symbioses properly function, how they contribute to animal traits, and how they have evolved. Because microbial communities have important impacts on human health, a basic understanding of the relationship between animals and microbes is potentially important for efforts to manipulate the human microbiome to improve health and prevent disease. In addition, pea aphids are invasive agricultural pests, and fungal pathogens are under consideration as a way of controlling aphid populations. Developing an understanding of how crop pests resist biocontrol agents is important to agricultural management. This work included two undergraduate students who completed projects that led to a peer-reviewed publication. Further, it involved the development and implementation of a classroom exercise using aphids that exposed introductory biology students to evolutionary and ecological concepts, which the primary investigator will use in future teaching and outreach efforts. Lastly, this award provided a unique opportunity for a US researcher to collaborate with foreign scientists and benefit from the expertise, facilities, and perspective available abroad.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 09/30/2017<br>      Modified by: Benjamin&nbsp;J&nbsp;Parker</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Animals host communities of microbes that play an important role in health and disease. Determining how these associations evolve in natural populations is a difficult challenge. Genetic variation provides the raw material for evolution to act, and biologists therefore study natural variation to learn how organisms are evolving. In addition, by comparing what genes differ between individuals, researchers can uncover molecular mechanisms underlying traits. This project used a tractable model system (pea aphids and their bacterial partners, which benefit aphids by protecting them from pathogens) to better understand the patterns and mechanisms underlying genetic variation in a simple animal-microbe association.  This work demonstrated that strains of the symbiotic bacterium Regiella insecticola differ in whether they protect aphids against a fungal infection. By using next-generation genome sequencing, it was found that Regiella genotypes differ in hundreds of genes and potentially protect their hosts by competing with fungal pathogens for soluble iron. It was further shown that Regiella may be coevolving with fungal pathogens in natural populations. In parallel, it was demonstrated that host aphid genotypes differ in whether they can accept and maintain Regiella infections. It was also found that an aphid?s genotype determines whether it benefits from hosting microbes, and if harboring bacteria harms a host?s fitness. Molecular techniques were used to show that aphids influence the phenotypic effects of hosting microbes by actively controlling bacterial densities, but do not appear to be influencing symbiont gene expression.  Together, this work suggests that variation in animal-microbe associations can be driven by both host and bacterial genetic mechanisms. Natural selection is likely balancing the costs and benefits of symbiont infection for animal hosts in different environments by acting on immune system genes that determine bacterial densities. This project has furthered our understanding of an important model for symbiosis research, and has identified candidate mechanisms for future research on the molecular underpinnings of animal-microbe interactions. More broadly, this work has contributed to an emerging view of the microbiota as a complex trait under host control, shaped by natural selection, that has important influences on animal health and disease.  Studying this model animal-microbe system has contributed to a more general understanding of how animal-microbe symbioses properly function, how they contribute to animal traits, and how they have evolved. Because microbial communities have important impacts on human health, a basic understanding of the relationship between animals and microbes is potentially important for efforts to manipulate the human microbiome to improve health and prevent disease. In addition, pea aphids are invasive agricultural pests, and fungal pathogens are under consideration as a way of controlling aphid populations. Developing an understanding of how crop pests resist biocontrol agents is important to agricultural management. This work included two undergraduate students who completed projects that led to a peer-reviewed publication. Further, it involved the development and implementation of a classroom exercise using aphids that exposed introductory biology students to evolutionary and ecological concepts, which the primary investigator will use in future teaching and outreach efforts. Lastly, this award provided a unique opportunity for a US researcher to collaborate with foreign scientists and benefit from the expertise, facilities, and perspective available abroad.       Last Modified: 09/30/2017       Submitted by: Benjamin J Parker]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
