<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>A New Robust and Energy-efficient Microactuator Device for Demanding Applications</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>06/01/2013</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>240076.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>240076</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07010000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>ECCS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Electrical, Commun &amp; Cyber Sys</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Nadia El-Masry</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>nelmasry@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924975</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The objective of this program is to explore and lay a solid foundation for a new generation of microactuator devices. The robust microactuator device developed in the program will satisfy the imperative demands of energy efficiency and operation in harsh environments, including high temperature and pressure, radiation, corrosion, chemical and biological domains, etc. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The intellectual merit is to develop a novel microactuator device technology which combines the advantages of photonic actuation and wide bandgap silicon carbide material. The all silicon carbide platform truly exploits the superior material properties of silicon carbide for demanding applications. The photonic actuation enables intrinsic safety, reliability, and electromagnetic interference immunity. The key technological challenge currently limiting silicon carbide microelectromechanical systems fabrication will be solved by an innovative surface micromachining process. High speed and high energy efficiency will be accomplished by a series of unique approaches. The proposed work is expected to achieve a new device technology offering harsh environment operability and long-term reliability, open a new strategic area of research on silicon carbide, and advance the state-of-the-art of a wide range of sensing and actuating systems.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The broader impacts are to expose graduate and undergraduate students involved in the project to an interdisciplinary approach for problem solving, including solid state electronics, mechanical engineering, photonic and quantum mechanical simulations, and device fabrication and characterization.  It will broaden dissemination to enhance scientific and technological understanding through journal and conference publications, K-12 outreach, and industrial interaction and partnership.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>05/09/2013</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/09/2013</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1307237</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Feng</FirstName>
<LastName>Zhao</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Feng Zhao</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>feng.zhao@wsu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>3605469187</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000630673</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/09/2013</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Washington State University</Name>
<CityName>PULLMAN</CityName>
<ZipCode>991641060</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5093359661</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>280 Lighty</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[PO BOX 641060]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Washington</StateName>
<StateCode>WA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>WA05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>041485301</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>WASHINGTON STATE UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>041485301</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Washington State University]]></Name>
<CityName>Vancouver</CityName>
<StateCode>WA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>986869600</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Washington</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>WA03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1517</Code>
<Text>EPMD-ElectrnPhoton&amp;MagnDevices</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>104E</Code>
<Text>MEMS/NEMS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8028</Code>
<Text>Sensor Technology</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0113</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2013~240076</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Microelectrochemical system (MEMS) has been recognized as a very useful technology for a wide range of applications. Demand are growing for operations of MEMS devices in harsh environmental conditions, such as in oil and gas exploration, aircraft propulsion, automotive engine, aerospace, etc. with extremes of pressure, temperature, vibration, shock, radiation, chemical (acids and bases), biological domains, corrosion attacks, and so on. Conventional MEMS material silicon (Si) has found limitations to operate in these environments due to the material properties, while a wide bandgap semiconductor silicon carbide (SiC) instead has been identified as the desirable replacement.&nbsp; However, due to the extreme chemical resistance of SiC, it is challenging to release suspended SiC structures to form SiC MEMS, which limited the research of SiC MEMS devices for abovementioned harsh environmental applications. The research supported by this award has successfully solved this long-existing challenge by an innovative technique through interdisciplinary research in chemistry, photonics, electrical and microelectronics, and research a new generation of microactuator devices which meet the imperative demands for high energy efficiency and harsh environment operations. The award has also supported two graduate students for research thesis work, provided research training and experience to three undergraduate including one African American student, and disseminated research results in three undergraduate courses and through peer-reviewed journal and conference publications. &nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 07/10/2017<br>      Modified by: Feng&nbsp;Zhao</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Microelectrochemical system (MEMS) has been recognized as a very useful technology for a wide range of applications. Demand are growing for operations of MEMS devices in harsh environmental conditions, such as in oil and gas exploration, aircraft propulsion, automotive engine, aerospace, etc. with extremes of pressure, temperature, vibration, shock, radiation, chemical (acids and bases), biological domains, corrosion attacks, and so on. Conventional MEMS material silicon (Si) has found limitations to operate in these environments due to the material properties, while a wide bandgap semiconductor silicon carbide (SiC) instead has been identified as the desirable replacement.  However, due to the extreme chemical resistance of SiC, it is challenging to release suspended SiC structures to form SiC MEMS, which limited the research of SiC MEMS devices for abovementioned harsh environmental applications. The research supported by this award has successfully solved this long-existing challenge by an innovative technique through interdisciplinary research in chemistry, photonics, electrical and microelectronics, and research a new generation of microactuator devices which meet the imperative demands for high energy efficiency and harsh environment operations. The award has also supported two graduate students for research thesis work, provided research training and experience to three undergraduate including one African American student, and disseminated research results in three undergraduate courses and through peer-reviewed journal and conference publications.         Last Modified: 07/10/2017       Submitted by: Feng Zhao]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
