<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Advancing Behavioral and Social Science Research for Public Policy: The Policy Roundtable of the Behavioral and Social Sciences</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>05/15/2013</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>04/30/2016</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>100000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>100000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>04010000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>SBE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>SMA</Abbreviation>
<LongName>SBE Off Of Multidisciplinary Activities</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Maryann Feldman</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The National Academies Policy Roundtable of the Behavioral and Social Sciences is exploring ways in which the behavioral and social sciences can better inform and otherwise contribute to more effective and efficient government policies and programs.  Building upon the recent National Academies report, Using Science as Evidence in Public Policy, the Roundtable brings together those who make or advise on policy, those who conduct policy-relevant research, and those who fund research and data collection in order to provide the interaction necessary for the production of relevant research that policy makers can use.  The Roundtable informs policy makers of the relevance and utility of behavioral and social science research and engages researchers in formulating researchable questions that meet their needs.  The Roundtable also contributes to the development of research to better understand and advance the use of science to inform public policy and is a source of ideas for future National Academies workshops, conferences, and studies. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Roundtable members discuss priority issues in the use of behavioral and social science research for public policy and engage in dialogue, share information, and suggest ideas for further exploration and further research.  A public workshop usually follows with presentations and discussions on identified topics that would further advance the use of science in public policy.  About three meetings of the Roundtable are to be held each year.  Brief summaries of the Roundtable discussions, or meeting recaps, are provided to members and a summary or proceedings of workshops is to be publicly available.  &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Broader Impacts.  For scientific research to continue to contribute to societal well-being, it is critical that decisions on public policies are informed by relevant scientific knowledge.  The creative dialogue within the Policy Roundtable and the presentations and discussions at its workshops will serve this important purpose.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>05/08/2013</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>11/19/2015</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.075</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1307895</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Miron</FirstName>
<LastName>Straf</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>L</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Miron L Straf</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>mstraf@nas.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2023343097</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000395809</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/08/2013</StartDate>
<EndDate>11/19/2015</EndDate>
<RoleCode>Former Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Melissa</FirstName>
<LastName>Welch-Ross</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Melissa Welch-Ross</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>mwelchross@nas.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2023342254</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000701723</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>11/19/2015</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>National Academy of Sciences</Name>
<CityName>Washington</CityName>
<ZipCode>200012721</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2023342254</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>500 FIFTH STREET NW</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>District of Columbia</StateName>
<StateCode>DC</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>00</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>DC00</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>041964057</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>NATIONAL ACADEMY OF SCIENCES</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>041964057</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[National Academy of Sciences]]></Name>
<CityName>Washington</CityName>
<StateCode>DC</StateCode>
<ZipCode>200012721</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[500 5th Street, NW]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>District of Columbia</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>00</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>DC00</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7626</Code>
<Text>SciSIP-Sci of Sci Innov Policy</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0113</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0114</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2013~50000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~50000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The Roundtable on the Communication and Use of Social and Behavioral Science supports the capacity for social and behavioral science (SBS) research to inform decisions and improve quality of life. The ability to meet most of society&rsquo;s challenges requires an understanding of human behavior.&nbsp; From health to education to homeland security, advances in social and behavioral science have contributed to solving important problems for individuals, organizations, and society.&nbsp; Conveying the messages of SBS research, and in some cases, its relevance to policy issues is complex and requires greater awareness of the issues involved to design strategic approaches.</p> <p>To this end, the Roundtable brings together in its membership and activities three sets of stakeholders&mdash;those who conduct the research, those who use it, and those who know how to communicate it&mdash;to discuss and develop strategies for promoting understanding and use of social and behavioral science. The roundtable&rsquo;s seminar series in particular is designed to provide a venue for the producers, users and communicators of research &ndash;on the roundtable and beyond&mdash;to exchange information and ideas to better define an issue or problem on a timely topic that needs attention to improve the communication and use of social and behavioral science. While focused on topics that pertain to social and behavioral science, roundtable activities speak to issues that are relevant to the communication and use of research from all science.&nbsp;</p> <p>Over the past year, the roundtable has refined its mission and explored with a wide range of experts the issues that would benefit from the roundtable&rsquo;s attention.&nbsp; To date, the roundtable has examined two topics as part of its seminar series. A first seminar on <strong><em>Clear and Credible Information from Social and Behavioral Science To Improve Societal Outcomes</em></strong> examined why decision-makers can struggle to obtain clear and credible information from social and behavioral science that meets their needs and what can be done. The seminar brought together experts who communicate science and support the use of science in decision-making such as from the Urban Institute, National Governor&rsquo;s Association, Pew Charitable Trusts, William T. Grant Foundation, and the Centers for Disease Control and Prevention. Such organizations use diverse ways of communicating and supporting the use of social and behavioral science for policy and other decisions. The discussion underscored the need to understand the ways in which states, cities, and communities in the United States vary in their capacity to access and use social and behavioral research and how they may benefit from additional support to help access such information (see http://sites.nationalacademies.org/DBASSE/DBASSE_170287 for a webcast of the event).</p> <p>A second seminar,<strong> <em>How to Improve News Coverage of Social and Behavioral Science, </em></strong>scheduled for August 9, will bring together individual researchers, science-based organizations, members of leading news organizations to address how to identify and more accurately convey newsworthy social and behavioral science research findings that can benefit the public.&nbsp; This seminar will be webcast to enable the discussion to reach a wide audience.</p> <p>The impact of this Roundtable over time, through its seminar series and other activities, is intended to increase awareness of: (1) the issues and challenges involved in communicating social and behavioral science research and ways of addressing these challenges, (2) how social and behavioral science is relevant to and used to inform decisions of individuals and society, and (3) ways in which social and behavioral scientists can conduct innovative research to benefit the public.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 07/29/2016<br>      Modified by: Melissa&nbsp;Welch-Ross</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The Roundtable on the Communication and Use of Social and Behavioral Science supports the capacity for social and behavioral science (SBS) research to inform decisions and improve quality of life. The ability to meet most of society?s challenges requires an understanding of human behavior.  From health to education to homeland security, advances in social and behavioral science have contributed to solving important problems for individuals, organizations, and society.  Conveying the messages of SBS research, and in some cases, its relevance to policy issues is complex and requires greater awareness of the issues involved to design strategic approaches.  To this end, the Roundtable brings together in its membership and activities three sets of stakeholders&mdash;those who conduct the research, those who use it, and those who know how to communicate it&mdash;to discuss and develop strategies for promoting understanding and use of social and behavioral science. The roundtable?s seminar series in particular is designed to provide a venue for the producers, users and communicators of research &ndash;on the roundtable and beyond&mdash;to exchange information and ideas to better define an issue or problem on a timely topic that needs attention to improve the communication and use of social and behavioral science. While focused on topics that pertain to social and behavioral science, roundtable activities speak to issues that are relevant to the communication and use of research from all science.   Over the past year, the roundtable has refined its mission and explored with a wide range of experts the issues that would benefit from the roundtable?s attention.  To date, the roundtable has examined two topics as part of its seminar series. A first seminar on Clear and Credible Information from Social and Behavioral Science To Improve Societal Outcomes examined why decision-makers can struggle to obtain clear and credible information from social and behavioral science that meets their needs and what can be done. The seminar brought together experts who communicate science and support the use of science in decision-making such as from the Urban Institute, National Governor?s Association, Pew Charitable Trusts, William T. Grant Foundation, and the Centers for Disease Control and Prevention. Such organizations use diverse ways of communicating and supporting the use of social and behavioral science for policy and other decisions. The discussion underscored the need to understand the ways in which states, cities, and communities in the United States vary in their capacity to access and use social and behavioral research and how they may benefit from additional support to help access such information (see http://sites.nationalacademies.org/DBASSE/DBASSE_170287 for a webcast of the event).  A second seminar, How to Improve News Coverage of Social and Behavioral Science, scheduled for August 9, will bring together individual researchers, science-based organizations, members of leading news organizations to address how to identify and more accurately convey newsworthy social and behavioral science research findings that can benefit the public.  This seminar will be webcast to enable the discussion to reach a wide audience.  The impact of this Roundtable over time, through its seminar series and other activities, is intended to increase awareness of: (1) the issues and challenges involved in communicating social and behavioral science research and ways of addressing these challenges, (2) how social and behavioral science is relevant to and used to inform decisions of individuals and society, and (3) ways in which social and behavioral scientists can conduct innovative research to benefit the public.          Last Modified: 07/29/2016       Submitted by: Melissa Welch-Ross]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
