<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Plaquette Percolation</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/15/2013</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>285381.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>285381</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DMS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Tomek Bartoszynski</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>tbartosz@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924885</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>There is a long and fruitful history of interaction between probability and many other fields such as combinatorics and ergodic theory. This proposal will further many of these connections in a number of fields including random simplicial complexes random matrix theory, extremal combinatorics and geometric group theory. In particular this proposal focuses on problems in the following areas: topology of random simplicial complexes, spectrum of random matrices, higher dimensional generalizations of percolation and subshifts of finite type.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Randomness is evident in many aspects of modern life from conflicting political polls to fluctuations in the stock market. Probability theory is the branch of mathematics which tries to quantify randomness. Over the last few decades the language, ideas and results from probability theory have been applied to many different branches of mathematics. This proposal seeks to continue this trend and extend the connections between probability theory and several branches of mathematics. This proposal also will apply probability theory to topology, a branch of mathematics which until recently has had little interaction with probability. The grant has will sponsor talks that will let undergraduates learn about the ways that mathematics has been applied to a variety of fields.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/24/2013</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/27/2015</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1308645</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Christopher</FirstName>
<LastName>Hoffman</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>E</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Christopher E Hoffman</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>hoffman@math.washington.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2065431725</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000392596</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/24/2013</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Washington</Name>
<CityName>Seattle</CityName>
<ZipCode>981950001</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2065434043</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>4333 Brooklyn Ave NE</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Washington</StateName>
<StateCode>WA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>WA07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>605799469</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF WASHINGTON</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>042803536</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Washington, Dept of Mathematics]]></Name>
<CityName>Seattle</CityName>
<StateCode>WA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>981954350</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[Box 354350]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Washington</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>WA07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1263</Code>
<Text>PROBABILITY</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0113</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0114</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0115</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2013~84940</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~99107</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2015~101334</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>This grant was used to conduct research in mathematics and to disseminate the results. The main areas of research were probability, combinatorics and stochastic topology. The most significant results came in a model called first-passage percolation, which comes from statistical physics. The results that originated from the grant were shared at universities around the country and around the world. The grant also funded several graduate students who were working on their Ph.D. dissertations. These students are now working at companies such as Microsoft and Google and Universities such as Duke and California-Berkeley. The project also funded an undergraduate research proposal. This project was one of the main components in the proposal of a student who was awarded a Goldwater Fellowship.</p> <p>The grant gave partial support to a lecture series called MathAcross Campus. This lecture series was aimed at a broad mathematically literate audience. This lecture series is very popular with undergraduates and exposes large audiences to ways that mathematics appears in the world around us. We had talks from world renowned experts about topics including mathematics and music, how mathematics is used in designing humanoid robots and how it can be used to explain the shape of river delta formations.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 12/24/2017<br>      Modified by: Christopher&nbsp;E&nbsp;Hoffman</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ This grant was used to conduct research in mathematics and to disseminate the results. The main areas of research were probability, combinatorics and stochastic topology. The most significant results came in a model called first-passage percolation, which comes from statistical physics. The results that originated from the grant were shared at universities around the country and around the world. The grant also funded several graduate students who were working on their Ph.D. dissertations. These students are now working at companies such as Microsoft and Google and Universities such as Duke and California-Berkeley. The project also funded an undergraduate research proposal. This project was one of the main components in the proposal of a student who was awarded a Goldwater Fellowship.  The grant gave partial support to a lecture series called MathAcross Campus. This lecture series was aimed at a broad mathematically literate audience. This lecture series is very popular with undergraduates and exposes large audiences to ways that mathematics appears in the world around us. We had talks from world renowned experts about topics including mathematics and music, how mathematics is used in designing humanoid robots and how it can be used to explain the shape of river delta formations.       Last Modified: 12/24/2017       Submitted by: Christopher E Hoffman]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
