<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Program management support for the integrated, multidisciplinary Bering Sea Project:   Maximizing return on investment</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>05/01/2013</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>04/30/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>324791.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>324791</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>06090100</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>GEO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>OPP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Office of Polar Programs (OPP)</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Marc Stieglitz</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>mstiegli@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924354</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This award will support program office and synergistic activities to conclude an integrated, multidisciplinary research program in the eastern Bering Sea, funded through a partnership between the National Science Foundation and the North Pacific Research Board (NPRB). Underway since 2007, the Bering Sea Project has involved dozens of individual research projects and more than 100 investigators, all working toward the goal of improving our understanding of how this highly productive (and economically critical) marine ecosystem may respond to climate change, particularly as mediated through changes in seasonal ice cover. This award seeks to maximize the return on NSF?s and NPRB?s investment during the final two years of the program, through several key activities deemed most critical to capturing and communicating the program's scientific accomplishments. The project would provide funds for 1) publication of thematic special issues of the scientific journal Deep-Sea Research II, 2) travel for members of the Bering Sea Project Science Advisory Board (SAB) to one in-person meeting in Arlington, Virginia and a scientific meeting (the 2014 Alaska Marine Science Symposium), and 3) travel and meeting expenses associated with a capstone open science meeting in 2014. From the start, the Bering Sea Project has incorporated a diverse suite of communication, outreach, and education activities to convey the scientific discoveries of the program to stakeholders, teachers, students, and the public. Funding would support print and electronic publication of short "headlines" scientific synopses, a longer Bering Sea Project magazine, and a programmatic "lessons learned" article.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>05/10/2013</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>03/11/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.078</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1308087</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Francis</FirstName>
<LastName>Wiese</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Francis Wiese</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>francis.wiese@nprb.org</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>9072246343</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000626392</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/10/2013</StartDate>
<EndDate>01/03/2014</EndDate>
<RoleCode>Former Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>John</FirstName>
<LastName>Hilsinger</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>John Hilsinger</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>John.Hilsinger@nprb.org</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>9072246343</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000644693</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/10/2013</StartDate>
<EndDate>01/03/2014</EndDate>
<RoleCode>Former Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Denby</FirstName>
<LastName>Lloyd</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Denby Lloyd</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>denby.lloyd@nprb.org</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>9072246343</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000662840</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>01/03/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Thomas</FirstName>
<LastName>VanPelt</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Thomas VanPelt</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>tom@xboundary.org</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>9072427725</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000667674</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>03/11/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Alaska SeaLife Center</Name>
<CityName>Seward</CityName>
<ZipCode>996641329</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>9072246343</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>P.O. Box 1329</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[301 Railway Avenue]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Alaska</StateName>
<StateCode>AK</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>00</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>AK00</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>015598378</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>SEWARD ASSOCIATION FOR THE ADVANCEMENT OF MARINE SCIENCE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[North Pacific Research Board]]></Name>
<CityName>Anchorage</CityName>
<StateCode>AK</StateCode>
<ZipCode>995011979</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[1007 W 3rd Ave. Ste 100]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Alaska</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>00</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>AK00</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>5280</Code>
<Text>ANS-Arctic Natural Sciences</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1079</Code>
<Text>ARCTIC RESEARCH</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>02XX</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2013~324791</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><strong>Program management support for the integrated, multidisciplinary Bering Sea Project: Maximizing return on investment</strong></p> <p>The Bering Sea Project, a partnership between the National Science Foundation and the North Pacific Research Board, was a seven-year effort involving nearly 100 principal investigators aiming to better understand the impacts of climate change and dynamic sea ice cover on the eastern Bering Sea ecosystem.&nbsp; Project scientists engaged in field research and ecosystem modeling to link climate, physical oceanography, plankton, fishes, seabirds, marine mammals, humans, traditional knowledge and economic outcomes to better understand the mechanisms that sustain this highly productive region that supports an enormous commercial fishing industry and supplies vital subsistence and cultural value to a wide range of coastal and island residents, including many Native communities.</p> <p>The main goals of the subsequent "Program management support for the integrated, multidisciplinary Bering Sea Project: Maximizing return on investment" award were to strengthen integration and synthesis of research projects comprising the Bering Sea Project, and maximize the communication of Bering Sea Project results.&nbsp; To accomplish these goals, our team worked to accomplish several key outcomes along two general tracks:</p> <p>1.<span style="text-decoration: underline;">Strengthen scientific integration and synthesis.</span></p> <p>The program office supported by this award served as a hub for communication, including monthly teleconference meetings of the project steering committee, called the "Science Advisory Board" (SAB).&nbsp; This facilitated scientific leadership and improved coordination across the entire program.&nbsp; To provide an opportunity to highlight results, facilitate collaboration, and share key findings with a broader scientific audience as the program concluded, the Bering Sea Project held a full-day "Open Science Meeting" (OSM) in conjunction with the ASLO/AGU/TOS Ocean Sciences Meeting in Honolulu, Hawaii, in February 2014.&nbsp; A series of 14 talks presented during the OSM&mdash; all with broad multi-author teams&mdash; showcased improved understanding of the interconnectivity among ecosystem elements in the Bering Sea and provided new information on elements of the ecosystem that have extremely high value to communities in Alaska and beyond (e.g. fish, such as walleye pollock and Pacific cod, and marine mammals, such as fur seals and walrus).&nbsp; Synthesis talks were also presented closer to the study region, at annual Alaska Marine Science Symposia in 2013 and 2014 in Anchorage, Alaska.</p> <p>The major products of the Bering Sea Project are peer-review scientific publications, and this award supported the editing and production of issues 2, 3, and 4 in a series of four special Bering Sea Project issues of the journal <em>Deep-Sea Research Part II</em>. &nbsp;These targeted special (thematic) issues provide two key functions. First, they provide a coordinated program footprint &ndash; a legacy product of the Bering Sea Project. Second, they provide a motivation and means to encourage timely publication and dissemination of research results from the program. &nbsp;These special issues lead to a major outcome of this award:&nbsp; increased integration among project components in the form of broad multi-authored publications, often engaging novel collaborations, and improved access to project results and discussion via the papers collected together in the special issues.&nbsp; This leads to improvements in sustainable and ecosystem-based harvest of fish populations and better targeting of future research planning.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>2.&nbsp;<span style="text-decoration: underline;">Capture and communicate Bering Sea Project results.</span>&nbsp;&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>The overall communication strategy was to create new products and communication platforms, building on existing resources and activities, to communicate research results with a range of audiences -- scientists, resource managers, communities, and the broader public. &nbsp;To accomplish this, we created a series of fifty "Headline" research summaries in partnership with individual PIs, who volunteered to showcase their most important or most interesting result. Headlines were developed by program office staff and collaborators to communicate results from both NPRB- and NSF-funded researchers, taking the form of two-page summaries derived from published technical material with accompanying illustrations, with editing for voice and length. &nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>We then used those headlines as raw material to craft an 85-page publication we called the Bering Sea Project "magazine", working together with graphic artists and the SAB. This is a richly illustrated summary report in magazine format to present a more comprehensive overview of the Bering Sea Project for a range of audiences (communities, stakeholders, policymakers, media, public and possibly educators/students), providing an overview of the project history and context, and touching on some of the learning experiences involved in executing such a large and broad program.&nbsp; The magazine is a print and digital publication that introduces the overall Bering Sea Program and describes processes and major results, further strengthening the core outcome of providing clearer and more in-depth communication of the Bering Sea Project to a broad audience beyond the scientific community. &nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 07/25/2017<br>      Modified by: Thomas&nbsp;Vanpelt</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Program management support for the integrated, multidisciplinary Bering Sea Project: Maximizing return on investment  The Bering Sea Project, a partnership between the National Science Foundation and the North Pacific Research Board, was a seven-year effort involving nearly 100 principal investigators aiming to better understand the impacts of climate change and dynamic sea ice cover on the eastern Bering Sea ecosystem.  Project scientists engaged in field research and ecosystem modeling to link climate, physical oceanography, plankton, fishes, seabirds, marine mammals, humans, traditional knowledge and economic outcomes to better understand the mechanisms that sustain this highly productive region that supports an enormous commercial fishing industry and supplies vital subsistence and cultural value to a wide range of coastal and island residents, including many Native communities.  The main goals of the subsequent "Program management support for the integrated, multidisciplinary Bering Sea Project: Maximizing return on investment" award were to strengthen integration and synthesis of research projects comprising the Bering Sea Project, and maximize the communication of Bering Sea Project results.  To accomplish these goals, our team worked to accomplish several key outcomes along two general tracks:  1.Strengthen scientific integration and synthesis.  The program office supported by this award served as a hub for communication, including monthly teleconference meetings of the project steering committee, called the "Science Advisory Board" (SAB).  This facilitated scientific leadership and improved coordination across the entire program.  To provide an opportunity to highlight results, facilitate collaboration, and share key findings with a broader scientific audience as the program concluded, the Bering Sea Project held a full-day "Open Science Meeting" (OSM) in conjunction with the ASLO/AGU/TOS Ocean Sciences Meeting in Honolulu, Hawaii, in February 2014.  A series of 14 talks presented during the OSM&mdash; all with broad multi-author teams&mdash; showcased improved understanding of the interconnectivity among ecosystem elements in the Bering Sea and provided new information on elements of the ecosystem that have extremely high value to communities in Alaska and beyond (e.g. fish, such as walleye pollock and Pacific cod, and marine mammals, such as fur seals and walrus).  Synthesis talks were also presented closer to the study region, at annual Alaska Marine Science Symposia in 2013 and 2014 in Anchorage, Alaska.  The major products of the Bering Sea Project are peer-review scientific publications, and this award supported the editing and production of issues 2, 3, and 4 in a series of four special Bering Sea Project issues of the journal Deep-Sea Research Part II.  These targeted special (thematic) issues provide two key functions. First, they provide a coordinated program footprint &ndash; a legacy product of the Bering Sea Project. Second, they provide a motivation and means to encourage timely publication and dissemination of research results from the program.  These special issues lead to a major outcome of this award:  increased integration among project components in the form of broad multi-authored publications, often engaging novel collaborations, and improved access to project results and discussion via the papers collected together in the special issues.  This leads to improvements in sustainable and ecosystem-based harvest of fish populations and better targeting of future research planning.     2. Capture and communicate Bering Sea Project results.       The overall communication strategy was to create new products and communication platforms, building on existing resources and activities, to communicate research results with a range of audiences -- scientists, resource managers, communities, and the broader public.  To accomplish this, we created a series of fifty "Headline" research summaries in partnership with individual PIs, who volunteered to showcase their most important or most interesting result. Headlines were developed by program office staff and collaborators to communicate results from both NPRB- and NSF-funded researchers, taking the form of two-page summaries derived from published technical material with accompanying illustrations, with editing for voice and length.       We then used those headlines as raw material to craft an 85-page publication we called the Bering Sea Project "magazine", working together with graphic artists and the SAB. This is a richly illustrated summary report in magazine format to present a more comprehensive overview of the Bering Sea Project for a range of audiences (communities, stakeholders, policymakers, media, public and possibly educators/students), providing an overview of the project history and context, and touching on some of the learning experiences involved in executing such a large and broad program.  The magazine is a print and digital publication that introduces the overall Bering Sea Program and describes processes and major results, further strengthening the core outcome of providing clearer and more in-depth communication of the Bering Sea Project to a broad audience beyond the scientific community.         Last Modified: 07/25/2017       Submitted by: Thomas Vanpelt]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
