<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Dissertation Research:  Closing the nitrogen budget:  Quantifying denitrification in an arid ecosystem undergoing nitrogen enrichment</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2013</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2015</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>20820.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>20820</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>08010209</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>BIO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DEB</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Environmental Biology</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Henry L. Gholz</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Adding reactive nitrogen, from fertilizer, deposition, or nitrogen fixing plants, to ecosystems can cause rapid and often detrimental changes considered undesirable by humans. The creation of dinitrogen gas (N2) through a process called denitrification is the primary mechanism that removes reactive nitrogen from an ecosystem. However, this process can also produce nitrous oxide (N2O), a greenhouse gas. Therefore, understanding how much N2 versus N2O is produced during denitrification is critical to understanding both climate and ecosystem nutrient balance. One of the challenges of studying denitrification in the real world is that it is very difficult to measure the production of N2 in the field. The work proposed here will take advantage of a new lab measurement technique to measure the production of N2 from soils and examine how denitrification, N2 and N2O production and nitrogen cycling change after the expansion of a nitrogen-fixing trees into an arid subtropical grassland.&lt;br/&gt;Arid lands occupy nearly a third of the Earth's surface and support large human populations, so understanding the processing of nitrogen in these systems is important for future land use and global climate management. This project will provide the first estimate of the N2 loss occurring during denitrification in an arid system nitrogen cycle, and help to refine a method that can then be applied to other sites and ecosystems. The primary research site used in this project is an active cattle ranch in Southern Texas that is regularly visited by students, land managers and nature enthusiasts. This project will take advantage of this public interface to educate on the effects and importance of human-driven landscape changes on ecosystem nutrient cycling.&lt;br/&gt;</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/12/2013</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/12/2013</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.074</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1309124</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Jed</FirstName>
<LastName>Sparks</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>P</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Jed P Sparks</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>jps66@cornell.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6072544270</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000423582</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/12/2013</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Fiona</FirstName>
<LastName>Soper</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>M</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Fiona M Soper</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>fiona.soper@umontana.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6073515013</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000630082</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/12/2013</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Cornell University</Name>
<CityName>Ithaca</CityName>
<ZipCode>148502820</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6072555014</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>373 Pine Tree Road</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>23</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NY23</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>872612445</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>CORNELL UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>002254837</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Cornell University]]></Name>
<CityName>Ithaca</CityName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<ZipCode>148532701</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[Corson Hall, 215 Tower Road]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>23</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NY23</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1181</Code>
<Text>ECOSYSTEM STUDIES</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1181</Code>
<Text>ECOSYSTEM STUDIES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9169</Code>
<Text>BIODIVERSITY AND ECOSYSTEM DYNAMICS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>EGCH</Code>
<Text>ENVIRONMENT AND GLOBAL CHANGE</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0113</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2013~20820</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Dry ecosystems, including deserts and grasslands make up 40% of the land on earth. Many of these ecosystems experience large inputs of nutrients, particularly nitrogen, as a result of human impacts and changing vegetation cover. New nitrogen can have several fates- it can be stored in the soil, taken up by plants, lost to waterways or released back to the atmospheric as nitrogen-based greenhouse gases or as inert N<sub>2</sub>. Loss of N<sub>2</sub> is an important way of removing reactive nitrogen from biological cycling and is desirable in decreasing both pollution and greenhouse gases. However, almost no measures of how important this process is in drylands or what environmental conditions might control it exist. This project applied laboratory-based methods to measure N<sub>2</sub> production from a south Texas savanna experiencing increased nitrogen inputs. We found that N<sub>2</sub> production in this ecosystem is low compared with other ecosystems, and with savannas on other continents. Under field conditions, N<sub>2</sub> production is unlikely to occur in the winter months, and in the summer months soil conditions are not conductive to high rates of production. Field measurements showed that other reactive nitrogen trace gases are likely a more significant component of nitrogen gas loss than N<sub>2</sub>. This suggests that new nitrogen that enters this ecosystem is likely stored or cycled in reactive forms, rather than removed as unreactive N<sub>2</sub>.</p> <p>This project fostered a collaboration between Cornell University, the Cary Institute of Ecosystem Studies and Texas A&amp;M University. As a part of this study, a female graduate student and a female undergraduate honors student received training in lab analytical methods, field measurements, data analysis and other professional skills.&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 08/08/2015<br>      Modified by: Fiona&nbsp;M&nbsp;Soper</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Dry ecosystems, including deserts and grasslands make up 40% of the land on earth. Many of these ecosystems experience large inputs of nutrients, particularly nitrogen, as a result of human impacts and changing vegetation cover. New nitrogen can have several fates- it can be stored in the soil, taken up by plants, lost to waterways or released back to the atmospheric as nitrogen-based greenhouse gases or as inert N2. Loss of N2 is an important way of removing reactive nitrogen from biological cycling and is desirable in decreasing both pollution and greenhouse gases. However, almost no measures of how important this process is in drylands or what environmental conditions might control it exist. This project applied laboratory-based methods to measure N2 production from a south Texas savanna experiencing increased nitrogen inputs. We found that N2 production in this ecosystem is low compared with other ecosystems, and with savannas on other continents. Under field conditions, N2 production is unlikely to occur in the winter months, and in the summer months soil conditions are not conductive to high rates of production. Field measurements showed that other reactive nitrogen trace gases are likely a more significant component of nitrogen gas loss than N2. This suggests that new nitrogen that enters this ecosystem is likely stored or cycled in reactive forms, rather than removed as unreactive N2.  This project fostered a collaboration between Cornell University, the Cary Institute of Ecosystem Studies and Texas A&amp;M University. As a part of this study, a female graduate student and a female undergraduate honors student received training in lab analytical methods, field measurements, data analysis and other professional skills.           Last Modified: 08/08/2015       Submitted by: Fiona M Soper]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
