<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>GOALI: Atomic Scale Modeling and Experimental Characterization of Non-Basal Deformation Modes in Mg Alloys</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/15/2013</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>03/31/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>300000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>300000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03070000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DMR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Materials Research</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Daryl Hess</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>dhess@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924942</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Technical Abstract:  &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project will provide a scientific basis for a quantitative and systematic approach to design Magnesium alloys with favorable combinations of strength and ductility through selective alloying. The approach is based on electronic-structure calculations of non-basal deformation modes including &lt;c+a&gt; slip and twinning including accurately accounting for chemistry effects due to alloying coupled with experimental observation and verification of computational predictions. Ab initio and atomistic simulations will be done to investigate (i) Mechanisms for tension twin nucleation and alloys that promote nucleation and growth of twins  (ii) the core structures and mobility of &lt;c+a&gt; dislocations in Mg (iii) effects of alloying on the structure and collective behavior of &lt;c+a&gt; dislocations.  Conventional transmission electron microscopy including bright field, and weak beam techniques will be conducted on deformed single crystal of Mg and binary Mg alloys to understand the effect of chemistry on &lt;c+a&gt; dislocations -based deformation response for specific forms of loading. This will provide connections to computations. Furthermore, aberration-corrected high resolution electron microscopy of dislocation core structures will enable a more direct connection with results from computations. The experiments and computations together will provide a comprehensive understanding of non-basal deformation in Mg alloys, the effect of chemistry on its relative ease, and a pathway to microstructurally-guided and scientifically-informed alloy design.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Non-technical Abstract:  &lt;br/&gt;The high strength-to-weight ratio of magnesium and magnesium-based alloys makes them excellent candidates for the transportation sector and in particular, the automotive industry that is focused on producing lighter-weight, more fuel-efficient vehicles. However, limited room temperature formability (a feature required to produce useful shapes by forming in a die for example) has prohibited the widespread use of Mg alloys.  Forming at elevated temperatures adds cost and makes the material less competitive. Formability is related to the ease of plastic deformation, a phenomenon that is facilitated by atomic level processes called slip and/or twinning. In essence, these atomic level mechanisms are the material's response to application of external forces and these mechanisms enable permanent macroscopic shape change in a material, referred to as plastic deformation. Difficulty in plastic deformation encourages an alternate undesirable response which is premature failure/fracture. In the case of magnesium alloys, the limited formability is related to anisotropic plastic deformation. This means plastic deformation is easy in some directions of the sheet that is being formed but not in others. The cause of this anisotropy lies in the strong differentials in stress (or force) needed to trigger some forms of plastic deformation as opposed to others, a characteristic of this alloy system.   This project is focused on identifying alloying elements using a combination of computations and experiments that can reduce the critical stress differential between these deformation modes to facilitate isotropic plastic deformation and thereby improve room temperature formability.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/19/2013</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/19/2013</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1309687</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>K. Sharvan</FirstName>
<LastName>Kumar</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>K. Sharvan Kumar</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>Sharvan_Kumar@brown.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>4018632862</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000211028</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/19/2013</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Louis</FirstName>
<LastName>Hector, Jr.</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME>Jr.</PI_SUFX_NAME>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Louis Hector, Jr.</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>Louis.Hector@gm.com</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5866512628</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000302015</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/19/2013</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Maryam</FirstName>
<LastName>Ghazisaeidi</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Maryam Ghazisaeidi</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>Maryam_Ghazisaeidi@brown.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>4018632777</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000632182</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/19/2013</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Jie</FirstName>
<LastName>Geng</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Jie Geng</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>Jie_Geng@brown.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>4018632777</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000632183</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/19/2013</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Brown University</Name>
<CityName>Providence</CityName>
<ZipCode>029129002</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>4018632777</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>BOX 1929</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[350 Eddy Street]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Rhode Island</StateName>
<StateCode>RI</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>RI01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>001785542</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>BROWN UNIVERSITY IN PROVIDENCE IN THE STATE OF RHODE ISLAND AND PROVIDENCE PLANTATIONS</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>001785542</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Brown University]]></Name>
<CityName>Providence</CityName>
<StateCode>RI</StateCode>
<ZipCode>029129002</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[182 Hope Street]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Rhode Island</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>RI01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1253</Code>
<Text>OFFICE OF MULTIDISCIPLINARY AC</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>8029</Code>
<Text>Comp&amp;Data Driven Mat Res(CDMR)</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1504</Code>
<Text>GRANT OPP FOR ACAD LIA W/INDUS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7433</Code>
<Text>CyberInfra Frmwrk 21st (CIF21)</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8084</Code>
<Text>CDS&amp;E</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0113</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2013~300000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>By virtue of their low density, Magnesium (Mg) and Mg-rich alloys are of significant interest in lightweight vehicle technology. However the ability to form these materials into useful shapes at ambient temperature (to be cost competitive with aluminum alloys and steels) and their inadequate damage resistance have been the Achilles heel to widespread implementation. These properties rely on &ldquo;the ease of plastic deformation&rdquo;, a phenomenon that is mediated by atomic level processes; facilitating these processes is central to enhancing these properties. The approach in this project has been to use computations to first understand the details of these atomic level processes in pure Mg and then to identify alloying additions that could potentially favorably modify them. Limited experiments were conducted to validate computations.</p> <p>&nbsp;Specific to Mg, there are two important atomic level processes that critically affect plastic deformability and need detailed understanding, if beneficial changes are to be effected: these are &ldquo;twinning&rdquo; and &ldquo; screw and edge dislocation structure and their motion in response to an applied stress&rdquo;.&nbsp;&nbsp; If these two processes are readily enabled, then plastic deformation can be realized. In the first year of this effort, we used computations to examine the influence of Zinc and Aluminum additions to Mg in various concentrations on &ldquo;twinning&rdquo; and determined both elements increase the necessary stress to activate twinning in agreement with experimental findings in the published literature.</p> <p>We next computed the structure and mobility of the  screw and edge dislocations in <em>pure Mg</em> because this knowledge is essential to explain the  configurations that we experimentally observed.&nbsp;We found lower stress values were required to move the edge dislocations compared to screw dislocations. However, the screw dislocation had an alternative metastable structure that permitted it to move more readily, consistent with experimental findings. Computations also revealed that the addition of Yttrium (Y) to Mg changes the atomic arrangement in the vicinity of a  edge dislocation in a favorable manner; this finding provides an atomic level explanation for published experimental results that demonstrated the benefits of Y addition to plastic deformability. Our computations showed the beneficial effect of increasing Y concentration on plasticity in that the stress to move  dislocations relative to that for moving basal dislocations (a competing mechanism and a measure of plastic anisotropy) decreased. Perhaps most important is the scientific understanding that has emerged at the fundamental level from this effort that will play a significant role in interpreting emerging results in this field as well as provide guidelines/methodology &nbsp;for further alloy design.</p> <p>The program has been instrumental in training graduate students and post-doctoral researchers in this contemporary approach of using computations-guided materials development rather than the tedious trial-and-error experimental approach that is traditional. The complex nature of the problem has demanded that the graduate student use cutting edge computational techniques to model at the atomic scale, such as the LAMMPS package for molecular dynamics modeling and density functional theory (DFT) calculations with VASP. In addition, an undergraduate student and a high school minority student were included in the project for an internship in the summer of 2015 that enabled them develop an appreciation for research. On the experimental front, training included using a variety of state-of-the-art tools including the FIB, the nanoindenter, EBSD and TEM. This project, by virtue of the complexity in coping with the hcp structure also placed new demands on computational capacity and led to new capabilities as well as new approaches/methodologies. &nbsp;For example,&nbsp;General Motors R&amp;D, our industry partner on this effort, dedicated more than 900 LINUX processors for this GOALI project at its High Performance Computing Center.&nbsp;Further, the computational methodology developed in this project will be useful for understanding defect structures and their response to applied stress and the consequences of alloying in other HCP metals and alloys of technological relevance, for example Ti and its alloys in the aerospace industry, and Zr and its alloys in the nuclear industry. &nbsp; Results from this project have been disseminated to the scientific community through presentations and peer-reviewed publications.&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 06/01/2017<br>      Modified by: K. Sharvan&nbsp;Kumar</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ By virtue of their low density, Magnesium (Mg) and Mg-rich alloys are of significant interest in lightweight vehicle technology. However the ability to form these materials into useful shapes at ambient temperature (to be cost competitive with aluminum alloys and steels) and their inadequate damage resistance have been the Achilles heel to widespread implementation. These properties rely on "the ease of plastic deformation", a phenomenon that is mediated by atomic level processes; facilitating these processes is central to enhancing these properties. The approach in this project has been to use computations to first understand the details of these atomic level processes in pure Mg and then to identify alloying additions that could potentially favorably modify them. Limited experiments were conducted to validate computations.   Specific to Mg, there are two important atomic level processes that critically affect plastic deformability and need detailed understanding, if beneficial changes are to be effected: these are "twinning" and " screw and edge dislocation structure and their motion in response to an applied stress".   If these two processes are readily enabled, then plastic deformation can be realized. In the first year of this effort, we used computations to examine the influence of Zinc and Aluminum additions to Mg in various concentrations on "twinning" and determined both elements increase the necessary stress to activate twinning in agreement with experimental findings in the published literature.  We next computed the structure and mobility of the  screw and edge dislocations in pure Mg because this knowledge is essential to explain the  configurations that we experimentally observed. We found lower stress values were required to move the edge dislocations compared to screw dislocations. However, the screw dislocation had an alternative metastable structure that permitted it to move more readily, consistent with experimental findings. Computations also revealed that the addition of Yttrium (Y) to Mg changes the atomic arrangement in the vicinity of a  edge dislocation in a favorable manner; this finding provides an atomic level explanation for published experimental results that demonstrated the benefits of Y addition to plastic deformability. Our computations showed the beneficial effect of increasing Y concentration on plasticity in that the stress to move  dislocations relative to that for moving basal dislocations (a competing mechanism and a measure of plastic anisotropy) decreased. Perhaps most important is the scientific understanding that has emerged at the fundamental level from this effort that will play a significant role in interpreting emerging results in this field as well as provide guidelines/methodology  for further alloy design.  The program has been instrumental in training graduate students and post-doctoral researchers in this contemporary approach of using computations-guided materials development rather than the tedious trial-and-error experimental approach that is traditional. The complex nature of the problem has demanded that the graduate student use cutting edge computational techniques to model at the atomic scale, such as the LAMMPS package for molecular dynamics modeling and density functional theory (DFT) calculations with VASP. In addition, an undergraduate student and a high school minority student were included in the project for an internship in the summer of 2015 that enabled them develop an appreciation for research. On the experimental front, training included using a variety of state-of-the-art tools including the FIB, the nanoindenter, EBSD and TEM. This project, by virtue of the complexity in coping with the hcp structure also placed new demands on computational capacity and led to new capabilities as well as new approaches/methodologies.  For example, General Motors R&amp;D, our industry partner on this effort, dedicated more than 900 LINUX processors for this GOALI project at its High Performance Computing Center. Further, the computational methodology developed in this project will be useful for understanding defect structures and their response to applied stress and the consequences of alloying in other HCP metals and alloys of technological relevance, for example Ti and its alloys in the aerospace industry, and Zr and its alloys in the nuclear industry.   Results from this project have been disseminated to the scientific community through presentations and peer-reviewed publications.           Last Modified: 06/01/2017       Submitted by: K. Sharvan Kumar]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
