<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Electronic, Magnetic, and Structural Properties of Low Dimensional and Multifunctional Materials</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2013</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>400000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>400000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03070000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DMR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Materials Research</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Tomasz Durakiewicz</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>tdurakie@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924892</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>****Technical Abstract****&lt;br/&gt;This proposal addresses fundamental problems where low dimensionality, anisotropy and size, combined with interacting electronic, magnetic, and lattice effects, lead to the physical properties of materials highly relevant to materials research. Materials of interests include quasi-one-dimensional organic segregated cation-anion charge transfer conductors, magnets, and superconductors on macro to nano-sized scales, and ferrimagnetic d- electron based compounds (such as AB2O4-type spinels) with strongly interacting charge, spin, orbital, and structural degrees of freedom. The thermodynamic variables used in this experimentally-based investigation include low temperatures, high magnetic fields, and high pressures, and the experimental tools include a broad range of methods in condensed matter physics. Scientifically, this project expands the understanding of how the order parameters in low dimensional and restricted geometry environments interact cooperatively, coexist, or exclude each other. In materials where magnetic and lattice effects strongly interact, low temperature and high magnetic field studies will give new insight into their complex interdependence. In terms of training, problem solving is emphasized. Young researchers in the group are exposed to a broad range of materials, methods, and to a large community of collaborators, both domestic and international. For education, the program's main approach is to bring the lab into the classroom and to the public through curricula, workshops and outreach programs.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;****Non-Technical Abstract****&lt;br/&gt;The scientific goals of the project will expand the understanding of how important properties of materials such as magnetism and superconductivity "talk to each other" and behave under extremes of temperature, magnetic field and pressure.  In such cases, one kind of stimulus can make a material respond in a different way (for instance thermal to electrical, magnetic to electrical or electrical to mechanical) and such effects can lead to the development of multifunctional materials of potential technological importance. Low dimensionality and anisotropy, where the properties of materials such as the flow of energy or current may be very different in different directions, are key parameters in the realization and control of function, and both organic and inorganic materials will be the focus of the investigations. In terms of education, problem solving is a main goal in the training of young researchers in the group, who are exposed to a broad range of materials, methods, and to a large community of collaborators, both domestic and international. For education and outreach, the program's main approach is to bring the lab into the classroom and to the public. The PI and the research group have a culture of outreach as part of their responsibility,  and have a sustained  level of involvement in STEM and diversity related programs in the laboratory, the university, the state, and nationally.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/05/2013</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/26/2015</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1309146</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>James</FirstName>
<LastName>Brooks</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>S</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>James S Brooks</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>brooks@magnet.fsu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>8506442836</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000480102</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/05/2013</StartDate>
<EndDate>10/27/2014</EndDate>
<RoleCode>Former Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Eun Sang</FirstName>
<LastName>Choi</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Eun Sang Choi</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>echoi@magnet.fsu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>8506445260</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000682956</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>10/27/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Florida State University</Name>
<CityName>TALLAHASSEE</CityName>
<ZipCode>323064166</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>8506445260</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>874 Traditions Way, 3rd Floor</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Florida</StateName>
<StateCode>FL</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>FL02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>790877419</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>FLORIDA STATE UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>159621697</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Florida State University]]></Name>
<CityName>Tallahassee</CityName>
<StateCode>FL</StateCode>
<ZipCode>323103706</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[NHMFL 1800 East Paul Dirac Dr.]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Florida</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>FL05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1710</Code>
<Text>CONDENSED MATTER PHYSICS</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0113</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0114</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0115</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2013~200000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~100000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2015~100000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The objective of this project is to investigate physical properties of low dimensional materials which are highly relevant to materials research. Materials of particular interest are organic charge transfer salts with quasi 1D or quasi 2D electronic properties. Organic charge transfer salts, also known as molecular conductors or organic conductors have provided fertile grounds for fundamental scientific researches for last four decades since a discovery of TTF-TCNQ [Tetrathiafulvalene-Tetracyanoquinodimethane<strong>]. </strong>In organic conductors, the atoms in an inorganic solid are replaced by molecules, whose nature and interaction of spin, charge, and lattice degree of freedom lead to diverse physical properties including superconductivity, magnetism, metal-insulator transition, and so forth. In this project, a greater emphasis was placed on the functionality and the technology transfer in the organic conductor based materials.</p> <p>Historically, there have been efforts to utilize the versatile properties of organic conductors for various applications. However, there were obstacles originated from the fragility of the single crystals and low yield from the conventional electrochemical synthesis. But in very recent years, a breakthrough in the synthesis of organic conductors, that is, synthesizing them on the surface of elastic polymeric substrates opened a new horizon to the field. In this project, we used the new synthesis method to make different kinds of organic conductor/polymer bilayer films and measured their physical properties that might lead to the technology application.</p> <p>In the report, three kinds of bilayer films are presented as representing examples. BEDT-TTF&nbsp; [Bis(ethylenedithio)tetrathiafulvalene] is a well-known organic molecule that has been a building block of many quasi 2D organic superconductors. When the BEDT-TTF is formed on polycarbonate substrate by the wet chemistry process, the resulting bilayer film is consist of elastic film and nano-sized BEDT-TTF molecules grown on it. The mechanical and optical properties (flexible and transparent) and the electrical properties of the resulting hybrid material are determined by the polymer substrate and the BEDT-TTF molecules, respectively. When the bilayer film is doped with iodine, the film becomes metallic and piezo-resistive, meaning its electrical conductivity is very sensitive to the strain exerted on the film. We found the gauge factor (sensitivity parameters as a strain sensor) is about 20, much larger than commercial metal strain gauges by about six times but smaller than the most sensitive Si based gauges by factor of 5. We demonstrated the usefulness of the material by measuring quantum oscillations of (BEDT-TTF)<sub>2</sub>Cu(NCS) organic superconductors with a device made of the bilayer film (Fig. 1). The most sophisticated tool required for the device fabrication was a pair of scissors.</p> <p>Secondly, we synthesized a bilayer film based on another class of organic conductors, TMTSF-iodine compound [TMTSF= Tetramethyltetraselenafulvalene] and rubber polymers. Of note is that the TMTSF is a building block of many Q1D organic superconductors. Consequently, the morphology of the TMTSF-Iodine on the rubber substrate is quite different from the (BEDT-TTF)-Iodine bilayer film; the former is nano-rod like and the latter nano-plates. Even more interestingly, the TMTSF nano-rods self-assemble to micrometer sized structures, which follows fractal formation as shown in Fig. 2. The underlying mechanism of such fractal formation is still under investigation. It was also found that the piezo-resistivity of this film is comparable to the (BEDT-TTF)-iodine/polycarbonate bilayer film.</p> <p>Last example is (BEDO-TTF)<sub>2.4</sub>I<sub>3</sub>-polycarbonate bilayer film [BEDO-TTF=bis(ethylenedioxy)tetrathiafulvalene]. In this bilayer film, a new kind of functionality, electrochromism, where the color of a material can be controlled by the electricity, was discovered. The controlling voltage is found to be of 2-3 V, lower than that of the previous known materials showing electrochromism. Since the substrate of the organic bilayer film is flexible, this interesting property can be utilized to make flexible displays.&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;In summary, we have studied physical properties of organic conductor bilayer films synthesized flexible polymer substrates. They show great potentials for technology applications as sensing devices and flexible displays. The methodology and knowledge we acquired through this project are also useful for future research projects and would promote more investigations of exploring organic conductors as new kind of technology material.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 09/28/2017<br>      Modified by: Eun Sang&nbsp;Choi</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Images (<span id="selectedPhoto0">1</span> of <span class="totalNumber"></span>)           </div> <div class="galControls" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1309146/1309146_10250324_1506434101770_Fig.1--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1309146/1309146_10250324_1506434101770_Fig.1--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Fig. 1"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1309146/1309146_10250324_1506434101770_Fig.1--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Fig. 1"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">A device to measure magnetic torque built from (BEDT-TTF)-iodine/polycarbonate film (brown strip). The resulting resistance difference between the left (reference arm) and right side (sensing arm) is detected by a Wheatstone resistance bridge circuit.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Dr. Eden Steven</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyright owner is an institution with an existing agreement allowing use by NSF</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Eun Sang&nbsp;Choi</div> <div class="imageTitle">Fig. 1</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1309146/1309146_10250324_1506434183713_Fig.2--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1309146/1309146_10250324_1506434183713_Fig.2--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Fig. 2"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1309146/1309146_10250324_1506434183713_Fig.2--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Fig. 2"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">The optical microscope (a) and the scanning electron microscope (b) (c) image of (TMTSF)-iodine/EVA (ethylene-vinyl-acrylate) rubber. The SEM image shows bundles of (TMTSF) nano-rods.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Dr. Eden Steven</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyright owner is an institution with an existing agreement allowing use by NSF</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Eun Sang&nbsp;Choi</div> <div class="imageTitle">Fig. 2</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The objective of this project is to investigate physical properties of low dimensional materials which are highly relevant to materials research. Materials of particular interest are organic charge transfer salts with quasi 1D or quasi 2D electronic properties. Organic charge transfer salts, also known as molecular conductors or organic conductors have provided fertile grounds for fundamental scientific researches for last four decades since a discovery of TTF-TCNQ [Tetrathiafulvalene-Tetracyanoquinodimethane]. In organic conductors, the atoms in an inorganic solid are replaced by molecules, whose nature and interaction of spin, charge, and lattice degree of freedom lead to diverse physical properties including superconductivity, magnetism, metal-insulator transition, and so forth. In this project, a greater emphasis was placed on the functionality and the technology transfer in the organic conductor based materials.  Historically, there have been efforts to utilize the versatile properties of organic conductors for various applications. However, there were obstacles originated from the fragility of the single crystals and low yield from the conventional electrochemical synthesis. But in very recent years, a breakthrough in the synthesis of organic conductors, that is, synthesizing them on the surface of elastic polymeric substrates opened a new horizon to the field. In this project, we used the new synthesis method to make different kinds of organic conductor/polymer bilayer films and measured their physical properties that might lead to the technology application.  In the report, three kinds of bilayer films are presented as representing examples. BEDT-TTF  [Bis(ethylenedithio)tetrathiafulvalene] is a well-known organic molecule that has been a building block of many quasi 2D organic superconductors. When the BEDT-TTF is formed on polycarbonate substrate by the wet chemistry process, the resulting bilayer film is consist of elastic film and nano-sized BEDT-TTF molecules grown on it. The mechanical and optical properties (flexible and transparent) and the electrical properties of the resulting hybrid material are determined by the polymer substrate and the BEDT-TTF molecules, respectively. When the bilayer film is doped with iodine, the film becomes metallic and piezo-resistive, meaning its electrical conductivity is very sensitive to the strain exerted on the film. We found the gauge factor (sensitivity parameters as a strain sensor) is about 20, much larger than commercial metal strain gauges by about six times but smaller than the most sensitive Si based gauges by factor of 5. We demonstrated the usefulness of the material by measuring quantum oscillations of (BEDT-TTF)2Cu(NCS) organic superconductors with a device made of the bilayer film (Fig. 1). The most sophisticated tool required for the device fabrication was a pair of scissors.  Secondly, we synthesized a bilayer film based on another class of organic conductors, TMTSF-iodine compound [TMTSF= Tetramethyltetraselenafulvalene] and rubber polymers. Of note is that the TMTSF is a building block of many Q1D organic superconductors. Consequently, the morphology of the TMTSF-Iodine on the rubber substrate is quite different from the (BEDT-TTF)-Iodine bilayer film; the former is nano-rod like and the latter nano-plates. Even more interestingly, the TMTSF nano-rods self-assemble to micrometer sized structures, which follows fractal formation as shown in Fig. 2. The underlying mechanism of such fractal formation is still under investigation. It was also found that the piezo-resistivity of this film is comparable to the (BEDT-TTF)-iodine/polycarbonate bilayer film.  Last example is (BEDO-TTF)2.4I3-polycarbonate bilayer film [BEDO-TTF=bis(ethylenedioxy)tetrathiafulvalene]. In this bilayer film, a new kind of functionality, electrochromism, where the color of a material can be controlled by the electricity, was discovered. The controlling voltage is found to be of 2-3 V, lower than that of the previous known materials showing electrochromism. Since the substrate of the organic bilayer film is flexible, this interesting property can be utilized to make flexible displays.    In summary, we have studied physical properties of organic conductor bilayer films synthesized flexible polymer substrates. They show great potentials for technology applications as sensing devices and flexible displays. The methodology and knowledge we acquired through this project are also useful for future research projects and would promote more investigations of exploring organic conductors as new kind of technology material.       Last Modified: 09/28/2017       Submitted by: Eun Sang Choi]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
