<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>A new paradigm in optical design: infinitely linear refraction artificial materials</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2013</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>360000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>360000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07010000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>ECCS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Electrical, Commun &amp; Cyber Sys</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Dominique Dagenais</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>ddagenai@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922980</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The objective of this proposal is to investigate and implement a new paradigm for optical design based on artificial materials determined by design. The approach is to generate infinitely refraction-linear artificial materials (IRAM) that maintain a linear relationship between incident and refracted angles over a large field of view. As a result, they are attractive to enhance performance, simplify design, and reduce form factor in highly non-paraxial and three-dimensional optics. IRAM are also attractive for creating new functionalities in integrated photonics.&lt;br/&gt;Intellectual merit - Classical optical imaging systems consist of a series of refracting surfaces interfacing among homogeneous isotropic materials. Traditional optical design aims at correcting aberrations via multiple surface and material systems that meet a set of performance requirements. Modern lens design can also take advantage of aspheric, graded index, diffractive or holographic lenses to reduce aberrations and overall complexity and size. However, designs are still based on ray tracing optimizations over hundreds of dimensions that typically result in tradeoffs in terms of performance, size, weight, and form factor. The paradigm proposed here provides new degrees of freedom at the material level that enable simpler designs and dramatically simplifies the design process.&lt;br/&gt;Broader Impacts - IRAM open up the possibility of exploring novel applications in integrated and free space photonics with vast economic potential. For instance, the approach is attractive for application in light/compact infrared imagers that outperform classical multi-element designs. The project integrates education and outreach, for instance by providing training opportunities for a diverse cadre of young students.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/14/2013</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/14/2013</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1310487</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Rafael</FirstName>
<LastName>Piestun</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Rafael Piestun</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>piestun@colorado.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>3037350894</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000489198</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/14/2013</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Colorado at Boulder</Name>
<CityName>Boulder</CityName>
<ZipCode>803031058</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>3034926221</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>3100 Marine Street, Room 481</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[572 UCB]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Colorado</StateName>
<StateCode>CO</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CO02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>007431505</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>REGENTS OF THE UNIVERSITY OF COLORADO, THE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>007431505</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Colorado at Boulder]]></Name>
<CityName>Boulder</CityName>
<StateCode>CO</StateCode>
<ZipCode>803090572</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[3100 Marine Street Room 479]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Colorado</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CO02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1517</Code>
<Text>EPMD-ElectrnPhoton&amp;MagnDevices</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>094E</Code>
<Text>Optoelectronic devices</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0113</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2013~360000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The objective of this project was to investigate and implement a new paradigm for optical design based on artificial materials determined by design. As a result, scientists and engineers have now access to techniques that help improve the performance of lenses and other optical elements</p> <p>The methods proposed are attractive to enhance performance, simplify design, and reduce form factor of optical systems while also creating new functional opportunities in micro- and nano-photonics.</p> <p>Traditional optical design aims at improving optical imaging systems via multiple lenses, multiple surfaces and/or multiple material systems that meet a set of performance requirements and constraints. Modern lens design can also take advantage of aspheric, graded index, diffractive or holographic lenses to produce better systems. However, even with all these techniques at hand, optical designs still required tradeoffs in terms of performance, size, weight, and form factor.</p> <p>The techniques put forward in this project have a two-fold effect, first providing additional flexibility at the material level, and second, simplifying the design process. These new concepts could be critical in integrated photonics where size is critical and the required nano-fabrication techniques are already in use. The possibility of designing materials that can change optical design opens up opportunities for new applications in biomedical micro-optical imaging, security, and consumer products.&nbsp;</p> <p>The project provided multiple opportunities for training of graduate students and postdoctoral researchers. It also contributed to the dissemination of the scientific and technical results of the research through journal publications and conference presentations.&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 10/26/2017<br>      Modified by: Rafael&nbsp;Piestun</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The objective of this project was to investigate and implement a new paradigm for optical design based on artificial materials determined by design. As a result, scientists and engineers have now access to techniques that help improve the performance of lenses and other optical elements  The methods proposed are attractive to enhance performance, simplify design, and reduce form factor of optical systems while also creating new functional opportunities in micro- and nano-photonics.  Traditional optical design aims at improving optical imaging systems via multiple lenses, multiple surfaces and/or multiple material systems that meet a set of performance requirements and constraints. Modern lens design can also take advantage of aspheric, graded index, diffractive or holographic lenses to produce better systems. However, even with all these techniques at hand, optical designs still required tradeoffs in terms of performance, size, weight, and form factor.  The techniques put forward in this project have a two-fold effect, first providing additional flexibility at the material level, and second, simplifying the design process. These new concepts could be critical in integrated photonics where size is critical and the required nano-fabrication techniques are already in use. The possibility of designing materials that can change optical design opens up opportunities for new applications in biomedical micro-optical imaging, security, and consumer products.   The project provided multiple opportunities for training of graduate students and postdoctoral researchers. It also contributed to the dissemination of the scientific and technical results of the research through journal publications and conference presentations.           Last Modified: 10/26/2017       Submitted by: Rafael Piestun]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
