<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>NSF East Asia and Pacific Summer Institute (EAPSI) for FY 2013 in Australia</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>06/01/2013</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2014</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>5070.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>5070</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Fellowship Award</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>01090000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>O/D</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Office Of The Director</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>OISE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Office Of Internatl Science &amp;Engineering</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Anne Emig</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>aemig@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927241</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This action funds Lindsey Furman Dougherty of the University of California Berkeley to conduct a research project in Biological Sciences during the summer of 2013 at the Queensland Brain Institute and University of Queensland (UQ) in Brisbane, Australia.  The project title is "Mechanisms, Ultrastructure and Behavioral Function of Flashing in Ctenoides Ales: Disco Clams.'" The host scientist is Dr. Justin Marshall. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The ocean's euphotic zone is an environment in which light is extremely variable, yet a wide array of organisms use visual displays that require ambient light for reflection. The bivalve mollusk Ctenoides ales lives at depths up to 20m and often inside crevices, where ambient light is dim and wavelength-restricted. Despite its light-limited habitat, this species evolved a reflective mantle edge that emits vivid light, leading to its common name, disco clam. C. ales is the only known bivalve with a behaviorally controlled photic display, yet virtually nothing is known about its mechanism, function or life history. Preliminary research in transmission electron microscopy, high speed video, spectrometry, hyperspectral imaging and particle modeling have advanced intracellular and mechanistic understanding of how the photic display is produced, but its behavioral purpose remains unknown. During this field season, hypotheses about the function of the flashing are being tested, including that it acts to attract phototaxic prey, larval juveniles for settlement, or is an aposematic warning toward predators. The study of photic displays by organisms advances knowledge about visual systems, communication, physical optics, photonics, structural composition and biomimetic technology.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Broader impacts of an EAPSI fellowship include providing the Fellow a first-hand research experience outside the U.S.; an introduction to the science, science policy, and scientific infrastructure of the respective location; and an orientation to the society, culture and language. These activities meet the NSF goal to educate for international collaborations early in the career of its scientists, engineers, and educators, thus ensuring a globally aware U.S. scientific workforce. Furthermore, undergraduate students at Berkeley and at UQ are helping with research and field studies, allowing insight into graduate-level work and collaboration. Research results are being disseminated through the Understanding Science website of the University of California Museum of Paleontology. Project updates, photographs and videos are being uploaded through a blog. As these bivalves are well known in aquariums and popular with the public, there is substantial interest in this project. This project is also being communicated through involvement with WIS (Women in Science) by examining the role of women in Australian scientific communities. Finally, the results are being communicated through community involvement in the Dinner With A Scientist program at the Oakland Zoo; Science Nights at multiple local elementary schools; and through volunteer efforts with the Expanding Your Horizons (EYH) Conference which targets girls in middle school, the Surfrider Foundation and SurfAid. This research and outreach are forging partnerships between the international community, UQ, and Berkeley.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>05/15/2013</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/15/2013</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.079</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1310703</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Lindsey</FirstName>
<LastName>Dougherty</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>F</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Lindsey F Dougherty</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress/>
<PI_PHON>5109320906</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000605740</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/15/2013</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Dougherty               Lindsey</Name>
<CityName>Boulder</CityName>
<ZipCode>803090265</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber/>
<StreetAddress/>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Colorado</StateName>
<StateCode>CO</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CO02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM/>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME/>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Dougherty               Lindsey]]></Name>
<CityName>Boulder</CityName>
<StateCode>CO</StateCode>
<ZipCode>803090265</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Colorado</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CO02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7316</Code>
<Text>EAPSI</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>5912</Code>
<Text>AUSTRALIA</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>5978</Code>
<Text>EAST ASIA AND PACIFIC PROGRAM</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7316</Code>
<Text>EAPSI</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0113</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2013~5070</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>My Australian EAPSI experience provided valuable technical analysis and in situ behavioral studies to my dissertation project, which focuses on the photic flashing display of the &ldquo;disco&rdquo; or &ldquo;electric&rdquo; clam, <em>Ctenoides ales</em>. The majority of the EAPSI project was conducted in the lab of my host, Dr. Justin Marshall, through the University of Queensland and the Queensland Brain Institute (QBI). Several weeks were also spent at the Lizard Island Research Station in the northern Great Barrier Reef, through the Australian Museum. In addition to time spent underwater in the field, several technical collaborations were facilitated through the program, including work on the light characteristics of the display through spectrometry, and the composition of the tissue through elemental analysis with the University of Queensland Centre for Microscopy and Microanalysis (CMM).</p> <p>My study focused on structural coloration, which is of particular interest in biomimetics, where photonic nanostructure influences countless technologies derived from natural design. The use of structural coloration by various taxa in the ocean&rsquo;s euphotic zone is especially interesting as long wavelengths are absorbed rapidly with depth, light attenuates with suspended solids, and available light varies between habitats. The bivalve mollusk <em>Ctenoides ales</em> lives at depths up to 50m and often inside small crevices, where ambient light is dim and wavelength-restricted. Despite this, the species evolved a reflective mantle edge that emits vivid light, resulting in its common name of &ldquo;disco&rdquo; or &ldquo;electric&rdquo; clam.</p> <p><em>C. ales</em> is the only bivalve known to have a behaviorally controlled light display, and the EAPSI program provided the first opportunity to conduct extended underwater observation and behavioral analysis, as well as analyze the characteristics of the light display itself using spectrometry, transmission electron microscopy, energy dispersive X-ray spectroscopy and particle modeling. Although behavioral data is still being analyzed, interpreted and elaborated upon, the results from the spectrometry and energy dispersive X-ray spectroscopy suggest that the results of this clam's photic display will contribute to the field of photonics, with reflection in <em>C. ales </em>resulting from a unique ultrastructure combined with specialized tissue movement.</p> <p>The EAPSI program broadened my perspectives on the value of international research and collaboration, including my work with fellow graduate students at the University of Queensland. Upon returning to the University of California, Berkeley in the spring semester of 2014 after spending the fall semester of 2013 teaching a field course in Moorea, I will mentor undergraduates from the Undergraduate Research Assistantship Program (URAP) to help analyze behavioral data from the EAPSI program, as well as expand upon the experiments that were set up in the field.</p> <p>I presented my results at the 2013 World Congress of Malacology conference in the Azores, and will also present my results at the 2014 Society of Integrative and Comparative Biology conference in Austin, Texas. The research we conducted was compiled in a manuscript which is currently in review for publication. The EAPSI program was an invaluable experience in collaboration across cultures and disciplines, with new insights for my research through the CMM and the QBI, as well as immense personal growth as an underwater field researcher. I look forward to continued collaboration with the people and institutions I was fortunate enough to encounter, and hope to continue to support and facilitate similar experiences for myself and other students in the future.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 12/01/2013<br>      Modified by: Lindsey&nbsp;F&nbsp;Dougherty</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol">...]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ My Australian EAPSI experience provided valuable technical analysis and in situ behavioral studies to my dissertation project, which focuses on the photic flashing display of the "disco" or "electric" clam, Ctenoides ales. The majority of the EAPSI project was conducted in the lab of my host, Dr. Justin Marshall, through the University of Queensland and the Queensland Brain Institute (QBI). Several weeks were also spent at the Lizard Island Research Station in the northern Great Barrier Reef, through the Australian Museum. In addition to time spent underwater in the field, several technical collaborations were facilitated through the program, including work on the light characteristics of the display through spectrometry, and the composition of the tissue through elemental analysis with the University of Queensland Centre for Microscopy and Microanalysis (CMM).  My study focused on structural coloration, which is of particular interest in biomimetics, where photonic nanostructure influences countless technologies derived from natural design. The use of structural coloration by various taxa in the oceanÆs euphotic zone is especially interesting as long wavelengths are absorbed rapidly with depth, light attenuates with suspended solids, and available light varies between habitats. The bivalve mollusk Ctenoides ales lives at depths up to 50m and often inside small crevices, where ambient light is dim and wavelength-restricted. Despite this, the species evolved a reflective mantle edge that emits vivid light, resulting in its common name of "disco" or "electric" clam.  C. ales is the only bivalve known to have a behaviorally controlled light display, and the EAPSI program provided the first opportunity to conduct extended underwater observation and behavioral analysis, as well as analyze the characteristics of the light display itself using spectrometry, transmission electron microscopy, energy dispersive X-ray spectroscopy and particle modeling. Although behavioral data is still being analyzed, interpreted and elaborated upon, the results from the spectrometry and energy dispersive X-ray spectroscopy suggest that the results of this clam's photic display will contribute to the field of photonics, with reflection in C. ales resulting from a unique ultrastructure combined with specialized tissue movement.  The EAPSI program broadened my perspectives on the value of international research and collaboration, including my work with fellow graduate students at the University of Queensland. Upon returning to the University of California, Berkeley in the spring semester of 2014 after spending the fall semester of 2013 teaching a field course in Moorea, I will mentor undergraduates from the Undergraduate Research Assistantship Program (URAP) to help analyze behavioral data from the EAPSI program, as well as expand upon the experiments that were set up in the field.  I presented my results at the 2013 World Congress of Malacology conference in the Azores, and will also present my results at the 2014 Society of Integrative and Comparative Biology conference in Austin, Texas. The research we conducted was compiled in a manuscript which is currently in review for publication. The EAPSI program was an invaluable experience in collaboration across cultures and disciplines, with new insights for my research through the CMM and the QBI, as well as immense personal growth as an underwater field researcher. I look forward to continued collaboration with the people and institutions I was fortunate enough to encounter, and hope to continue to support and facilitate similar experiences for myself and other students in the future.          Last Modified: 12/01/2013       Submitted by: Lindsey F Dougherty]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
