<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>NSF East Asia and Pacific Summer Institute (EAPSI) for FY 2013 in China</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>06/01/2013</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2014</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>5000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>5000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Fellowship Award</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>01090000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>O/D</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Office Of The Director</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>OISE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Office Of Internatl Science &amp;Engineering</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Anne Emig</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>aemig@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927241</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This action funds Josef B. Stiegler of The George Washington University to conduct a research project in Biology during the summer of 2013 at the Institute of Vertebrate Paleontology and Paleoanthropology in Beijing, China.  The project title is "The Anatomy and Evolutionary Relationships of a Peculiar Dinosaur from Wucaiwan (Xinjiang, People's Republic of China)."  The host scientist is Xu Xing.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The theropod dinosaur Limusaurus inextricabilis is a basal ceratosaur of uncertain relationships from the Jurassic Shishugou formation of Xinjiang. Its highly reduced, four-fingered hand has undergone bilateral digital reduction, a condition previously unknown in Mesozoic theropods but known to be present in the three-fingered hands of birds via embryological evidence. This project documents the skeletal anatomy of Limusaurus, in order to resolve its relationships within Ceratosauria. Should it occupy a basal position within the clade, it may provide evidence for a frameshift in digit identity in the most recent common ancestor of Limusaurus and more derived theropods (including birds), or that ancestor's stem lineage.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Broader impacts of an EAPSI fellowship include providing the Fellow a first-hand research experience outside the U.S.; an introduction to the science, science policy, and scientific infrastructure of the respective location; and an orientation to the society, culture and language.   These activities meet the NSF goal to educate for international collaborations early in the career of its scientists, engineers, and educators, thus ensuring a globally aware U.S. scientific workforce.  Furthermore, the evolution of dinosaurs is a topic of great interest to the public and is often introduced to children at a young age. Given the potential for this project to resolve a conflict between paleontological and embryological evidence regarding the evolution of the hand along the lineage leading to modern birds, it may provide further opportunities to engage the public with science and an accessible example of evolutionary-developmental biology (evo-devo) for science education. Data and educational materials related to this project will be publicly available via the Morphobank website upon publication of the results.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>05/16/2013</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/16/2013</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.079</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1311000</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Josef</FirstName>
<LastName>Stiegler</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>B</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Josef B Stiegler</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress/>
<PI_PHON>2025569676</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000633752</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/16/2013</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Stiegler                Josef          B</Name>
<CityName>Washington</CityName>
<ZipCode>200520021</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber/>
<StreetAddress/>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>District of Columbia</StateName>
<StateCode>DC</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>00</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>DC00</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM/>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME/>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Stiegler                Josef          B]]></Name>
<CityName>Washington</CityName>
<StateCode>DC</StateCode>
<ZipCode>200520021</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>District of Columbia</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>00</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>DC00</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7316</Code>
<Text>EAPSI</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>5978</Code>
<Text>EAST ASIA AND PACIFIC PROGRAM</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7316</Code>
<Text>EAPSI</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9200</Code>
<Text>US CHINA COOP IN BASIC SCIENCE</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0113</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2013~5000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>&nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp;The fossil record of theropod dinosaurs has become one of the most well-documented origins of a major group of living vertebrate, birds, and the evolution of many features which were once thought to be uniquely avian have been discovered in Mesozoic theropods. The evolution of the three-fingered hand in birds is one avian feature posessed by theropods, but documentation of the transition from a five to three-fingered hand has eluded paleontologists. The dinosaur <em>Limusaurus inextricabilis</em> is an important species in the debate over the origins of the avian hand, and this project included a detailed description of its anatomy, which will be published at a later date. Additional data collected from other theropod dinosaurs during this project will contribute to a large analysis of theropod evolutionary relationships that seeks to clarify the deep branching relationships of the group. With knowledge of these deep relationships, the principal investigator and other paleontologists can better test hypotheses regarding the origins of the avian hand.</p> <p>&nbsp; &nbsp;The felloswhip funded by this award allowed the primary investigator to study numerous theropod dinosaur specimens housed at Chinese institutions. The data collected will prove invaluable to the morphological description of <em>Limusaurus,&nbsp;</em>a work that will provide an unprecedented level of knowledge of the cranial and postcranial anatomy of small ceratosaurian theropods.</p> <p>&nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp;Studies of ontogenetic and intraspecific variation in theropod dinosaurs are sometimes made difficult by small sample sizes. Numerous articulated skeletons of juvenile through sub-adult <em>Limusaurus </em>are housed at the host institution of this fellowship (Institute of Vertebrate Paleontology and Paleoanthropology, Beijing), and accordingly the publications resulting from this project will provide new information on ontogenetic and intraspecific information in <em>Limusaurus</em>&nbsp;and will inform other studies of basal theropod dinosaurs.&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; Preliminary results from the analysis of theropod interrelationships indicate strong support for new hypotheses of theropod evolutionary relationships, which will impact future studies of theropod character evolution and biogeography. In addition to achieving the major goals of data collection for the project, the award allowed the primary investigator to participate in field work in Inner Mongolia, to form new collaborations with Chinese scientists, and to make new discoveries in the collections of Chinese institutions. A new species of theropod from the Middle Jurassic of Sichuan Province was discovered by the primary investigator in the collections of one of the visited institutions, and will be described by the primary investigator in collaboration with Chinese scientists.</p> <p>&nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp;The broader impacts of this project included providing the primary investigator with a first-hand research experience outside the U.S.; an introduction to the science, science policy, and scientific infrastructure of China; and an orientation to Chinese society, culture and language. These activities meet the NSF goal to educate for international collaborations early in the career of its scientists, engineers, and educators, thus ensuring a globally aware U.S. scientific workforce. Furthermore, the evolution of dinosaurs is a topic of great interest to the public and is often introduced to children at a young age. This project seeks to resolve a conflict between paleontological and embryological evidence regarding the evolution of the hand along the lineage leading to modern birds. By investigating questions related to this topic, the project may provide further opportunities to engage the public with science and an accessible example of evolutionary-developmental biology (evo-devo) for science edu...]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[      The fossil record of theropod dinosaurs has become one of the most well-documented origins of a major group of living vertebrate, birds, and the evolution of many features which were once thought to be uniquely avian have been discovered in Mesozoic theropods. The evolution of the three-fingered hand in birds is one avian feature posessed by theropods, but documentation of the transition from a five to three-fingered hand has eluded paleontologists. The dinosaur Limusaurus inextricabilis is an important species in the debate over the origins of the avian hand, and this project included a detailed description of its anatomy, which will be published at a later date. Additional data collected from other theropod dinosaurs during this project will contribute to a large analysis of theropod evolutionary relationships that seeks to clarify the deep branching relationships of the group. With knowledge of these deep relationships, the principal investigator and other paleontologists can better test hypotheses regarding the origins of the avian hand.     The felloswhip funded by this award allowed the primary investigator to study numerous theropod dinosaur specimens housed at Chinese institutions. The data collected will prove invaluable to the morphological description of Limusaurus, a work that will provide an unprecedented level of knowledge of the cranial and postcranial anatomy of small ceratosaurian theropods.       Studies of ontogenetic and intraspecific variation in theropod dinosaurs are sometimes made difficult by small sample sizes. Numerous articulated skeletons of juvenile through sub-adult Limusaurus are housed at the host institution of this fellowship (Institute of Vertebrate Paleontology and Paleoanthropology, Beijing), and accordingly the publications resulting from this project will provide new information on ontogenetic and intraspecific information in Limusaurus and will inform other studies of basal theropod dinosaurs.        Preliminary results from the analysis of theropod interrelationships indicate strong support for new hypotheses of theropod evolutionary relationships, which will impact future studies of theropod character evolution and biogeography. In addition to achieving the major goals of data collection for the project, the award allowed the primary investigator to participate in field work in Inner Mongolia, to form new collaborations with Chinese scientists, and to make new discoveries in the collections of Chinese institutions. A new species of theropod from the Middle Jurassic of Sichuan Province was discovered by the primary investigator in the collections of one of the visited institutions, and will be described by the primary investigator in collaboration with Chinese scientists.       The broader impacts of this project included providing the primary investigator with a first-hand research experience outside the U.S.; an introduction to the science, science policy, and scientific infrastructure of China; and an orientation to Chinese society, culture and language. These activities meet the NSF goal to educate for international collaborations early in the career of its scientists, engineers, and educators, thus ensuring a globally aware U.S. scientific workforce. Furthermore, the evolution of dinosaurs is a topic of great interest to the public and is often introduced to children at a young age. This project seeks to resolve a conflict between paleontological and embryological evidence regarding the evolution of the hand along the lineage leading to modern birds. By investigating questions related to this topic, the project may provide further opportunities to engage the public with science and an accessible example of evolutionary-developmental biology (evo-devo) for science education. Data and educational materials related to this project will be publicly available via the Morphobank website upon publication of the results.          Last Modified: 12/01/2013       Submitted by: Josef B...]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
