<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>AIR Option 2:  Research Allianace Polymer, Polymer-Ceramic and Natural Polymer Based Systems for Soft Tissue and Bone Repair and Regeneration</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>05/15/2013</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>04/30/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>800000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>864000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07070000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>IIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Industrial Innovation &amp; Partnersh</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Prakash Balan</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>pbalan@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032925341</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This PFI: AIR Research Alliance project focuses on the translation and transfer of bone and soft tissue regeneration technologies to new products for musculoskeletal repair.   Autograft and allograft based products are currently used for repair purposes and have several limitations including suboptimal strength, possible negative immune effects and risks of disease transmission. The new technologies and proposed products overcome the drawbacks posed by autografts and allografts.  These new product technologies are potentially stronger, bioactive, more biocompatible and completely degradable while being ideally suited for load-bearing bone healing and soft tissue repair and regeneration applications. There are estimated to be over 1 million bone graft implants performed each year throughout the world. Production costs for the proposed technologies will be in the range of $500 per implant, yielding a $2000 net profit per implant. Our objective in the first 3 years is to achieve a 2% market share of bone grafts (20,000 grafts) which would provide $40 million in revenue per year. Every year, 400,000 rotator cuff repair procedures performed in the US require the use of a tendon augmentation device. Production costs are $1,000 per implant, yielding a $4000 profit per implant. We conservatively believe that 30% of repair operations would benefit from our soft tissue regeneration system (120,000 repairs) and that a 10% market share would be 12,000 repairs. This translates to a profit of 48 million per year. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;In order to move these technologies to commercialization, we have categorized different products into short-term, mid-term and long-term time frames spanning 1 to 5 years. Short-term products include grafts fabricated from the materials alone without inclusion of any biologics. The short-term products, classified as devices or implants, create a short route to 510k FDA clearance (approval).  An ample financial base from the aforementioned products will allow re-investment of R &amp; D efforts toward the commercialization of subsequent products or to pursue an out-license or acquisition exit after subsequent 510k approvals. The strong patent portfolio and constant revenue from the initial product commercialization will create a self-sustainable academic centered innovation ecosystem. All these activities will ensure workforce development, create new jobs and businesses, and foster economic development. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Third party partnerships engaged to transfer the technologies to the market domain include technology niche analysis, business plan development, and initiation of new startup ventures for existing products and new products. The potential economic impact is expected to approximate 100 million per year in the next 2 to 3 years which will contribute to the U.S. competitiveness in the orthopaedic device fixation, repair, and regeneration market.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Societal impact short term, the proposed devices successfully address issues and drawbacks related to biological grafts currently used and will improve treatment efficiency/cost, enhance patient compliance and contribute to a better quality of life. The developed products will be used as alternatives to current grafts.  Identified material compositions and designs may find application in the delivery of growth factors, antibiotics and pain medications for treating a variety of musculoskeletal ailments in the long term. This proposed project has immense economic potential as well as a broad impact in education by bridging the interfaces of chemistry, biology, medicine and materials science.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Educationally, the proposed research will focus on the recruitment and training of underrepresented minorities at the undergraduate and graduate levels, thus ensuring a competitive and diverse dissemination of scientific knowledge. Students and fellows will be engaged in business plan development and encouraged to complete an internship with the third party investors to enhance their entrepreneurial skill sets.&lt;br/&gt;</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>05/06/2013</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/04/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1311907</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Cato</FirstName>
<LastName>Laurencin</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>T</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Cato T Laurencin</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>laurencin@uchc.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>8606792594</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000222410</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/06/2013</StartDate>
<EndDate>06/24/2014</EndDate>
<RoleCode>Former Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Cato</FirstName>
<LastName>Laurencin</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>T</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Cato T Laurencin</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>laurencin@uchc.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>8606792594</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000222410</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/04/2016</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Sangamesh</FirstName>
<LastName>Kumbar</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Sangamesh Kumbar</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>kumbar@uchc.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>8606793955</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000526995</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/06/2013</StartDate>
<EndDate>06/24/2014</EndDate>
<RoleCode>Former Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Sangamesh</FirstName>
<LastName>Kumbar</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Sangamesh Kumbar</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>kumbar@uchc.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>8606793955</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000526995</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/04/2016</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Connecticut Health Center</Name>
<CityName>Farmington</CityName>
<ZipCode>060305335</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>8606794040</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>263 Farmington Ave.</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Connecticut</StateName>
<StateCode>CT</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CT05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>022254226</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF CONNECTICUT</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>004534830</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Connecticut Health Center]]></Name>
<CityName>Farmington</CityName>
<StateCode>CT</StateCode>
<ZipCode>060300001</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[263 Farmington Avenue]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Connecticut</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CT05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>8019</Code>
<Text>Accelerating Innovation Rsrch</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>115E</Code>
<Text>RESEARCH EXP FOR TEACHERS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>116E</Code>
<Text>RESEARCH EXP FOR UNDERGRADS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7218</Code>
<Text>RET SUPP-Res Exp for Tchr Supp</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7233</Code>
<Text>RES EXPERIENCE FOR TEACHERS(RET)-SUPPLEM</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8019</Code>
<Text>Accelerating Innovation Rsrch</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9231</Code>
<Text>SUPPL FOR UNDERGRAD RES ASSIST</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9251</Code>
<Text>REU SUPP-Res Exp for Ugrd Supp</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0113</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0115</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2013~832000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2015~32000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><strong>Project Summary: &nbsp;Polymer, Polymer-Ceramic and Natural Polymer Based Systems for Soft Tissue and Bone Repair and Regeneration</strong></p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>The repair and replacement of damaged hard tissues such as bone is a major clinical problem in the U.S. and around the world. In the U.S. alone, more than 500,000 hip and knee replacements are performed and over 6 million fractures are treated each year.<sup> </sup>With an aging population, the numbers of bone related injuries worldwide are projected to significantly increase requiring surgical intervention to treat damaged tissue. The current market for bone grafting and implants represents over a 4.8-billion-dollar industry, which is expected to grow exponentially in the future.<sup> </sup>Thus, there is a great need for developing biological graft substitutes with adequate mechanical and pore properties to achieve effective bone repair and regeneration. <em><span style="text-decoration: underline;">This grant developed biodegradable mechanically strong micro-nanostructured bone graft prototypes for bone healing applications with high commercialization potential.</span></em><strong> </strong>As pertinent as bone injuries, are soft tissue injuries, which include damage to skin, muscles, ligaments and tendons throughout the body. Tendon tears inflict all stages of life, encompassing acute, degenerative and traumatic injuries. In the civilian population 50% of musculoskeletal injuries involve tendon and ligament soft tissue. For instance, tendon tears represent a major portion of the personal medical costs and loss of GDP attributed to musculoskeletal pathology, totaling $127.4 billion and $849 billion or 7.7% loss of gross domestic product.<em><span style="text-decoration: underline;"> This grant developed micro-nanostructured biodegradable fiber matrices for soft tissue repair and regeneration with a potential commercial product.</span></em></p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p><strong>Intellectual Merit: </strong>This project proposed to develop two biodegradable scaffold technologies for bone and soft tissue regeneration applications. The investigators developed prototype synthetic bone graft substitutes for load bearing bone healing applications, as well as micro-noncontoured polymeric fiber matrices with the ability to deliver bioactive factors to promote tendon healing. The novel material compositions and micro-nanostructures identified and developed have great commercialization potential in the field of orthopedic fixation devices. Particularly the polysaccharide material platform we have developed is potentially stronger, more biocompatible and can be customized to meet the needs of biological sciences and biomedical engineering. We identified several product segments for which there exists a need for a degradable and biocompatible material platform and combined them with mechanical competence &ndash; a must for successful musculoskeletal applications. From the findings of this research we have published a total of 21 research articles, 18 invited book chapters and 22 conference presentations. Additionally, 3 patent disclosures have been made on applications based on the novel materials and technologies developed. <strong>Broader Impact:</strong> This work has provided greater understanding on the role of micro-nanostructures in musculoskeletal regeneration and addressed fundamental issues, particularly the effects of <em>in vitro</em> microenvironment and tissue formation <em>in vivo</em>. The developed products have the potential to be used as alternatives to current grafts, and identified material compositions and designs may find application in the delivery of growth factors, antibiotics and pain medications. This project has helped us to identify opportunities and realize commercialization potential of multiple orthopedic fixation devices. This interdisciplinary project has also demonstrated a broad impact in education by bridging the interfaces of chemistry, biology, and materials science. <strong><span style="text-decoration: underline;">Educationally</span></strong><strong>,</strong> this research project promoted training of underrepresented minorities at the undergraduate and graduate levels, thus ensuring a competitive and diverse dissemination of scientific knowledge. These funds were also helpful in training 5 high schools, 21 undergraduate independent study research, 13 senior design project students, 5 graduate and 2 postdoctoral fellows on various aspects of the technology development and commercialization aspects. Many undergraduate students are co-authors on publications that have resulted from this work. Project tasks were accomplished by graduate students and postdoctoral fellows under the supervision of the project PIs. The students and fellows met with third party investors and gained insights on product development, innovation, regulatory guidelines and commercialization aspects. In addition, the PI has shared the research findings in the classroom and developed a new course on drug delivery aimed at the undergraduate and graduate level. This grant has also provided opportunity for undergraduate summer research. The PI and his team have actively participated in school outreach programs, mentoring juniors and seniors from underrepresented minority groups. In this way, the educational efforts from this grant have aimed to promote, cultivate, and sustain an educational STEM pipeline.&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 05/03/2017<br>      Modified by: Sangamesh&nbsp;Kumbar</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Images (<span id="selectedPhoto0">1</span> of <span class="totalNumber"></span>)           </div> <div class="galControls" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1311907/1311907_10243912_1493823382295_Picture1--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1311907/1311907_10243912_1493823382295_Picture1--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Micro-nano structured bone graft"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1311907/1311907_10243912_1493823382295_Picture1--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Micro-nano structured bone graft"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Polysaccharide matrices for bone tissue regeneration with focus on material-protein and material-cell interactions</div> <div class="imageCredit">10.1039/C6RA15363A (Paper) RSC Adv., 2016, 6, 80851-80866</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Public Domain</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Sangamesh&nbsp;Kumbar</div> <div class="imageTitle">Micro-nano structured bone graft</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1311907/1311907_10243912_1493823500460_Picture2--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1311907/1311907_10243912_1493823500460_Picture2--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Micro-nano structured matrix for soft tissue regeneration"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1311907/1311907_10243912_1493823500460_Picture2--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Micro-nano structured matrix for soft tissue regeneration"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Fibrous matrices as cell and factor delivery devices for tendon tissue engineering</div> <div class="imageCredit">Kumbar laboratory</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Public Domain</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Sangamesh&nbsp;Kumbar</div> <div class="imageTitle">Micro-nano structured matrix for soft tissue regeneration</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1311907/1311907_10243912_1493823729957_Picture3--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1311907/1311907_10243912_1493823729957_Picture3--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Polysaccharide material platform"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1311907/1311907_10243912_1493823729957_Picture3--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Polysaccharide material platform"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Polysaccharide materials for drug delivery and tissue engineering applications</div> <div class="imageCredit">Kumbar laboratory</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Sangamesh&nbsp;Kumbar</div> <div class="imageTitle">Polysaccharide material platform</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Project Summary:  Polymer, Polymer-Ceramic and Natural Polymer Based Systems for Soft Tissue and Bone Repair and Regeneration     The repair and replacement of damaged hard tissues such as bone is a major clinical problem in the U.S. and around the world. In the U.S. alone, more than 500,000 hip and knee replacements are performed and over 6 million fractures are treated each year. With an aging population, the numbers of bone related injuries worldwide are projected to significantly increase requiring surgical intervention to treat damaged tissue. The current market for bone grafting and implants represents over a 4.8-billion-dollar industry, which is expected to grow exponentially in the future. Thus, there is a great need for developing biological graft substitutes with adequate mechanical and pore properties to achieve effective bone repair and regeneration. This grant developed biodegradable mechanically strong micro-nanostructured bone graft prototypes for bone healing applications with high commercialization potential. As pertinent as bone injuries, are soft tissue injuries, which include damage to skin, muscles, ligaments and tendons throughout the body. Tendon tears inflict all stages of life, encompassing acute, degenerative and traumatic injuries. In the civilian population 50% of musculoskeletal injuries involve tendon and ligament soft tissue. For instance, tendon tears represent a major portion of the personal medical costs and loss of GDP attributed to musculoskeletal pathology, totaling $127.4 billion and $849 billion or 7.7% loss of gross domestic product. This grant developed micro-nanostructured biodegradable fiber matrices for soft tissue repair and regeneration with a potential commercial product.     Intellectual Merit: This project proposed to develop two biodegradable scaffold technologies for bone and soft tissue regeneration applications. The investigators developed prototype synthetic bone graft substitutes for load bearing bone healing applications, as well as micro-noncontoured polymeric fiber matrices with the ability to deliver bioactive factors to promote tendon healing. The novel material compositions and micro-nanostructures identified and developed have great commercialization potential in the field of orthopedic fixation devices. Particularly the polysaccharide material platform we have developed is potentially stronger, more biocompatible and can be customized to meet the needs of biological sciences and biomedical engineering. We identified several product segments for which there exists a need for a degradable and biocompatible material platform and combined them with mechanical competence &ndash; a must for successful musculoskeletal applications. From the findings of this research we have published a total of 21 research articles, 18 invited book chapters and 22 conference presentations. Additionally, 3 patent disclosures have been made on applications based on the novel materials and technologies developed. Broader Impact: This work has provided greater understanding on the role of micro-nanostructures in musculoskeletal regeneration and addressed fundamental issues, particularly the effects of in vitro microenvironment and tissue formation in vivo. The developed products have the potential to be used as alternatives to current grafts, and identified material compositions and designs may find application in the delivery of growth factors, antibiotics and pain medications. This project has helped us to identify opportunities and realize commercialization potential of multiple orthopedic fixation devices. This interdisciplinary project has also demonstrated a broad impact in education by bridging the interfaces of chemistry, biology, and materials science. Educationally, this research project promoted training of underrepresented minorities at the undergraduate and graduate levels, thus ensuring a competitive and diverse dissemination of scientific knowledge. These funds were also helpful in training 5 high schools, 21 undergraduate independent study research, 13 senior design project students, 5 graduate and 2 postdoctoral fellows on various aspects of the technology development and commercialization aspects. Many undergraduate students are co-authors on publications that have resulted from this work. Project tasks were accomplished by graduate students and postdoctoral fellows under the supervision of the project PIs. The students and fellows met with third party investors and gained insights on product development, innovation, regulatory guidelines and commercialization aspects. In addition, the PI has shared the research findings in the classroom and developed a new course on drug delivery aimed at the undergraduate and graduate level. This grant has also provided opportunity for undergraduate summer research. The PI and his team have actively participated in school outreach programs, mentoring juniors and seniors from underrepresented minority groups. In this way, the educational efforts from this grant have aimed to promote, cultivate, and sustain an educational STEM pipeline.           Last Modified: 05/03/2017       Submitted by: Sangamesh Kumbar]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
