<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Type Ia Supernovae in the Near Infrared - Clearing a Path through the Dust</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2013</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>500608.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>500608</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03020000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>AST</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Astronomical Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Hans Krimm</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>hkrimm@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922761</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Type Ia supernovae (SNeIa) have enjoyed a remarkable decade as the premiere tool for measuring cosmological distances in the Universe. But precision measurements of dark energy with SNeIa in rest-frame optical light are currently limited by systematic uncertainties stemming from an incomplete understanding of SNIa colors, dust, and host environments, as well as the calibration of astronomical measurements. Recent work has demonstrated that SNeIa are superior distance indicators in the near-infrared (NIR), with more standard peak H-band magnitudes, and a relative insensitivity to dust. This presents us with the timely opportunity to exploit NIR SNIa observations and new methods in SNIa cosmology to free SNeIa from their systematic shackles and fully exploit their potential in current and future dark energy missions. &lt;br/&gt;NIR observations to date have been largely limited to z &lt; 0.03 where distance measurements have suffered from significant peculiar velocity uncertainties. &lt;br/&gt;This project will support an approved 72-night three-year NOAO Survey on the WIYN 3.5-m telescope to observe 144 SNeIa in the NIR from 0.03 &lt; z &lt; 0.08.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This NOAO Survey program focuses on SNeIa in the Hubble flow to obtain reliable NIR luminosities free from peculiar-velocity confusion and the uncertainties of dust. This effort includes a particular focus on accurate calibration incorporating recently demonstrated techniques for characterization of telescope systems and the Earth?s atmosphere. The results of this work will (1) extend the NIR Hubble diagram past currently available samples, (2) quantitatively demonstrate the degree to which SNeIa are robust standard candles in the NIR, (3) provide key insights about the color evolution and intrinsic properties of SNeIa and their host galaxies, and (4) establish a well-calibrated low-redshift anchor for future NIR supernova surveys from JWST, Euclid, and WFIRST/NEW.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The research of this proposal will involve a strong undergraduate component to involve the next generation in active large astronomical research projects. This project will provide training and mentoring to a graduate student and postdoctoral researcher, who will in turn work with the undergraduates to enable them to make significant contributions to the success of the research and outreach missions of this proposal.&lt;br/&gt;The underlying theme of this proposal is using the variable sky to explore the cosmos. This theme will be shared with the public of all ages and backgrounds through public displays of the results. To communicate the new time-domain nature of astronomy this project will create portable sky projections and movies based on Pan-STARRS, SDSS, and WIYN supernova images in near real-time. These will involve both continuous unattended displays visible in public places as well as more targeted displays at specific public events with students and astronomers on-hand to directly engage with the public. An integration of cutting-edge astronomical surveys into the daily experience of citizens, particularly younger members, will spark a lifetime of interest across a diverse spectrum of the population. These efforts will be undertaken in partnership with the Pittsburgh Carnegie Science Museum to bring the dynamic sky to the public's eye.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>09/05/2013</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/23/2015</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1311862</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>William</FirstName>
<LastName>Wood-Vasey</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>M</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>William M Wood-Vasey</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>wmwv@pitt.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>4126242751</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000517073</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/05/2013</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Pittsburgh</Name>
<CityName>Pittsburgh</CityName>
<ZipCode>152133203</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>4126247400</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>300 Murdoch Building</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[3420 Forbes Avenue]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Pennsylvania</StateName>
<StateCode>PA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>18</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>PA18</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>004514360</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF PITTSBURGH, THE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>004514360</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Pittsburgh]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>PA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>152132303</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Pennsylvania</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>18</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>PA18</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1215</Code>
<Text>STELLAR ASTRONOMY &amp; ASTROPHYSC</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1207</Code>
<Text>OBSERVATIONAL ASTRONOMY</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0113</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0114</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0115</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2013~178691</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~164847</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2015~157070</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>This award supported the "SweetSpot" survey of nearby supernovae.&nbsp; Sweet observed 115 supernovae in infrared wavelengths using the WIYN 3.5-m telescope at Kitt Peak National Observatory.&nbsp; Additional spatially-resolved spectra were made of 36 host galaxies of supernovae to investigate the dependence of the supernova properties on their local environments in the galaxies in which they exploded.&nbsp; These infrared observations contribute a new perspective over the traditional visual light observations of supernovae that have been used to measure the accelerating expansion of the Universe.&nbsp; Preliminary results indicate that observing supernovaa in infrared wavelengths leads to more accurate distance measurements than when using only observations in visible light.<br /><br />These data are already being used to investigate how to more accurately measure distances to supernova to improve our measurements of dark energy driving this expansion.&nbsp; This work supported two graduate students who each successfully completed their PhDs during the period of this award.&nbsp; Two papers by these graduate students were submitted to astronomical journals describing the work and two more are in preparation.&nbsp; The first SweetSpot data release paper features 74 of the 115 supernovae.&nbsp; Thumbnail images of each of these supernova and the gaalxies that hosted them are included in the attached image.<br /><br />This work further supported a postdoc studying spatially-resolved spectra of galaxies that have hosted supernovae.&nbsp; His work contributed to 6 papers, including a Nature paper on the discovery of a kilonova associated with a gravitational wave event.<br /><br />The work was shared with the public through several public talks given at the historic Allegheny Observatory.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 01/24/2018<br>      Modified by: William&nbsp;M&nbsp;Wood-Vasey</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Image         </div> <div class="galControls onePhoto" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation onePhoto" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1311862/1311862_10275628_1516811568893_postage_stamps_lowres--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1311862/1311862_10275628_1516811568893_postage_stamps_lowres--rgov-800width.jpg" title="SweetSpot_Supernova_DR1"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1311862/1311862_10275628_1516811568893_postage_stamps_lowres--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="SweetSpot_Supernova_DR1"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">74 supernovae from the first data release of the SweetSpot Survey.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Michael Wood-Vasey</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">William&nbsp;M&nbsp;Wood-Vasey</div> <div class="imageTitle">SweetSpot_Supernova_DR1</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ This award supported the "SweetSpot" survey of nearby supernovae.  Sweet observed 115 supernovae in infrared wavelengths using the WIYN 3.5-m telescope at Kitt Peak National Observatory.  Additional spatially-resolved spectra were made of 36 host galaxies of supernovae to investigate the dependence of the supernova properties on their local environments in the galaxies in which they exploded.  These infrared observations contribute a new perspective over the traditional visual light observations of supernovae that have been used to measure the accelerating expansion of the Universe.  Preliminary results indicate that observing supernovaa in infrared wavelengths leads to more accurate distance measurements than when using only observations in visible light.  These data are already being used to investigate how to more accurately measure distances to supernova to improve our measurements of dark energy driving this expansion.  This work supported two graduate students who each successfully completed their PhDs during the period of this award.  Two papers by these graduate students were submitted to astronomical journals describing the work and two more are in preparation.  The first SweetSpot data release paper features 74 of the 115 supernovae.  Thumbnail images of each of these supernova and the gaalxies that hosted them are included in the attached image.  This work further supported a postdoc studying spatially-resolved spectra of galaxies that have hosted supernovae.  His work contributed to 6 papers, including a Nature paper on the discovery of a kilonova associated with a gravitational wave event.  The work was shared with the public through several public talks given at the historic Allegheny Observatory.       Last Modified: 01/24/2018       Submitted by: William M Wood-Vasey]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
