<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>DISSERTATION RESEARCH: Evolutionary genomics of inter-kingdom host jumping in the fungal genus Elaphocordyceps</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>06/01/2013</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2015</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>18980.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>18980</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>08010206</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>BIO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DEB</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Environmental Biology</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Simon Malcomber</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>smalcomb@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032928227</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This study seeks to use genetic data to elucidate mechanisms underlying host specificity in a group of fungi that are either pathogens of insects or other fungi.  Through previous research, whole genome data was generated for two very closely related species, one beetle pathogen and one truffle pathogen.  In this study, an experiment will be performed where the truffle pathogen will be grown in conditions containing the truffle and without, and the comparison of how the fungus responds to these conditions (measured using messenger RNA) will gives clues as to which genes and pathways are necessary for truffle pathogenesis.  In addition, whole genome data will be produced for more species within this genus, including a cicada pathogen and another truffle pathogen.  These additional genomes will allow larger generalizations to be made about species within this genus parasitizing different hosts, and to identify host-specific gene sets.  Little is known about the infection of new hosts by fungal pathogens and is of increasing importance as the climate continues to change and communities become more global.  Knowledge of the genomic differences of species parasitizing different hosts can inform how fungi are able to switch hosts.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The broader impacts of this study include, but are not limited to, the following.  First, a major impact of this proposal will be the production of an electronically available high school biology module on fungal pathogens of insects and other fungi.  This will be created as a resource for both teachers and students, and include classroom, field, and laboratory exercises.  An integral part of this module will be 5 lessons plans, complete with presentation slides, to comprise an entire insect pathogenic fungi unit.  This will be made publically available at the Cordyceps Electronic Monograph at http://cordyceps.us.  Second, it is of little doubt, based on all previously sequenced genomes of related species, that the study organisms will each have a significant repertoire of secondary metabolites, and a major impact of this project will be the identification of these gene clusters which could lead to the identification and development of novel natural products, with potential applications in medicine and biocontrol.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>04/30/2013</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>04/30/2013</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.074</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1311572</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Joseph</FirstName>
<LastName>Spatafora</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>W</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Joseph W Spatafora</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>spatafoj@science.oregonstate.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5417375304</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000361008</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/30/2013</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Catherine</FirstName>
<LastName>Quandt</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>A</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Catherine A Quandt</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>owensbyc@science.oregonstate.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5417375284</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000553137</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/30/2013</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Oregon State University</Name>
<CityName>Corvallis</CityName>
<ZipCode>973318507</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5417374933</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>OREGON STATE UNIVERSITY</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Oregon</StateName>
<StateCode>OR</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>OR04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>053599908</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>OREGON STATE UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>053599908</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Oregon State University]]></Name>
<CityName>Corvallis</CityName>
<StateCode>OR</StateCode>
<ZipCode>973318507</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Oregon</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>OR04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1171</Code>
<Text>PHYLOGENETIC SYSTEMATICS</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1171</Code>
<Text>PHYLOGENETIC SYSTEMATICS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9179</Code>
<Text>GRADUATE INVOLVEMENT</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>EGCH</Code>
<Text>ENVIRONMENT AND GLOBAL CHANGE</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>SMET</Code>
<Text>SCIENCE, MATH, ENG &amp; TECH EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0113</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2013~18980</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><span>This project was focused on mechanisms underlying host jumping in several species of fungi in the genus<span>&nbsp;</span><em><span>Tolypocladium</span></em><span>&nbsp;</span>(=<em><span>Elaphocordyceps</span></em>). &nbsp;</span></p> <p><span>There were two major project outcomes in the realm of intellectual merit. &nbsp;First, the draft genomes of two new species of fungi, one a pathogen of cicadas (<em><span>T. paradoxum</span></em>) and the other a parasite of truffles (<em><span>T. capitatum</span></em>), were produced. &nbsp;The comparison of these two species with two previously sequenced <em>Tolypocladium</em> species provided a significant advancement in our understanding of the evolution of inter-kingdom host switching in these fungi. &nbsp;In particular, this project provided genetic evidence that rejected the findings of previous studies that after a switch to truffle parasitism, there had been multiple reversions to insect pathogenesis. &nbsp;To the contrary, we find that the insect pathogens form the earliest diverging lineages of the genus. &nbsp;We also identified genes that are specific to the insect pathogens and those that are specific to the truffle parasites.&nbsp; Second,&nbsp;this project has provided a massive amount of sequence data as evidence for what kinds of genes are important when a fungus (<em><span>T. ophioglossoides</span></em>) grows on the tissue of another, host fungus. This was obtained in a growth experiment that also resulted in the creation of a novel media type as a part of this project. &nbsp;The experiment identified several potential mechanisms through which<span>&nbsp;</span><em><span>T. ophioglossoides</span></em><span>&nbsp;</span>may be recognizing, breaking down, and attaching to its fungal host. &nbsp;This is the first study looking at genes involved in truffle parasitism.</span></p> <p><span>There were several broader impacts of this project as well. &nbsp;The first of which was the creation of&nbsp;lesson plans and slide shows at the&nbsp;high school or college level, which are&nbsp;available for free online and cover an introduction to Kingdom Fungi, and an introduction to insect pathogenic fungi. &nbsp;These lessons include various methods to engage students including a discussion, interesting videos, and an easy-to-setup activity. &nbsp;An undergraduate student was also trained and participated in the bioinformatic methods used in the comparative genomic analyses in this study. &nbsp;</span></p> <p><span>This project also greatly contributed to the Co-PI's dissertation research and final thesis, resulting in two extra thesis chapters. &nbsp;This project provided the Co-PI with extra professional development and the opportunity to mentor an undergraduate student.</span></p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 08/29/2015<br>      Modified by: Catherine&nbsp;A&nbsp;Quandt</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Image         </div> <div class="galControls onePhoto" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation onePhoto" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2015/1311572/1311572_10243231_1440890969152_To--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2015/1311572/1311572_10243231_1440890969152_To--rgov-800width.jpg" title="T. ophioglossoides"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2015/1311572/1311572_10243231_1440890969152_To--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="T. ophioglossoides"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">T. ophioglossoides fruiting from Elaphomyces truffle it has parasitized.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Alisha Quandt</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <...]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ This project was focused on mechanisms underlying host jumping in several species of fungi in the genus Tolypocladium (=Elaphocordyceps).    There were two major project outcomes in the realm of intellectual merit.  First, the draft genomes of two new species of fungi, one a pathogen of cicadas (T. paradoxum) and the other a parasite of truffles (T. capitatum), were produced.  The comparison of these two species with two previously sequenced Tolypocladium species provided a significant advancement in our understanding of the evolution of inter-kingdom host switching in these fungi.  In particular, this project provided genetic evidence that rejected the findings of previous studies that after a switch to truffle parasitism, there had been multiple reversions to insect pathogenesis.  To the contrary, we find that the insect pathogens form the earliest diverging lineages of the genus.  We also identified genes that are specific to the insect pathogens and those that are specific to the truffle parasites.  Second, this project has provided a massive amount of sequence data as evidence for what kinds of genes are important when a fungus (T. ophioglossoides) grows on the tissue of another, host fungus. This was obtained in a growth experiment that also resulted in the creation of a novel media type as a part of this project.  The experiment identified several potential mechanisms through which T. ophioglossoides may be recognizing, breaking down, and attaching to its fungal host.  This is the first study looking at genes involved in truffle parasitism.  There were several broader impacts of this project as well.  The first of which was the creation of lesson plans and slide shows at the high school or college level, which are available for free online and cover an introduction to Kingdom Fungi, and an introduction to insect pathogenic fungi.  These lessons include various methods to engage students including a discussion, interesting videos, and an easy-to-setup activity.  An undergraduate student was also trained and participated in the bioinformatic methods used in the comparative genomic analyses in this study.    This project also greatly contributed to the Co-PI's dissertation research and final thesis, resulting in two extra thesis chapters.  This project provided the Co-PI with extra professional development and the opportunity to mentor an undergraduate student.          Last Modified: 08/29/2015       Submitted by: Catherine A Quandt]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
