<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>WNY Genetics in Research Partnership: Expanding Exposure, Career Exploration and Interactive Projects in Basic Genome Analysis and Bioinformatics</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/15/2013</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>1136573.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>1136573</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>11090000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>EHR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DRL</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Research On Learning</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>David Haury</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This project will develop an ongoing partnership with disadvantaged schools across a 14-county region of New York that will facilitate teacher and student recruitment, preparation, and mentorship for careers in science, technology, engineering, and mathematics (STEM).  Project activities will focus on basic genome analysis and bioinformatics, and the partnership will be directed by the University at Buffalo Department of Biotechnical and Clinical Laboratory Sciences (BCLS) and the New York State Area Health Education Center System (NYS AHEC).  Thirty biology teachers annually from partnering schools will attend a two-week summer workshop at the University at Buffalo where they will receive training in use of the Integrated Microbial Genomes Annotation Collaboration Toolkit (IMG-ACT) of the U.S. Department of Energy Joint Genome Institute. During Semester I of each school year of the project, NYS AHEC will organize college and career exploration sessions to familiarize students with the gene annotation project and to provide a "real world" context.  Students will develop career plans by the end of Semester I as well as indicate their interest in participating in gene annotation activities during Semester II. During Semester II, each teacher will work with at least 5 students (150 total per year) on a genome annotation project using the IMG-ACT. Each spring, a Capstone Symposium will be held, bringing participating students and teachers together to present their projects and to interact with university faculty, researchers and bioscience employers.  Formative and summative evaluation activities will be conducted for all teacher and student participants who participated in multiple years of the project to assess broader based outcomes related to changes in knowledge, behavior and dispositions toward STEM-related careers.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Bioinformatics is in a period of rapid growth, and genomics is becoming increasingly important to the life sciences and health care practices. Genetic and genomic research are expanding throughout the biological sciences, and bioinformatics is providing tools for enhanced understanding of health and improvements in prevention, detection, diagnosis, and treatment of disease. Growth has been so rapid that some areas are experiencing shortages of trained researchers, and the health professions have been challenged to keep up with developments. Moreover, this era of great research potential coincides with a trend of declining student interest in science, and the nation has had particular difficulty addressing minority underrepresentation in STEM fields. There is an urgent need for teacher and student exposure to science role models, as well as instructional approaches that allow students to work with real scientific data and tools, and to make connections between what they are studying and the problems their families and communities are facing.  As students and teachers perform the gene annotations associated with this project they will simultaneously be learning to use public domain bioinformatics software and conducting a research project.  They will experience the excitement of making novel discoveries, as well as some of the uncertainty associated with any scientific experiment.  They will learn to question assumptions and to formulate and test hypotheses about the genes they are annotating, rather than simply performing scripted laboratory exercises. It is expected that the hands-on approach to learning and basic bioinformatics research, along with the STEM related career exploration sessions and continued NYS AHEC support of student participants, will motivate students, and better prepare them to seek out academic programs and careers in STEM-related areas. Teachers will obtain professional development and training in basic bioinformatics that can then be incorporated into their general classroom teaching.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/13/2013</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/13/2013</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.076</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1311902</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Stephen</FirstName>
<LastName>Koury</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>T</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Stephen T Koury</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>stvkoury@buffalo.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>7166455000</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000557595</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/13/2013</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>SUNY at Buffalo</Name>
<CityName>Buffalo</CityName>
<ZipCode>142282567</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>7166452634</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>520 Lee Entrance</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[Suite 211]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>26</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NY26</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>038633251</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>RESEARCH FOUNDATION FOR THE STATE UNIVERSITY OF NEW YORK, THE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>020657151</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[SUNY at Buffalo]]></Name>
<CityName>Buffalo</CityName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<ZipCode>142143000</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[3435 Main Street, 26 Cary Hall]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>26</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NY26</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7227</Code>
<Text>ITEST-Inov Tech Exp Stu &amp; Teac</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<Appropriation>
<Code>13XX</Code>
<Name>H-1B FUND, EHR, NSF</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>045176</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2013~1136573</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The Western New York Genetics in Research Partnership (WNYGRP), funded by an ITEST Strategies Award from NSF, revolved around an innovative technology experience called the <em>Genomics Education National Initiative Annotation Collaboration Toolkit</em> (<em>GENI</em>-<em>ACT</em>). GENI-ACT is a &ldquo;hands-on&rdquo; cyber-learning approach using bioinformatics software in the classroom: <a href="https://geni-act.org/">https://geni-act.org/</a>&nbsp; GENI-ACT uses a modular approach to perform bioinformatics analyses on genomes of selected clinically significant bacteria. Genes from <em>K. sedentarius </em>were selected and assigned to teachers, who implemented modules (http://ubwp.buffalo.edu/wnygirp/educational-resources/)&nbsp;with their students in small groups during the second half of the school year, mentored by a WNYGRP faculty member. Students presented their findings (http://ubwp.buffalo.edu/wnygirp/student-research/)&nbsp;at an annual Capstone Symposium at the University at Buffalo (UB).</p> <p><strong>Establishment of the Partnership:</strong></p> <p>WNYGRP successfully established a bioinformatics and genomics pipeline for recruiting students into STEM careers, with an emphasis on high school students from economically disadvantaged schools in a fourteen county region of western New York, including the cities of Buffalo and Rochester. In total, 74 high school teachers in 33 high schools were part of the partnership, which is comprised of UB, including the departments of Biotechnical and Clinical Laboratory Sciences and Family Medicine and<em> the NYS Center of Excellence in Bioinformatics and Life Sciences</em> (CBLS); the New York State Area Health Education Center System (NYSAHEC), including two AHEC centers, Erie-Niagara (EN AHEC) and Western New York Rural (R-AHEC); Oak Ridge Associated Universities; UB faculty with expertise in genome annotation; and a NYS STEM Master High School Teacher.</p> <p><strong>Teacher and Student Recruitment:</strong> <br /> Of the 74 Biology teachers recruited over three years, nearly half (46%) were recruited from schools with a higher than average proportion of economically disadvantaged students. Each teacher participated in a week-long training workshop during the summer to prepare them to use the GENI-ACT. Teachers showed significant increases in content knowledge in bioinformatics and genetics from the beginning to the end of the workshop.</p> <p>The fourth year of the project (a no-cost extension) invited teachers who participated in years 1-3 to return to develop and integrate genome annotation into their courses or afterschool programs and work with a new cohort of students using GENI-ACT. Of 19 returning teachers, the majority indicated using GENI-ACT in the development of a NEW/addition to a CURRENT Bioinformatics/Genomics after-school program or club at their school. A majority also expressed interest in participating in future Capstone events, mentoring other teachers in the WNYGRP, and participating in future professional meetings in bioinformatics and genomics involving WNYGRP.</p> <p><strong>Career Focuses Activities: <br /> </strong>The GENI-ACT modules intervention was supported by an activity series for all interested students at participating high schools during the first half of the school year, with 1,948 high school students attending at least one activity across three years. Activities included STEM college and career guidance facilitated by R-AHEC or EN AHEC and an introduction to genome annotation and the GENI-ACT program facilitated by UB faculty experts. &nbsp;<br /> <br /> As of Fall 2016, National Student Clearinghouse Data indicated that 115 high school students who were exposed to at least one AHEC activity had enrolled in a 2 or 4 year college. Almost half (55) indicated a STEM-related major, with 13 of those students enrolled in Biology, Biochemistry or Biomedical Engineering. One student participant indicated that being involved in the program &ldquo;&hellip;taught me a lot about genes and has opened my mind to consider a career/major in genetic engineering.&rdquo;</p> <p><strong>Experimental Design Results: </strong></p> <p>An experimental design randomized 667 students recruited by the teachers, assigning 343 to the Intervention group (who received GENI-ACT training), and the remaining 324 to the Comparison group (no GENI-ACT training) over three years. The Intervention group completed up to nine modules using GENI-ACT across the second half of the school year, culminating in the annual Capstone Symposium. Students in the Intervention group significantly increased their content knowledge of bioinformatics and gene annotation by well over 50% by the end of the school year, while Comparison students did not. Teachers received training in the preparation of posters for scientific meetings to guide students in preparing posters about their work in GENI-ACT. During Capstone events, students and teachers from different schools interacted with one another and with WNYGRP staff and UB faculty. During year 4, the returning teachers worked with an additional 200 students who participated in the Capstone.</p> <p><strong>Internship Opportunities: </strong></p> <p>Ongoing career support included development of internship opportunities. A list of 12 specific internships developed by the partnership was made available to students during year 3. When surveyed students were asked if they applied to summer internships, 10 students (3 Intervention and 7 Comparison) indicated that they had applied for internships, naming several of the opportunities specifically developed by WNYGRP.</p> <p><strong>2016 Video Showcase:</strong> <br /> A video about the WNYGRP was created and presented at the&nbsp;2016 NSF video showcase <em>Advancing STEM Learning For All: Sharing Cutting Edge Work and Community Discourse</em>. <a href="http://stemforall2016.videohall.com/presentations/709">http://stemforall2016.videohall.com/presentations/709</a></p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 11/06/2017<br>      Modified by: Stephen&nbsp;T&nbsp;Koury</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Images (<span id="selectedPhoto0">1</span> of <span class="totalNumber"></span>)           </div> <div class="galControls" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1311902/1311902_10267116_1510002760859_students3--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1311902/1311902_10267116_1510002760859_students3--rgov-800width.jpg" title="McKinley High School Capstone Poster"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1311902/1311902_10267116_1510002760859_students3--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="McKinley High School Capstone Poster"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Students and teacher from McKinley High School showcasing their gene annotation research at the 2017 Capstone Symposium.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Western New York Genetics in Research Partnership</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Stephen&nbsp;T&nbsp;Koury</div> <div class="imageTitle">McKinley High School Capstone Poster</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1311902/1311902_10267116_1510001483108_partnership--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1311902/1311902_10267116_1510001483108_partnership--rgov-800width.jpg" title="The WNY Genetics in Research Partnership"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1311902/1311902_10267116_1510001483108_partnership--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="The WNY Genetics in Research Partnership"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">This map of the western NY area shows schools that took part in the project.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Western New York Genetics In Research Partnership</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Royalty-free (restricted use - cannot be shared)</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Stephen&nbsp;T&nbsp;Koury</div> <div class="imageTitle">The WNY Genetics in Research Partnership</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1311902/1311902_10267116_1510002120764_GENI-ACT--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1311902/1311902_10267116_1510002120764_GENI-ACT--rgov-800width.jpg" title="T-Coffee analysis within GENI-ACT"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1311902/1311902_10267116_1510002120764_GENI-ACT--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="T-Coffee analysis within GENI-ACT"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">A typical screen from the Sequence Based Similarity module of GENI-ACT showing the use of T-Coffee to perform a multiple sequence alignment.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Western New York Genetics in Research Partnership</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Public Domain</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Stephen&nbsp;T&nbsp;Koury</div> <div class="imageTitle">T-Coffee analysis within GENI-ACT</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1311902/1311902_10267116_1510002262626_Capstone--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1311902/1311902_10267116_1510002262626_Capstone--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Overview of the 2017 Capstone Poster Session"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1311902/1311902_10267116_1510002262626_Capstone--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Overview of the 2017 Capstone Poster Session"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Image of the atrium of the Center for the Arts at the University at Buffalo during the 2017 Capstone Symposium.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Western New York Genetics in Research Partnership</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Public Domain</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Stephen&nbsp;T&nbsp;Koury</div> <div class="imageTitle">Overview of the 2017 Capstone Poster Session</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1311902/1311902_10267116_1510002407447_students2--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1311902/1311902_10267116_1510002407447_students2--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Students from Lackawanna High School With Their Capstone Poster"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1311902/1311902_10267116_1510002407447_students2--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Students from Lackawanna High School With Their Capstone Poster"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Students in front of the poster they prepared to present the results of the gene annotation research at the 2017 Capstone Symposium</div> <div class="imageCredit">Western New York Genetics in Research Partnership</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Stephen&nbsp;T&nbsp;Koury</div> <div class="imageTitle">Students from Lackawanna High School With Their Capstone Poster</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1311902/1311902_10267116_1510001951812_students1--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1311902/1311902_10267116_1510001951812_students1--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Students working on gene annotation"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1311902/1311902_10267116_1510001951812_students1--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Students working on gene annotation"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Students from Williamsville East High School working on their gene annotations using GENI-ACT.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Western New York Genetics In Research Partnership</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Stephen&nbsp;T&nbsp;Koury</div> <div class="imageTitle">Students working on gene annotation</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The Western New York Genetics in Research Partnership (WNYGRP), funded by an ITEST Strategies Award from NSF, revolved around an innovative technology experience called the Genomics Education National Initiative Annotation Collaboration Toolkit (GENI-ACT). GENI-ACT is a "hands-on" cyber-learning approach using bioinformatics software in the classroom: https://geni-act.org/  GENI-ACT uses a modular approach to perform bioinformatics analyses on genomes of selected clinically significant bacteria. Genes from K. sedentarius were selected and assigned to teachers, who implemented modules (http://ubwp.buffalo.edu/wnygirp/educational-resources/) with their students in small groups during the second half of the school year, mentored by a WNYGRP faculty member. Students presented their findings (http://ubwp.buffalo.edu/wnygirp/student-research/) at an annual Capstone Symposium at the University at Buffalo (UB).  Establishment of the Partnership:  WNYGRP successfully established a bioinformatics and genomics pipeline for recruiting students into STEM careers, with an emphasis on high school students from economically disadvantaged schools in a fourteen county region of western New York, including the cities of Buffalo and Rochester. In total, 74 high school teachers in 33 high schools were part of the partnership, which is comprised of UB, including the departments of Biotechnical and Clinical Laboratory Sciences and Family Medicine and the NYS Center of Excellence in Bioinformatics and Life Sciences (CBLS); the New York State Area Health Education Center System (NYSAHEC), including two AHEC centers, Erie-Niagara (EN AHEC) and Western New York Rural (R-AHEC); Oak Ridge Associated Universities; UB faculty with expertise in genome annotation; and a NYS STEM Master High School Teacher.  Teacher and Student Recruitment:   Of the 74 Biology teachers recruited over three years, nearly half (46%) were recruited from schools with a higher than average proportion of economically disadvantaged students. Each teacher participated in a week-long training workshop during the summer to prepare them to use the GENI-ACT. Teachers showed significant increases in content knowledge in bioinformatics and genetics from the beginning to the end of the workshop.  The fourth year of the project (a no-cost extension) invited teachers who participated in years 1-3 to return to develop and integrate genome annotation into their courses or afterschool programs and work with a new cohort of students using GENI-ACT. Of 19 returning teachers, the majority indicated using GENI-ACT in the development of a NEW/addition to a CURRENT Bioinformatics/Genomics after-school program or club at their school. A majority also expressed interest in participating in future Capstone events, mentoring other teachers in the WNYGRP, and participating in future professional meetings in bioinformatics and genomics involving WNYGRP.  Career Focuses Activities:   The GENI-ACT modules intervention was supported by an activity series for all interested students at participating high schools during the first half of the school year, with 1,948 high school students attending at least one activity across three years. Activities included STEM college and career guidance facilitated by R-AHEC or EN AHEC and an introduction to genome annotation and the GENI-ACT program facilitated by UB faculty experts.      As of Fall 2016, National Student Clearinghouse Data indicated that 115 high school students who were exposed to at least one AHEC activity had enrolled in a 2 or 4 year college. Almost half (55) indicated a STEM-related major, with 13 of those students enrolled in Biology, Biochemistry or Biomedical Engineering. One student participant indicated that being involved in the program "&hellip;taught me a lot about genes and has opened my mind to consider a career/major in genetic engineering."  Experimental Design Results:   An experimental design randomized 667 students recruited by the teachers, assigning 343 to the Intervention group (who received GENI-ACT training), and the remaining 324 to the Comparison group (no GENI-ACT training) over three years. The Intervention group completed up to nine modules using GENI-ACT across the second half of the school year, culminating in the annual Capstone Symposium. Students in the Intervention group significantly increased their content knowledge of bioinformatics and gene annotation by well over 50% by the end of the school year, while Comparison students did not. Teachers received training in the preparation of posters for scientific meetings to guide students in preparing posters about their work in GENI-ACT. During Capstone events, students and teachers from different schools interacted with one another and with WNYGRP staff and UB faculty. During year 4, the returning teachers worked with an additional 200 students who participated in the Capstone.  Internship Opportunities:   Ongoing career support included development of internship opportunities. A list of 12 specific internships developed by the partnership was made available to students during year 3. When surveyed students were asked if they applied to summer internships, 10 students (3 Intervention and 7 Comparison) indicated that they had applied for internships, naming several of the opportunities specifically developed by WNYGRP.  2016 Video Showcase:   A video about the WNYGRP was created and presented at the 2016 NSF video showcase Advancing STEM Learning For All: Sharing Cutting Edge Work and Community Discourse. http://stemforall2016.videohall.com/presentations/709          Last Modified: 11/06/2017       Submitted by: Stephen T Koury]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
