<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>DISSERTATION RESEARCH: Why species delimitation matters: Cryptic diversity, complete species-level phylogeny, and Andean diversification of an American marsupial clade</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>06/01/2013</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2016</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>19641.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>19641</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>08010206</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>BIO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DEB</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Environmental Biology</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Simon Malcomber</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>smalcomb@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032928227</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The Neotropics is one of the most biodiverse regions of the world. However, understanding the historical processes underlying this diversity is a challenging task due in part to the complex geographic and climatological history of this region. For mammals, this task is further hindered by our lack of fundamental knowledge about biodiversity, such as the number of species occurring in this area, their distribution, and how they are related to each other. This is particularly true for a group of small opossums (Thylamyini), which are broadly distributed throughout the Neotropics but are often morphologically indistinguishable from each other. There are 37 currently recognized species of Thylamyini, but preliminary analyses suggest that species diversity may be nearly double that.&lt;br/&gt; This project aims to discover the true diversity of this ecologically important group of mammals using multiple nuclear and mitochondrial DNA sequences as well as morphology. This revised view of mammalian diversity will have profound implications for our understanding of diversification in the Neotropics and will provide the basis for much needed conservation strategies in this time of global extinction.  In addition, the proposed outreach and educational activities will continue to strengthen developing collaborations between US and Colombian institutions of higher education.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>04/30/2013</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>11/17/2015</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.074</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1311163</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Sharon</FirstName>
<LastName>Jansa</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>A</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Sharon A Jansa</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>jansa003@umn.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6126246293</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000442743</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/30/2013</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Juan</FirstName>
<LastName>Diaz-Nieto</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>F</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Juan F Diaz-Nieto</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>diaz0154@umn.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6126255700</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000628606</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/30/2013</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Minnesota-Twin Cities</Name>
<CityName>Minneapolis</CityName>
<ZipCode>554552070</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6126245599</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>200 OAK ST SE</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Minnesota</StateName>
<StateCode>MN</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MN05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>555917996</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>REGENTS OF THE UNIVERSITY OF MINNESOTA</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>117178941</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Minnesota-Twin Cities]]></Name>
<CityName>Saint Paul</CityName>
<StateCode>MN</StateCode>
<ZipCode>551086097</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[1987 Upper Burford Circle]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Minnesota</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MN04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1171</Code>
<Text>PHYLOGENETIC SYSTEMATICS</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1171</Code>
<Text>PHYLOGENETIC SYSTEMATICS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9179</Code>
<Text>GRADUATE INVOLVEMENT</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>EGCH</Code>
<Text>ENVIRONMENT AND GLOBAL CHANGE</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>SMET</Code>
<Text>SCIENCE, MATH, ENG &amp; TECH EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0113</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2013~19641</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p class="normal">Since the discovery of the New World, the Neotropics has held the attention biologists who have sought to describe and explain the origins of its tremendous biodiversity.&nbsp; Recent advances in the reconstruction of geology and paleoclimates have helped to unveil the complex history of the Neotropics, and suggest that geological events, such as river formation, mountain uplift, and historical climate change played an important role in shaping the history of life.&nbsp; Although we cannot travel back in time to observe how earth history influenced life history, we can generate and test hypotheses about the impact of historical events on the current biota.&nbsp; Analytical tools such as molecular phylogenetics (using DNA data to reconstruct the history of life), biogeographic reconstruction, and analyses of diversification rates are powerful tools that permit this line of inquiry.&nbsp; Despite these tools, one of the largest impediments to this line of research is that most of the species on earth are still waiting to be discovered and described.&nbsp; Therefore, the task of testing hypotheses of diversification is hindered by our lack of knowledge concerning the species diversity of most clades.</p> <p class="normal">The goal of this project was to understand species limits, phylogenetic history, biogeographic patterns, and diversification for one part of the Neotropical fauna, the mouse opossums of the genus <em>Marmosops.&nbsp; </em>These marsupials are distributed from Panama to southern Bolivia and southeastern Brazil and occur in highland and lowland forests of the Andes, Pantepui, Amazonia, and the Atlantic forests.&nbsp; The last comprehensive taxonomic study of this group was completed in 1933 - well before molecular data could be used to understand biodiversity - and no study has ever included a thorough geographic sampling of <em>Marmosops</em> species from throughout their range.&nbsp; To address this problem, we generated DNA sequences from &gt;200 museum specimens of <em>Marmosops</em>, including at least one representative of each recognized species.&nbsp; We analyzed these data using modern analytical approaches that are designed to discover species and infer phylogenetic and biogeographic history.</p> <p class="normal">We discovered that there is a deep, phylogenetic split within Marmosops that occurred about 9 million years ago, and gave rise to two species-rich lineages with broadly overlapping geographic distributions.&nbsp; Members of the two groups differ in mean size where they occur together, suggesting a long independent history of geographic dispersal and ecological adaptation.&nbsp; Moreover, we discovered that the current diversity of the genus is probably underestimated by at least half (there are currently 15 named species; our analyses suggest there may be at least 35 species in this group).&nbsp; Many of these species are &ldquo;cryptic&rdquo; (i.e. they look very similar to each other but have high levels of DNA sequence divergence), and could only have been discovered using the molecular data we gathered for this project.</p> <p class="normal">Intellectual Merit: This research has refined our understanding of the diversity and diversification of mouse opossums in South and Central America.&nbsp; We now suggest that this group may be twice as diverse as previously recognized, and that the diversity of this group unfolded over the last 9 million years of earth history.&nbsp; Several biogeographic events that occurred over this time period, including river formation and mountain uplift, appear to have played an important role in shaping the diversification of this important member of the Neotropical fauna.</p> <p class="normal">Broader Impacts: This project formed the dissertation research of Juan Diaz-N, a Colombian native who completed his dissertation at the University of Minnesota.&nbsp; He has now returned to Colombia to assume a faculty position at the Universidad EAFIT in Medellin Colombia.&nbsp; Products of this work to date include four publications, a published dissertation, and numerous presentations at scientific meetings.&nbsp;&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 04/04/2017<br>      Modified by: Sharon&nbsp;A&nbsp;Jansa</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[Since the discovery of the New World, the Neotropics has held the attention biologists who have sought to describe and explain the origins of its tremendous biodiversity.  Recent advances in the reconstruction of geology and paleoclimates have helped to unveil the complex history of the Neotropics, and suggest that geological events, such as river formation, mountain uplift, and historical climate change played an important role in shaping the history of life.  Although we cannot travel back in time to observe how earth history influenced life history, we can generate and test hypotheses about the impact of historical events on the current biota.  Analytical tools such as molecular phylogenetics (using DNA data to reconstruct the history of life), biogeographic reconstruction, and analyses of diversification rates are powerful tools that permit this line of inquiry.  Despite these tools, one of the largest impediments to this line of research is that most of the species on earth are still waiting to be discovered and described.  Therefore, the task of testing hypotheses of diversification is hindered by our lack of knowledge concerning the species diversity of most clades. The goal of this project was to understand species limits, phylogenetic history, biogeographic patterns, and diversification for one part of the Neotropical fauna, the mouse opossums of the genus Marmosops.  These marsupials are distributed from Panama to southern Bolivia and southeastern Brazil and occur in highland and lowland forests of the Andes, Pantepui, Amazonia, and the Atlantic forests.  The last comprehensive taxonomic study of this group was completed in 1933 - well before molecular data could be used to understand biodiversity - and no study has ever included a thorough geographic sampling of Marmosops species from throughout their range.  To address this problem, we generated DNA sequences from &gt;200 museum specimens of Marmosops, including at least one representative of each recognized species.  We analyzed these data using modern analytical approaches that are designed to discover species and infer phylogenetic and biogeographic history. We discovered that there is a deep, phylogenetic split within Marmosops that occurred about 9 million years ago, and gave rise to two species-rich lineages with broadly overlapping geographic distributions.  Members of the two groups differ in mean size where they occur together, suggesting a long independent history of geographic dispersal and ecological adaptation.  Moreover, we discovered that the current diversity of the genus is probably underestimated by at least half (there are currently 15 named species; our analyses suggest there may be at least 35 species in this group).  Many of these species are "cryptic" (i.e. they look very similar to each other but have high levels of DNA sequence divergence), and could only have been discovered using the molecular data we gathered for this project. Intellectual Merit: This research has refined our understanding of the diversity and diversification of mouse opossums in South and Central America.  We now suggest that this group may be twice as diverse as previously recognized, and that the diversity of this group unfolded over the last 9 million years of earth history.  Several biogeographic events that occurred over this time period, including river formation and mountain uplift, appear to have played an important role in shaping the diversification of this important member of the Neotropical fauna. Broader Impacts: This project formed the dissertation research of Juan Diaz-N, a Colombian native who completed his dissertation at the University of Minnesota.  He has now returned to Colombia to assume a faculty position at the Universidad EAFIT in Medellin Colombia.  Products of this work to date include four publications, a published dissertation, and numerous presentations at scientific meetings.            Last Modified: 04/04/2017       Submitted by: Sharon A Jansa]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
