<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>WORKSHOP: The 2013 HRI Pioneers Workshop at the 2013 ACM/IEEE International Conference on Human-Robot Interaction</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>02/01/2013</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>01/31/2014</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>34575.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>34575</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>05020000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>CSE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>IIS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Information &amp; Intelligent Systems</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Ephraim Glinert</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>eglinert@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032928930</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This is funding to support a Young Pioneers Workshop (doctoral consortium) of approximately 20 graduate students and post-docs (including 15 U.S. participants) from diverse research communities (e.g., computer science and engineering, psychology, cognitive science, robotics, human factors, human-computer interaction design, and communications), along with distinguished research faculty.  NSF funding will be used solely to cover travel, housing, and subsistence for eligible U.S. attendees.  The event will take place on Sunday, March 3, 2013, immediately preceding the Eighth Annual Human Robot Interaction Conference (HRI 2013), to be held March 3-6, 2013, in Tokyo, Japan, and which is jointly sponsored by ACM and IEEE.  HRI is a single-track, highly selective annual international conference that seeks to showcase the very best inter- and multi-disciplinary research in human-robot interaction with roots in social psychology, cognitive science, HCI, human factors, artificial intelligence, robotics, organizational behavior, anthropology and many more, and invites broad participation.  The theme of HRI 2013 is "Holistic Human-Robot Development."  Robotic solutions are increasingly applied to real world problems such as our aging society, renewable energy, climate control, emergency response, education and exploration. These societal problems require a holistic approach to the design and development of robots that meet human needs, address technical challenges, and foster acceptance in everyday settings.  More information about the conference is available online at http://humanrobotinteraction.org/2013.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The Young Pioneers Workshop is designed to complement the conference, by providing a forum for students and recent graduates in the field of HRI to share their current research with their peers and a panel of senior researchers in a setting that is less formal and more interactive than the main conference. During the workshop, participants will talk about the important upcoming research themes in the field, encouraging the formation of collaborative relationships across disciplines and geographic boundaries. To these ends, the workshop format will include oral presentations from 2 student attendees, poster presentations from all student attendees, a hands-on breakout session with group presentations, a keynote, and a panel presentation by senior researchers who will share their expertise and insights on how to address the interdisciplinary challenge of HRI.  The afternoon breakout session will involve small groups of 3-5 attendees with diverse backgrounds, working to design an integrative HRI project, thereby encouraging group participation and the cultivation of cross-disciplinary ideas.  The presentation session afterward will allow each breakout group to present a summary to the entire workshop; the organizers anticipate that the discussions will continue during dinner. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Broader Impacts:  This workshop will afford a unique opportunity for the best of the next generation of researchers in human-robot interaction to be exposed to and discuss current and relevant topics as they are being studied in several different research communities (including but not limited to computer science and engineering, psychology, robotics, human factors and ergonomics, and HCI).  This is important for the field, because it has been recognized that transformative advances in research in this fledgling area can only come through the melding of cross-disciplinary knowledge and multinational perspectives. Participants will be encouraged to create a social network both among themselves and with senior researchers at a critical stage in their professional development, to form collaborative relationships, and to generate new research questions to be addressed during the coming years.  Participants will also gain leadership and service experience, as the workshop is largely student organized and student led.  The PI has expressed his strong commitment to recruiting women and members from other under-represented groups.  To further ensure diversity, the event organizers will consider an applicant's potential to offer a fresh perspective and point of view with respect to HRI, and no more than one applicant will be accepted from any given institution.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>01/17/2013</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>01/17/2013</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.070</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1311610</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Peter</FirstName>
<LastName>Kahn</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>H</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Peter H Kahn</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>pkahn@uw.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2066169395</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000451980</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>01/17/2013</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Washington</Name>
<CityName>Seattle</CityName>
<ZipCode>981950001</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2065434043</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>4333 Brooklyn Ave NE</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Washington</StateName>
<StateCode>WA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>WA07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>605799469</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF WASHINGTON</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>042803536</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Washington]]></Name>
<CityName>Seattle</CityName>
<StateCode>WA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>981951525</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[4333 Brooklyn Ave NE]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Washington</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>WA07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7367</Code>
<Text>HCC-Human-Centered Computing</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7367</Code>
<Text>Cyber-Human Systems</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7556</Code>
<Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0113</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2013~34575</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><span>The 2013 Human-Robot Interaction Pioneers Workshop was held on March 3, 2013 in Tokyo, Japan. In its eighth year, this workshop provided a forum for 23 graduate students and postdocs in the field of human-robot interaction to learn about the current state of research, to present their work, and to network with one another and with select senior researchers in a welcoming and interactive setting. In addition to gaining knowledge of current research conducted by their colleagues, the workshop participants engaged in a high level dialog involving the sharing of cross-disciplinary knowledge and multinational perspectives.</span></p> <p><span>The main objective of this workshop was to establish a support structure for promoting student involvement in the research community of human-robot interaction. This objective was accomplished in the following ways:</span></p> <p><span>1) by providing student researchers with the opportunity to present and share their research with their peers and senior researchers in the field;</span></p> <p><span>2) by encouraging student researchers to form collaborative relationships and generate new research questions through a number of workshop activities such as student presentations and group breakout session;</span></p> <p><span>3) and by providing student organizers of the workshop with leadership and service experience that can become a stepping stone to continued leadership opportunities within the research community.</span></p> <p><span>This year's workshop theme focused on the societal impact of human-robot interaction research and fostered in-depth discussions among the workshop participants and the senior researchers in the field on issues such as the ethical implications of using robots in the military, and the potential reification of sexism in current robot designs. These discussions served to increase the awareness of higher level issues of social import among student researchers in the field, affording them a unique role in shaping the field and directing the course of future research that&nbsp;aim to foster human social wellbeing and flourishing.<br /></span></p> <p><span>In a post-workshop survey, 72% of the workshop participants strongly expressed that they will be able to use what they learned at the workshop toward their future work, and 96% of the workshop participants strongly expressed that the workshop helped them to meet and network with others in the field.</span></p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 02/07/2014<br>      Modified by: Peter&nbsp;H&nbsp;Kahn</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Image         </div> <div class="galControls onePhoto" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation onePhoto" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2014/1311610/1311610_10228790_1391562799072_DSCF5804--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2014/1311610/1311610_10228790_1391562799072_DSCF5804--rgov-800width.jpg" title="2013 HRI Pioneers Workshop"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2014/1311610/1311610_10228790_1391562799072_DSCF5804--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="2013 HRI Pioneers Workshop"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">The cohort of 2013 HRI Pioneers Workshop participants.</div> <div class="imageCredit">2013 HRI Pioneers</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Public Domain</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Peter&nbsp;H&nbsp;Kahn</div> <div class="imageTitle">2013 HRI Pioneers Workshop</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The 2013 Human-Robot Interaction Pioneers Workshop was held on March 3, 2013 in Tokyo, Japan. In its eighth year, this workshop provided a forum for 23 graduate students and postdocs in the field of human-robot interaction to learn about the current state of research, to present their work, and to network with one another and with select senior researchers in a welcoming and interactive setting. In addition to gaining knowledge of current research conducted by their colleagues, the workshop participants engaged in a high level dialog involving the sharing of cross-disciplinary knowledge and multinational perspectives.  The main objective of this workshop was to establish a support structure for promoting student involvement in the research community of human-robot interaction. This objective was accomplished in the following ways:  1) by providing student researchers with the opportunity to present and share their research with their peers and senior researchers in the field;  2) by encouraging student researchers to form collaborative relationships and generate new research questions through a number of workshop activities such as student presentations and group breakout session;  3) and by providing student organizers of the workshop with leadership and service experience that can become a stepping stone to continued leadership opportunities within the research community.  This year's workshop theme focused on the societal impact of human-robot interaction research and fostered in-depth discussions among the workshop participants and the senior researchers in the field on issues such as the ethical implications of using robots in the military, and the potential reification of sexism in current robot designs. These discussions served to increase the awareness of higher level issues of social import among student researchers in the field, affording them a unique role in shaping the field and directing the course of future research that aim to foster human social wellbeing and flourishing.   In a post-workshop survey, 72% of the workshop participants strongly expressed that they will be able to use what they learned at the workshop toward their future work, and 96% of the workshop participants strongly expressed that the workshop helped them to meet and network with others in the field.       Last Modified: 02/07/2014       Submitted by: Peter H Kahn]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
