<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Dissertation Research: Pedogenesis and Anthropedogenesis on the Southern Piedmont</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>05/15/2013</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>04/30/2015</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>17113.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>17113</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>08010209</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>BIO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DEB</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Environmental Biology</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Henry L. Gholz</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This study builds on current research focused on deep soil carbon storage following reforestation in the Southern Piedmont region of the southeastern United States.  Globally, soil contains more carbon than that stored in all land vegetation.  However, most studies trying to connect carbon storage with changes in land use have ignored soil deeper than one meter.  The investigators hypothesize that the widespread trends of reforestation in this region over the last century have led to deep carbon storage that depends intimately on the chemical behavior of soil iron.  To test this hypothesis, specialized carbon measurements (radiocarbon dating) will be made to a depth of two meters in soils that have been either reforested or not reforested over the last century.  The carbon measurements will be interpreted alongside results of new analyses of soil iron to provide insights on changes in deep soil carbon storage following reforestation.  &lt;br/&gt; &lt;br/&gt;In the Southern Piedmont, reforested land is by far the dominant land use. This project will improve regional management of forests by showing how reforestation affects the storage of deep soil carbon.  The project will also enhance an interdisciplinary collaborations among Duke University, researchers in the International Soil Carbon Network and the German GeoForschungsZentrum program.  All project data will be made freely available online as part of a widely disseminated soil carbon database for use by other researchers. Results will also be presented to diverse audiences at various scientific meetings, in peer-reviewed publications, and at regional public hearings on land use.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>05/10/2013</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/10/2013</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.074</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1311614</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Daniel</FirstName>
<LastName>Richter</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>D</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Daniel D Richter</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>drichter@duke.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>9196138031</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000196178</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/10/2013</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Allan</FirstName>
<LastName>Bacon</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Allan Bacon</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>allan.bacon@duke.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>9196843030</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000634037</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/10/2013</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Duke University</Name>
<CityName>Durham</CityName>
<ZipCode>277054010</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>9196843030</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>2200 W. Main St, Suite 710</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[Erwin Square]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>North Carolina</StateName>
<StateCode>NC</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NC01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>044387793</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>DUKE UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>044387793</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Duke University]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>NC</StateCode>
<ZipCode>277080328</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>North Carolina</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NC04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1181</Code>
<Text>ECOSYSTEM STUDIES</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1181</Code>
<Text>ECOSYSTEM STUDIES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9169</Code>
<Text>BIODIVERSITY AND ECOSYSTEM DYNAMICS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9179</Code>
<Text>GRADUATE INVOLVEMENT</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>EGCH</Code>
<Text>ENVIRONMENT AND GLOBAL CHANGE</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>SMET</Code>
<Text>SCIENCE, MATH, ENG &amp; TECH EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0113</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2013~17113</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Globally soils contain more carbon than terrestrial vegetation and the atmosphere.&nbsp; Accordingly, understanding the soil carbon cycle and it&rsquo;s response to human forces (such as land use change) are critical if we are to understand and manage Earth&rsquo;s carbon cycle.&nbsp; In most soils the carbon cycle is periodically coupled to the iron cycle.&nbsp; Here, for the first time, we studied the relationship between soil carbon accumulation during reforestation and carbon-iron cycling.&nbsp; We found that reforestation does indeed increase soil carbon contents but exactly where in the soil these increases occur depends almost entirely on carbon-iron cycling.&nbsp; Essentially, carbon-iron cycling creates &ldquo;hotspots&rdquo; for soil carbon accumulation.&nbsp; Considering that carbon-iron cycling is common to a variety of soils around the world, our findings identify soil processes that likely influence carbon on a global scale and provided valuable insights to inform future investigations aimed at a comprehensive understanding of soil carbon.</p> <p>Over the course of this investigation new international and interdisciplinary collaborations were forged.&nbsp; Soil scientists from Duke University collaborated with geochemists from GeoResearchCenter (GFZ-Potsdam, Germany) and researchers within the International Soil Carbon Network (ISCN) to complete this project and make all of its data freely available in a soil carbon database aimed at facilitating global syntheses.&nbsp; This project was also instrumental in training the next generation of scientists by supporting Allan R. Bacon&rsquo;s dissertation research.&nbsp; Specifically, he was given the opportunity to (1) learn and use cutting edge analytical approaches to study soil carbon cycling, (2) work on an international and interdisciplinary team, and (3) mentor other students in a laboratory setting.&nbsp; Finally, this project provides valuable information to forest managers, land managers, and policy makers about how and why soil carbon contents are influenced by land use change, specifically reforestation.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 06/09/2015<br>      Modified by: Daniel&nbsp;D&nbsp;Richter</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Globally soils contain more carbon than terrestrial vegetation and the atmosphere.  Accordingly, understanding the soil carbon cycle and itÆs response to human forces (such as land use change) are critical if we are to understand and manage EarthÆs carbon cycle.  In most soils the carbon cycle is periodically coupled to the iron cycle.  Here, for the first time, we studied the relationship between soil carbon accumulation during reforestation and carbon-iron cycling.  We found that reforestation does indeed increase soil carbon contents but exactly where in the soil these increases occur depends almost entirely on carbon-iron cycling.  Essentially, carbon-iron cycling creates "hotspots" for soil carbon accumulation.  Considering that carbon-iron cycling is common to a variety of soils around the world, our findings identify soil processes that likely influence carbon on a global scale and provided valuable insights to inform future investigations aimed at a comprehensive understanding of soil carbon.  Over the course of this investigation new international and interdisciplinary collaborations were forged.  Soil scientists from Duke University collaborated with geochemists from GeoResearchCenter (GFZ-Potsdam, Germany) and researchers within the International Soil Carbon Network (ISCN) to complete this project and make all of its data freely available in a soil carbon database aimed at facilitating global syntheses.  This project was also instrumental in training the next generation of scientists by supporting Allan R. BaconÆs dissertation research.  Specifically, he was given the opportunity to (1) learn and use cutting edge analytical approaches to study soil carbon cycling, (2) work on an international and interdisciplinary team, and (3) mentor other students in a laboratory setting.  Finally, this project provides valuable information to forest managers, land managers, and policy makers about how and why soil carbon contents are influenced by land use change, specifically reforestation.       Last Modified: 06/09/2015       Submitted by: Daniel D Richter]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
