<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Dissertation Research: Investigating the Role of a Cryptic Life Stage in Fern Evolution and Community Assembly</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>06/01/2013</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2015</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>21970.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>21970</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>08010206</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>BIO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DEB</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Environmental Biology</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Simon Malcomber</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>smalcomb@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032928227</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Ferns represent a successful and diverse lineage, unified by a unique life cycle that has persisted for hundreds of millions of years. Unlike bryophytes or seed plants, the haploid gametophyte and diploid sporophyte of ferns are capable of occurring largely independent of one another, and thus represent distinct ecological entities. Current knowledge of fern ecology is based almost exclusively on the larger, easily observable sporophyte stage; fern gametophytes in contrast have been mostly ignored by ecologists due to their small size (typically &lt;1 cm) and lack of morphological characters for reliable species identification. The gametophyte represents the sexual phase responsible for reproduction, however, and is thus critically important to understanding fern ecology. Recent advances in DNA barcoding methods now allow for the reliable identification of fern gametophytes, and have opened new avenues for research into this neglected area of plant biology. This study will leverage an extensive DNA barcode library of the ferns of Moorea, French Polynesia to identify field-collected gametophytes and compare the distribution and ecological adaptations of fern gametophytes and sporophytes in a broad evolutionary context. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project will provide benefits to multiple groups including both the local community on Moorea and university students in the U.S., and will have important implications for fern conservation. Outreach activities including a multilingual museum display on fern biodiversity are planned for the Atitia community center on Moorea. In addition, data for this research will be partially generated by undergraduates trained at Harvard University. Knowledge of biodiversity will be increased by adding to museum holdings and describing new species. Finally, investigations into species? gametophyte distribution will reveal distribution patterns that will be important to consider when designing conservation programs for endangered fern species.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>05/30/2013</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>09/18/2013</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.074</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1311169</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Charles</FirstName>
<LastName>Davis</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>C</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Charles C Davis</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>cdavis@oeb.harvard.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6174952365</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000328557</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/30/2013</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Joel</FirstName>
<LastName>Nitta</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>H</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Joel H Nitta</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>jnitta@fas.harvard.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6174955501</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000630663</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/30/2013</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Harvard University</Name>
<CityName>Cambridge</CityName>
<ZipCode>021385369</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6174955501</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1033 MASSACHUSETTS AVE</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[5th Floor]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
<StateCode>MA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MA05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>082359691</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>PRESIDENT AND FELLOWS OF HARVARD COLLEGE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>001963263</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Harvard University]]></Name>
<CityName>Cambridge</CityName>
<StateCode>MA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>021382020</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[22 Divinity Ave]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MA05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1171</Code>
<Text>PHYLOGENETIC SYSTEMATICS</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1171</Code>
<Text>PHYLOGENETIC SYSTEMATICS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9179</Code>
<Text>GRADUATE INVOLVEMENT</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>EGCH</Code>
<Text>ENVIRONMENT AND GLOBAL CHANGE</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>SMET</Code>
<Text>SCIENCE, MATH, ENG &amp; TECH EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0113</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2013~21970</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Ferns are an ancient lineage of plants that play key roles in ecosystems around the world. Although ferns are often depicted as small shrubs, this is actually only the diploid phase of the life cycle, or sporophyte. Ferns also posses a much smaller, free-living haploid phase, or gametophyte. Gametophytes are the sexual phase responsible for producing the next generation, and are therefore critically important to understanding fern ecology and evolution. However, the ecology of fern gametophytes is poorly known because they are morphologically simple and cannot be identified to species in the field. This represents a critical gap in our understanding of fern biology.</p> <p>To better understand the ecological role of fern gametophytes, we conducted a survey of co-occurring fern sporophytes and gametophytes along an elevational gradient from 200 to 2000m on the islands of Moorea and Tahiti, French Polynesia. We first constructed a DNA barcode library using two chloroplast gene regions including 90% of the Tahitian fern flora. We identified field-collected gametophytes to species by sequencing their DNA and matching it to known species in the barcode library. We collected over 1600 gametophytes, and successfully identified 1390 (86%) using this DNA barcode system. With the gametophytes confidently identified to species, we then analyzed the diversity patterns of fern gametophytes and sporophytes at our study site. We found that species richness of fern sporophytes reaches a maximum at medium elevations, and that fern sporophyte communities become increasingly phylogenetically clustered at higher elevations. In contrast, species richness of fern gametophytes was consistent across sites, and gametophyte communities tended to be more phylogentically overdispersed relative to sporophytes. We found several individual cases where gametophytes had broader ranges than sporophytes, including two species that are not known as sporophytes from the study area. We also investigated the physiology of fern sporophytes and gametophytes in the filmy fern clade. Within this group, we found that desiccation tolerance of both generations reflected habitat: terrestrial species had low to zero tolerance, whereas epiphytes had greater tolerance. However, photosynthetic optima did not vary between growth habits, but were lower in gametophytes than sporophytes.</p> <p>Our broad survey of fern sporophytes and gametophytes across an elevational gradient reveals that fern sporophytes may be more sensitive to environmental filtering than gametophytes at high elevations. This is broadly consistent with recent studies showing that fern gametophytes tend to have greater physiological tolerances than fern sporophytes. However, our study focusing on the physiology of the filmy fern clade shows that fern gametophytes are not simply tougher than sporophytes in all aspects of their physiology, but are rather specifically adapted to low-light, high-humidity microhabitats. Sporophytes likely experience vastly different environments than gametophytes by elevating their leaves above the soil-air interface. The geographic range of gametophytes is probably determined by the availability of favorable microhabitats, and extends beyond the range of sporophytes when these microhabitats occur without corresponding appropriate habitat for sporophytes. Overall, our study highlights the importance of including diverse life history stages in surveys of community structure, and contributes to our understanding of how fern communities are assembled in nature.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 08/31/2015<br>      Modified by: Joel&nbsp;H&nbsp;Nitta</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Ferns are an ancient lineage of plants that play key roles in ecosystems around the world. Although ferns are often depicted as small shrubs, this is actually only the diploid phase of the life cycle, or sporophyte. Ferns also posses a much smaller, free-living haploid phase, or gametophyte. Gametophytes are the sexual phase responsible for producing the next generation, and are therefore critically important to understanding fern ecology and evolution. However, the ecology of fern gametophytes is poorly known because they are morphologically simple and cannot be identified to species in the field. This represents a critical gap in our understanding of fern biology.  To better understand the ecological role of fern gametophytes, we conducted a survey of co-occurring fern sporophytes and gametophytes along an elevational gradient from 200 to 2000m on the islands of Moorea and Tahiti, French Polynesia. We first constructed a DNA barcode library using two chloroplast gene regions including 90% of the Tahitian fern flora. We identified field-collected gametophytes to species by sequencing their DNA and matching it to known species in the barcode library. We collected over 1600 gametophytes, and successfully identified 1390 (86%) using this DNA barcode system. With the gametophytes confidently identified to species, we then analyzed the diversity patterns of fern gametophytes and sporophytes at our study site. We found that species richness of fern sporophytes reaches a maximum at medium elevations, and that fern sporophyte communities become increasingly phylogenetically clustered at higher elevations. In contrast, species richness of fern gametophytes was consistent across sites, and gametophyte communities tended to be more phylogentically overdispersed relative to sporophytes. We found several individual cases where gametophytes had broader ranges than sporophytes, including two species that are not known as sporophytes from the study area. We also investigated the physiology of fern sporophytes and gametophytes in the filmy fern clade. Within this group, we found that desiccation tolerance of both generations reflected habitat: terrestrial species had low to zero tolerance, whereas epiphytes had greater tolerance. However, photosynthetic optima did not vary between growth habits, but were lower in gametophytes than sporophytes.  Our broad survey of fern sporophytes and gametophytes across an elevational gradient reveals that fern sporophytes may be more sensitive to environmental filtering than gametophytes at high elevations. This is broadly consistent with recent studies showing that fern gametophytes tend to have greater physiological tolerances than fern sporophytes. However, our study focusing on the physiology of the filmy fern clade shows that fern gametophytes are not simply tougher than sporophytes in all aspects of their physiology, but are rather specifically adapted to low-light, high-humidity microhabitats. Sporophytes likely experience vastly different environments than gametophytes by elevating their leaves above the soil-air interface. The geographic range of gametophytes is probably determined by the availability of favorable microhabitats, and extends beyond the range of sporophytes when these microhabitats occur without corresponding appropriate habitat for sporophytes. Overall, our study highlights the importance of including diverse life history stages in surveys of community structure, and contributes to our understanding of how fern communities are assembled in nature.          Last Modified: 08/31/2015       Submitted by: Joel H Nitta]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
