<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>DISSERTATION RESEARCH: Assessing the effects of climate change on biotic interactions structuring herbivore communities</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>06/01/2013</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2015</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>15294.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>15294</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>08010208</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>BIO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DEB</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Environmental Biology</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Douglas Levey</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>dlevey@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032925196</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Climate change is likely to increase average temperatures by 2 ? 6&amp;#730; C over the next century. Unfortunately, scientists lack the data necessary to make accurate predictions about the effects of this increase on biological communities. Most experiments on warming have focused on single species. In contrast, this project will test effects of increasing temperatures on multiple plant, herbivore, and predator species. To examine whether temperature alters effectiveness of how plants defend themselves against insect pests, plants will be grown under different temperatures and exposed to insect herbivores at different times. To examine whether rising temperatures can increase the rate at which the same insects are eaten by their predators, entire communities of plants, herbivores and predators will be reared under current and future temperature conditions. The ability of predatory insects to control populations of herbivorous insects will then be measured. These two experiments will identify how climate change might affect complex interactions between plants and insects, which will aid researchers in developing predictive models.&lt;br/&gt; &lt;br/&gt;Invasive insect species are responsible for considerable damage to economically important crop species. Importantly, many of the herbivores used in the two experiments described here are agricultural and horticultural pests or are closely related to such pests. The results of the first experiment will determine whether economically important plants will be able to adequately defend themselves against insect pests under warmer climates. Likewise, the second experiment will determine whether predators can control population sizes of agricultural pests, which could be important in preventing pest outbreaks.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>05/24/2013</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/24/2013</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.074</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1311464</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Deron</FirstName>
<LastName>Burkepile</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>E</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Deron E Burkepile</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>deron.burkepile@lifesci.ucsb.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>8058933067</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000505751</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/24/2013</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Nathan</FirstName>
<LastName>Lemoine</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Nathan Lemoine</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>nlemo001@fiu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>3053482494</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000629494</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/24/2013</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Florida International University</Name>
<CityName>Miami</CityName>
<ZipCode>331990001</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>3053482494</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>11200 SW 8TH ST</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[MARC 430]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Florida</StateName>
<StateCode>FL</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>26</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>FL26</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>071298814</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>FLORIDA INTERNATIONAL UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>159621697</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Florida International University]]></Name>
<CityName>Miami</CityName>
<StateCode>FL</StateCode>
<ZipCode>331990001</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[11200 SW 8TH ST]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Florida</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>26</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>FL26</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1182</Code>
<Text>POP &amp; COMMUNITY ECOL PROG</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9169</Code>
<Text>BIODIVERSITY AND ECOSYSTEM DYNAMICS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9179</Code>
<Text>GRADUATE INVOLVEMENT</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>EGCH</Code>
<Text>ENVIRONMENT AND GLOBAL CHANGE</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>SMET</Code>
<Text>SCIENCE, MATH, ENG &amp; TECH EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0113</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2013~15294</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Climate change will increase atmospheric temperatures worldwide. Such severe temperature increases might change the relationship between plants and insects in a number of ways. First, insects may choose to feed on a smaller set of plants because of altered nutritional requirements. Second, many insects consume more plant material at higher temperatures, thus the negative effects of insects on plant health might be adversely affected by climate change. The aim of this grant was to examine each of these two topics using realistic climate change experiments.</p> <p>In order to conduct our experiments, we used funding from the DDIG to construct a large, heated garden in order to accurately mimic expected temperature increases from climate change. In addition to the research outlined here, this new experimental facility is a permanent installation that provides research infrastructure for a number of undergraduate and graduate students in the future.</p> <p>Our goal in the first experiment was to determine whether climate warming might alter the nutritional demands of insect herbivores. Insect metabolism increases exponentially with temperature, leading insects to consume more plant material in order to fuel these increased metabolic demands. Rising temperatures also facilitate protein breakdown. As proteins are nitrogen-rich, increased protein turnover rates at high temperatures might increase insect demand for nitrogen. We raised beetworm caterpillars (<em>Spodoptera exigua</em>) on diets of varying nitrogen content at two different temperatures: one representing current spring temperatures in Maryland and the other representing a moderate increase in future spring temperatures. We found that increasing nitrogen content in food did not have a large effect on caterpillars at low temperatures, indicating that nitrogen is not limiting. However, under warming, increasing dietary nitrogen led to rapid increases in growth rate, indicating that nitrogen is strongly limiting to growth at high temperatures. This is due to the fact that caterpillars reared at warm temperatures produced ~150% more metabolic nitrogen waste, indicative of greater protein breakdown at high temperatures. Increased nitrogen demands at higher temperatures may force insects to either consume more plant material to meet these demands or restrict their feeding to a select set of nutritious plant species.</p> <p>The second experiment sought to determine whether climate change magnifies the negative impact of insect pests on plant health and reproduction. To accomplish this, we grew evening primrose (<em>Oenothera biennis</em>) under current and future temperatures. Japanese beetles (<em>Popillia japonica</em>), a major agricultural pest, were excluded from half of the plants. When grown at current, ambient temperatures, Japanese beetles ate a large number of flowers, resulting in shorter plants with fewer seed pods. However, primrose was able to compensate by filling the remaining seed pods with more, albeit smaller, seeds. This enabled primrose to produce roughly equal numbers of seeds despite heavy defoliation and flower damage caused by Japanese beetles. Under warmed, future conditions, Japanese beetles had little influence on plant health. Plants were generally shorter and produced more flowers and seed pods packed with numerous, small seeds. Primrose grown under warmed conditions therefore outproduced plants grown at ambient temperatures. Interestingly, Japanese beetles had little impact on plant health or reproduction in warmed garden beds, aside from a small increase in the number of seeds. This enabled plants exposed to herbivores to actually outproduce plants protected from herbivores, but only when grown under warmed conditions. Consequently, climate warming may restructure the long-standing relationship between plants and insects.</p> <p>Our research will shed light on the potential impact of c...]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Climate change will increase atmospheric temperatures worldwide. Such severe temperature increases might change the relationship between plants and insects in a number of ways. First, insects may choose to feed on a smaller set of plants because of altered nutritional requirements. Second, many insects consume more plant material at higher temperatures, thus the negative effects of insects on plant health might be adversely affected by climate change. The aim of this grant was to examine each of these two topics using realistic climate change experiments.  In order to conduct our experiments, we used funding from the DDIG to construct a large, heated garden in order to accurately mimic expected temperature increases from climate change. In addition to the research outlined here, this new experimental facility is a permanent installation that provides research infrastructure for a number of undergraduate and graduate students in the future.  Our goal in the first experiment was to determine whether climate warming might alter the nutritional demands of insect herbivores. Insect metabolism increases exponentially with temperature, leading insects to consume more plant material in order to fuel these increased metabolic demands. Rising temperatures also facilitate protein breakdown. As proteins are nitrogen-rich, increased protein turnover rates at high temperatures might increase insect demand for nitrogen. We raised beetworm caterpillars (Spodoptera exigua) on diets of varying nitrogen content at two different temperatures: one representing current spring temperatures in Maryland and the other representing a moderate increase in future spring temperatures. We found that increasing nitrogen content in food did not have a large effect on caterpillars at low temperatures, indicating that nitrogen is not limiting. However, under warming, increasing dietary nitrogen led to rapid increases in growth rate, indicating that nitrogen is strongly limiting to growth at high temperatures. This is due to the fact that caterpillars reared at warm temperatures produced ~150% more metabolic nitrogen waste, indicative of greater protein breakdown at high temperatures. Increased nitrogen demands at higher temperatures may force insects to either consume more plant material to meet these demands or restrict their feeding to a select set of nutritious plant species.  The second experiment sought to determine whether climate change magnifies the negative impact of insect pests on plant health and reproduction. To accomplish this, we grew evening primrose (Oenothera biennis) under current and future temperatures. Japanese beetles (Popillia japonica), a major agricultural pest, were excluded from half of the plants. When grown at current, ambient temperatures, Japanese beetles ate a large number of flowers, resulting in shorter plants with fewer seed pods. However, primrose was able to compensate by filling the remaining seed pods with more, albeit smaller, seeds. This enabled primrose to produce roughly equal numbers of seeds despite heavy defoliation and flower damage caused by Japanese beetles. Under warmed, future conditions, Japanese beetles had little influence on plant health. Plants were generally shorter and produced more flowers and seed pods packed with numerous, small seeds. Primrose grown under warmed conditions therefore outproduced plants grown at ambient temperatures. Interestingly, Japanese beetles had little impact on plant health or reproduction in warmed garden beds, aside from a small increase in the number of seeds. This enabled plants exposed to herbivores to actually outproduce plants protected from herbivores, but only when grown under warmed conditions. Consequently, climate warming may restructure the long-standing relationship between plants and insects.  Our research will shed light on the potential impact of climate change on plant-insect interactions. Such knowledge is important if we are to accurately predict how clima...]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
