<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>NSF East Asia and Pacific Summer Institute (EAPSI) for FY 2013 in Korea</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>06/01/2013</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2014</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>5070.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>5070</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Fellowship Award</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>01090000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>O/D</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Office Of The Director</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>OISE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Office Of Internatl Science &amp;Engineering</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Anne Emig</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>aemig@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927241</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This action funds Alena Mikhaylova of the University of Texas at Arlington to conduct a research project in Engineering during the summer of 2013 at Kyungpook National University in Daegu, Republic of Korea.  The project title is "Effect of Steel Fiber Distribution and Orientation on Mechanical Characteristics of Zero-Slump Concrete." The host scientist is Yeol Choi, Ph.D., P.E.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The application of steel fiber as alternative reinforcement in concrete has gained popularity in recent years due to added ductility and crack control, which leads to more sustainable structures. The proposed research program is aiming to establish the relationship between uniformity of fiber distribution within concrete matrix and material strength in concrete specimens. Quantitative and statistical analyses are being conducted for the representative sample of specimens by counting the number of fibers in a specimen per unit area. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Broader impacts of an EAPSI fellowship include providing the Fellow a first-hand research experience outside the U.S.; an introduction to the science, science policy, and scientific infrastructure of the respective location; and an orientation to the society, culture and language.   These activities meet the NSF goal to educate for international collaborations early in the career of its scientists, engineers, and educators, thus ensuring a globally aware U.S. scientific workforce.  Furthermore, the results of the study conducted at the host institution will be presented at international conferences and related concrete meetings and organizations. The findings will also be submitted as journal manuscripts to the top tier peer reviewed journals such as ACI Structural, ASCE structural and Transportation Research Record.  The results of this study and experience abroad will be presented to the meetings of Society of Women Engineers (SWE) in order to excite other female undergraduate and graduate students to join NSF programs such the EAPSI.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>05/15/2013</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/15/2013</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.079</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1311060</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Alena</FirstName>
<LastName>Mikhaylova</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Alena Mikhaylova</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress/>
<PI_PHON>8172720977</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000631823</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/15/2013</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Mikhaylova              Alena</Name>
<CityName>Grand Prairie</CityName>
<ZipCode>750520619</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber/>
<StreetAddress/>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Texas</StateName>
<StateCode>TX</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>30</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>TX30</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM/>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME/>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Mikhaylova              Alena]]></Name>
<CityName>Grand Prairie</CityName>
<StateCode>TX</StateCode>
<ZipCode>750520619</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Texas</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>30</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>TX30</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7316</Code>
<Text>EAPSI</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>5942</Code>
<Text>KOREA</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>5978</Code>
<Text>EAST ASIA AND PACIFIC PROGRAM</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7316</Code>
<Text>EAPSI</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0113</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2013~5070</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>I have always admired Asian culture and was a big fan of Korean and Japanese cuisine. When I found out about the opportunity to do a research through NSF EAPSI program, without any hesitation I thought I wanted to go to Korea. &nbsp;After submitting an application I impatiently awaited for the results until I finally learned&nbsp;that I was receiving the fellowship. It was amazing, my first trip to an Asian country and I could conduct a research in a unique setting with foreign research team.</p> <p>I immediately started learning basic Korean phrases and read about the cultural differences so that when I arrived I wouldn't feel completely lost. &nbsp;At the same time I started preparing my specimens that I was intending to take with me for the studies.</p> <p>My research on how well steel fiber is distributed in concrete pipe specimens walls was a primary goal. The use of fiber in concrete structures have increasingly gained popularity over the years. Addition or even &nbsp;a complete replacement of conventional steel bars with strong steel fiber may improve the structure's performance by increasing its strength, crack resistance and ductility, in addition steel fiber may eliminate a problem of corrosion that is experienced by so many reinforced concrete structures. Since steel fibers are discontinuous, the corrosion does not spread to the whole structure and is typically contained within one fiber.</p> <p>For the past years I have been studying concrete pipes that are reinforced with steel fibers. Concrete pipes are typically buried underground away from our eyes, however they play an important role in our infrastructure by conveying water from storm, sewage or transporting water to accommodate the agricultural needs. Burying the pipes underground will require them to be strong, so they can support loads from above the ground, such as cars, trains, pavements and sometimes buildings.&nbsp;Steel fiber can provide enough strength to the pipe, however sufficient amount of fiber needs to be added into concrete mix and also fibers need to be distributed evenly, so the pipe doesn't have any weak points. During my prior studies on steel fiber concrete pipes it was found that results of the strength test vary from specimen to specimen for the same fiber content used, thus it was important to investigate fiber distribution in concrete pipe specimens.</p> <p>In my research I &nbsp;wanted to see how well the steel fiber was distributed in different pipe specimens. To conduct research in Korea I first produced several steel fiber reinforced specimens in the United States, thus making sure I was using the same materials and techniques as I have used in my previous research on fiber pipes. From each pipes I extracted several core samples for the studies and have them shipped to Korea.</p> <p>Upon arrival to South Korea I divided each core sample into three pieces to study fiber distribution within each layer. Number of fibers per each layer was counted using imaging technique, by taking an image of each side of the exposed surface and subjecting it to analysis using image processing software.</p> <p>the study suggested that fiber distribution varies within layers and is not uniform within the thickness of the pipe wall for all fiber content. In addition, fiber distribution varies more (more non-uniform) in specimens with smaller content of steel fiber. This revelation was important to know to understand the origin of the scattered results of pipes' strength tests.</p> <p>My fellow researchers from Korean host university helped me every step of the way while I was there. &nbsp;During my stay I was also involved into testing of full scale concrete slabs with openings reinforced with composite fiber beams conducted at the state-of-the-art facility.</p> <p>I became good friends with students in the lab of the hosting university, I got to travel the country with them and other NSF EA...]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ I have always admired Asian culture and was a big fan of Korean and Japanese cuisine. When I found out about the opportunity to do a research through NSF EAPSI program, without any hesitation I thought I wanted to go to Korea.  After submitting an application I impatiently awaited for the results until I finally learned that I was receiving the fellowship. It was amazing, my first trip to an Asian country and I could conduct a research in a unique setting with foreign research team.  I immediately started learning basic Korean phrases and read about the cultural differences so that when I arrived I wouldn't feel completely lost.  At the same time I started preparing my specimens that I was intending to take with me for the studies.  My research on how well steel fiber is distributed in concrete pipe specimens walls was a primary goal. The use of fiber in concrete structures have increasingly gained popularity over the years. Addition or even  a complete replacement of conventional steel bars with strong steel fiber may improve the structure's performance by increasing its strength, crack resistance and ductility, in addition steel fiber may eliminate a problem of corrosion that is experienced by so many reinforced concrete structures. Since steel fibers are discontinuous, the corrosion does not spread to the whole structure and is typically contained within one fiber.  For the past years I have been studying concrete pipes that are reinforced with steel fibers. Concrete pipes are typically buried underground away from our eyes, however they play an important role in our infrastructure by conveying water from storm, sewage or transporting water to accommodate the agricultural needs. Burying the pipes underground will require them to be strong, so they can support loads from above the ground, such as cars, trains, pavements and sometimes buildings. Steel fiber can provide enough strength to the pipe, however sufficient amount of fiber needs to be added into concrete mix and also fibers need to be distributed evenly, so the pipe doesn't have any weak points. During my prior studies on steel fiber concrete pipes it was found that results of the strength test vary from specimen to specimen for the same fiber content used, thus it was important to investigate fiber distribution in concrete pipe specimens.  In my research I  wanted to see how well the steel fiber was distributed in different pipe specimens. To conduct research in Korea I first produced several steel fiber reinforced specimens in the United States, thus making sure I was using the same materials and techniques as I have used in my previous research on fiber pipes. From each pipes I extracted several core samples for the studies and have them shipped to Korea.  Upon arrival to South Korea I divided each core sample into three pieces to study fiber distribution within each layer. Number of fibers per each layer was counted using imaging technique, by taking an image of each side of the exposed surface and subjecting it to analysis using image processing software.  the study suggested that fiber distribution varies within layers and is not uniform within the thickness of the pipe wall for all fiber content. In addition, fiber distribution varies more (more non-uniform) in specimens with smaller content of steel fiber. This revelation was important to know to understand the origin of the scattered results of pipes' strength tests.  My fellow researchers from Korean host university helped me every step of the way while I was there.  During my stay I was also involved into testing of full scale concrete slabs with openings reinforced with composite fiber beams conducted at the state-of-the-art facility.  I became good friends with students in the lab of the hosting university, I got to travel the country with them and other NSF EAPSI fellows, I got to stay with a Korean family who lived in a traditional Korean house, I experienced unforgettable temple stay and Korean spiri...]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
