<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>DISSERTATION RESEARCH: Predicting Plant Life-Cycles in Changing Environments</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>05/15/2013</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>04/30/2016</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>20402.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>20402</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>08010208</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>BIO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DEB</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Environmental Biology</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Douglas Levey</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>dlevey@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032925196</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>A critical goal in ecology is to predict how organisms will respond to altered climate. Since responses to temperature differ at different stages in the development of most plants and animals, one must investigate these responses in each life stage. For plants, the environment that each life stage is exposed to is determined by the timing of germination, reproduction, and seed dispersal. Plants can use environmental cues such as temperature, moisture, and day length to time these developmental transitions so that life stages occur during favorable times of year. For example, temperature during seed maturation can influence the level of seed dormancy, and the timing and duration of seed maturation can determine the seasonal conditions during seed dispersal. However, little is known about how the environment during seed development affects plant life cycles. This project will provide empirical estimates of the environmental sensitivities to temperature of seed dispersal, dormancy, and germination in the plant Arabidopsis thaliana, and incorporate these estimates into linked models to predict when a plant will be in each of its life stages when exposed to a particular regime of temperature. Experiments in the field and in growth chambers will characterize how variable temperatures during seed maturation alter dormancy level, levels of gene expression of a key dormancy gene, and the timing of seed dispersal. The experiments will provide critical information on the least understood phase of the life cycle of annual plants. Integrating these data into the life-cycle model will improve predictions of organismal responses to changing climates.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This research is important to society because accurately predictions of life-cycle timing in plants will be necessary to anticipate the ecological consequences of global warming, and to manage weeds and other invasive species as plant ranges expand across landscapes. The project will also contribute to the scientific training of a Ph.D. student and three undergraduate, and to educational outreach through the creation of an interactive teaching module for undergraduate and high school students.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>05/07/2013</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/07/2013</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.074</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1311406</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Kathleen</FirstName>
<LastName>Donohue</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Kathleen Donohue</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>k.donohue@duke.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>9196137467</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000196329</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/07/2013</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Liana</FirstName>
<LastName>Burghardt</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Liana Burghardt</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>ltb6@duke.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>9196843030</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000633464</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/07/2013</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Duke University</Name>
<CityName>Durham</CityName>
<ZipCode>277054010</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>9196843030</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>2200 W. Main St, Suite 710</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[Erwin Square]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>North Carolina</StateName>
<StateCode>NC</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NC01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>044387793</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>DUKE UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>044387793</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Duke University]]></Name>
<CityName>Durham</CityName>
<StateCode>NC</StateCode>
<ZipCode>277080338</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[Science Drive]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>North Carolina</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NC04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1182</Code>
<Text>POP &amp; COMMUNITY ECOL PROG</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0113</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2013~20402</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>In the near future, humans will need to adapt agricultural and conservation practices to account for the changing climate context in which organisms will find themselves. The work undertaken by L. Burghardt that was funded by this doctoral improvement grant illustrates a framework for understanding adaptation and response to climate of a model organism. The long&shy; term goal is to apply these same techniques to understanding adaptation of species that are important for agriculture or conservation reasons.&nbsp;</p> <p>It has long been known that both genetic variation and environmental conditions have profound effects on phenotypes, but evolutionary ecologists have struggled with how to quantify and predict the two effects simultaneously. The developmental threshold models that we built for the model organism <em>A. thaliana</em> describe this relationship in a novel way and offers a way to predict complex phenotypes in complex environments.</p> <p>This integrated life cycle model addresses many long standing goals in the fields of evolutionary ecology and genetics. First, it predicts complex life&shy;history variation across a geographic range, which can be useful for predicting the behavior of introduced organisms. In addition, it can be applied to predicting changes in life history in response to climate change. Secondly, this approach quantifies the effect of genetic changes in specific life&shy; history stages, such as germination or flowering, on overall life histories in specific environments. In particular, our work has highlighted the importance of seed dormancy for life cycle determination in this species and explains the empirical observation of latitudinal and altitudinal clines in seed dormancy. It thereby has the potential to identify key physiological traits of organisms that influence their life cycles in diverse environments.</p> <p>Lastly, this method allows prediction how the timing of one life stage can influence the timing of other life-stage transitions. Correlations between say germination and flowering time have long been observed in field experiments. These correlations can be due to a gene having a direct effect on two life stage transitions. Alternatively these correlations could be due to the fact that changing the timing of germination changes the environmental conditions that determine the timing of flowering. To our knowledge, no other method can explore the relationship between life-stage transitions in this way.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 05/11/2016<br>      Modified by: Kathleen&nbsp;Donohue</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ In the near future, humans will need to adapt agricultural and conservation practices to account for the changing climate context in which organisms will find themselves. The work undertaken by L. Burghardt that was funded by this doctoral improvement grant illustrates a framework for understanding adaptation and response to climate of a model organism. The long&shy; term goal is to apply these same techniques to understanding adaptation of species that are important for agriculture or conservation reasons.   It has long been known that both genetic variation and environmental conditions have profound effects on phenotypes, but evolutionary ecologists have struggled with how to quantify and predict the two effects simultaneously. The developmental threshold models that we built for the model organism A. thaliana describe this relationship in a novel way and offers a way to predict complex phenotypes in complex environments.  This integrated life cycle model addresses many long standing goals in the fields of evolutionary ecology and genetics. First, it predicts complex life&shy;history variation across a geographic range, which can be useful for predicting the behavior of introduced organisms. In addition, it can be applied to predicting changes in life history in response to climate change. Secondly, this approach quantifies the effect of genetic changes in specific life&shy; history stages, such as germination or flowering, on overall life histories in specific environments. In particular, our work has highlighted the importance of seed dormancy for life cycle determination in this species and explains the empirical observation of latitudinal and altitudinal clines in seed dormancy. It thereby has the potential to identify key physiological traits of organisms that influence their life cycles in diverse environments.  Lastly, this method allows prediction how the timing of one life stage can influence the timing of other life-stage transitions. Correlations between say germination and flowering time have long been observed in field experiments. These correlations can be due to a gene having a direct effect on two life stage transitions. Alternatively these correlations could be due to the fact that changing the timing of germination changes the environmental conditions that determine the timing of flowering. To our knowledge, no other method can explore the relationship between life-stage transitions in this way.          Last Modified: 05/11/2016       Submitted by: Kathleen Donohue]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
