<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Materials World Network:   Project Summary Disorder Tuned Quantum Phases in Topological Insulators</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2013</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>410000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>410000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03070000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DMR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Materials Research</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Tomasz Durakiewicz</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>tdurakie@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924892</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>TECHNICAL SUMMARY:&lt;br/&gt;In the last few years there has been an explosive development in materials science. It began with the theoretical prediction of a new class of three dimensional (3D) topological insulators (TIs) which are fully gapped in the bulk, and with unusual gapless protected 2D Dirac surface states. This protection arises from the linear energy-momentum dispersion, with the surface states near the Fermi surface residing on a single Dirac cone. If realized, these systems could be the Holy Grail in the fields of spintronics and fault-tolerant quantum computing. However, access to this 2D quantum matter is a challenge, owing to the difficulty of separating surface contribution from the finite conductivity of the bulk. In this MWN project supported by the Division of Materials Research, swift (~ MeV range) electron and / or proton beams will be utilized to create controlled disorder by (a) tuning the bulk carrier density and Fermi level across the Dirac point, and (b) reducing bulk conductivity by forcing Anderson localization. The former will result in charge compensation in a bulk TI. The later will test recent theoretical ideas of Quantized Anomalous Hall Effect (QAHE) and, even more remarkably, (c) test a recent prediction of a Topological Anderson Insulator - a nontrivial quantum phase with quantized conductance obtained by introducing disorder in a metal with strong spin-orbit interaction. Determining the precise dose at which this occurs should establish a new large-scale route to achieving intrinsic quantum transport of the topological surfaces states.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;NON-TECHNICAL SUMMARY:&lt;br/&gt;The ability to control the quantum mechanical properties of materials is one of the forefront challenges for material scientists and condensed matter physicists. In the past few decades several bottom-up approaches striving to engineer new materials (thereby controlling their properties) at the atomic level have been devised to achieve this goal. In this proposal a top-down material modification approach will be utilized in which a controlled amount of defects will be introduced to alter the electrical properties of topological insulators (TI's) - a newly discovered class of materials which promises to offer a robust platform for quantum computing. Owing to the unique properties of TI's disorder introduced by particle irradiation will only affect the unwanted / parasitic electrical properties of these materials, while simultaneously enhancing the desired quantum properties that will foster the realization of revolutionary electronic devices and the synthesis of novel states of matter.  &lt;br/&gt;This proposal is an international collaboration between the condensed matter physics group of the PI at The City College of New York (CCNY) - CUNY, and groups at Ecolé Polytechnique in Palaiseau, France, with unique expertise in swift particle irradiation techniques and advanced optical spectroscopy. This collaboration combines the complementary technical strengths of materials science with particle beam technology to control and tune key electronic properties of the newly discovered functional materials class. CCNY is a federally recognized minority serving institution. Ecole Polytechnique is one of the leading institutes of higher education in France, with a decidedly international outlook. The research program will have a great educational impact on the students involved, both graduate and undergraduate, for it will facilitate international visits and exchanges that will broaden their educational range and provide training in a wide spectrum of materials synthesis and experimental characterization techniques in a collaborative spirit.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>09/05/2013</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>09/05/2013</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1312483</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Lia</FirstName>
<LastName>Krusin-Elbaum</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Lia Krusin-Elbaum</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>krusin@sci.ccny.cuny.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2126505418</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000579114</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/05/2013</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>CUNY City College</Name>
<CityName>New York</CityName>
<ZipCode>100319101</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2126505418</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>Convent Ave at 138th St</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>13</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NY13</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>603503991</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>RESEARCH FOUNDATION OF THE CITY UNIVERSITY OF NEW YORK</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>073268849</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[CUNY City College]]></Name>
<CityName>New York</CityName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<ZipCode>100319101</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[160 Convent Avenue]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>13</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NY13</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7222</Code>
<Text>XC-Crosscutting Activities Pro</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7488</Code>
<Text>MATERIALS WORLD NETWORK</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0113</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2013~410000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><strong><span>Overview:</span></strong><span class="fontstyle0"><span>&nbsp;Topological Dirac insulators and metals belong to a remarkable class of quantum solids where&nbsp;distinct electronic band structure with the relativistic Dirac spectrum is undergirding novel&nbsp;quantum phenomena that include quantized anomalous and spin Hall effects and dissipationless transport of charge associated with such states. Two-dimensional (2D) materials and van&nbsp;der Waals layers, in which electronic band structure and topological effects can be tuned by&nbsp;doping and/or stacking them into hybrid hetero-structures, are particularly amenable to&nbsp;exploration, since they can be assembled by mechanical exfoliation. Such systems can display&nbsp;a plethora of surprising emergent properties not associated with the 3D parent systems. They&nbsp;can, for example, host complex orders such as exotic 2D superconductivity or 2D spin textures,&nbsp;switchable bandgaps, tunable two-dimensional electron gases (2DEG), or topologically&nbsp;protected spin-helical surface states in 3D topological insulators (TIs) &ndash; all with a potentially&nbsp;disruptive impact on charge- and spin-based and opto-electronics, and information processing.</span></span><span>&nbsp;</span></p> <p><strong><span>Intellectual merit:</span></strong><span class="fontstyle0"><span>&nbsp;The aim of the work under the international collaborative MWN project of CCNY with LSI at&nbsp;&Eacute;cole Polytechnique, France, is to understand the effects of disorder on quantum states of&nbsp;topological insulators (TIs) by implementing particle irradiation and other techniques to install&nbsp;disorder in a controlled way. Our key previous achievements have been demonstration of&nbsp;robust quantum transport on topological surfaces using irradiation with high-energy (2.5 MeV)&nbsp;electron beams, with atomic structure and electronic Dirac spectrum of surface states&nbsp;remaining intact (</span></span><span class="fontstyle2"><em><span>Nature Comm</span></em></span><span class="fontstyle2"><span>.&nbsp;</span></span><span class="fontstyle3"><strong><span>7</span></strong></span><span class="fontstyle0"><span>, 10957 (2016)), and controlling interfacial charge transfer&nbsp;(</span></span><span class="fontstyle2"><em><span>Nano Lett.&nbsp;</span></em></span><span class="fontstyle0"><span>2015 and 2016).</span></span><span>&nbsp;</span></p> <p><span class="fontstyle0"><span>This year&rsquo;s central result is our discovery of a robust Quantized Anomalous Hall Conductance&nbsp;(QAHC) of precisely one conductance quantum&nbsp;</span></span><span class="fontstyle2"><span>G</span></span><span class="fontstyle0"><span>0&nbsp;= e2/</span></span><span class="fontstyle2"><span>h&nbsp;</span></span><span class="fontstyle0"><span>in&nbsp;</span></span><span class="fontstyle2"><span>bulk (hundreds of QLs) crystals&nbsp;</span></span><span class="fontstyle0"><span>with only 2 at% of magnetic (Mn) dopants at the highest temperature yet (several Kelvin). The&nbsp;discovery was possible through fine-tuning the Fermi level (</span></span><span class="fontstyle2"><span>E</span></span><span class="fontstyle0"><span>F) into the Dirac gap with thermal&nbsp;processing in vacuum we developed to reposition Mn dopants, and by our previously&nbsp;demonstrated high-energy irradiation technique.&nbsp;</span></span><span>&nbsp;</span></p> <p><strong><span>Broader impacts:</span></strong><span class="fontstyle0"><span>&nbsp;Our finding opens new pathways to achieve tunable dissipationless&nbsp;transport in quantum Hall systems and&nbsp;</span></span><span>may serve as a platform for achieving proximal chiral <span>superconductivity in 2D hybrid&nbsp;</span>nanostructures</span>.&nbsp;CCNY is a minority serving institution. This international collaboration opened incredibly valuable scientific and cultural horizons to our students, especially to the interning undergrads. It gave our graduate students the opportunity to visit first-class international research institutions, where it exposed the students to a richness of new approaches and techniques that&nbsp;would be unavailable to them&nbsp;otherwise.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 11/15/2018<br>      Modified by: Lia&nbsp;Krusin-Elbaum</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Overview: Topological Dirac insulators and metals belong to a remarkable class of quantum solids where distinct electronic band structure with the relativistic Dirac spectrum is undergirding novel quantum phenomena that include quantized anomalous and spin Hall effects and dissipationless transport of charge associated with such states. Two-dimensional (2D) materials and van der Waals layers, in which electronic band structure and topological effects can be tuned by doping and/or stacking them into hybrid hetero-structures, are particularly amenable to exploration, since they can be assembled by mechanical exfoliation. Such systems can display a plethora of surprising emergent properties not associated with the 3D parent systems. They can, for example, host complex orders such as exotic 2D superconductivity or 2D spin textures, switchable bandgaps, tunable two-dimensional electron gases (2DEG), or topologically protected spin-helical surface states in 3D topological insulators (TIs) &ndash; all with a potentially disruptive impact on charge- and spin-based and opto-electronics, and information processing.   Intellectual merit: The aim of the work under the international collaborative MWN project of CCNY with LSI at &Eacute;cole Polytechnique, France, is to understand the effects of disorder on quantum states of topological insulators (TIs) by implementing particle irradiation and other techniques to install disorder in a controlled way. Our key previous achievements have been demonstration of robust quantum transport on topological surfaces using irradiation with high-energy (2.5 MeV) electron beams, with atomic structure and electronic Dirac spectrum of surface states remaining intact (Nature Comm. 7, 10957 (2016)), and controlling interfacial charge transfer (Nano Lett. 2015 and 2016).   This year?s central result is our discovery of a robust Quantized Anomalous Hall Conductance (QAHC) of precisely one conductance quantum G0 = e2/h in bulk (hundreds of QLs) crystals with only 2 at% of magnetic (Mn) dopants at the highest temperature yet (several Kelvin). The discovery was possible through fine-tuning the Fermi level (EF) into the Dirac gap with thermal processing in vacuum we developed to reposition Mn dopants, and by our previously demonstrated high-energy irradiation technique.    Broader impacts: Our finding opens new pathways to achieve tunable dissipationless transport in quantum Hall systems and may serve as a platform for achieving proximal chiral superconductivity in 2D hybrid nanostructures. CCNY is a minority serving institution. This international collaboration opened incredibly valuable scientific and cultural horizons to our students, especially to the interning undergrads. It gave our graduate students the opportunity to visit first-class international research institutions, where it exposed the students to a richness of new approaches and techniques that would be unavailable to them otherwise.          Last Modified: 11/15/2018       Submitted by: Lia Krusin-Elbaum]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
