<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Experiments in Magnetohydrodynamic and Hydrodynamic Instabilities of Astrophysical Interest</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/15/2013</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>487630.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>487630</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03020000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>AST</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Astronomical Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Nigel Sharp</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>nsharp@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924905</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Efficient dissipation of the orbital energy of plasma occurs in accretion disks ranging from those in which planets form around protostars, to those around supermassive black holes in active galactic nuclei.  Two mechanisms have been proposed for the turbulence that drives dissipation and angular-momentum transport in such disks: (1) a linear instability of magnetized and electrically conducting flow known as magnetorotational instability (MRI); and (2) nonlinear hydrodynamic shear-flow instability.  Two experiments are running at Princeton: the Liquid-Metal experiment studies MRI and related magnetohydrodynamic (MHD) instabilities, while the Hydrodynamic Turbulence Experiment studies nonlinear hydrodynamic transitions.  Recently, the MHD experiment has demonstrated robust nonaxisymmetric Shercliff-layer instabilities in strong axial magnetic fields, paving a clear path towards a first conclusive demonstration of MRI in the laboratory.  The present contribution to this research will focus on experimental studies of the following questions: (1) Why are quasi-keplerian flows resistant to turbulence? and (2) How do MRI, Shercliff-layer instabilities, and other MHD activity, drive angular momentum transport?  This requires adding crucial diagnostics for direct global torque measurements, measuring local Reynolds and Maxwell stresses in the liquid-metal flow; and making critical hardware improvements to increase and control rotation speeds.  This research will educate the next generation of scientists and forge links with neighboring disciplines such as geophysics, fluid dynamics, and plasma physics, while advancing laboratory astrophysics generally.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>09/16/2013</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/27/2018</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1312463</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Jeremy</FirstName>
<LastName>Goodman</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Jeremy Goodman</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>jeremy@astro.princeton.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6092583586</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000476737</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/16/2013</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Hantao</FirstName>
<LastName>Ji</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Hantao Ji</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>hji@pppl.gov</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6092432162</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000339095</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/16/2013</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Princeton University</Name>
<CityName>Princeton</CityName>
<ZipCode>085442020</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6092583090</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>Off. of Research &amp; Proj. Admin.</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[P.O. Box 36]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New Jersey</StateName>
<StateCode>NJ</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>12</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NJ12</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>002484665</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>TRUSTEES OF PRINCETON UNIVERSITY, THE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>002484665</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Princeton University]]></Name>
<CityName>Princeton</CityName>
<StateCode>NJ</StateCode>
<ZipCode>085441001</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[4 Ivy Lane]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New Jersey</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>12</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NJ12</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1217</Code>
<Text>EXTRAGALACTIC ASTRON &amp; COSMOLO</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1205</Code>
<Text>LABORATORY ASTROPHYSICS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1206</Code>
<Text>THEORETICAL &amp; COMPUTATIONAL ASTROPHYSICS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0113</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2013~487630</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>This project was part of an effort to demonstrate magnetorotational instability (MRI) via a laboratory experiment. Astronomers believe that MRI causes turbulence and flow (accretion) onto the central object of various astronomical disks, including the disks in which planets form around young stars, and also those surrounding supermassive black holes in quasars. &nbsp;While the basic instability is well understood theoretically and via computer simulations, it has never been directly observed in space or in the lab. &nbsp;Thus the primary intellectual merit of this project is to make such an observation, and secondarily, to pave the way for more ambitious future experiments that will show MRI in its nonlinear, turbulent state, which is not well understood and which remains difficult to simulate without issues surrounding numerical resolution and other sources of error. &nbsp;The broader impact is to further the still nascent field of laboratory astrophysical magnetohydrodynamics.</p> <p>The essential ingredients for MRI are a differentially rotating and electrically conducting fluid (a liquid, gas, or plasma), and a magnetic field threading the fluid. &nbsp;The instability feeds upon the rotation, which is more rapid for mass elements closer to the central body or rotation axis. &nbsp;It relies on the ``donkey principle": a sufficiently weak retarding force causes orbiting mass elements to move closer to the axis and to orbit more rapidly, while a weak propulsive force has the opposite effects. &nbsp;By this principle, two satellites orbiting the Earth, if connected by a weak elastic tether, would move apart, one to a lower and faster orbit, and the other to a higher and slower one. &nbsp;In MRI, the magnetic field plays the role of the tether; the orbiting gas/fluid must be a good electrical conductor to "grasp" the field and stretch it. &nbsp;Our group has previously demonstrated experimentally that rapid rotation alone (of the type relevant to astronomical disks) is insufficient for instability or turbulence without magnetic field.</p> <p>The laboratory Taylor-Couette apparatus (diagrammed in the first figure) involves a room-temperature liquid-metal gallium alloy confined between concentric rotating cylinders and subjected to magnetic fields up to ten thousand times stronger than the Earth's. &nbsp;With the help of these NSF funds, the apparatus was upgraded to drive the rotation of the fluid more strongly and more controllably, to improve diagnostics (since the liquid metal is opaque, the flow is measured via magnetic and ultrasound sensors rather than cameras), and to explore systematically a range of rotation rates and magnetic field strengths, as summarized in the second figure. &nbsp;Instabilities were found,characterized, and published. &nbsp;But since there are at least two other types of instability that occur in this experiment, an unambiguous signature of MRI has yet to be demonstrated. The effort continues with other funds.</p> <p>The funds provided by NSF went principally to support a postdoctoral researcher, who carried out much of the work necessary to ``shake down" and use the main experimental apparatus. &nbsp;But several graduate students, summer undergraduate interns, and even high-school students were involved in ancillary tasks. &nbsp;These included computer simulations of the experiment, helping to take data, and performing an MRI-analog experiment involving a mass-spring system embedded in unmagnetized hydrodynamic flow.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 11/30/2019<br>      Modified by: Jeremy&nbsp;Goodman</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Images (<span id="selectedPhoto0">1</span> of <span class="totalNumber"></span>)           </div> <div class="galControls" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1312463/1312463_10280812_1575139102757_apparatus_drawing--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1312463/1312463_10280812_1575139102757_apparatus_drawing--rgov-800width.jpg" title="MRI apparatus"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1312463/1312463_10280812_1575139102757_apparatus_drawing--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="MRI apparatus"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">A CAD drawing of the apparatus.  Inner cylinder is shown in black where it contacts the fluid; outer cylinder is not shown. Gray encaps above and below the fluid, separated by 28 cm, are made of copper and divided into rings, the inner of which rotates independently of the cylinders.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Princeton MRI Experiment</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Royalty-free (unrestricted use)</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Jeremy&nbsp;Goodman</div> <div class="imageTitle">MRI apparatus</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1312463/1312463_10280812_1575143441852_BubblePlot--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1312463/1312463_10280812_1575143441852_BubblePlot--rgov-800width.jpg" title="parameter space"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1312463/1312463_10280812_1575143441852_BubblePlot--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="parameter space"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Axes: inner-cylinder rotation rate (vertical) vs. applied magnetic field (horizontal).  Black dots show theoretical rate of growth of MRI; blue curve is stabilityboundary.  Colored points are experimental measurements, with size proportional to strength of disturbance.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Princeton MRI Experiment</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyright owner is an institution with an existing agreement allowing use by NSF</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Jeremy&nbsp;Goodman</div> <div class="imageTitle">parameter space</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ This project was part of an effort to demonstrate magnetorotational instability (MRI) via a laboratory experiment. Astronomers believe that MRI causes turbulence and flow (accretion) onto the central object of various astronomical disks, including the disks in which planets form around young stars, and also those surrounding supermassive black holes in quasars.  While the basic instability is well understood theoretically and via computer simulations, it has never been directly observed in space or in the lab.  Thus the primary intellectual merit of this project is to make such an observation, and secondarily, to pave the way for more ambitious future experiments that will show MRI in its nonlinear, turbulent state, which is not well understood and which remains difficult to simulate without issues surrounding numerical resolution and other sources of error.  The broader impact is to further the still nascent field of laboratory astrophysical magnetohydrodynamics.  The essential ingredients for MRI are a differentially rotating and electrically conducting fluid (a liquid, gas, or plasma), and a magnetic field threading the fluid.  The instability feeds upon the rotation, which is more rapid for mass elements closer to the central body or rotation axis.  It relies on the ``donkey principle": a sufficiently weak retarding force causes orbiting mass elements to move closer to the axis and to orbit more rapidly, while a weak propulsive force has the opposite effects.  By this principle, two satellites orbiting the Earth, if connected by a weak elastic tether, would move apart, one to a lower and faster orbit, and the other to a higher and slower one.  In MRI, the magnetic field plays the role of the tether; the orbiting gas/fluid must be a good electrical conductor to "grasp" the field and stretch it.  Our group has previously demonstrated experimentally that rapid rotation alone (of the type relevant to astronomical disks) is insufficient for instability or turbulence without magnetic field.  The laboratory Taylor-Couette apparatus (diagrammed in the first figure) involves a room-temperature liquid-metal gallium alloy confined between concentric rotating cylinders and subjected to magnetic fields up to ten thousand times stronger than the Earth's.  With the help of these NSF funds, the apparatus was upgraded to drive the rotation of the fluid more strongly and more controllably, to improve diagnostics (since the liquid metal is opaque, the flow is measured via magnetic and ultrasound sensors rather than cameras), and to explore systematically a range of rotation rates and magnetic field strengths, as summarized in the second figure.  Instabilities were found,characterized, and published.  But since there are at least two other types of instability that occur in this experiment, an unambiguous signature of MRI has yet to be demonstrated. The effort continues with other funds.  The funds provided by NSF went principally to support a postdoctoral researcher, who carried out much of the work necessary to ``shake down" and use the main experimental apparatus.  But several graduate students, summer undergraduate interns, and even high-school students were involved in ancillary tasks.  These included computer simulations of the experiment, helping to take data, and performing an MRI-analog experiment involving a mass-spring system embedded in unmagnetized hydrodynamic flow.          Last Modified: 11/30/2019       Submitted by: Jeremy Goodman]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
