<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>AIR Option 2:  Research Alliance Situational Intelligence for Smart Grid Optimization and Intelligent Control</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>05/01/2013</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2020</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>690666.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>971770</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07070000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>IIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Industrial Innovation &amp; Partnersh</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Jesus Soriano Molla</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>jsoriano@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927795</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This PFI: AIR Research Alliance project focuses on the translation and transfer of situational intelligence and intelligent control technologies to fill real-time modern power system operation technology gaps.  A utility-like control center will be developed at Clemson University to demonstrate these technologies and for rapid prototyping of real-time technologies for smart grid control centers. The technologies have the following market-valued features: scalability, systems-thinking approach, and grid intelligence that will increase real-time responsiveness to variable and uncertain generation, changing power loads and component failures, improve the dynamic and transient behavior of the power network, improve grid reliability, ensure local and wide area stability, reduce greenhouse gas emissions, and assist human experts in control centers to respond quickly in a reliable and secure manner compared to the leading competing technologies in situational awareness and control center energy management systems (EMSs) in this market domain.  &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The project accomplishes this transfer to the market by developing situational intelligence systems and intelligent dynamic stochastic optimal power flow control for electric power control centers resulting in creation of new jobs in smart-grid analytics and modern power system operations, commercial products including intelligent EMSs for control  centers, and intelligent decision-making and control tools with the potential to license, generate royalties, and sustain an innovation eco-system for developing leading-edge modern power system control center applications that will  result in spinoffs.  &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The partnership engaged to transfer the technologies to the market domain include independent research laboratories and small businesses who will contribute to the development of the technology, control center platform vendors  who will integrate the technology, and utilities that will test out the technology.  The potential economic impact is expected to be in several millions of dollars in the next five years, which will contribute to the U.S. competitiveness in the maximum penetration of variable and uncertain generation with enhanced control center operations capability.  The societal impact, both short and long term, addresses national needs, especially for highly interconnected power system, in terms of sustainability, security, and reliability. Our nation's critical infrastructures depend on the electricity infrastructure to be reliable, secure and efficient. Situational intelligence and intelligent control for the electric power grid allows for: mitigation or even prevention of blackouts - billions of dollars saving in losses; high levels of renewable energy penetration; softening of negative effects of the climate change on the economy; minimization of impacts and rapid recovery from natural disasters such as earthquakes, hurricanes and malicious attacks.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>04/28/2013</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>01/23/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1312260</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Ganesh</FirstName>
<LastName>Venayagamoorthy</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>K</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Ganesh K Venayagamoorthy</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>gkumar@ieee.org</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>8646565936</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000492539</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/28/2013</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Clemson University</Name>
<CityName>CLEMSON</CityName>
<ZipCode>296345701</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>8646562424</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>230 Kappa Street</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[Suite 200]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>South Carolina</StateName>
<StateCode>SC</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>SC03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>042629816</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>CLEMSON UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>042629816</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Clemson University]]></Name>
<CityName>Clemson</CityName>
<StateCode>SC</StateCode>
<ZipCode>296340001</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>South Carolina</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>SC03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>101y</Code>
<Text/>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1504</Code>
<Text>GOALI-Grnt Opp Acad Lia wIndus</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1662</Code>
<Text>PFI-Partnrships for Innovation</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>8019</Code>
<Text>Accelerating Innovation Rsrch</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>019Z</Code>
<Text>Grad Prep APG:Enhan. Experience</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>115E</Code>
<Text>RESEARCH EXP FOR TEACHERS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>116E</Code>
<Text>RESEARCH EXP FOR UNDERGRADS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1662</Code>
<Text>PARTNRSHIPS FOR INNOVATION-PFI</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7218</Code>
<Text>RET SUPP-Res Exp for Tchr Supp</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7233</Code>
<Text>RES EXPERIENCE FOR TEACHERS(RET)-SUPPLEM</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8019</Code>
<Text>Accelerating Innovation Rsrch</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8032</Code>
<Text>Software Services and Applications</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8808</Code>
<Text>Veterans Research Supplements</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9231</Code>
<Text>SUPPL FOR UNDERGRAD RES ASSIST</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9251</Code>
<Text>REU SUPP-Res Exp for Ugrd Supp</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0113</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0115</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0116</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0119</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>40XX</Code>
<Name>NSF TRUST FUND</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>048960</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2013~831997</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2015~6000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2016~10000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2019~123773</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>A scalable technology for the development of situational intelligence system and intelligent dynamicstochastic optimal power flow (DSOPF) control for electric power control centers was proposed. A new computational method based on D-layered, N-dimensional cellular computational network was developed and patented for situational intelligence and DSOPF. Situational intelligence here refers to situational awareness with predictions into the near-future. The advances were in the development of a scalable computational method to deal with big data in real-time and development of the next generation situational intelligence for smart electric power system operations and controls. The development of situational intelligence and DSOPF from a computational systems thinking perspective for power systems is novel. New algorithms and architectures for situational intelligence and DSOPF increases real-time responsiveness to variable and uncertain generation, changing power loads and component failures, improve the dynamic and transient behavior of the power network, improve grid reliability, ensure local and wide area stability, reduce greenhouse gas emissions and assist human experts in control centers to respond fast in a reliable andsecure manner. Real-time demonstration of a situational intelligence system for a smart power system with synchronized measurements was carried out on a real-time digital simulator, a high speed computing platform&nbsp; to assist in the transfer of proposed research to the electric power industry. A utility-like control center was developed to demonstrate these technologies andfor rapid prototyping of real-time control center technologies.</p> <p>This PFI: AIR project made significant impact on national needs, especially for the highly interconnected power system, interms of sustainability, security, and reliability. Our nation&rsquo;s critical infrastructures depend on the electricity infrastructure to be reliable, secure and efficient. Situational intelligence and intelligent control for the electric power grid allows for: mitigation or even prevention of blackouts &ndash; billions of dollars saving in losses; high levels of renewable energy penetration; minimal impacts and rapid recovery from natural disasters such as earthquakes, hurricanes and malicious attacks.Underrepresented minority students and female students from ECE were recruited to participate in the research, innovative and entrepreneurial activities of this proposal. The innovations of this project was disseminated through presentations, tutorials and papers at local,national and international seminars, conferences and workshops. Results were also published in highly reputed journals such as IEEE Transactions. The PI is the Chair of the IEEE PES working group on Intelligent Control Systems and IEEE CIS Task Force on Smart Grid among other professional society leadership positions. All these avenues were used to disseminate the findings of this proposal.&nbsp;</p> <p>In summary: Seven&nbsp;PhD degree students, one MS degree student and one MEng student have been graduated. Five other PhD degree students are in progress. 29 journal refereed papers and 103 conference refereed papers have been published to date from the findings of the project. Two patents have been granted (US 9,778,629 and US 9,507,367 B2). Six tutorials have been presented locally, nationally and internationally. 14 Plenary/Keynote talks have been presented locally, nationally and internationally. 39 Panel talks have been presented locally, nationally and internationally. 49 invited lectures and seminars have been presented locally, nationally andinternationally. Over ten undergraduate research students have been trained in topics related to the fields of Electrical Engineering, Computer Engineering, and Computer Science. Pilot implementation of some of technologies have been carried out in the electric utility environment.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 07/16/2021<br>      Modified by: Ganesh&nbsp;K&nbsp;Venayagamoorthy</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ A scalable technology for the development of situational intelligence system and intelligent dynamicstochastic optimal power flow (DSOPF) control for electric power control centers was proposed. A new computational method based on D-layered, N-dimensional cellular computational network was developed and patented for situational intelligence and DSOPF. Situational intelligence here refers to situational awareness with predictions into the near-future. The advances were in the development of a scalable computational method to deal with big data in real-time and development of the next generation situational intelligence for smart electric power system operations and controls. The development of situational intelligence and DSOPF from a computational systems thinking perspective for power systems is novel. New algorithms and architectures for situational intelligence and DSOPF increases real-time responsiveness to variable and uncertain generation, changing power loads and component failures, improve the dynamic and transient behavior of the power network, improve grid reliability, ensure local and wide area stability, reduce greenhouse gas emissions and assist human experts in control centers to respond fast in a reliable andsecure manner. Real-time demonstration of a situational intelligence system for a smart power system with synchronized measurements was carried out on a real-time digital simulator, a high speed computing platform  to assist in the transfer of proposed research to the electric power industry. A utility-like control center was developed to demonstrate these technologies andfor rapid prototyping of real-time control center technologies.  This PFI: AIR project made significant impact on national needs, especially for the highly interconnected power system, interms of sustainability, security, and reliability. Our nation’s critical infrastructures depend on the electricity infrastructure to be reliable, secure and efficient. Situational intelligence and intelligent control for the electric power grid allows for: mitigation or even prevention of blackouts &ndash; billions of dollars saving in losses; high levels of renewable energy penetration; minimal impacts and rapid recovery from natural disasters such as earthquakes, hurricanes and malicious attacks.Underrepresented minority students and female students from ECE were recruited to participate in the research, innovative and entrepreneurial activities of this proposal. The innovations of this project was disseminated through presentations, tutorials and papers at local,national and international seminars, conferences and workshops. Results were also published in highly reputed journals such as IEEE Transactions. The PI is the Chair of the IEEE PES working group on Intelligent Control Systems and IEEE CIS Task Force on Smart Grid among other professional society leadership positions. All these avenues were used to disseminate the findings of this proposal.   In summary: Seven PhD degree students, one MS degree student and one MEng student have been graduated. Five other PhD degree students are in progress. 29 journal refereed papers and 103 conference refereed papers have been published to date from the findings of the project. Two patents have been granted (US 9,778,629 and US 9,507,367 B2). Six tutorials have been presented locally, nationally and internationally. 14 Plenary/Keynote talks have been presented locally, nationally and internationally. 39 Panel talks have been presented locally, nationally and internationally. 49 invited lectures and seminars have been presented locally, nationally andinternationally. Over ten undergraduate research students have been trained in topics related to the fields of Electrical Engineering, Computer Engineering, and Computer Science. Pilot implementation of some of technologies have been carried out in the electric utility environment.             Last Modified: 07/16/2021       Submitted by: Ganesh K Venayagamoorthy]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
