<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>RUI: The Hydrodynamics and Observational Signatures of Binary Mergers</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2013</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>231312.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>231312</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03020000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>AST</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Astronomical Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Hans Krimm</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>hkrimm@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922761</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>A large variety of interesting astrophysical objects and systems are thought to pass through a contact or semidetached binary stage. The ultimate outcomes of such evolution include exotica such as binary neutron stars, planetary nebulae with double degenerate cores, ultracompact X-ray binaries, and blue stragglers. In a contact binary system, the two components orbit within a larger common envelope and maintain physical contact, while in a semidetached binary, one star gradually accretes mass from a companion overflowing its Roche lobe. In either case, one or both binary components can expand on a stellar evolution timescale, often causing the binary to become unstable and merge. If the binary components have degenerate cores, the cores can separately survive the merger to form systems with binary compact objects. Regardless of the parent stars, the merger of a binary can result in so-called mergebursts, characterized by a sudden and drastic observed increase in luminosity and by ejecta streaming away from the merger product. Making use of a smoothed particle hydrodynamics (SPH) code, Starsmasher, we will perform a parameter sweep covering such scenarios, varying both the evolutionary state of the parent stars and the mass ratio. We will determine the conditions under which a binary merges, and we will study carefully the dynamics and observable characteristics of the merger and merger product, including its light curve, continuum spectrum, and outflow velocity. Our results will complement binary stellar evolution and population synthesis calculations, they will assist in the interpretation of observations, and they will help explain the formation channels of numerous exotic objects, including specific examples such as V1309 Sco.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project represents an opportunity to foster a connection between researchers at Allegheny College and RIT. The proposed project will provide a valuable research focus for undergraduates at Allegheny. Undergraduates, often grappling with career plans, certainly will benefit from early exposure to intercollegiate collaboration and from building a solid foundation in computational methods, an area with broad applications. Based on his experience with Allegheny College students and their career trajectories, the PI expects that this project will equip them well for success in graduate school and in technically oriented careers. In addition, through the PI's teaching and outreach efforts, the project proposed here has the potential to reach a wide range of people and raise the scientific literacy of both local and national audiences.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>09/05/2013</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>09/05/2013</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1313091</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>James</FirstName>
<LastName>Lombardi</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>C</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>James C Lombardi</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>jalombar@allegheny.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>8143322975</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000220533</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/05/2013</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Allegheny College</Name>
<CityName>Meadville</CityName>
<ZipCode>163353902</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>8143325380</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>520 North Main Street</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Pennsylvania</StateName>
<StateCode>PA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>16</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>PA16</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>074973918</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>ALLEGHENY COLLEGE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>074973918</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Allegheny College]]></Name>
<CityName>Meadville</CityName>
<StateCode>PA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>163351509</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[520 North Main Street]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Pennsylvania</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>16</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>PA16</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1215</Code>
<Text>STELLAR ASTRONOMY &amp; ASTROPHYSC</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1206</Code>
<Text>THEORETICAL &amp; COMPUTATIONAL ASTROPHYSICS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9229</Code>
<Text>RES IN UNDERGRAD INST-RESEARCH</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0113</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2013~231312</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Over the four years covered by this grant, the PI (James Lombardi) has worked together with numerous Allegheny College undergraduate students to help determine both what happens when stars collide and how those stellar collisions appear to an observer.&nbsp; By supporting travel to conferences and workshops, the grant has allowed the PI&rsquo;s group to establish and maintain connections to other researchers.&nbsp; In these ways, the project has provided a valuable research focus for undergraduates, both for senior projects and in independent studies.&nbsp; These undergraduates have benefitted from early exposure to intercollegiate collaboration and from building a solid foundation in computational methods, an area with broad applications.&nbsp; Their work has equipped them well for success in graduate school and in technically oriented careers.</p> <p>Besides published papers of our results, two main outcomes are codes that we have made publicly available: (1) our hydrodynamics code StarSmasher which simulates the collisions of stars (or even planets), and (2) our visualization tool FluxE which shows what these collisions would look like. With these codes, we can see not only how mass moves during a merger but also what regions are bright and dim.&nbsp; Our tools allow researchers to determine, for example, why a system brightens when viewed from one direction but not when viewed from another.&nbsp; Results from a FluxE visualization of a StarSmasher simulation are attached: the panel of images on the right shows mass being ejected from a system of two merging stars, while the curves on the left show the resulting brightness versus time as viewed in three different wavelengths of light.</p> <p>The work to make our hydrodynamics code more robust, user friendly, and widely available has led to its being utilized in related problems that involve astrophysical collisions and outflows but that were not envisioned in the initial grant proposal.&nbsp; In particular, we have used StarSmasher and its techniques to consider and publish calculations of collisions between planets, the outflow from the merger of a neutron star and a black hole, and events which involve a star being shredded by the tidal forces of a black hole.</p> <p>In addition, through the PI&rsquo;s teaching and outreach efforts, the project has reached a wide range of people. Indeed, the PI has regularly incorporated experiences gained from his research in his teaching and in his outreach presentations, which include planetarium shows, observing sessions, and night hikes with children and adults of all ages.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 11/30/2017<br>      Modified by: James&nbsp;C&nbsp;Lombardi</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Image         </div> <div class="galControls onePhoto" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation onePhoto" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1313091/1313091_10275644_1512066686637_Panel_Image--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1313091/1313091_10275644_1512066686637_Panel_Image--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Merging stars"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1313091/1313091_10275644_1512066686637_Panel_Image--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Merging stars"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">The red, green, and blue curves on the left represent the brightness versus time of two simulated stars as they merge, as viewed in three different wavelengths of light.  Vertical line segments on these light curves correspond to frames on the right, as labeled.</div> <div class="imageCredit">DOI: https://doi.org/10.1145/3002151.3002154</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">James&nbsp;C&nbsp;Lombardi</div> <div class="imageTitle">Merging stars</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Over the four years covered by this grant, the PI (James Lombardi) has worked together with numerous Allegheny College undergraduate students to help determine both what happens when stars collide and how those stellar collisions appear to an observer.  By supporting travel to conferences and workshops, the grant has allowed the PI?s group to establish and maintain connections to other researchers.  In these ways, the project has provided a valuable research focus for undergraduates, both for senior projects and in independent studies.  These undergraduates have benefitted from early exposure to intercollegiate collaboration and from building a solid foundation in computational methods, an area with broad applications.  Their work has equipped them well for success in graduate school and in technically oriented careers.  Besides published papers of our results, two main outcomes are codes that we have made publicly available: (1) our hydrodynamics code StarSmasher which simulates the collisions of stars (or even planets), and (2) our visualization tool FluxE which shows what these collisions would look like. With these codes, we can see not only how mass moves during a merger but also what regions are bright and dim.  Our tools allow researchers to determine, for example, why a system brightens when viewed from one direction but not when viewed from another.  Results from a FluxE visualization of a StarSmasher simulation are attached: the panel of images on the right shows mass being ejected from a system of two merging stars, while the curves on the left show the resulting brightness versus time as viewed in three different wavelengths of light.  The work to make our hydrodynamics code more robust, user friendly, and widely available has led to its being utilized in related problems that involve astrophysical collisions and outflows but that were not envisioned in the initial grant proposal.  In particular, we have used StarSmasher and its techniques to consider and publish calculations of collisions between planets, the outflow from the merger of a neutron star and a black hole, and events which involve a star being shredded by the tidal forces of a black hole.  In addition, through the PI?s teaching and outreach efforts, the project has reached a wide range of people. Indeed, the PI has regularly incorporated experiences gained from his research in his teaching and in his outreach presentations, which include planetarium shows, observing sessions, and night hikes with children and adults of all ages.          Last Modified: 11/30/2017       Submitted by: James C Lombardi]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
