<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Collaborative Research: Deciphering Brown Dwarf Spectra: Disentangling Temperature, Age, Metallicity, Cloud Signatures</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2013</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>76682.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>76682</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03020000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>AST</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Astronomical Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Faith Vilas</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This collaborative proposal brings together the theoretical and observational skills from two researchers to conduct a study of L-dwarfs, which are relatively cool brown dwarf stellar objects.  They will use optical and infrared spectroscopy and photometry of approximately thirty L- dwarfs to constrain and revise models of the atmospheres and evolution of low mass stellar objects. They will use archive data from Spitzer IRAC and 2MASS surveys, and new data from a 1.3-m telescope in Chile and 2.4-m MDM telescope. They will focus on determining accurate values of effective temperature, mass and metallicity of the dwarfs, and to better understand why many young brown dwarfs are not as luminous as models predict.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Broader impacts include the research training of undergraduate students from underrepresented groups from the City University of New York system, supporting the AstroBetter blog, producing planetarium videos and other public outreach activities through the American Museum of Natural History.&lt;br/&gt;</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>09/19/2013</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/18/2015</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1313132</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Emily</FirstName>
<LastName>Rice</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>L</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Emily L Rice</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>emily.rice@mhc.cuny.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>3109664146</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000505728</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/19/2013</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>CUNY College of Staten Island</Name>
<CityName>Staten Island</CityName>
<ZipCode>103146609</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>7189822254</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>2800 Victory Boulevard</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[1A-211]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>11</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NY11</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>620128079</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>RESEARCH FOUNDATION OF THE CITY UNIVERSITY OF NEW YORK</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>073268849</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[CUNY College of Staten Island]]></Name>
<CityName>Staten Island</CityName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<ZipCode>103146609</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[2800 Victory Blvd]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>11</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NY11</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1215</Code>
<Text>STELLAR ASTRONOMY &amp; ASTROPHYSC</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1206</Code>
<Text>THEORETICAL &amp; COMPUTATIONAL ASTROPHYSICS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1207</Code>
<Text>OBSERVATIONAL ASTRONOMY</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0113</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0114</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0115</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2013~24938</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~24938</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2015~26806</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>This project supported Prof. Emily Rice (PI), CUNY physics graduate student Joe Filippazzo, and several undergraduate student researchers in conducting spectral analysis of brown dwarfs. Brown dwarfs are objects that form like stars do, from collapsing clouds of gas and dust, but without enough mass to reach a high enough core temperature to stably generate energy by fusing hydrogen into helium. Thus brown dwarfs cool, shrink, and fade with time. Brown dwarf spectral classes include M, L, T, and Y dwarfs, and they overlap in observational properties as well as in atmospheric and physical properties with young, high-mass exoplanets. This project focused on the warmest brown dwarfs, L dwarfs, for which solid condensates (dust) are expected to contribute significantly to their atmospheric and observational properties. Young, cool M dwarfs are estimated to have substellar masses and dusty atmospheres so they were also included in several studies.</p> <p>Dr. Filippazzo&rsquo;s thesis project focused on deriving the fundamental parameters of nearly 200 brown dwarfs using their distance-calibrated spectral energy distributions (SEDs), which describe their energy output over a broad range of wavelengths at low resolution. Using SEDs, Dr. Filippazzo determined the overall power output (bolometric luminosity) of each object, from which he could infer a surface temperature and mass, assuming a value for radius estimated from evolutionary models, often constrained by an independently-determined age. These measurements are as close to empirical as possible for single objects. This project produced age-sensitive relationships of luminosity, temperature, and absolute magnitude as functions of spectral type and absolute magnitude to disentangle the effects of degenerate physical parameters of temperature, surface gravity, and clouds on spectral morphology. It also characterized the longer-wavelength reddening of low gravity L dwarfs and identified a systematically cooler temperature of up to 300 K from field age objects of the same spectral type and 400 K cooler from field age objects of the same intrinsic brightness.</p> <p>This project has supported numerous undergraduate student researchers working on projects related to the scientific goals of this grant. Most student researchers were from the City University of New York, and one was from Barnard College. In addition to performing analysis related to their projects, research students participated in on site and/or remote observing, presented their work in talks and as posters at numerous student and professional research conferences, and participated in various education and outreach activities relevant to their personal interests and communities.</p> <p><strong>Intellectual Merit</strong></p> <p>This project combined an unprecedented observational dataset with foundational model atmospheres to determine the fundamental parameters of a large, diverse sample of low-mass stars and brown dwarfs, providing a framework for understanding the properties of young, high-mass exoplanets. The work defined and described &ldquo;normal&rdquo; and &ldquo;outlier&rdquo; brown dwarfs both in terms of their observational properties and their atmospheric and physical properties. The work increased the number of young brown dwarfs with ages constrained by membership in nearby young moving groups of young stars, and established methods for understanding these objects.</p> <p><strong>Broader Impacts</strong></p> <p>Both the PI and the student were active in education and public outreach during the duration of the grant period. Rice and Filippazzo both taught lecture and/or lab sections of general education introductory astronomy at the CUNY College of Staten Island. The PI and students presented numerous public talks and participated in educational and outreach events, including at the Hayden Planetarium, the American Museum of Natural History, Astronomy on Tap NYC, and various amateur astronomy groups. Dr. Filippazzo is now a Research &amp; Instrument Analyst at the Space Telescope Science Institute, and several undergraduate student researchers, all identifying as members of groups historically underrepresented in STEM, will begin or already have continued on to graduate programs, including in astronomy (Harvard &amp; UC&nbsp;Berkeley), chemistry (Caltech), and engineering (NYU).</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 11/28/2017<br>      Modified by: Emily&nbsp;L&nbsp;Rice</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Images (<span id="selectedPhoto0">1</span> of <span class="totalNumber"></span>)           </div> <div class="galControls" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1313132/1313132_10283078_1511886572797_BDNYCFeb15--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1313132/1313132_10283078_1511886572797_BDNYCFeb15--rgov-800width.jpg" title="BDNYC Research group in February 2015"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1313132/1313132_10283078_1511886572797_BDNYCFeb15--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="BDNYC Research group in February 2015"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Members of the BDNYC research group in February 2015, taken at AMNH.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Emily Rice</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Creative Commons</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Emily&nbsp;L&nbsp;Rice</div> <div class="imageTitle">BDNYC Research group in February 2015</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1313132/1313132_10283078_1511374385810_MKO14--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1313132/1313132_10283078_1511374385810_MKO14--rgov-800width.jpg" title="CUNY students at the NASA IRTF in Hawaii"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1313132/1313132_10283078_1511374385810_MKO14--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="CUNY students at the NASA IRTF in Hawaii"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">CUNY undergraduate students Munazza Alam (left) and Sara Camnasio (right) at the NASA Infrared Telescope Facility on Mauna Kea, Hawaii in December 2014</div> <div class="imageCredit">Emily Rice</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Creative Commons</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Emily&nbsp;L&nbsp;Rice</div> <div class="imageTitle">CUNY students at the NASA IRTF in Hawaii</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1313132/1313132_10283078_1511886179375_RemoteObserving25July2017--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1313132/1313132_10283078_1511886179375_RemoteObserving25July2017--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Students remote observing from AMNH"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1313132/1313132_10283078_1511886179375_RemoteObserving25July2017--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Students remote observing from AMNH"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">CUNY students and an artist observing with CAPSCAM on the DuPont Telescope at Las Campanas, Chile remotely from AMNH.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Jackie Faherty</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Creative Commons</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Emily&nbsp;L&nbsp;Rice</div> <div class="imageTitle">Students remote observing from AMNH</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1313132/1313132_10283078_1511886328181_VictoriaAAS229--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1313132/1313132_10283078_1511886328181_VictoriaAAS229--rgov-800width.jpg" title="CUNY Hunter College student Victoria DiTomasso with her poster at AAS 229"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1313132/1313132_10283078_1511886328181_VictoriaAAS229--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="CUNY Hunter College student Victoria DiTomasso with her poster at AAS 229"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">CUNY Hunter College student Victoria DiTomasso with her research poster at AAS 229.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Victoria DiTomasso</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Creative Commons</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Emily&nbsp;L&nbsp;Rice</div> <div class="imageTitle">CUNY Hunter College student Victoria DiTomasso with her poster at AAS 229</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1313132/1313132_10283078_1511372550369_VictoriaAMNH2015--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1313132/1313132_10283078_1511372550369_VictoriaAMNH2015--rgov-800width.jpg" title="CUNY student presents her research project at the AMNH summer student symposium in 2015"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1313132/1313132_10283078_1511372550369_VictoriaAMNH2015--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="CUNY student presents her research project at the AMNH summer student symposium in 2015"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">CUNY student Victoria DiTomasso presents her research project at the AMNH summer student symposium in August 2015</div> <div class="imageCredit">Victoria DiTomasso</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Creative Commons</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Emily&nbsp;L&nbsp;Rice</div> <div class="imageTitle">CUNY student presents her research project at the AMNH summer student symposium in 2015</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ This project supported Prof. Emily Rice (PI), CUNY physics graduate student Joe Filippazzo, and several undergraduate student researchers in conducting spectral analysis of brown dwarfs. Brown dwarfs are objects that form like stars do, from collapsing clouds of gas and dust, but without enough mass to reach a high enough core temperature to stably generate energy by fusing hydrogen into helium. Thus brown dwarfs cool, shrink, and fade with time. Brown dwarf spectral classes include M, L, T, and Y dwarfs, and they overlap in observational properties as well as in atmospheric and physical properties with young, high-mass exoplanets. This project focused on the warmest brown dwarfs, L dwarfs, for which solid condensates (dust) are expected to contribute significantly to their atmospheric and observational properties. Young, cool M dwarfs are estimated to have substellar masses and dusty atmospheres so they were also included in several studies.  Dr. Filippazzo?s thesis project focused on deriving the fundamental parameters of nearly 200 brown dwarfs using their distance-calibrated spectral energy distributions (SEDs), which describe their energy output over a broad range of wavelengths at low resolution. Using SEDs, Dr. Filippazzo determined the overall power output (bolometric luminosity) of each object, from which he could infer a surface temperature and mass, assuming a value for radius estimated from evolutionary models, often constrained by an independently-determined age. These measurements are as close to empirical as possible for single objects. This project produced age-sensitive relationships of luminosity, temperature, and absolute magnitude as functions of spectral type and absolute magnitude to disentangle the effects of degenerate physical parameters of temperature, surface gravity, and clouds on spectral morphology. It also characterized the longer-wavelength reddening of low gravity L dwarfs and identified a systematically cooler temperature of up to 300 K from field age objects of the same spectral type and 400 K cooler from field age objects of the same intrinsic brightness.  This project has supported numerous undergraduate student researchers working on projects related to the scientific goals of this grant. Most student researchers were from the City University of New York, and one was from Barnard College. In addition to performing analysis related to their projects, research students participated in on site and/or remote observing, presented their work in talks and as posters at numerous student and professional research conferences, and participated in various education and outreach activities relevant to their personal interests and communities.  Intellectual Merit  This project combined an unprecedented observational dataset with foundational model atmospheres to determine the fundamental parameters of a large, diverse sample of low-mass stars and brown dwarfs, providing a framework for understanding the properties of young, high-mass exoplanets. The work defined and described "normal" and "outlier" brown dwarfs both in terms of their observational properties and their atmospheric and physical properties. The work increased the number of young brown dwarfs with ages constrained by membership in nearby young moving groups of young stars, and established methods for understanding these objects.  Broader Impacts  Both the PI and the student were active in education and public outreach during the duration of the grant period. Rice and Filippazzo both taught lecture and/or lab sections of general education introductory astronomy at the CUNY College of Staten Island. The PI and students presented numerous public talks and participated in educational and outreach events, including at the Hayden Planetarium, the American Museum of Natural History, Astronomy on Tap NYC, and various amateur astronomy groups. Dr. Filippazzo is now a Research &amp; Instrument Analyst at the Space Telescope Science Institute, and several undergraduate student researchers, all identifying as members of groups historically underrepresented in STEM, will begin or already have continued on to graduate programs, including in astronomy (Harvard &amp; UC Berkeley), chemistry (Caltech), and engineering (NYU).       Last Modified: 11/28/2017       Submitted by: Emily L Rice]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
