<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>CAREER: Ergodic Theory of Nonamenable Group Actions</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/20/2012</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>09/30/2016</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>382249.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>382249</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DMS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Edward Taylor</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This project is concerned with three subjects within the ergodic theory of nonamenable group actions: entropy, rigidity/flexibility phenomena, and pointwise ergodic theorems.  Since Kolmogorov's initial breakthrough (1958), dynamical entropy has played a major role in the ergodic theory of amenable actions. The principal recently discovered a generalization of Kolmogorov's entropy to actions by sofic groups. This class of groups contains many familiar and interesting groups, including all linear groups, thereby providing the first extension of entropy theory to certain nonamenable groups. This new development opens the door to an abundance of problems that could have a great impact in ergodic theory and other fields (e.g., statistical physics, probabilistic combinatorics, operator algebras). In the last decade, there has been an explosion of interest in rigidity theory for nonamenable group actions (see, for example, works of A.Furman, D. Gaboriau, and S. Popa). New results indicate that, under special conditions, measure-conjugacy is equivalent to a priori weaker forms of equivalence of actions, such as orbit equivalence and von Neumann equivalence. It is expected that the principal investigator's new entropy theory can make an important contribution to rigidity theory by determining more precisely when it is an orbit equivalence or von Neumann equivalence invariant. The principal investigator has recently proven the first orbit equivalence flexibility results in the nonamenable setting. It is expected that the techniques developed for the proof will be more broadly applicable and could result in a general orbit equivalence flexibility theory for certain groups and actions. Pointwise ergodic theorems have a long history, beginning with Birkhoff. In collaboration with A. Nevo, the principal investigator is developing general methods for proving pointwise ergodic theorems for actions of discrete, nonamenable groups. Successes so far include new pointwise ergodic averaging sequences for actions of free groups and the first pointwise ergodic theorems for actions of general word-hyperbolic groups with respect to ball and spherical averages. The new techniques remove a fundamental obstacle in that they reduce the problem to the amenable case, which can then be solved by the classical Wiener-Calderon-Folner theory. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The educational component of the project includes yearly workshops at Texas A&amp;M for the purposes of introducing graduate students to the latest research developments and bringing together the diverse groups of researchers working in areas important to the project. The principal investigator plans to mentor undergraduates through his department's honors program and to give popular talks at math club meetings and during his department's summer programs for undergraduates and high school students. The principal investigator also plans to invite an expert expositor as a distinguished lecturer to give a series of inspiring talks on topics of current interest. This project directly provides for the training of a graduate student. It should be easy to attract one because the principal investigator's recent results are accessible and lead to an open field of problems whose solutions could have significant impact in ergodic theory and other areas.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>05/13/2013</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/13/2013</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1313520</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Lewis</FirstName>
<LastName>Bowen</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Lewis Bowen</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>lpbowen@math.utexas.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5124711132</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000511625</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/13/2013</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Texas at Austin</Name>
<CityName>Austin</CityName>
<ZipCode>787595316</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5124716424</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>3925 W Braker Lane, Ste 3.340</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Texas</StateName>
<StateCode>TX</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>10</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>TX10</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>170230239</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF TEXAS AT AUSTIN</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>042000273</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Texas at Austin]]></Name>
<CityName>Austin</CityName>
<StateCode>TX</StateCode>
<ZipCode>787137726</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[PO Box 7726]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Texas</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>21</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>TX21</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1265</Code>
<Text>GEOMETRIC ANALYSIS</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1267</Code>
<Text>TOPOLOGY</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1281</Code>
<Text>ANALYSIS PROGRAM</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>0000</Code>
<Text>UNASSIGNED</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1045</Code>
<Text>CAREER-Faculty Erly Career Dev</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1187</Code>
<Text>PECASE- eligible</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>OTHR</Code>
<Text>OTHER RESEARCH OR EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0110</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2010~382249</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The goal of my research is to extend the methods and results of ergodic theory to non-amenable settings. In a nutshell, ergodic theory studies the long-run behaviour of dynamical systems in which the initial state is random. It was developed in the early 1900s to provide tools for statistical physics. It is now recognized as an important body of techniques that has found applications in nearly all areas of mathematics. It is natural and useful to replace the notion of time with a group of transformations. This motivates the central problem of my research: what are the appropriate analogs of the main results and methods of ergodic theory in this new setting? What new phenomena appear and how do these phenomena relate to the structure of the group? Exploring these questions has led to interactions with other research fields such as descriptive set theory, operator algebras, probabilistic combinatorics and high-dimensional metric measure spaces.&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>The setting of classical ergodic theory is the following: consider observing a system that evolves in time. The initial state of the system is not known in advance and is therefore modeled probabilistically. The collection of all possible states is represented by a probability space and the advance of time is modeled by a map from the space to itself.&nbsp; Ergodic theory addresses two types of questions: (1) how does the trajectory of a typical initial state reflect average properties? (2) what are the important features or characteristics of such systems?</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>The transformation representing time can be replaced with a group&nbsp; of symmetries of the measure space. For example, statistical physics often models matter at the atomic scale as an array of random variables indexed by the cubic lattice. The collection of these random variables may be considered as a random point in a probability space. There are three spatial transformations of this space that together generate a group of symmetries.&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>This example has a special feature. The cube with side-length n has (surface area)-to-volume ratio 6/n which can be made as small as desired by choosing n large. For this reason, if one is studying matter in a large but finite box (with respect to the atomic scale), it is usually reasonable to assume that boundary effects are insignificant and this justifies replacing the finite box with infinite space. In general, a group is called amenable if it has the property that one can find bounded subsets with as small (surface area)-to-volume ratio as desired. Under this hypothesis, many proofs reduce to two steps: (1) the case of processes restricted to a finite box and (2) how to make sense of the limit as the size of the box tends to infinity. Most ergodic theory results have been extended to actions by amenable groups.&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>By comparison the ergodic theory for non-amenable groups is under-developed, much richer and is the subject of this career award. Project findings include:&nbsp; development of a new entropy theory for actions of non-amenable groups (previously there was no entropy theory at all), the construction and application of new techniques for obtaining pointwise ergodic theorems for arbitrary groups, results on the shape of the space of group actions up to a weak form of equivalence that nonetheless plays an important role in classication, new constructions of stationary actions of groups (in theory these actions exist in abundance; however explicit constructions are rare and therefore they remain mysterious), and a proof that homological conditions play an important role in obstructions to approximation.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>This project has also supported six workshops half of which were strongly attended by junior participants (the other half were mini-workshops consisting of around 10 participants each). It also supported 3 graduate students, one undergraduate and one postdoc. The PI has given lectures all around the world including a 5-part Minerva lecture series at Princeton as part of this award. The lectures include general lectures to the public and undergraduate math clubs.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 11/24/2016<br>      Modified by: Lewis&nbsp;Bowen</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The goal of my research is to extend the methods and results of ergodic theory to non-amenable settings. In a nutshell, ergodic theory studies the long-run behaviour of dynamical systems in which the initial state is random. It was developed in the early 1900s to provide tools for statistical physics. It is now recognized as an important body of techniques that has found applications in nearly all areas of mathematics. It is natural and useful to replace the notion of time with a group of transformations. This motivates the central problem of my research: what are the appropriate analogs of the main results and methods of ergodic theory in this new setting? What new phenomena appear and how do these phenomena relate to the structure of the group? Exploring these questions has led to interactions with other research fields such as descriptive set theory, operator algebras, probabilistic combinatorics and high-dimensional metric measure spaces.      The setting of classical ergodic theory is the following: consider observing a system that evolves in time. The initial state of the system is not known in advance and is therefore modeled probabilistically. The collection of all possible states is represented by a probability space and the advance of time is modeled by a map from the space to itself.  Ergodic theory addresses two types of questions: (1) how does the trajectory of a typical initial state reflect average properties? (2) what are the important features or characteristics of such systems?     The transformation representing time can be replaced with a group  of symmetries of the measure space. For example, statistical physics often models matter at the atomic scale as an array of random variables indexed by the cubic lattice. The collection of these random variables may be considered as a random point in a probability space. There are three spatial transformations of this space that together generate a group of symmetries.      This example has a special feature. The cube with side-length n has (surface area)-to-volume ratio 6/n which can be made as small as desired by choosing n large. For this reason, if one is studying matter in a large but finite box (with respect to the atomic scale), it is usually reasonable to assume that boundary effects are insignificant and this justifies replacing the finite box with infinite space. In general, a group is called amenable if it has the property that one can find bounded subsets with as small (surface area)-to-volume ratio as desired. Under this hypothesis, many proofs reduce to two steps: (1) the case of processes restricted to a finite box and (2) how to make sense of the limit as the size of the box tends to infinity. Most ergodic theory results have been extended to actions by amenable groups.      By comparison the ergodic theory for non-amenable groups is under-developed, much richer and is the subject of this career award. Project findings include:  development of a new entropy theory for actions of non-amenable groups (previously there was no entropy theory at all), the construction and application of new techniques for obtaining pointwise ergodic theorems for arbitrary groups, results on the shape of the space of group actions up to a weak form of equivalence that nonetheless plays an important role in classication, new constructions of stationary actions of groups (in theory these actions exist in abundance; however explicit constructions are rare and therefore they remain mysterious), and a proof that homological conditions play an important role in obstructions to approximation.     This project has also supported six workshops half of which were strongly attended by junior participants (the other half were mini-workshops consisting of around 10 participants each). It also supported 3 graduate students, one undergraduate and one postdoc. The PI has given lectures all around the world including a 5-part Minerva lecture series at Princeton as part of this award. The lectures include general lectures to the public and undergraduate math clubs.          Last Modified: 11/24/2016       Submitted by: Lewis Bowen]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
