<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>SEES Fellows: Integrating biology and econometrics across multiple scales for sustainable wildlife trade management</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2013</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>418464.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>418464</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03090000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CHE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Chemistry</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Anne-Marie Schmoltner</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>aschmolt@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924716</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>In this Award from the NSF Science, Engineering and Education for Sustainability Fellows (SEES Fellows Program) Dr. Mary E. Blair from the American Museum of Natural History will carry out genetic measurements of  slow lorises combined with socioeconomic studies of those people involved in the trade of these animals.  This award has support from: the Biology Directorate, the Directorate for Social, Behavioral and Economic Sciences, and the Office of International and Integrative Activities.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The proposed work will combine genetic information from slow lorises as well as socioeconomic data for individuals involved in the trade of these species, to test the hypothesis that the trade in these species is concentrated in Vietnam, which serves as a major transit market for trade within Southeast Asia and to study whether regional and international demand are more important than local factors in driving this trade. The work is unique in that it integrates socioeconomic and biological analyses at multiple scales to develop a better understanding of wildlife trade.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The aim of studies like that proposed in this work is to better understand the socioeconomic drivers that influence the trade in wildlife.  The ultimate aim of work like this is to better inform policy makers about the underlying social and economic drivers of this trade, with an eye towards developing sustainable management strategies to mitigate the threat to species from this trade.   &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Dr. Blair will be working with collaborators Dr. Eleanor J. Sterling of the Center for Biodiversity and Conservation at the American Museum of Natural History, Prof. Gautam Sethi at Bard College's Center for Environmental Policy and Dr. Minh D. Le from the Centre for Natural Resources and Environmental Studies at Vietnam National University.  Dr. Blair will also be mentoring young students in this project, and she will develop outreach materials for use in the United States and Vietnam.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project is supported under the NSF Science, Engineering and Education for Sustainability Fellows (SEES Fellows) program, with the goal of helping to enable discoveries needed to inform actions that lead to environmental, energy and societal sustainability while creating the necessary workforce to address these challenges. With SEES Fellows support, this project will enable a promising early career researcher to establish themselves in an independent research career related to sustainability.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/27/2013</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/27/2013</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1313908</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Mary</FirstName>
<LastName>Blair</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>E</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Mary E Blair</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>mblair1@amnh.org</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2123137077</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000497963</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/27/2013</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>American Museum Natural History</Name>
<CityName>New York</CityName>
<ZipCode>100240000</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2127695975</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>Central Park West at 79th St</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>08</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NY08</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>061202768</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>AMERICAN MUSEUM OF NATURAL HISTORY, THE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>061202768</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[American Museum Natural History]]></Name>
<CityName>New York</CityName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<ZipCode>100240000</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[Central Park West at 79th St]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>08</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NY08</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>8055</Code>
<Text>SEES Fellows</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1061</Code>
<Text>VIETNAM</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8055</Code>
<Text>Capacity-Building Projects</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0113</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2013~418464</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>This SEES Fellows award supported a Fellow at the Center for Biodiversity and Conservation at the American Museum of Natural History (CBC-AMNH) and collaborators at Bard College, Long Island University, and Vietnam National University to develop a research framework to better understand the complex drivers of wildlife trade by integrating socioeconomic and biological analyses at multiple scales.</p> <p>Over four years, this award contributed to advance basic knowledge about wildlife trade in Vietnam and about slow lorises, nocturnal primates that are threatened by trade. It has also contributed to advance research on wildlife trade more broadly via the development of a novel conceptual and analytical framework to design and implement interdisciplinary research on wildlife trade systems in varied contexts. Findings from the research have resulted in four peer&shy;-reviewed publications in high-profile journals and three student theses, as of October 2017. Findings have been presented at a minimum of 19 academic symposia and conferences, including at the International Primatological Congress, the Association of American Geographers, the Society for Conservation Biology Asia Section, and the Lower Mekong Research Collaboration Initiative Symposium. In addition, the Fellow was invited to present on this research three times as the keynote speaker at research symposia and more than 29 times at college and university department seminars.</p> <p>The Fellow gained team leadership skills and developed valuable networks and experiences in high-level international scientific and government exchange. To further develop improved long-term capacity for interdisciplinary scientific research and conservation management, this award also supported the training of both U.S. and Vietnamese graduate and undergraduate students in biology, anthropology, and economics through hands-on research. This included a Master's capstone project at Bard College and internships for seven graduate students including two NSF IGERT trainees, eleven undergraduate interns including two NSF REU students, two undergraduate honors theses at Vietnam National University, and two high school students through the AMNH Science Research Mentoring Program. Seven of these students presented their research at professional scientific conferences including at the International Primatological Congress and the Student Conference on Conservation Science &ndash; New York, funded either by this award or synergistic awards such as a NSF BIO REU Mentor-Student Travel Scholarship. This project also supported several activities to broaden the human diversity of students pursuing careers in conservation science as a part of CBC-AMNH&rsquo;s Enhancing Diversity in Conservation Science Initiative, including five workshops on career development held at professional conferences.</p> <p>This award supported four additional training events and workshops focused on strengthening capacity for interdisciplinary conservation science across a wide range of communities including students, faculty, government scientists and officials, and conservation practitioners. These events included a spatial econometrics workshop at Bard College, a conservation genetics and forensic science training course at Vietnam National University, and two slow loris conservation workshops at the Vietnam Forestry Administration (VNFOREST). In addition, the nocturnal survey methods developed for this research were adopted by VNFOREST&rsquo;s national-level training program for protected area staff.</p> <p>This award also supported numerous outreach initiatives to raise public awareness about slow loris conservation, wildlife trade, and to support effective decision&shy;making for conservation of trade-targeted species worldwide. Research, training, and workshops supported by this award directly informed Vietnam&rsquo;s first National Primate Conservation Action Plan, which was signed into effect by the Prime Minister with Decision 628 in May, 2017.&nbsp; This work has also provided crucial input into the International Union for Conservation of Nature (IUCN)&rsquo;s Red List assessment for slow lorises, and has generated a genetic and morphological reference database to facilitate identification of species and geographic provenance of wildlife trade confiscations. Also, more than 35 items of popular media have been generated about this research including 18 blog posts and press releases, 3 podcasts, 6 videos, 5 magazine articles, 3 high profile public events. These diverse outlets, including the New York Times and AMNH&rsquo;s popular SciCafe series, highlighted why wildlife trade is an important issue for human health, security, and well-being, and how a holistic understanding of the issue can advance more equitable and effective mitigation approaches.</p> <p>The research collaborations fostered by the award are long lasting and have achieved funding through&nbsp;USAID&nbsp;Partnerships for Enhanced Engagement in Research to expand interdisciplinary research and training efforts through new partnerships in Cambodia and Laos, and from U.S. Fish and Wildlife Service to develop training activities and technical support for government agencies in Vietnam on forensic techniques for wildlife trade enforcement. In addition, two Vietnamese graduate students have received funding to continue work on slow loris conservation and monitoring at key sites in Vietnam. The Fellow has received support from Fulbright, NASA, and the Prince Albert II of Monaco Foundation to continue development of decision support tools and interdisciplinary conservation science training for both U.S. and Vietnamese students and scientists that will inform the proposed review and expansion of protected areas in Vietnam in 2025.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 11/28/2017<br>      Modified by: Mary&nbsp;E&nbsp;Blair</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ This SEES Fellows award supported a Fellow at the Center for Biodiversity and Conservation at the American Museum of Natural History (CBC-AMNH) and collaborators at Bard College, Long Island University, and Vietnam National University to develop a research framework to better understand the complex drivers of wildlife trade by integrating socioeconomic and biological analyses at multiple scales.  Over four years, this award contributed to advance basic knowledge about wildlife trade in Vietnam and about slow lorises, nocturnal primates that are threatened by trade. It has also contributed to advance research on wildlife trade more broadly via the development of a novel conceptual and analytical framework to design and implement interdisciplinary research on wildlife trade systems in varied contexts. Findings from the research have resulted in four peer&shy;-reviewed publications in high-profile journals and three student theses, as of October 2017. Findings have been presented at a minimum of 19 academic symposia and conferences, including at the International Primatological Congress, the Association of American Geographers, the Society for Conservation Biology Asia Section, and the Lower Mekong Research Collaboration Initiative Symposium. In addition, the Fellow was invited to present on this research three times as the keynote speaker at research symposia and more than 29 times at college and university department seminars.  The Fellow gained team leadership skills and developed valuable networks and experiences in high-level international scientific and government exchange. To further develop improved long-term capacity for interdisciplinary scientific research and conservation management, this award also supported the training of both U.S. and Vietnamese graduate and undergraduate students in biology, anthropology, and economics through hands-on research. This included a Master's capstone project at Bard College and internships for seven graduate students including two NSF IGERT trainees, eleven undergraduate interns including two NSF REU students, two undergraduate honors theses at Vietnam National University, and two high school students through the AMNH Science Research Mentoring Program. Seven of these students presented their research at professional scientific conferences including at the International Primatological Congress and the Student Conference on Conservation Science &ndash; New York, funded either by this award or synergistic awards such as a NSF BIO REU Mentor-Student Travel Scholarship. This project also supported several activities to broaden the human diversity of students pursuing careers in conservation science as a part of CBC-AMNH?s Enhancing Diversity in Conservation Science Initiative, including five workshops on career development held at professional conferences.  This award supported four additional training events and workshops focused on strengthening capacity for interdisciplinary conservation science across a wide range of communities including students, faculty, government scientists and officials, and conservation practitioners. These events included a spatial econometrics workshop at Bard College, a conservation genetics and forensic science training course at Vietnam National University, and two slow loris conservation workshops at the Vietnam Forestry Administration (VNFOREST). In addition, the nocturnal survey methods developed for this research were adopted by VNFOREST?s national-level training program for protected area staff.  This award also supported numerous outreach initiatives to raise public awareness about slow loris conservation, wildlife trade, and to support effective decision&shy;making for conservation of trade-targeted species worldwide. Research, training, and workshops supported by this award directly informed Vietnam?s first National Primate Conservation Action Plan, which was signed into effect by the Prime Minister with Decision 628 in May, 2017.  This work has also provided crucial input into the International Union for Conservation of Nature (IUCN)?s Red List assessment for slow lorises, and has generated a genetic and morphological reference database to facilitate identification of species and geographic provenance of wildlife trade confiscations. Also, more than 35 items of popular media have been generated about this research including 18 blog posts and press releases, 3 podcasts, 6 videos, 5 magazine articles, 3 high profile public events. These diverse outlets, including the New York Times and AMNH?s popular SciCafe series, highlighted why wildlife trade is an important issue for human health, security, and well-being, and how a holistic understanding of the issue can advance more equitable and effective mitigation approaches.  The research collaborations fostered by the award are long lasting and have achieved funding through USAID Partnerships for Enhanced Engagement in Research to expand interdisciplinary research and training efforts through new partnerships in Cambodia and Laos, and from U.S. Fish and Wildlife Service to develop training activities and technical support for government agencies in Vietnam on forensic techniques for wildlife trade enforcement. In addition, two Vietnamese graduate students have received funding to continue work on slow loris conservation and monitoring at key sites in Vietnam. The Fellow has received support from Fulbright, NASA, and the Prince Albert II of Monaco Foundation to continue development of decision support tools and interdisciplinary conservation science training for both U.S. and Vietnamese students and scientists that will inform the proposed review and expansion of protected areas in Vietnam in 2025.          Last Modified: 11/28/2017       Submitted by: Mary E Blair]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
