<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Core Support for the Board on Life Sciences</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>04/01/2013</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>03/31/2016</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>300003.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>300003</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>08080000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>BIO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DBI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Biological Infrastructure</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Anne Maglia</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>An award is made to the National Academy of Sciences to support the Board on Life Sciences to: 1) hold one Board meeting per year, and 2) support staff time to develop topics for new studies and other projects and perform tasks related to completed studies. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The Board on Life Sciences serves as the National Academy of Sciences' focal point for a wide range of technical and policy topics in the life sciences, including genomics, biodiversity conservation, bioterrorism, and key topics in basic biolgical and biomedical research, such as stem cells. The Board organizes and oversees studies that provide advice to government and the scientific community on the biological sciences and their impact on society. The Board also oversees important studies on the improvement of biology education, particularly at the undergraduate level, and the maintenance of a robust life sciences workforce. More information can be found at: http://dels.nas.edu/bls/</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>03/29/2013</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>03/29/2013</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.074</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1313700</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Frances</FirstName>
<LastName>Sharples</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>E</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Frances E Sharples</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>fsharples@nas.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2023342187</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000142172</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>03/29/2013</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>National Academy of Sciences</Name>
<CityName>Washington</CityName>
<ZipCode>200012721</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2023342254</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>500 FIFTH STREET NW</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>District of Columbia</StateName>
<StateCode>DC</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>00</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>DC00</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>041964057</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>NATIONAL ACADEMY OF SCIENCES</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>041964057</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[National Academy of Sciences]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>DC</StateCode>
<ZipCode>200012736</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>District of Columbia</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>00</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>DC00</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1165</Code>
<Text>ADVANCES IN BIO INFORMATICS</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0113</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2013~300003</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The project "Core Support for the Board on Life Sciences" (BLS) provides funding to enable BLS to continue to produce the kinds of significant results for the government, the scientific community, and the public discussed that it has in the past. BLS serves as the National Academy of Sciences' focal point for a wide range of technical and policy topics in the life sciences, including genomics, biodiversity conservation, bioterrorism, and other key topics in basic biological research, such as metagenomics and glycoscience. The Board organizes and oversees studies that provide advice to government and the scientific community on the life sciences and their impact on society. It also oversees important studies on the improvement of biology education, particularly at the undergraduate level, and the maintenance of a robust life sciences workforce.</p> <p>Throughout its 25 year history, BLS has produced numerous reports that have had major impacts on science and policy. in1988, <em>Mapping and Sequencing the Human Genome </em>helped tip the scales in favor of proceeding with this crucial project. Also in 1988, the term "biodiversity" entered into public usage with the publication of the report<em> Biodiversity</em>, which first drew attention to the many threats to biodiversity and its ecological importance. Other important reports for NSF have included <em>The National Ecological Observatory Network (NEON): Addressing the Nation's Environmental Challenges</em>; <em>The New Science of Metagenomics: Revealing the Secrets of Our Microbial Planet</em>; <em>The Role of Theory in Advancing 21st Century Biology</em>; <em>A New Biology for the 21st Century</em>; and <em>Enhancing the Value and Sustainability of Field Stations and Marine Laboratories in the 21st Century</em>. All of these reports are available for free download on the National Academies Press website at <a href="http://www.nap.edu/">http://www.nap.edu/</a>.</p> <p>BLS regularly seeks support from NSF with the goal of acquiring resources that enable it to continue to carry out its activities. Core funding enables BLS to perform its critical roles: overseeing the execution of on-going projects, providing guidance on future directions, bringing the expertise of Board members to bear on the evaluation of emerging issues, and shaping BLS's portfolio of projects in response to the evolving needs of the life sciences. For these activities, BLS's two meeetings per year with its advisory Board members are of vital importance, and one of these is typically supported by NSF's funding. Core support is also essential to allow the BLS staff to do the work required to develop new studies, gathering and analyzing information and&nbsp;conferring with sponsors and others to define needs and craft clear project descriptions. Core funding from NSF is crucial to maintaining BLS's ability to respond to the need for impartial, objective, scientifically informed advice on a diverse array of issues dealing with biolgicla research.&nbsp;</p> <p>Some of BLS's&nbsp;current work&nbsp;includes a project on <em>Gene Drive Research in Non-Human Organisms: Recommendations for Responsible Conduct</em>. A gene drive is a gene editing technique&nbsp;designed to deliberately spread through populations of insects, other animals, or plants. It offers&nbsp;a potential new way to control infectious disease, such as human and avian malaria, by inhibiting the ability of mosquito populations to spread such diseases. Gene drives might also be used to reduce or eradicate populations of invasive species, such as destructive rodents. But because their application requires that organisms carrying gene drives be released in the environment, there are many ecological and ethical issues surrounding this new technology. The report from this project, whcih is scheduled for release in early May, 2016, will review the state of the science of gene drives and provide ...]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The project "Core Support for the Board on Life Sciences" (BLS) provides funding to enable BLS to continue to produce the kinds of significant results for the government, the scientific community, and the public discussed that it has in the past. BLS serves as the National Academy of Sciences' focal point for a wide range of technical and policy topics in the life sciences, including genomics, biodiversity conservation, bioterrorism, and other key topics in basic biological research, such as metagenomics and glycoscience. The Board organizes and oversees studies that provide advice to government and the scientific community on the life sciences and their impact on society. It also oversees important studies on the improvement of biology education, particularly at the undergraduate level, and the maintenance of a robust life sciences workforce.  Throughout its 25 year history, BLS has produced numerous reports that have had major impacts on science and policy. in1988, Mapping and Sequencing the Human Genome helped tip the scales in favor of proceeding with this crucial project. Also in 1988, the term "biodiversity" entered into public usage with the publication of the report Biodiversity, which first drew attention to the many threats to biodiversity and its ecological importance. Other important reports for NSF have included The National Ecological Observatory Network (NEON): Addressing the Nation's Environmental Challenges; The New Science of Metagenomics: Revealing the Secrets of Our Microbial Planet; The Role of Theory in Advancing 21st Century Biology; A New Biology for the 21st Century; and Enhancing the Value and Sustainability of Field Stations and Marine Laboratories in the 21st Century. All of these reports are available for free download on the National Academies Press website at http://www.nap.edu/.  BLS regularly seeks support from NSF with the goal of acquiring resources that enable it to continue to carry out its activities. Core funding enables BLS to perform its critical roles: overseeing the execution of on-going projects, providing guidance on future directions, bringing the expertise of Board members to bear on the evaluation of emerging issues, and shaping BLS's portfolio of projects in response to the evolving needs of the life sciences. For these activities, BLS's two meeetings per year with its advisory Board members are of vital importance, and one of these is typically supported by NSF's funding. Core support is also essential to allow the BLS staff to do the work required to develop new studies, gathering and analyzing information and conferring with sponsors and others to define needs and craft clear project descriptions. Core funding from NSF is crucial to maintaining BLS's ability to respond to the need for impartial, objective, scientifically informed advice on a diverse array of issues dealing with biolgicla research.   Some of BLS's current work includes a project on Gene Drive Research in Non-Human Organisms: Recommendations for Responsible Conduct. A gene drive is a gene editing technique designed to deliberately spread through populations of insects, other animals, or plants. It offers a potential new way to control infectious disease, such as human and avian malaria, by inhibiting the ability of mosquito populations to spread such diseases. Gene drives might also be used to reduce or eradicate populations of invasive species, such as destructive rodents. But because their application requires that organisms carrying gene drives be released in the environment, there are many ecological and ethical issues surrounding this new technology. The report from this project, whcih is scheduled for release in early May, 2016, will review the state of the science of gene drives and provide guidance for responsible practices in gene drive research both in lab and field release settings. Another project that is currently underway is Future Biotechnology Products and Opportunities to Enhance Capabilities ...]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
