<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>SBIR Phase I:  Novel Optical Materials for Cooking Fast Foods without Fryer Oils</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2013</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>03/31/2014</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>149927.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>149927</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07070000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>IIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Industrial Innovation &amp; Partnersh</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Steven Konsek</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>skonsek@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927021</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This Small Business Innovation Research (SBIR) Phase I project will develop innovative optical materials with the potential to revolutionize fried food production and numerous other industries.  A new technology is needed to solve health and safety risk problems that are associated with oil immersion cooking.  Oil immersion cooking results in unacceptably large increases in absorbed oil and fat content in fried foods.   The research objective is to develop an oil-less frying technique based on spectrally selective infrared light.  Conventional infrared heating elements are poorly suited to these frying applications because they are not spectrally selective and emit large portions of their energy at longer wavelengths that quickly scorch and damage food products.  This research will develop a series of advanced ceramic materials, which when heated only emit light at selective shorter infrared wavelengths that are useful in frying fast foods.  If successful, this research will result in array of materials which can rapidly and efficiently fry foods that are tasty, without the need for oil, while using less energy and costing less than traditional oil immersion cooking.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The broader impact/commercial potential of this project will be in the food industry.  The commercial focus will initially be on cooking fast foods without fryer oils.   French fries, for example, can absorb 30% by weight of the cooking oil used in deep frying.   This new infrared cooking technology has the potential to significantly reduce society?s consumption of deep fryer oils and fats which are a major contributor to the obesity epidemic.  Cooking using wavelength-selective infrared light energy has the potential to achieve superior or comparable taste quality without the absorbed oil.  This technology will also enhance scientific and technological understanding in the areas of food processing, bulk drying, and sterilization.  Many other important applications exist for true wavelength selective infrared emitting materials that do not radiate energy at wavelengths which overheat, burn, or destroy valuable food characteristics during processing.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/03/2013</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/03/2013</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1314426</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Luke</FirstName>
<LastName>Ferguson</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>G</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Luke G Ferguson</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>info@C12Materials.com</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2067958925</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000633566</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/03/2013</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>C12 Advanced Technologies, LLC</Name>
<CityName>Everett</CityName>
<ZipCode>982043590</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2067958925</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>3101 111th Street SW</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[Suite R]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Washington</StateName>
<StateCode>WA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>WA02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>078568778</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>C12 ADVANCED TECHNOLOGIES, LLC</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[C12 Advanced Technologies, LLC]]></Name>
<CityName>Everett</CityName>
<StateCode>WA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>982043590</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[3101 111th Street SW, Suite R]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Washington</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>WA02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>5371</Code>
<Text>SBIR Phase I</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>094E</Code>
<Text>Optoelectronic devices</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>123E</Code>
<Text>CENTERS: ADVANCED MATERIALS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>5371</Code>
<Text>SMALL BUSINESS PHASE I</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0113</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2013~149927</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p style="margin-bottom: 0in;">&nbsp;</p> <p style="margin-bottom: 0in;"><span style="font-family: Tahoma,sans-serif;"><span style="font-size: small;">The process heating industry can be characterized as a mature industry, and includes many drying, curing, preheating, and coating applications that are energy intensive.  There have been few truly innovative changes since gas-fired heaters became available on the commercial market more than 50 years ago.  Regardless of the materials used (ceramic or metal), or the construction (solid or fibers), gas-fired heaters have seldom reached surface temperatures above 1100 C, and therefore have not been able to compete successfully with electric &ldquo;shortwave&rdquo; heat lamp systems.  Most importantly, it has not been possible to effectively control or optimize gas-fired heaters, and efficiently &ldquo;match&rdquo; their spectral power to the product that is being heated.  This lack of spectral control results in large amounts of energy being wasted, and can cause burning or scorching problems in many sensitive applications. </span></span></p> <p style="margin-bottom: 0in;">&nbsp;</p> <p style="margin-bottom: 0in;"><span style="font-family: Tahoma,sans-serif;"><span style="font-size: small;">We believe that our newly developed C12 Spectrally Selective heating technology can have a large impact on the global process heating industry.  Our research has clearly shown that this new heating technology has the potential to provide very effective spectral control, and that it can operate with abundant, low-cost natural gas energy sources.</span></span></p> <p style="margin-bottom: 0in;">&nbsp;</p> <p style="margin-bottom: 0in;"><span style="font-family: Tahoma,sans-serif;"><span style="font-size: small;">Plastic thermoforming provides an example of how the new gas-fired C12 Spectrally Selective heating technology would compete favorably with high cost electric heat lamp systems.  The thermoforming industry has well over 500 manufacturers representing 6,300 manufacturing lines in the US.  Of these, 95% utilize electric shortwave heat lamps.  Thermoforming machine manufacturers have identified that the </span></span><em><span style="font-family: Tahoma,sans-serif;"><span style="font-size: small;">electric energy cost to heat the plastic sheet accounts for 35% to 50% of the cost of the end product</span></span></em><span style="font-family: Tahoma,sans-serif;"><span style="font-size: small;">.  These manufacturers have estimated that the ability to use natural gas as the primary energy source for heating could reduce this number to less than 10% due to the 3 to 1 cost advantage of natural gas. </span></span></p> <p style="margin-bottom: 0in;">&nbsp;</p> <p style="margin-bottom: 0in;"><span style="font-family: Tahoma,sans-serif;"><span style="font-size: small;">The most important reasons for not using gas energy sources have been due to the low operating temperatures and spectral control limitations of commercially available gas heaters.  The new C12 Spectrally Selective heaters have proven capable of producing a high-temperature shortwave spectrum that is easily comparable, or superior to, expensive heat lamp systems, and they are the </span></span><em><span style="font-family: Tahoma,sans-serif;"><span style="font-size: small;">only</span></span></em><span style="font-family: Tahoma,sans-serif;"> </span><span style="font-family: Tahoma,sans-serif;"><span style="font-size: small;">cost-efficient gas-fired heating technology that can meet this need.  As shown in Figure 1, the peak output remains nearly constant at 1.5 micrometers with the new C12 shortwave selective heaters, regardless of the heater temperature or input power to the burner.  Unlike conventional heaters, very little energy is wasted or radiated at mid or long wavelengths. </span></span></p> <p style="margin-bottom: 0in;">&nbsp;</p> <p style="margin-bottom: 0in;"><span s...]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[  The process heating industry can be characterized as a mature industry, and includes many drying, curing, preheating, and coating applications that are energy intensive.  There have been few truly innovative changes since gas-fired heaters became available on the commercial market more than 50 years ago.  Regardless of the materials used (ceramic or metal), or the construction (solid or fibers), gas-fired heaters have seldom reached surface temperatures above 1100 C, and therefore have not been able to compete successfully with electric "shortwave" heat lamp systems.  Most importantly, it has not been possible to effectively control or optimize gas-fired heaters, and efficiently "match" their spectral power to the product that is being heated.  This lack of spectral control results in large amounts of energy being wasted, and can cause burning or scorching problems in many sensitive applications.    We believe that our newly developed C12 Spectrally Selective heating technology can have a large impact on the global process heating industry.  Our research has clearly shown that this new heating technology has the potential to provide very effective spectral control, and that it can operate with abundant, low-cost natural gas energy sources.   Plastic thermoforming provides an example of how the new gas-fired C12 Spectrally Selective heating technology would compete favorably with high cost electric heat lamp systems.  The thermoforming industry has well over 500 manufacturers representing 6,300 manufacturing lines in the US.  Of these, 95% utilize electric shortwave heat lamps.  Thermoforming machine manufacturers have identified that the electric energy cost to heat the plastic sheet accounts for 35% to 50% of the cost of the end product.  These manufacturers have estimated that the ability to use natural gas as the primary energy source for heating could reduce this number to less than 10% due to the 3 to 1 cost advantage of natural gas.    The most important reasons for not using gas energy sources have been due to the low operating temperatures and spectral control limitations of commercially available gas heaters.  The new C12 Spectrally Selective heaters have proven capable of producing a high-temperature shortwave spectrum that is easily comparable, or superior to, expensive heat lamp systems, and they are the only cost-efficient gas-fired heating technology that can meet this need.  As shown in Figure 1, the peak output remains nearly constant at 1.5 micrometers with the new C12 shortwave selective heaters, regardless of the heater temperature or input power to the burner.  Unlike conventional heaters, very little energy is wasted or radiated at mid or long wavelengths.    We were clearly able to achieve our primary goals, and demonstrate successful results, by constructing a small prototype gas-fired burner assembly that had been fitted with novel "shortwave selective" heater tiles and performing a number of simple experiments.  Figure 2 shows our prototype gas-fired heater in operation.    In one set of experiments we cooked par-fried potatoes with this novel prototype heater.  As shown in Figure 3, the temperature of each potato sample climbed rapidly to just over 100 C, and then remained constant at this plateau level.  Each sample was held long enough to form a golden brown crust.  Our par-fry tests closely resembled standard results obtained with shortwave electric heat lamp systems in the time that it took to reach peak temperature, and compared quite favorably.   In another set of experiments, apple slices were prepared from commercially available Gala Apples and dried using the novel prototype heater.  The peak temperature of the apple slices was kept below 75 degrees Celsius, (a temperature range that is commonly used in convection drying ovens according to reports in the literature). As shown in Figure 4, the temperature of one apple sample reached a peak temperature of 70 C in 3.7 minutes and had 50% of th...]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
