<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Collaborative research:  Mechanisms of reproductive, developmental, and early life stage impacts of marine oil spills in a vertebrate sentinel model</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>02/15/2013</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>01/31/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>298080.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>298080</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>06040300</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>GEO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>OCE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Ocean Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Henrietta Edmonds</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>hedmonds@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927427</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Marine oil spills can release large volumes of persistently toxic chemicals into the environment, and many large active oil fields are in close proximity to high-density coastal human populations where humans can be exposed through clean-up and remediation efforts, through contact with oiled media in popular vacation areas, and through the food chain. Despite many large oil spills in recent years close to populated regions, and a few studies testing for acute and psychological impacts in humans, remarkably little is known of the medium and long-term health impacts of oil spills on important biological processes such as reproduction, development, growth, and performance. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;In this project, a research team from the University of California at Davis, the Louisiana State University Agricultural Center, and the Louisiana State University and A &amp; M College will explore the biological impact of the Deepwater Horizon oil spill to study such effects. They will use the Gulf killifish as a sentinel animal model because they offer an opportunity to carefully link cause with effect by virtue of their relatively short life cycle, a well-provisioned molecular and physiological toolkit, their local residence and well-documented exposure to the event in the field, and because they are tractable for laboratory and field studies providing an opportunity to verify predicted effects in the real world. Fish are established models for human health and development, and killifish are particularly appropriate for studying consequences of the DWH oil spill specifically because they are abundant, local, and non-migratory residents of Gulf of Mexico regions directly affected by the spill event. The team already has evidence that killifish were exposed and affected by the event. Now their objectives are to test for oil spill effects at various sensitive stages of the vertebrate life cycle including effects that span generations, to characterize the spatial and temporal extent of vertebrate risk from the spill, and to test for the influence of individual and population genetic variation on sensitivity to oil pollution. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Broader Impacts: There remains a clear deficiency in our understanding of health effects from hydrocarbon exposures that emerge over the medium and long term.  This research will offer insight into risk and mechanisms of oil spill impacts in a vertebrate model, offer biomarkers predictive or reflective of impaired biological processes, and accelerate the discovery of genetic and physiological risk factors. The project will support the training of PhD students and undergraduate researchers. PhD students from both LSU and UC-Davis will participate in EnvironMentors, a program that pairs graduate students with students from local high schools for an academic year, during which time participants are guided in the completion of an independent research project to be presented as a scientific poster at a local science fair. The LSU group will also present these posters and other summarized research results at Ocean Commotion, a yearly event organized by the Louisiana Sea Grant College Program, which attract thousands of local K-8 students. Given the socio-economical landscape of Louisiana, a diverse elementary school and undergraduate student body will be engaged by these outreach efforts. Furthermore, undergraduate research participation of groups that are historically underrepresented in the sciences will be supported through programs offered by the Howard Hughes Medical Institute (LSU), the Louisiana Alliance for Minority Participation (LSU), and Aggie Ambassadors program (UC Davis). &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;JOINT FUNDING BY NSF AND NIEHS:  The original proposal on which this project is based (R01 ES021934-01) was submitted to the National Institutes of Environmental Health Sciences (NIH/NIEHS) in response to Funding Opportunity Announcement RFA-ES-11-013 , "Oceans, Great Lakes and Human Health (R01)", an opportunity jointly sponsored by NSF.   This project is cooperatively funded through separate awards from NSF and NIEHS.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>02/12/2013</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>02/02/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.050</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1314466</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Christopher</FirstName>
<LastName>Green</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>C</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Christopher C Green</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>ccgree@gmail.com</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2255788231</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000536069</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>02/12/2013</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Louisiana State University Agricultural Center</Name>
<CityName>Baton Rouge</CityName>
<ZipCode>708030100</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2255786030</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>Corner of Highland and Parker</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[104 J. Norman Efferson Hall]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Louisiana</StateName>
<StateCode>LA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>06</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>LA06</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>783201833</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>LOUISIANA STATE UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>940050792</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Louisiana State University Agricultural Center]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>LA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>708206103</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Louisiana</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>06</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>LA06</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>8028</Code>
<Text>Oceans &amp; Human Health</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>5987</Code>
<Text>GULF OF MEXICO OIL SPILL-2010</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7696</Code>
<Text>ENVIRONMENT, HEALTH &amp; SAFETY</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0113</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0114</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0115</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0116</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2013~76640</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~73826</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2015~73139</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2016~74475</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>We used Gulf killifish, a common fish within many estuarine environments throughout the Gulf of Mexico, to determine impacts of oil exposure on reproduction and parental investment throughout multiple generations. Parents were exposed to oil via the creation of water accommodated fractions (WAF) which resulted in total polycyclic aromatic hydrocarbons ranging between 20-40 ug/L across a 40 day exposure periods.&nbsp; Male testes size was significantly reduced in fishes exposed to oil. Throughout this period sperm motility and concentration were reduced but were not statistically significant.&nbsp; Female egg output throughout a 40 day spawning period was not different between the oil and control groups, however, a significantly greater number of embryos failed to hatch from females that were previously exposed to oil. &nbsp;We determined larval fitness by calculating a survival activity index, which consists of assessing the amount of yolk and time each larva can live before they expire from starvation. Larvae from oil treated adults resulted in significantly lower survival activity index values indicating that they would require food earlier to survive. &nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>Fish produce mucus on their skin to protect them in the water and this mucus potentially contains information about their health and reproductive status. Collection of this mucus from fish proved to be a way to measure the effects of oil exposures. We investigated the use of mucus as an effective and non-lethal alternative to determine concentrations of 11-ketotestosterone (11-KT) and vitellogenin (VTG) of <em>F. grandis </em>through comparative assays with blood plasma.&nbsp; We determined that a significant positive relationship was present between the mucus and blood plasma concentrations for both 11-KT and VTG. The collection of mucus from these small fishes allows for multiple collections across time. Survival rate for the fish in these studies was high (&gt;95%), illustrating the potential for this technique to be more widely adopted for use in fishes, especially with rare or endangered populations when blood sampling and excessive handling can be problematic and in instances when carrying out a repeated sampling regime. &nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>It appears that populations with a history of exposure to certain pollutants have different resistance to future pollutant exposure. Different Gulf killifish populations were collected from sites representing historically contaminated, historically &lsquo;clean&rsquo;, or &lsquo;reference&rsquo; sites. The contaminated site included Vince Bayou, TX characterized as a U.S. Superfund site with a long history of organic contamination with &lsquo;clean&rsquo; and reference sites included Gangs Bayou, TX. These populations of <em>F. grandis </em>with different exposure histories were exposed to WAF for 60 days, and followed 40 additional days after WAF treatments.&nbsp; Males appeared to show adaptations to PAH exposure, with WAF exposed males from Vince Bayou (superfund site) resulting in increased 11-KT concentrations while Gangs Bayou exposed males (reference site) had an expected decrease in 11-KT concentrations. &nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>The impact of prior oil exposures on resulting larvae and sexually mature adults was examined further by creating a two-generation examination that exposed adults and their offspring to oil compounds. &nbsp;For this work we exposed oil to adult Gulf killifish and examined the resulting young then allowed those young to be reared in a clean environment to adulthood.&nbsp; We then performed a 40 oil exposure similar to the oil exposure their parents encountered.&nbsp; Eggs produced from the initial oil exposed parents had significantly thinner egg shells when examined via histology.&nbsp; Similar to our previous work on sperm quality we found that males exposed to oil had significantly reduced sperm concentrations.&nbsp; Although these could potentially impact the number viable embryos, there were no differences in the numbers of embryos produced or hatched from these parents. Larvae produced from parents that were exposed to oil survived fewer days after hatch, indicating that they would be possibly more susceptible to starvation in the wild. After these progeny reached sexual maturity we exposed them to naphthalene for 40 days and determined how they responded via liver detoxifying enzymes and mucus immune defense.&nbsp; The activity of a biomarker for liver breakdown of PAHs (known as 7-ethoxy-resorufin-O-deethylase) was significantly increased in groups of killifish that underwent exposure to naphthalene compared to their control counterparts. There were no significant interactions among the effects of time, treatment, or parental history. When we examined an enzyme in the mucus associated with immune defense (lysozyme) we found that that Naphthalene exposed individuals from control parents were significantly different in mucosal lysozyme when compared to mucosal lysozyme of naphthalene exposed individuals with WAF exposed parents but were not significantly different from their respective control treatments.&nbsp; The results of this study suggest that within the F<sub>1</sub> generation there is some degree of reproductive impairment in Gulf killifish undergoing a chronic WAF exposure to crude oil. For the next generation, there is evidence of limited alteration to PAH tolerance within two generations of exposure to PAHs as demonstrated by both liver function (EROD) and lysozyme activity within the mucus.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 04/27/2018<br>      Modified by: Christopher&nbsp;C&nbsp;Green</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ We used Gulf killifish, a common fish within many estuarine environments throughout the Gulf of Mexico, to determine impacts of oil exposure on reproduction and parental investment throughout multiple generations. Parents were exposed to oil via the creation of water accommodated fractions (WAF) which resulted in total polycyclic aromatic hydrocarbons ranging between 20-40 ug/L across a 40 day exposure periods.  Male testes size was significantly reduced in fishes exposed to oil. Throughout this period sperm motility and concentration were reduced but were not statistically significant.  Female egg output throughout a 40 day spawning period was not different between the oil and control groups, however, a significantly greater number of embryos failed to hatch from females that were previously exposed to oil.  We determined larval fitness by calculating a survival activity index, which consists of assessing the amount of yolk and time each larva can live before they expire from starvation. Larvae from oil treated adults resulted in significantly lower survival activity index values indicating that they would require food earlier to survive.       Fish produce mucus on their skin to protect them in the water and this mucus potentially contains information about their health and reproductive status. Collection of this mucus from fish proved to be a way to measure the effects of oil exposures. We investigated the use of mucus as an effective and non-lethal alternative to determine concentrations of 11-ketotestosterone (11-KT) and vitellogenin (VTG) of F. grandis through comparative assays with blood plasma.  We determined that a significant positive relationship was present between the mucus and blood plasma concentrations for both 11-KT and VTG. The collection of mucus from these small fishes allows for multiple collections across time. Survival rate for the fish in these studies was high (&gt;95%), illustrating the potential for this technique to be more widely adopted for use in fishes, especially with rare or endangered populations when blood sampling and excessive handling can be problematic and in instances when carrying out a repeated sampling regime.       It appears that populations with a history of exposure to certain pollutants have different resistance to future pollutant exposure. Different Gulf killifish populations were collected from sites representing historically contaminated, historically ?clean?, or ?reference? sites. The contaminated site included Vince Bayou, TX characterized as a U.S. Superfund site with a long history of organic contamination with ?clean? and reference sites included Gangs Bayou, TX. These populations of F. grandis with different exposure histories were exposed to WAF for 60 days, and followed 40 additional days after WAF treatments.  Males appeared to show adaptations to PAH exposure, with WAF exposed males from Vince Bayou (superfund site) resulting in increased 11-KT concentrations while Gangs Bayou exposed males (reference site) had an expected decrease in 11-KT concentrations.       The impact of prior oil exposures on resulting larvae and sexually mature adults was examined further by creating a two-generation examination that exposed adults and their offspring to oil compounds.  For this work we exposed oil to adult Gulf killifish and examined the resulting young then allowed those young to be reared in a clean environment to adulthood.  We then performed a 40 oil exposure similar to the oil exposure their parents encountered.  Eggs produced from the initial oil exposed parents had significantly thinner egg shells when examined via histology.  Similar to our previous work on sperm quality we found that males exposed to oil had significantly reduced sperm concentrations.  Although these could potentially impact the number viable embryos, there were no differences in the numbers of embryos produced or hatched from these parents. Larvae produced from parents that were exposed to oil survived fewer days after hatch, indicating that they would be possibly more susceptible to starvation in the wild. After these progeny reached sexual maturity we exposed them to naphthalene for 40 days and determined how they responded via liver detoxifying enzymes and mucus immune defense.  The activity of a biomarker for liver breakdown of PAHs (known as 7-ethoxy-resorufin-O-deethylase) was significantly increased in groups of killifish that underwent exposure to naphthalene compared to their control counterparts. There were no significant interactions among the effects of time, treatment, or parental history. When we examined an enzyme in the mucus associated with immune defense (lysozyme) we found that that Naphthalene exposed individuals from control parents were significantly different in mucosal lysozyme when compared to mucosal lysozyme of naphthalene exposed individuals with WAF exposed parents but were not significantly different from their respective control treatments.  The results of this study suggest that within the F1 generation there is some degree of reproductive impairment in Gulf killifish undergoing a chronic WAF exposure to crude oil. For the next generation, there is evidence of limited alteration to PAH tolerance within two generations of exposure to PAHs as demonstrated by both liver function (EROD) and lysozyme activity within the mucus.          Last Modified: 04/27/2018       Submitted by: Christopher C Green]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
