<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>EAGER: US-Ireland Femtojoule-per-bit Communications with Nanopillar Lasers on Si</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2013</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2016</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>160000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>160000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07010000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>ECCS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Electrical, Commun &amp; Cyber Sys</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Dominique Dagenais</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>ddagenai@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922980</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Objective: This proposal brings together an international US-Ireland team of scientists at University of California Los Angeles (UCLA),  the Cork Institute of Technology (CIT), and Queen's University Belfast (QUB) to explore a bottom-up approach to electrically-driven photonic crystal lasers (PCLs) using III-V nano-pillars (NP) grown on Si. This proposal presents a unique set of capabilities to remove deficiencies in NP characterization, making it possible to develop NP lasers to their potential. &lt;br/&gt;Intellectual merit: The NP-PCLs have been engineered to surpass the necessary 10 fJ/bit requirement for inter-chip communication by implementing a high-Q, small current aperture cavity with greater than 90% waveguide coupling efficiency. With this international collaboration a rapid development process is possible, where NP growth and device fabrication is performed at UCLA, pump-probe spectroscopy and emission dynamics is performed at TNI, and atom probe tomography and scanning Raman spectroscopy at QUB. The combined effort of the groups will allow researchers to quickly characterize material quality and gain, and evaluate device designs.&lt;br/&gt;Broader impacts: The cooperative interaction between the US and Ireland allows for a comprehensive project going much further than would be possible for any individual partner. The participating groups will exchange best practices in areas involving interdisciplinary research, student involvement in research, and community participation.  These themes are supported by several efforts to incorporate the findings into nano-materials curricula, train graduate, undergraduate and high school students, and form a concerted effort aimed at increasing minority student participation both in the US and Ireland.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>04/08/2013</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>04/08/2013</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1314253</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Diana</FirstName>
<LastName>Huffaker</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Diana Huffaker</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>dianah@uta.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>3103027841</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000422393</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/08/2013</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of California-Los Angeles</Name>
<CityName>LOS ANGELES</CityName>
<ZipCode>900951406</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>3107940102</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>10889 Wilshire Boulevard</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[Suite 700]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>33</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CA33</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>092530369</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF CALIFORNIA, LOS ANGELES</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>071549000</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[UCLA Electrical Engineering Department]]></Name>
<CityName>Los Angeles</CityName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>900951594</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[405 Westwood Plaza, 18-141 Engr4]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>33</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CA33</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1517</Code>
<Text>EPMD-ElectrnPhoton&amp;MagnDevices</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>103E</Code>
<Text>Energy efficient electronics</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7916</Code>
<Text>EAGER</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0113</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2013~160000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The <strong>intellectual merit</strong> of this project is addressed by the scientific discoveries enabled by the international collaboration between research groups in the U.S. and Ireland. These teams brought together unique expertise in material growth, ultra-fast spectroscopy, and micro-raman characterization to elucidate and overcome the limitations of III-V nanopillars grown on Silicon substrates. As a result of this effort, the collaborators have been able to quantify the quality of the nanopillar material and correlate these finding to specific aspects of the material growth. This ability has led to the development of an in-situ surface passivation technique capable of producing nanopillars with carrier lifetimes that are comparable to bulk materials, as well as the development of nanopillars on Silicon substrates with similar performance. This technique was applied to the growth of nanopillars on Silicon-on-Insulator substrates, an essential requirement for photonic integration, to realize high-uniformity and high-quality nanopillar arrays on optical waveguides.</p> <p>The <strong>broader impacts</strong> of this project have been addressed at several levels, including K-12 community outreach, undergraduate and graduate research experience, and international collaboration producing culturally progressive scientists. The graduate students involved in this project participate in outreach programs organized by the California Nano-Systems Institute at UCLA, as well as spend significant time in mentoring undergraduate students. The PIs are committed to inclusion and participation of under-represented minorities (URM) in research. Several URM undergraduate and graduate students involved in this project received both research training in technical laboratory skills and mentoring in professional development. Furthermore, students funded by this project have engaged in international collaboration and exchange. Finally, the research outcomes of this project have led to significant advancements in the ability to produce high-quality III-V nanomaterials on Silicon substrates. These findings will enable further research and development to achieve high-performance III-V nano-devices on Silicon.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 11/02/2016<br>      Modified by: Diana&nbsp;Huffaker</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The intellectual merit of this project is addressed by the scientific discoveries enabled by the international collaboration between research groups in the U.S. and Ireland. These teams brought together unique expertise in material growth, ultra-fast spectroscopy, and micro-raman characterization to elucidate and overcome the limitations of III-V nanopillars grown on Silicon substrates. As a result of this effort, the collaborators have been able to quantify the quality of the nanopillar material and correlate these finding to specific aspects of the material growth. This ability has led to the development of an in-situ surface passivation technique capable of producing nanopillars with carrier lifetimes that are comparable to bulk materials, as well as the development of nanopillars on Silicon substrates with similar performance. This technique was applied to the growth of nanopillars on Silicon-on-Insulator substrates, an essential requirement for photonic integration, to realize high-uniformity and high-quality nanopillar arrays on optical waveguides.  The broader impacts of this project have been addressed at several levels, including K-12 community outreach, undergraduate and graduate research experience, and international collaboration producing culturally progressive scientists. The graduate students involved in this project participate in outreach programs organized by the California Nano-Systems Institute at UCLA, as well as spend significant time in mentoring undergraduate students. The PIs are committed to inclusion and participation of under-represented minorities (URM) in research. Several URM undergraduate and graduate students involved in this project received both research training in technical laboratory skills and mentoring in professional development. Furthermore, students funded by this project have engaged in international collaboration and exchange. Finally, the research outcomes of this project have led to significant advancements in the ability to produce high-quality III-V nanomaterials on Silicon substrates. These findings will enable further research and development to achieve high-performance III-V nano-devices on Silicon.          Last Modified: 11/02/2016       Submitted by: Diana Huffaker]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
