<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Collaborative Research:  Characterizing the Roles of Atmospheric Structure and Clouds on the Radiation and Precipitation Budgets at Summit, Greenland</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>10/01/2013</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>09/30/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>140409.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>140409</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>06090100</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>GEO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>OPP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Office of Polar Programs (OPP)</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Cynthia Suchman</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>csuchman@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922092</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Funds are provided to characterize the interactions among the atmospheric state, cloud properties, radiation, and precipitation at Summit, Greenland. The objective is to investigate a number of important cloud-related processes, how these interact with the Arctic climate system, and their impact on the surface energy and mass budgets. Specific foci will include:&lt;br/&gt;1) Low-cloud persistence mechanisms that lead to long-lived Arctic stratiform clouds, which interact strongly with the atmospheric structure and surface energy budget;&lt;br/&gt;2) Cloud-phase partitioning, which determines the cloud microphysical composition and, ultimately, the effects that clouds have on atmospheric radiation and the hydrologic cycle; and&lt;br/&gt;3) Precipitation partitioning, in order to understand the different modes of precipitation at Summit and how these impact the total surface accumulation.&lt;br/&gt;To address these topics, this project will utilize detailed observations from a suite of ground-based remote sensors deployed at Summit as part of the NSF/AON-funded ICECAPS project in combination with data from satellite-borne active remote sensors. High-resolution numerical modeling will also be used to investigate many of the fine-scale cloud processes and their mesoscale influences. These studies over the Greenland Ice Sheet will also be considered within the context of similar measurements and model studies made at other Arctic locations in order to understand these important processes over Summit and, in a more general sense, across the Arctic.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Atmospheric water vapor, clouds, and precipitation greatly affect the surface energy and cryospheric mass balances in the Arctic, and are responsible for much of the variability in these balances. It is thought that recent rapid melting of Arctic sea ice may be driven, in part, by changes in cloud cover and radiation. Cloud-related processes and feedbacks are known to be one of the greatest sources of uncertainty in global climate models, and these shortcomings have been clearly identified in model simulations over the Arctic.  Thus, the results of this project should improve our understanding of Arctic cloud processes and their inclusion in climate models, which, in turn, will improve predictability.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt; As broader impacts of this research, the project will provide important data analysis and integration experience for four new graduate students at the participating universities. In addition, data and results from this study will be integrated into undergraduate coursework and summer workshops for high school students and teachers.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/21/2013</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/21/2013</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.078</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1314358</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>David</FirstName>
<LastName>Turner</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>D</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>David D Turner</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>dave.turner@noaa.gov</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>3034976097</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000412350</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/21/2013</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Oklahoma Norman Campus</Name>
<CityName>NORMAN</CityName>
<ZipCode>730199705</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>4053254757</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>201 Stephenson Parkway</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[Five Partners Place, Suite 3100]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Oklahoma</StateName>
<StateCode>OK</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>OK04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>848348348</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF OKLAHOMA</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>046862181</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Oklahoma Norman Campus]]></Name>
<CityName>Norman</CityName>
<StateCode>OK</StateCode>
<ZipCode>730727304</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[120 David L. Boren Blvd.]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Oklahoma</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>OK04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>5280</Code>
<Text>ANS-Arctic Natural Sciences</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1079</Code>
<Text>ARCTIC RESEARCH</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>02XX</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2013~140409</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The National Science Foundation supported a long-term observation program called the&nbsp;Integrated Characterization of Energy, Clouds, Atmospheric state, and Precipitation at Summit (ICECAPS) Project.&nbsp;&nbsp;ICECAPS deployed an extensive array of in-situ and advanced ground-based remote sensors to Summit Station in the center of the Greenland Ice Sheet in July 2010 to make detailed observations of cloud and precipitation properties, the thermodynamic and kinematic evolution of the troposphere, and downwelling radiative energy at the surface.&nbsp;&nbsp;The ICECAPS project is currently scheduled to continue collecting these observations at least until the summer of 2020.&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>This project (&ldquo;<em>Collaborative Research: Characterizing the Roles of Atmospheric Structure and Clouds on the Radiation and Precipitation Budgets at Summit, Greenland</em>&rdquo;) has utilized the ICECAPS observations to perform a wide range of research into different phenomena.&nbsp;&nbsp;To date, over 30 scientific papers have been published as part of this project.&nbsp;&nbsp;Some of the high-level research accomplishments include:&nbsp;</p> <ul> <li>Development of the first comprehensive observationally-based characterization of the surface energy budget at Summit, and how the different components (e.g., radiation, sensible heating, etc) evolve over the annual cycle</li> <li>Performed an in-depth study of the melt event in July 2012, wherein over 95% of the Greenland ice sheet experienced melting, and demonstrated the critical role that liquid-bearing clouds played in enhancing the radiative energy at the surface that contributed to the melt</li> <li>Characterized the snowfall rates and properties at Summit, and how the snowfall changes with large scale weather patterns</li> <li>Investigated how the lifetime and microphysical properties of long-lived mixed-phase clouds depends on the large-scale mesoscale environment</li> <li>Characterized the downwelling spectral infrared radiative flux at Summit, and how a model reanalysis compares with the ICECAPS observations</li> <li>Improved the accuracy of liquid water absorption models in the microwave, which greatly improves the accuracy of space-based observations of cloud properties</li> </ul> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>This research was conducted by a research team that spanned across six universities (University of Colorado, Washington State University, University of Wisconsin-Madison, Vanderbilt University, University of Oklahoma, University of&nbsp;&nbsp;Idaho), and included researchers from national laboratories such as NOAA&rsquo;s Earth System Research Laboratory and DOE&rsquo;s Argonne National Laboratory.&nbsp;&nbsp;In addition, 15 graduate students at these universities were involved in this research.&nbsp;&nbsp;These students gained valuable insights into Arctic processes, experience working with observational data, developing and applying higher-order data processing algorithms, and conducting scientific analyses. Many of these students have also spent time in the field, which has enriched their graduate education experience and will support their development as young scientists.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 01/29/2019<br>      Modified by: David&nbsp;D&nbsp;Turner</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The National Science Foundation supported a long-term observation program called the Integrated Characterization of Energy, Clouds, Atmospheric state, and Precipitation at Summit (ICECAPS) Project.  ICECAPS deployed an extensive array of in-situ and advanced ground-based remote sensors to Summit Station in the center of the Greenland Ice Sheet in July 2010 to make detailed observations of cloud and precipitation properties, the thermodynamic and kinematic evolution of the troposphere, and downwelling radiative energy at the surface.  The ICECAPS project is currently scheduled to continue collecting these observations at least until the summer of 2020.      This project ("Collaborative Research: Characterizing the Roles of Atmospheric Structure and Clouds on the Radiation and Precipitation Budgets at Summit, Greenland") has utilized the ICECAPS observations to perform a wide range of research into different phenomena.  To date, over 30 scientific papers have been published as part of this project.  Some of the high-level research accomplishments include:   Development of the first comprehensive observationally-based characterization of the surface energy budget at Summit, and how the different components (e.g., radiation, sensible heating, etc) evolve over the annual cycle Performed an in-depth study of the melt event in July 2012, wherein over 95% of the Greenland ice sheet experienced melting, and demonstrated the critical role that liquid-bearing clouds played in enhancing the radiative energy at the surface that contributed to the melt Characterized the snowfall rates and properties at Summit, and how the snowfall changes with large scale weather patterns Investigated how the lifetime and microphysical properties of long-lived mixed-phase clouds depends on the large-scale mesoscale environment Characterized the downwelling spectral infrared radiative flux at Summit, and how a model reanalysis compares with the ICECAPS observations Improved the accuracy of liquid water absorption models in the microwave, which greatly improves the accuracy of space-based observations of cloud properties      This research was conducted by a research team that spanned across six universities (University of Colorado, Washington State University, University of Wisconsin-Madison, Vanderbilt University, University of Oklahoma, University of  Idaho), and included researchers from national laboratories such as NOAA?s Earth System Research Laboratory and DOE?s Argonne National Laboratory.  In addition, 15 graduate students at these universities were involved in this research.  These students gained valuable insights into Arctic processes, experience working with observational data, developing and applying higher-order data processing algorithms, and conducting scientific analyses. Many of these students have also spent time in the field, which has enriched their graduate education experience and will support their development as young scientists.          Last Modified: 01/29/2019       Submitted by: David D Turner]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
