<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>RAPID: Identifying and Modeling the Interdependencies of Restoration Efforts across Infrastructures</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>02/01/2013</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>01/31/2015</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>31500.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>31500</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CMMI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Civil, Mechanical, &amp; Manufact Inn</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Dennis Wenger</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The objective of this Rapid Research Grant (RAPID) award is to investigate the concept of restoration interdependencies amongst infrastructure systems in responding to extreme events.  A restoration interdependency is defined as the need for an infrastructure manager to consider the restoration efforts of another infrastructure in decision-making about his or her infrastructure's restoration.  For example, debris may need to be cleared from an area prior to rebuilding or replacing power lines in that area.  This would imply a precedence interdependency between the debris removal and the power infrastructure: an event needs to occur in the debris removal prior to an event (the rebuilding) starting in the power infrastructure's restoration efforts.  This research seeks to identify, classify, and determine the frequency of restoration interdependencies after Hurricane Sandy by (1) interviewing infrastructure managers involved in the restoration efforts and (2) analyzing electronic media.   &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The results of this research will contribute to the resiliency of a community by enhancing our knowledge of what an infrastructure manager must consider in determining an infrastructure's restoration efforts.  This analysis will help infrastructure managers better understand the level of coordination or information-sharing required across restoration efforts in order to take into account these restoration interdependencies.  It will further help determine how restoration efforts should be planned to robustly handle restoration interdependencies, thereby shortening the time required for the restoration of vital services after an extreme event.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>01/18/2013</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>01/18/2013</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1314350</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Joe</FirstName>
<LastName>Chow</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>H</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Joe H Chow</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>chowj@rpi.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5182766374</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000387088</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>01/18/2013</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>William</FirstName>
<LastName>Wallace</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>A</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>William A Wallace</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>wallaw@rpi.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5182766854</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000180395</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>01/18/2013</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>John</FirstName>
<LastName>Mitchell</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>E</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>John E Mitchell</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>mitchj@rpi.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON/>
<NSF_ID>000124876</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>01/18/2013</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Thomas</FirstName>
<LastName>Sharkey</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Thomas Sharkey</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>tcshark@clemson.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>8646567891</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000526318</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>01/18/2013</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Rensselaer Polytechnic Institute</Name>
<CityName>Troy</CityName>
<ZipCode>121803522</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5182766000</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>110 8TH ST</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>20</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NY20</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>002430742</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>RENSSELAER POLYTECHNIC INSTITUTE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>002430742</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Rensselaer Polytechnic Institute]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<ZipCode>121803522</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>20</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NY20</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1638</Code>
<Text>HDBE-Humans, Disasters, and th</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>036E</Code>
<Text>CIVIL INFRASTRUCTURE</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>041E</Code>
<Text>HAZARD AND DISASTER REDUCTION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>042E</Code>
<Text>HAZARD AND DISASTER RESPONSE</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1576</Code>
<Text>NATIONL EARTHQK HZRD REDCT PRG</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7914</Code>
<Text>RAPID</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8293</Code>
<Text>Hurricane Sandy</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0113</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2013~31500</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The outcome of this research is a deeper understanding of the new concept of <em>restoration interdependencies</em> across infrastructures after a large-scale disruptive event impacts an area, like Hurricane Sandy impacted New York and New Jersey in October 2012.&nbsp; Restoration interdependences occur whenever a restoration task in one infrastructure is impacted by a restoration task (or lack thereof) in a different infrastructure.&nbsp; &nbsp;For example, the clearing of downed trees from a street (in the road infrastructure) may not be able to start until a power crew inspects and removes downed power lines from the street.&nbsp; This situation represents a precedence relationship where a task in the power infrastructure needs to be completed before a task in the road infrastructure can begin.&nbsp;&nbsp; Restoration interdependencies then <em>link</em> the restoration efforts of multiple infrastructures which could drive the need for communication and coordination across these efforts.&nbsp;</p> <p>This project identified five classes of restoration interdependencies by cataloging incidents of them which occurred after Hurricane Sandy.&nbsp;&nbsp; The focus of this effort was on incidents reported by major newspapers in the impacted areas. &nbsp;&nbsp;The identification of these different classes has provided an improved situational awareness of&nbsp; interdependent infrastructure restoration efforts and the various factors that could impact the timeline of an individual system&rsquo;s restoration efforts.&nbsp; In addition, knowledge of these interdependencies will make achievable the most effective coordination and information-sharing mechanisms among different systems in order to mitigate their impact.&nbsp; In addition to identifying these classes of restoration interdependencies, this project also created new computational models and algorithms in order to determine the <em>loss</em> in restoration effectiveness resulting from decentralization in interdependent infrastructure restoration and the reduction in this loss that results from <em>information-sharing</em> among infrastructures.&nbsp; &nbsp;&nbsp;Computational results of applying these models and algorithms to realistically constructed data sets &nbsp;have shown that information-sharing can mitigate the loss in restoration effectiveness resulting from decentralization by up to forty percent.&nbsp;&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 03/04/2015<br>      Modified by: Thomas&nbsp;Sharkey</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The outcome of this research is a deeper understanding of the new concept of restoration interdependencies across infrastructures after a large-scale disruptive event impacts an area, like Hurricane Sandy impacted New York and New Jersey in October 2012.  Restoration interdependences occur whenever a restoration task in one infrastructure is impacted by a restoration task (or lack thereof) in a different infrastructure.   For example, the clearing of downed trees from a street (in the road infrastructure) may not be able to start until a power crew inspects and removes downed power lines from the street.  This situation represents a precedence relationship where a task in the power infrastructure needs to be completed before a task in the road infrastructure can begin.   Restoration interdependencies then link the restoration efforts of multiple infrastructures which could drive the need for communication and coordination across these efforts.   This project identified five classes of restoration interdependencies by cataloging incidents of them which occurred after Hurricane Sandy.   The focus of this effort was on incidents reported by major newspapers in the impacted areas.   The identification of these different classes has provided an improved situational awareness of  interdependent infrastructure restoration efforts and the various factors that could impact the timeline of an individual systemÆs restoration efforts.  In addition, knowledge of these interdependencies will make achievable the most effective coordination and information-sharing mechanisms among different systems in order to mitigate their impact.  In addition to identifying these classes of restoration interdependencies, this project also created new computational models and algorithms in order to determine the loss in restoration effectiveness resulting from decentralization in interdependent infrastructure restoration and the reduction in this loss that results from information-sharing among infrastructures.    Computational results of applying these models and algorithms to realistically constructed data sets  have shown that information-sharing can mitigate the loss in restoration effectiveness resulting from decentralization by up to forty percent.            Last Modified: 03/04/2015       Submitted by: Thomas Sharkey]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
