<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Physics Theorynet Outreach Program</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2013</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2015</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>12000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>12000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03010000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>PHY</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Physics</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Keith Dienes</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>kdienes@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032925314</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This awards funds the Physics TheoryNet outreach program coordinated by Professors Tomasz R. Taylor and Brent D. Nelson at Northeastern University in Boston.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The main component of Physics TheoryNet is direct interaction between Greater Boston area theoretical physicists and high-school students, through lecture presentations, demonstrations and question-and-answer sessions during regular class hours and after classes. Presentation topics include physics in the news (such as dark energy or the Large Hadron Collider), traditional subjects of interest to young science students (such as black holes, time travel or extra dimensions), or concepts related to the high-school physics curriculum. The program also promotes physics as a field of study when students go on to college. Teachers and physicists gather each semester at Northeastern University to arrange visits, share experiences and develop a learning community.   The TheoryNet program also has a broader impact on Greater Boston area communities by increasing students' understanding of science and raising the awareness of the importance of fundamental research.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>09/06/2013</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>09/06/2013</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1314392</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Tomasz</FirstName>
<LastName>Taylor</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>R</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Tomasz R Taylor</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>taylor@neu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6174372940</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000298958</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/06/2013</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Brent</FirstName>
<LastName>Nelson</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>D</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Brent D Nelson</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>B.Nelson@neu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6173735600</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000440921</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/06/2013</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Northeastern University</Name>
<CityName>BOSTON</CityName>
<ZipCode>021155005</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6173733004</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>360 HUNTINGTON AVE</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[177-500]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
<StateCode>MA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MA07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>001423631</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>NORTHEASTERN UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>001423631</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Northeastern University]]></Name>
<CityName>Boston</CityName>
<StateCode>MA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>021155005</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[360 Huntington Ave]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MA07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1286</Code>
<Text>Elem. Particle Physics/Theory</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0113</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2013~12000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The grant supported outreach activities of Physics Theorynet - a network of ten physics faculty paired with ten high school teachers working in the larger Boston area, including eastern Massachusetts, Rhode Island and southern New Hampshire. Every year, each physicist visited two or more high school physics classes, typically at the senior level. Physicists gave presentations on various research topics in theoretical physics, often on those covered in newspapers' science sections: black holes, dark matter, time travel, Higgs particle discovery at the Large Hadron Collider etc. They answered questions and ran live demonstrations related to the physics concepts discussed in the presentations. For example, the electron motion in a magnetic field created by a Helmholtz coil was used to illustrate the role of magnets at the Large Hadron Collider. Bubble chambers were used to visualize elementary particles. Physicists also described what are the daily activities of research scientists and how progress is made in science, drawing on illustrations from their own experiences. The purpose of visits was to present physics as a vibrant science with numerous technological applications and to explain the nature of scientific discovery. The outcomes were discussed at joint meetings of teachers and physicists held at the beginning of each semester at Northeastern University.<br />Over three years, more than five thousand Boston area students met with Theorynet physicists. The outcomes of Theorynet outreach activities were documented in student questionnaires and in teachers' reports.There is evidence that following the visits, students have a much more positive view of a potential career in science. The focus on the cutting edge science appeals to the interests of students and creates much more engagement in physics. The visits by female physicists offered a role model for the young women considering STEM careers. There is also evidence that Theorynet not only provides a fruitful context for teaching about modern physics but also about the nature of the scientific enterprise more generally. The program increased students' understanding of science and raised their awarness of the importance of fundamental research.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 09/17/2015<br>      Modified by: Tomasz&nbsp;R&nbsp;Taylor</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The grant supported outreach activities of Physics Theorynet - a network of ten physics faculty paired with ten high school teachers working in the larger Boston area, including eastern Massachusetts, Rhode Island and southern New Hampshire. Every year, each physicist visited two or more high school physics classes, typically at the senior level. Physicists gave presentations on various research topics in theoretical physics, often on those covered in newspapers' science sections: black holes, dark matter, time travel, Higgs particle discovery at the Large Hadron Collider etc. They answered questions and ran live demonstrations related to the physics concepts discussed in the presentations. For example, the electron motion in a magnetic field created by a Helmholtz coil was used to illustrate the role of magnets at the Large Hadron Collider. Bubble chambers were used to visualize elementary particles. Physicists also described what are the daily activities of research scientists and how progress is made in science, drawing on illustrations from their own experiences. The purpose of visits was to present physics as a vibrant science with numerous technological applications and to explain the nature of scientific discovery. The outcomes were discussed at joint meetings of teachers and physicists held at the beginning of each semester at Northeastern University. Over three years, more than five thousand Boston area students met with Theorynet physicists. The outcomes of Theorynet outreach activities were documented in student questionnaires and in teachers' reports.There is evidence that following the visits, students have a much more positive view of a potential career in science. The focus on the cutting edge science appeals to the interests of students and creates much more engagement in physics. The visits by female physicists offered a role model for the young women considering STEM careers. There is also evidence that Theorynet not only provides a fruitful context for teaching about modern physics but also about the nature of the scientific enterprise more generally. The program increased students' understanding of science and raised their awarness of the importance of fundamental research.       Last Modified: 09/17/2015       Submitted by: Tomasz R Taylor]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
