<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>SBIR Phase I:  Adrenaline: A Browser-Based Platform for Mobile Enterprise Apps</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2013</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2014</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>150000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>179999</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07070000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>IIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Industrial Innovation &amp; Partnersh</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Prakash Balan</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>pbalan@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032925341</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This Small Business Innovation Research (SBIR) Phase I project addresses the challenges presented by increasing mobile device use in enterprises. These mobile devices are managed by employees, contain personal data, and use diverse hardware and software systems. The company developed a new web browser, which they built from the ground up specifically for mobile devices. The company's mission is to use their browser as a platform for enterprise developers to build and deploy cross-­platform enterprise-­class mobile web apps. The fundamental question this research will answer is whether a browser can be a suitable platform for hosting enterprise mobile apps. As such, this research has three primary objectives. (1) Advance the state-­of-­the-­art in mobile web app design methodology by developing new abstractions, such as web push and background execution, that enable mobile web apps to access native features in a platform independent way. (2) Develop a system that encapsulates enterprise mobile web apps and data securely, with management functions to enable information technology (IT) staff to manage enterprise apps, data, and users. (3) Implement advanced debugging tools for web app developers. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The broader impact/commercial potential of this project is in enabling enterprises to use mobile devices, such as smart phones and tablets, in the workplace to access company apps and data securely. Although mobile devices provide workers with ubiquitous access to enterprise apps and data, employees often use these mobile devices for work and in their personal lives. The company's technology provides a mechanism to encapsulate enterprise apps and data and to keep enterprise data separate from personal data. Overall the proposed technology makes it easier and more cost effective for enterprise developers to write pure HTML5 apps that run on a diverse set of mobile devices, gives users the freedom to use mobile devices for both work and for personal use, and provides IT administrators with complete control over enterprise apps and data. International Data Corporation (IDC) estimates that the market segment the company operates in - mobile enterprise app platforms - will reach $3 billion by 2015. By providing fundamental advances in mobile web browsers, development tools, and application services.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/21/2013</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>12/02/2013</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1315654</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Samuel</FirstName>
<LastName>King</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>T</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Samuel T King</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>sam@adrenalinebrowser.com</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2173726312</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000636088</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/21/2013</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Adrenaline Mobility</Name>
<CityName>Champaign</CityName>
<ZipCode>618207460</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2173726312</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>60 Hazelwood Drive</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Illinois</StateName>
<StateCode>IL</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>13</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>IL13</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>078544684</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>ADRENALINE MOBILITY, INC.</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Adrenaline Mobility]]></Name>
<CityName>Champaig</CityName>
<StateCode>IL</StateCode>
<ZipCode>618207460</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[60 Hazelwood Drive]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Illinois</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>13</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>IL13</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>5371</Code>
<Text>SBIR Phase I</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>153E</Code>
<Text>Wireless comm &amp; sig processing</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>5371</Code>
<Text>SMALL BUSINESS PHASE I</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8032</Code>
<Text>Software Services and Applications</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0113</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0114</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2013~150000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~29999</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p class="p1">Two ways businesses are cutting costs and enabling higher productivity are through cloud-based backend services and enterprise apps on mobile devices.&nbsp; This combination provides cost effective, scalable, and reliable backend services through the cloud and increasing access to enterprise data via mobile devices.&nbsp; However, many recent studies point to security as the most pressing concern for companies adopting this technology.&nbsp; The problem, according to the studies, is that companies are uncomfortable giving up control of their data and worry about data loss from the cloud or from lost or stolen mobile devices.</p> <p class="p1">Adrenaline&rsquo;s novel technology provides strong security for mobile apps.&nbsp; For security, Adrenaline uses military-grade end-to-end encryption to protect user&rsquo;s data before storing it on a mobile device and before sending it to cloud servers. This level of protection eliminates threats from malicious users, threats across the network, and threats from the cloud provider and their infrastructure itself. In fact, even the Adrenaline designers themselves are unable to read or tamper with their customer&rsquo;s data.&nbsp; Adrenaline&rsquo;s unique design enables enterprises to retain control of their data while gaining the scalability, reliability, and cost effectiveness of cloud-based backend services.</p> <p class="p1">Despite this unparalleled level of security, Adrenaline is still easy to use.&nbsp; Adrenaline provides a library that developers put in their apps.&nbsp; This library has simple APIs for enabling developers to store encrypted data seamlessly in the cloud, obviating the need for developers to deal with complex security issues like key management, encrypted query processing, or secure message passing.&nbsp; Adrenaline handles these complex security issues automatically in their library, enabling development teams with little or no security training to write secure mobile apps quickly.</p> <p class="p1">The first major outcome from this Phase I SBIR project is the Adrenaline.io system. Adrenaline.io is an implementation of the Adrenaline platform and includes a developer console where programmers can sign up for an account and monitor their app.&nbsp; It also includes libraries that developers can add to their web and mobile apps to access the Adrenaline platform easily.</p> <p class="p1">The second major outcome of this Phase I SBIR effort is the release of the Keys by Adrenaline product. Keys is a mobile app that stores passwords on a user&rsquo;s mobile phone. When the user wants to login to a website, the Keys app scans a QR code in their browser, which then logs them into the website automatically. The main competitive advantage of Keys is that it runs on top of the Adrenaline.io platform, which provides strong security for user's sensitive data and ensures that the data never leaves the user's phone. Keys is the first step towards transforming user's phones into their mobile identity and it brings passwords into the 21st century.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 02/03/2014<br>      Modified by: Samuel&nbsp;T&nbsp;King</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[Two ways businesses are cutting costs and enabling higher productivity are through cloud-based backend services and enterprise apps on mobile devices.  This combination provides cost effective, scalable, and reliable backend services through the cloud and increasing access to enterprise data via mobile devices.  However, many recent studies point to security as the most pressing concern for companies adopting this technology.  The problem, according to the studies, is that companies are uncomfortable giving up control of their data and worry about data loss from the cloud or from lost or stolen mobile devices. AdrenalineÆs novel technology provides strong security for mobile apps.  For security, Adrenaline uses military-grade end-to-end encryption to protect userÆs data before storing it on a mobile device and before sending it to cloud servers. This level of protection eliminates threats from malicious users, threats across the network, and threats from the cloud provider and their infrastructure itself. In fact, even the Adrenaline designers themselves are unable to read or tamper with their customerÆs data.  AdrenalineÆs unique design enables enterprises to retain control of their data while gaining the scalability, reliability, and cost effectiveness of cloud-based backend services. Despite this unparalleled level of security, Adrenaline is still easy to use.  Adrenaline provides a library that developers put in their apps.  This library has simple APIs for enabling developers to store encrypted data seamlessly in the cloud, obviating the need for developers to deal with complex security issues like key management, encrypted query processing, or secure message passing.  Adrenaline handles these complex security issues automatically in their library, enabling development teams with little or no security training to write secure mobile apps quickly. The first major outcome from this Phase I SBIR project is the Adrenaline.io system. Adrenaline.io is an implementation of the Adrenaline platform and includes a developer console where programmers can sign up for an account and monitor their app.  It also includes libraries that developers can add to their web and mobile apps to access the Adrenaline platform easily. The second major outcome of this Phase I SBIR effort is the release of the Keys by Adrenaline product. Keys is a mobile app that stores passwords on a userÆs mobile phone. When the user wants to login to a website, the Keys app scans a QR code in their browser, which then logs them into the website automatically. The main competitive advantage of Keys is that it runs on top of the Adrenaline.io platform, which provides strong security for user's sensitive data and ensures that the data never leaves the user's phone. Keys is the first step towards transforming user's phones into their mobile identity and it brings passwords into the 21st century.          Last Modified: 02/03/2014       Submitted by: Samuel T King]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
