<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Building Capacity for Science Standards through Networked Improvement Communities</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>10/01/2013</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>750000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>866008</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>11090000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>EHR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DRL</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Research On Learning</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Michael Ford</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>miford@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032925153</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The college and career readiness standards in science represent both a challenge and an opportunity for educators. The opportunity lies in the vision that new standards set for the creation of a STEM ready workforce and scientifically literate citizens. Specifically, the standards clarify important content and science practices that students should be proficient in by the time they graduate. The bar is set higher for students, not only in terms of the content and practices but also in terms of the inherent linguistic demands of participating in the practices. Consequently, more will be required of teachers, teacher educators and the broader education community. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project brings together teams of teachers, teacher educators, administrators, and researchers to inquire into the development of ambitious and equitable practices that support learning the scientific practices (such as developing and using scientific models, and building evidence-based scientific explanations and arguments, communicating findings, etc.) and creating scaffolds for the special language demands of the scientific practices, particularly for English Language Learners (Lee, Quinn &amp; Valdés, 2013). The researchers are implementing a model for change referred to as a Networked Improvement Community, or NIC (Bryk, Gomez &amp; Grunow, 2011). This community will link Local Improvement Networks (LINs are groups of teachers, teacher educators, administrators and researchers) through a web-based technological infrastructure to support the continual improvement of rigorous and equitable forms of classroom instruction. The LINs are all working with high English Language Learner populations and are committed to improving science instruction for all students. The investigators are helping LINs define a problem space using the standards, performance progressions for ambitious teaching practices, and data on students' performance on assessments. As a community, the investigators use these resources to ask: What works? For whom? And under what conditions? More than just sharing tools or training teacher developers, the NIC is engaged in rapid prototyping of tools and practices with a specific focus on improving instruction for English Language Learners. The Networked Improvement Community affords the opportunity for members to share and empirically test tools and other curricular resources so that productive variations of practices and tools can be generated. The system will accelerate the development of both teaching practices and professional learning models aligned with the college and career ready standards in science and understanding how to develop and sustain NICs that are oriented specifically around the improvement of instruction.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>09/18/2013</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>09/16/2015</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.076</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1315995</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Mark</FirstName>
<LastName>Windschitl</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Mark Windschitl</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>mwind@u.washington.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2062214736</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000390878</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/18/2013</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Jessica</FirstName>
<LastName>Thompson</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>J</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Jessica J Thompson</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>jjthomps@u.washington.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2062214630</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000498905</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/18/2013</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Washington</Name>
<CityName>Seattle</CityName>
<ZipCode>981950001</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2065434043</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>4333 Brooklyn Ave NE</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Washington</StateName>
<StateCode>WA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>WA07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>605799469</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF WASHINGTON</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>042803536</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Washington]]></Name>
<CityName>Seattle</CityName>
<StateCode>WA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>981051016</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[4333 Brooklyn Ave NE]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Washington</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>WA07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7645</Code>
<Text>Discovery Research K-12</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0413</Code>
<Name>NSF Education &amp; Human Resource</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040106</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0415</Code>
<Name>NSF Education &amp; Human Resource</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040106</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2013~750000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2015~116008</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>This research-practice partnership project brought together teams of teachers, coaches, teacher educators, administrators, and educational researchers from 9 secondary schools in one school district to inquire into the development of ambitious and equitable teaching practices that support learning the Next Generation Science Standards. The instructional improvement work focused on the NGSS scientific practices (e.g., developing and using scientific models and building evidence-based scientific explanations)<em>, </em>and creating scaffolds for the new language demands of the scientific practices, particularly for English Language Learners (Lee, Quinn, &amp; Vald&eacute;s, 2013)<em>. </em>We applied a model for change referred to as a Networked Improvement Community (Bryk, Gomez, Grunow, 2011), and developed a set of professional learning structures and practices that centered on long-term investigation of students&rsquo; ideas and resources and their perceptions of how classrooms supported their learning. School-based teams used a Studio model and Data Days to engage in improvement cycles, asking: <em>Which practices work? For whom? And under what conditions? </em>Importantly, the professional learning structures developed with NSF funding are now fully funded by the school district, such that Studios, Data Days, coaches and the development of a teacher-leader cadre continue.</p> <p><em>School and teacher level outcomes.</em> Based on a discourse analysis of Studios and Data Days we found that the teams engaged in three phases of inquiry: learning new practices, incubating with practices, and testing practices with data. All teams eventually engaged in each phase by specifying and refining focal &ldquo;foothold&rdquo; practices and tools, articulating theories of student learning, and collecting and analyzing practical measures from students (exit tickets that incorporated students voice and experiences). Foothold practices were defined as &ldquo;bite size&rdquo; practices that could be implemented daily, address issues of equitable talk/participation and rigor, contribute to alignment of common work of teams by reducing the variation of small tests of practice in classrooms, and can spread and spark development of more complex practices across the network. The teams named and worked on five foothold practices, which we described in the form of a &ldquo;change packages&rdquo; (with prototypical sequences of the practices, exit tickets, and case studies of teams learning from inquiry, see ambitiousscienceteaching.org).</p> <p>Teams worked on practice improvement during Studios and Data Days. The number of Data Days in which teachers (N=51) participated (as follow-ups to Studios) predicted significant improvement in teacher practice across one year, as well as across a three-year period (N=20) as measured by classroom observations of four science teaching practices. Teachers reported significant improvement in their science teaching practice, and adapting instruction for ELLs.</p> <p>Initially it was a struggle to integrate EL practices with science teaching practices having EL and science coaches co-plan Studios supported teachers in taking risks with their teaching and developing tools to notice how ELs learned. By year three, expertise about hybrid EL-Science teaching practices had developed in two schools. This knowledge was shared across schools at convenings and workshops.</p> <p class="p1"><em>Network outcomes.</em> Social Networking Analysis indicated that the number of teachers reporting no connections decreased over time as the network broadened to include more schools. Exponential random graph model (ERGM) analysis showed that once teachers formed a tie, they were significantly more likely to maintain the tie over time both within and across schools. Coaches were important to the stability of the network of schools.</p> <p class="p1">Over the course of the project teachers across all schools improved the quality of their professional interactions as they began to focus on analyzing student work and examining their own content understanding. Tools facilitated these interactions. In 2016-17, 94% of interactions used at least one of the network tools. New tools (e.g., exit tickets and sentence stems) helped the community focus on discourse in classrooms. Model scaffolds and summary tables remained important tools, yet they came to support planning not just enactment.</p> <p><em>Student outcomes.</em> Standardized tests for science are given to all 8<sup>th</sup>&nbsp;and 10<sup>th</sup>&nbsp;grade students in Washington State. Historically, schools in this district have had science test passing rates (i.e., meeting standards) well below the state's average passing rate. Using school passing rate averages relative to the state's passing rate one year before and after participation, we found that participating schools improved significantly. Specifically, the average relative passing rate improvement was 2.6% (this was for an average participation rate of two years). In addition, for additional each year of participation in the project (greater than two years), relative passing rate improvement increased by 8%, which is also statistically significant.&nbsp;In fact, the&nbsp;number of years a school participated in the project explained 86% of the variation in science test passing rate improvement (a very large effect size).&nbsp;Estimates did not substantively differ for middle schools and high schools (which showed no significant difference in relative improvement rates), nor did they substantively change when controlling for schools' percentage of students enrolled with free or reduced lunch status.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 10/26/2017<br>      Modified by: Jessica&nbsp;J&nbsp;Thompson</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Images (<span id="selectedPhoto0">1</span> of <span class="totalNumber"></span>)           </div> <div class="galControls" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1315995/1315995_10282879_1508363210630_Figure2b--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1315995/1315995_10282879_1508363210630_Figure2b--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Sociograms of the network 2012-17"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1315995/1315995_10282879_1508363210630_Figure2b--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Sociograms of the network 2012-17"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Figure 2. Sociograms of the network 2012-17 from SNA</div> <div class="imageCredit">Elizabeth Sanders and Nathan Abe</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Jessica&nbsp;J&nbsp;Thompson</div> <div class="imageTitle">Sociograms of the network 2012-17</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1315995/1315995_10282879_1508360489021_Figure3--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1315995/1315995_10282879_1508360489021_Figure3--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Foothold practices developed and improved by the network through disciplined inquiry"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1315995/1315995_10282879_1508360489021_Figure3--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Foothold practices developed and improved by the network through disciplined inquiry"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Figure 3. Foothold practices developed and improved by the network through disciplined inquiry</div> <div class="imageCredit">Jessica Thompson</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Jessica&nbsp;J&nbsp;Thompson</div> <div class="imageTitle">Foothold practices developed and improved by the network through disciplined inquiry</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1315995/1315995_10282879_1508353054910_Figure1--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1315995/1315995_10282879_1508353054910_Figure1--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Overview of professional learning activities"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1315995/1315995_10282879_1508353054910_Figure1--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Overview of professional learning activities"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Figure 1. An overview of professional learning activities supporting instructional teams in collaboratively improving teaching, from the perspective of an individual school in the network.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Christine Chew</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Jessica&nbsp;J&nbsp;Thompson</div> <div class="imageTitle">Overview of professional learning activities</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1315995/1315995_10282879_1508522972863_Figure4--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1315995/1315995_10282879_1508522972863_Figure4--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Longitudinal shifts in quality of professional learning opportunity"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1315995/1315995_10282879_1508522972863_Figure4--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Longitudinal shifts in quality of professional learning opportunity"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Figure 4. Quality and strength of professional relationships as indicated by SNA from 2012-2017</div> <div class="imageCredit">Jessica Thompson</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Jessica&nbsp;J&nbsp;Thompson</div> <div class="imageTitle">Longitudinal shifts in quality of professional learning opportunity</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1315995/1315995_10282879_1508525929490_Figure5--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1315995/1315995_10282879_1508525929490_Figure5--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Tool use in the Network 2012-17"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1315995/1315995_10282879_1508525929490_Figure5--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Tool use in the Network 2012-17"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Figure 5. Planning, reflection and enactment tools used in interactions among teachers, coaches and researchers, as indicated by SNA.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Jessica Thompson</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Jessica&nbsp;J&nbsp;Thompson</div> <div class="imageTitle">Tool use in the Network 2012-17</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ This research-practice partnership project brought together teams of teachers, coaches, teacher educators, administrators, and educational researchers from 9 secondary schools in one school district to inquire into the development of ambitious and equitable teaching practices that support learning the Next Generation Science Standards. The instructional improvement work focused on the NGSS scientific practices (e.g., developing and using scientific models and building evidence-based scientific explanations), and creating scaffolds for the new language demands of the scientific practices, particularly for English Language Learners (Lee, Quinn, &amp; Vald&eacute;s, 2013). We applied a model for change referred to as a Networked Improvement Community (Bryk, Gomez, Grunow, 2011), and developed a set of professional learning structures and practices that centered on long-term investigation of students? ideas and resources and their perceptions of how classrooms supported their learning. School-based teams used a Studio model and Data Days to engage in improvement cycles, asking: Which practices work? For whom? And under what conditions? Importantly, the professional learning structures developed with NSF funding are now fully funded by the school district, such that Studios, Data Days, coaches and the development of a teacher-leader cadre continue.  School and teacher level outcomes. Based on a discourse analysis of Studios and Data Days we found that the teams engaged in three phases of inquiry: learning new practices, incubating with practices, and testing practices with data. All teams eventually engaged in each phase by specifying and refining focal "foothold" practices and tools, articulating theories of student learning, and collecting and analyzing practical measures from students (exit tickets that incorporated students voice and experiences). Foothold practices were defined as "bite size" practices that could be implemented daily, address issues of equitable talk/participation and rigor, contribute to alignment of common work of teams by reducing the variation of small tests of practice in classrooms, and can spread and spark development of more complex practices across the network. The teams named and worked on five foothold practices, which we described in the form of a "change packages" (with prototypical sequences of the practices, exit tickets, and case studies of teams learning from inquiry, see ambitiousscienceteaching.org).  Teams worked on practice improvement during Studios and Data Days. The number of Data Days in which teachers (N=51) participated (as follow-ups to Studios) predicted significant improvement in teacher practice across one year, as well as across a three-year period (N=20) as measured by classroom observations of four science teaching practices. Teachers reported significant improvement in their science teaching practice, and adapting instruction for ELLs.  Initially it was a struggle to integrate EL practices with science teaching practices having EL and science coaches co-plan Studios supported teachers in taking risks with their teaching and developing tools to notice how ELs learned. By year three, expertise about hybrid EL-Science teaching practices had developed in two schools. This knowledge was shared across schools at convenings and workshops. Network outcomes. Social Networking Analysis indicated that the number of teachers reporting no connections decreased over time as the network broadened to include more schools. Exponential random graph model (ERGM) analysis showed that once teachers formed a tie, they were significantly more likely to maintain the tie over time both within and across schools. Coaches were important to the stability of the network of schools. Over the course of the project teachers across all schools improved the quality of their professional interactions as they began to focus on analyzing student work and examining their own content understanding. Tools facilitated these interactions. In 2016-17, 94% of interactions used at least one of the network tools. New tools (e.g., exit tickets and sentence stems) helped the community focus on discourse in classrooms. Model scaffolds and summary tables remained important tools, yet they came to support planning not just enactment.  Student outcomes. Standardized tests for science are given to all 8th and 10th grade students in Washington State. Historically, schools in this district have had science test passing rates (i.e., meeting standards) well below the state's average passing rate. Using school passing rate averages relative to the state's passing rate one year before and after participation, we found that participating schools improved significantly. Specifically, the average relative passing rate improvement was 2.6% (this was for an average participation rate of two years). In addition, for additional each year of participation in the project (greater than two years), relative passing rate improvement increased by 8%, which is also statistically significant. In fact, the number of years a school participated in the project explained 86% of the variation in science test passing rate improvement (a very large effect size). Estimates did not substantively differ for middle schools and high schools (which showed no significant difference in relative improvement rates), nor did they substantively change when controlling for schools' percentage of students enrolled with free or reduced lunch status.       Last Modified: 10/26/2017       Submitted by: Jessica J Thompson]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
