<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Infrastructure for Broadening Participation in STEM (IBP-STEM)</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2013</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>1149998.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>1299990</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>06030203</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>GEO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>EAR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Earth Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Lina Patino</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>lpatino@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032925047</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The underlying mission of the Infrastructure for Broadening Participation in STEM (IBP-STEM) initiative is to increase diversity in the Science, Technology, Engineering and Mathematics (STEM) workforce. The Institute for Broadening Participation (IBP) operates on a model of targeted activities supported by strategic infrastructure to support underrepresented students in their efforts to seek and successfully apply to research, funding, mentoring, and professional development opportunities, and succeed in their chosen academic and career pathways; assist faculty and administrators in their efforts to support and mentor students, build partnerships, and contribute to the pool of best practices; and grow diversity awareness and cultural competency in programs, departments, and institutions. IBP's four-pronged approach to broadening participation and increasing diversity in STEM includes: (1) Catalyzing partnerships to cultivate a community of practice and culture of diversity, reduce isolation among diversity practitioners and increase information sharing; (2) Extensive face-to-face and virtual outreach to draw constituents to the resources available via IBP that support students and faculty through the entire STEM pathway; (3) Creating and maintaining strategic web resources, open to all members of the STEM academy nationally, to make resources and information on programs, best practices, and references easily available and accessible; and (4) Synthesizing information to compile and translate research and best practices into materials and resources that are engaging, usable, and directly relevant to a broad constituency of STEM faculty, administrators, program staff, and students.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>09/06/2013</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>04/07/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.050</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1315956</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Ashanti</FirstName>
<LastName>Johnson</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Ashanti Johnson</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>johnsonptfamily@gmail.com</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2146042797</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000371643</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/06/2013</StartDate>
<EndDate>04/07/2016</EndDate>
<RoleCode>Former Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>David</FirstName>
<LastName>Siegfried</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>David Siegfried</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>dsiegfried@ibparticipation.org</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2074241185</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000675608</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/07/2016</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Institute for Broadening Participation</Name>
<CityName>Damariscotta</CityName>
<ZipCode>045430607</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2075635929</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>P.O. Box 607</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Maine</StateName>
<StateCode>ME</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>ME01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>198071891</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>INSTITUTE FOR BROADENING PARTICIPATION</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Institute for Broadening Participation]]></Name>
<CityName>Damariscotta</CityName>
<StateCode>ME</StateCode>
<ZipCode>045430607</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[281 Main Street]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Maine</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>ME01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1053</Code>
<Text>GLOB LEARN &amp; OBSER TO BEN ENVI</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1139</Code>
<Text>RSCH EXPER FOR UNDERGRAD SITES</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1219</Code>
<Text>SPECIAL PROGRAMS IN ASTRONOMY</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1260</Code>
<Text>INFRASTRUCTURE PROGRAM</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1515</Code>
<Text>AGEP</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1575</Code>
<Text>EDUCATION AND HUMAN RESOURCES</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1690</Code>
<Text>EDUCATION/HUMAN RESOURCES,OCE</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>5294</Code>
<Text>Antarctic Education</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7137</Code>
<Text>Postdoctoral Fellowships</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>8074</Code>
<Text>EarthCube</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>9134</Code>
<Text>Integrative Activities in Phys</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EPSCoR Co-Funding</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7433</Code>
<Text>CyberInfra Frmwrk 21st (CIF21)</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0113</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0114</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0115</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>02XX</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0413</Code>
<Name>NSF Education &amp; Human Resource</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040106</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0414</Code>
<Name>NSF Education &amp; Human Resource</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040106</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2013~1049998</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~100000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2015~149992</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><strong>IBP-STEM Final Outcomes Report</strong></p> <p>The IBP-STEM initiative was designed to extend the reach and support of the activities of the Institute for Broadening Participation (IBP) and its resources for broadening participation and increasing diversity in STEM fields and the STEM workforce. While the project was inclusive of all STEM disciplines and all NSF program areas, an added focus was directed to five NSF funding program areas: GEO, BIO, MPS, EPSCoR and AGEP.</p> <p>IBP has designed four linked strategies to promote the participation of students from underrepresented groups in STEM research, as well as the activities and infrastructure to support them. During the program period, IBP implemented and refined these strategies and methods in support of its ongoing mission to increase diversity in STEM: (1) Creating and maintaining <em>impactful web resources</em> for students, faculty and parents; (2) Conducting extensive <em>face-to-face and virtual outreach</em> to disseminate resources and support broadening participation efforts; (3) <em>Catalyzing partnerships</em> to cultivate communities of practice and a culture of diversity; and (4) <em>Synthesizing information</em> to compile and translate research and best practices into materials and resources that are engaging, usable, and directly relevant to a broad constituency of students and STEM faculty, administrators, and program staff.</p> <p>IBP&rsquo;s website, <a href="http://www.Pathwaystoscience.org">www.Pathwaystoscience.org</a>, is the primary resource made available to students and faculty, and includes a library component and a dynamic program and faculty search component. The library contains practical guides and an archive of webinars for students considering STEM research, a mentoring manual for students and faculty with a focus on the summer research experience and the needs of underrepresented minorities, and articles and references related to broadening participation in STEM for faculty and other practitioners. The dynamic search component includes a user-friendly search tool, a database of current fully-funded research opportunities for undergraduates, graduates and postdocs, and a directory of faculty and administrators associated with broadening participation in STEM. Over the course of the IBP-STEM project, the Pathways to science website has grown to receive 3 million visits per year, and continues to serve underrepresented minority student and the faculty who support them. Website evaluation results show that Pathwaystoscience helps students who were not previously considering pursuing STEM research, as well as those who are.</p> <p>A Regional Specialists (RS) corps of 15 &ndash; 20 recruitment professionals form the backbone of IBP&rsquo;s nationally focused face-to-face outreach effort. Over the course of the project, these college and university-based professionals have disseminated information about IBP&rsquo;s resources at conferences and meetings, and continue to keep IBP aware of changes and opportunities for students and early career faculty in STEM. RS&rsquo;s also collect student and faculty contact information that supports IBP&rsquo;s extensive virtual outreach effort; IBP&rsquo;s student directory includes students from upper-level high school through graduate level and its members are approximately 70% underrepresented minority. This effort has grown to reach tens of thousands of students and faculty each year with information and resources on STEM research opportunities.</p> <p>Since its inception in 2003, IBP has worked to develop and facilitate the connections among STEM research programs, the PI&rsquo;s that develop them, and the administrators of diversity-focused initiatives across the country. The IBP-STEM project has allowed IBP to deepen relationships in specific NSF program areas, and to develop evaluation capacity that continues to support diversity initiatives within STEM programs at HBCUs and PWIs. IBP hosts a National Broadening Participation listserve and a National AGEP listserve, which provide forums for dissemination and communication by STEM professionals focused on broadening participation, and include and connect 74 and 313 members respectively. Additionally, IBP has established a sustaining donor-member funding model that supports core website and virtual outreach activities, and includes over 100 members representing institutions, departments, programs, individuals and students (<a href="http://pathwaystoscience.org/members.aspx">http://pathwaystoscience.org/members.aspx</a>). IBP continues to collaborate on NSF proposals that include a broadening participation component and IBP also provides letters of collaboration and support as well as program evaluation services.</p> <p>Over the course of the project, IBP has composed and published practical guides on the Pathways website, given poster presentations at conferences, such as the Understanding Interventions in STEM conference, conducted workshops on aspects of diversity, and published articles in journals and other periodicals, such as <em>Oceanography</em> and <em>SEEN</em> magazine. The research and dissemination capacity IBP has developed will continue to serve students from underrepresented groups and the faculty who support them, as IBP grows and develops into the future.</p> <p>Thanks to the grant from the NSF, IBP has in become a fully sustainable, unique and valuable resource for STEM students from underrepresented groups, and the faculty who support and advocate for them.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 01/01/2018<br>      Modified by: David&nbsp;Siegfried</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ IBP-STEM Final Outcomes Report  The IBP-STEM initiative was designed to extend the reach and support of the activities of the Institute for Broadening Participation (IBP) and its resources for broadening participation and increasing diversity in STEM fields and the STEM workforce. While the project was inclusive of all STEM disciplines and all NSF program areas, an added focus was directed to five NSF funding program areas: GEO, BIO, MPS, EPSCoR and AGEP.  IBP has designed four linked strategies to promote the participation of students from underrepresented groups in STEM research, as well as the activities and infrastructure to support them. During the program period, IBP implemented and refined these strategies and methods in support of its ongoing mission to increase diversity in STEM: (1) Creating and maintaining impactful web resources for students, faculty and parents; (2) Conducting extensive face-to-face and virtual outreach to disseminate resources and support broadening participation efforts; (3) Catalyzing partnerships to cultivate communities of practice and a culture of diversity; and (4) Synthesizing information to compile and translate research and best practices into materials and resources that are engaging, usable, and directly relevant to a broad constituency of students and STEM faculty, administrators, and program staff.  IBP?s website, www.Pathwaystoscience.org, is the primary resource made available to students and faculty, and includes a library component and a dynamic program and faculty search component. The library contains practical guides and an archive of webinars for students considering STEM research, a mentoring manual for students and faculty with a focus on the summer research experience and the needs of underrepresented minorities, and articles and references related to broadening participation in STEM for faculty and other practitioners. The dynamic search component includes a user-friendly search tool, a database of current fully-funded research opportunities for undergraduates, graduates and postdocs, and a directory of faculty and administrators associated with broadening participation in STEM. Over the course of the IBP-STEM project, the Pathways to science website has grown to receive 3 million visits per year, and continues to serve underrepresented minority student and the faculty who support them. Website evaluation results show that Pathwaystoscience helps students who were not previously considering pursuing STEM research, as well as those who are.  A Regional Specialists (RS) corps of 15 &ndash; 20 recruitment professionals form the backbone of IBP?s nationally focused face-to-face outreach effort. Over the course of the project, these college and university-based professionals have disseminated information about IBP?s resources at conferences and meetings, and continue to keep IBP aware of changes and opportunities for students and early career faculty in STEM. RS?s also collect student and faculty contact information that supports IBP?s extensive virtual outreach effort; IBP?s student directory includes students from upper-level high school through graduate level and its members are approximately 70% underrepresented minority. This effort has grown to reach tens of thousands of students and faculty each year with information and resources on STEM research opportunities.  Since its inception in 2003, IBP has worked to develop and facilitate the connections among STEM research programs, the PI?s that develop them, and the administrators of diversity-focused initiatives across the country. The IBP-STEM project has allowed IBP to deepen relationships in specific NSF program areas, and to develop evaluation capacity that continues to support diversity initiatives within STEM programs at HBCUs and PWIs. IBP hosts a National Broadening Participation listserve and a National AGEP listserve, which provide forums for dissemination and communication by STEM professionals focused on broadening participation, and include and connect 74 and 313 members respectively. Additionally, IBP has established a sustaining donor-member funding model that supports core website and virtual outreach activities, and includes over 100 members representing institutions, departments, programs, individuals and students (http://pathwaystoscience.org/members.aspx). IBP continues to collaborate on NSF proposals that include a broadening participation component and IBP also provides letters of collaboration and support as well as program evaluation services.  Over the course of the project, IBP has composed and published practical guides on the Pathways website, given poster presentations at conferences, such as the Understanding Interventions in STEM conference, conducted workshops on aspects of diversity, and published articles in journals and other periodicals, such as Oceanography and SEEN magazine. The research and dissemination capacity IBP has developed will continue to serve students from underrepresented groups and the faculty who support them, as IBP grows and develops into the future.  Thanks to the grant from the NSF, IBP has in become a fully sustainable, unique and valuable resource for STEM students from underrepresented groups, and the faculty who support and advocate for them.       Last Modified: 01/01/2018       Submitted by: David Siegfried]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
