<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Partial hyperbolicity and rigidity</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2012</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2014</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>172488.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>172488</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DMS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Bruce P. Palka</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This project is guided by the far-reaching goal of developing a general theory of partially hyperbolic systems along the lines of the hyperbolic theory developed over the past forty years. In particular, the principal investigator will study the following topics: ergodic properties of conservative partially hyperbolic diffeomorphisms; physical measures for (dissipative) partially hyperbolic diffeomorphisms; rigidity phenomena connected to partially hyperbolic group actions; and ergodicty of singular partially hyperbolic systems. These research goals will be carried out through a variety of modalities, including published papers in peer-reviewed journals, a collaborative book project, supervising Ph.D. students, and speaking at conferences, including the upcoming International Congress of Mathematicians in Hyderabad, India.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The principal investigator is a leading expert in the field of partially hyperbolic dynamics. A dynamical system is a system (for example, a state space for a physical process) that evolves over time according to a deterministic set of rules. Well-studied classes of dynamical systems include the so-called hyperbolic systems, which display chaotic, unpredictable features at every point, and KAM systems, which have stable regions of regular motion. The partially hyperbolic systems are a more general class of dynamical systems than the hyperbolic class, and include systems that combine hyperbolicity in some directions with KAM behavior in other directions.  Partially hyperbolic systems occur widely in dynamical systems that arise in physics. For example, planetary motion usually contains partially hyperbolic subdynamics. The principal investigator has had a well-developed research plan for over fifteen years to study partially hyperbolic systems and is poised to raise the theory of these systems to a new level of generality and applicability.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>12/20/2012</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>12/20/2012</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1316534</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Anne</FirstName>
<LastName>Wilkinson</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>M</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Anne M Wilkinson</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>wilkinso@math.uchicago.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>8474915486</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000314704</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>12/20/2012</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Chicago</Name>
<CityName>Chicago</CityName>
<ZipCode>606372612</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>7737028669</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>6054 South Drexel Avenue</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[Suite 300]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Illinois</StateName>
<StateCode>IL</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>IL01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>005421136</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF CHICAGO, THE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>005421136</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Chicago]]></Name>
<CityName>Chicago</CityName>
<StateCode>IL</StateCode>
<ZipCode>606375418</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[5801 South Ellis]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Illinois</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>IL01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1281</Code>
<Text>ANALYSIS PROGRAM</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0110</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0112</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2010~71284</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2012~101204</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><span>Wilkinson's work centers on asymptotic features -- topological,</span><br /><span>geometric and probabilistic -- &nbsp;of smooth dynamical systems, in</span><br /><span>particular diffeomorphisms of closed manifolds. &nbsp;With Keith Burns, she</span><br /><span>has proved to the most general criterion to date for stable ergodicity</span><br /><span>of a conservative dynamical system. &nbsp;The class of diffeomorphisms they</span><br /><span>consider -- the partially hyperbolic diffeomorphisms -- displays</span><br /><span>complex dynamical characteristics that are only beginning to be</span><br /><span>understood. Part of Wilkinson's research program has been to delineate</span><br /><span>some of these features, including pathological foliations, rigidity of</span><br /><span>partially hyperbolic actions, and existence of physically significant</span><br /><span>invariant measures for partially hyperbolic actions. In current work with</span><br /><span>Artur Avila and Sylvain Crovisier, Wilkinson is revisiting the 19th Century</span><br /><span>Boltzmann Ergodic Hypothesis, and has established an important</span><br /><span>step toward its realization in the $C^1$ category, namely: $C^1$-generically,</span><br /><span>positive entropy with respect to volume implies ergodicity.</span><br /><br /><span>&nbsp;Wilkinson also</span><br /><span>studies the interplay between dynamics and the algebraic structure of</span><br /><span>the group of diffeomorphisms, and has proved, with Christian Bonatti</span><br /><span>and Crovisier, that the $C^1$ generic diffeomorphism has</span><br /><span>trivial centralizer, commuting only with itself and its iterates (thus</span><br /><span>answering in the $C^1$ case one of Smale's "Problems for the 21st</span><br /><span>Century.") &nbsp;Much of Wilkinson's work involves the interplay between</span><br /><span>dynamics and other areas, such as her result with Burns and Howard</span><br /><span>Masur on the ergodicity of the Weil-Petersson geodesic flow for the</span><br /><span>moduli space of Riemann surfaces. &nbsp;Her interests thus bring her into</span><br /><span>close interaction, through seminars and advising, with a broad swath</span><br /><span>of the graduate population at Chicago.</span></p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 02/05/2015<br>      Modified by: Anne&nbsp;M&nbsp;Wilkinson</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Wilkinson's work centers on asymptotic features -- topological, geometric and probabilistic --  of smooth dynamical systems, in particular diffeomorphisms of closed manifolds.  With Keith Burns, she has proved to the most general criterion to date for stable ergodicity of a conservative dynamical system.  The class of diffeomorphisms they consider -- the partially hyperbolic diffeomorphisms -- displays complex dynamical characteristics that are only beginning to be understood. Part of Wilkinson's research program has been to delineate some of these features, including pathological foliations, rigidity of partially hyperbolic actions, and existence of physically significant invariant measures for partially hyperbolic actions. In current work with Artur Avila and Sylvain Crovisier, Wilkinson is revisiting the 19th Century Boltzmann Ergodic Hypothesis, and has established an important step toward its realization in the $C^1$ category, namely: $C^1$-generically, positive entropy with respect to volume implies ergodicity.   Wilkinson also studies the interplay between dynamics and the algebraic structure of the group of diffeomorphisms, and has proved, with Christian Bonatti and Crovisier, that the $C^1$ generic diffeomorphism has trivial centralizer, commuting only with itself and its iterates (thus answering in the $C^1$ case one of Smale's "Problems for the 21st Century.")  Much of Wilkinson's work involves the interplay between dynamics and other areas, such as her result with Burns and Howard Masur on the ergodicity of the Weil-Petersson geodesic flow for the moduli space of Riemann surfaces.  Her interests thus bring her into close interaction, through seminars and advising, with a broad swath of the graduate population at Chicago.       Last Modified: 02/05/2015       Submitted by: Anne M Wilkinson]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
