<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>NSF East Asia and Pacific Summer Institute (EAPSI) for FY 2013 in Taiwan</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>06/01/2013</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2014</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>5299.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>5299</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Fellowship Award</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>01090000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>O/D</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Office Of The Director</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>OISE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Office Of Internatl Science &amp;Engineering</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Anne Emig</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>aemig@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927241</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This action funds Alison Marie Tseng of the University of Pittsburgh to conduct a research project in the Social, Behavioral and Economic Sciences area during the summer of 2013 at National Taiwan Normal University in Taipei.  The project title is "The Effect of Being Immersed in a First or Second Language Environment on Bilingual Translation." The host scientist is Dr. Jun Ren Lee.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Previous research has demonstrated that translation ambiguity, the availability of multiple translations, is relatively common and affects adult second language learning and adult bilingual processing. Previous research on translation ambiguity has primarily focused on European languages. However, the United States Census 2010 showed that, between 2000 and 2010, the Asian population increased more than other populations. Further, within the Asian population, the largest population was the Chinese population. Given this, it is imperative to include non-European languages in general, and Mandarin in particular, in the research on translation ambiguity. This project collects English-Mandarin translation norms in Taiwan, allowing a direct comparison between translation norms collected in the United States and in Taiwan. This research answers the questions of: (1) whether translation ambiguity is relatively common between English and Mandarin; (2) whether the correlations between translation ambiguity and word-level characteristics such as concreteness and frequency hold when the two languages do not share an orthography; and (3) how language environment affects the translations that are provided. Further, this research examines the types of errors that are made across a range of proficiencies, allowing for a characterization of the types of errors that bilinguals make in the progression from novice to expert.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Broader impacts of an EAPSI fellowship include providing the Fellow a first-hand research experience outside the U.S.; an introduction to the science, science policy, and scientific infrastructure of the respective location; and an orientation to the society, culture and language.   These activities meet the NSF goal to educate for international collaborations early in the career of its scientists, engineers, and educators, thus ensuring a globally aware U.S. scientific workforce.  Furthermore, the results of the proposed research could be used to understand how bilinguals resolve translation ambiguity in their day-to-day communication, and how to reduce errors caused by translation ambiguity. Bilinguals must resolve this ambiguity regularly in their day-to-day communication to avoid errors in communication.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>05/16/2013</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/16/2013</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.079</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1316727</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Alison</FirstName>
<LastName>Tseng</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>M</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Alison M Tseng</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress/>
<PI_PHON>8148734844</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000578319</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/16/2013</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Phillips                Alison         M</Name>
<CityName>Pittsburgh</CityName>
<ZipCode>152605169</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber/>
<StreetAddress/>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Pennsylvania</StateName>
<StateCode>PA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>14</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>PA14</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM/>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME/>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Phillips                Alison         M]]></Name>
<CityName>Pittsburgh</CityName>
<StateCode>PA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>152605169</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Pennsylvania</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>14</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>PA14</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7316</Code>
<Text>EAPSI</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>5924</Code>
<Text>TAIWAN</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>5978</Code>
<Text>EAST ASIA AND PACIFIC PROGRAM</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7316</Code>
<Text>EAPSI</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0113</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2013~5299</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Previous research has demonstrated that translation ambiguity (i.e., when a word in a language maps onto multiple words in another language) is relatively common and affects adult second language learning and adult bilingual language processing. Through this award, English-Mandarin translation norms were collected from 25 Mandarin-English bilinguals at the National Taiwan Normal University, allowing for a direct comparison with English-Mandarin translation norms collected in the United States. To collect the English-Mandarin translation norms, bilinguals were asked to complete an English-to-Mandarin translation task, in which they saw a list of 562 English words and were asked to write the first Mandarin translation (using traditional characters or simplified characters) that they thought of. Participants also completed a language history questionnaire, which asked them to describe their previous language learning experiences and to rate their proficiency in Mandarin and in English. The written responses from the translation task were transcribed by a native Mandarin speaker and were coded for accuracy. Ambiguity status (i.e., translation unambiguous or translation ambiguous) was determined for words that received at least one correct translation. Ambiguity type (i.e., form ambiguous, meaning ambiguous, or form + meaning ambiguous) was determined for translation-ambiguous words. Error type (i.e., omission error, form error, and meaning error) was determined for incorrect translations. A comprehensive analysis of the number-of-translations norms between English and Mandarin will also (1) determine whether translation ambiguity is relatively common between English and Mandarin, two languages that are from different language families; (2) examine whether there are correlations between translation ambiguity and word-level characteristics (e.g., concreteness and frequency) for English and Mandarin, two languages that have different orthographies, and (3) characterize the types of errors that Mandarin &ndash; English bilinguals make across a range of proficiencies. By collecting number-of-translations norms between English and Mandarin, the results of this research can be used to develop training programs that can reduce the difficulty that native English speakers have learning Mandarin as a second language and that native Mandarin speakers have learning English as a second language. The results of this research can also be used to understand how bilinguals resolve translation ambiguity in their day-to-day communication, and how to reduce errors when bilinguals do not resolve translation ambiguity in their day-to-day communication.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 11/29/2013<br>      Modified by: Alison&nbsp;M&nbsp;Tseng</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Previous research has demonstrated that translation ambiguity (i.e., when a word in a language maps onto multiple words in another language) is relatively common and affects adult second language learning and adult bilingual language processing. Through this award, English-Mandarin translation norms were collected from 25 Mandarin-English bilinguals at the National Taiwan Normal University, allowing for a direct comparison with English-Mandarin translation norms collected in the United States. To collect the English-Mandarin translation norms, bilinguals were asked to complete an English-to-Mandarin translation task, in which they saw a list of 562 English words and were asked to write the first Mandarin translation (using traditional characters or simplified characters) that they thought of. Participants also completed a language history questionnaire, which asked them to describe their previous language learning experiences and to rate their proficiency in Mandarin and in English. The written responses from the translation task were transcribed by a native Mandarin speaker and were coded for accuracy. Ambiguity status (i.e., translation unambiguous or translation ambiguous) was determined for words that received at least one correct translation. Ambiguity type (i.e., form ambiguous, meaning ambiguous, or form + meaning ambiguous) was determined for translation-ambiguous words. Error type (i.e., omission error, form error, and meaning error) was determined for incorrect translations. A comprehensive analysis of the number-of-translations norms between English and Mandarin will also (1) determine whether translation ambiguity is relatively common between English and Mandarin, two languages that are from different language families; (2) examine whether there are correlations between translation ambiguity and word-level characteristics (e.g., concreteness and frequency) for English and Mandarin, two languages that have different orthographies, and (3) characterize the types of errors that Mandarin &ndash; English bilinguals make across a range of proficiencies. By collecting number-of-translations norms between English and Mandarin, the results of this research can be used to develop training programs that can reduce the difficulty that native English speakers have learning Mandarin as a second language and that native Mandarin speakers have learning English as a second language. The results of this research can also be used to understand how bilinguals resolve translation ambiguity in their day-to-day communication, and how to reduce errors when bilinguals do not resolve translation ambiguity in their day-to-day communication.          Last Modified: 11/29/2013       Submitted by: Alison M Tseng]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
