<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>NSF East Asia and Pacific Summer Institute (EAPSI) for FY 2013 in Taiwan</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>06/01/2013</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2014</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>5070.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>5070</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Fellowship Award</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>01090000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>O/D</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Office Of The Director</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>OISE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Office Of Internatl Science &amp;Engineering</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Anne Emig</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>aemig@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927241</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This action funds Vu Nguyen of the University of Colorado at Boulder to conduct a research project in Geoscience during the summer of 2013 at National Central University in Jhongli, Taiwan.  The project title is "Impacts on the Upper Atmosphere from Long Period Planetary Waves Generated from Below." The host scientist is Dr. Loren Chang.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The research project investigates the ways in which planetary waves, global-scale atmospheric oscillations generated in the lower/middle atmosphere, can drive the variability of the upper atmosphere. It specifically focuses on the 16-day planetary wave and its effects on the upper atmosphere through nonlinear interactions with atmospheric tides.  The first phase of the project involves the implementation of the 16-day planetary wave in an atmospheric general circulation model developed by the National Center for Atmospheric Research. Model results are utilized to identify the main mechanisms through which the effects of the 16-day planetary wave are transmitted to the upper atmosphere. The second phase of the project compares the model results to observations from the Constellation Observing System for Meteorology Ionospheric and Climate (COSMIC), a satellite mission funded jointly by Taiwan and the United States. The results of the project will improve our understanding of the atmosphere as a complete system and eventually be utilized to make better predictions for the upper atmosphere, a region housing space technology that is critical to the progress of science and the functioning of global society.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Broader impacts of an EAPSI fellowship include providing the Fellow a first-hand research experience outside the U.S.; an introduction to the science, science policy, and scientific infrastructure of the respective location; and an orientation to the society, culture and language.   These activities meet the NSF goal to educate for international collaborations early in the career of its scientists, engineers, and educators, thus ensuring a globally aware U.S. scientific workforce.  Furthermore, the research conducted will be presented at an international conference during the stay in Taiwan to disseminate the information to a broad, global audience. After arrival back in the United States, the international experience gained under the EAPSI fellowship will be shared with others in order to encourage future participation in the program and to highlight the benefits of international endeavors.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>05/16/2013</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/16/2013</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.079</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1316682</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Vu</FirstName>
<LastName>Nguyen</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Vu Nguyen</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress/>
<PI_PHON>7192916572</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000635241</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/16/2013</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Nguyen                  Vu</Name>
<CityName>Colorado Springs</CityName>
<ZipCode>809207633</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber/>
<StreetAddress/>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Colorado</StateName>
<StateCode>CO</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CO05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM/>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME/>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Nguyen                  Vu]]></Name>
<CityName>Colorado Springs</CityName>
<StateCode>CO</StateCode>
<ZipCode>809207633</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Colorado</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CO05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7316</Code>
<Text>EAPSI</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>5924</Code>
<Text>TAIWAN</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>5978</Code>
<Text>EAST ASIA AND PACIFIC PROGRAM</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7316</Code>
<Text>EAPSI</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0113</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2013~5070</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The research project investigated the ways in which planetary waves, global-scale atmospheric oscillations generated in the lower/middle atmosphere, can drive the variability of the higher portions of the atmosphere. It specifically focused on the 16-day planetary wave and the mechanisms that drive its seasonal and global structure. &nbsp;The first phase of the project involved the implementation of the 16-day planetary wave in an atmospheric general circulation model developed by the National Center for Atmospheric Research. Model results were analyzed to identify the main mechanisms that control the vertical propagation of the 16-day wave. The second phase of the project incorporated observations in order to assess the validity of the model results.&nbsp; The main conclusion of the project was that the general structure of the 16-day planetary wave was reproduced in the atmospheric model. The research results will be used to identify and analyze additional mechanisms through which planetary waves can connect the dynamics of the lower and upper atmosphere.&nbsp; In the longer term, the results of the project will improve our understanding of the atmosphere as a complete system and eventually be utilized to make better predictions for the upper atmosphere, a region housing space technology that is critical to the progress of science and the functioning of global society.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>Broader impacts of an EAPSI fellowship included providing the Fellow a first-hand research experience outside the U.S.; an introduction to the science, science policy, and scientific infrastructure of the respective location; and an orientation to the society, culture and language.&nbsp;&nbsp; These activities met the NSF goal to educate for international collaborations early in the career of its scientists, engineers, and educators, thus ensuring a globally aware U.S. scientific workforce.&nbsp; Furthermore, related research was presented at an international conference during the stay in Taiwan to disseminate the information to a broad, global audience. After arrival back in the United States, the international experience gained under the EAPSI fellowship was shared with others in order to encourage future participation in the program and to highlight the benefits of international endeavors.<strong>&nbsp;</strong></p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 11/28/2013<br>      Modified by: Vu&nbsp;Nguyen</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The research project investigated the ways in which planetary waves, global-scale atmospheric oscillations generated in the lower/middle atmosphere, can drive the variability of the higher portions of the atmosphere. It specifically focused on the 16-day planetary wave and the mechanisms that drive its seasonal and global structure.  The first phase of the project involved the implementation of the 16-day planetary wave in an atmospheric general circulation model developed by the National Center for Atmospheric Research. Model results were analyzed to identify the main mechanisms that control the vertical propagation of the 16-day wave. The second phase of the project incorporated observations in order to assess the validity of the model results.  The main conclusion of the project was that the general structure of the 16-day planetary wave was reproduced in the atmospheric model. The research results will be used to identify and analyze additional mechanisms through which planetary waves can connect the dynamics of the lower and upper atmosphere.  In the longer term, the results of the project will improve our understanding of the atmosphere as a complete system and eventually be utilized to make better predictions for the upper atmosphere, a region housing space technology that is critical to the progress of science and the functioning of global society.     Broader impacts of an EAPSI fellowship included providing the Fellow a first-hand research experience outside the U.S.; an introduction to the science, science policy, and scientific infrastructure of the respective location; and an orientation to the society, culture and language.   These activities met the NSF goal to educate for international collaborations early in the career of its scientists, engineers, and educators, thus ensuring a globally aware U.S. scientific workforce.  Furthermore, related research was presented at an international conference during the stay in Taiwan to disseminate the information to a broad, global audience. After arrival back in the United States, the international experience gained under the EAPSI fellowship was shared with others in order to encourage future participation in the program and to highlight the benefits of international endeavors.           Last Modified: 11/28/2013       Submitted by: Vu Nguyen]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
