<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>NSF East Asia and Pacific Summer Institute (EAPSI) for FY 2013 in Korea</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>06/01/2013</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2014</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>5000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>5000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Fellowship Award</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>01090000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>O/D</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Office Of The Director</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>OISE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Office Of Internatl Science &amp;Engineering</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Anne Emig</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>aemig@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927241</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This action funds Sara Elizabeth Rowland of the University of Maryland at the Institute of Marine and Environmental Technology to conduct a research project in Biological Sciences during the summer of 2013 at the Korean Institute of Ocean Science and Technology in Ansan, Korea. The project title is "Analysis of Protein Folding in Thermophilic Hydrogen Producing Microbes." The host scientist is Dr. Sung Gyun Kang. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Biohydrogen offers a clean alternative to the utilization of fossil fuels. The proper folding of enzymes including carbon monoxide dehydrogenase and hydrogenase is critical for efficient yield in select carboxydotrophic hydrogen producing microbial systems. Molecular chaperones are proteins that assist in the proper folding of other proteins including enzymes. This project investigates the development of a more productive hydrogenogenic system by introducing unique chaperones from specialized bacteria that use carbon monoxide as an energy and carbon source into Thermococcus onnurineus strain NA1, a carboxydotrophic hyperthermophilic hydrogen producing microbe.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Broader impacts of an EAPSI fellowship include providing the Fellow a first-hand research experience outside the U.S.; an introduction to the science, science policy, and scientific infrastructure of the respective location; and an orientation to the society, culture and language. These activities meet the NSF goal to educate for international collaborations early in the career of its scientists, engineers, and educators, thus ensuring a globally aware U.S. scientific workforce.  Furthermore, the Fellow will share the EAPSI-facilitated research experience with her home academic institution upon completion of the program, potentially encouraging new international collaborations between institutes.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>05/16/2013</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/16/2013</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.079</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1316585</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Sara</FirstName>
<LastName>Rowland</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>E</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Sara E Rowland</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress/>
<PI_PHON>2405073238</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000636620</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/16/2013</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Rowland                 Sara           E</Name>
<CityName>Columbia</CityName>
<ZipCode>210450002</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber/>
<StreetAddress/>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Maryland</StateName>
<StateCode>MD</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MD03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM/>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME/>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Rowland                 Sara           E]]></Name>
<CityName>Columbia</CityName>
<StateCode>MD</StateCode>
<ZipCode>210450002</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Maryland</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MD03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7316</Code>
<Text>EAPSI</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>5942</Code>
<Text>KOREA</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>5978</Code>
<Text>EAST ASIA AND PACIFIC PROGRAM</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7316</Code>
<Text>EAPSI</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0113</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2013~5000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Molecular chaperones are present in organisms across all domains of life and have the vital task of maintaining protein homeostasis in the cell. Chaperonins are a type of ubiquitous ATP-dependent molecular chaperone that interact with denatured proteins and promote their proper folding. <em>Carboxydothermus hydrogenoformans </em>is a carbon monoxide-utilizing thermophilc, hydrogenogenic bacterium (Wu, 2005). It contains a canonical, bacterial-type chaperonin called GroESL as well as an unusual, structurally archaeal-like chaperonin that is phylogentically distinct from both the bacterial and archaeal chaperonins (Techtmann, 2010). <em>Thermococcus onnurineus </em>NA1 is genetically tractable hydrogen-producing, CO-utilizing hyperthermophilic archaeon that contains two typical archaeal chaperonin subunits, making it an ideal system for further <em>in vivo</em> charcterization of the two distinct <em>C.h.</em> chaperonins (Lee, 2008). The insertion of both the bacterial and archaeal-like <em>C.h.</em> chaperonins individually into each subunit location in WT NA1, and previously constructed NA1 alpha and beta chaperonin deletion mutants, will help to define each chaperonins&rsquo; substrate specificity. Biohydrogen production in particular will be examined in each constructed NA1 strain, as both <em>C.h.</em> and NA1 contain [NiFe] hydrogenases that could be an obligate target for the archaeal-like <em>C.h.</em> chaperonin (Wu, 2005; Lee, 2008).&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>Korea Institute of Ocean Science &amp; Technology is a world-renowned marine research center whose Marine Biotechnology Division is expert in <em>Thermococcus onnurineus</em> NA1 biohydrogen production and genetics. The 2013 Korea EAPSI program enabled my training in NA1 genetics under the direct supervision of KIOST senior research scientists in a laboratory specifically suited for work with biohydrogen producing anaerobic thermophiles. Due to this direct training in transforming construct development, and on the culturing, transformation, plating, and screening of NA1, I am able to continue construction of the <em>C.h.</em> chaperonin containing NA1 strains and research with KIOST researchers.&nbsp;</p> <p><strong>References</strong></p> <p>Lee et al. 2008. The complete genome sequence of <em>Thermococcus</em> <em>onnurineus</em> NA1 reveals a mixed heterotrophic and carboxydotrophic metabolism. Journal of Bacteriology 190(22):7491-7499.</p> <p>Techtmann, SM and FT Robb. 2010. Archaeal-like chaperonins in bacteria. PNAS 107(47):20269-20274.</p> <p>Wu, M et al. 2005. Life in Hot Carbon Monoxide: The Complete Genome Sequence of <em>Carboxydothermus hydrogenoformans</em> Z-2901. PLoS Genet 1(5):e65. DOI:10.1371/journal.pgen.0010065.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 12/04/2013<br>      Modified by: Sara&nbsp;E&nbsp;Rowland</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Molecular chaperones are present in organisms across all domains of life and have the vital task of maintaining protein homeostasis in the cell. Chaperonins are a type of ubiquitous ATP-dependent molecular chaperone that interact with denatured proteins and promote their proper folding. Carboxydothermus hydrogenoformans is a carbon monoxide-utilizing thermophilc, hydrogenogenic bacterium (Wu, 2005). It contains a canonical, bacterial-type chaperonin called GroESL as well as an unusual, structurally archaeal-like chaperonin that is phylogentically distinct from both the bacterial and archaeal chaperonins (Techtmann, 2010). Thermococcus onnurineus NA1 is genetically tractable hydrogen-producing, CO-utilizing hyperthermophilic archaeon that contains two typical archaeal chaperonin subunits, making it an ideal system for further in vivo charcterization of the two distinct C.h. chaperonins (Lee, 2008). The insertion of both the bacterial and archaeal-like C.h. chaperonins individually into each subunit location in WT NA1, and previously constructed NA1 alpha and beta chaperonin deletion mutants, will help to define each chaperoninsÆ substrate specificity. Biohydrogen production in particular will be examined in each constructed NA1 strain, as both C.h. and NA1 contain [NiFe] hydrogenases that could be an obligate target for the archaeal-like C.h. chaperonin (Wu, 2005; Lee, 2008).      Korea Institute of Ocean Science &amp; Technology is a world-renowned marine research center whose Marine Biotechnology Division is expert in Thermococcus onnurineus NA1 biohydrogen production and genetics. The 2013 Korea EAPSI program enabled my training in NA1 genetics under the direct supervision of KIOST senior research scientists in a laboratory specifically suited for work with biohydrogen producing anaerobic thermophiles. Due to this direct training in transforming construct development, and on the culturing, transformation, plating, and screening of NA1, I am able to continue construction of the C.h. chaperonin containing NA1 strains and research with KIOST researchers.   References  Lee et al. 2008. The complete genome sequence of Thermococcus onnurineus NA1 reveals a mixed heterotrophic and carboxydotrophic metabolism. Journal of Bacteriology 190(22):7491-7499.  Techtmann, SM and FT Robb. 2010. Archaeal-like chaperonins in bacteria. PNAS 107(47):20269-20274.  Wu, M et al. 2005. Life in Hot Carbon Monoxide: The Complete Genome Sequence of Carboxydothermus hydrogenoformans Z-2901. PLoS Genet 1(5):e65. DOI:10.1371/journal.pgen.0010065.                Last Modified: 12/04/2013       Submitted by: Sara E Rowland]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
