<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>NeTS: Small: Collaborative Research: Efficient Spectrum Access for Gbps WLANs in a Crowd of Legacy Networks</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>10/01/2013</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>09/30/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>222947.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>222947</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>05050000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>CSE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CNS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Computer and Network Systems</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Alexander Sprintson</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>asprints@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922170</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Next-generation WLAN protocols will rely heavily on spectrum aggregation to achieve Gbps throughput. But the aggregated wideband spectrum may be severely underutilized and even starved when it overlaps with legacy narrowband channels.  As WLAN protocols continue their expansion and diversification, such heterogeneous spectrum sharing becomes increasingly prevalent, raising coexistence as a fundamental problem and practical problem. The objective of this research is to gain insights into coexistence of Gbps and legacy WLANs through measurement studies, develop optimization-driven protocols to enable efficient spectrum sharing between them, and validate the protocols in a medium-scale software-radio testbed.  The proposed solutions improve the MAC layer's awareness of heterogeneous spectrum sharing, and enforce intelligent control over the PHY layer through fine-grained spectrum access and opportunistic spectrum aggregation.  They have the potential to realize Gbps wireless networking even in a crowd of low-rate legacy networks/devices.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;By addressing the key issues of heterogeneous spectrum sharing, the proposed research helps accelerate the deployment of Gbps WLANs which will, in turn, improve the quality of experience for billions of WiFi end-users.  It will also train graduate students with a balanced mix of theory and hands-on experiences,  and synthesize their knowledge in both computer science and communications engineering.  Undergraduate students will also participate in this project, with the complementary support from the undergraduate research programs in the PI's institutions.  The PIs will interact closely with industry for possible transitioning of the research results.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/19/2013</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/19/2013</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.070</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1317411</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Kang</FirstName>
<LastName>Shin</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>G</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Kang G Shin</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>kgshin@eecs.umich.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>7347630391</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000435838</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/19/2013</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Regents of the University of Michigan - Ann Arbor</Name>
<CityName>Ann Arbor</CityName>
<ZipCode>481091274</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>7347636438</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>3003 South State St. Room 1062</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Michigan</StateName>
<StateCode>MI</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>12</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MI12</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>073133571</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>REGENTS OF THE UNIVERSITY OF MICHIGAN</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>073133571</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Michigan Ann Arbor]]></Name>
<CityName>Ann Arbor</CityName>
<StateCode>MI</StateCode>
<ZipCode>481092121</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[2260 Hayward Street]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Michigan</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>12</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MI12</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7363</Code>
<Text>Networking Technology and Syst</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7363</Code>
<Text>RES IN NETWORKING TECH &amp; SYS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7923</Code>
<Text>SMALL PROJECT</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0113</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2013~222947</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The explosive growth of mobile devices and application traffic has been a driving force for high-throughput wireless Internet access. The 802.11ac, a new Gbps WiFi standard, is expected to play a crucial role in meeting such demands in next-generation wireless networks.</p> <p>It can support up to 6.93Gbps data-rate by integrating advanced communications technologies, such as multi-user MIMO, frame aggregation, and wideband transmission. Meanwhile, the legacy WiFi devices (802.11 a/g/n) will continue their dominant role over the next few years, and are unlikely to fade away because of their unique advantages, such as energy-efficiency and low cost. Therefore, the Gbps wireless devices must maintain compatibility and support coexistence with legacy devices from the early stage of their development. The distinct PHY-layer spectrum usage of Gbps and legacy WiFi poses a major challenge for their coexistence. The high throughput of 802.11ac mainly comes from its 80MHz and 160MHz wideband transmissions, whereas legacy devices commonly adopt 20MHz channel by default. As wireless spectrum remains a limited/scarce resource, wideband Gbps networks must partially share spectrum with narrowband legacy networks. Basic MAC operations in 802.11ac, such as carrier sensing, treat each 160MHz-channel as an atomic block.&nbsp; Hence, the entire band needs to suspend its transmission even when only part of it is occupied by a legacy narrowband channel.&nbsp; As a result, a wideband 802.11ac network may severely under-utilize its spectrum, and may even be starved when it shares spectrum with multiple narrowband legacy networks. This is a major impediment to the evolution of WiFi toward a Gbps WLAN.&nbsp;</p> <p>To address this challenge, this project has uncovered the cause and effect of variable-width channel coexistence, and developed <em>Fine-grained Spectrum Sharing</em> (FSS) that solves the general problem of fair and efficient spectrum sharing among users with heterogeneous channel-widths.&nbsp;</p> <p>Instead of deeming its spectrum band as an atomic block, an FSS user FSS's spectrum adaptation is driven by a decentralized optimization framework. It preserves the 802.11 CSMA/CA primitives while allowing users to contend for each spectrum chunk, and can opportunistically split a wide-band channel or bond multiple (discontiguous) chunks to ensure fair and efficient access to available spectrum.&nbsp; In making such adaptation decisions, it balances the benefit from discontiguous chunks and the cost of guardband -- a unique tradeoff in WLANs with heterogeneous channel-widths. FSS is shown to improve throughput by multiple folds, while maintaining fairness of spectrum sharing for heterogeneous WLANs.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 01/04/2019<br>      Modified by: Kang&nbsp;G&nbsp;Shin</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The explosive growth of mobile devices and application traffic has been a driving force for high-throughput wireless Internet access. The 802.11ac, a new Gbps WiFi standard, is expected to play a crucial role in meeting such demands in next-generation wireless networks.  It can support up to 6.93Gbps data-rate by integrating advanced communications technologies, such as multi-user MIMO, frame aggregation, and wideband transmission. Meanwhile, the legacy WiFi devices (802.11 a/g/n) will continue their dominant role over the next few years, and are unlikely to fade away because of their unique advantages, such as energy-efficiency and low cost. Therefore, the Gbps wireless devices must maintain compatibility and support coexistence with legacy devices from the early stage of their development. The distinct PHY-layer spectrum usage of Gbps and legacy WiFi poses a major challenge for their coexistence. The high throughput of 802.11ac mainly comes from its 80MHz and 160MHz wideband transmissions, whereas legacy devices commonly adopt 20MHz channel by default. As wireless spectrum remains a limited/scarce resource, wideband Gbps networks must partially share spectrum with narrowband legacy networks. Basic MAC operations in 802.11ac, such as carrier sensing, treat each 160MHz-channel as an atomic block.  Hence, the entire band needs to suspend its transmission even when only part of it is occupied by a legacy narrowband channel.  As a result, a wideband 802.11ac network may severely under-utilize its spectrum, and may even be starved when it shares spectrum with multiple narrowband legacy networks. This is a major impediment to the evolution of WiFi toward a Gbps WLAN.   To address this challenge, this project has uncovered the cause and effect of variable-width channel coexistence, and developed Fine-grained Spectrum Sharing (FSS) that solves the general problem of fair and efficient spectrum sharing among users with heterogeneous channel-widths.   Instead of deeming its spectrum band as an atomic block, an FSS user FSS's spectrum adaptation is driven by a decentralized optimization framework. It preserves the 802.11 CSMA/CA primitives while allowing users to contend for each spectrum chunk, and can opportunistically split a wide-band channel or bond multiple (discontiguous) chunks to ensure fair and efficient access to available spectrum.  In making such adaptation decisions, it balances the benefit from discontiguous chunks and the cost of guardband -- a unique tradeoff in WLANs with heterogeneous channel-widths. FSS is shown to improve throughput by multiple folds, while maintaining fairness of spectrum sharing for heterogeneous WLANs.          Last Modified: 01/04/2019       Submitted by: Kang G Shin]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
