<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Collaborative STEP: Bridges to STEM Careers</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/15/2013</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>475046.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>475046</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>11040200</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>EHR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DUE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Undergraduate Education</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Connie Della-Piana</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>cdellapi@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032925309</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This project is a collaboration between the University of Houston - Clear Lake (UHCL), an upper-level undergraduate and graduate university, and three campuses of the San Jacinto Community College district (SJC) to increase attainment of STEM associates and baccalaureate degrees, as well as to facilitate and increase transfer of STEM students across the institutions. The project focuses on increasing student engagement and persistence through the development of face-to-face and technology-enhanced learning networks, both within and across campuses. Supporting initiatives include extended orientation programs, peer and faculty mentoring, career-awareness and enhancement activities, and modest financial aid. The intellectual merit of the project lies in the strong partnership between the baccalaureate and associates institutions, well-designed and coherent project elements which build on literature-based best practices and successful pilot studies, clear implementation strategies, well-planned evaluation, and extensive involvement of local STEM industries. Broader impacts include enhanced support at these Hispanic-serving institutions, with additional efforts to reach women, veterans and/or low-income students. Project graduates deepen and diversify the local STEM workforce, and the project provides a useful model for linking associates and baccalaureate institutions, as well as local STEM employers, to support student retention and success.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>09/07/2013</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>09/07/2013</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.076</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1317386</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>James</FirstName>
<LastName>Meeks</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>James Meeks</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>Jim.Meeks@sjcd.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2819223451</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000563535</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/07/2013</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Norman</FirstName>
<LastName>Liebling</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>H</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Norman H Liebling</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>norman.liebling@sjcd.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2819912609</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000602297</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/07/2013</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Nathanial</FirstName>
<LastName>Wiggins</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Nathanial Wiggins</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>nathanial.wiggins@sjcd.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2819912609</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000614495</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/07/2013</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>San Jacinto College District</Name>
<CityName>Pasadena</CityName>
<ZipCode>775043398</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2819986146</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>4624 Fairmont Parkway</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Texas</StateName>
<StateCode>TX</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>09</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>TX09</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>077422798</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>SAN JACINTO COMMUNITY COLLEGE DISTRICT</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>077422798</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[San Jacinto Community College District]]></Name>
<CityName>Pasadena</CityName>
<StateCode>TX</StateCode>
<ZipCode>775043323</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[4624 Fairmont Parkway]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Texas</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>36</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>TX36</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1796</Code>
<Text>STEP-STEM Talent Expansn Pgm</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9178</Code>
<Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>SMET</Code>
<Text>SCIENCE, MATH, ENG &amp; TECH EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0413</Code>
<Name>NSF Education &amp; Human Resource</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040106</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2013~475046</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The NSF Bridges to STEM Careers (BSC) program is a five-year collaborative grant between University of Houston &ndash; Clear Lake (UHCL) and San Jacinto College (SJC) that aims to increase student success in STEM fields between the schools with focus on mathematics, physics, computer science, and computer engineering. The elements of the grant are Summer Orientations, Tech Fridays, STEM Challenge, Peer Mentoring and Scholarships. The university and community college work together to design and facilitate events, many of which are student-driven. The overall objective of the grant is to increase student success through a transferable model that uses both formal and informal elements of education. Specific objectives can be divided into shared goals for UHCL and SJC, SJC goals, and UHCL goals.</p> <p>Shared SJC and UHCL goals include recruitment and retention efforts. We intended to recruit 60 SJC and 40 UHCL students who show academic potential and are either underrepresented in STEM or veterans into to the BSC program. This has been met and tracked through a BSC website enrollment system, which proved useful for both communication and data collection. Another shared goal is to have 20 additional SJC students transfer to UHCL in STEM fields, particularly the targeted computer science, computer information systems, computer engineering, information technology, mathematics and physics. This has been met and UHCL is now the primary transfer partner of SJC. Finally, the goal of strengthening ties between institutions has been met and continues to be a priority because of the mutual benefits of articulation agreements and vertical alignment.</p> <p>The primary SJC objective is to increase the number of students by at least 30% in STEM fields. The vertical alignment and shared activities with UHCL provided a fertile ground for program growth. The AS Mathematics represents a strong transfer option for students in STEM fields at UHCL and shows more than 300% increase during the lifetime of the grant. In addition, SJC has been recognized as one of the top schools in the nation by the Aspen Institute in part from the efforts of the grant. UHCL also has strong program growth and continued funding demonstrates the effectiveness of the multi-faceted approach.</p> <p>Peer mentoring with extra-curricular activities have been effective in retention and success. Consider the set of courses Intro to Engineering, Engineering Graphics, Programming for Engineers, Linear Algebra, Differential Equations, University Physics 1 and University Physics 2. Of these, there were 42 honors courses offered and 83 traditional lectures. The honors sections had BSC mentors and offered overrides for any students no in the honors program who wanted to participate. With 33.6% as a service-learning honors structure, the retention of 94.4% outperformed the 85.4% during the grant. Additionally, the A-C success rates have success of 89.2% compared to the 72.0% of traditional lectures when a peer mentor is present. College Algebra, a gateway course for many students, averaged 9% greater success when a peer mentor is present.</p> <p>Successful students have enjoyed access to scholarships, with $154,500 awarded to 283 students. In addition to BSC scholarships, the structure of the BSC program naturally allows for knowledge utilization to be achieved in curriculum through service-learning projects. In 50 of these projects from classes with BSC mentors, 28% won either won scholarships to support the students or institutional research funding, used to support projects for other students. The transferable academic model was initiated by a NASA Microgravity University project for acoustic flame suppression in a microgravity environment and continues with a collaborative entry into the NASA Swarmathon for the 4<sup>th</sup>&nbsp;continual year. These successful students enjoy academic support to publish and present regionally and nationally and there have been 6 student publications as a result.</p> <p>Sustainability for the summer orientation will be accomplished through a Houston Robotics and AI Day, where multiple local institutions and companies have an opportunity to participate. Tech Fridays and the STEM Challenge will continue through funding at UHCL. The scholarships cannot be sustained and so the research funding for students and scholarships through civic engagement are promoted instead. Overall, the multi-faceted approach has been effective for both institutions. The scholarships are significant for students and it has been noted that the scholarships received after performing research or being a part of service-learning result in students seeking further research opportunities. Thus, it is recommended that future institutions looking to use a similar approach use scholarships for service-learning rewards instead of traditional essay-style scholarships because the engaged student populations can be more directly identified and rewarded.</p> <p>The grant has been transformative in the region and has allowed the colleges to directly engage the community. In 2017, more than 10,000 K12 students were engaged through activities in which SJC and UHCL students participated on collaborative projects with industry sponsors. This bridge from K12 to industry and graduate school represents an exciting future for education.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 11/01/2018<br>      Modified by: James&nbsp;Meeks</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Images (<span id="selectedPhoto0">1</span> of <span class="totalNumber"></span>)           </div> <div class="galControls" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1317386/1317386_10276522_1538269328697_Swarmathon--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1317386/1317386_10276522_1538269328697_Swarmathon--rgov-800width.jpg" title="NASA Swarmathon image"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1317386/1317386_10276522_1538269328697_Swarmathon--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="NASA Swarmathon image"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">This is an image of our NASA Swarmathon team, who is collaborative with UHCL and competitive with UH. Our combined team has won multiple awards, including a 2nd place award for our simulation. This is an example of a project with a student mentor.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Alexandra Duhe</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyright owner is an institution with an existing agreement allowing use by NSF</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">James&nbsp;Meeks</div> <div class="imageTitle">NASA Swarmathon image</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1317386/1317386_10276522_1538269134359_SharedOrientation--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1317386/1317386_10276522_1538269134359_SharedOrientation--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Orientation photo"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1317386/1317386_10276522_1538269134359_SharedOrientation--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Orientation photo"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">This is an orientation photo from a shared orientation with both SJC and UHCL. These orientations provide information for both schools and shared activities. It also gives students an opportunity to meet faculty at both institutions.</div> <div class="imageCredit">UHCL media department</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyright owner is an institution with an existing agreement allowing use by NSF</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">James&nbsp;Meeks</div> <div class="imageTitle">Orientation photo</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1317386/1317386_10276522_1538267021430_ScholarshipThanks--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1317386/1317386_10276522_1538267021430_ScholarshipThanks--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Scholarship thank you"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1317386/1317386_10276522_1538267021430_ScholarshipThanks--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Scholarship thank you"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">This is a thank you note from a student who won this scholarship award and continued to win awards to get his degree. Several of these notes are delivered to the faculty and the accounting office each semester and it shows the sincere reach of the scholarships.</div> <div class="imageCredit">San Jacinto Foundation Accounting Office</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyright owner is an institution with an existing agreement allowing use by NSF</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">James&nbsp;Meeks</div> <div class="imageTitle">Scholarship thank you</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1317386/1317386_10276522_1538269581723_STEMChallenge--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1317386/1317386_10276522_1538269581723_STEMChallenge--rgov-800width.jpg" title="STEM Challenge"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1317386/1317386_10276522_1538269581723_STEMChallenge--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="STEM Challenge"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">This is a picture from a STEM Challenge. In these exciting weekend competitions, students from high schools and colleges in the region compete for prizes, including scholarships and internships. Industry sponsors and local faculty act as judges to math, science, computer and building challenges.</div> <div class="imageCredit">UHCL media department</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyright owner is an institution with an existing agreement allowing use by NSF</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">James&nbsp;Meeks</div> <div class="imageTitle">STEM Challenge</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1317386/1317386_10276522_1538270538743_TechFriday--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1317386/1317386_10276522_1538270538743_TechFriday--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Tech Friday"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1317386/1317386_10276522_1538270538743_TechFriday--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Tech Friday"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">This is a Tech Friday, where students pick up skills in computer science. Topics such as chariplexing LEDs and making your own video game in Unity frequently have full registrations. These are three hour activities, usually once per month in the long semester. These continue to be popular.</div> <div class="imageCredit">UHCL media department</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyright owner is an institution with an existing agreement allowing use by NSF</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">James&nbsp;Meeks</div> <div class="imageTitle">Tech Friday</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1317386/1317386_10276522_1538270788312_BSCGraduationNumbers--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1317386/1317386_10276522_1538270788312_BSCGraduationNumbers--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Graduation Data"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1317386/1317386_10276522_1538270788312_BSCGraduationNumbers--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Graduation Data"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">This is graduation data for BSC areas before and during the grant. Note the large increase in mathematics degrees, accompanied with increased collaboration among university partners for clean transfer of student credits.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Nathanial Wiggins</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyright owner is an institution with an existing agreement allowing use by NSF</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">James&nbsp;Meeks</div> <div class="imageTitle">Graduation Data</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The NSF Bridges to STEM Careers (BSC) program is a five-year collaborative grant between University of Houston &ndash; Clear Lake (UHCL) and San Jacinto College (SJC) that aims to increase student success in STEM fields between the schools with focus on mathematics, physics, computer science, and computer engineering. The elements of the grant are Summer Orientations, Tech Fridays, STEM Challenge, Peer Mentoring and Scholarships. The university and community college work together to design and facilitate events, many of which are student-driven. The overall objective of the grant is to increase student success through a transferable model that uses both formal and informal elements of education. Specific objectives can be divided into shared goals for UHCL and SJC, SJC goals, and UHCL goals.  Shared SJC and UHCL goals include recruitment and retention efforts. We intended to recruit 60 SJC and 40 UHCL students who show academic potential and are either underrepresented in STEM or veterans into to the BSC program. This has been met and tracked through a BSC website enrollment system, which proved useful for both communication and data collection. Another shared goal is to have 20 additional SJC students transfer to UHCL in STEM fields, particularly the targeted computer science, computer information systems, computer engineering, information technology, mathematics and physics. This has been met and UHCL is now the primary transfer partner of SJC. Finally, the goal of strengthening ties between institutions has been met and continues to be a priority because of the mutual benefits of articulation agreements and vertical alignment.  The primary SJC objective is to increase the number of students by at least 30% in STEM fields. The vertical alignment and shared activities with UHCL provided a fertile ground for program growth. The AS Mathematics represents a strong transfer option for students in STEM fields at UHCL and shows more than 300% increase during the lifetime of the grant. In addition, SJC has been recognized as one of the top schools in the nation by the Aspen Institute in part from the efforts of the grant. UHCL also has strong program growth and continued funding demonstrates the effectiveness of the multi-faceted approach.  Peer mentoring with extra-curricular activities have been effective in retention and success. Consider the set of courses Intro to Engineering, Engineering Graphics, Programming for Engineers, Linear Algebra, Differential Equations, University Physics 1 and University Physics 2. Of these, there were 42 honors courses offered and 83 traditional lectures. The honors sections had BSC mentors and offered overrides for any students no in the honors program who wanted to participate. With 33.6% as a service-learning honors structure, the retention of 94.4% outperformed the 85.4% during the grant. Additionally, the A-C success rates have success of 89.2% compared to the 72.0% of traditional lectures when a peer mentor is present. College Algebra, a gateway course for many students, averaged 9% greater success when a peer mentor is present.  Successful students have enjoyed access to scholarships, with $154,500 awarded to 283 students. In addition to BSC scholarships, the structure of the BSC program naturally allows for knowledge utilization to be achieved in curriculum through service-learning projects. In 50 of these projects from classes with BSC mentors, 28% won either won scholarships to support the students or institutional research funding, used to support projects for other students. The transferable academic model was initiated by a NASA Microgravity University project for acoustic flame suppression in a microgravity environment and continues with a collaborative entry into the NASA Swarmathon for the 4th continual year. These successful students enjoy academic support to publish and present regionally and nationally and there have been 6 student publications as a result.  Sustainability for the summer orientation will be accomplished through a Houston Robotics and AI Day, where multiple local institutions and companies have an opportunity to participate. Tech Fridays and the STEM Challenge will continue through funding at UHCL. The scholarships cannot be sustained and so the research funding for students and scholarships through civic engagement are promoted instead. Overall, the multi-faceted approach has been effective for both institutions. The scholarships are significant for students and it has been noted that the scholarships received after performing research or being a part of service-learning result in students seeking further research opportunities. Thus, it is recommended that future institutions looking to use a similar approach use scholarships for service-learning rewards instead of traditional essay-style scholarships because the engaged student populations can be more directly identified and rewarded.  The grant has been transformative in the region and has allowed the colleges to directly engage the community. In 2017, more than 10,000 K12 students were engaged through activities in which SJC and UHCL students participated on collaborative projects with industry sponsors. This bridge from K12 to industry and graduate school represents an exciting future for education.       Last Modified: 11/01/2018       Submitted by: James Meeks]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
