<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Student Teams Engaging Peers for Undergraduate Progress (STEP-UP)</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2013</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>829979.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>829979</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>11040200</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>EHR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DUE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Undergraduate Education</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Connie Della-Piana</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>cdellapi@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032925309</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This project is being supported under a special funding focus for STEP, "Graduate 10K+," an activity of the National Science Foundation, supported in part by donations from the Intel Foundation and the GE Foundation, to stimulate comprehensive action at universities and colleges to help increase the annual number of new B.S. graduates in engineering and computer science by 10,000 over the next decade. In particular, this project team is focusing on improving retention and graduation of students in its School of Engineering, with a particular emphasis on providing peer-led enrichment sessions and tutoring support for three mathematics courses (Pre-Calculus and Calculus I and II) identified as attrition points. Additional initiatives include enhanced mentoring by peers, faculty and practicing engineers, implementation of a student tracking program to allow early intervention for struggling students, and involving first-year students in design-team and professional activities to strengthen their connections to the engineering program. The intellectual merit of the project lies in its multi-pronged approach that leverages best practices from the STEM educational literature, as well as successful pilot studies of the mathematics interventions. The broader impacts comprise enhanced achievement, retention, and graduation of engineering students to enter the local and regional workforce, as well as assessment and dissemination of the approaches to serve as a model for other institutions of similar size and circumstances to adopt.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>05/02/2013</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/02/2013</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.076</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1317651</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Seref</FirstName>
<LastName>Karacal</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>C</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Seref C Karacal</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>skaraca@siue.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6186502435</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000199291</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/02/2013</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>George</FirstName>
<LastName>Pelekanos</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>George Pelekanos</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>gpeleka@siue.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6186502342</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000237971</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/02/2013</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Ryan</FirstName>
<LastName>Krauss</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>W</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Ryan W Krauss</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>rkrauss@siue.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6186505189</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000497456</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/02/2013</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Ryan</FirstName>
<LastName>Fries</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Ryan Fries</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>rfries@siue.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6186503010</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000528586</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/02/2013</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Zenia</FirstName>
<LastName>Agustin</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Zenia Agustin</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>zagusti@siue.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6186505006</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000546146</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/02/2013</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Southern Illinois University at Edwardsville</Name>
<CityName>Edwardsville</CityName>
<ZipCode>620250001</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6186503010</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>Campus Box 1046</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Illinois</StateName>
<StateCode>IL</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>13</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>IL13</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>006331342</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>SOUTHERN ILLINOIS UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>143941909</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Southern Illinois University at Edwardsville]]></Name>
<CityName>Edwardsville</CityName>
<StateCode>IL</StateCode>
<ZipCode>620250001</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[Campus Box 1046]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Illinois</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>13</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>IL13</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>8281</Code>
<Text>Jobs Council</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8215</Code>
<Text>Special Track in STEP: G10K+</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9178</Code>
<Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>SMET</Code>
<Text>SCIENCE, MATH, ENG &amp; TECH EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>40XX</Code>
<Name>NSF TRUST FUND</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>048960</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2013~829979</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>This project allowed us to take a holistic approach to student's success in the School of Engineering during their first year of studies at Southern Illinois University Edwardsville. Major project activities included; i) successful implementation of the mathematics Enrichment Sessions (ES), which is a combination of supplemental instruction and peer-led active problem solving methods in small groups, in engineering sections of Calculus I and Calculus II, ii) Peer Mentoring program, iii) &nbsp;Mathematics Tutoring, iv) Overhaul of our Freshman level Introduction to Engineering course.</p> <p>The ES leaders are selected among the junior and senior level engineering students through an interview process and were trained on how to be an effective facilitator. To gauge the effectiveness of the ES approach, the ES group and the non-ES group were compared relative to two measures: proportion of students who passed Calculus I, that is proportion who earned letter grades of A, B, or C, and proportion of students who earned grades of A or B. It has been shown in the literature that students who earn grades of at least B in Calculus I tend to perform better in subsequent mathematics and physics courses. The results for Calculus I during the five-year project implementation showed that the passing rates of those who registered for ES sections on average improved by 17.3%. &nbsp;Furthermore, the proportion of engineering majors who earned grades of at least B was also significantly higher for the ES group compared to the non-ES group.</p> <p>The results for the Calculus II ES sections over the five-year project period showed similar improvements. The proportion of students who earned grades of A, B or C in the ES group is significantly higher than the proportion of students who passed in the non-ES group and indicate on average 11.6% improvement. The same relationship is true for those students who earned grades of A or B (on average it was 10.2% higher). In addition, the proportion of students who withdrew from the Calculus I and Calculus II courses was about 5% lower for the ES group compared to the non-ES group.</p> <p>Although keeping student interest and persistent in the Peer Mentoring program was a challenge beyond the first semester of each academic year, all of the mentors and the mentees who actively engaged in the program expressed benefits and satisfaction with the program.&nbsp; Various student engagement strategies such as project-based mentoring, study groups, social and/or academic activities and various engineering community and student organization engagement methods are tried and their impacts are discussed in project publications.</p> <p>The revamped introductory level engineering course provided improved interaction between the students and their prospective departments. The course is now offered in four different modules scheduled in four different sections that meet at the same time and four effective instructors who teach a project-based 4-week long module in their specialty area take turns between the sections.</p> <p>The tutoring program is offered in freshmen residence hall between 6-9 pm Sundays through Thursdays throughout the semester. The tutors coordinated with the ES Leaders and Mentors.</p> <p>The overall impact of the project showed that the graduation and retention rates in the school improved since the implementation of the project. The project also benefited the ES leaders, peer mentors and tutors as they had the chance to improve their mathematics, communication, organizational and leadership skills.&nbsp; The results of the ES study allowed the senior project team secure funding through an internal program to continue with the mathematics ES method for all sections of Calculus I taught on campus primarily taken by STEM majors.&nbsp; This project also allowed the school leadership to make convincing narrative about the direction the school was moving and resulted in $3.35 million in private donations for facility improvement projects since 2018. &nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 09/30/2019<br>      Modified by: Seref&nbsp;C&nbsp;Karacal</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ This project allowed us to take a holistic approach to student's success in the School of Engineering during their first year of studies at Southern Illinois University Edwardsville. Major project activities included; i) successful implementation of the mathematics Enrichment Sessions (ES), which is a combination of supplemental instruction and peer-led active problem solving methods in small groups, in engineering sections of Calculus I and Calculus II, ii) Peer Mentoring program, iii)  Mathematics Tutoring, iv) Overhaul of our Freshman level Introduction to Engineering course.  The ES leaders are selected among the junior and senior level engineering students through an interview process and were trained on how to be an effective facilitator. To gauge the effectiveness of the ES approach, the ES group and the non-ES group were compared relative to two measures: proportion of students who passed Calculus I, that is proportion who earned letter grades of A, B, or C, and proportion of students who earned grades of A or B. It has been shown in the literature that students who earn grades of at least B in Calculus I tend to perform better in subsequent mathematics and physics courses. The results for Calculus I during the five-year project implementation showed that the passing rates of those who registered for ES sections on average improved by 17.3%.  Furthermore, the proportion of engineering majors who earned grades of at least B was also significantly higher for the ES group compared to the non-ES group.  The results for the Calculus II ES sections over the five-year project period showed similar improvements. The proportion of students who earned grades of A, B or C in the ES group is significantly higher than the proportion of students who passed in the non-ES group and indicate on average 11.6% improvement. The same relationship is true for those students who earned grades of A or B (on average it was 10.2% higher). In addition, the proportion of students who withdrew from the Calculus I and Calculus II courses was about 5% lower for the ES group compared to the non-ES group.  Although keeping student interest and persistent in the Peer Mentoring program was a challenge beyond the first semester of each academic year, all of the mentors and the mentees who actively engaged in the program expressed benefits and satisfaction with the program.  Various student engagement strategies such as project-based mentoring, study groups, social and/or academic activities and various engineering community and student organization engagement methods are tried and their impacts are discussed in project publications.  The revamped introductory level engineering course provided improved interaction between the students and their prospective departments. The course is now offered in four different modules scheduled in four different sections that meet at the same time and four effective instructors who teach a project-based 4-week long module in their specialty area take turns between the sections.  The tutoring program is offered in freshmen residence hall between 6-9 pm Sundays through Thursdays throughout the semester. The tutors coordinated with the ES Leaders and Mentors.  The overall impact of the project showed that the graduation and retention rates in the school improved since the implementation of the project. The project also benefited the ES leaders, peer mentors and tutors as they had the chance to improve their mathematics, communication, organizational and leadership skills.  The results of the ES study allowed the senior project team secure funding through an internal program to continue with the mathematics ES method for all sections of Calculus I taught on campus primarily taken by STEM majors.  This project also allowed the school leadership to make convincing narrative about the direction the school was moving and resulted in $3.35 million in private donations for facility improvement projects since 2018.            Last Modified: 09/30/2019       Submitted by: Seref C Karacal]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
