<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>HCC: Small: Understanding and Supporting Communication Across Language Boundaries</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2013</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>496039.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>544039</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>05020000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>CSE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>IIS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Information &amp; Intelligent Systems</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>William Bainbridge</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>wbainbri@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032928930</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Computer-mediated communication (CMC) tools and social media have the potential to allow people to interact fluidly across national boundaries but linguistic boundaries still pose challenges to communication. Advances in machine translation (MT) and other technologies have resulted in new tools that could allow people to communicate with one another using their native language, but translation errors create sizeable misunderstandings when MT is used in conversational settings. The goal of the proposed research is to better understand and support communication between people who speak different native languages by enhancing MT output with other information, such as keyword highlighting or pictorial representations. To achieve this goal, the project will (a) explore how the use of MT vs. English affects inter-lingual communication and coordination; (b) iteratively develop and test new tools that provide additional representations of meaning to smooth gaps in MT output; and (c) assess the value of these enhanced MT tools for communication and collaboration in a series of carefully controlled laboratory studies. The results will help delineate the design and technical space for new tools for inter-lingual communication.  &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The project will contribute to the fields of computer-mediated communication and computer-supported cooperative work by developing new theories and understandings of how people use technology to communicate and collaborate across language boundaries. It will contribute to human-computer interaction and related fields through the development of new techniques and tools for enhancing the output of machine translation. The annotated inter-lingual dialogues generated in experiments will also enrich the development of machine translation systems. Finally, the work will explore new technical issues around real-time keyword highlighting and multilingual picture retrieval. The project will also provide new tools and knowledge for communication across language boundaries that will be made widely available to the research community and general public, thus improving people's ability to engage with others across language boundaries, in global organizations and at the personal level, on social network sites and other international forms of new media.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/21/2013</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>04/05/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.070</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1318899</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Susan</FirstName>
<LastName>Fussell</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Susan Fussell</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>sfussell@cornell.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6072558154</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000209199</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/21/2013</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Cornell University</Name>
<CityName>Ithaca</CityName>
<ZipCode>148502820</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6072555014</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>373 Pine Tree Road</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>23</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NY23</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>872612445</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>CORNELL UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>002254837</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Cornell University]]></Name>
<CityName>Ithaca</CityName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<ZipCode>148534203</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[330 Kennedy Hall]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>23</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NY23</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7367</Code>
<Text>HCC-Human-Centered Computing</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7367</Code>
<Text>Cyber-Human Systems</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7923</Code>
<Text>SMALL PROJECT</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9251</Code>
<Text>REU SUPP-Res Exp for Ugrd Supp</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0113</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0114</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0115</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0116</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2013~496039</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~16000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2015~16000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2016~16000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Communication tools and social media have the potential to allow people to interact fluidly across national, cultural and linguistic boundaries in ways that would have been difficult if not impossible in the past. For example, businesses increasingly rely upon virtual teams that bring together workers from diverse geographic, cultural and linguistic backgrounds to work on shared tasks. While virtual teams can provide many benefits, such as a wider range of expertise, these teams also face challenges due to differences in members' native languages. Although the teams generally use English as a common language, individual members often vary in their English fluency, and this difference in fluency can lead to miscommunication and lower productivity.&nbsp;&nbsp;</p> <p>In this project, we developed and tested a series of novel computer-mediated communication tools to support multilingual teams.&nbsp;&nbsp;Each of these tools aimed to enhance the output of machine translation algorithms to make this output more useful for team communication. Our premise was that machine translation has the potential to alleviate communication problems in multilingual teams, but that it currently has limited accuracy, especially in real time conversation.&nbsp;&nbsp;We use techniques from the fields of human-computer interaction (HCI) and computer-mediated communication (CMC) to identify the challenges of multilingual teams and to develop and test new communication tools to address these challenges.</p> <p>Specifically, the project consisted of three activities. In Activity 1, we used ethnographic studies, surveys and lab experiments to understand the communication problems faced by multilingual teams. In Activity 2, we developed a series of novel CMC tools that use highlighting, images, sentiment analysis and other techniques to enhance machine translation output to make it more useful for team communication. In Activity 3, we tested these tools in laboratory experiments and in field settings.</p> <p>Over the time period of the grant, we uncovered many insights about the communication challenges of multilingual teams. For example, our observations of multilingual teams found that these teams routinely rely on a wide variety of translation tools to address specific points of confusing during meetings. We also found that team members' translation needs varied depending on the type of communication (formal meetings versus casual conversations). In addition, we developed a number of new communication tools and techniques that made significant improvements to communication in multilingual teams, including automatically highlighting keywords in machine translated messages, presenting multiple translation of a single message, adding links to information on people and places mentioned in translated messages, and providing information about the sentiment expressed by the translated message.&nbsp;</p> <p>Intellectual merit: The project contributed to the fields of computer-mediated communication and computer-supported cooperative work by developing new theories and understandings of how people use technology to communicate and collaborate across language boundaries. It contributed to human-computer interaction and related fields through the development of new techniques and tools for enhancing the output of machine translation. It also contributed to the fields of psychology, communication, and organizational behavior by increasing our knowledge of team dynamics in multilingual settings.</p> <p>Broader impacts: The grant provided training for 8 doctoral students, six of whom have earned their degree and taken jobs in academia or industry. It also provided training for over 50 undergraduate and Master's students. Our CMC tools were demonstrated at science fairs for high school students and for the general public, in undergraduate courses, and at leading conferences.&nbsp;&nbsp;The work led to over 25 publications in top journals and conference proceedings, and our findings were presented at major conferences and in invited addresses at top academic institutions and companies in both the U.S. and Taiwan. The tools we developed have been made freely available to the public.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 03/17/2019<br>      Modified by: Susan&nbsp;Fussell</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Communication tools and social media have the potential to allow people to interact fluidly across national, cultural and linguistic boundaries in ways that would have been difficult if not impossible in the past. For example, businesses increasingly rely upon virtual teams that bring together workers from diverse geographic, cultural and linguistic backgrounds to work on shared tasks. While virtual teams can provide many benefits, such as a wider range of expertise, these teams also face challenges due to differences in members' native languages. Although the teams generally use English as a common language, individual members often vary in their English fluency, and this difference in fluency can lead to miscommunication and lower productivity.    In this project, we developed and tested a series of novel computer-mediated communication tools to support multilingual teams.  Each of these tools aimed to enhance the output of machine translation algorithms to make this output more useful for team communication. Our premise was that machine translation has the potential to alleviate communication problems in multilingual teams, but that it currently has limited accuracy, especially in real time conversation.  We use techniques from the fields of human-computer interaction (HCI) and computer-mediated communication (CMC) to identify the challenges of multilingual teams and to develop and test new communication tools to address these challenges.  Specifically, the project consisted of three activities. In Activity 1, we used ethnographic studies, surveys and lab experiments to understand the communication problems faced by multilingual teams. In Activity 2, we developed a series of novel CMC tools that use highlighting, images, sentiment analysis and other techniques to enhance machine translation output to make it more useful for team communication. In Activity 3, we tested these tools in laboratory experiments and in field settings.  Over the time period of the grant, we uncovered many insights about the communication challenges of multilingual teams. For example, our observations of multilingual teams found that these teams routinely rely on a wide variety of translation tools to address specific points of confusing during meetings. We also found that team members' translation needs varied depending on the type of communication (formal meetings versus casual conversations). In addition, we developed a number of new communication tools and techniques that made significant improvements to communication in multilingual teams, including automatically highlighting keywords in machine translated messages, presenting multiple translation of a single message, adding links to information on people and places mentioned in translated messages, and providing information about the sentiment expressed by the translated message.   Intellectual merit: The project contributed to the fields of computer-mediated communication and computer-supported cooperative work by developing new theories and understandings of how people use technology to communicate and collaborate across language boundaries. It contributed to human-computer interaction and related fields through the development of new techniques and tools for enhancing the output of machine translation. It also contributed to the fields of psychology, communication, and organizational behavior by increasing our knowledge of team dynamics in multilingual settings.  Broader impacts: The grant provided training for 8 doctoral students, six of whom have earned their degree and taken jobs in academia or industry. It also provided training for over 50 undergraduate and Master's students. Our CMC tools were demonstrated at science fairs for high school students and for the general public, in undergraduate courses, and at leading conferences.  The work led to over 25 publications in top journals and conference proceedings, and our findings were presented at major conferences and in invited addresses at top academic institutions and companies in both the U.S. and Taiwan. The tools we developed have been made freely available to the public.          Last Modified: 03/17/2019       Submitted by: Susan Fussell]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
