<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>RI: Small: Probabilistic Goal-Based Imitation Learning</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2013</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>400000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>400000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>05020000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>CSE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>IIS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Information &amp; Intelligent Systems</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>James Donlon</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>jdonlon@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032928074</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Humans are extremely adept at learning new skills by watching and imitating others. Attempts to endow robots with a similar ability have failed to generalize beyond specific tasks, partly because the focus has been on following the trajectory of an action demonstrated by an expert. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The current project investigates a new interdisciplinary approach to imitation learning that is inspired by how humans learn via goal-based imitation. The project's specific objectives include: (1) a new method for imitation based on inferring the underlying goals of human actions rather than following trajectories: actions are executed based on sequences of inferred goals and successfully executed action sequences are cached as higher level goals, leading to hierarchical goal-based imitation; (2) a new approach based on hierarchical Bayesian models (HBMs) is proposed for generalization across objects and tasks, and (3) developmental studies of goal-based imitation learning are proposed for testing predictions of the project?s models in imitation learning experiments with children. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The project represents one of the first efforts to develop rigorous probabilistic models of goal-based imitation learning based on insights from human learning. The results are expected to pave the way for a new generation of machines that can interact fluently with humans, learn new skills from human teachers, and cooperatively solve problems with human partners. The project also provides graduate and undergraduate students with multidisciplinary training in computer science and cognitive science, with K-12 outreach activities aimed at encouraging students from underrepresented groups to pursue careers in science and engineering.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/06/2013</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/06/2013</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.070</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1318733</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Andrew</FirstName>
<LastName>Meltzoff</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>N</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Andrew N Meltzoff</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>meltzoff@uw.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2066852045</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000194125</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/06/2013</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Rajesh</FirstName>
<LastName>Rao</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Rajesh Rao</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>rao@cs.washington.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2066859141</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000491279</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/06/2013</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Dieter</FirstName>
<LastName>Fox</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Dieter Fox</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>fox@cs.washington.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2066852517</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000210667</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/06/2013</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Washington</Name>
<CityName>Seattle</CityName>
<ZipCode>981950001</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2065434043</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>4333 Brooklyn Ave NE</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Washington</StateName>
<StateCode>WA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>WA07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>605799469</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF WASHINGTON</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>042803536</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Washington]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>WA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>981952350</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Washington</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>WA07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7495</Code>
<Text>Robust Intelligence</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7495</Code>
<Text>ROBUST INTELLIGENCE</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7923</Code>
<Text>SMALL PROJECT</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0113</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2013~400000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Robots that can work as part of human-robot teams and learn new skills from humans &ldquo;on-the-job&rdquo; can be of tremendous value to human society in areas such as eldercare, education, and social service. The ability to learn from human partners confers significant advantages to machines deployed in the field because not all scenarios can be anticipated and programmed at design time.</p> <p>This project contributed new methods for robots to learn autonomously from their environment as well as from humans via observation and demonstration. New methods were developed for intent inference and robotic goal-based imitation learning, allowing robots to bootstrap their ability to understand and imitate human actions based on their own self-experience. The project's results on crowdsourcing robotic learning has opened the door to a new approach to large-scale&nbsp;human-assisted robot learning. The project also developed a new end-to-end solution to the problem of information gathering by mobile robots by leveraging detailed user surveys, natural language-based interaction, and new probabilistic models. This research paves the way for scalable learning of objects and places in human environments by autonomous robots.</p> <p>Beyond the fields of robotics and artificial intelligence, the project also contributed new computational models for explaining experimental results in developmental science on how infants learn to follow gaze and imitate, leading to new novel experiments to test these models based on infants watching interacting "social" robots.</p> <p>Besides contributing to research, the project provided interdisciplinary training for four graduate students, three undergraduate students, and a postdoctoral trainee in the areas of human-robot interaction, cognitive science, machine learning, and probabilistic modeling.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 10/27/2018<br>      Modified by: Rajesh&nbsp;Rao</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Robots that can work as part of human-robot teams and learn new skills from humans "on-the-job" can be of tremendous value to human society in areas such as eldercare, education, and social service. The ability to learn from human partners confers significant advantages to machines deployed in the field because not all scenarios can be anticipated and programmed at design time.  This project contributed new methods for robots to learn autonomously from their environment as well as from humans via observation and demonstration. New methods were developed for intent inference and robotic goal-based imitation learning, allowing robots to bootstrap their ability to understand and imitate human actions based on their own self-experience. The project's results on crowdsourcing robotic learning has opened the door to a new approach to large-scale human-assisted robot learning. The project also developed a new end-to-end solution to the problem of information gathering by mobile robots by leveraging detailed user surveys, natural language-based interaction, and new probabilistic models. This research paves the way for scalable learning of objects and places in human environments by autonomous robots.  Beyond the fields of robotics and artificial intelligence, the project also contributed new computational models for explaining experimental results in developmental science on how infants learn to follow gaze and imitate, leading to new novel experiments to test these models based on infants watching interacting "social" robots.  Besides contributing to research, the project provided interdisciplinary training for four graduate students, three undergraduate students, and a postdoctoral trainee in the areas of human-robot interaction, cognitive science, machine learning, and probabilistic modeling.          Last Modified: 10/27/2018       Submitted by: Rajesh Rao]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
