<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Data-Driven Time-Frequency Analysis via Nonlinear Optimization</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>12/01/2013</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>11/30/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>300000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>300000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DMS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Leland Jameson</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>ljameson@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924883</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This investigator proposes to develop a new data-driven time-frequency analysis method to study nonlinear and non-stationary data. The key idea is to look for the sparsest time-frequency representation of a signal over the largest possible dictionary using nonlinear optimization. Such a method is motivated by physical applications and the need to extract instantaneous frequency and trend from multiscale data arising from many scientific and engineering applications. Although several methods have been introduced to extract instantaneous frequency from a multiscale signal, these methods suffer from various limitations and do not have a solid mathematical foundation. The data-driven time-frequency analysis method developed by this investigator and his colleagues provides a mathematically rigorous definition of instantaneous frequency. This investigator and his colleagues have developed an efficient nonlinear matching pursuit method based on L1-regularized nonlinear least squares to decompose the signal. This method can be used to extract physically meaningful information of the signal such as instantaneous frequency and trend. The preliminary results show that this method can decompose a wide range of physical signals accurately and efficiently. Applications of this method to some real world data from geo-science and biomedical applications have led to some new discoveries. One of the main objectives of this proposal is to carry out a rigorous convergence study of this method and apply it to solve some challenging real world problems in biomedical and geo-science applications.&lt;br/&gt; &lt;br/&gt;Developing effective data analysis methods is an important path to understand some hidden patterns such as trend and cycles from the massive amount of data. So far, most data analysis methods use a predetermined basis to process data. Most of these methods can handle only linear and stationary data. To better understand the physical mechanisms hidden in data, one needs to develop effective methods that can handle the non-stationarity and nonlinearity of the data. Such methods require the use of a data-driven basis that is adaptive to the data instead of being determined a priori. The data-driven time-frequency method developed by this investigator and his colleagues has a solid mathematical foundation and uses a novel nonlinear optimization technique. Application of this method to the 9 year AMSU data over tropical oceans has led to the discovery of a new near-annual trend. This method has been applied to analyze blood pressure wave data, leading to a completely new way of diagnosing patients with cardiovascular diseases. The proposed method could provide a completely new way to analyze real world data. The proposed research will help train students and postdocs in this emerging research area. The knowledge, techniques and tools developed in this project will be disseminated through publishing in the open literature, and making available as open-source the software tools that are developed.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>11/27/2013</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>11/27/2013</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1318377</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Thomas</FirstName>
<LastName>Hou</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>Y</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Thomas Y Hou</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>hou@acm.caltech.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6263954546</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000443265</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>11/27/2013</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>California Institute of Technology</Name>
<CityName>PASADENA</CityName>
<ZipCode>911250600</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6263956219</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1200 E California Blvd</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[Mail Code 273-6]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>27</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CA27</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>009584210</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>CALIFORNIA INSTITUTE OF TECHNOLOGY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>009584210</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[California Institute of Technology]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>911250001</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>27</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CA27</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1271</Code>
<Text>COMPUTATIONAL MATHEMATICS</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9263</Code>
<Text>COMPUTATIONAL SCIENCE &amp; ENGING</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0114</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~300000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Big data have become a part of our life nowadays. With the modern information technology, we can collect massive amounts of data relatively easily. How to extract useful information contents from these massive data has become a big challenge. In addition to those big data from social media and various commercial networks, we also use data to make new scientific discoveries. The recent breakthrough in detecting gravitational waves by LIGO is an excellent example in which collecting and analyzing data guided by fundamental physical understanding could lead to new scientific breakthroughs and discoveries. Indeed, this effort was awarded the 2017 Nobel Prize in Physics . Unlike the data collected from the social media or commercial networks, physical data that we collect usually describe some very complex physical phenomena. These physical processes are too complicated and the scales of these problems are so large that we cannot afford to simulate them by even the largest computers available. Developing effective data analysis methods that can extract hidden physical patterns and information from these big datasets &nbsp;is an important path through which we can understand the underlying processes of natural phenomena.</p> <p>The main objective of the proposed research is to develop a new generation of truly adaptive data analysis method. Such method is motivated by physical applications and the need to extract instantaneous frequency and trend from <span style="text-decoration: underline;">multiscale</span> data arising from many scientific and engineering applications. In real-world applications, we often deal with signals that have ever-changing frequency. To better understand the physical mechanisms hidden in the data, one needs to develop truly adaptive data analysis methods that can handle the non-<span style="text-decoration: underline;">stationarity</span> and <span style="text-decoration: underline;">nonlinearity</span> of the data. Such methods should be adaptive to the nature of the data, which requires the use of an adaptive basis that is derived from the data rather than being determined a priori.</p> <p>During the funding period of this proposal, we have developed a new data-driven time-frequency analysis method to study nonlinear and non-stationary data. &nbsp;The key idea is to look for the sparsest time-frequency representation of a signal over the largest possible dictionary using nonlinear optimization. By sparsity, we mean that there are only very few nonzero coefficients when we project the data into some basis functions to be determined from the data. &nbsp;We further develop an efficient nonlinear matching pursuit method to solve this nonlinear <span style="text-decoration: underline;">nonconvex</span> optimization problem. This method can be used to extract physically meaningful information of the signal such as instantaneous frequency and trend. Moreover, our method has a solid mathematical foundation and is stable to noise perturbation. We have demonstrated that our method can decompose a wide range of physical signals accurately and efficiently. Applications of our method to some real world data from <span style="text-decoration: underline;">geoscience</span> and <span style="text-decoration: underline;">biomedical</span> applications have led to some new discoveries. &nbsp;</p> <p>Traditional data analysis methods such as the Fourier transform or Wavelet transform use predetermined basis functions. Although these methods provide an effective way to represent&nbsp;a large class of data, the extracted components contain mixtures of multiple physical modes, thus lose the intrinsic physical meaning underlying these datasets. Our strategy is to enlarge the dictionary to consist of an extremely large class of basis functions. This large dictionary is the key to achieve high level of adaptivity and enable us to extract the intrinisic physical modes from the multiscale physical data.</p> <p>Our research findings have already generated considerable impact in a number of scientific fields that involve data analysis. Application of our method to the 9 year <span style="text-decoration: underline;">AMSU</span> data over tropical oceans has led to the discovery of a new near-annual trend. Our method has been applied to analyze blood pressure wave data, leading to a completely new way of diagnosing patients with cardiovascular diseases. The proposed method could change the way we analyze real world data in a fundamental way.</p> <p>This research has trained a number of talented Ph.D. students and postdocs. This includes my former female postdoc, Qin Li, who is now a tenure-track assistant professor in University of Wisconsin at Madison, Dr. Hayden Schaeffer, who is now a tenure-track assistant professor in Carnegie-Mellon University, Dr. Zhiwen Zhang, who is now a tenure-track assistant professor in Hong Kong University, Dr. Pengchuan Zhang, who is a researcher at Microsoft Research Deep Learning Group. He is the first applied mathematician that they have hired in the deep learning group.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 02/22/2018<br>      Modified by: Thomas&nbsp;Y&nbsp;Hou</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Big data have become a part of our life nowadays. With the modern information technology, we can collect massive amounts of data relatively easily. How to extract useful information contents from these massive data has become a big challenge. In addition to those big data from social media and various commercial networks, we also use data to make new scientific discoveries. The recent breakthrough in detecting gravitational waves by LIGO is an excellent example in which collecting and analyzing data guided by fundamental physical understanding could lead to new scientific breakthroughs and discoveries. Indeed, this effort was awarded the 2017 Nobel Prize in Physics . Unlike the data collected from the social media or commercial networks, physical data that we collect usually describe some very complex physical phenomena. These physical processes are too complicated and the scales of these problems are so large that we cannot afford to simulate them by even the largest computers available. Developing effective data analysis methods that can extract hidden physical patterns and information from these big datasets  is an important path through which we can understand the underlying processes of natural phenomena.  The main objective of the proposed research is to develop a new generation of truly adaptive data analysis method. Such method is motivated by physical applications and the need to extract instantaneous frequency and trend from multiscale data arising from many scientific and engineering applications. In real-world applications, we often deal with signals that have ever-changing frequency. To better understand the physical mechanisms hidden in the data, one needs to develop truly adaptive data analysis methods that can handle the non-stationarity and nonlinearity of the data. Such methods should be adaptive to the nature of the data, which requires the use of an adaptive basis that is derived from the data rather than being determined a priori.  During the funding period of this proposal, we have developed a new data-driven time-frequency analysis method to study nonlinear and non-stationary data.  The key idea is to look for the sparsest time-frequency representation of a signal over the largest possible dictionary using nonlinear optimization. By sparsity, we mean that there are only very few nonzero coefficients when we project the data into some basis functions to be determined from the data.  We further develop an efficient nonlinear matching pursuit method to solve this nonlinear nonconvex optimization problem. This method can be used to extract physically meaningful information of the signal such as instantaneous frequency and trend. Moreover, our method has a solid mathematical foundation and is stable to noise perturbation. We have demonstrated that our method can decompose a wide range of physical signals accurately and efficiently. Applications of our method to some real world data from geoscience and biomedical applications have led to some new discoveries.    Traditional data analysis methods such as the Fourier transform or Wavelet transform use predetermined basis functions. Although these methods provide an effective way to represent a large class of data, the extracted components contain mixtures of multiple physical modes, thus lose the intrinsic physical meaning underlying these datasets. Our strategy is to enlarge the dictionary to consist of an extremely large class of basis functions. This large dictionary is the key to achieve high level of adaptivity and enable us to extract the intrinisic physical modes from the multiscale physical data.  Our research findings have already generated considerable impact in a number of scientific fields that involve data analysis. Application of our method to the 9 year AMSU data over tropical oceans has led to the discovery of a new near-annual trend. Our method has been applied to analyze blood pressure wave data, leading to a completely new way of diagnosing patients with cardiovascular diseases. The proposed method could change the way we analyze real world data in a fundamental way.  This research has trained a number of talented Ph.D. students and postdocs. This includes my former female postdoc, Qin Li, who is now a tenure-track assistant professor in University of Wisconsin at Madison, Dr. Hayden Schaeffer, who is now a tenure-track assistant professor in Carnegie-Mellon University, Dr. Zhiwen Zhang, who is now a tenure-track assistant professor in Hong Kong University, Dr. Pengchuan Zhang, who is a researcher at Microsoft Research Deep Learning Group. He is the first applied mathematician that they have hired in the deep learning group.                Last Modified: 02/22/2018       Submitted by: Thomas Y Hou]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
