<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>TACL 2013</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>06/01/2013</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2016</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>34690.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>34690</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DMS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Tomek Bartoszynski</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>tbartosz@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924885</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The the 2013 installment of the biennial conference series Topology, Algebras, and Categories in Logic (TACL 2013) will take place  at Vanderbilt University from July 28th to August 1st, 2013. The conference will be held in conjunction with the 28th annual Shanks Lecture Series. The 2013 Shanks Lecturer will be the Fields Medalist  Vladimir Voevodsky (Institute for Advanced Studies), who will deliver two lectures on his work on univalent foundations of mathematics. The conference proper will be preceded by a four-day summer school. The scientific program of the combined events will include -- in addition to the Shanks Lectures -- invited lectures, training tutorials and contributed talks (standard and featured/selected).&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The conference is of interdisciplinary nature and brings together a number of areas contributing to the study of logic, via semantic and syntactic methods. TACL allows for interaction between methodologies from different areas of mathematics (including Topology, Algebra and Category Theory) and the formation of hybrid approaches (for example, Algebraic Proof Theory). At the same time, via the study of classical&lt;br/&gt;and non-classical logics, the conference allows the investigation of the applicability of logic to diverse disciplines ranging from classical algebra, to constructive mathematics and analysis, topology, geometry, theoretical computer science, mathematical linguistics and philosophy.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The combined event will be publicized  widely. Due to the high quality of the planed scientific program, upwards of 120 mathematicians, logicians and computer scientists are expected to participate. This proposal supports attendance by principal speakers and other participants, particularly targeting those without other sources of support, early career researchers, women, disabled persons and minorities. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Information about the combined events can be found at the conference website:&lt;br/&gt;http://www.math.vanderbilt.edu/~tacl2013/</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>03/25/2013</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>03/25/2013</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1318130</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Constantine</FirstName>
<LastName>Tsinakis</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Constantine Tsinakis</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>constantine.tsinakis@vanderbilt.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6153226672</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000070314</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>03/25/2013</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Nikolaos</FirstName>
<LastName>Galatos</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Nikolaos Galatos</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>ngalatos@du.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>3038713581</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000497460</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>03/25/2013</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Vanderbilt University</Name>
<CityName>Nashville</CityName>
<ZipCode>372350002</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6153222631</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>Sponsored Programs Administratio</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[PMB 407749 2301 Vanderbilt Place]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Tennessee</StateName>
<StateCode>TN</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>TN05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>965717143</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>VANDERBILT UNIVERSITY, THE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>004413456</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Vanderbilt University]]></Name>
<CityName>Nashville</CityName>
<StateCode>TN</StateCode>
<ZipCode>372113630</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[21st Avenue]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Tennessee</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>TN05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1268</Code>
<Text>FOUNDATIONS</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7556</Code>
<Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0113</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2013~34690</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The grant provided partial support for the following events that were held at Vanderbilt University: The sixth installment of the conference series Topology, Algebra and Categories in Logic (TACL 2013), from July 28-August 1, 2013; the accompanying Summer School from July 24-27, 2013; and three satellite workshops featuring particular themes of the conference held in 2013, 2015 and 2016.</p> <p>The conference series focuses on three interconnecting mathematical themes central to the semantical study of logics and their applications, namely algebraic, categorical, and topological methods. It brings together different disciplines with the goal of exploring problems in logic. Partly due to its success, researchers have started employing tools used outside their immediate areas, either individually or in collaboration with specialists in research fields featured in the series. Such interactions have also naturally lead to new directions that combine ideas from two or more research fields. This has been a gradual and arduous process and TACL can boast of having participants that are at least somewhat familiar with most of the featured areas. However, young researchers and students &ndash; who attend the conference and work in TACL fields -- have had a more restricted and specialized repertoire of tools and knowledge. To fill the gap and expose such researchers to a variety of methods that can be used to study logic, a four-day Summer School was held during the week preceding TACL 2013. It primarily targeted graduate students and postdocs, but also more senior researchers who were not familiar with aspects of neighboring areas. It was received with great enthusiasm and has since become a permanent feature of the series.</p> <p>The scientific program of TACL 2013 included invited lectures, and contributed talks. The featured lecturer &mdash; Professor Vladimir Voevodsky of the Institute for Advanced Studies &mdash; delivered the 2013 Shanks lecture. There were seven additional plenary talks, and an estimated seventy contributed talks.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 08/30/2016<br>      Modified by: Constantine&nbsp;Tsinakis</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The grant provided partial support for the following events that were held at Vanderbilt University: The sixth installment of the conference series Topology, Algebra and Categories in Logic (TACL 2013), from July 28-August 1, 2013; the accompanying Summer School from July 24-27, 2013; and three satellite workshops featuring particular themes of the conference held in 2013, 2015 and 2016.  The conference series focuses on three interconnecting mathematical themes central to the semantical study of logics and their applications, namely algebraic, categorical, and topological methods. It brings together different disciplines with the goal of exploring problems in logic. Partly due to its success, researchers have started employing tools used outside their immediate areas, either individually or in collaboration with specialists in research fields featured in the series. Such interactions have also naturally lead to new directions that combine ideas from two or more research fields. This has been a gradual and arduous process and TACL can boast of having participants that are at least somewhat familiar with most of the featured areas. However, young researchers and students &ndash; who attend the conference and work in TACL fields -- have had a more restricted and specialized repertoire of tools and knowledge. To fill the gap and expose such researchers to a variety of methods that can be used to study logic, a four-day Summer School was held during the week preceding TACL 2013. It primarily targeted graduate students and postdocs, but also more senior researchers who were not familiar with aspects of neighboring areas. It was received with great enthusiasm and has since become a permanent feature of the series.  The scientific program of TACL 2013 included invited lectures, and contributed talks. The featured lecturer &mdash; Professor Vladimir Voevodsky of the Institute for Advanced Studies &mdash; delivered the 2013 Shanks lecture. There were seven additional plenary talks, and an estimated seventy contributed talks.       Last Modified: 08/30/2016       Submitted by: Constantine Tsinakis]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
