<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>AF: Small: Super-Fast Distributed Algorithms</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2013</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2016</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>397953.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>397953</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>05010000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>CSE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CCF</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division of Computing and Communication Foundations</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Rahul Shah</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>A distributed algorithm is one that runs simultaneously on multiple processors where pairwise communication is allowed.  The main goal of this project is to design "super-fast" distributed algorithms, i.e., algorithms that run in sub-logarithmic time in a distributed setting. Distributed algorithms that run in logarithmic time (or even poly-logarithmic time) have traditionally been considered fast. A well-known example of a fast distributed algorithm is the 25-year old algorithm for the maximal independent set (MIS) problem due to Luby that requires a logarithmic number of communication rounds. The main premise of this project is that for a variety of fundamental problems in distributed computing, it is possible to design super-fast distributed algorithms. The project aims to develop algorithmic techniques towards this goal and to apply them to classic distributed computing problems such as MIS, node coloring, and a host of other distributed optimization problems. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;As networks increase in size, become more dynamic (e.g., peer-to-peer and mobile networks), and become less reliable (e.g., in wireless settings), there is a greater need for super-fast algorithms. One simple motivation is that if an algorithm is super-fast, it can simply recompute its output in response to a change or a fault in the underlying network. The work proposed here will advance the state of the art in distributed algorithms. Some of the problems to be studied are old ones where recent work suggests the possibility of progress. Others are new ones where existing techniques seem inadequate. While the main focus of this project is basic research, applications of super-fast algorithms in wireless, peer-to-peer, and mobile networks will be natural and expected outcomes.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/09/2013</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/09/2013</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.070</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1318166</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Sriram</FirstName>
<LastName>Pemmaraju</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>V</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Sriram V Pemmaraju</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>sriram-pemmaraju@uiowa.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>3193532956</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000241797</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/09/2013</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Iowa</Name>
<CityName>IOWA CITY</CityName>
<ZipCode>522421320</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>3193352123</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>2 GILMORE HALL</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Iowa</StateName>
<StateCode>IA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>IA02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>062761671</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF IOWA, THE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>062761671</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[The University of Iowa]]></Name>
<CityName>Iowa City</CityName>
<StateCode>IA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>522421320</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[101G, MacLean Hall]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Iowa</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>IA02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7926</Code>
<Text>ALGORITHMS</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7923</Code>
<Text>SMALL PROJECT</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7926</Code>
<Text>ALGORITHMS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0113</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2013~397953</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Distributed algorithms, i.e., algorithms whose execution is distributed across many computers that can communicate with each other, have become commonplace. Distributed algorithms include algorithms that run over the internet (e.g., for routing e-mail), algorithms that are executed by sensors that communicate over radio channels, and algorithms for processing large volume of data, that run on clusters of computers.</p> <p>The focus of this project is the design of "super-fast" distributed algorithms and the PI's research in this direction has introduced several new algorithm-design techniques and algorithm-analysis techniques for fundamental distributed computing problems. Specifically, the PI's research pursued two inter-related strands: one on the design of "super-fast" distributed algorithms for classical models of distributed computing (e.g., models of the internet) and one on the design of "super-fast" distributed algorithms for models of large-scale cluster-computing. While the outcomes of the research are largely theoretical, some of the techniques introduced by the PI's research is expected to be useful in algorithm implementation in well-known practical systems such as Apache Spark.</p> <p>The PI mentored and trained three PhD students during this research, two of whom have gone on to positions in the tech industry focused on the design and implementation of distributed and parallel algorithms. Examples of research ideas from the project have made their way into presentations by the PI at undergraduate institutions in the upper-midwest.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 11/30/2016<br>      Modified by: Sriram&nbsp;V&nbsp;Pemmaraju</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Distributed algorithms, i.e., algorithms whose execution is distributed across many computers that can communicate with each other, have become commonplace. Distributed algorithms include algorithms that run over the internet (e.g., for routing e-mail), algorithms that are executed by sensors that communicate over radio channels, and algorithms for processing large volume of data, that run on clusters of computers.  The focus of this project is the design of "super-fast" distributed algorithms and the PI's research in this direction has introduced several new algorithm-design techniques and algorithm-analysis techniques for fundamental distributed computing problems. Specifically, the PI's research pursued two inter-related strands: one on the design of "super-fast" distributed algorithms for classical models of distributed computing (e.g., models of the internet) and one on the design of "super-fast" distributed algorithms for models of large-scale cluster-computing. While the outcomes of the research are largely theoretical, some of the techniques introduced by the PI's research is expected to be useful in algorithm implementation in well-known practical systems such as Apache Spark.  The PI mentored and trained three PhD students during this research, two of whom have gone on to positions in the tech industry focused on the design and implementation of distributed and parallel algorithms. Examples of research ideas from the project have made their way into presentations by the PI at undergraduate institutions in the upper-midwest.          Last Modified: 11/30/2016       Submitted by: Sriram V Pemmaraju]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
