<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>HCC: Small: Activity-Enriched Computing</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/15/2013</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>499976.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>499976</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>05020000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>CSE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>IIS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Information &amp; Intelligent Systems</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Ephraim Glinert</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>eglinert@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032928930</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Although myriad extraordinary benefits have resulted from the web and expanding network connectivity, the intertwining of computers with virtually every aspect of life also brings a growing stream of interruptions.  These interruptions and the fragmenting of activity they produce are increasingly accepted parts of modern life.  A critical research challenge for human-centered computing is how to smooth and mitigate the impact of interruptions as well as assist in resuming interrupted activities.  Meeting this challenge will require moving beyond the traditional document-centric view of information to address the complexity of real activity, its often fragmented history, and the need to access information arrayed across digital and paper media.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project will explore the design of systems that will allow people to exploit visual and episodic memory to benefit from the capture of the history and context of their computer-mediated activities.  The heart of the project is rethinking the nature of data as stored in computers from being a state to being an inspectable activity history of interaction that can be presented to users.  Activity-enriched computing has the potential to reshape how we use computers by creating systems that react to and are augmented by the history of past events, changing the computer environment to one in which history is always available to assist if needed.  The primary scientific contributions will be to (a) develop an activity-enriched computing framework for designing a new class of systems in which history is a first-class element, (b) prototype and evaluate activity-enriched applications, and (c) extend theory and methods for representing, visualizing, and analyzing activity histories.  Scientific contributions will include a novel activity-enriched computing framework that will (a) capture the rich detail of computer-mediated activity, (b) identify and make meaningful and useful episodes available, (c) link the worlds of paper and digital documents, and (d) exploit summarization and visual access mechanisms to support navigation of activity histories and ease resuming interrupted activities.  The overarching objective is to lessen the impact of interruptions and aid reestablishment of context.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Broader Impacts:  The broader impacts of the proposed activity include the potential to radically improve the efficacy of all computer-mediated activities.  The results of the project and the software developed will be widely disseminated and made available on the project website.  Additional impact will result from training students in the interdisciplinary approach required to design activity-enriched computing applications, providing research opportunities for both graduate and undergraduate students.  A long-term impact will be to crystallize a research community to further develop and evolve activity-enriched computing.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>09/06/2013</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/15/2015</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.070</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1319829</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>James</FirstName>
<LastName>Hollan</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>D</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>James D Hollan</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>hollan@cogsci.ucsd.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>8585348156</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000264179</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/06/2013</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of California-San Diego</Name>
<CityName>La Jolla</CityName>
<ZipCode>920930934</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>8585344896</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>Office of Contract &amp; Grant Admin</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[9500 Gilman Drive, 0934]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>49</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CA49</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>804355790</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF CALIFORNIA, SAN DIEGO</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>071549000</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of California-San Diego]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>920930934</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>49</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CA49</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7367</Code>
<Text>HCC-Human-Centered Computing</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7367</Code>
<Text>Cyber-Human Systems</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7923</Code>
<Text>SMALL PROJECT</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0113</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0114</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0115</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2013~198307</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~156728</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2015~144941</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Although many extraordinary benefits have resulted from the web and expanding network connectivity, the intertwining of computers with virtually every aspect of life also brings a growing stream of interruptions. These interruptions and the fragmenting of activity they produce are increasingly accepted parts of modern life. A critical research challenge for human-centered computing is how to smooth and mitigate the impact of interruptions as well as assist in resuming interrupted activities. Meeting this challenge will require moving beyond the legacy document-centric view of information to address the complexity of real activity and its often fragmented history.</p> <p>This project has focused on capturing, visualizing, and analyzing computer-mediated activity. In addition, it has addressed the value concerns associated with activity&nbsp;capture. One outcome of the project is software to capture and assist in the analysis of video and other time-based data. This software is open-source and available on the public GitHub site.</p> <p>Motivated by the known efficiency of images for cueing memory, we conducted two studies of how visual histories of computer-mediated activity might aid users in restoring the mental context of suspended activities. In the first exploratory study, we demonstrated that users provided a visual history consisting of small thumbnail images of their desktop can reconstruct detailed mental contexts of earlier computer work. Surprising we also found that static images were more effective than animations.&nbsp; In the second observational study, we examined methods and cues that web developers, scientific writers, and graphic designers currently use to restore mental context. We found that participants from all three professions engage in situated sensemaking, reconstructing context by generating stories to explain cues in their documents with implicit meaning, such as sudden changes in writing quality or the shape of blocks of code. We identified characteristics of each activity that influence the information, artifacts, and strategies participants used to reconstruct context. We concluded that visual histories can help users reconstruct mental context but that challenges remain in designing lightweight image-based cues that help users reconstruct a context for a range of activities.</p> <p>This work motivated us to examine the use and issues of activity with computational notebooks. Computational notebooks combine code, visualizations, and text in a single document. Researchers, data analysts, and even journalists are rapidly adopting this new medium. We conducted three studies of how they are using notebooks to document and share exploratory data analyses. In the first, we analyzed over a million computational notebooks on GitHub, finding that one in four had no explanatory text but consisted entirely of visualizations or code. In a second study, we examined over 200 academic computational notebooks, finding that although the vast majority described methods, only a minority discussed reasoning or results. In a third study, we interviewed 15 academic data analysts, finding that most considered computational notebooks personal, exploratory, and messy. Importantly, they typically used other media to share analyses. These studies demonstrate a tension between exploration and explanation in constructing and sharing computational notebooks. We conclude with opportunities to encourage explanation in computational media without hindering exploration and developed a folding mechanism to help.</p> <p>Intellectually, the heart of this project involved rethinking the nature of data as stored in computers from being a state to being an inspectable activity history of interaction that can be presented to users in ways that engage visual and episodic memory. What we term <em>activity-enriched computing</em> has the potential to reshape how we use computers by creating systems that react to and are augmented by the history of past events, changing the computer environment to one in which history is always available to assist if needed.</p> <p>The intellectual merit of our research effort derives from developing and evaluating a novel activity-enriched computing framework designed to (1) capture the rich detail of computer-mediated activity, (2) identify and make meaningful and useful episodes available, and (3) exploit summarization and visual access mechanisms to support navigation of activity histories and ease resuming interrupted activities. The overarching objective has been to lessen the impact of interruptions and aid reestablishment of context.</p> <p>The broader impact of the proposed activity is the promise of activity-enriched computing to radically improve the efficacy of all computer-mediated activities. The results of the project and the software developed have been widely disseminated and made available on the web. Additional&nbsp;impact has been the training students in the interdisciplinary approach required to design activity-enriched computing applications, providing research opportunities for both graduate and undergraduate students. Our long-term goal is to crystallize a research community to further develop and evolve activity-enriched computing.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 01/25/2019<br>      Modified by: James&nbsp;D&nbsp;Hollan</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Although many extraordinary benefits have resulted from the web and expanding network connectivity, the intertwining of computers with virtually every aspect of life also brings a growing stream of interruptions. These interruptions and the fragmenting of activity they produce are increasingly accepted parts of modern life. A critical research challenge for human-centered computing is how to smooth and mitigate the impact of interruptions as well as assist in resuming interrupted activities. Meeting this challenge will require moving beyond the legacy document-centric view of information to address the complexity of real activity and its often fragmented history.  This project has focused on capturing, visualizing, and analyzing computer-mediated activity. In addition, it has addressed the value concerns associated with activity capture. One outcome of the project is software to capture and assist in the analysis of video and other time-based data. This software is open-source and available on the public GitHub site.  Motivated by the known efficiency of images for cueing memory, we conducted two studies of how visual histories of computer-mediated activity might aid users in restoring the mental context of suspended activities. In the first exploratory study, we demonstrated that users provided a visual history consisting of small thumbnail images of their desktop can reconstruct detailed mental contexts of earlier computer work. Surprising we also found that static images were more effective than animations.  In the second observational study, we examined methods and cues that web developers, scientific writers, and graphic designers currently use to restore mental context. We found that participants from all three professions engage in situated sensemaking, reconstructing context by generating stories to explain cues in their documents with implicit meaning, such as sudden changes in writing quality or the shape of blocks of code. We identified characteristics of each activity that influence the information, artifacts, and strategies participants used to reconstruct context. We concluded that visual histories can help users reconstruct mental context but that challenges remain in designing lightweight image-based cues that help users reconstruct a context for a range of activities.  This work motivated us to examine the use and issues of activity with computational notebooks. Computational notebooks combine code, visualizations, and text in a single document. Researchers, data analysts, and even journalists are rapidly adopting this new medium. We conducted three studies of how they are using notebooks to document and share exploratory data analyses. In the first, we analyzed over a million computational notebooks on GitHub, finding that one in four had no explanatory text but consisted entirely of visualizations or code. In a second study, we examined over 200 academic computational notebooks, finding that although the vast majority described methods, only a minority discussed reasoning or results. In a third study, we interviewed 15 academic data analysts, finding that most considered computational notebooks personal, exploratory, and messy. Importantly, they typically used other media to share analyses. These studies demonstrate a tension between exploration and explanation in constructing and sharing computational notebooks. We conclude with opportunities to encourage explanation in computational media without hindering exploration and developed a folding mechanism to help.  Intellectually, the heart of this project involved rethinking the nature of data as stored in computers from being a state to being an inspectable activity history of interaction that can be presented to users in ways that engage visual and episodic memory. What we term activity-enriched computing has the potential to reshape how we use computers by creating systems that react to and are augmented by the history of past events, changing the computer environment to one in which history is always available to assist if needed.  The intellectual merit of our research effort derives from developing and evaluating a novel activity-enriched computing framework designed to (1) capture the rich detail of computer-mediated activity, (2) identify and make meaningful and useful episodes available, and (3) exploit summarization and visual access mechanisms to support navigation of activity histories and ease resuming interrupted activities. The overarching objective has been to lessen the impact of interruptions and aid reestablishment of context.  The broader impact of the proposed activity is the promise of activity-enriched computing to radically improve the efficacy of all computer-mediated activities. The results of the project and the software developed have been widely disseminated and made available on the web. Additional impact has been the training students in the interdisciplinary approach required to design activity-enriched computing applications, providing research opportunities for both graduate and undergraduate students. Our long-term goal is to crystallize a research community to further develop and evolve activity-enriched computing.       Last Modified: 01/25/2019       Submitted by: James D Hollan]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
