<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Improved Cyberinfrastructure To Support Coral Reef Research And Education At The Hawaii Institute Of Marine Biology</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/15/2013</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2016</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>235778.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>235778</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>08080000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>BIO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DBI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Biological Infrastructure</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Peter McCartney</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>pmccartn@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032928470</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The Hawai'i Institute of Marine Biology (HIMB) at the University of Hawai'i is awarded a grant to upgrade its communication and data storage capacity to take advantage of a 10 Gigabit fiber optic cable line that is being provided by Hawaiian Telecom to Coconut Island from the Oahu main line.  The HIMB research community generates large amounts of highly heterogeneous data stemming from diverse experimental sources, such as DNA sequencing data, confocal microscopy image analysis, and environmental data sensors on the surrounding coral reefs.  The high magnitude and diversity of the data collected and used by researchers at HIMB impacts the island?s data network, the storage and computational capacity, and requires a modular and timely approach to data management with robust underlying infrastructure that can efficiently handle it.  Thus, HIMB has designed a complete upgrade of its cyber infrastructure. These improvements will take place in two phases: Phase I involves the upgrade of the entire HIMB Network, including the replacement of the central networking and data storage equipment, as well as the deployment of a single centralized HIMB wireless access network throughout the island. Phase II will provide a secure data storage facility and set of user-friendly, web-based data transfer and analysis software.  A description of the research facility and its faculty is available at http://www.hawaii.edu/HIMB. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The new HIMB portal system will significantly enhance the ability of HIMB researchers to collaborate and share data with other researchers at UH and across institutions, as well as work with resource managers and NGOs to extend the availability and utility of their research findings.  HIMB will be able to extend access to HIMB data resources to faculty at UH Manoa main campus and Community Colleges for use in their courses and research.  For example, with improved cyberinfrastructure, we can offer opportunities for college students to remotely operate the confocal microscope to view images of live marine organisms.  HIMB is a partner in the NSF Pacific Climate Education Partnership teacher Institute and COSEE Island Earth.  This partnership will be delivering teacher summer institutes on climate change science to middle school teachers in Hawaii, American Samoa, Republic of the Marshall Islands, and Palau or the Mariana Islands.  The greater bandwidth of the new HIMB system will enhance these teacher institutes by making available real time data exploration.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>09/09/2013</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>09/09/2013</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.074</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1319270</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Jo-ann</FirstName>
<LastName>Leong</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>C</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Jo-ann C Leong</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>joannleo@hawaii.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>8082367402</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000474494</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/09/2013</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Gwen</FirstName>
<LastName>Jacobs</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>A</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Gwen A Jacobs</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>gwenj@hawaii.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>8089565767</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000472728</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/09/2013</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Judith</FirstName>
<LastName>Lemus</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>D</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Judith D Lemus</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>jlemus@hawaii.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>8082367422</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000460714</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/09/2013</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Erik</FirstName>
<LastName>Franklin</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>C</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Erik C Franklin</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>erik.franklin@hawaii.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>8084408607</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000084785</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/09/2013</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Mahdi</FirstName>
<LastName>Belcaid</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Mahdi Belcaid</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>mahdi@hawaii.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>8089565175</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000637601</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/09/2013</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Hawaii</Name>
<CityName>Honolulu</CityName>
<ZipCode>968222234</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>8089567800</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>2440 Campus Road, Box 368</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Hawaii</StateName>
<StateCode>HI</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>HI01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>965088057</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF HAWAII SYSTEMS</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>009438664</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Hawaii Institute of Marine Biology]]></Name>
<CityName>Kaneohe</CityName>
<StateCode>HI</StateCode>
<ZipCode>967443014</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[46-007 Lilipuna Road]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Hawaii</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>HI02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1104</Code>
<Text>FIELD STATIONS</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0113</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2013~235778</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Cyberinfrastructure Improvement</p> <p>NSF funding provided much needed upgrades to the existing network components at the Hawaii Institute of Marine Biology (HIMB) &nbsp;The project also included the provision of a 10 Gigabit fiberoptic cable by Hawaiian Telecom and a capital improvement Hawaii state funded project to drill underground lines to host cable, electrical, water, and sewage between Oahu island and Coconut Island. &nbsp;The project made it possible to carry out research on coral reefs that rely on complex computational applications and data transmission capacity for robust data archiving and analysis. &nbsp;With these upgrades, HIMB researchers participate with the Coral Reef Ecosystem Observtory Network (CREON) partners in monitoring coral reef ecosystems, and will be a founding partner in the new National Estuarine Research Reserve site at He`eia on Kaneohe Bay.</p> <p>Education and Outreach:</p> <p class="p1">We are collecting observations of live coral images from the SensorNode underwater camera, which, along with confocal images of bleached or stressed corals, will be used in resource packets for teacher workshops on climate change and coral reef biology. &nbsp;One such activity on detecting coral disease using fluorescence has been developed and presented at public science education events (Caldwell et. al, 2015). &nbsp;We are also developing a website with archived images and videos of both live and fixed specimens that will be integrated into <span class="s1">3-Dimensional interactive display system&nbsp;</span>for teaching purposes.&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 12/01/2016<br>      Modified by: Jo-Ann&nbsp;C&nbsp;Leong</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Cyberinfrastructure Improvement  NSF funding provided much needed upgrades to the existing network components at the Hawaii Institute of Marine Biology (HIMB)  The project also included the provision of a 10 Gigabit fiberoptic cable by Hawaiian Telecom and a capital improvement Hawaii state funded project to drill underground lines to host cable, electrical, water, and sewage between Oahu island and Coconut Island.  The project made it possible to carry out research on coral reefs that rely on complex computational applications and data transmission capacity for robust data archiving and analysis.  With these upgrades, HIMB researchers participate with the Coral Reef Ecosystem Observtory Network (CREON) partners in monitoring coral reef ecosystems, and will be a founding partner in the new National Estuarine Research Reserve site at He`eia on Kaneohe Bay.  Education and Outreach: We are collecting observations of live coral images from the SensorNode underwater camera, which, along with confocal images of bleached or stressed corals, will be used in resource packets for teacher workshops on climate change and coral reef biology.  One such activity on detecting coral disease using fluorescence has been developed and presented at public science education events (Caldwell et. al, 2015).  We are also developing a website with archived images and videos of both live and fixed specimens that will be integrated into 3-Dimensional interactive display system for teaching purposes.           Last Modified: 12/01/2016       Submitted by: Jo-Ann C Leong]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
