<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>NeTS: Small: Collaborative Research: Enabling Network Agility Through Virtualized Infrastructure Migration</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2013</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>249999.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>249999</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>05050000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>CSE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CNS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Computer and Network Systems</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Darleen Fisher</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>dlfisher@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032928950</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Virtualized infrastructure is becoming increasingly routine, and so the ability to manage it well is important.  Cloud computing is built on virtualized computing infrastructure.  Software Defined Networks are virtualized data networks.   The combination of virtualized computing and communications constitutes the next wave of innovation in  provisioning bespoke infrastructure.  This project addresses ways of making such virtualized infrastructure more reliable, by planning and managing the migration of the virtual network structure and associated computation from one set of supporting physical infrastruture to another. Triggers for VN migration include attacks, massive failures, performance collapse or degradation, or changes in the service demands that require an increase or decrease in resource allocation in order to both satisfy users and reduce power consumption. This ability to adapt to network dynamics is referred to as VI migration (VIM). &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;There are many challenges in deploying VIM for the applications above. First, different network agility objectives might require different VIM models and techniques. For example, the trigger to migrate for proactive defense to defeat reconnaissance would need to be time based , whereas, for power management the trigger would be signi&amp;#64257;cant change of network traf&amp;#64257;c load. Second, VN migrations may need to be planned in advance (for example, in the case of proactive defense) but in some cases they cannot be planned in advance and need to be deployed in real time (in response to faults, for example). Third, although most existing theories permit reasoning about correctness of network operation only once as the system stabilizes to a static state, investigating formal frameworks that support migration strategies that are correct-by-construction under continuous movement is a prime research task. To address these challenges this project will develop a VIM architecture that is designed to work in the context of the GENI and PlanetLab virtualization technologies, but which could be used as the basis for other industrial systems. The architecture consists of two main components: a Strategy Synthesizer block and a Migration Mechanism block. The inputs to the Strategy Synthesizer block uses models of the VI and the Migration Mechanism block interacts directly with the substrate to implement the desired migration. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;VIM is a powerful technique for energy control in Cloud infrastructure and effective tools for managing VIM are expected to facilitate significant savings in IT energy consumption.   In addition to the potential commercial and network security impacts of the work, the PIs have identified local and outreach activities that further the participation of women and minorities.  The experimental and evaluation aspects of the work will be incorporated as project elements in graduate courses.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/21/2013</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/21/2013</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.070</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1320662</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Ehab</FirstName>
<LastName>Al-Shaer</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>S</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Ehab S Al-Shaer</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>ealshaer@uncc.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6308900225</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000107327</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/21/2013</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of North Carolina at Charlotte</Name>
<CityName>CHARLOTTE</CityName>
<ZipCode>282230001</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>7046871888</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>9201 University City Boulevard</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>North Carolina</StateName>
<StateCode>NC</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>12</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NC12</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>066300096</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF NORTH CAROLINA AT CHARLOTTE, THE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>142363428</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of North Carolina at Charlotte]]></Name>
<CityName>Charlotte</CityName>
<StateCode>NC</StateCode>
<ZipCode>282230001</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[9201 University City Blvd.]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>North Carolina</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>12</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NC12</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7363</Code>
<Text>Networking Technology and Syst</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7923</Code>
<Text>SMALL PROJECT</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0113</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2013~249999</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Stealthy and sophisticated DDoS attacks on cyber infrastructure can be highly devastating, as they can cause major disruption of the service availability and significant degradation of network performance. The aim of this project is to develop techniques and frameworks to make cyber infrastructure resilient to sophisticated attacks such as highly distributed and stealthy denial of services attacks that targets critical links, malicious man-in-the-middle switches, attack of failures on control plan that will cause a catastrophic impact of data plan. This project leverages and complements the power of the virtual network (VN) technology to develop and integrate new agility capability in the cyber infrastructure. The new capabilities of cyber agility developed in this project enable VN to intelligently and nonintrusive migrate to deceive and avoid infrastructure attacks. The project has four objectives: (1) Developing a framework for network agility via enabling virtual network (VN) migration, (2) Investigating, developing and evaluating formal strategies for VN migration, (3)&nbsp; Investigating, developing and evaluating VN migration mechanisms on two distinct Virtual Infrastructure such as PlanetLab and GENI, and (4)&nbsp; developing network agility case studies for our proposal work considering a range of security and resource management applications that benefit from VN migration.</p> <p>To accomplish these goals, the following research tasks were completed:</p> <p>- The project developed a model formal for specifying and validating the VN migration strategies for enabling correct-by-construction VN migration planning by dynamically reallocating and remapping network resources while preserving the VN placement requirements and security properties.&nbsp;</p> <p>- The project offers a novel mitigation technique to avoid and mitigate stealthy DDoS infrastructure attack (such as Crossfire attack) proactively through frequently mutating the footprint of critical resources and constantly deceiving the adversaries during their reconnaissance about the actual critical links in the network.</p> <p>- The project offers a practical mechanism for efficient&nbsp;VN migration that identifies the appropriate configuration sequence, which was implemented and tested on both PlanetLab and GENI infrastructure. The project shows that router/node migration can be implemented to guarantee minimal interruption and quality of service degradation.</p> <p>- This project offers a new metric to quantitatively measure the potential susceptibility of any arbitrary target server or domain to stealthy infrastructure DDoS attacks and proposes proactive route mutation techniques to reduce minimize the susceptibility and improve the availability and resilience of critical services. &nbsp;Intuitively, an enterprise is considered highly susceptible if there exists only a small set of static critical links and it shares these links with a majority of its geographical neighbors.&nbsp; In our susceptibility measurement experiments, we use PlanetLab to evaluate the susceptibility of different enterprises on the Internet. Our analyses reveal that many public servers have only a few critical links and congesting only four critical links&nbsp;can cause&nbsp; 60- 90% service degradation in most cases.</p> <p>- This project offers new resilient network reachability through proactive routing mutation that periodically reroutes active flow to increase the routing diversity and invalidate the attackers&rsquo; knowledge of the critical links. &nbsp;The proposed approach guarantees the creation of provably-correct route mutations that satisfy the cyber mission requirements such as security and&nbsp; QoS, and resilience requirements such as avoiding overlapping with highly susceptible critical links. &nbsp;Our evaluation shows that the effectiveness of our solution ranges from 75-85% for a network of 1000 nodes, and the route mutation configuration time does not exceed 100ms, and the average mutation path length is reasonable (about 9 hops). These figures validate the practical feasibility, effectiveness, and scalability of our approach.</p> <p>- In this project produces novel VN agility techniques to defend against man-in-the-middle (MitM) attacks on SDN due to compromised switches that can severely degrade network throughput and cause data flooding by dropping only a small&nbsp;fraction&nbsp;of control&nbsp;traffic unsuspiciously. In this attack model, a malicious MitM along the control path can randomly drop a small fraction of control traffic to cause significant data throughput reduction and data flooding at the SDN switches. This is because the control message response time of the controller greatly influences the available buffer capacity at the switches and network throughput. Our developed system can discover man-in-the-middle attacks in large scale networks in a few minutes.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 04/01/2019<br>      Modified by: Ehab&nbsp;S&nbsp;Al-Shaer</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Stealthy and sophisticated DDoS attacks on cyber infrastructure can be highly devastating, as they can cause major disruption of the service availability and significant degradation of network performance. The aim of this project is to develop techniques and frameworks to make cyber infrastructure resilient to sophisticated attacks such as highly distributed and stealthy denial of services attacks that targets critical links, malicious man-in-the-middle switches, attack of failures on control plan that will cause a catastrophic impact of data plan. This project leverages and complements the power of the virtual network (VN) technology to develop and integrate new agility capability in the cyber infrastructure. The new capabilities of cyber agility developed in this project enable VN to intelligently and nonintrusive migrate to deceive and avoid infrastructure attacks. The project has four objectives: (1) Developing a framework for network agility via enabling virtual network (VN) migration, (2) Investigating, developing and evaluating formal strategies for VN migration, (3)  Investigating, developing and evaluating VN migration mechanisms on two distinct Virtual Infrastructure such as PlanetLab and GENI, and (4)  developing network agility case studies for our proposal work considering a range of security and resource management applications that benefit from VN migration.  To accomplish these goals, the following research tasks were completed:  - The project developed a model formal for specifying and validating the VN migration strategies for enabling correct-by-construction VN migration planning by dynamically reallocating and remapping network resources while preserving the VN placement requirements and security properties.   - The project offers a novel mitigation technique to avoid and mitigate stealthy DDoS infrastructure attack (such as Crossfire attack) proactively through frequently mutating the footprint of critical resources and constantly deceiving the adversaries during their reconnaissance about the actual critical links in the network.  - The project offers a practical mechanism for efficient VN migration that identifies the appropriate configuration sequence, which was implemented and tested on both PlanetLab and GENI infrastructure. The project shows that router/node migration can be implemented to guarantee minimal interruption and quality of service degradation.  - This project offers a new metric to quantitatively measure the potential susceptibility of any arbitrary target server or domain to stealthy infrastructure DDoS attacks and proposes proactive route mutation techniques to reduce minimize the susceptibility and improve the availability and resilience of critical services.  Intuitively, an enterprise is considered highly susceptible if there exists only a small set of static critical links and it shares these links with a majority of its geographical neighbors.  In our susceptibility measurement experiments, we use PlanetLab to evaluate the susceptibility of different enterprises on the Internet. Our analyses reveal that many public servers have only a few critical links and congesting only four critical links can cause  60- 90% service degradation in most cases.  - This project offers new resilient network reachability through proactive routing mutation that periodically reroutes active flow to increase the routing diversity and invalidate the attackers? knowledge of the critical links.  The proposed approach guarantees the creation of provably-correct route mutations that satisfy the cyber mission requirements such as security and  QoS, and resilience requirements such as avoiding overlapping with highly susceptible critical links.  Our evaluation shows that the effectiveness of our solution ranges from 75-85% for a network of 1000 nodes, and the route mutation configuration time does not exceed 100ms, and the average mutation path length is reasonable (about 9 hops). These figures validate the practical feasibility, effectiveness, and scalability of our approach.  - In this project produces novel VN agility techniques to defend against man-in-the-middle (MitM) attacks on SDN due to compromised switches that can severely degrade network throughput and cause data flooding by dropping only a small fraction of control traffic unsuspiciously. In this attack model, a malicious MitM along the control path can randomly drop a small fraction of control traffic to cause significant data throughput reduction and data flooding at the SDN switches. This is because the control message response time of the controller greatly influences the available buffer capacity at the switches and network throughput. Our developed system can discover man-in-the-middle attacks in large scale networks in a few minutes.       Last Modified: 04/01/2019       Submitted by: Ehab S Al-Shaer]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
