<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>RI: Small: Automated Planning of Experiments for Design Optimization</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2013</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>440000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>483840</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>05020000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>CSE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>IIS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Information &amp; Intelligent Systems</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Jie Yang</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>jyang@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924768</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Many engineering and scientific projects require planning experimental activities in order to optimize an objective. Such planning involves jointly reasoning about both the budget-limited resource constraints among activities along with the utility of potential information that they may provide. Unfortunately, for many real-world planning problems, with rich structure among potential activities, tools from classic experimental design are not directly applicable due to their simplifying assumptions and poor scalability. This project aims to transform the practice of experimental planning by developing new algorithms that account for the complexities exhibited in a wide range of domains.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The project involves three key activities. First, the experimental design description language (EDDL) is being created for formally modeling complex real-world experimental domains. Second, novel planning algorithms are being developed for efficiently computing high-quality solutions to problems expressed in EDDL. Third, work with bioengineers is assessing and improving the usability of the tools and producing benchmark problems based on real and simulated bioengineering data. The creation of the language and benchmarks will help facilitate algorithm comparisons for continued progress by the wider research community.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The broader impact of the project is to facilitate experiment planning in a wide range of experimental domains for which there are currently no available computational tools. Currently, in such domains, planning is largely ad-hoc and often done without computer support. Our research has broad economic impact potential by helping engineers and scientists to get the most value out of limited experimental resources. The project also advances high school, undergraduate, and graduate education in the areas of computer science and bio-engineering, with an emphasis on recruiting female students. The students will get the unique experience of working across disciplines and research labs.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/31/2013</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/06/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.070</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1320943</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Alan</FirstName>
<LastName>Fern</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Alan Fern</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>afern@eecs.oregonstate.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5417373437</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000088242</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/31/2013</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Xiaoli</FirstName>
<LastName>Fern</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>Z</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Xiaoli Z Fern</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>xfern@eecs.oregonstate.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5417372557</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000288466</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/31/2013</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Oregon State University</Name>
<CityName>Corvallis</CityName>
<ZipCode>973318507</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5417374933</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>OREGON STATE UNIVERSITY</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Oregon</StateName>
<StateCode>OR</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>OR04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>053599908</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>OREGON STATE UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>053599908</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Oregon State University]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>OR</StateCode>
<ZipCode>973318507</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Oregon</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>OR04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7495</Code>
<Text>Robust Intelligence</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7495</Code>
<Text>ROBUST INTELLIGENCE</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7923</Code>
<Text>SMALL PROJECT</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9251</Code>
<Text>REU SUPP-Res Exp for Ugrd Supp</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0113</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0114</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0115</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0116</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2013~136059</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~319941</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2015~13440</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2016~14400</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Many engineering and scientific projects require planning experimental activities in order to optimize an objective. Such planning involves jointly reasoning about both the budget-limited resource constraints among activities along with the utility of potential information that they may provide. Unfortunately, for many real-world planning problems, with rich structure among potential activities, tools from classic experimental design are not directly applicable due to their simplifying assumptions and poor scalability. This project developed new algorithms for automating the planning of experiments and experimental activities in such domains.&nbsp;</p> <p>The intellectual merit of the work was to significantly extend the capabilities of automated planning algorithms to handle the complexity of experimental-design planning problems. These complexities include large action spaces, large hybrid state spaces, long planning horizons, and large degrees of uncertainty about experimental activities and outcomes. The project produced&nbsp; new algorithms within the framework of Monte-Carlo Tree Search, which&nbsp; addresses these fundamental challenges. In addition, the algorithms were analyzed at a theoretical level, which provided insight into conditions under which they can be expected to perform well and even near optimally.</p> <p>The broader impact of the project was to facilitate experiment planning in a wide range of experimental domains for which there are currently no available computational tools. Prior to the project,&nbsp; planning in such domains was&nbsp; largely ad-hoc and often done without computer support. During the project collaborators in bio-engineering and material science were engaged to guide the algorithm design and to collect data for evaluating the algorithms. This experience has set the stage for engaging additional collaborators in the future and making the use of software for experimental design much more common in industry, science, and engineering.&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 01/24/2018<br>      Modified by: Alan&nbsp;Fern</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Many engineering and scientific projects require planning experimental activities in order to optimize an objective. Such planning involves jointly reasoning about both the budget-limited resource constraints among activities along with the utility of potential information that they may provide. Unfortunately, for many real-world planning problems, with rich structure among potential activities, tools from classic experimental design are not directly applicable due to their simplifying assumptions and poor scalability. This project developed new algorithms for automating the planning of experiments and experimental activities in such domains.   The intellectual merit of the work was to significantly extend the capabilities of automated planning algorithms to handle the complexity of experimental-design planning problems. These complexities include large action spaces, large hybrid state spaces, long planning horizons, and large degrees of uncertainty about experimental activities and outcomes. The project produced  new algorithms within the framework of Monte-Carlo Tree Search, which  addresses these fundamental challenges. In addition, the algorithms were analyzed at a theoretical level, which provided insight into conditions under which they can be expected to perform well and even near optimally.  The broader impact of the project was to facilitate experiment planning in a wide range of experimental domains for which there are currently no available computational tools. Prior to the project,  planning in such domains was  largely ad-hoc and often done without computer support. During the project collaborators in bio-engineering and material science were engaged to guide the algorithm design and to collect data for evaluating the algorithms. This experience has set the stage for engaging additional collaborators in the future and making the use of software for experimental design much more common in industry, science, and engineering.           Last Modified: 01/24/2018       Submitted by: Alan Fern]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
