<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>III: Small: Causal and Statistical Inference in the Presence of Confounding Factors</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>06/01/2013</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>499919.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>499919</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>05020000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>CSE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>IIS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Information &amp; Intelligent Systems</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Sylvia Spengler</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>sspengle@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032928930</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Technical:&lt;br/&gt;The presence of unmeasured confounding factors can result in incorrect statistical and causal inferences if the confounding factors are correlated with the observed data. This phenomenon has been well documented in at least two important applications. One application is identifying genetic variation involved in disease from populations of related individuals. A second application is identifying genes active in a disease when comparing disease and health samples. In this proposal we propose a new approach to correct for unobserved confounders in taking advantage of insights into how confounders affect high dimensional data. These insights motivate a formal definition for a specific type of confounder which we term a 'low-rank confounder.' Formalizing this definition allows us to motivate methods for correcting for the effects of these types confounders even when the confounders are not observed. Our proposal will develop a theory of how confounders affect data and under what conditions unobserved confounders can be corrected. The proposed theory is related to recent developments in understanding sparsity which has been well studied in electrical engineering, computer science and statistics. The result of our proposed methods will lead to improved methods for applications where such confounders are present.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Non-technical:&lt;br/&gt;Inference of knowledge from high dimensional data is a fundamental problem affecting virtually all areas of science including physics, astronomy, chemistry, computer science, social science and many areas of biology. Many of these problems are driven by recently available large sources of data and advances in measurement or data collection technologies. A major challenge is the presence of unknown (and unmeasured) confounding factors. Confounding factors are variables that are often not observed in the data, but are correlated with various features of the data. Unfortunately, confounding factors can cause incorrect inferences. This phenomenon has been well documented in at least two important applications: one application is identifying genetic variation involved in disease from populations of related individuals, and a second application is identifying genes active in a disease when comparing disease and health samples. There are traditional approaches to perform inference if the confounders are observed in the data. However, dealing with unobserved confounders is more difficult. This project will develop and study a new approach to correct for unobserved confounders, taking advantage of insights into how confounders affect high dimensional data. The project has broad impact due to its utility in a wide range of scientific questions, through the interdisciplinary research opportunities provided to undergraduate and graduate students, and through the distribution of software and data.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/04/2013</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/04/2013</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.070</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1320589</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Eleazar</FirstName>
<LastName>Eskin</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Eleazar Eskin</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>eeskin@cs.ucla.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>3104284809</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000491080</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/04/2013</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of California-Los Angeles</Name>
<CityName>LOS ANGELES</CityName>
<ZipCode>900951406</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>3107940102</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>10889 Wilshire Boulevard</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[Suite 700]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>33</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CA33</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>092530369</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF CALIFORNIA, LOS ANGELES</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>071549000</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of California-Los Angeles]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>900951596</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[420 Westwood Plaza, 4732 BH]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>33</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CA33</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7364</Code>
<Text>Info Integration &amp; Informatics</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7923</Code>
<Text>SMALL PROJECT</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0113</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2013~499919</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Inference of knowledge from high dimensional data is a fundamental problem that affects virtually all areas of science&mdash;including physics, astronomy, chemistry, computer science, the social sciences, and the biological sciences. This problem is driven by recent advances in data collection and measurement technologies, which have produced large sources of data.</p> <p>One challenge in the analysis of high dimensional data is that the data can be affected by unknown factors, which may cause incorrect conclusions to be drawn from the analysis. These factors are referred to as unknown (or unmeasured) confounding factors. These confounding factors are variables that are not observed in the data, yet they are correlated with various features of the data.</p> <p>This project developed and tested new approaches to correct for unobserved confounders, taking advantage of insights into how confounders affect high dimensional data. This insight led to a method which can correct for the confounding factors without needing to observe them. We used this basic framework to make contributions to multiple analytical problems in genomics. During the course of the project, we applied our framework and developed tools for analyzing genetic data confounded by population structure, expression data confounded by technical artifacts, and epigenetic data confounded by cell type composition. We also developed methodologies for incorporating environmental and clinical co-variates into genetic data. Throughout the project, we developed multiple impactful tools that implement our methods and are widely available to the scientific community.</p> <p>During the first year, we addressed the problem of multiple confounding factors that may identify spurious (false) regulatory hotspots in expression quantitative trait loci (eQTL) mapping. eQTL mapping is a tool that can systematically identify genetic variation that affects gene expression. eQTL mapping studies have shown that specific genomic locations, referred to as regulatory hotspots, may affect the expression levels of many genes. eQTL studies can help identify genetic variants involved in the development of complex diseases and traits, but studies have shown that various confounding factors may induce spurious regulatory hotspots. In response, we developed a novel statistical method that effectively eliminates spurious hotspots while retaining genuine hotspots.</p> <p>During the second year, we began addressing the problem of population structure as a confounding factor in genome-wide association studies (GWAS). GWAS seeks associations between single-nucleotide polymorphisms (SNPs) and diseases. One challenge to producing accurate GWAS results is that of relatedness, termed &ldquo;population structure,&rdquo; within a study cohort. Population structure can cause a GWAS method to incorrectly identify genetic variants as associated with a disease. Developing GWAS techniques to effectively test for association while correcting for population structure is a computational and statistical challenge. In response, we developed GAMMA, a novel approach for simultaneously analyzing many phenotypes and correcting for population structure. We also developed several approaches capable of improving the efficiency and accuracy of multiple-trait association mapping and identifying multiple causal variants with multiple association signals.</p> <p>During the third year, we developed a novel approach for imputing phenotypes in GWAS and a new algorithm that corrects for cell heterogeneity as a confounding factor in epigenome-wide association studies (EWAS). In the first case, we take advantage of additional, related phenotypes&mdash;typically considered a confounding factor&mdash;to impute the phenotype of interest or target phenotype and then perform association analysis. In the second case, we developed ReFACTor, an algorithm that provides improved estimates of cell type composition, resulting in increased power and control for false positives in EWAS.</p> <p>During the fourth year, we expanded our work on population structure as a low ranking confounder in GWAS to include genome-wide gene-by-environment association analyses. One of the main challenges in assessing gene-by-environment interactions (GEIs) in GWAS is to control the effects of population structure that may cause spurious associations. We developed a statistical approach based on mixed models to account for population structure on GEI statistics. We also developed an algorithm for modeling the effects of selection or ascertainment bias. These low ranking confounders emerge when the case&ndash;control disease status is coded as variables with discrete values. It is harder to model the correlation structure and perform inference in such a model when one variable is discrete and one is continuous&mdash;as opposed to when both are continuous.</p> <p>This project has broad impact due to its utility in a wide range of scientific problems, the interdisciplinary research opportunities provided to undergraduate and graduate students, and the distribution of software and data. Our project contributed to the development of a new undergraduate degree program at UCLA in Bioinformatics. This program has trained many students who were inspired by the research area to continue their studies in a Ph.D. program. We also partnered with an undergraduate summer program at UCLA, Bruins in Genomics. This program seeks to increase the interest among undergraduate students in pursuing graduate study and aims to broaden participation in research by recruiting underrepresented minority students.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 08/16/2017<br>      Modified by: Eleazar&nbsp;Eskin</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Inference of knowledge from high dimensional data is a fundamental problem that affects virtually all areas of science&mdash;including physics, astronomy, chemistry, computer science, the social sciences, and the biological sciences. This problem is driven by recent advances in data collection and measurement technologies, which have produced large sources of data.  One challenge in the analysis of high dimensional data is that the data can be affected by unknown factors, which may cause incorrect conclusions to be drawn from the analysis. These factors are referred to as unknown (or unmeasured) confounding factors. These confounding factors are variables that are not observed in the data, yet they are correlated with various features of the data.  This project developed and tested new approaches to correct for unobserved confounders, taking advantage of insights into how confounders affect high dimensional data. This insight led to a method which can correct for the confounding factors without needing to observe them. We used this basic framework to make contributions to multiple analytical problems in genomics. During the course of the project, we applied our framework and developed tools for analyzing genetic data confounded by population structure, expression data confounded by technical artifacts, and epigenetic data confounded by cell type composition. We also developed methodologies for incorporating environmental and clinical co-variates into genetic data. Throughout the project, we developed multiple impactful tools that implement our methods and are widely available to the scientific community.  During the first year, we addressed the problem of multiple confounding factors that may identify spurious (false) regulatory hotspots in expression quantitative trait loci (eQTL) mapping. eQTL mapping is a tool that can systematically identify genetic variation that affects gene expression. eQTL mapping studies have shown that specific genomic locations, referred to as regulatory hotspots, may affect the expression levels of many genes. eQTL studies can help identify genetic variants involved in the development of complex diseases and traits, but studies have shown that various confounding factors may induce spurious regulatory hotspots. In response, we developed a novel statistical method that effectively eliminates spurious hotspots while retaining genuine hotspots.  During the second year, we began addressing the problem of population structure as a confounding factor in genome-wide association studies (GWAS). GWAS seeks associations between single-nucleotide polymorphisms (SNPs) and diseases. One challenge to producing accurate GWAS results is that of relatedness, termed "population structure," within a study cohort. Population structure can cause a GWAS method to incorrectly identify genetic variants as associated with a disease. Developing GWAS techniques to effectively test for association while correcting for population structure is a computational and statistical challenge. In response, we developed GAMMA, a novel approach for simultaneously analyzing many phenotypes and correcting for population structure. We also developed several approaches capable of improving the efficiency and accuracy of multiple-trait association mapping and identifying multiple causal variants with multiple association signals.  During the third year, we developed a novel approach for imputing phenotypes in GWAS and a new algorithm that corrects for cell heterogeneity as a confounding factor in epigenome-wide association studies (EWAS). In the first case, we take advantage of additional, related phenotypes&mdash;typically considered a confounding factor&mdash;to impute the phenotype of interest or target phenotype and then perform association analysis. In the second case, we developed ReFACTor, an algorithm that provides improved estimates of cell type composition, resulting in increased power and control for false positives in EWAS.  During the fourth year, we expanded our work on population structure as a low ranking confounder in GWAS to include genome-wide gene-by-environment association analyses. One of the main challenges in assessing gene-by-environment interactions (GEIs) in GWAS is to control the effects of population structure that may cause spurious associations. We developed a statistical approach based on mixed models to account for population structure on GEI statistics. We also developed an algorithm for modeling the effects of selection or ascertainment bias. These low ranking confounders emerge when the case&ndash;control disease status is coded as variables with discrete values. It is harder to model the correlation structure and perform inference in such a model when one variable is discrete and one is continuous&mdash;as opposed to when both are continuous.  This project has broad impact due to its utility in a wide range of scientific problems, the interdisciplinary research opportunities provided to undergraduate and graduate students, and the distribution of software and data. Our project contributed to the development of a new undergraduate degree program at UCLA in Bioinformatics. This program has trained many students who were inspired by the research area to continue their studies in a Ph.D. program. We also partnered with an undergraduate summer program at UCLA, Bruins in Genomics. This program seeks to increase the interest among undergraduate students in pursuing graduate study and aims to broaden participation in research by recruiting underrepresented minority students.          Last Modified: 08/16/2017       Submitted by: Eleazar Eskin]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
