<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>NeTS: Small: Real-Time Wireless Sensor-Actuator Networks</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>10/01/2013</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>09/30/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>500000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>500000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>05050000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>CSE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CNS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Computer and Network Systems</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Monisha Ghosh</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Recent years have witnessed rapid adoption of wireless sensor-actuator networks (WSANs) in process industries. Real-world deployments of industrial standards such as WirelessHART have demonstrated the feasibility to achieve reliable wireless communication in industrial environments. However, existing wireless technologies still face significant challenges in supporting process control applications that impose stringent real-time requirements on network communication. Moreover, optimizing control performance over wireless networks is challenging due to the coupling between control performance and communication delays, as well as inter-dependencies among multiple layers of the network protocol stack. To meet these critical challenges faced by process industries, this project is developing a control-aware network design approach for WSANs. This holistic approach integrates wireless networking, real-time scheduling and non-linear optimization in a unified framework with three novel technologies: (1) an efficient local search approach that leverages real-time scheduling analysis to optimize control performance over wireless networks; (2) an agile multilayer optimization approach that adapts transmission scheduling, routing and sampling rate selection in a hierarchical fashion in response to network changes; (3) a hierarchical network architecture that enables large-scale real-time wireless control networks. The project implements and evaluates the network architecture and protocols using realistic industrial process control applications on physical wireless testbeds through collaboration with Emerson, an industrial leader of the WirelessHART standard.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Successful completion of this research will enable a broad range of process control applications with high societal and industrial impacts such as oil refining, petrochemicals and water treatment. Collaboration with industrial partners will lead to real-world deployments and technology transfer to process industries through industrial standards. This research will produce an open-source implementation of the real-time wireless protocol stack, which will further broaden the impacts on research, education and industry.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>09/11/2013</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/30/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.070</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1320921</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Chenyang</FirstName>
<LastName>Lu</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Chenyang Lu</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>lu@cse.wustl.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>3149354855</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000243191</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/11/2013</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Yixin</FirstName>
<LastName>Chen</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Yixin Chen</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>chen@cse.wustl.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>3149357528</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000302236</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/11/2013</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Washington University</Name>
<CityName>Saint Louis</CityName>
<ZipCode>631304862</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>3147474134</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>CAMPUS BOX 1054</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[1 Brookings Drive]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Missouri</StateName>
<StateCode>MO</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MO01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>068552207</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>WASHINGTON UNIVERSITY, THE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>068552207</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Washington University]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>MO</StateCode>
<ZipCode>631304899</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Missouri</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MO01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7363</Code>
<Text>Networking Technology and Syst</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7923</Code>
<Text>SMALL PROJECT</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0113</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2013~500000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>In the era of Industrial Internet, process industries are adopting wireless sensor-actuator networks (WSANs) as the communication infrastructure for process automation. Real-world deployments of industrial wireless standards such as WirelessHART have demonstrated the feasibility to achieve reliable wireless communication in industrial environments. However, existing wireless technologies still face significant challenges in supporting process <em>control</em> applications that impose stringent real-time and dependability requirements on network communication. To meet these critical challenges faced by industries, this project produced a suite of novel wireless protocols, algorithms, and systems to drastically enhance the real-time performance of industrial WSANs.&nbsp; The new wireless protocol stack enables efficient and dependable industrial automation through data communication protocols and network adaptation strategies tailored for feedback control systems. &nbsp;The project implements and demonstrates the efficacy of the network architecture and protocols as parts of a WirelessHART protocol stack on both physical wireless testbeds and network-in-the-loop simulations of wireless control systems.&nbsp; This project has also produced and enhanced the <em>Wireless Cyber-Physical Simulator (WCPS)</em>, an open-source simulation environment for holistic and high-fidelity simulations of wirelss control systems.</p> <p>While industrial deployment has been mostly limited to monitoring applications today, technologies produced in this research will enable a broad range of industrial <em>control</em> applications with high societal and industrial impacts (e.g., oil refining, petrochemicals and water treatment), and thereby help unleash the power of wireless technologies in industrial automation.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 01/17/2019<br>      Modified by: Chenyang&nbsp;Lu</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ In the era of Industrial Internet, process industries are adopting wireless sensor-actuator networks (WSANs) as the communication infrastructure for process automation. Real-world deployments of industrial wireless standards such as WirelessHART have demonstrated the feasibility to achieve reliable wireless communication in industrial environments. However, existing wireless technologies still face significant challenges in supporting process control applications that impose stringent real-time and dependability requirements on network communication. To meet these critical challenges faced by industries, this project produced a suite of novel wireless protocols, algorithms, and systems to drastically enhance the real-time performance of industrial WSANs.  The new wireless protocol stack enables efficient and dependable industrial automation through data communication protocols and network adaptation strategies tailored for feedback control systems.  The project implements and demonstrates the efficacy of the network architecture and protocols as parts of a WirelessHART protocol stack on both physical wireless testbeds and network-in-the-loop simulations of wireless control systems.  This project has also produced and enhanced the Wireless Cyber-Physical Simulator (WCPS), an open-source simulation environment for holistic and high-fidelity simulations of wirelss control systems.  While industrial deployment has been mostly limited to monitoring applications today, technologies produced in this research will enable a broad range of industrial control applications with high societal and industrial impacts (e.g., oil refining, petrochemicals and water treatment), and thereby help unleash the power of wireless technologies in industrial automation.       Last Modified: 01/17/2019       Submitted by: Chenyang Lu]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
