<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>SHF: CSR: Small: A Cooperative Framework for Topology Awareness on Large-Scale Systems</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>10/01/2013</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>09/30/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>498377.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>510377</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>05050000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>CSE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CNS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Computer and Network Systems</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Marilyn McClure</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>mmcclure@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032925197</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>As the number of computer nodes increases, so does the size of the interconnect network. Historically, floating point was the most costly component of a system, but this is no longer the case. Systems today, and those anticipated in the future, are increasingly bound by their communication infrastructure and the power dissipation associated with data movement across the rapidly growing number of nodes. How to address the increasing cost of data movement on ever-growing systems is becoming critical.&lt;br/&gt; &lt;br/&gt;This project will develop a framework named COTA, a COoperative framework for Topology Awareness. COTA will be an integrated framework that coordinates across the hardware, job scheduler, runtime, and application to jointly attack the increasing concern of data movement for communication- and power-efficiency on large-scale systems. Most importantly, the framework will support topology awareness not only at job startup, but also during job execution. The newly developed mapping algorithms, topology-aware methods and tools, and topology-aware models will provide a critical foundation for the realization of topology awareness on current and future systems. This research will have a direct impact on system productivity as well as a broad range of application domains that use parallel systems for simulations. The project will also enhance the curriculum at Illinois Institute of technology, broaden the participation by underrepresented groups, and outreach to the surrounding communities.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/05/2013</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/31/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.070</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1320125</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Zhiling</FirstName>
<LastName>Lan</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Zhiling Lan</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>lan@iit.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>3125675710</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000304384</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/05/2013</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Jia</FirstName>
<LastName>Wang</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Jia Wang</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>jwang@ece.iit.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>3125673696</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000514539</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/05/2013</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Illinois Institute of Technology</Name>
<CityName>Chicago</CityName>
<ZipCode>606163717</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>3125673035</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>10 West 35th Street</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[Suite 7D71]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Illinois</StateName>
<StateCode>IL</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>IL01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>042084434</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>ILLINOIS INSTITUTE OF TECHNOLOGY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>042084434</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Illinois Institute of Technology]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>IL</StateCode>
<ZipCode>606163732</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Illinois</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>IL01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7354</Code>
<Text>CSR-Computer Systems Research</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7923</Code>
<Text>SMALL PROJECT</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9178</Code>
<Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9251</Code>
<Text>REU SUPP-Res Exp for Ugrd Supp</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0113</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0114</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2013~498377</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~12000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The objective of this project is to develop COTA, a cooperative framework for topology awareness on large-scale systems through a co-design approach. The research has two important outcomes. One is the design of <em>application aware job scheduling policies</em> to allocate system resources according to high-level application information, and the other is the development of <em>topology aware task mapping methods</em> to map application processes onto allocated resources according to specific application communication pattern. &nbsp;The scheduling policies developed in this project contributed to substantial improvement of system performance by up to 60%. The task mapping algorithms developed in this project resulted in significant reduction of application communication time by up to 72%. Finally, job interference among applications for shared network resources can cause dramatic performance variation on Dragonfly and Fat-tree systems, demanding new research efforts to address this challenge on massively parallel platforms. COTA is the first systematic approach to address the increasing cost of data movement on ever-growing systems. The research has a direct impact on system productivity as well as a broad range of scientific domains that use parallel systems for simulations.</p> <p>This project produced 20+ technical papers at premier conferences and journals, as well as three doctoral dissertations. Other products include an event-driven scheduling simulator CQSim, a topology aware task mapping library TOPOMap, and a light-weight user-transparent communication profiler LibProfil. These tools are freely available to the community at http://www.cs.iit.edu/~lan/software.html.</p> <p>Another key outcome was the training of a group of students, ranging from freshmen to senior graduate students, in the field of parallel computing. The PI contributed to numerous outreach activities to recruit underrepresented minorities in this project. Six female students including four graduate and two undergraduate students participated in this project.&nbsp;&nbsp;</p> <p>The PIs enhanced several courses at Illinois Tech including CS550 &ldquo;Advanced Operating Systems&rdquo;, CS546 &ldquo;Parallel and Distributed Processing&rdquo;, ECE449 &ldquo;Object-Oriented programming and Computer Simulation&rdquo;, and ECE 587 &ldquo;Hardware/Software Co-Design&rdquo;.&nbsp; The PI also created a new course CS451 (&ldquo;Introduction to Parallel and Distributed Computing&rdquo;). It is an introductory course of parallel and distributed concepts to undergraduate students at Illinois Tech.&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 11/14/2017<br>      Modified by: Zhiling&nbsp;Lan</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The objective of this project is to develop COTA, a cooperative framework for topology awareness on large-scale systems through a co-design approach. The research has two important outcomes. One is the design of application aware job scheduling policies to allocate system resources according to high-level application information, and the other is the development of topology aware task mapping methods to map application processes onto allocated resources according to specific application communication pattern.  The scheduling policies developed in this project contributed to substantial improvement of system performance by up to 60%. The task mapping algorithms developed in this project resulted in significant reduction of application communication time by up to 72%. Finally, job interference among applications for shared network resources can cause dramatic performance variation on Dragonfly and Fat-tree systems, demanding new research efforts to address this challenge on massively parallel platforms. COTA is the first systematic approach to address the increasing cost of data movement on ever-growing systems. The research has a direct impact on system productivity as well as a broad range of scientific domains that use parallel systems for simulations.  This project produced 20+ technical papers at premier conferences and journals, as well as three doctoral dissertations. Other products include an event-driven scheduling simulator CQSim, a topology aware task mapping library TOPOMap, and a light-weight user-transparent communication profiler LibProfil. These tools are freely available to the community at http://www.cs.iit.edu/~lan/software.html.  Another key outcome was the training of a group of students, ranging from freshmen to senior graduate students, in the field of parallel computing. The PI contributed to numerous outreach activities to recruit underrepresented minorities in this project. Six female students including four graduate and two undergraduate students participated in this project.    The PIs enhanced several courses at Illinois Tech including CS550 "Advanced Operating Systems", CS546 "Parallel and Distributed Processing", ECE449 "Object-Oriented programming and Computer Simulation", and ECE 587 "Hardware/Software Co-Design".  The PI also created a new course CS451 ("Introduction to Parallel and Distributed Computing"). It is an introductory course of parallel and distributed concepts to undergraduate students at Illinois Tech.           Last Modified: 11/14/2017       Submitted by: Zhiling Lan]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
