<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Collaborative Research: Accounting for the Emergence, Persistence, and Media Coverage of Social Action Organizations</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2013</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2016</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>89898.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>89898</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>04050000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>SBE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>SES</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Divn Of Social and Economic Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>marie cornwall</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>SES-1321802 Tulane University &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Patrick Rafail &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;SES-1322568 &lt;br/&gt;John McCarthy &lt;br/&gt;University of Southern California &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project aims to complete the collection of a six year time series of social action mobilization occurring between 2009 and 2014. Building on the results from previous research, the investigators propose to address three important theoretical questions. The first aims to understand what social structural variation (e.g. income inequality, rates of unemployment) across U.S. states and local communities increases the likelihood that social action will occur and recur. The second asks what community contexts facilitate the founding of social action organization as well as the factors influencing the organizational linkages and survival of these groups over time. The third, asks which factors influence the intensity, tone, and content of newspaper coverage of such groups. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;To address these questions, the researchers will assemble a database of social action events as well as organizational foundings, other local activities such as meetings or demonstrations, and organization survival by combining multiple sources of data including internet listings, systematic searches of 432 local newspapers, and content coding of newspaper stories of covered events. The research will geographically situate each event and organization, which will be linked to a larger database of social structural indicators, information on election cycle outcomes, and newspaper characteristics. Statistical approaches to modeling the processes will include hierarchical regression, survival analysis, web scraping, text mining, and natural language processing.  &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Broader Impact&lt;br/&gt;The proposed project has enormous potential for having broader impact in several ways. First, it will provide a comprehensive, systematic analysis of social action groups. Second, the investigators will create a public use data set to allow diverse additional investigations of the causes and consequences of social action group mobilization from a wide variety of perspectives beyond our own. And, finally, the researchers will be able to chronicle these social movements from infancy into maturity as well as signs of their decline. Additionally, the project incorporates specific research experiences for both graduate and undergraduate students.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/28/2013</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/28/2013</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.075</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1321802</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Patrick</FirstName>
<LastName>Rafail</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Patrick Rafail</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>prafail@tulane.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5048654000</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000638073</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/28/2013</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Tulane University</Name>
<CityName>NEW ORLEANS</CityName>
<ZipCode>701185698</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5048654000</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>6823 ST CHARLES AVENUE</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Louisiana</StateName>
<StateCode>LA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>LA01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>053785812</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>ADMINISTRATORS OF THE TULANE EDUCATIONAL FUND, THE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>053785812</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Tulane University]]></Name>
<CityName>New Orleans</CityName>
<StateCode>LA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>701185665</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[6823 St. Charles Avenue]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Louisiana</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>LA01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1331</Code>
<Text>Sociology</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9251</Code>
<Text>REU SUPP-Res Exp for Ugrd Supp</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0113</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2013~89898</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The Tea Party movement emerged rapidly following the 2008 U.S. national election erupting with an initial wave of more than one thousand Tax Day protests on April 15, 2009, followed by similar waves in 2010, 2011, and 2012. During this period, Tea Party organizations were founded across the country in thousands of communities. In contrast to quite anemic levels of progressive protest during the first decade of the 21<sup>st</sup> century, this apparent grass-roots and populist uprising projected an anti-tax and anti-government message in communities across the nation. The completion of this project will make available a comprehensive time series of several aspects of Tea Party mobilization between 2009 and 2014.</p> <p>&nbsp;The project reveals three core findings. First, mobilization declined significantly between 2009 and 2014. We tracked protests surrounding the annual tax day rallies staged by the Tea Party, and found that while more than 1,100 events took place in 2009, just 22 occurred in 2014. Second, despite having a strong organizational presence across the United States in 2009, many of the thousands of local Tea Party chapters have ceased activities. Of the remaining groups, most are not connected to the national Tea Party movement. Third, the relationship between the Tea Party and the media is quite complex, even when examining the mutually beneficial linkage between the Tea Party and Fox News. Media attention to the Tea Party has been highly cyclical, and over time became increasingly focused on activities of political leaders rather than local movement organizations and actors.</p> <p>In the course of completing this research, extensive databases on the Tea Party were built, and we are taking the final steps to make them freely available to the public. These databases include: (1) the location, size, and other details of the annual tax day rallies between 2009 and 2014; (2) the founding date, location, and mobilization history of local Tea Party chapters; and (3) the date, major topic, and publication information from newspaper articles, cable news references, and blog posts about the Tea Party between 2009 and 2014.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 09/21/2016<br>      Modified by: Patrick&nbsp;Rafail</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The Tea Party movement emerged rapidly following the 2008 U.S. national election erupting with an initial wave of more than one thousand Tax Day protests on April 15, 2009, followed by similar waves in 2010, 2011, and 2012. During this period, Tea Party organizations were founded across the country in thousands of communities. In contrast to quite anemic levels of progressive protest during the first decade of the 21st century, this apparent grass-roots and populist uprising projected an anti-tax and anti-government message in communities across the nation. The completion of this project will make available a comprehensive time series of several aspects of Tea Party mobilization between 2009 and 2014.   The project reveals three core findings. First, mobilization declined significantly between 2009 and 2014. We tracked protests surrounding the annual tax day rallies staged by the Tea Party, and found that while more than 1,100 events took place in 2009, just 22 occurred in 2014. Second, despite having a strong organizational presence across the United States in 2009, many of the thousands of local Tea Party chapters have ceased activities. Of the remaining groups, most are not connected to the national Tea Party movement. Third, the relationship between the Tea Party and the media is quite complex, even when examining the mutually beneficial linkage between the Tea Party and Fox News. Media attention to the Tea Party has been highly cyclical, and over time became increasingly focused on activities of political leaders rather than local movement organizations and actors.  In the course of completing this research, extensive databases on the Tea Party were built, and we are taking the final steps to make them freely available to the public. These databases include: (1) the location, size, and other details of the annual tax day rallies between 2009 and 2014; (2) the founding date, location, and mobilization history of local Tea Party chapters; and (3) the date, major topic, and publication information from newspaper articles, cable news references, and blog posts about the Tea Party between 2009 and 2014.       Last Modified: 09/21/2016       Submitted by: Patrick Rafail]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
