<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Computational Algorithms for Imaging, Design and Inverse Problems of Particle Propagation in Heterogeneous Media</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/15/2013</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>259565.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>259565</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DMS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Leland Jameson</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>ljameson@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924883</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This project is concerned with the computational study of some imaging, optimal design and inverse problems related to systems of kinetic equations that model the propagation of particles in complex heterogeneous media. The objective is to develop fast and robust numerical algorithms by intelligently utilizing information on the structures of both the model equations and the inverse problems that we obtained through computational and mathematical studies of them, sometimes in simplified settings. Precisely, the proposed research include (i) to develop fast forward and inversion algorithms by preconditioning the computation with computationally less expensive models; (ii) to develop efficient computational strategies for uncertainty quantification and variance reduction in the imaging and inverse problems involve randomness; and (iii) to develop and validate direct non-iterative methods for imaging in extended targets in heterogeneous media. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The main motivation for the study is the application of the problems in (i) optimizing the delivery of radiation therapy to caner patients; (ii) designing efficient nano-scale semiconductor devices; and (iii) imaging extended targets in highly-scattering random environments. The proposed research is expected to have long-term impacts in the practices of intensity-modulated radiation treatment planning for cancer treatment, semiconductor solar cell design for energy harvesting, and imaging in heterogeneous environment for homeland security applications. The project involves a significant education component that aims at training both undergraduate and graduate students. The ideas and techniques developed in this project will be incorporated into a graduate level class on numerical methods for imaging and inverse problems which will benefit graduates who are interested in applying advanced mathematical and computational techniques to solve real-world problems. The lecture notes for this graduate class will be made accessible to the general public through the PI's webpage hosted by the PI's institution.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/08/2013</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/08/2013</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1321018</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Kui</FirstName>
<LastName>Ren</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Kui Ren</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>kr2002@columbia.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2128544731</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000497770</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/08/2013</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Texas at Austin</Name>
<CityName>Austin</CityName>
<ZipCode>787595316</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5124716424</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>3925 W Braker Lane, Ste 3.340</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Texas</StateName>
<StateCode>TX</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>10</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>TX10</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>170230239</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF TEXAS AT AUSTIN</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>042000273</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Texas at Austin]]></Name>
<CityName>Austin</CityName>
<StateCode>TX</StateCode>
<ZipCode>787121532</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[101 E. 27th Street, Suite 5.300]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Texas</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>25</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>TX25</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1271</Code>
<Text>COMPUTATIONAL MATHEMATICS</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9263</Code>
<Text>COMPUTATIONAL SCIENCE &amp; ENGING</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0113</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2013~259565</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><span><span style="font-size: small;">This project is concerned with computational studies of imaging, design and inverse problems related to system of partial differential equations that model the propagation of waves and particles in complex media such as biological tissues. The studies are motivated by applications in biomedical imaging and radiation treatment planning.</span></span></p> <p><span><span style="font-size: small;"><br /></span></span></p> <p><span><span style="font-size: small;">During the project period, detailed mathematical analysis have been performed on the proposed research problems. The analysis not only increased our fundamental understanding of such problems, but also led to fast and robust computational methods for solving such problems. More precisely, (i) we analyzed in detail quantitative photoacoustic tomography in different application regimes (including for instance fluorescence photoacoustic imaging, two-photon photoacoustic imaging), and developed several non-iterative (thus efficient) quantitative image reconstruction strategies. (ii) We studied the problem of charge transport in semiconductor-electrolyte based solar cells and constructed a mathematical model for the simulation of charge transfer in such solar cells. Based on the mathematical model, we developed several numerical algorithms for large scale numerical simulations. </span><span><span style="font-size: small;">&nbsp;</span></span><span style="font-size: small;">(iii) We developed a fast solver for the radiative transport equation for simulating the propagation of electromagnetic radiation in in biological tissues. This fast solver is currently being incorporated into an optimization-based radiation treatment planning algorithm.</span></span></p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p><span><span style="font-size: small;">&nbsp;</span></span><span><span style="font-size: small;">This project directly involved the training of three graduate students and one postdoctoral researcher. Moreover, this project has provided research problems for two undergraduate students for their research internships. The three graduate students have all finished their PhD thesis on the topics of research in this project.&nbsp;Several research outcomes of this project&nbsp;are integrated into a graduate&nbsp;course on inverse problems and imaging&nbsp;that have been taught at the&nbsp;PI's institution. In terms of research achievements, this project has led to ten published papers and seven manuscripts under review. The graduate students and the principle investigator have given forty-six presentations on results from this project in international conferences, workshops and seminars.</span></span></p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 10/02/2017<br>      Modified by: Kui&nbsp;Ren</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ This project is concerned with computational studies of imaging, design and inverse problems related to system of partial differential equations that model the propagation of waves and particles in complex media such as biological tissues. The studies are motivated by applications in biomedical imaging and radiation treatment planning.     During the project period, detailed mathematical analysis have been performed on the proposed research problems. The analysis not only increased our fundamental understanding of such problems, but also led to fast and robust computational methods for solving such problems. More precisely, (i) we analyzed in detail quantitative photoacoustic tomography in different application regimes (including for instance fluorescence photoacoustic imaging, two-photon photoacoustic imaging), and developed several non-iterative (thus efficient) quantitative image reconstruction strategies. (ii) We studied the problem of charge transport in semiconductor-electrolyte based solar cells and constructed a mathematical model for the simulation of charge transfer in such solar cells. Based on the mathematical model, we developed several numerical algorithms for large scale numerical simulations.  (iii) We developed a fast solver for the radiative transport equation for simulating the propagation of electromagnetic radiation in in biological tissues. This fast solver is currently being incorporated into an optimization-based radiation treatment planning algorithm.      This project directly involved the training of three graduate students and one postdoctoral researcher. Moreover, this project has provided research problems for two undergraduate students for their research internships. The three graduate students have all finished their PhD thesis on the topics of research in this project. Several research outcomes of this project are integrated into a graduate course on inverse problems and imaging that have been taught at the PI's institution. In terms of research achievements, this project has led to ten published papers and seven manuscripts under review. The graduate students and the principle investigator have given forty-six presentations on results from this project in international conferences, workshops and seminars.       Last Modified: 10/02/2017       Submitted by: Kui Ren]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
