<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>CNIC: US-India Collaborative Research to Decipher Function and Evolution of GABAergic Neurotransmission in Planaria</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2013</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2016</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>29570.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>29570</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>01090000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>O/D</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Office Of The Director</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>OISE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Office Of Internatl Science &amp;Engineering</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Cassandra Dudka</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>cdudka@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927250</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>1322626&lt;br/&gt;Latha Ramakrishnan &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This Catalyzing New International Collaboration (CNIC) award supports U.S.-India Collaborative Research to Decipher Function and Evolution of GABAergic Neurotransmission in Planaria. Professor Latha Ramakrishnan, St. Cloud State University will initiate an international collaboration with Dr. Priyadarsi De, Indian Institute of Science Education and Research-Kolkata to develop novel reagents for investigating the evolution and function of GABAergic neurotransmission. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The interdisciplinary research endeavor is to design and fabricate cell-type targeted nanomaterials for GABAergic gene function analysis in planaria using a powerful new gene knockdown technique for tissue specific controlled suppression of gene expression. The technique could provide a discrete tool for the functional characterization of the GABA receptor family in planarians and inform our understanding of the evolution of this important pathway. There is increasing interest in the invertebrate organism as a model for various neurobiological and developmental studies. The researchers combined expertise spans chemistry, physical chemistry, molecular biology, and materials science.    &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The award supports travel for the US PI and senior undergraduate student to visit the collaborator?s lab in India where they will develop and learn how to synthesize the polymeric nanoparticles that will be derivatized to promote specific knockdown of key mRNA targets. Proof of principle experiments will be carried out by graduate and undergraduate students in the respective laboratories with the overall goal of submitting a competitive pre-proposal to the Integrative Organismal Systems, Neural Systems Cluster. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;If the project goals are achieved, this research could significantly impact the neurosciences and    other fields such as materials science and nanotechnology. It may also have far-reaching broader impacts on multidisciplinary research and it will have provided a unique international research experience for the next generation of student participants in this project.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/30/2013</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/30/2013</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.079</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1322626</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Latha</FirstName>
<LastName>Ramakrishnan</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Latha Ramakrishnan</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>lramakrishnan@stcloudstate.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>3203083257</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000073090</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/30/2013</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>St. Cloud State University</Name>
<CityName>St. Cloud</CityName>
<ZipCode>563014498</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>3203084932</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>720 Fourth Avenue South</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Minnesota</StateName>
<StateCode>MN</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>06</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MN06</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>027613855</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>ST. CLOUD STATE UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>064754757</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[St. Cloud State University]]></Name>
<CityName>St. Cloud</CityName>
<StateCode>MN</StateCode>
<ZipCode>563014498</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[720 4th Ave S]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Minnesota</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>06</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MN06</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7299</Code>
<Text>Catalyzing New Intl Collab</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>5919</Code>
<Text>INDIA (COOPERATIVE SCIENCE)</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>5976</Code>
<Text>AFRICA, NEAR EAST, &amp; SO ASIA</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0113</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2013~29570</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>This award initiated new international research collaboration between researchers at St. Cloud State University and Indian Institute of Science Education and Research- Kolkata (IISER-K) in India. &nbsp;The intellectual merits of this research collaboration is promising preliminary results demonstrating the delivery of SiRNA into cells using the cationic polymeric nanoparticles synthesized by researchers at IISER-K. &nbsp;This award also brought tangible results in terms of additional collaboration on a different research project which resulted in one publication and one manuscript under revision. &nbsp;The many broader impacts of this award include involvement, research training, and professional development of 10 students including 2 IISER-K graduate students and 2 high school summer research students. &nbsp;Among the six undergraduate student researchers, the student whose travel to IISER-K to get research training from the Indian research team is currently pursuing Masters degree in polymer science, demonstrating the significant influence of this award. &nbsp;This award resulted in three conference presentations (oral and poster) for the PI, and one national society meeting and three campus research colloquium presentations for the student researchers. &nbsp;In addition, two undergraduate thesis work has already resulted from this award with two more on the way. &nbsp;Yet another tangible outcome is the PI has since the award was asked to serve on graduate (Ph.D.) thesis committee of two graduate students in India.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 11/13/2016<br>      Modified by: Latha&nbsp;Ramakrishnan</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ This award initiated new international research collaboration between researchers at St. Cloud State University and Indian Institute of Science Education and Research- Kolkata (IISER-K) in India.  The intellectual merits of this research collaboration is promising preliminary results demonstrating the delivery of SiRNA into cells using the cationic polymeric nanoparticles synthesized by researchers at IISER-K.  This award also brought tangible results in terms of additional collaboration on a different research project which resulted in one publication and one manuscript under revision.  The many broader impacts of this award include involvement, research training, and professional development of 10 students including 2 IISER-K graduate students and 2 high school summer research students.  Among the six undergraduate student researchers, the student whose travel to IISER-K to get research training from the Indian research team is currently pursuing Masters degree in polymer science, demonstrating the significant influence of this award.  This award resulted in three conference presentations (oral and poster) for the PI, and one national society meeting and three campus research colloquium presentations for the student researchers.  In addition, two undergraduate thesis work has already resulted from this award with two more on the way.  Yet another tangible outcome is the PI has since the award was asked to serve on graduate (Ph.D.) thesis committee of two graduate students in India.       Last Modified: 11/13/2016       Submitted by: Latha Ramakrishnan]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
