<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>WORKSHOP: Appellate Court Decisions and Potential Transformations in Public Policy</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2013</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2015</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>49831.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>49831</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>04050000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>SBE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>SES</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Divn Of Social and Economic Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Jonathan Gould</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This workshop will contribute to analysis of how appellate court decisions contribute to changes in public policy.  Most research concerning that issue has noted that courts are most likely to change public policy when they have other groups and powerful institutions allied with them.  This project will bring multiple scholars together to consider state-level change, and allow an evaluation of how such change is implemented in a major complex policy field with multiple organizations that would resist change.  It will be important to track how organizations mobilize for change, and how they respond to its potential, and whether and how politically powerful organizations mobilize for implementation.  Furthermore, it will allow evaluation of policy change via the courts and potential diffusion across states. The project will link with literature in criminology as well as literature on courts and social change; in state courts, the most relevant literature has concerned school finance reform, making the project potentially broadly important in multiple subfields.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The project will contribute to the training of scholars in law and social sciences.  It will also inform policymakers concerning court decisions and public policy.  The project will draw together scholars closely connected to public policymakers and scholars, therefore making the realization of potential broader impacts highly likely.  The policy issue is extremely important to multiple states, so the policy impact is likely to be broad.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/20/2013</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/20/2013</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.075</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1322228</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Carroll</FirstName>
<LastName>Seron</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Carroll Seron</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>seron@uci.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>9498246279</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000472559</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/20/2013</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>John</FirstName>
<LastName>Hipp</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>John Hipp</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>hippj@uci.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>9498248247</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000500481</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/20/2013</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Charis</FirstName>
<LastName>Kubrin</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Charis Kubrin</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>ckubrin@uci.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>9498240704</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000632528</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/20/2013</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Susan</FirstName>
<LastName>Turner</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Susan Turner</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>sfturner@uci.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>9498244768</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000638803</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/20/2013</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of California-Irvine</Name>
<CityName>Irvine</CityName>
<ZipCode>926977600</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>9498247295</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>160 Aldrich Hall</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>45</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CA45</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>046705849</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF CALIFORNIA, IRVINE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>071549000</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of California-Irvine]]></Name>
<CityName>Irvine</CityName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>926977080</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[3379 SE II]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>45</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CA45</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1372</Code>
<Text>LSS-Law And Social Sciences</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>0000</Code>
<Text>UNASSIGNED</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>OTHR</Code>
<Text>OTHER RESEARCH OR EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0113</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2013~49831</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>On July 14, 2015 President Obama became the first sitting president in American history to step inside a federal prison when he paid a visit to the Federal Correctional Facility El Reno about thirty miles from Oklahoma City. His political agenda in making this unusual visit was to bring attention to a growing bipartisan support for sweeping reform of the entire criminal justice system.&nbsp; In staking his position on the long overdue need to reform our criminal justice system, President Obama reminded us that the U.S. has less than five percent of the world&rsquo;s population yet nearly 25 percent of the world&rsquo;s incarcerated population.&nbsp;</p> <p>In 2011, the Supreme Court had also weighed in on U.S. policies around mass incarceration when the Court held in <em>Brown v. Plata</em> that overcrowding in California&rsquo;s prisons resulted in cruel and unusual punishment in violation of the Constitution&rsquo;s Eighth Amendment. The Supreme Court&rsquo;s <em>Plata</em> decision required the California Department of Corrections and Rehabilitation to reduce the state prison population by approximately 33,000 people (to 137.5 percent of design capacity) over a two-year timeframe. In response, the state enacted a controversial new law in October of 2011: &ldquo;Public Safety Realignment&rdquo; (Assembly Bill [AB] 109). Realignment is designed to comply with the <em>Plata </em>order by devolving from the state to each of its 58 counties the responsibility for supervising a sizeable class of offenders.&nbsp; Joan Petersilia, a leading scholar in the field of criminal justice, has described California&rsquo;s Realignment of prisons and jails as &ldquo;the biggest criminal justice experiment ever conducted in America&rdquo; but, she goes on to note, &ldquo;most people don't even realize it's happening.&rdquo;</p> <p>To begin to address this oversight, on October 17-18, 2014, with support from the National Science Foundation Charis Kubrin and Carroll Seron convened a workshop at the University of California, Irvine with the goal of bringing together the leading scholars who research prisons, mass incarceration and related policies. Four broad themes were addressed:</p> <ol> <li><strong>The origins of the crisis:</strong> The legal mandates spawned by the U.S. Supreme Court&rsquo;s ruling in <em>Brown v. Plata</em> and the state&rsquo;s response to the ruling via Realignment<em> </em>are products of over 20 years of controversy and litigation involving government actors, special interest groups, public interest or &ldquo;cause&rdquo; lawyers and advocacy groups. </li> <li><strong>&nbsp;</strong><strong>The diffusion and translation of law and policy reform: </strong>The effects of the <em>Plata</em> case and Realignment, including the ways in which the Court&rsquo;s order is diffusing itself throughout California as well as the multiple forces that are mediating its diffusion, are key to understanding the implications of this experiment in criminal justice reform. Among the key issues to understand is how the 58 counties across the state, each with very different histories, politics and demographic profiles, take steps in response to new regulatory and statutory guidelines around incarceration.&nbsp; These findings are key to understanding California&rsquo;s response but given the state&rsquo;s place in the national debate over criminal justice reform, these developments are being closely watched by policy makers throughout the country.</li> <li><strong>The impact of prison downsizing on the criminal justice system</strong>: &nbsp;Of keen interest to policymakers and the public is whether Realignment has caused crime to increase or decrease, including whether those implicated by the law will reoffend at higher or lower rates.</li> <li><strong>The future of decarceration:</strong> &nbsp;The ultimate aim is to leverage knowledge gained about developments in California t...]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ On July 14, 2015 President Obama became the first sitting president in American history to step inside a federal prison when he paid a visit to the Federal Correctional Facility El Reno about thirty miles from Oklahoma City. His political agenda in making this unusual visit was to bring attention to a growing bipartisan support for sweeping reform of the entire criminal justice system.  In staking his position on the long overdue need to reform our criminal justice system, President Obama reminded us that the U.S. has less than five percent of the worldÆs population yet nearly 25 percent of the worldÆs incarcerated population.   In 2011, the Supreme Court had also weighed in on U.S. policies around mass incarceration when the Court held in Brown v. Plata that overcrowding in CaliforniaÆs prisons resulted in cruel and unusual punishment in violation of the ConstitutionÆs Eighth Amendment. The Supreme CourtÆs Plata decision required the California Department of Corrections and Rehabilitation to reduce the state prison population by approximately 33,000 people (to 137.5 percent of design capacity) over a two-year timeframe. In response, the state enacted a controversial new law in October of 2011: "Public Safety Realignment" (Assembly Bill [AB] 109). Realignment is designed to comply with the Plata order by devolving from the state to each of its 58 counties the responsibility for supervising a sizeable class of offenders.  Joan Petersilia, a leading scholar in the field of criminal justice, has described CaliforniaÆs Realignment of prisons and jails as "the biggest criminal justice experiment ever conducted in America" but, she goes on to note, "most people don't even realize it's happening."  To begin to address this oversight, on October 17-18, 2014, with support from the National Science Foundation Charis Kubrin and Carroll Seron convened a workshop at the University of California, Irvine with the goal of bringing together the leading scholars who research prisons, mass incarceration and related policies. Four broad themes were addressed:  The origins of the crisis: The legal mandates spawned by the U.S. Supreme CourtÆs ruling in Brown v. Plata and the stateÆs response to the ruling via Realignment are products of over 20 years of controversy and litigation involving government actors, special interest groups, public interest or "cause" lawyers and advocacy groups.   The diffusion and translation of law and policy reform: The effects of the Plata case and Realignment, including the ways in which the CourtÆs order is diffusing itself throughout California as well as the multiple forces that are mediating its diffusion, are key to understanding the implications of this experiment in criminal justice reform. Among the key issues to understand is how the 58 counties across the state, each with very different histories, politics and demographic profiles, take steps in response to new regulatory and statutory guidelines around incarceration.  These findings are key to understanding CaliforniaÆs response but given the stateÆs place in the national debate over criminal justice reform, these developments are being closely watched by policy makers throughout the country. The impact of prison downsizing on the criminal justice system:  Of keen interest to policymakers and the public is whether Realignment has caused crime to increase or decrease, including whether those implicated by the law will reoffend at higher or lower rates. The future of decarceration:  The ultimate aim is to leverage knowledge gained about developments in California to advance theory and method concerning the broader questions of the possibility for prison downsizing as well as their effects on crime and public safety.   In the first social scientific analysis on the complexities of prison downsizing, the leading scholars in the field lend their expertise to explore these themes in the March 2016 issue of The Annals of American Political and Social Science.    ...]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
