<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>RAPID: Communication and Understanding of Hurricane Sandy Storm Surge Forecast and Warning Information</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>03/01/2013</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>02/28/2015</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>49273.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>49273</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CMMI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Civil, Mechanical, &amp; Manufact Inn</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Dennis Wenger</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This Rapid Response Research Grant (RAPID) provides funding to put a team of experienced researchers in the field to collect important time-sensitive data related to Tropical Storm/Hurricane/Superstorm Sandy.  The severe aftermath of this storm put new urgency on the need for better understanding of and improvement in forecast and warning communication.  The accurate forecast from the National Hurricane Center provided sufficient warning time for people to take action. For many, however, realization of the need to act came too late.  This storm transitioned from tropical storm to hurricane to extratropical (ET) storm as it approached landfall in the New York City area. That transition resulted in operational changes in responsibilities within the National Weather Service (NWS) along with possible changes in how media and emergency management interpreted the storm's hazards. During the Friday to Sunday time before Monday landfall, when critical decisions had to be made, Sandy was barely a Category 1 hurricane, possibly leading people to think it would not have a dangerous storm surge.  Its major impact was on an area not highly accustomed to planning for major hurricanes and having experienced one, Irene, with very different characteristics the year before.  These factors may have contributed to response delay, but research is needed to find out what actually happened in the forecast communication process and make recommendations for improvement.   &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Results gathered will contribute to investigating ways for improving storm forecast communication to promote public safety and reduce hurricane costs.  At least 125 people died (mostly from storm surge), and estimates indicate Sandy is likely to become one of the most costly weather events on record. Thousands of businesses, homes, and families were destroyed, many never to recover.  If the increasing ability of the National Hurricane Center to make accurate storm surge forecasts is to translate into saving lives and lessening the damage and need for recovery so costly to government,  the forecast communication and government response process must be improved.  This need is the rationale to this project's gathering of time-sensitive information and its analysis.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>02/12/2013</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>02/12/2013</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1322088</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Hugh</FirstName>
<LastName>Gladwin</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Hugh Gladwin</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>gladwin@fiu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>3056089961</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000236568</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>02/12/2013</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Betty</FirstName>
<LastName>Morrow</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>H</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Betty H Morrow</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>betty@bmorrow.com</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>3053855953</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000567962</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>02/12/2013</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Florida International University</Name>
<CityName>Miami</CityName>
<ZipCode>331990001</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>3053482494</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>11200 SW 8TH ST</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[MARC 430]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Florida</StateName>
<StateCode>FL</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>26</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>FL26</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>071298814</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>FLORIDA INTERNATIONAL UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>159621697</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Florida International University]]></Name>
<CityName>Miami</CityName>
<StateCode>FL</StateCode>
<ZipCode>331990001</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[11200 S.W. 8 Street]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Florida</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>26</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>FL26</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1385</Code>
<Text>SSA-Special Studies &amp; Analysis</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>036E</Code>
<Text>CIVIL INFRASTRUCTURE</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>041E</Code>
<Text>HAZARD AND DISASTER REDUCTION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>042E</Code>
<Text>HAZARD AND DISASTER RESPONSE</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7914</Code>
<Text>RAPID</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8293</Code>
<Text>Hurricane Sandy</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0113</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2013~49273</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Superstorm Sandy or Hurricane Sandy (hereafter Sandy) caused many casualties and widespread damage.&nbsp; The National Science Foundation funded this project to gather data quickly on people's Sandy experience before memories faded or changed.&nbsp; The project had three goals:</p> <ol> <li>Understand what information people saw and heard about Sandy as it approached and affected their evacuation decision-making.</li> <li>Determine whether the multiple agencies and entities having different forecast and risk communication responsibilities contributed to confusion in public response.</li> <li>Make recommendations about how to improve hurricane forecast communication and response.</li> </ol> <p>Research began two months after Sandy with interviews of forecasters, media, and emergency management officials to understand communication of forecast information and emergency management decisions during the days before Sandy's landfall. Researchers then designed a telephone survey of households in Sandy evacuation areas covering information people received prior to landfall, what they expected in terms of potential impacts, and whether they found out if they needed to evacuate. The survey randomly selected for interview 1000 households from high storm surge neighborhoods in coastal New Jersey and New York. Of households reached and asked to do the survey, 79% completed it.&nbsp; Thirty-two percent of survey respondents evacuated for Sandy.</p> <p>Analysis of survey data focused on understanding why interviews did or did not evacuate.&nbsp; Following are the only factors that proved important predictors of evacuation:</p> <ol> <li>Evacuation orders mattered most: people who knew they were ordered or recommended to evacuate were much more likely to evacuate.</li> <li>Risk location mattered: though all areas surveyed were at risk, people living in the lowest elevation areas nearest to the coast were more likely to evacuate</li> <li>Awareness of storm surge risk mattered: people more likely to evacuate had a higher prior perception of surge risk.</li> <li>Jurisdiction mattered: New Jersey residents were somewhat more likely to evacuate than New York residents.</li> <li>Higher income households were somewhat less likely to evacuate: a possible consequence of the demographics of a sample limited to areas along the coastline.</li> </ol> <p>As noted people already aware of surge risk were more ready to heed evacuation orders when notified but many were not aware of evacuation orders or recommendations for their area.&nbsp; Interviews with emergency managers indicated many political authorities did not want to plan evacuations until they knew where high storm surge would occur.&nbsp; However, predicting location of surge risk with any confidence ahead of the watch/warning period (in Sandy&rsquo;s case Saturday morning about 54 hours before landfall) is impossible because location and height of storm surge level is so dependent on the track, size, and strength of the hurricane before landfall. Sixty-four percent of interviewees had become concerned about Sandy by Saturday, but many did not translate that into understanding the need to evacuate.&nbsp; Study evidence indicates both risk and evacuation order needed effective communication given the area&rsquo;s relative lack of hurricane experience.&nbsp; Prior to Saturday the public was not alerted to the possibility of evacuation from risk areas. By Saturday little clear information came from authorities on when and for whom evacuation might be ordered.&nbsp; The lack might have arisen from the effect of multiple governmental agencies involved in translating the forecast into evacuation orders and the consequent timing of public response.</p> <p>The study also looked at whether changing the classification of Sandy from hurricane to extra-tropical cyclone had an effect on people's evacuation decision.&nbsp; From the perspective of inte...]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Superstorm Sandy or Hurricane Sandy (hereafter Sandy) caused many casualties and widespread damage.  The National Science Foundation funded this project to gather data quickly on people's Sandy experience before memories faded or changed.  The project had three goals:  Understand what information people saw and heard about Sandy as it approached and affected their evacuation decision-making. Determine whether the multiple agencies and entities having different forecast and risk communication responsibilities contributed to confusion in public response. Make recommendations about how to improve hurricane forecast communication and response.   Research began two months after Sandy with interviews of forecasters, media, and emergency management officials to understand communication of forecast information and emergency management decisions during the days before Sandy's landfall. Researchers then designed a telephone survey of households in Sandy evacuation areas covering information people received prior to landfall, what they expected in terms of potential impacts, and whether they found out if they needed to evacuate. The survey randomly selected for interview 1000 households from high storm surge neighborhoods in coastal New Jersey and New York. Of households reached and asked to do the survey, 79% completed it.  Thirty-two percent of survey respondents evacuated for Sandy.  Analysis of survey data focused on understanding why interviews did or did not evacuate.  Following are the only factors that proved important predictors of evacuation:  Evacuation orders mattered most: people who knew they were ordered or recommended to evacuate were much more likely to evacuate. Risk location mattered: though all areas surveyed were at risk, people living in the lowest elevation areas nearest to the coast were more likely to evacuate Awareness of storm surge risk mattered: people more likely to evacuate had a higher prior perception of surge risk. Jurisdiction mattered: New Jersey residents were somewhat more likely to evacuate than New York residents. Higher income households were somewhat less likely to evacuate: a possible consequence of the demographics of a sample limited to areas along the coastline.   As noted people already aware of surge risk were more ready to heed evacuation orders when notified but many were not aware of evacuation orders or recommendations for their area.  Interviews with emergency managers indicated many political authorities did not want to plan evacuations until they knew where high storm surge would occur.  However, predicting location of surge risk with any confidence ahead of the watch/warning period (in SandyÆs case Saturday morning about 54 hours before landfall) is impossible because location and height of storm surge level is so dependent on the track, size, and strength of the hurricane before landfall. Sixty-four percent of interviewees had become concerned about Sandy by Saturday, but many did not translate that into understanding the need to evacuate.  Study evidence indicates both risk and evacuation order needed effective communication given the areaÆs relative lack of hurricane experience.  Prior to Saturday the public was not alerted to the possibility of evacuation from risk areas. By Saturday little clear information came from authorities on when and for whom evacuation might be ordered.  The lack might have arisen from the effect of multiple governmental agencies involved in translating the forecast into evacuation orders and the consequent timing of public response.  The study also looked at whether changing the classification of Sandy from hurricane to extra-tropical cyclone had an effect on people's evacuation decision.  From the perspective of interviewees (both qualitative interviews and telephone survey) the designation did not matter. The National Hurricane Center was accepted as the definitive source of forecast information through the entire period, and technical changes in ju...]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
