<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Light Element Incorporation in Nominally Anhydrous Minerals</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>01/01/2014</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>343154.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>343154</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>06030107</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>GEO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>EAR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Earth Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Sonia Esperanca</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Water is essential not only to life, but also to geological processes such as volcanic eruption, magma melting and rising, and rock deformation.  In the geological world, a major reservoir of water is tied up in solid rock deep in the Earth where it is chemically bound to the minerals. In these minerals, water is present both as the H2O molecule, and also as its precursor, the hydrogen atom bound to oxygen atoms in the form of hydroxide groups. Although the concentrations are relatively low, usually less than a few hundred parts per million, the volume of this rock is great. A large proportion of this water is incorporated into minerals we normally think of as anhydrous. These nominally anhydrous minerals include feldspars, quartz, olivine, garnets, and pyroxenes. For a couple decades, the Caltech lab has developed the first generation of analytical standards for determining the 'water' content of nominally anhydrous minerals using a variety of analytical tools. These standards have seen wide distribution across the United States and abroad. The standards were originally developed for use with infrared spectroscopy, but now, another analytical technique known as secondary ion mass spectrometry offers comparable or better sensitivity on smaller areas. The new method is not self-calibrating and has relied, in part, on the standards previously developed for infrared spectroscopy.  In some ways, the first generation of standards is proving less than optimal in view of the improved spatial sensitivity offered by the new methods. The proposed study will re-evaluate existing standards and develop new, second generation ones to optimize the new-found analytical capabilities. Part of this work will involve an extensive characterization of feldspars, one of the few major rock-forming minerals that still need to be investigated using the mass spectrometry methods. This effort is particularly topical due to interest from the community in measuring H in feldspars from both terrestrial and extraterrestrial samples. It will also study fluorine ion incorporation in minerals with the goal of improving calibration protocols while systematically studying samples derived from the Earth's mantle were indications of a coupling between hydrogen and fluorine have been previously suggested. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;These studies are critical to the ultimate fundamental question of where the important volatile components such as water reside in the earth and how they influence the properties of rocks and minerals. They address the questions of which phases contain trace 'water' and at what concentrations. They also contribute to understanding the spatial distribution of these volatiles throughout our planet. The analytical standards are also used to address questions about the existence of critical volatiles elsewhere in the solar system such as the moon. The presence or absence of small amounts of 'water' in nominally anhydrous synthetic minerals and related synthetic solids of technological importance plays an important role in operational success of devices such as supports for high power electronic circuits, electro-optic crystals used in data communication and fiber optics, and timing circuits used in computers, watches and telecommunication devices. This research will broaden the communities understanding of the important role that trace amounts of hydrogen and fluorine play in such minerals and materials, and will benefit the international community through the development of new standards and assessment of calibration protocols for these elements. This work also provides opportunities for direct participation in the research process by students training to be professional scientists and engineers.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>01/02/2014</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>12/10/2018</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.050</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1322082</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>George</FirstName>
<LastName>Rossman</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>R</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>George R Rossman</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>grr@gps.caltech.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6263956471</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000340784</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>01/02/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>California Institute of Technology</Name>
<CityName>PASADENA</CityName>
<ZipCode>911250600</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6263956219</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1200 E California Blvd</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[Mail Code 273-6]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>27</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CA27</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>009584210</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>CALIFORNIA INSTITUTE OF TECHNOLOGY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>009584210</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[California Institute of Technology]]></Name>
<CityName>Pasadena</CityName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>911252500</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[1200 E. California Blvd]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>27</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CA27</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1573</Code>
<Text>Petrology and Geochemistry</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0114</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0115</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0116</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~113923</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2015~114498</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2016~114733</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; Small amounts of water bound in the structure of minerals can dramatically alter a variety of their physical properties such as melting point, cation diffusion, and radiation stability. While understating the role of water is minerals is highly important, accurate analysis of the amount of water in these minerals has proven challenging. In the current project, we conducted an assessment of hydrous species in feldspars which are the major mineral group in the crust of planet earth. Our work concentrated on the analytical aspects of OH analysis with infrared spectroscopy and secondary ion mass spectrometry methods. Our analytical data by the two methods proved to be well-correlated and demonstrated the feasibility of quantitatively measuring H concentrations as low as 1 to 2 ppm by weight water in feldspars.</p> <p>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; Oxygen-bound hydrogen is the primary chemical way that hydrogen enters minerals and melts, but other ways are possible. We also examined hydrogen bound to nitrogen species in geomaterials and found that N-H compounds are the main species in which nitrogen is present under reducing conditions in glasses quenched from melts.</p> <p>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; A major collaboration with Charles Geiger, Salzburg, Austria, was begun that is directed at trying to understand at an atomic level, the mechanism through which OH enters garnet and often replaces silicate groups in the garnet structure. Calcium rich garnets can have some to nearly all of their silicate groups replaced by four OH groups in what is well-known as the hydrogarnet substitution. But we also find smaller amounts of silicate replacement in garnets that are dominantly magnesium, iron or manganese in their compositions. Using our extensive library of infrared spectra of OH in garnets of diverse compositions, we were able to identify a number of nano-sized clusters containing variable amounts of locally bound hydrogarnet units in otherwise silicate dominated calcium-rich grossular garnets. These observations were extended to iron and titanium-rich garnets in the andradite and schorlomite series where the infrared spectroscopy indicated the presence of similar clusters of grossular-related hydrogarnet imbedded in the iron and titanium garnets.</p> <p>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; In addition, we used our analytical methods to collaborate with workers as the Natural History Museum of Los Angeles and other institutions involved with the discovery and characterization of new mineral phases. Many of the new phases involve the element tellurium and present new types of atomic structural arrangements. Also characterized were new phases in meteorites. One of these was bridgmanite, the mineral believed to be the most abundant mineral in earth, but believed to exist only at great depths in our planet. Another was the discovery of a high pressure form of ice known as ice-VII confined in minute inclusions in diamonds. A novel discovery was the characterization of both a new mineral species and also the rarest gemstone, kyawthuite, for which only a single example is known in the form of a faceted gem. &nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 01/30/2020<br>      Modified by: George&nbsp;R&nbsp;Rossman</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[             Small amounts of water bound in the structure of minerals can dramatically alter a variety of their physical properties such as melting point, cation diffusion, and radiation stability. While understating the role of water is minerals is highly important, accurate analysis of the amount of water in these minerals has proven challenging. In the current project, we conducted an assessment of hydrous species in feldspars which are the major mineral group in the crust of planet earth. Our work concentrated on the analytical aspects of OH analysis with infrared spectroscopy and secondary ion mass spectrometry methods. Our analytical data by the two methods proved to be well-correlated and demonstrated the feasibility of quantitatively measuring H concentrations as low as 1 to 2 ppm by weight water in feldspars.              Oxygen-bound hydrogen is the primary chemical way that hydrogen enters minerals and melts, but other ways are possible. We also examined hydrogen bound to nitrogen species in geomaterials and found that N-H compounds are the main species in which nitrogen is present under reducing conditions in glasses quenched from melts.              A major collaboration with Charles Geiger, Salzburg, Austria, was begun that is directed at trying to understand at an atomic level, the mechanism through which OH enters garnet and often replaces silicate groups in the garnet structure. Calcium rich garnets can have some to nearly all of their silicate groups replaced by four OH groups in what is well-known as the hydrogarnet substitution. But we also find smaller amounts of silicate replacement in garnets that are dominantly magnesium, iron or manganese in their compositions. Using our extensive library of infrared spectra of OH in garnets of diverse compositions, we were able to identify a number of nano-sized clusters containing variable amounts of locally bound hydrogarnet units in otherwise silicate dominated calcium-rich grossular garnets. These observations were extended to iron and titanium-rich garnets in the andradite and schorlomite series where the infrared spectroscopy indicated the presence of similar clusters of grossular-related hydrogarnet imbedded in the iron and titanium garnets.              In addition, we used our analytical methods to collaborate with workers as the Natural History Museum of Los Angeles and other institutions involved with the discovery and characterization of new mineral phases. Many of the new phases involve the element tellurium and present new types of atomic structural arrangements. Also characterized were new phases in meteorites. One of these was bridgmanite, the mineral believed to be the most abundant mineral in earth, but believed to exist only at great depths in our planet. Another was the discovery of a high pressure form of ice known as ice-VII confined in minute inclusions in diamonds. A novel discovery was the characterization of both a new mineral species and also the rarest gemstone, kyawthuite, for which only a single example is known in the form of a faceted gem.         Last Modified: 01/30/2020       Submitted by: George R Rossman]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
