<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Collaborative Research:  Implementation and Evaluation of a Sustainable Computer-Based Tutoring System for Introductory Linear Circuit Analysis</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/15/2013</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>75000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>75000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>11040200</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>EHR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DUE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Undergraduate Education</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Abby Ilumoka</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>ailumoka@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922703</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>PARTICIPATING INSTITUTIONS: &lt;br/&gt;Arizona State University (ASU - Lead)&lt;br/&gt;University of Virginia (UVA)&lt;br/&gt;University of Notre Dame (ND)&lt;br/&gt;University of the Pacific (UOP)&lt;br/&gt;Colorado State University (CSU)&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;PROJECT DESCRIPTION &lt;br/&gt;This project is developing and evaluating a computer-aided tutoring system to support the teaching of elementary linear circuit analysis. It is expanding a prototype system to cover topics in a traditional two-semester linear circuits course. The system can generate circuit problems with random topologies and element values for DC, steady-state AC, and transient circuits; allowing students to study concepts related to Fourier analysis, Laplace transforms, Bode plots, and three-phase circuits. Problem solutions are produced using a variety of special pedagogical features, including exercises designed to correct common student misconceptions. The system accepts a rich variety of inputs such as equations, re-drawn circuit diagrams, waveform sketches, matrix equations, as well as conventional numerical and multiple-choice answers. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The web-based system is being employed and evaluated in a variety of ways in linear circuit classes at ASU, UVA, ND, and UOP. Dr. Daniel Robinson (at CSU) is conducting rigorous evaluation and analysis of the resulting qualitative and quantitative student learning data collected at these institutions. Through testing the software system in a variety of public and private schools, the team is demonstrating that the system can provide rapid feedback to instructors and enhance student learning - in areas that students have the most difficulty.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;BROADER SIGNIFICANCE &lt;br/&gt;The project is directly impacting more than 4300 students and having a significant effect on engineering education, since many engineering students in various disciplines take circuits courses. It is also expected that the system will be highly suitable for incorporation into massive open on-line courses (MOOCs) addressing this subject area. Student engagement is being increased through the use of interactive exercises that provide rapid feedback to students at each step of a problem. The team is also developing a tutorial authoring interface and execution engine that allows tutorial writers (e.g., instructors) to design more effective tutoring sequences by using the features of the circuit generation and solution modules. The approach is adaptable to other subject areas in electrical engineering, as well as other engineering disciplines. Some of the simpler tutorials and modules on basic circuit properties are being made available to high school students and the general public via a website designed for that purpose.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>09/13/2013</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>01/23/2015</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.076</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1323396</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Archie</FirstName>
<LastName>Holmes</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>L</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME>Jr.</PI_SUFX_NAME>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Archie L Holmes</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>archieholmes@virginia.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>4349247770</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000380660</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/13/2013</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Virginia Main Campus</Name>
<CityName>CHARLOTTESVILLE</CityName>
<ZipCode>229044195</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>4349244270</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>P.O.  BOX 400195</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Virginia</StateName>
<StateCode>VA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>VA05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>065391526</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>RECTOR &amp; VISITORS OF THE UNIVERSITY OF VIRGINIA</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>065391526</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Virginia]]></Name>
<CityName>Charlottesville</CityName>
<StateCode>VA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>229044195</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[P. O. Box 400195]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Virginia</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>VA05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7511</Code>
<Text>TUES-Type 2 Project</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9178</Code>
<Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>SMET</Code>
<Text>SCIENCE, MATH, ENG &amp; TECH EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0413</Code>
<Name>NSF Education &amp; Human Resource</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040106</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2013~75000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Many of the complex problems that society faces will require engineers who can recall prior technical knowledge, acquire new technical knowledge and skills, and apply this knowledge in novel, non-routine ways.&nbsp; This type of problem solving places a large cognitive demand on engineers.&nbsp; One of the important goals of engineering education is to prepare engineers to work in this dynamic and demanding environment. The hypothesis driving this program is that the fundamental understanding of core engineering concepts subjects is a critical issue for educating future engineers.&nbsp;&nbsp; The ability to understand and apply these core concepts provides engineers a deeper understanding of current technology and innovations.&nbsp; It also provides a platform on which they can solve current problems and develop the knowledge and technology needed to address tomorrow&rsquo;s challenges.&nbsp; As a result, educational activities which lead to students correctly applying core concepts in problem solving activities will ultimately be the most successful.</p> <p>The mechanism that has been developed under previous work at Arizona State University (ASU) was to create a step-based computer-aided tutoring system (known as Circuit Tutor) to enhance student learning via the use of interactive exercises which provide rapid feedback to students at each step of a problem, as opposed to most existing answer-based systems that provide little help in identifying the source of errors. &nbsp;Circuit Tutor accomplishes this by both creating and solving its own circuit problems on the fly using a sophisticated three-step algorithm. As a result,&nbsp; each student has access to an unlimited source of fully worked and explained examples at various levels of gradually increasing difficulty, as well as exercises designed to be completely isomorphic to those examples, but completely different both in circuit topology and element values.&nbsp; The initial results showed that students preferred this method of learning elementary linear circuit analysis compared to other methods (e.g., traditional homework and other commercial system) and there is initial evidence of improved student learning.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>In this project the goal was to expand, disseminate, and evaluate Circuit Tutor at a variety of higher education institutions (University of Notre Dame, University of the Pacific, and Morgan State University). Important outcomes of this work included:</p> <p><span style="text-decoration: underline;">&nbsp;</span></p> <ul> <li>a randomly assigned study where a statistically significant (<em>p</em> &lt; 0.05) effect size (Cohen <em>d</em>-value) of 1.21 standard deviations (<em>&sigma;</em>) was measured for Circuit Tutor compared to paper homework (average scores increasing from 58 to 86% for Circuit Tutor but only from 59 to 62% for paper exercises)</li> </ul> <ul> <li>a randomly assigned study comparing Circuit Tutor to publisher-based homework system (WileyPLUS), where, for a combination of nodal and mesh analysis problems, Circuit Tutor outperformed WileyPLUS [average of 40.2/50 (<em>&sigma;</em> = 16.2) compared to 33.6/50 (<em>&sigma;</em> = 15.9)]. This difference was statistically significant (<em>p</em> &lt; 0.008) with an effect size of <em>d</em> = 0.41 <em>&sigma;</em>.</li> </ul> <ul> <li>In another study comparing Circuit Tutor to WileyPLUS, survey results showed that 86% preferred Circuit Tutor, 9% preferred WileyPLUS, and 6% liked both equally.&nbsp; Further, 94% felt that Circuit Tutor more effectively taught them the topic for which they used it, 3% felt that WileyPLUS was more effective, and 6% were neutral.&nbsp;</li> </ul> <p>Overall Student satisfaction (over 3350 students in 82 class sections taught by 38 different instructors at 10 different colleges) showed that students viewed the tutorials provided in Circuit Tutor between 92-96% favorable (i.e., very useful or somewhat useful), with 65-74% rating them very useful &ldquo;very useful.&rdquo;&nbsp; Breaking this data down by institution showed consistent responses in every case, with 92% favorable at ASU, 94% at Notre Dame, 95% at University of the Pacific, 97% at Morgan State University, and 95% at Messiah College (with at least ~150 responses for each institution).</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 11/30/2017<br>      Modified by: Archie&nbsp;L&nbsp;Holmes</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Many of the complex problems that society faces will require engineers who can recall prior technical knowledge, acquire new technical knowledge and skills, and apply this knowledge in novel, non-routine ways.  This type of problem solving places a large cognitive demand on engineers.  One of the important goals of engineering education is to prepare engineers to work in this dynamic and demanding environment. The hypothesis driving this program is that the fundamental understanding of core engineering concepts subjects is a critical issue for educating future engineers.   The ability to understand and apply these core concepts provides engineers a deeper understanding of current technology and innovations.  It also provides a platform on which they can solve current problems and develop the knowledge and technology needed to address tomorrow?s challenges.  As a result, educational activities which lead to students correctly applying core concepts in problem solving activities will ultimately be the most successful.  The mechanism that has been developed under previous work at Arizona State University (ASU) was to create a step-based computer-aided tutoring system (known as Circuit Tutor) to enhance student learning via the use of interactive exercises which provide rapid feedback to students at each step of a problem, as opposed to most existing answer-based systems that provide little help in identifying the source of errors.  Circuit Tutor accomplishes this by both creating and solving its own circuit problems on the fly using a sophisticated three-step algorithm. As a result,  each student has access to an unlimited source of fully worked and explained examples at various levels of gradually increasing difficulty, as well as exercises designed to be completely isomorphic to those examples, but completely different both in circuit topology and element values.  The initial results showed that students preferred this method of learning elementary linear circuit analysis compared to other methods (e.g., traditional homework and other commercial system) and there is initial evidence of improved student learning.     In this project the goal was to expand, disseminate, and evaluate Circuit Tutor at a variety of higher education institutions (University of Notre Dame, University of the Pacific, and Morgan State University). Important outcomes of this work included:     a randomly assigned study where a statistically significant (p &lt; 0.05) effect size (Cohen d-value) of 1.21 standard deviations (&sigma;) was measured for Circuit Tutor compared to paper homework (average scores increasing from 58 to 86% for Circuit Tutor but only from 59 to 62% for paper exercises)   a randomly assigned study comparing Circuit Tutor to publisher-based homework system (WileyPLUS), where, for a combination of nodal and mesh analysis problems, Circuit Tutor outperformed WileyPLUS [average of 40.2/50 (&sigma; = 16.2) compared to 33.6/50 (&sigma; = 15.9)]. This difference was statistically significant (p &lt; 0.008) with an effect size of d = 0.41 &sigma;.   In another study comparing Circuit Tutor to WileyPLUS, survey results showed that 86% preferred Circuit Tutor, 9% preferred WileyPLUS, and 6% liked both equally.  Further, 94% felt that Circuit Tutor more effectively taught them the topic for which they used it, 3% felt that WileyPLUS was more effective, and 6% were neutral.    Overall Student satisfaction (over 3350 students in 82 class sections taught by 38 different instructors at 10 different colleges) showed that students viewed the tutorials provided in Circuit Tutor between 92-96% favorable (i.e., very useful or somewhat useful), with 65-74% rating them very useful "very useful."  Breaking this data down by institution showed consistent responses in every case, with 92% favorable at ASU, 94% at Notre Dame, 95% at University of the Pacific, 97% at Morgan State University, and 95% at Messiah College (with at least ~150 responses for each institution).       Last Modified: 11/30/2017       Submitted by: Archie L Holmes]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
