<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>An Online Center for African Linguistics Research: Expansion of the Afranaph Project</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2013</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>480842.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>557122</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>04040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>SBE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>BCS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Behavioral and Cognitive Sci</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Joan Maling</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>jmaling@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032928046</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Perhaps the single most pressing question in theoretical linguistics is the following: Are the new patterns in grammar that we discover challenges to the view that fundamental principles of mental organization in humans are specifically linguistic, or do languages and the grammars that underlie them arise strictly as function of the purpose they serve? The Afranaph Project addresses this question by expanding our understanding of African languages. The project uses internet access and the expertise of native speakers of African languages who have been trained as linguists in order to elicit rich and specialized data from many understudied languages of Africa, some of them endangered. The principal goal of this project is the discovery, documentation, analysis and explanation of new empirical patterns of interest to linguistic theory and typology. New NSF support will permit the researchers to develop and integrate a variety of research initiatives and insure that all data collection from the new projects envisioned enrich the effectiveness of the existing resources, which are the database and website, and permit the researchers to expand their coverage from the 25 languages to over 40 by the end of the new funding. The data, research tools, analyses and explanatory essays are freely available on the website http://www.africananaphora.rutgers.edu. Open access is fundamental to the project's second goal, which is to build an integrated research community around the resources by expanding the network of consultants and researchers. For each language in the project, there is at least one African native speaker linguist, mostly linguists early in their career, who, through Afranaph collaborations, become familiar with Western scholars and modern methodologies in formal linguistics. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The Afranaph Project formerly specialized in the study of anaphora, the linguistic devices that are used to refer back (such as pronouns and reflexives), but now the research expertise developed in anaphora studies will be applied to many new research domains, including  the meaning, morphology and syntax of tense and aspect, sentential embedding, noun classes, and agreement, and crosslinguistic study adds to the aggregate of information available for each language in the project.  The Afranaph project supports the scholarship and documentation of minority languages, some of them endangered. It enhances the training of junior scholars and the creation of new international partnerships.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/13/2013</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/24/2018</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.075</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1324404</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Kenneth</FirstName>
<LastName>Safir</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>J</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Kenneth J Safir</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>safir@linguistics.rutgers.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>7328286422</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000130489</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/13/2013</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Rutgers University New Brunswick</Name>
<CityName>Piscataway</CityName>
<ZipCode>088543925</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>8489320150</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>33 Knightsbridge Road</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[2nd Floor East Wing]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New Jersey</StateName>
<StateCode>NJ</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>06</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NJ06</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>001912864</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>RUTGERS, THE STATE UNIVERSITY OF NEW JERSEY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>001912864</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Rutgers University]]></Name>
<CityName>New Brunswick</CityName>
<StateCode>NJ</StateCode>
<ZipCode>089011184</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New Jersey</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>06</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NJ06</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1311</Code>
<Text>Linguistics</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1311</Code>
<Text>LINGUISTICS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9178</Code>
<Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9179</Code>
<Text>GRADUATE INVOLVEMENT</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>SMET</Code>
<Text>SCIENCE, MATH, ENG &amp; TECH EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0113</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0116</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2013~480842</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2016~76280</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Since no other species can learn to speak a human language, the language faculty that permits us to master the language of the community we are born into is an important part of what identifies us as human. Yet we know very little about most of the world&rsquo;s languages and are theories of what humans are capable of still depend on our understanding of the languages known to science. About one third of the world&rsquo;s 6500 or so languages are spoken in Africa and very few of them have received careful scientific study. The Afranaph Project, supported by NSF over 17 years, including four years of this grant, is designed to increase our understanding of the languages of Africa by using the talents and training of linguists who are native speakers of African languages. Afranaph researchers elicit rich and specialized data aimed at discovering empirical patterns in African languages that are relevant to research questions in theoretical linguistics, that is, the branch of linguistics that tries to determine what exactly the human language faculty consists of.</p> <p>During the grant period, the number of languages explored by our detailed elicitation techniques reached over fifty, providing novel information on a great variety of African languages, including some that are virtually unstudied and/or endangered. As the data we collect from our different subprojects is pooled, we enter it into a database we have designed that permits intralinguistic and cross-linguistic searches and comparisons, as well as specialized searches relevant to the specific interests of our researchers. It is also used as a model for field researchers and in linguistics pedagogy for research in comparative grammar. General use of our resources is possible because all of our data and our database can be accessed and searched by any interested party without permissions or password protection.</p> <p>Our database is dynamic, that is, it is constantly expanding its empirical reach and is continually adding new functions, often transforming some of our previous functions. For this reason, though it was not our original goal, the evolution of our database has also become an experiment in database design. That design has drawn the interest of other academic and hard science database designers and in that sense Afranaph may turn out to have an impact on research in unrelated fields. The PI has been invited to conferences in the US, Europe and Africa to explain the Afranaph Database design, including its specialized portals searching multiproject pooled data, its broad participation of researchers, and the live free access it permits.</p> <p>In addition to exploring African languages for theoretical goals, an important part of our mission is to build a community around a resource that nurtures and enables research and researchers interested in African languages. This internet-based community includes our native-speaker linguist consultants, theoretical and descriptive linguists (many of whom are also our consultants), students of linguistics and young scholars at various stages of building their careers. It also permits African linguists, many of them isolated from other linguists, to form relationships and collaborations with Western linguists to the benefit of both.</p> <p>However, we measure our success by the contributions to linguistic research that has grown from our efforts at Afranaph, and these include the results we report on our website, at conferences, and in publications in books and journals. Much of what we have discovered concerns abstract properties of very concrete linguistic facts, such as the way we refer back to entities mentioned earlier (e.g. with pronouns and other forms &ndash; known technically as &ldquo;anaphora&rdquo;). We have explored how clauses are held together and how the role players in events are distinguished by agreement marking. We have investigated how meanings are constructed by the relations between words in syntax and the relations of the subparts from which words are constructed (morphology). One sort of result is our confirmation that word-formation and syntax largely overlap, especially in Bantu and Atlantic branches of the Niger-Congo family. We have also discovered constructions and grammar relations that have not been attested before, such as actual clauses in Lubukusu and voice agreement with complementizers in Setswana and Ikalanga. These constructions appear to be obscure oddities, but turn out to be outward signs of deeper generalizations about human grammars. In our various publications, we explore the consequences of our research into African languages for big questions concerning what is universal in the human language faculty, on the one hand, and what has to be learned by exposure to the language of one&rsquo;s specific language community.</p> <p>The Afranaph Project is now a standard repository and research platform for those studying African languages and it is thanks to the support of NSF that this fundamental resource has come into being.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 07/15/2020<br>      Modified by: Kenneth&nbsp;J&nbsp;Safir</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Since no other species can learn to speak a human language, the language faculty that permits us to master the language of the community we are born into is an important part of what identifies us as human. Yet we know very little about most of the world’s languages and are theories of what humans are capable of still depend on our understanding of the languages known to science. About one third of the world’s 6500 or so languages are spoken in Africa and very few of them have received careful scientific study. The Afranaph Project, supported by NSF over 17 years, including four years of this grant, is designed to increase our understanding of the languages of Africa by using the talents and training of linguists who are native speakers of African languages. Afranaph researchers elicit rich and specialized data aimed at discovering empirical patterns in African languages that are relevant to research questions in theoretical linguistics, that is, the branch of linguistics that tries to determine what exactly the human language faculty consists of.  During the grant period, the number of languages explored by our detailed elicitation techniques reached over fifty, providing novel information on a great variety of African languages, including some that are virtually unstudied and/or endangered. As the data we collect from our different subprojects is pooled, we enter it into a database we have designed that permits intralinguistic and cross-linguistic searches and comparisons, as well as specialized searches relevant to the specific interests of our researchers. It is also used as a model for field researchers and in linguistics pedagogy for research in comparative grammar. General use of our resources is possible because all of our data and our database can be accessed and searched by any interested party without permissions or password protection.  Our database is dynamic, that is, it is constantly expanding its empirical reach and is continually adding new functions, often transforming some of our previous functions. For this reason, though it was not our original goal, the evolution of our database has also become an experiment in database design. That design has drawn the interest of other academic and hard science database designers and in that sense Afranaph may turn out to have an impact on research in unrelated fields. The PI has been invited to conferences in the US, Europe and Africa to explain the Afranaph Database design, including its specialized portals searching multiproject pooled data, its broad participation of researchers, and the live free access it permits.  In addition to exploring African languages for theoretical goals, an important part of our mission is to build a community around a resource that nurtures and enables research and researchers interested in African languages. This internet-based community includes our native-speaker linguist consultants, theoretical and descriptive linguists (many of whom are also our consultants), students of linguistics and young scholars at various stages of building their careers. It also permits African linguists, many of them isolated from other linguists, to form relationships and collaborations with Western linguists to the benefit of both.  However, we measure our success by the contributions to linguistic research that has grown from our efforts at Afranaph, and these include the results we report on our website, at conferences, and in publications in books and journals. Much of what we have discovered concerns abstract properties of very concrete linguistic facts, such as the way we refer back to entities mentioned earlier (e.g. with pronouns and other forms &ndash; known technically as "anaphora"). We have explored how clauses are held together and how the role players in events are distinguished by agreement marking. We have investigated how meanings are constructed by the relations between words in syntax and the relations of the subparts from which words are constructed (morphology). One sort of result is our confirmation that word-formation and syntax largely overlap, especially in Bantu and Atlantic branches of the Niger-Congo family. We have also discovered constructions and grammar relations that have not been attested before, such as actual clauses in Lubukusu and voice agreement with complementizers in Setswana and Ikalanga. These constructions appear to be obscure oddities, but turn out to be outward signs of deeper generalizations about human grammars. In our various publications, we explore the consequences of our research into African languages for big questions concerning what is universal in the human language faculty, on the one hand, and what has to be learned by exposure to the language of one’s specific language community.  The Afranaph Project is now a standard repository and research platform for those studying African languages and it is thanks to the support of NSF that this fundamental resource has come into being.          Last Modified: 07/15/2020       Submitted by: Kenneth J Safir]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
