<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>EAGER: Synthesis, Material Investigation and Device Effect Demonstration of Nano Diamond Wires</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2013</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2015</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>205839.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>213839</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07010000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>ECCS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Electrical, Commun &amp; Cyber Sys</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Dimitris Pavlidis</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The objective of this program is to begin the exploration of the feasibility, phase-transition conditions and growth mechanism of a new allotrope of carbon diamond nanowires.  Through this exploration, the team will try to establish an understanding of the basic science underlying and a synthetic process for reproducible growth of diamond nanowires.  The objective will be met through iterative cycles of synthesis, materials characterization, and device effect demonstration.  &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The intellectual merit of the proposed project is in proving the existence and feasibility of synthesizing a new form of carbon - diamond nanowires, in understanding their synthesis that apparently could take place so-far only at an extraordinarily low temperature and pressure, both of which being greatly lower than the corresponding conditions known as required for the diamond-graphite phase-transitions. Successful completion of this Early-Concept study could help door to further advances in the broad carbon-electronic revolution exemplified by C60, carbon nanotube, and graphene, only this time on the diamond (SP3-bond) side of the family. It could help enrich the classical phase-transition theory with the effects of nano-scale capillary pressure and the surface charges in the nano-regime. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The broader impact of this research project are expected in two primary areas; 1) The advancement of fundamental science in the nano-scale regime of the diamond-graphite phase-transitions, 2) international collaboration between USA, Korea, Australia, and Domenico Republic, with many students participating and contributing to the common goal of bringing to existence of yet another new form of carbon nanostructures diamond nanowires.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/19/2013</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/31/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1324776</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Jimmy</FirstName>
<LastName>Xu</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Jimmy Xu</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>Jimmy_Xu@brown.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>4018631439</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000218732</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/19/2013</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Brown University</Name>
<CityName>Providence</CityName>
<ZipCode>029129002</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>4018632777</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>BOX 1929</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[350 Eddy Street]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Rhode Island</StateName>
<StateCode>RI</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>RI01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>001785542</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>BROWN UNIVERSITY IN PROVIDENCE IN THE STATE OF RHODE ISLAND AND PROVIDENCE PLANTATIONS</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>001785542</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Brown University]]></Name>
<CityName>Providence</CityName>
<StateCode>RI</StateCode>
<ZipCode>029129002</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[BOX 1929]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Rhode Island</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>RI01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1517</Code>
<Text>EPMD-ElectrnPhoton&amp;MagnDevices</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>100E</Code>
<Text>Novel devices &amp; vacuum electronics</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7916</Code>
<Text>EAGER</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9102</Code>
<Text>WOMEN, MINORITY, DISABLED, NEC</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9251</Code>
<Text>REU SUPP-Res Exp for Ugrd Supp</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0113</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0114</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2013~205839</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~8000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p class="MsoNormal" style="margin-bottom: .0001pt; mso-pagination: none;"><span style="mso-bidi-font-size: 12.0pt; line-height: 107%;" lang="EN-US">By all accounts, diamond is a material of extremes. Besides its beauty and attraction as glamorous jewelry, it is the hardest, thermally most conductive, highest in break-down field, and greatest in atomic density of any known material. Adding to this list, it is likely the most stable in single-photon emission even at room temperature. Despite the tremendous attention and publicity given to discoveries of new carbon forms such as C60, carbon nanotubes, and graphene, diamond and graphite have remained two most successful carbon allotropes exploited in technologies and science to date. The chance discovery of crystalline diamond nanowires, in the PI&rsquo;s lab at Brown University, signified a step forward in diamond research. However, reproducibly synthesizing the crystalline diamond nanowires has remained challenging. In this EAGER project, we took step to meet this challenge and pursued an investigation of the material properties and device potential of single-crystalline diamond nanowires, including specific device-enabling effects such as microwave manipulation and control of single-photon emission and low-threshold electron field emission.</span></p> <p class="MsoNormal" style="margin-bottom: .0001pt; mso-pagination: none;"><span style="mso-bidi-font-size: 12.0pt; line-height: 107%;" lang="EN-US">During the two years period of exploratory research, this project has produced a number of outcomes which could be highlighted as the <strong><em>intellectual merits</em></strong> of this research.&nbsp; These include new techniques for improving the reproducibility of diamond nanowires and the unexpected discovery of yet another new carbon allotrope &ndash; graphite nanowires. Specifically, the concept of catalyst engineering was proposed to provide ultrasmall (sub-5-nm) noble metals or iron-family catalysts and to support sufficiently high capillary pressure (&gt; 4 GPa) during atmospheric chemical vapor-liquid-solid (VLS) growth of diamond nanowires. In addition to the catalyst engineering, efforts have been made for careful optimization of growth parameters, such as temperature, time, and gas flow ratios. Such modifications and numerous experimental growth trials resulted in the development of straight carbon nanowires from the ultrasmall Pt catalyst and the unexpected discovery of crystalline graphite nanowires from the ultrasmall alloyed iron-family catalysts. The introduction of the ultrasmall, noble metal catalysts and the establishment of the new characterization protocols demonstrated in this project proved effective in accelerating the synthesis processes, the yield, and the subsequent sample selection. In addition, the discovery of the graphite nanowire would enrich understandings of 1-D carbon nanomaterials, the Li atom intercalation process that is vital for Li-ion batteries, and the electron field emission and possibly light emission in graphite. During the period, findings from the research were disseminated via 4 invited talks, 3 conference presentations, and 1 journal publication, which are share with other engineering applications, the underlying physical mechanism and surface chemistry.</span></p> <p class="MsoNormal" style="margin-bottom: .0001pt; mso-pagination: none;"><span style="font-family: 'Times New Roman', serif; line-height: 107%;">The </span><strong style="font-family: 'Times New Roman', serif; line-height: 107%;"><em>broader impact</em></strong><span style="font-family: 'Times New Roman', serif; line-height: 107%;"> resulted from this project is primarily in three areas; 1) The advancement of fundamental science of carbon nanostructures, 2) the international collaboration with several research teams, and 3) comprehensive research training of postdoctoral researchers, graduate and undergraduate...]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[By all accounts, diamond is a material of extremes. Besides its beauty and attraction as glamorous jewelry, it is the hardest, thermally most conductive, highest in break-down field, and greatest in atomic density of any known material. Adding to this list, it is likely the most stable in single-photon emission even at room temperature. Despite the tremendous attention and publicity given to discoveries of new carbon forms such as C60, carbon nanotubes, and graphene, diamond and graphite have remained two most successful carbon allotropes exploited in technologies and science to date. The chance discovery of crystalline diamond nanowires, in the PIÆs lab at Brown University, signified a step forward in diamond research. However, reproducibly synthesizing the crystalline diamond nanowires has remained challenging. In this EAGER project, we took step to meet this challenge and pursued an investigation of the material properties and device potential of single-crystalline diamond nanowires, including specific device-enabling effects such as microwave manipulation and control of single-photon emission and low-threshold electron field emission. During the two years period of exploratory research, this project has produced a number of outcomes which could be highlighted as the intellectual merits of this research.  These include new techniques for improving the reproducibility of diamond nanowires and the unexpected discovery of yet another new carbon allotrope &ndash; graphite nanowires. Specifically, the concept of catalyst engineering was proposed to provide ultrasmall (sub-5-nm) noble metals or iron-family catalysts and to support sufficiently high capillary pressure (&gt; 4 GPa) during atmospheric chemical vapor-liquid-solid (VLS) growth of diamond nanowires. In addition to the catalyst engineering, efforts have been made for careful optimization of growth parameters, such as temperature, time, and gas flow ratios. Such modifications and numerous experimental growth trials resulted in the development of straight carbon nanowires from the ultrasmall Pt catalyst and the unexpected discovery of crystalline graphite nanowires from the ultrasmall alloyed iron-family catalysts. The introduction of the ultrasmall, noble metal catalysts and the establishment of the new characterization protocols demonstrated in this project proved effective in accelerating the synthesis processes, the yield, and the subsequent sample selection. In addition, the discovery of the graphite nanowire would enrich understandings of 1-D carbon nanomaterials, the Li atom intercalation process that is vital for Li-ion batteries, and the electron field emission and possibly light emission in graphite. During the period, findings from the research were disseminated via 4 invited talks, 3 conference presentations, and 1 journal publication, which are share with other engineering applications, the underlying physical mechanism and surface chemistry. The broader impact resulted from this project is primarily in three areas; 1) The advancement of fundamental science of carbon nanostructures, 2) the international collaboration with several research teams, and 3) comprehensive research training of postdoctoral researchers, graduate and undergraduate students. The project was exploratory in nature and high-risk.  The growth mechanisms of the diamond and graphite nanowires were not understood at all at the start, which now are better understood.  It is expected that this exploration will eventually lead to advances that may expand the frontier of carbon electronics, by introducing new members to the amazingly versatile Carbon family as did the discoveries for C60, carbon nanotubes, and graphene. The studies have also impacted on various institutional resources via collaborations between researchers in other institutions and internationals. Such institutions include AFRL, Seoul National University in Korea, and IEMN in France. Those collaborations are expected to continue ...]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
