<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>IBSS-Ex: The Adaptive Nature of Adult Literacy</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2013</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2016</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>250000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>250000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>04010000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>SBE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>SMA</Abbreviation>
<LongName>SBE Off Of Multidisciplinary Activities</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Thomas Baerwald</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This interdisciplinary research project focuses on the way adults with varying age and cognitive profiles choose what to read in order to learn when they have access to multiple sources of text.  The contemporary science of literacy faces challenges from rapid changes in the nature of both reading and the reader.  As literacy moves into electronic environments, learning rarely is characterized by steady, linear progress through a textbook or given set of texts.  Rather, it is increasingly dependent on the learner's ability to effectively navigate through multiple sources of information that self-regulates the flow of information.  At the same time, the population is rapidly aging, and longer lifespans as associated with longer workspans, with the need for expanding skill sets placing more demands on lifelong literacy.  In this exploratory study, the researchers will seek to understand how reading processes operate in contemporary ecologies of literacy.  The project is grounded in theories and methods from the psychological, education, and computer sciences.  Much is known about the psychology and neuroscience of reading in terms of the cognitive processes underlying how meaning is constructed from the printed word, but missing from this perspective is the ecology of reading in which individuals must choose what to read.  This gap is addressed through the use of computer science approaches in the study of web browsing, which consider how learners explore information sources.  These approaches neglect the processes through which mental representations of meaning are created through the encounter with particular texts, however.  This project's researchers will start with the assumption that in authentic ecologies of literacy, individuals both explore (search, navigate, forage) and exploit (read) particular texts for various purposes, including information gathering.  Their emphasis will be on "reading in the wild" -- on how these different phases of literacy interact and influence one another in complex ecologies of literacy.  A range of computational, experimental, and naturalistic methods will be used, including studies of how individuals learn about a topic through exploration on an electronic tablet, where they select buttons with content cues to reveal sentences that provide information about the topic.  Patterns of choice, timing, and memory performance will be measured to build models of exploration and information uptake (exploitation).  This research is will probe exploration as an adaptation that plays a domain-general role in cognition, augments learning by increasing efficiency of information uptake, and affords the opportunity for learners to achieve a match between text and cognitive resources.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Models of learning in complex text environments are needed to guide instructional design in new reading ecologies, especially among adults for whom literacy engagement is primarily self-guided.  This project will enrich theoretical understanding of reading as a complex learning and problem solving skill needed by people of all ages.  It will develop a measurement and modeling approach to study how people read when confronted with multiple options through the use of data from electronic tablets that will allow the direct assessment of literacy behaviors.  The project also will involve graduate and undergraduate students from educational psychology, computer science, and engineering in order to enhance interdisciplinary education and training opportunities in literacy science.  This project is supported through the NSF Interdisciplinary Behavioral and Social Sciences Research (IBSS) competition.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/29/2013</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/29/2013</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.075</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1328545</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Wai-Tat</FirstName>
<LastName>Fu</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Wai-Tat Fu</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>wfu@illinois.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2172448617</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000243175</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/29/2013</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Daniel</FirstName>
<LastName>Morrow</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>G</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Daniel G Morrow</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>dgm@uiuc.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2172441875</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000258379</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/29/2013</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Elizabeth A. L.</FirstName>
<LastName>Stine-Morrow</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Elizabeth A. L. Stine-Morrow</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>eals@illinois.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2172442167</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000639906</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/29/2013</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign</Name>
<CityName>Champaign</CityName>
<ZipCode>618207406</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2173332187</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1901 South First Street</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[Suite A]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Illinois</StateName>
<StateCode>IL</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>13</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>IL13</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>041544081</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF ILLINOIS</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>041544081</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign]]></Name>
<CityName>Urbana</CityName>
<StateCode>IL</StateCode>
<ZipCode>618013620</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[506 South Wright St]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Illinois</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>13</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>IL13</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>8213</Code>
<Text>Interdiscp Behav&amp;SocSci IBSS</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8213</Code>
<Text>IBSS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8605</Code>
<Text>SBE 2020</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9179</Code>
<Text>GRADUATE INVOLVEMENT</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0113</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2013~250000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>It has been recognized for some time that conventional reading co-opts cognitive and neural mechanisms evolved for object recognition and spoken language communication, but as the ecology of reading is shifting more and more to interactive electronic environments, recent theories postulate that literacy activities increasingly depend on search. In this view, multitext and hypertext environments are becoming the norm, such that contemporary readers forage and consume information relying on mechanisms evolved for food foraging that are necessary to survive in wild. Information Foraging Theory, then, holds that readers self-regulate attention so as to alternate between search in the ecology for information sources, or &ldquo;patches,&rdquo; and consumption of the information within a patch. We examined the extent to which general foraging principles applied to how adults read in multitext environments.</p> <p>First, consistent with the adaptive nature of foraging in the wild (as characterized by Charnov&rsquo;s theorem), readers were more likely to persist in reading a particular text when there was a greater cost in switching to a new text. Under such high switch cost, readers also showed better memory for the content. The implication is that in electronic ecologies that afford facile switching among sources, readers are likely to &ldquo;satisfice,&rdquo; that is, to read relatively superficially, and consequently, retain relatively less of the information from any one text. This finding was substantively replicated in another study that directly compared foraging with experimenter-controlled presentation: in foraging, readers encoded information more efficiently, but allocated less time than needed to achieve optimal recall. Such findings suggest that learning in electronic environments might be enhanced by introducing some &ldquo;productive cost,&rdquo; such as a retrieval task, when switching between sources.</p> <p>Second, we found individual differences in rate of information uptake that generalized across three different foraging tasks, suggesting the existence of common mechanisms in consuming information. Switching, on the other hand, was task-specific. We found no evidence for consistent individual differences across task in the tendency to switch, but rather the likelihood of switching depended on two factors: perceived rate of information gain and the extent to which the larger ecology afforded easy access to other sources. Persistence in consuming information for a source is engendered by the perception that information rate is being maintained (e.g., continuing to find items in a puzzle, or learning novel information in a text), as well as an ecology that incurs some cost in disengaging from one source to find another. Put another way, exploration is stimulated by a perceived decrease in information uptake or an ecology that minimizes the effort needed to find alternative sources.&nbsp;</p> <p>Finally, we found that foragers base decisions about when to switch among sources on perceived learning. Cues to perceived learning seem to derive primarily from the amount of information in the text, and not from the fluency with which the information is processed.</p> <p>Collectively, our findings suggest that reading in multitext environments can be conceptualized in terms of foraging models. Thus, reading is a cultural practice that is shaped by the ecology in which it occurs. Our work has been a first step in exploring the way in which reading processes involve search and exploration &ndash; and how that interacts with the learning processes in consuming text.&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 11/30/2016<br>      Modified by: Elizabeth A. L.&nbsp;Stine-Morrow</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ It has been recognized for some time that conventional reading co-opts cognitive and neural mechanisms evolved for object recognition and spoken language communication, but as the ecology of reading is shifting more and more to interactive electronic environments, recent theories postulate that literacy activities increasingly depend on search. In this view, multitext and hypertext environments are becoming the norm, such that contemporary readers forage and consume information relying on mechanisms evolved for food foraging that are necessary to survive in wild. Information Foraging Theory, then, holds that readers self-regulate attention so as to alternate between search in the ecology for information sources, or "patches," and consumption of the information within a patch. We examined the extent to which general foraging principles applied to how adults read in multitext environments.  First, consistent with the adaptive nature of foraging in the wild (as characterized by Charnov?s theorem), readers were more likely to persist in reading a particular text when there was a greater cost in switching to a new text. Under such high switch cost, readers also showed better memory for the content. The implication is that in electronic ecologies that afford facile switching among sources, readers are likely to "satisfice," that is, to read relatively superficially, and consequently, retain relatively less of the information from any one text. This finding was substantively replicated in another study that directly compared foraging with experimenter-controlled presentation: in foraging, readers encoded information more efficiently, but allocated less time than needed to achieve optimal recall. Such findings suggest that learning in electronic environments might be enhanced by introducing some "productive cost," such as a retrieval task, when switching between sources.  Second, we found individual differences in rate of information uptake that generalized across three different foraging tasks, suggesting the existence of common mechanisms in consuming information. Switching, on the other hand, was task-specific. We found no evidence for consistent individual differences across task in the tendency to switch, but rather the likelihood of switching depended on two factors: perceived rate of information gain and the extent to which the larger ecology afforded easy access to other sources. Persistence in consuming information for a source is engendered by the perception that information rate is being maintained (e.g., continuing to find items in a puzzle, or learning novel information in a text), as well as an ecology that incurs some cost in disengaging from one source to find another. Put another way, exploration is stimulated by a perceived decrease in information uptake or an ecology that minimizes the effort needed to find alternative sources.   Finally, we found that foragers base decisions about when to switch among sources on perceived learning. Cues to perceived learning seem to derive primarily from the amount of information in the text, and not from the fluency with which the information is processed.  Collectively, our findings suggest that reading in multitext environments can be conceptualized in terms of foraging models. Thus, reading is a cultural practice that is shaped by the ecology in which it occurs. Our work has been a first step in exploring the way in which reading processes involve search and exploration &ndash; and how that interacts with the learning processes in consuming text.           Last Modified: 11/30/2016       Submitted by: Elizabeth A. L. Stine-Morrow]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
