<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>The 2013 Tropical Cyclone Research Forum; College Park, Maryland; March 5-7, 2013</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>02/15/2013</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>01/31/2015</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>8000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>8000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>06020105</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>GEO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>AGS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Atmospheric &amp; Geospace Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Chungu Lu</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>clu@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927110</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The Tropical Cyclone Research Forum will be held on March 5-7, 2013 at the NOAA Center for Weather and Climate Prediction in College Park, Maryland. The theme of the workshop is "Tropical Cyclone Research: Our Vision for the Future". Topics include: snapshots of tropical cyclone R&amp;D; federal numerical modeling initiatives; transitioning research to operations; tropical cyclone model development and technology transfer; observations and observing strategies for tropical cyclones and the environment; improvements in tropical cyclone forecast and warning products and services; and social science applications to the tropical cyclone forecast and warning notification problem. The Tropical Cyclone Research Forum is sponsored by NSF, NOAA/OAR and the Office of Naval Research.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Intellectual merit: &lt;br/&gt;At the Tropical Cyclone Research Forum, representatives from the academic research community, industry and federal agencies will have the opportunity to discuss the latest developments in tropical cyclone research such as:&lt;br/&gt;1. Review of the 2012 hurricane/typhoon season from both an operations and reconnaissance perspective;&lt;br/&gt;2. The Navy's Model Development and Improvement Program/Hurricane Forecast Improvement Program (HFIP);&lt;br/&gt;3. NSF program initiatives, to include the University-based National Ensemble Program;&lt;br/&gt;4. Earth System Predication Capability (ESPC)/Next-Generation Suite of Models;&lt;br/&gt;5. Joint Hurricane Testbed: Project Updates and Plans for the Future;&lt;br/&gt;6. Improvements in tropical cyclone forecast and warning products and services, to include storm surge and inland flooding.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Broader impacts: &lt;br/&gt;The workshop is important to the nation because it brings together the academic research community, industry, federal agencies and other user communities such as emergency management, to prepare for the upcoming hurricane season and make improvements to the Nation's hurricane forecasting and warning program.  Some graduate students will also participate in this workshop, promoting education and training that NSF sees as importance to science and society.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>02/20/2013</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>02/20/2013</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.050</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1329355</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Meg</FirstName>
<LastName>Austin</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Meg Austin</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>Austin@ucar.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>3034978630</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000311427</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>02/20/2013</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University Corporation For Atmospheric Res</Name>
<CityName>Boulder</CityName>
<ZipCode>803012252</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>3034971000</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>3090 Center Green Drive</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Colorado</StateName>
<StateCode>CO</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CO02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>078339587</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY CORPORATION FOR ATMOSPHERIC RESEARCH</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>078339587</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University Corporation for Atmospheric Research]]></Name>
<CityName>Boulder</CityName>
<StateCode>CO</StateCode>
<ZipCode>803055602</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[1850 Table Mesa Dr]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Colorado</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CO02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1525</Code>
<Text>Physical &amp; Dynamic Meteorology</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>0000</Code>
<Text>UNASSIGNED</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>OTHR</Code>
<Text>OTHER RESEARCH OR EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0113</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2013~8000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The 67<sup>th</sup> Interdepartmental Hurricane Conference/Tropical Cyclone Research Forum (IHC/TCRF) was held on March 5-7, 2013, at the NOAA Center for Weather and Climate Prediction (NCWCP) in College Park, MD. There were 255 total registrants; 114 registered to attend in person, and 141 participated virtually via the internet and teleconferencing. It was particularly noteworthy that when the Federal offices in Washington, DC, (including the conference facility) were shut down due to the winter storm on Wednesday, March 6, the forum was conducted exclusively in the virtual mode and the day&rsquo;s agenda was fully and successfully accomplished.</p> <p class="Default">&nbsp;</p> <p class="Default">The IHC/TCRF had the following objectives:</p> <ol> <li>Assess the progress in addressing the operational priorities of the operational centers (NHC, CPHC, and JTWC) and adjust future research priorities as needed.</li> <li>Review ongoing numerical modeling initiatives within NOAA, Navy, NASA, and NSF.</li> <li>Receive updates on Joint Hurricane Testbed projects ready for transition from research into operations.</li> <li>Explore other R&amp;D opportunities (modeling and observational) that will promote improvements in forecasting and understanding of TCs and their associated affects.</li> <li>Investigate the application of social science to the TC forecast and warning notification problem.</li> </ol> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>The IHC/TCRF included plenary sessions, poster sessions, a Working Group for Hurricane and Winter Storms Operations and Research (WG/HWSOR) meeting and a panel discussion on the emergency response to Hurricane Sandy.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>Conference sessions addressed the following topics:</p> <p class="Default">1. Tropical Cyclone Research, Federal Agency Overview</p> <p class="Default">2. Working Group for Tropical Cyclone Research</p> <p class="Default">3. Federal Modeling Initiatives</p> <p class="Default">4. 2012 Tropical Cyclone Season in Review</p> <p class="Default">5. Joint Hurricane Testbed Project Updates</p> <p class="Default">6. Tropical Cyclone Model Development and Technology Transfer</p> <p class="Default">7. Observations and Observing St rategies for Tropical Cyclones and their Environment</p> <p class="Default">8. Improvements in Tropical Cyclone Forecast and Warning Products and Services&nbsp;</p> <p class="Default">9. Social Science Applications to the Tropical Cyclone Forecast and Warning Notification Problem<strong>&nbsp;</strong></p> <p class="Default">&nbsp;</p> <p>The Working Group for Hurricane and Winter Storms Operations and Research (WG/HWSOR) meeting was held virtually on March 4, 2013, immediately prior to the formal opening of the IHC/TCRF. Final working group results were presented during the final plenary session of the Tropical Cyclone Research Forum by the working group chair.</p> <p class="Default">&nbsp;</p> <p class="Default">The panel discussion on the Emergency Response to Hurricane Sandy was moderated by Mr. Brian Norcross from The Weather Channel. Panelists included Captain Thomas Scardino, Executive Officer, Emergency Management Section, New Jersey Homeland Security Branch, and Mr. Richard A. French, New York State Office of Emergency Management.</p> <p class="Default">&nbsp;</p> <p class="Default">Keynote speakers included Congressman Chaka Fattah, a senior member of the House Appropriations Committee and the ranking member on the Subcommittee on Commerce, Justice, Science and related agencies (CJS), and Dr. Louis Uccellini, Director, National Weather Service.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>The Richard H. Hagemeyer Award, which is presented annually to honor the memory of the long-time director of the NWS Pacific Region, was awarded to Dr. James D. McFadden, Chief, Programs and Projects at NOAA&rsquo;s Aircraft Operations Center, MacDill AFB, FL, for his substantial contributions to our Nation&rsquo;s tropical cyclone fore...]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The 67th Interdepartmental Hurricane Conference/Tropical Cyclone Research Forum (IHC/TCRF) was held on March 5-7, 2013, at the NOAA Center for Weather and Climate Prediction (NCWCP) in College Park, MD. There were 255 total registrants; 114 registered to attend in person, and 141 participated virtually via the internet and teleconferencing. It was particularly noteworthy that when the Federal offices in Washington, DC, (including the conference facility) were shut down due to the winter storm on Wednesday, March 6, the forum was conducted exclusively in the virtual mode and the dayÆs agenda was fully and successfully accomplished.   The IHC/TCRF had the following objectives:  Assess the progress in addressing the operational priorities of the operational centers (NHC, CPHC, and JTWC) and adjust future research priorities as needed. Review ongoing numerical modeling initiatives within NOAA, Navy, NASA, and NSF. Receive updates on Joint Hurricane Testbed projects ready for transition from research into operations. Explore other R&amp;D opportunities (modeling and observational) that will promote improvements in forecasting and understanding of TCs and their associated affects. Investigate the application of social science to the TC forecast and warning notification problem.      The IHC/TCRF included plenary sessions, poster sessions, a Working Group for Hurricane and Winter Storms Operations and Research (WG/HWSOR) meeting and a panel discussion on the emergency response to Hurricane Sandy.     Conference sessions addressed the following topics: 1. Tropical Cyclone Research, Federal Agency Overview 2. Working Group for Tropical Cyclone Research 3. Federal Modeling Initiatives 4. 2012 Tropical Cyclone Season in Review 5. Joint Hurricane Testbed Project Updates 6. Tropical Cyclone Model Development and Technology Transfer 7. Observations and Observing St rategies for Tropical Cyclones and their Environment 8. Improvements in Tropical Cyclone Forecast and Warning Products and Services  9. Social Science Applications to the Tropical Cyclone Forecast and Warning Notification Problem     The Working Group for Hurricane and Winter Storms Operations and Research (WG/HWSOR) meeting was held virtually on March 4, 2013, immediately prior to the formal opening of the IHC/TCRF. Final working group results were presented during the final plenary session of the Tropical Cyclone Research Forum by the working group chair.   The panel discussion on the Emergency Response to Hurricane Sandy was moderated by Mr. Brian Norcross from The Weather Channel. Panelists included Captain Thomas Scardino, Executive Officer, Emergency Management Section, New Jersey Homeland Security Branch, and Mr. Richard A. French, New York State Office of Emergency Management.   Keynote speakers included Congressman Chaka Fattah, a senior member of the House Appropriations Committee and the ranking member on the Subcommittee on Commerce, Justice, Science and related agencies (CJS), and Dr. Louis Uccellini, Director, National Weather Service.     The Richard H. Hagemeyer Award, which is presented annually to honor the memory of the long-time director of the NWS Pacific Region, was awarded to Dr. James D. McFadden, Chief, Programs and Projects at NOAAÆs Aircraft Operations Center, MacDill AFB, FL, for his substantial contributions to our NationÆs tropical cyclone forecast and warning program.     The outcome of the forum was a report which includes key takeaways, future action items, and the presentations given. The report is available at: http://www.ofcm.gov/ihc13/summary.pdf    The 2013 IHC/TCRF was sponsored by NSF, NOAA OAR and the Office of Naval Research. The conference is important because it brings together the academic research community, industry, Federal agencies and other user communities such as emergency management, to prepare for the upcoming hurricane season and make improvements to the NationÆs hurricane forecasting and warning program.                Last...]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
