<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>CPS: Synergy: Collaborative Research: Thermal-Aware Management of Cyber-Physical Systems</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>10/01/2013</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>09/30/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>460000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>460000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>05050000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>CSE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CNS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Computer and Network Systems</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>David Corman</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>dcorman@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032928754</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Processors in cyber-physical systems are increasingly being used in applications where they must operate in harsh ambient conditions and a computational workload which can lead to high chip temperatures.  Examples include cars, robots, aircraft and spacecraft.  High operating temperatures accelerate the aging of the chips, thus increasing transient and permanent failure rates. Current ways to deal with this mostly turn off the processor core or drastically slow it down when some part of it is seen to exceed a given temperature threshold.  However, this pass/fail approach ignores the fact that (a) processors experience accelerated aging due to high temperatures, even if these are below the threshold, and (b) while deadlines are a constraint for real-time tasks to keep the controlled plant in the allowed state space, the actual controller response times that will increase if the voltage or frequency is lowered (to cool down the chip) are what determine the controlled plant performance.  Existing approaches also fail to exploit the tradeoff between controller reliability (affected by its temperature history) and the performance of the plant.  This project addresses these issues.   Load-shaping algorithms are being devised to manage thermal stresses while ensuring appropriate levels of control quality.  Such actions include task migration, changing execution speed, selecting an alternative algorithm or software implementation of control functions, and terminating prematurely optional portions of iterative tasks. Validation platforms for this project include automobiles and unmanned aerial vehicles.  These platforms have been chosen based on both their importance to society and the significant technical challenges they pose.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;With CPS becoming ever more important in our lives and businesses, this project which will make CPS controllers more reliable and/or economical has broad potential social and economic impacts. Collaboration with General Motors promotes transition of the new technology to industry. The project includes activities to introduce students to thermal control in computing, in courses spanning high-school, undergraduate and graduate curricula.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>09/19/2013</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>09/19/2013</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.070</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1329831</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Israel</FirstName>
<LastName>Koren</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Israel Koren</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>koren@ecs.umass.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>4135452643</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000471910</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/19/2013</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>C.Mani</FirstName>
<LastName>Krishna</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>C.Mani Krishna</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>krishna@ecs.umass.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>4135450574</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000180745</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/19/2013</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Massachusetts Amherst</Name>
<CityName>Hadley</CityName>
<ZipCode>010359450</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>4135450698</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>Research Administration Building</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[100 Venture Way, Suite 201]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
<StateCode>MA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MA02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>153926712</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF MASSACHUSETTS</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>079520631</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Massachusetts Amherst]]></Name>
<CityName>Amherst</CityName>
<StateCode>MA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>010039284</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[151 Holdsworth Way]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MA02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1714</Code>
<Text>Special Projects - CNS</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7918</Code>
<Text>CYBER-PHYSICAL SYSTEMS (CPS)</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0113</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2013~460000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Cyber-physical applications are proliferating. They consist of a physical plant monitored and controlled by a set of processors. The plant may range in geographical extent from a node a few feet in diameter to one spanning a continent.&nbsp;</p> <p>This project is about mitigating the harmful effects of heating on processor lifetimes. It is well known that elevated temperatures cause a dramatic reduction in device lifetime; indeed, there are many failure mechanisms where such decline is exponential.&nbsp;</p> <p>Most thermal mitigation approaches can be broadly categorized as either proactive or reactive. Proactive approaches reduce the amount of heat generated and provide effective means to rapidly dissipate it. Reactive methods adapt the workload schedule or even adjust the total workload so as to limit the thermal damage to the processor cores.</p> <p>A key distinguishing feature of this project is the way in which state information and dynamics about the controlled plant and information about the computational workload (obtained by prior profiling) is used. We start by describing how state and plant dynamics information is used.</p> <p>The physical plant can be characterized by a state variable which represents features of significance. For example, a boiler may be characterized by a state vector consisting of its current temperature and pressure. An aircraft state vector may include its pitch angle, pitch angle rate, angle of attack, etc. The dynamics of the plant are mathematical laws which specify how the state vector evolves in reaction to actuator and environmental inputs.&nbsp;</p> <p>Based on the current plant state and its dynamics, it is possible to check if any error on the part of the computers can drive the plant outside a specified safe subset of its state space within a given time. If this is not possible, then the plant is resilient against computer failure for a certain amount of time. In these states, therefore, there is no need for fault-tolerance. In the (usually rare) instance of computational failure, the control system will have plenty of time to recognize a control input error and react to it before the safety of the plant is jeopardized. It is therefore wasteful to implement fault tolerance all the time; much better to apply it selectively only when the plant is in a state that demands it. Now, fault tolerance is obtained through computational redundancy, most often by running multiple copies of the task and comparing (and voting on) the outputs generated by these copies.&nbsp; Removing the need for fault-tolerance for a large fraction of the time therefore dramatically reduces the computational workload. This, in turn, leads to reduced energy consumption and cooler processors, thereby enhancing processor lifetimes. Work in this project has shown the considerable gains in reliability and energy economy obtained as a result. Procedures have been devised whereby the system can rapidly identify whether the plant is in a subspace requiring no fault-tolerance and adjusting the workload appropriately. A design framework for cyber-physical systems has been developed to implement this approach.</p> <p>Work in this project has shown the considerable gains in reliability and energy economy obtained as a result. Procedures have been devised whereby the system can rapidly identify whether the plant is in a subspace requiring no fault-tolerance and adjusting the workload appropriately.</p> <p>Another avenue explored in this project has been to appropriately target energy savings through dynamic voltage and frequency scaling (DVFS). It is well known that running processors at a lower voltage and frequency level dramatically reduces its energy consumption; indeed, energy consumption to execute a task can go down roughly quadratically and execution time rise approximately linearly as the voltage is reduced. Traditionally, DVFS uses slack in the schedule to slow the processor down in a greedy fashion. By contrast, the approach developed in this project targets slowdown periods towards phases of high task activity. As a result, greater energy savings are attained per unit of slowdown.&nbsp;</p> <p>The intellectual merit of this work consists of developing approaches that exploit plant-side information to better manage the cyber part of a cyber-physical system. This work is facilitated by the fact that extensive plant-side information about its current state and dynamics is available (especially for life-critical applications). Simulation studies have shown the significant improvements to processor lifetime as a result.</p> <p>The broader impact of this project stems from the increasingly important role that cyber-physical systems play in today's society. This role is only projected to increase in the next few decades.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 11/26/2018<br>      Modified by: C.Mani&nbsp;Krishna</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Cyber-physical applications are proliferating. They consist of a physical plant monitored and controlled by a set of processors. The plant may range in geographical extent from a node a few feet in diameter to one spanning a continent.   This project is about mitigating the harmful effects of heating on processor lifetimes. It is well known that elevated temperatures cause a dramatic reduction in device lifetime; indeed, there are many failure mechanisms where such decline is exponential.   Most thermal mitigation approaches can be broadly categorized as either proactive or reactive. Proactive approaches reduce the amount of heat generated and provide effective means to rapidly dissipate it. Reactive methods adapt the workload schedule or even adjust the total workload so as to limit the thermal damage to the processor cores.  A key distinguishing feature of this project is the way in which state information and dynamics about the controlled plant and information about the computational workload (obtained by prior profiling) is used. We start by describing how state and plant dynamics information is used.  The physical plant can be characterized by a state variable which represents features of significance. For example, a boiler may be characterized by a state vector consisting of its current temperature and pressure. An aircraft state vector may include its pitch angle, pitch angle rate, angle of attack, etc. The dynamics of the plant are mathematical laws which specify how the state vector evolves in reaction to actuator and environmental inputs.   Based on the current plant state and its dynamics, it is possible to check if any error on the part of the computers can drive the plant outside a specified safe subset of its state space within a given time. If this is not possible, then the plant is resilient against computer failure for a certain amount of time. In these states, therefore, there is no need for fault-tolerance. In the (usually rare) instance of computational failure, the control system will have plenty of time to recognize a control input error and react to it before the safety of the plant is jeopardized. It is therefore wasteful to implement fault tolerance all the time; much better to apply it selectively only when the plant is in a state that demands it. Now, fault tolerance is obtained through computational redundancy, most often by running multiple copies of the task and comparing (and voting on) the outputs generated by these copies.  Removing the need for fault-tolerance for a large fraction of the time therefore dramatically reduces the computational workload. This, in turn, leads to reduced energy consumption and cooler processors, thereby enhancing processor lifetimes. Work in this project has shown the considerable gains in reliability and energy economy obtained as a result. Procedures have been devised whereby the system can rapidly identify whether the plant is in a subspace requiring no fault-tolerance and adjusting the workload appropriately. A design framework for cyber-physical systems has been developed to implement this approach.  Work in this project has shown the considerable gains in reliability and energy economy obtained as a result. Procedures have been devised whereby the system can rapidly identify whether the plant is in a subspace requiring no fault-tolerance and adjusting the workload appropriately.  Another avenue explored in this project has been to appropriately target energy savings through dynamic voltage and frequency scaling (DVFS). It is well known that running processors at a lower voltage and frequency level dramatically reduces its energy consumption; indeed, energy consumption to execute a task can go down roughly quadratically and execution time rise approximately linearly as the voltage is reduced. Traditionally, DVFS uses slack in the schedule to slow the processor down in a greedy fashion. By contrast, the approach developed in this project targets slowdown periods towards phases of high task activity. As a result, greater energy savings are attained per unit of slowdown.   The intellectual merit of this work consists of developing approaches that exploit plant-side information to better manage the cyber part of a cyber-physical system. This work is facilitated by the fact that extensive plant-side information about its current state and dynamics is available (especially for life-critical applications). Simulation studies have shown the significant improvements to processor lifetime as a result.  The broader impact of this project stems from the increasingly important role that cyber-physical systems play in today's society. This role is only projected to increase in the next few decades.             Last Modified: 11/26/2018       Submitted by: C.Mani Krishna]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
