<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>RUI: Specificity of Arf-dependent Golgi trafficking: A mechanistic analysis</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/15/2013</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>164250.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>164250</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>08070000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>BIO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>MCB</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Molecular and Cellular Bioscience</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Charles Cunningham</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>chacunni@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922283</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The regulated movement of membrane vesicles within the cell is a process essential to life. This trafficking of membrane vesicles mediates the transport of proteins within the cell and the secretion of certain selected proteins from the cell. Minor defects in these processes can result in devastating physiological consequences. The correct trafficking of vesicles requires a high level of specificity, as transport vesicles containing only the correct cargoes (e.g. specific proteins) must form at the proper donor membrane and be delivered to the right target membrane. However, the mechanisms that underlie the specificity of membrane transport remain largely undefined. In this project fission yeast will be used to investigate these regulatory mechanisms, especially those mediated by the ADP Ribosylation Factor Guanine Nucleotide Exchange Factors that are known to play a role in determining the specificity of secretory traffic. Broader Impacts. This project will enhance undergraduate research through 1) integration into inquiry-based teaching laboratories, 2) providing research projects for 4-7 senior biology students each year and 3) summer research opportunities for undergraduate students.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/13/2013</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/13/2013</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.074</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1329506</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Melanie</FirstName>
<LastName>Styers</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Melanie Styers</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>mstyers@bsc.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2052264882</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000585804</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/13/2013</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Birmingham Southern College</Name>
<CityName>Birmingham</CityName>
<ZipCode>352540002</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2052264985</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>900 Arkadelphia Road</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Alabama</StateName>
<StateCode>AL</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>AL07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>067136580</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>BIRMINGHAM-SOUTHERN COLLEGE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>067136580</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Birmingham-Southern College]]></Name>
<CityName>Birmingham</CityName>
<StateCode>AL</StateCode>
<ZipCode>352540002</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[900 Arkadelphia Road]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Alabama</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>AL07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1114</Code>
<Text>Cellular Dynamics and Function</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1114</Code>
<Text>CELLULAR SYSTEMS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7465</Code>
<Text>NANOSCALE BIO CORE</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9178</Code>
<Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9183</Code>
<Text>GENERAL FOUNDATIONS OF BIOTECHNOLOGY</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9251</Code>
<Text>REU SUPP-Res Exp for Ugrd Supp</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0113</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2013~164250</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><strong>Intellectual Merit:</strong></p> <p>The results of this project have yielded important new insights into the mechanisms that regulate membrane transport and organellar homeostasis in fission yeast; these studies will inform future studies in mammalian systems. Our work has begun to clarify the distinct membrane transport pathways regulated by the sec71p and sec72p proteins, yeast homologs of the mammalian BIG1 and BIG2 proteins. Specifically, our results suggest that sec71p and sec72p regulate two distinct pathways that transport proteins and lipids to the vacuole. One pathway traffics proteins directly from the Golgi apparatus to the vacuole, while the second transits the endosome <em>en route</em> to the vacuole. Since BIG1 and BIG2 are known to play key roles in mammalian development, including disorders of the central nervous system such as autosomal recessive periventricular heterotopia with microcephaly, these studies may help us to identify new brain-specific cargo proteins trafficked along these pathways, as well as to better understand the general membrane trafficking mechanisms that underlie human development.</p> <p>In addition to understanding these vacuolar trafficking pathways, in exploring regulators of sec71p and sec72p function, we identified the yeast protein ypt4p, a homolog of the mammalian Rab4 protein, as a regulator of vacuole size and homeostasis. We found that cells lacking either <em>ypt4</em> or the <em>Chediak-Higashi Syndrome 1</em> (<em>CHS1/LYST</em>) homolog <em>lvs1</em> possessed enlarged vacuoles. CHS is a human syndrome characterized by recurrent infections, albinism, and peripheral neuropathy. Our results demonstrate that overexpression of lvs1p reverses vacuole enlargement in <em>ypt4</em><em>?</em><em> </em>cells, implicating lvs1p as a regulator of vacuolar fission that acts downstream of ypt4p. This study was published this year in the journal <em>Cellular Logistics,</em> and a number of the students supported by NSF funding were authors on the paper.</p> <p>In addition to this publication, findings from this study were also disseminated through 12 presentations by the PI and her students at the American Society for Cell Biology Annual Meeting and the Southeast Regional Yeast Meeting over this time period. In addition, each student presented his or her work on campus through BSC&rsquo;s summer research seminar and poster session or Natural Sciences Senior Conference.</p> <p><strong>&nbsp;</strong></p> <p><strong>Broader Impacts:</strong></p> <p>Funding from this grant has impacted education and workforce development at BSC in three major ways: 1) by supporting the training of undergraduate student researchers, 2) by supporting the institutional infrastructure for research, and 3) by supporting training in the Responsible Conduct of Research.</p> <p>This grant has supported the training of 23 undergraduate research students in the Styers laboratory, including 12 women and 5 students from underrepresented minorities. Exposure of undergraduates to scientific research will increase their competitiveness when applying for employment or for graduate or professional school. As a result of this educational experience, we anticipate that many of these students will go on to further training in STEM fields, thus enhancing our scientific workforce. Already, of the 18 senior research students who contributed to this project, 2 are enrolled in Ph.D. programs, 6 are in medical school, 1 is in engineering school, 3 are training for allied health careers, 3 are working in academic or for-profit research, and 2 are applying to graduate or professional programs. Exposure to authentic research at the undergraduate level has both excited these students for further study and helped them to develop the critical thinking and scientific reasoning skills needed to undertake the challenges associated with advanced training or joining the workforce.</p> <p>Funds from this proposal also supported the purchase of a Zeiss LSM 410 confocal microscope and a Licor Odyssey FC instrument that have contributed to the infrastructure for undergraduate research at Birmingham-Southern College. Acquisition of these instruments has provided hands-on experience with cutting-edge scientific technologies in a research-based setting for undergraduate students, allowing them to understand the complexities associated with biological research and data collection. These instruments have been used to support research in the PI&rsquo;s laboratory and in the laboratories of other BSC faculty, including Dr. Wayne Shew of the Department of Biology and Dr. Kate Hayden of the Department of Chemistry and Physics, benefiting a number of biology and chemistry research students. In addition, equipment purchased through this grant has also impacted students through integration into course-based research in biology courses at BSC, including Introductory Cell and Molecular Biology and Advanced Cell Biology, which together enroll approximately 100 students each year. Over the last 4 years, the Licor Odyssey FC has been used to visualize DNA and analyze protein expression by hundreds of students enrolled in these courses.</p> <p>With the support of this grant, the PI has developed a Responsible Conduct of Research workshop that impacted approximately 60 summer research students engaged in research in various disciplines in the natural sciences over the last 4 years. Thus, funding from this grant has promoted a broader culture of undergraduate research and ethical conduct at Birmingham-Southern College.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 10/26/2017<br>      Modified by: Melanie&nbsp;Styers</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Intellectual Merit:  The results of this project have yielded important new insights into the mechanisms that regulate membrane transport and organellar homeostasis in fission yeast; these studies will inform future studies in mammalian systems. Our work has begun to clarify the distinct membrane transport pathways regulated by the sec71p and sec72p proteins, yeast homologs of the mammalian BIG1 and BIG2 proteins. Specifically, our results suggest that sec71p and sec72p regulate two distinct pathways that transport proteins and lipids to the vacuole. One pathway traffics proteins directly from the Golgi apparatus to the vacuole, while the second transits the endosome en route to the vacuole. Since BIG1 and BIG2 are known to play key roles in mammalian development, including disorders of the central nervous system such as autosomal recessive periventricular heterotopia with microcephaly, these studies may help us to identify new brain-specific cargo proteins trafficked along these pathways, as well as to better understand the general membrane trafficking mechanisms that underlie human development.  In addition to understanding these vacuolar trafficking pathways, in exploring regulators of sec71p and sec72p function, we identified the yeast protein ypt4p, a homolog of the mammalian Rab4 protein, as a regulator of vacuole size and homeostasis. We found that cells lacking either ypt4 or the Chediak-Higashi Syndrome 1 (CHS1/LYST) homolog lvs1 possessed enlarged vacuoles. CHS is a human syndrome characterized by recurrent infections, albinism, and peripheral neuropathy. Our results demonstrate that overexpression of lvs1p reverses vacuole enlargement in ypt4? cells, implicating lvs1p as a regulator of vacuolar fission that acts downstream of ypt4p. This study was published this year in the journal Cellular Logistics, and a number of the students supported by NSF funding were authors on the paper.  In addition to this publication, findings from this study were also disseminated through 12 presentations by the PI and her students at the American Society for Cell Biology Annual Meeting and the Southeast Regional Yeast Meeting over this time period. In addition, each student presented his or her work on campus through BSC?s summer research seminar and poster session or Natural Sciences Senior Conference.     Broader Impacts:  Funding from this grant has impacted education and workforce development at BSC in three major ways: 1) by supporting the training of undergraduate student researchers, 2) by supporting the institutional infrastructure for research, and 3) by supporting training in the Responsible Conduct of Research.  This grant has supported the training of 23 undergraduate research students in the Styers laboratory, including 12 women and 5 students from underrepresented minorities. Exposure of undergraduates to scientific research will increase their competitiveness when applying for employment or for graduate or professional school. As a result of this educational experience, we anticipate that many of these students will go on to further training in STEM fields, thus enhancing our scientific workforce. Already, of the 18 senior research students who contributed to this project, 2 are enrolled in Ph.D. programs, 6 are in medical school, 1 is in engineering school, 3 are training for allied health careers, 3 are working in academic or for-profit research, and 2 are applying to graduate or professional programs. Exposure to authentic research at the undergraduate level has both excited these students for further study and helped them to develop the critical thinking and scientific reasoning skills needed to undertake the challenges associated with advanced training or joining the workforce.  Funds from this proposal also supported the purchase of a Zeiss LSM 410 confocal microscope and a Licor Odyssey FC instrument that have contributed to the infrastructure for undergraduate research at Birmingham-Southern College. Acquisition of these instruments has provided hands-on experience with cutting-edge scientific technologies in a research-based setting for undergraduate students, allowing them to understand the complexities associated with biological research and data collection. These instruments have been used to support research in the PI?s laboratory and in the laboratories of other BSC faculty, including Dr. Wayne Shew of the Department of Biology and Dr. Kate Hayden of the Department of Chemistry and Physics, benefiting a number of biology and chemistry research students. In addition, equipment purchased through this grant has also impacted students through integration into course-based research in biology courses at BSC, including Introductory Cell and Molecular Biology and Advanced Cell Biology, which together enroll approximately 100 students each year. Over the last 4 years, the Licor Odyssey FC has been used to visualize DNA and analyze protein expression by hundreds of students enrolled in these courses.  With the support of this grant, the PI has developed a Responsible Conduct of Research workshop that impacted approximately 60 summer research students engaged in research in various disciplines in the natural sciences over the last 4 years. Thus, funding from this grant has promoted a broader culture of undergraduate research and ethical conduct at Birmingham-Southern College.       Last Modified: 10/26/2017       Submitted by: Melanie Styers]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
