<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>CPS: Synergy: Collaborative Research: Thermal-Aware Management of Cyber-Physical Systems</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>10/01/2013</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>09/30/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>539999.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>539999</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>05050000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>CSE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CNS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Computer and Network Systems</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>David Corman</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>dcorman@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032928754</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Processors in cyber-physical systems are increasingly being used in applications where they must operate in harsh ambient conditions and a computational workload which can lead to high chip temperatures.  Examples include cars, robots, aircraft and spacecraft.  High operating temperatures accelerate the aging of the chips, thus increasing transient and permanent failure rates. Current ways to deal with this mostly turn off the processor core or drastically slow it down when some part of it is seen to exceed a given temperature threshold.  However, this pass/fail approach ignores the fact that (a) processors experience accelerated aging due to high temperatures, even if these are below the threshold, and (b) while deadlines are a constraint for real-time tasks to keep the controlled plant in the allowed state space, the actual controller response times that will increase if the voltage or frequency is lowered (to cool down the chip) are what determine the controlled plant performance.  Existing approaches also fail to exploit the tradeoff between controller reliability (affected by its temperature history) and the performance of the plant.  This project addresses these issues.   Load-shaping algorithms are being devised to manage thermal stresses while ensuring appropriate levels of control quality.  Such actions include task migration, changing execution speed, selecting an alternative algorithm or software implementation of control functions, and terminating prematurely optional portions of iterative tasks. Validation platforms for this project include automobiles and unmanned aerial vehicles.  These platforms have been chosen based on both their importance to society and the significant technical challenges they pose.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;With CPS becoming ever more important in our lives and businesses, this project which will make CPS controllers more reliable and/or economical has broad potential social and economic impacts. Collaboration with General Motors promotes transition of the new technology to industry. The project includes activities to introduce students to thermal control in computing, in courses spanning high-school, undergraduate and graduate curricula.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>09/19/2013</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/29/2018</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.070</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1329702</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Kang</FirstName>
<LastName>Shin</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>G</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Kang G Shin</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>kgshin@eecs.umich.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>7347630391</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000435838</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/19/2013</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Ella</FirstName>
<LastName>Atkins</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>M</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Ella M Atkins</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>ematkins@umich.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>7346157456</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000247733</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/19/2013</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Shige</FirstName>
<LastName>Wang</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Shige Wang</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>shige.wang@gm.com</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>7346268922</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000525202</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>11/01/2013</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Regents of the University of Michigan - Ann Arbor</Name>
<CityName>Ann Arbor</CityName>
<ZipCode>481091274</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>7347636438</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>3003 South State St. Room 1062</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Michigan</StateName>
<StateCode>MI</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>12</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MI12</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>073133571</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>REGENTS OF THE UNIVERSITY OF MICHIGAN</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>073133571</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Michigan Ann Arbor]]></Name>
<CityName>Ann Arbor</CityName>
<StateCode>MI</StateCode>
<ZipCode>481092121</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[2260 Hayward Street]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Michigan</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>12</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MI12</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1714</Code>
<Text>Special Projects - CNS</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7918</Code>
<Text>CYBER-PHYSICAL SYSTEMS (CPS)</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0113</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2013~539999</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><span>Multicore chips are increasingly used in cyber-physical&nbsp;</span>systems (CPSs) where they must operate in harsh ambient conditions and a computational workload which can lead to high chip temperatures. Examples include cars, robots, and drones.&nbsp; High operating temperatures accelerate the aging of the chips, resulting in increasing transient and permanent failure rates. &nbsp;</p> <p>Common ways to deal with this mostly turn off the core or drastically slow it down when some part of it is seen to exceed a given temperature limit. However, this pass-fail approach ignores the fact that (a) processors experience accelerated aging due to high temperatures, even if these are below the threshold, and (b) while deadlines are a constraint for real-time tasks to keep the controlled plant in the allowed state-space, the actual controller response times---that will increase if the operating voltage/frequency is lowered (to cool down the chip)---are the ones that determine the controlled plant performance.&nbsp; Existing approaches fail to exploit the tradeoff between controller reliability (influenced by its temperature history) and the plant's performance. &nbsp;</p> <p><span>This project has addressed these issues by devising load-shaping algorithms to&nbsp;</span>manage thermal stresses while ensuring appropriate levels of control quality.&nbsp; Load-shaping actions include task migration, changing execution speed, inserting idle periods, selecting an alternative algorithm or software implementation of control functions, and terminating prematurely optional portions, if any, of iterative tasks.</p> <p><span>The results of this&nbsp;</span>project not only make significant scientific advance but also improve the reliability, and hence the safety of CPS controllers. CPS, as originally intended, covers areas which require high reliability but which are extremely cost-sensitive (e.g., automotive CPSs).&nbsp; This project has made an important stride in these application areas.</p> <p>This project has made many (in)tagible contributions in transitioning &nbsp;the research results to industry via close collaboration with an industry partner, and also to education by introducing new materials of combining thermal and timing aspects in a graduate level course and term projects. It also recurited, trained and dispatched two excellent graduate students, one to industry and the other to academia.&nbsp;</p> <p><span><br /></span></p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 12/31/2019<br>      Modified by: Kang&nbsp;G&nbsp;Shin</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Multicore chips are increasingly used in cyber-physical systems (CPSs) where they must operate in harsh ambient conditions and a computational workload which can lead to high chip temperatures. Examples include cars, robots, and drones.  High operating temperatures accelerate the aging of the chips, resulting in increasing transient and permanent failure rates.    Common ways to deal with this mostly turn off the core or drastically slow it down when some part of it is seen to exceed a given temperature limit. However, this pass-fail approach ignores the fact that (a) processors experience accelerated aging due to high temperatures, even if these are below the threshold, and (b) while deadlines are a constraint for real-time tasks to keep the controlled plant in the allowed state-space, the actual controller response times---that will increase if the operating voltage/frequency is lowered (to cool down the chip)---are the ones that determine the controlled plant performance.  Existing approaches fail to exploit the tradeoff between controller reliability (influenced by its temperature history) and the plant's performance.    This project has addressed these issues by devising load-shaping algorithms to manage thermal stresses while ensuring appropriate levels of control quality.  Load-shaping actions include task migration, changing execution speed, inserting idle periods, selecting an alternative algorithm or software implementation of control functions, and terminating prematurely optional portions, if any, of iterative tasks.  The results of this project not only make significant scientific advance but also improve the reliability, and hence the safety of CPS controllers. CPS, as originally intended, covers areas which require high reliability but which are extremely cost-sensitive (e.g., automotive CPSs).  This project has made an important stride in these application areas.  This project has made many (in)tagible contributions in transitioning  the research results to industry via close collaboration with an industry partner, and also to education by introducing new materials of combining thermal and timing aspects in a graduate level course and term projects. It also recurited, trained and dispatched two excellent graduate students, one to industry and the other to academia.                 Last Modified: 12/31/2019       Submitted by: Kang G Shin]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
