<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>A Queueing Framework for Synthetic Circuits in E. coli</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2013</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>961252.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>961252</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>08070700</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>BIO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>MCB</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Molecular and Cellular Bioscience</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Edward Crane</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Intellectual Merit: Biological cells can cope with processing bottlenecks and also leverage the dynamics of bottlenecks to robustly control cellular behavior. This realization prompts a re-evaluation of the fundamental design principles believed to govern biological circuits. This project will investigate synthetic and native circuits in E. coli that are known to experience bottlenecks stemming from the competition of basic cellular components (created, modified, or degraded) for the shared molecular machinery. The experimental data combined with the theoretical predictions will allow the development and validation of queueing theoretical principles relevant to biological systems. Queueing theory is commonly applied to resolve performance limitations in traffic and communications systems. Fluorescence microscopy, microfluidics, and synthetic biology will be combined with quantitative modeling to probe protein degradative mechanisms and stress response pathways in terms of queueing theory in E. coli. Successful accomplishment of this project will lead to effective strategies for the synthesis and understanding of biological circuits that either avoid or exploit processing bottlenecks to perform specific tasks. The successful demonstration of the biological queueing theory is likely to impact also the more traditional disciplines, including telecommunication networks, call centers and transportation systems.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Broader Impacts: Part of this project will lead to the construction of new content for elementary school STEM education with a specific emphasis on the interdisciplinary aspect of science. This will be done largely through close collaboration with Kids' Tech University (KTU), a successful elementary school program at Virginia Tech with the single goal to create "the future workforce in science, technology, engineering, and mathematics (STEM) by sparking kids' interest in these fields." This collaboration will result in the generation, presentation, and distribution of interactive booths to illustrate interdisciplinary phenomena related to this project. Graduate and undergraduate students will be mentored in service learning to ensure effective outreach and to provide these students with teaching experience.  Undergraduates will be supported to construct modules for Virtual KTU, which freely provides interactive web-based demonstrations of STEM topics to students of all ages and educators.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/30/2013</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/30/2013</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.074</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1330180</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Kristy</FirstName>
<LastName>Collins</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Kristy Collins</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>kdivitto@vt.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5402311389</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000507353</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/30/2013</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>William</FirstName>
<LastName>Mather</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>H</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>William H Mather</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>wmather@vt.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>4042100278</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000627095</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/30/2013</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University</Name>
<CityName>BLACKSBURG</CityName>
<ZipCode>240610001</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5402315281</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>Sponsored Programs 0170</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[300 Turner Street NW, Suite 4200]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Virginia</StateName>
<StateCode>VA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>09</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>VA09</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>003137015</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>VIRGINIA POLYTECHNIC INSTITUTE AND STATE UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>003137015</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University]]></Name>
<CityName>Blacksburg</CityName>
<StateCode>VA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>240603580</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[1880 Pratt Drive]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Virginia</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>09</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>VA09</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1491</Code>
<Text>Cellular &amp; Biochem Engineering</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7275</Code>
<Text>Cross-BIO Activities</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>144E</Code>
<Text>Synthetic biology</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1757</Code>
<Text>Quantitative sys bio and biotech</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7465</Code>
<Text>NANOSCALE BIO CORE</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8007</Code>
<Text>BioMaPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9178</Code>
<Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9179</Code>
<Text>GRADUATE INVOLVEMENT</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0113</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2013~961252</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Queueing theory is a mathematical framework that describes much of our everyday life, whether we are waiting in line to receive our drivers license or on hold with our local internet service provider.&nbsp; NSF Award 1330180 funded a project that sought to translate the basic idea of waiting in line to a deeper understanding of natural and man-made biological circuits in the model bacterium E. coli, especially with respect to how the queueing of molecules to processing (often degradation) machinery can lead to pronounced coupling between seemingly independent biological circuits.&nbsp; These efforts focused on E. coli, but the generality of the framework allows our results to be extended to other systems such as mammalian cells.<br /><br />The intellectual impact of this award appeared in both theoretical and experimental realms.&nbsp; Our theoretical understanding of queueing theory in the context of biological networks was advanced by exact mathematical results and intensive computer simulations for complex queueing networks, which as a whole provided us with a solid foundation for how coupling and strong correlation between different parts of a large network can readily arise due to queueing phenomena, especially near the queueing tipping point (when "servers" can barely keep up with the demand for "service").&nbsp; We complemented the theoretical studies with experimental studies of synthetic (man-made) gene networks in E. coli, with which we demonstrated that queueing theory leads to verified predictions in complex circuits.&nbsp; Furthermore, we developed a new experimental library of protein degradation tags that allow us to tune the coupling between networks to be either strong or weak - this capability was absent or at best limited at the start of the award.&nbsp; By the end of this award, we had discovered and began to investigate how queueing theory could lead to a revision of our basic understanding of bacterial persistence, which is one of the major phenomena behind chronic infections and antibiotic resistance.&nbsp; Our work was published in highly visible scientific journals and presented in numerous professional conferences.<br /><br />The broader impacts of this award cannot be localized to the primary place of work (Blacksburg, VA).&nbsp; NSF funding to the outreach program (Kids' Tech University) provided valuable on-site exposure to science and technology for hundreds of children from surrounding states for each year of the award.&nbsp; The online component of this program (Virtual Kids' Tech University) had undergraduates develop and publish online games to help convey the scientific principles of our work to a young audience, and these products are now freely available worldwide.&nbsp; Professional development of the future workforce was ensured through the completion of two doctoral theses (both now in scientific jobs), the training of one postdoctoral scholar (now a faculty member), and the training of numerous undergraduate and graduate students.&nbsp; Two undergraduates even appeared as authors on scientific publications!&nbsp; Finally, we reiterate that our scientific results are expected to be far-reaching beyond the scope of our own work, since queueing networks are expected to appear as central elements in all organisms.<br /><br /><br /></p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 10/29/2017<br>      Modified by: William&nbsp;H&nbsp;Mather</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Queueing theory is a mathematical framework that describes much of our everyday life, whether we are waiting in line to receive our drivers license or on hold with our local internet service provider.  NSF Award 1330180 funded a project that sought to translate the basic idea of waiting in line to a deeper understanding of natural and man-made biological circuits in the model bacterium E. coli, especially with respect to how the queueing of molecules to processing (often degradation) machinery can lead to pronounced coupling between seemingly independent biological circuits.  These efforts focused on E. coli, but the generality of the framework allows our results to be extended to other systems such as mammalian cells.  The intellectual impact of this award appeared in both theoretical and experimental realms.  Our theoretical understanding of queueing theory in the context of biological networks was advanced by exact mathematical results and intensive computer simulations for complex queueing networks, which as a whole provided us with a solid foundation for how coupling and strong correlation between different parts of a large network can readily arise due to queueing phenomena, especially near the queueing tipping point (when "servers" can barely keep up with the demand for "service").  We complemented the theoretical studies with experimental studies of synthetic (man-made) gene networks in E. coli, with which we demonstrated that queueing theory leads to verified predictions in complex circuits.  Furthermore, we developed a new experimental library of protein degradation tags that allow us to tune the coupling between networks to be either strong or weak - this capability was absent or at best limited at the start of the award.  By the end of this award, we had discovered and began to investigate how queueing theory could lead to a revision of our basic understanding of bacterial persistence, which is one of the major phenomena behind chronic infections and antibiotic resistance.  Our work was published in highly visible scientific journals and presented in numerous professional conferences.  The broader impacts of this award cannot be localized to the primary place of work (Blacksburg, VA).  NSF funding to the outreach program (Kids' Tech University) provided valuable on-site exposure to science and technology for hundreds of children from surrounding states for each year of the award.  The online component of this program (Virtual Kids' Tech University) had undergraduates develop and publish online games to help convey the scientific principles of our work to a young audience, and these products are now freely available worldwide.  Professional development of the future workforce was ensured through the completion of two doctoral theses (both now in scientific jobs), the training of one postdoctoral scholar (now a faculty member), and the training of numerous undergraduate and graduate students.  Two undergraduates even appeared as authors on scientific publications!  Finally, we reiterate that our scientific results are expected to be far-reaching beyond the scope of our own work, since queueing networks are expected to appear as central elements in all organisms.          Last Modified: 10/29/2017       Submitted by: William H Mather]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
