<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>The Bacterial Nucleotide Excision Repair Pathway: Structure and Mechanism</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>03/01/2014</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>02/28/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>510000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>510000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>08070100</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>BIO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>MCB</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Molecular and Cellular Bioscience</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Karen Cone</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>kccone@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924967</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Intellectual Merit:  Understanding the biochemical pathways associated with how genes and genomes are inherited, and changed, remains an urgent priority. The goal of this work is to gain structure-based understanding of one such pathway in bacteria, e.g., nucleotide excision repair (NER) of DNA damage induced by exposure to ultraviolet light. The first steps of bacterial NER are performed by three proteins, UvrA, UvrB, and UvrC, which associate into several dynamic multi-protein complexes as repair proceeds. The UvrA-UvrB ensemble scans the genome, distinguishing lesion-containing damaged DNA from native, and, then, cooperates with the UvrC nuclease and other factors to repair the damage. This work will test novel hypotheses for three incompletely understood mechanisms of NER: a) discrimination of native from damaged, b) ATP/ADP dynamics during NER, and c) localization of UvrB to the lesion. This study takes a multi-disciplinary approach, integrating structural, biochemical, single-molecule, and biophysical strategies to understand relationships between the structure, function, and dynamics of relevant macromolecules as the genome is scanned for lesions. Structure-based analyses of genetic mechanisms during NER will provide deeper insights into the connections between DNA repair, DNA replication, inheritance, and transcription. More broadly, analysis of the relationship between shape-based recognition of DNA, proposed by the PI as a mechanism for discriminating damaged and native DNA, and protein conformational changes will contribute to a comprehensive understanding of fundamental principles that underlie the way that DNA is recognized by proteins in biological systems. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Broader Impacts: One of the central challenges for science education is how to impart quantitative skills to younger colleagues. The PI approaches this problem by using research on DNA repair, a fundamental biological process, as a platform to teach such skills. This project builds on the PI's past efforts at Harvard University, which now continue at City College of New York. CCNY is a public Ph.D.-granting institution that attracts undergraduate/doctoral students from diverse socioeconomic strata, and ethnic and racial backgrounds. Towards advancing education in science, technology, engineering and mathematics (STEM), the PI will teach two courses at CCNY, into which the described research will be integrated, and which will impact ~100 undergraduate/doctoral students. In addition, in partnership with The Urban Assembly, the PI will perform educational outreach in the New York Public School system, which will include meetings with students (grades 6-12), and collaborations with teachers on lesson plans. The science performed in the PI's group is multi-disciplinary and involves close collaborations between several research groups. The PI actively mentors post-docs, and, they, in turn, teach and mentor junior colleagues. The results of the research will be published in peer-reviewed journals. Research materials will be made available to the scientific community in several ways, including depositions to the Protein Data Bank.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>02/18/2014</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>03/07/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.074</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1330528</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>David</FirstName>
<LastName>Jeruzalmi</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>David Jeruzalmi</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>dj@ccny.cuny.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2126506062</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000270461</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>02/18/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>CUNY City College</Name>
<CityName>New York</CityName>
<ZipCode>100319101</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2126505418</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>Convent Ave at 138th St</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>13</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NY13</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>603503991</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>RESEARCH FOUNDATION OF THE CITY UNIVERSITY OF NEW YORK</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>073268849</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[CUNY City College]]></Name>
<CityName>New York</CityName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<ZipCode>100319101</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[Convent Ave at 138th St]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>13</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NY13</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1112</Code>
<Text>Genetic Mechanisms</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7465</Code>
<Text>NANOSCALE BIO CORE</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9178</Code>
<Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9179</Code>
<Text>GRADUATE INVOLVEMENT</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0114</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0115</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0116</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~170000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2015~170000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2016~170000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><div class="page" title="Page 1"> <div class="layoutArea"> <div class="column"> <p><span>The goal of this work is a structure-based understanding of nucleotide excision repair (NER) in bacteria. The first steps of NER are performed by three proteins: UvrA, UvrB, and UvrC. The UvrA&bull;UvrB (AB) ensemble recognizes damaged DNA, and cooperates with UvrC and other factors to repair DNA. In prior work, we have developed a model that explains three incompletely understood mechanisms of NER: 1) discrimination of native from damaged DNA by UvrA, 2) the role of nucleotide dynamics in NER, and 3) localization of UvrB to the lesion. Below, we apply structural, biochemical, and physical biochemical methods to test this model.</span></p> <div class="page" title="Page 1"> <div class="layoutArea"> <div class="column"> <p><span>The specific aims/objectives of this study for the project period are:<br /></span></p> </div> </div> </div> <div class="page" title="Page 1"> <div class="layoutArea"> <div class="column"> <p><span>1) How does UvrA discriminate damaged from native DNA?&nbsp;</span><span>We have shown that UvrA adopts two structural states, designated open and closed, with significantly different DNA binding surfaces (open: wide and shallow, closed: narrow and deep). We propose that these states allow for damage recognition, and will use single-molecule fluorescence to determine if UvrA cycles between these states during discrimination. These studies will be complemented by biophysical and structural analyses to determine the fundamental basis of discrimination.</span></p> <p><span>2) How does UvrA change in structure in response to nucleotide?&nbsp;</span><span>Our hypothesis is that one of UvrA&rsquo;s two ATP binding sites, the proximal site, governs interactions between UvrA and UvrB, DNA, and that the second site, the distal site, is involved in opening and closing of UvrA. To better understand the role of ATP, we will determine structures of UvrA in various nucleotide states. The predicted unique properties of the open and closed states of UvrA will be analyzed via biochemical analysis of each state trapped by disulfide crosslinking</span><span>.&nbsp;</span><span>Mutant proteins will be used to understand how changes in nucleotide state impact the function of UvrA.</span></p> <p><span>3) How do UvrA and UvrB cooperate to process DNA damage?&nbsp;</span><span>Our hypothesis is that UvrA in the AB complex contacts lesion-DNA first, is then evicted, whereupon two copies of UvrB translocate and assemble a dimeric entity at the lesion. To understand this choreography, we will use biophysical methods to determine positions of UvrA and UvrB relative to the lesion. These studies will be complemented by X-ray structures of AB complexes on damaged DNA.</span></p> <div class="page" title="Page 7"> <div class="section"> <div class="layoutArea"> <div class="column"> <p><span>Our three peer-reviewed papers contributed to a better understanding of the molecular events associated with the early steps of nucleotide excision repair as mediated by the UvrA, UvrB, and UvrC proteins. In addition, o</span>ur collaborative work enabled routine single particle CryoEM sample and grid characterization by tomography.</p> <p>Four trainees contributed to the reported science, including, one high school student, one undergraduate student, one master's student, and one doctoral student.</p> <p>In addition to science, the PI partnered with four high schools in New York City to engage students (grades 9-12) in STEM. These are: 1) The Urban Assembly School for Wildlife Conservation (UASWC, Bronx, NY), 2) Hunter High School (Manhattan, NY), and 3) the A. Philip Randolph Campus High School (Manhattan, NY), and 4) The New Explorations into Science, Technology, and Math (NEST+M) High School (Manhattan, NY). Students in these high schools come from groups underrepresented in science. The PI&rsquo;s involvement consists of a) hosting high-school interns, b) visits for career days at high schools, c) tours of science facilities at CCNY, e) judging science fairs, and f) collaborations with teachers on course development.</p> <div class="page" title="Page 2"> <div class="section"> <div class="layoutArea"> <div class="column"> <p><span>The PI is a co-organizer of the New York Structural Biology Discussion Group. This group organizes two meetings each year (January and August) which bring together ~300 - 400 structural biologists from the New York City region for a day-long meeting.</span></p> <p><span>The PI, with colleagues at CCNY (Professors Christine Li, Biology and Professor Renata Miller, English), initiated a program titled &ldquo;Opportunities in Research and the Creative Arts&rdquo; (ORCA). The ORCA program promotes faculty-student engagement by bringing undergraduate research and creative works, from science to humanities to the arts, to parts of City College where such activity was previously unknown.</span></p> </div> </div> </div> </div> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> </div> </div> </div> </div> <p><span><br /></span></p> </div> </div> </div> <p>&nbsp;</p> </div> </div> </div> <div class="page" title="Page 1"> <div class="layoutArea"></div> </div> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 05/11/2019<br>      Modified by: David&nbsp;Jeruzalmi</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[    The goal of this work is a structure-based understanding of nucleotide excision repair (NER) in bacteria. The first steps of NER are performed by three proteins: UvrA, UvrB, and UvrC. The UvrA&bull;UvrB (AB) ensemble recognizes damaged DNA, and cooperates with UvrC and other factors to repair DNA. In prior work, we have developed a model that explains three incompletely understood mechanisms of NER: 1) discrimination of native from damaged DNA by UvrA, 2) the role of nucleotide dynamics in NER, and 3) localization of UvrB to the lesion. Below, we apply structural, biochemical, and physical biochemical methods to test this model.     The specific aims/objectives of this study for the project period are:         1) How does UvrA discriminate damaged from native DNA? We have shown that UvrA adopts two structural states, designated open and closed, with significantly different DNA binding surfaces (open: wide and shallow, closed: narrow and deep). We propose that these states allow for damage recognition, and will use single-molecule fluorescence to determine if UvrA cycles between these states during discrimination. These studies will be complemented by biophysical and structural analyses to determine the fundamental basis of discrimination.  2) How does UvrA change in structure in response to nucleotide? Our hypothesis is that one of UvrA?s two ATP binding sites, the proximal site, governs interactions between UvrA and UvrB, DNA, and that the second site, the distal site, is involved in opening and closing of UvrA. To better understand the role of ATP, we will determine structures of UvrA in various nucleotide states. The predicted unique properties of the open and closed states of UvrA will be analyzed via biochemical analysis of each state trapped by disulfide crosslinking. Mutant proteins will be used to understand how changes in nucleotide state impact the function of UvrA.  3) How do UvrA and UvrB cooperate to process DNA damage? Our hypothesis is that UvrA in the AB complex contacts lesion-DNA first, is then evicted, whereupon two copies of UvrB translocate and assemble a dimeric entity at the lesion. To understand this choreography, we will use biophysical methods to determine positions of UvrA and UvrB relative to the lesion. These studies will be complemented by X-ray structures of AB complexes on damaged DNA.      Our three peer-reviewed papers contributed to a better understanding of the molecular events associated with the early steps of nucleotide excision repair as mediated by the UvrA, UvrB, and UvrC proteins. In addition, our collaborative work enabled routine single particle CryoEM sample and grid characterization by tomography.  Four trainees contributed to the reported science, including, one high school student, one undergraduate student, one master's student, and one doctoral student.  In addition to science, the PI partnered with four high schools in New York City to engage students (grades 9-12) in STEM. These are: 1) The Urban Assembly School for Wildlife Conservation (UASWC, Bronx, NY), 2) Hunter High School (Manhattan, NY), and 3) the A. Philip Randolph Campus High School (Manhattan, NY), and 4) The New Explorations into Science, Technology, and Math (NEST+M) High School (Manhattan, NY). Students in these high schools come from groups underrepresented in science. The PI?s involvement consists of a) hosting high-school interns, b) visits for career days at high schools, c) tours of science facilities at CCNY, e) judging science fairs, and f) collaborations with teachers on course development.      The PI is a co-organizer of the New York Structural Biology Discussion Group. This group organizes two meetings each year (January and August) which bring together ~300 - 400 structural biologists from the New York City region for a day-long meeting.  The PI, with colleagues at CCNY (Professors Christine Li, Biology and Professor Renata Miller, English), initiated a program titled "Opportunities in Research and the Creative Arts" (ORCA). The ORCA program promotes faculty-student engagement by bringing undergraduate research and creative works, from science to humanities to the arts, to parts of City College where such activity was previously unknown.                                          Last Modified: 05/11/2019       Submitted by: David Jeruzalmi]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
