<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>SBIR Phase II:Statistical Inference for Advanced Entity Resolution</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2013</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>02/29/2016</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>500000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>623999</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07070000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>IIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Industrial Innovation &amp; Partnersh</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Peter Atherton</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>patherto@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032928772</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This Small Business Innovation Research (SBIR) Phase II project aims to make it possible to do a better job of integrating information about entities, such as people, companies, and products, extracted from heterogeneous data sources. This integration problem can be challenging when different formats and terminology are used to describe the same entity. This problem can be addressed by a statistical learning approach that allows a system to estimate the probability of a match between entity references, rather than computing a score based on ad-hoc rules or weights.  The research focuses on refinements to this statistical learning approach that will enable a system to handle diverse types of real-world data.  Because the approach is based on sound statistical principles and uses evidence compiled from large datasets, it can produce more accurate results than existing commercial methods. Moreover, these advantages are amplified when handling data that that has highly variable, missing or noisy attributes, such as data extracted from websites.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The broader impact of this project lies in enabling enterprises to perform more accurate and reliable data integration.  Today, enterprises often have difficulty utilizing data extracted from unstructured or semi-structured source because the extracted data is noisy and difficult to integrate. This capability is critical for some of the nation's largest companies and institutions. For instance, the technology being developed in this project will reduce the cost of integrating data from hospitals and health information providers. It also can help intelligence agencies do a better job of connecting the dots, when investigating companies and individuals, and help human resource managers do a better job of finding;and recruiting job candidates. Ultimately the technology resulting from this project will help many types of enterprises make better use of the growing amount of information accessible through the Web and private networks.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/20/2013</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/09/2015</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1330223</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Steven</FirstName>
<LastName>Minton</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>N</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Steven N Minton</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>steven.n.minton@gmail.com</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>3103839234</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000594499</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/20/2013</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>InferLink Corporation</Name>
<CityName>El Segundo</CityName>
<ZipCode>902452901</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>3103839234</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>326 Loma Vista Street</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>33</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CA33</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>053003017</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>INFERLINK CORPORATION</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[InferLink Corporation]]></Name>
<CityName>El Segundo</CityName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>902454929</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[2361 Rosecrans Ave, Suite 348]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>33</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CA33</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>5373</Code>
<Text>SBIR Phase II</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>116E</Code>
<Text>RESEARCH EXP FOR UNDERGRADS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>123E</Code>
<Text>CENTERS: ADVANCED MATERIALS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>132E</Code>
<Text>CENTERS: SENSING &amp; INFO SYS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>169E</Code>
<Text>SBIR Tech Enhan Partner (TECP)</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>5373</Code>
<Text>SMALL BUSINESS PHASE II</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7744</Code>
<Text>RAHSS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8033</Code>
<Text>Hardware Software Integration</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8240</Code>
<Text>SBIR/STTR CAP</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9231</Code>
<Text>SUPPL FOR UNDERGRAD RES ASSIST</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9251</Code>
<Text>REU SUPP-Res Exp for Ugrd Supp</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9261</Code>
<Text>RESRCH ASSIST-MINORITY H.S. ST</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0113</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0115</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2013~500000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2015~123999</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>This SBIR project focused on the developing a better probabilistic model of entity resolution for applications involving noisy, open-world domains. Entity Resolution is the problem of determining whether multiple observations refer to the same entity (a person, organization, product, etc.).&nbsp;&nbsp; The problem has broad applicability, since identifying whether one has seen an entity before is a critical capability for intelligent agents.&nbsp; Whether an &ldquo;observation&rdquo; is a sensory input, a text mention, or a database record, the same core issues are often relevant.</p> <p>There were several technical significant advances developed in the course of the project. First, we developed a better modeling methods for handling noisy data produced from text extraction systems, and showed that these techniques led to increased resolution accuracy using real world data.&nbsp; Second, we investigated accuracy issues due to uncertainty regarding attribute values, including relational data.&nbsp; One significant outcome was the development of a new approach for handling uncertainty due to rarely occurring values.&nbsp; In entity resolution applications rare values are important because they convey more information than commonly occurring values, and as a result, our technique was shown to significantly improve accuracy in these situations.&nbsp; Third, we developed an approach leading to improved entity resolution for applications involving foreign language data that require a mix of translation and transliteration, as is the case when resolving organization names.</p> <p>This project has also had commercial impact.&nbsp; One of the outcomes is a utility patent application, number 14/626,859, titled "Inferentially Matching Jobs to Job Candidates&rdquo;.&nbsp; This patent was assigned to a spinoff company that InferLink launched, Innotrieve, which has developed products based in part on this invention.&nbsp; The patent focuses on the use of machine learning to associate job titles and job skills, and using this information for matching. Given a knowledge base of job skills and titles, and their relationships, Innotrieve's software can determine that a &ldquo;software engineer,&rdquo; a &ldquo;developer&rdquo; and someone with the skills of &ldquo;agile development and Java&rdquo; all refer to people who program software for a living. Further, the system can then infer that if a job description is for a &ldquo;programmer&rdquo; who is proficient in &ldquo;C++&rdquo; and &ldquo;software engineering methods&rdquo; then all of those previous candidates are likely to be good fits.</p> <p>The enhanced entity resolution technology developed in this project was also deployed commercially by another recent InferLink spinoff company, Cytenna Corporation. Cytenna aggregates information from the Web about security vulnerabilities, and uses entity resolution as part of the aggregation process.&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 05/26/2016<br>      Modified by: Steven&nbsp;N&nbsp;Minton</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ This SBIR project focused on the developing a better probabilistic model of entity resolution for applications involving noisy, open-world domains. Entity Resolution is the problem of determining whether multiple observations refer to the same entity (a person, organization, product, etc.).   The problem has broad applicability, since identifying whether one has seen an entity before is a critical capability for intelligent agents.  Whether an "observation" is a sensory input, a text mention, or a database record, the same core issues are often relevant.  There were several technical significant advances developed in the course of the project. First, we developed a better modeling methods for handling noisy data produced from text extraction systems, and showed that these techniques led to increased resolution accuracy using real world data.  Second, we investigated accuracy issues due to uncertainty regarding attribute values, including relational data.  One significant outcome was the development of a new approach for handling uncertainty due to rarely occurring values.  In entity resolution applications rare values are important because they convey more information than commonly occurring values, and as a result, our technique was shown to significantly improve accuracy in these situations.  Third, we developed an approach leading to improved entity resolution for applications involving foreign language data that require a mix of translation and transliteration, as is the case when resolving organization names.  This project has also had commercial impact.  One of the outcomes is a utility patent application, number 14/626,859, titled "Inferentially Matching Jobs to Job Candidates".  This patent was assigned to a spinoff company that InferLink launched, Innotrieve, which has developed products based in part on this invention.  The patent focuses on the use of machine learning to associate job titles and job skills, and using this information for matching. Given a knowledge base of job skills and titles, and their relationships, Innotrieve's software can determine that a "software engineer," a "developer" and someone with the skills of "agile development and Java" all refer to people who program software for a living. Further, the system can then infer that if a job description is for a "programmer" who is proficient in "C++" and "software engineering methods" then all of those previous candidates are likely to be good fits.  The enhanced entity resolution technology developed in this project was also deployed commercially by another recent InferLink spinoff company, Cytenna Corporation. Cytenna aggregates information from the Web about security vulnerabilities, and uses entity resolution as part of the aggregation process.           Last Modified: 05/26/2016       Submitted by: Steven N Minton]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
