<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Preparing for a warmer future: Conformational ensembles, dynamics and interactions from variable temperature crystallography</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2013</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>660535.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>660535</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>08070400</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>BIO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>MCB</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Molecular and Cellular Bioscience</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Engin Serpersu</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>eserpers@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927124</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>An understanding of the 3D structure of proteins and other molecules of life is essential to understanding their function and to the design of new medicines. Most atomic-resolution protein structures are determined using X-ray crystallography.  But while proteins function at biological (generally, near room) temperature, in the last decade nearly all X-ray crystallography has been performed on protein crystals cooled to cryogenic temperatures, where many important details of structure and dynamics may be compromised. This project will explore the wealth of additional information that may be accessible using protein crystals with liquid solvent.  Structural data sets collected at temperatures between ~330 and 200 K will allow exploration of how protein conformational ensembles and energy landscapes evolve, and of the signatures of and interactions leading to cold denaturation. Ultra-fast and variable-rate cooling will be used to characterize timescales of large and/or highly correlated protein motions, and to better preserve room temperature structure for examination at 100 K. The project builds on recent developments in sample handling and data collection and in refinement and analysis tools, and aims to substantially extend these developments.  &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Broader Impacts&lt;br/&gt; This project will enable a broadening in the scope of crystallographic studies of proteins, and contribute to a comprehensive understanding of the relation between protein structure and function, relevant to the understanding biology and to the development of new biologically active compounds.  It builds on past efforts in fundamental studies and methods development that have led to commercial tools used by crystallographers worldwide. Undergraduate and graduate student researchers will receive cross-disciplinary training in advanced methods and will be critical in propagating these methods to the broader structural biology community. This research program is complemented by vigorous efforts in undergraduate introductory course curriculum reform aimed at improving the retention and subject mastery of life science and engineering students.  It is also complemented by a broad effort in STEM teacher recruiting and training and in institutional change that provides a model for how research-focused STEM departments can address critical teacher shortages in our middle and high schools.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/24/2013</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/17/2017</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.074</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1330685</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Robert</FirstName>
<LastName>Thorne</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>E</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Robert E Thorne</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>ret6@cornell.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6072556487</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000306272</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/24/2013</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Cornell University</Name>
<CityName>Ithaca</CityName>
<ZipCode>148502820</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6072555014</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>373 Pine Tree Road</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>23</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NY23</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>872612445</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>CORNELL UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>002254837</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Cornell University]]></Name>
<CityName>Ithaca</CityName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<ZipCode>148532501</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[529 Clark Hall]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>23</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NY23</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1144</Code>
<Text>Molecular Biophysics</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1144</Code>
<Text>BIOMOLECULAR SYSTEMS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7465</Code>
<Text>NANOSCALE BIO CORE</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9178</Code>
<Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9179</Code>
<Text>GRADUATE INVOLVEMENT</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0113</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2013~660535</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Proteins are key molecules of life. Their atomic structure and the resulting interactions with other molecules determines their function.&nbsp; Most protein structures have been determined by X-ray crystallography, performed using protein crystals cooled to T=100 K.&nbsp; However, cryocooled proteins cannot function, and cooling damages protein crystals, especially if ice forms within the large fraction of their volume occupied by solvent. &nbsp;Much could be learned through structural studies between room or biological temperature and the protein-solvent glass transition near 200 K, but rapid ice formation has prevented this.</p> <p>The primary goals of this project have been to understand what happens to protein and solvent within protein crystals when they are cooled, and to develop methods for studying protein conformational ensembles and energy landscapes versus temperature. Both solvent freezing temperatures and ice nucleation rates are strongly suppressed by nanoconfinement within protein crystals, so that protein structure can be probed in the presence of liquid solvent down to 200 K, even in crystals with 7 nm solvent cavities. &nbsp;Measurements on three proteins reveal a freeze-out of minority side-chain conformers, development of new conformers, and a reduction in harmonic thermal motions on cooling.&nbsp; The freeze-out of minority conformers occurs heterogeneously within the protein, indicating that it arises from the complex local energy landscape and is independent of the T~200 K glass transition. &nbsp;Comparison of the effects of dehydration and cooling on side chain conformations reveals strong similarities, highlighting the difficulty of separating intrinsic protein behavior from that arising from crystal packing interactions, and the need for measurements on high solvent content, weakly packed crystals.</p> <p>When internal ice forms in protein crystals, it exhibits extensive stacking disorder characteristic of growth within deeply supercooled solvent. &nbsp;A novel crystallography-based approach shows that only a fraction of the internal solvent crystallizes, and that solvent within a protein's first two hydration layers does not crystallize.&nbsp;</p> <p>On cooling, crystal disorder increases due to differential contraction of protein and solvent and the resulting solvent flows, and due to arrested relaxation of the protein's conformational ensemble toward its low-temperature equilibrium. &nbsp;When the internal solvent remains liquid at low temperature, slow relaxation of the protein's structure can lead to a reversal of solvent flows and dramatic improvements in crystal order.&nbsp; These protein structural relaxations reflect changes in protein-solvent interactions that underlie cold denaturation, and protein crystals allow these changes to be probed at much lower temperatures than is possible using proteins in solution. &nbsp;A novel measurement technique yielded the glass-phase densities of aqueous solutions of several common cryoprotectants. These allow quantitative estimates of internal solvent expansion and flows during cooling, and also of electron density contrast in cryocrystallography, cryoSAXS, and cryoEM.</p> <p>Experiments and analysis of radiation damage to protein crystals, caused by the illuminating X-rays, reveal complex modifications to experimentally determined structure factors that depend on the spatial distribution of irradiation and the data collection protocol.&nbsp; When these factors are accounted for, the underlying relation between diffracted intensity, wavevector, and dose can be determined, and this relation is quantitatively reproduced by a new model for radiation damage.</p> <p>Together, these results establish robust methods for maximizing the quality of structural information obtained in X-ray crystallography of proteins and for probing temperature-dependent protein conformational ensembles and energy landscapes.&nbsp; These methods will be particularly useful for &nbsp;crystals of membrane proteins and large complexes that have large solvent contents and large solvent cavities, for which conventional T=100 K data collection can be challenging.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 12/09/2018<br>      Modified by: Robert&nbsp;E&nbsp;Thorne</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Proteins are key molecules of life. Their atomic structure and the resulting interactions with other molecules determines their function.  Most protein structures have been determined by X-ray crystallography, performed using protein crystals cooled to T=100 K.  However, cryocooled proteins cannot function, and cooling damages protein crystals, especially if ice forms within the large fraction of their volume occupied by solvent.  Much could be learned through structural studies between room or biological temperature and the protein-solvent glass transition near 200 K, but rapid ice formation has prevented this.  The primary goals of this project have been to understand what happens to protein and solvent within protein crystals when they are cooled, and to develop methods for studying protein conformational ensembles and energy landscapes versus temperature. Both solvent freezing temperatures and ice nucleation rates are strongly suppressed by nanoconfinement within protein crystals, so that protein structure can be probed in the presence of liquid solvent down to 200 K, even in crystals with 7 nm solvent cavities.  Measurements on three proteins reveal a freeze-out of minority side-chain conformers, development of new conformers, and a reduction in harmonic thermal motions on cooling.  The freeze-out of minority conformers occurs heterogeneously within the protein, indicating that it arises from the complex local energy landscape and is independent of the T~200 K glass transition.  Comparison of the effects of dehydration and cooling on side chain conformations reveals strong similarities, highlighting the difficulty of separating intrinsic protein behavior from that arising from crystal packing interactions, and the need for measurements on high solvent content, weakly packed crystals.  When internal ice forms in protein crystals, it exhibits extensive stacking disorder characteristic of growth within deeply supercooled solvent.  A novel crystallography-based approach shows that only a fraction of the internal solvent crystallizes, and that solvent within a protein's first two hydration layers does not crystallize.   On cooling, crystal disorder increases due to differential contraction of protein and solvent and the resulting solvent flows, and due to arrested relaxation of the protein's conformational ensemble toward its low-temperature equilibrium.  When the internal solvent remains liquid at low temperature, slow relaxation of the protein's structure can lead to a reversal of solvent flows and dramatic improvements in crystal order.  These protein structural relaxations reflect changes in protein-solvent interactions that underlie cold denaturation, and protein crystals allow these changes to be probed at much lower temperatures than is possible using proteins in solution.  A novel measurement technique yielded the glass-phase densities of aqueous solutions of several common cryoprotectants. These allow quantitative estimates of internal solvent expansion and flows during cooling, and also of electron density contrast in cryocrystallography, cryoSAXS, and cryoEM.  Experiments and analysis of radiation damage to protein crystals, caused by the illuminating X-rays, reveal complex modifications to experimentally determined structure factors that depend on the spatial distribution of irradiation and the data collection protocol.  When these factors are accounted for, the underlying relation between diffracted intensity, wavevector, and dose can be determined, and this relation is quantitatively reproduced by a new model for radiation damage.  Together, these results establish robust methods for maximizing the quality of structural information obtained in X-ray crystallography of proteins and for probing temperature-dependent protein conformational ensembles and energy landscapes.  These methods will be particularly useful for  crystals of membrane proteins and large complexes that have large solvent contents and large solvent cavities, for which conventional T=100 K data collection can be challenging.          Last Modified: 12/09/2018       Submitted by: Robert E Thorne]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
