<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>SBIR Phase II:  Low-cost smart window film</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2013</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>01/31/2016</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>701228.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>841473</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07070000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>IIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Industrial Innovation &amp; Partnersh</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Steven Konsek</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>skonsek@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927021</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This Small Business Innovation Research Phase II project will develop "Low Cost Smart Window Film" that reduces building energy consumption by dynamically optimizing solar gain. Low cost roll to roll processing techniques will be used to create unique electrochromic layers. The novel electrochromic layers will be scaled-up and used to construct insulated glass windows. Systematic characterization of the electrochromic film stability to UV and high temperature exposure will be evaluated and their long term reliability performance will be improved to meet the requirements. Upon successful completion of the project, the electrochromic windows expect to achieve enhanced solar modulation at fast switching speeds and manufactured at 2-3x lower cost than the currently available smart windows.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The broader impact/commercial potential of this project pertains to residential and commercial buildings represent a prime opportunity to improve energy efficiency and sustainability worldwide. In the United States lighting and thermal management within buildings account for 20% of yearly energy consumption. The economic and environmental benefits of using electrochromic windows are clear: reducing one quad of energy use would yield an average savings of $10.6 billion, while eliminating about 21.5 gigawatts of power produced by fossil fuels and saving nearly 59 million metric tons of CO2 emissions.  It is estimated that the use electrochromic windows in building can achieve a 50% reduction in peak energy demand and a 30% reduction in overall energy use. Still, current electrochromic windows in the market have not reached their market potential due to their high cost.  Novel electrochromic windows are based on an innovative material system that increases performance while reducing production cost. Wide scale adoption of this technology will enhance market penetration for dynamic windows.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/29/2013</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/09/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1330833</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Damoder</FirstName>
<LastName>Reddy</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Damoder Reddy</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>damoder.reddy@argilinc.com</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>4088584808</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000620611</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/29/2013</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>ARGIL, INC.</Name>
<CityName>Los Gatos</CityName>
<ZipCode>950321910</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>4088584808</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>16457 West Mozart Ave.</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>18</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CA18</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>078459650</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>ARGIL, INC</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[ARGIL, INC.]]></Name>
<CityName>San Jose</CityName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>951381400</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[5941 Optical Court]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>19</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CA19</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>5373</Code>
<Text>SBIR Phase II</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>094E</Code>
<Text>Optoelectronic devices</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>123E</Code>
<Text>CENTERS: ADVANCED MATERIALS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>169E</Code>
<Text>SBIR Tech Enhan Partner (TECP)</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>5373</Code>
<Text>SMALL BUSINESS PHASE II</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8021</Code>
<Text>Materials Engineering</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0113</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0114</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2013~701228</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~140245</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>This Small Business Innovation Research project developed<br />&ldquo;Low Cost Smart Window Coating&rdquo; that reduces building energy consumption by dynamically optimizing solar gain. Scalable solution processed techniques were used to create unique low cost electrochromic layers. The novel electrochromic layers were examined for compatibility and performance then subsequently used to construct solid state energy efficient electrochromic window glass. Systematic characterization of the solid state electrochromic devices lead to the successful fabrication of electrochromic window glass that achieved enhanced solar modulation at fast switching speeds.&nbsp; Argil developed low cost smart window film which meets many of the customer requirements for an architectural&nbsp;smart window product.&nbsp;Scaled up electrochromic polymer to 10kg level and developed roll to roll coating from a solution.&nbsp; Smart window film developed during this research can be produced at 3-5x lower cost than the commercial products available in the market today. Achieved neutral grey color in the&nbsp;clear state and dark state &ndash; a rare achievement for a smart window&nbsp;film. Built several impressive prototypes such as 10&rdquo; x 30&rdquo;&nbsp;electrochromic film incorporated in a residential window</p> <p>The broader impact/commercial potential of this project pertains to<strong><span> </span></strong>residential<br />and commercial buildings represent a prime opportunity to improve energy<br />efficiency and sustainability worldwide. Currently, lighting and thermal<br />management within buildings account for 20% of the United State&rsquo;s<br />yearly energy consumption. The economic and environmental benefits of using electrochromic windows are clear: reducing one quad of energy use would yield an average savings of $10.6 billion, while eliminating about 21.5 gigawatts of power produced by fossil fuels and saving nearly 59 million metric tons of CO<sub><span style="font-size: x-small;">2</span></sub> emissions.&nbsp; It is estimated that the use electrochromic windows in building can achieve a 50% reduction in peak energy demand and a 30% reduction in overall energy use. Still, current electrochromic windows in the market have not reached their market potential due to their high cost.&nbsp; Novel electrochromic windows are based on an innovative design that increases performance while reducing production cost. Wide scale adoption of this unique technology will not only enhance market penetration for dynamic windows but establish a new benchmark for performance and cost.<em>&nbsp;</em></p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 03/14/2016<br>      Modified by: Damoder&nbsp;Reddy</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ This Small Business Innovation Research project developed "Low Cost Smart Window Coating" that reduces building energy consumption by dynamically optimizing solar gain. Scalable solution processed techniques were used to create unique low cost electrochromic layers. The novel electrochromic layers were examined for compatibility and performance then subsequently used to construct solid state energy efficient electrochromic window glass. Systematic characterization of the solid state electrochromic devices lead to the successful fabrication of electrochromic window glass that achieved enhanced solar modulation at fast switching speeds.  Argil developed low cost smart window film which meets many of the customer requirements for an architectural smart window product. Scaled up electrochromic polymer to 10kg level and developed roll to roll coating from a solution.  Smart window film developed during this research can be produced at 3-5x lower cost than the commercial products available in the market today. Achieved neutral grey color in the clear state and dark state &ndash; a rare achievement for a smart window film. Built several impressive prototypes such as 10" x 30" electrochromic film incorporated in a residential window  The broader impact/commercial potential of this project pertains to residential and commercial buildings represent a prime opportunity to improve energy efficiency and sustainability worldwide. Currently, lighting and thermal management within buildings account for 20% of the United StateÆs yearly energy consumption. The economic and environmental benefits of using electrochromic windows are clear: reducing one quad of energy use would yield an average savings of $10.6 billion, while eliminating about 21.5 gigawatts of power produced by fossil fuels and saving nearly 59 million metric tons of CO2 emissions.  It is estimated that the use electrochromic windows in building can achieve a 50% reduction in peak energy demand and a 30% reduction in overall energy use. Still, current electrochromic windows in the market have not reached their market potential due to their high cost.  Novel electrochromic windows are based on an innovative design that increases performance while reducing production cost. Wide scale adoption of this unique technology will not only enhance market penetration for dynamic windows but establish a new benchmark for performance and cost.           Last Modified: 03/14/2016       Submitted by: Damoder Reddy]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
