<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Role of the P Clusters and FeMo-Cofactors in Nitrogenase Catalysis</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2013</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>450377.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>450377</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>08070400</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>BIO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>MCB</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Molecular and Cellular Bioscience</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Engin Serpersu</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>eserpers@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927124</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The proposed work involves implementing a multidisciplinary approach using basic biochemistry, spectroscopy, and x-ray crystallography techniques to probe some of the key outstanding issues regarding the mechanism of the key enzyme in nitrogen fixation, nitrogenase. We will probe the hypothesis that the redox-dependent structural changes are key to modulating the midpoint potential and defining the role of the P cluster in gated intermolecular electron transfer. The combined use of key site-directed variants and a europium complex redox mediator will facilitate the capture of defined states of the enzyme relevant to the catalytic mechanism that are not possible to observe in the native state, and will answer questions regarding substrate binding to the FeMo-cofactor. Basic research on biological nitrogen fixation could contribute to less energy demanding and more environmentally sound mechanisms to meet the growing demands for fixed nitrogen associated with global population growth, as the availability of fixed nitrogen sources for plant growth is a limiting factor in global nutrition and the production of nitrogenous fertilizers is very energy demanding and can have negative environmental implications. Broader Impacts include student training and significant contributions to training K-12 teachers through the development of an online course on Agriculture and Energy along with other efforts aimed at teachers in remote rural areas that include tribal schools.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/24/2013</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/24/2013</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.074</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1330807</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Lance</FirstName>
<LastName>Seefeldt</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>C</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Lance C Seefeldt</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>seefeldt@cc.usu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>4357973964</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000455762</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/24/2013</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>John</FirstName>
<LastName>Peters</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>W</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>John W Peters</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>jw.peters@wsu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5093353412</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000362566</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/24/2013</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Montana State University</Name>
<CityName>BOZEMAN</CityName>
<ZipCode>597172470</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>4069942381</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>328 MONTANA HALL</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Montana</StateName>
<StateCode>MT</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>00</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MT00</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>625447982</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>MONTANA STATE UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>079602596</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Montana State University]]></Name>
<CityName>Bozeman</CityName>
<StateCode>MT</StateCode>
<ZipCode>597172470</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[309 Montana Hall]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Montana</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>00</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MT00</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1144</Code>
<Text>Molecular Biophysics</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1144</Code>
<Text>BIOMOLECULAR SYSTEMS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7465</Code>
<Text>NANOSCALE BIO CORE</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9179</Code>
<Text>GRADUATE INVOLVEMENT</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0113</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2013~450377</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The overall impact of<strong>&nbsp;</strong>research on biological nitrogen fixation goes far beyond the potential agronomic and economic impact on global plant productivity.&nbsp;&nbsp;The production of nitrogenous fertilizers is an energy demanding process requiring hydrogen typically produced from reforming fossil fuels and high-temperature and high-pressure conditions.&nbsp;&nbsp;In addition, the long-term application of nitrogenous fertilizers has the potential for long-term detrimental environmental and ecological implications.&nbsp;&nbsp;As the global population continues to increase, the demand for food and energy also increases.&nbsp;&nbsp;It is clear that the importance of having a fundamental knowledge of the intricacies of biological nitrogen fixation has the potential to offset the demand for fertilizer production.&nbsp;&nbsp;One of the most fascinating biochemical reactions, nitrogen fixation involves a multiple electron reduction and the activation of the strong nitrogen-nitrogen triple bond.&nbsp;&nbsp;Nitrogenase has been a difficult enzyme to characterize mechanistically and studies to date that have provided insights into various aspects of the mechanism have provided significant advancements in biochemical, structural, and computation methods.&nbsp;&nbsp;The complex two-component enzyme nitrogenase is an ideal model system for the study of general processes of metal-mediated catalysis, biological electron transfer, complex metal cluster assembly, protein-protein interactions, nucleotide-dependent conformational change, and signal transduction.&nbsp; This fascinating ambient condition reaction catalyzed by the nitrogenase biochemical system has profound implications for humanity. &nbsp;The current method for commercial nitrogen reduction consumes approximately 1-2% of the world's energy portfolio, and is an expensive and dangerous process.&nbsp; The ultimate aim of this basic research is to lay the foundation for the development of advanced bio-mimetic materials that could catalyze nitrogen fixation under less energy intensive conditions.&nbsp; Modeling and fabrication of these bio-inspired materials will be incumbent upon a more comprehensive understanding of the mechanistic fundamentals of this complex multi-component metalloreductase.&nbsp; The parallels drawn from this system also have profound impacts on medicine and drug development, as many disorders and pathologies are correlated to proteins that undergo ATP dependent conformational changes.</p> <p>This challenging project was aimed at capturing and structurally characterizing key intermediates of nitrogenase to provide insights into the catalytic mechanism. Exploiting recent insights how to stabilize intermediates in solution were exploited in crystals. Using a new technique we have been able to poise nitrogenase at different reduction potentials electrochemical in a solution of redox mediators. This allowed capturing a never short-lived intermediate in a metal cluster termed the P cluster and for the first time be able to characterize the progression of structural changes that promote the driving force for injection of electrons to the active site FeMo-cofactor. This is the first time that we know of where potentiometric redox titrations have been conducted on protein crystals thereby providing a significant technological advance. Additional work allowed the characterization of substrates at the active site Fe Mo-cofactor and the subsequent structural determination using x-ray diffraction methods. The work represents the first observation of substrate interactions at the nitrogenase active site providing significant insights into the catalytic mechanism. The importance of nitrogen fixation was a topic of teacher training in a &ldquo;Science Horizons&rdquo; summer training program where high school teachers from Montana High Schools including tribal high schools actively generate educational materials for the classroom in contemporary basic and applied science.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 11/14/2017<br>      Modified by: John&nbsp;W&nbsp;Peters</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The overall impact of research on biological nitrogen fixation goes far beyond the potential agronomic and economic impact on global plant productivity.  The production of nitrogenous fertilizers is an energy demanding process requiring hydrogen typically produced from reforming fossil fuels and high-temperature and high-pressure conditions.  In addition, the long-term application of nitrogenous fertilizers has the potential for long-term detrimental environmental and ecological implications.  As the global population continues to increase, the demand for food and energy also increases.  It is clear that the importance of having a fundamental knowledge of the intricacies of biological nitrogen fixation has the potential to offset the demand for fertilizer production.  One of the most fascinating biochemical reactions, nitrogen fixation involves a multiple electron reduction and the activation of the strong nitrogen-nitrogen triple bond.  Nitrogenase has been a difficult enzyme to characterize mechanistically and studies to date that have provided insights into various aspects of the mechanism have provided significant advancements in biochemical, structural, and computation methods.  The complex two-component enzyme nitrogenase is an ideal model system for the study of general processes of metal-mediated catalysis, biological electron transfer, complex metal cluster assembly, protein-protein interactions, nucleotide-dependent conformational change, and signal transduction.  This fascinating ambient condition reaction catalyzed by the nitrogenase biochemical system has profound implications for humanity.  The current method for commercial nitrogen reduction consumes approximately 1-2% of the world's energy portfolio, and is an expensive and dangerous process.  The ultimate aim of this basic research is to lay the foundation for the development of advanced bio-mimetic materials that could catalyze nitrogen fixation under less energy intensive conditions.  Modeling and fabrication of these bio-inspired materials will be incumbent upon a more comprehensive understanding of the mechanistic fundamentals of this complex multi-component metalloreductase.  The parallels drawn from this system also have profound impacts on medicine and drug development, as many disorders and pathologies are correlated to proteins that undergo ATP dependent conformational changes.  This challenging project was aimed at capturing and structurally characterizing key intermediates of nitrogenase to provide insights into the catalytic mechanism. Exploiting recent insights how to stabilize intermediates in solution were exploited in crystals. Using a new technique we have been able to poise nitrogenase at different reduction potentials electrochemical in a solution of redox mediators. This allowed capturing a never short-lived intermediate in a metal cluster termed the P cluster and for the first time be able to characterize the progression of structural changes that promote the driving force for injection of electrons to the active site FeMo-cofactor. This is the first time that we know of where potentiometric redox titrations have been conducted on protein crystals thereby providing a significant technological advance. Additional work allowed the characterization of substrates at the active site Fe Mo-cofactor and the subsequent structural determination using x-ray diffraction methods. The work represents the first observation of substrate interactions at the nitrogenase active site providing significant insights into the catalytic mechanism. The importance of nitrogen fixation was a topic of teacher training in a "Science Horizons" summer training program where high school teachers from Montana High Schools including tribal high schools actively generate educational materials for the classroom in contemporary basic and applied science.       Last Modified: 11/14/2017       Submitted by: John W Peters]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
