<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Standard Research: Global Governance and Science in Complex Regulatory Regimes</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/15/2013</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2016</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>298725.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>298725</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>04050000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>SBE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>SES</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Divn Of Social and Economic Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Frederick Kronz</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>fkronz@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927283</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Overview&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This STS research project is a study of policy and science; specifically, it will examine regulatory science in the governance arenas of biofuels and geo-engineering. Its primary goals are to produce generalizable knowledge about how science operates within complex (multi-level and multi-sector) regulatory frameworks for emerging technologies, and to conceptualize and evaluate the legitimacy of regulatory science within these evolving regimes. To obtain that knowledge, the PI will analyze legal documents (such as case law, litigation briefs, expert testimony, legislative history, and legal commentaries) and non-legal documents (including reports, media accounts, industry lobbying documents, and press releases). He will also conduct a series of semi-structured interviews with key actors involved in national and international policy related to sustainable biofuels and geo-engineering.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Intellectual Merit &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The results of this project will enrich existing accounts of the role of expertise in global governance and produce policy relevant ideas in the arenas of biofuels and geo-engineering. Global governance has largely moved away from international treaty structures to complex (pluralist and fragmented) treaty structures. In the complex context, regulatory science and diverse forms of technical reasoning move across levels of government, and they span the private and public sectors. Understanding what ideals of democratic governance mean in such contexts requires sharper theoretical tools, which the PI plans to develop by synthesizing intellectual approaches from STS and law; the resulting hybrid approach will facilitate a deeper understanding of the interrelated dimensions of legal jurisdiction, scientific authority, and democratic governance.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Broader Impacts&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project will serve to address an urgent need for good public policy on the governance of biofuels and geo-engineering by providing tangible ideas for improving the legitimacy of administrative process. It also promises to provide a more systematic understanding of science and democracy, which is expected to advance relevant academic fields; and it will provide useful resources for policymakers, including a deeper analytic and practical toolkit. Finally, the project will build human capital and infrastructure by training graduate students and a postdoctoral fellow, and strengthening academic and policy networks across nations.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>09/04/2013</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>09/30/2013</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.075</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1331256</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>David</FirstName>
<LastName>Winickoff</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>David Winickoff</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>winickoff@berkeley.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5106430319</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000105492</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/04/2013</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of California-Berkeley</Name>
<CityName>BERKELEY</CityName>
<ZipCode>947101749</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5106433891</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>Sponsored Projects Office</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[1608 Fourth Street, Suite 220]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>13</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CA13</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>124726725</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>REGENTS OF THE UNIVERSITY OF CALIFORNIA, THE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>071549000</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of California-Berkeley]]></Name>
<CityName>Berkeley</CityName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>947203114</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[130 Mulford Hall]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>13</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CA13</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7603</Code>
<Text>STS-Sci, Tech &amp; Society</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>8022</Code>
<Text>STAR Metrics</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>0000</Code>
<Text>UNASSIGNED</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8815</Code>
<Text>Studies of Policy Sci Eng Tech</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>OTHR</Code>
<Text>OTHER RESEARCH OR EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0113</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2013~298725</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>This project conducted a comparative study of the role of science and expertise in the governance of two areas of emerging technology: biofuels and geoengineering. The goals of this project were to produce knowledge about how science informs the regulation of emerging technologies in global governance and to evaluate the legitimacy of how science is used therein. &nbsp;Another goal was to provide policy-relevant ideas for the governance of biofuels and geoengineering. A further goal was to help train a new generation of policymakers and scholars in these areas.</p> <p>Previous academic work has examined the role of science in global governance, showing how the production and use of science in these settings have large social consequences for human lives. Today, great changes are occurring in global governance. In general, there is a movement from international treaties towards a mix of highly diverse and overlapping sets of laws, regulations and other norms.&nbsp; More needs to be known about how science and expertise should operate within the nested and overlapping governance arrangements that are common today.</p> <p>Spanning the fields of Science and Technology Studies and Political Science, this project broke new intellectual ground on these questions. In particular, the project introduced the new concept of &ldquo;epistemic jurisdiction&rdquo; that can help people interpret and explain how science is working in global governance. Epistemic jurisdiction refers to the power to produce or sanction technical knowledge for a given political community, topical arena or geographical territory. Epistemic jurisdiction is especially controversial in global governance because there few agreed sources of science advice for policy.&nbsp; It is a finding of this project that global regulatory actors &ndash; like those who set technical standards -- must compete for epistemic jurisdiction in a variety of ways. The project explored these dynamics in the arena of global sustainability standards for biofuels, and identified similar dynamics in the field of geoengineering. In order to produce global regulatory science, technical bodies must manage an array of conflicting imperatives &ndash; including scientific virtue, due process and the need to recruit adoptees to perpetuate the standards.&nbsp; At different levels of governance, those drafting technical standards struggle to balance loyalties to country, to company or constituency and to the larger project of internationalization.</p> <p>The project helped train one post-doctoral scholar in the field of political science, one graduate student in the field of science policy, and four undergraduates in the field of environmental policy.&nbsp; These students engaged in regular research meetings, helped develop an international workshop, and drafted research memoranda and articles. Also in this vein, one specific objective of the grant was to address the differential participation in science policy across the Global North and South. This was part of the project&rsquo;s effort to consider "legitimacy" as an object of study in global governance of geoengineering and biofuels. In July 2014, the project team organized and convened a workshop at U.C. Berkeley to explore this aspect of legitimacy among 45 mid-career leaders from the Global South in the field of sustainable development to explore attitudes and views on geoengineering research.</p> <p>Thus, project results respond to an urgent need for good public policy on the governance of biofuels and geoengineering. To this point, the results from the project have been published in top journals in the relevant fields, including <em>Social Studies of Science</em> and <em>Nature Climate Change</em>. Published work promises to help those designing processes and procedures in global governance to produce better regulatory science and better social outcomes. &nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 12/03/2016<br>      Modified by: David&nbsp;Winickoff</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ This project conducted a comparative study of the role of science and expertise in the governance of two areas of emerging technology: biofuels and geoengineering. The goals of this project were to produce knowledge about how science informs the regulation of emerging technologies in global governance and to evaluate the legitimacy of how science is used therein.  Another goal was to provide policy-relevant ideas for the governance of biofuels and geoengineering. A further goal was to help train a new generation of policymakers and scholars in these areas.  Previous academic work has examined the role of science in global governance, showing how the production and use of science in these settings have large social consequences for human lives. Today, great changes are occurring in global governance. In general, there is a movement from international treaties towards a mix of highly diverse and overlapping sets of laws, regulations and other norms.  More needs to be known about how science and expertise should operate within the nested and overlapping governance arrangements that are common today.  Spanning the fields of Science and Technology Studies and Political Science, this project broke new intellectual ground on these questions. In particular, the project introduced the new concept of "epistemic jurisdiction" that can help people interpret and explain how science is working in global governance. Epistemic jurisdiction refers to the power to produce or sanction technical knowledge for a given political community, topical arena or geographical territory. Epistemic jurisdiction is especially controversial in global governance because there few agreed sources of science advice for policy.  It is a finding of this project that global regulatory actors &ndash; like those who set technical standards -- must compete for epistemic jurisdiction in a variety of ways. The project explored these dynamics in the arena of global sustainability standards for biofuels, and identified similar dynamics in the field of geoengineering. In order to produce global regulatory science, technical bodies must manage an array of conflicting imperatives &ndash; including scientific virtue, due process and the need to recruit adoptees to perpetuate the standards.  At different levels of governance, those drafting technical standards struggle to balance loyalties to country, to company or constituency and to the larger project of internationalization.  The project helped train one post-doctoral scholar in the field of political science, one graduate student in the field of science policy, and four undergraduates in the field of environmental policy.  These students engaged in regular research meetings, helped develop an international workshop, and drafted research memoranda and articles. Also in this vein, one specific objective of the grant was to address the differential participation in science policy across the Global North and South. This was part of the project?s effort to consider "legitimacy" as an object of study in global governance of geoengineering and biofuels. In July 2014, the project team organized and convened a workshop at U.C. Berkeley to explore this aspect of legitimacy among 45 mid-career leaders from the Global South in the field of sustainable development to explore attitudes and views on geoengineering research.  Thus, project results respond to an urgent need for good public policy on the governance of biofuels and geoengineering. To this point, the results from the project have been published in top journals in the relevant fields, including Social Studies of Science and Nature Climate Change. Published work promises to help those designing processes and procedures in global governance to produce better regulatory science and better social outcomes.            Last Modified: 12/03/2016       Submitted by: David Winickoff]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
