<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Measuring Anisotropy in Fibrous Soft Materials by MR Imaging of Slow and Fast Shear Waves</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2013</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>429222.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>475222</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CMMI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Civil, Mechanical, &amp; Manufact Inn</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>kara peters</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The objectives of this research are to measure the direction-dependent, mechanical properties of fibrous soft materials, such as artificial tissue, muscle or white matter in the brain. The proposed approach is to use magnetic resonance imaging to visualize and measure the propagation of elastic waves in the material. The speed of wave propagation through a solid material depends on its stiffness, and in a fibrous material the stiffness depends on the direction of loading. By using magnetic resonance imaging to visualize shear waves, it is possible to estimate these mechanical properties without invasive procedures or destructive testing. This approach will be validated by applying it to measure mechanical properties of fibrin gels in which fiber alignment is produced by polymerizing the gel in a magnetic field. It will then be used to non-invasively characterize mechanical properties of the brain.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;If successful, the benefits of the research will include an improved ability to model and simulate the behavior of fibrous materials. It will enable accurate computer simulations of the mechanisms of traumatic brain injury and improved understanding of injury mechanics. Since white matter in the brain is particularly sensitive to mechanical deformation, the ability to model it correctly is extremely important to the design of protective devices and the development of therapeutic approaches. In addition, the proposed research may lead to new methods to monitor the condition of muscle, tendon, brain, or artificial tissue.  The engineered gels used in this project may also have medical applications as tissue surrogates or scaffolds for nerve growth. A broad benefit of the project is that high school and undergraduate engineering students will learn to apply state-of-the-art imaging methods to understand complex mechanical behavior of an important class of materials.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/29/2013</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>03/06/2017</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1332433</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Philip</FirstName>
<LastName>Bayly</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>V</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Philip V Bayly</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>pvb@me.wustl.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>3149356081</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000178467</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/29/2013</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Joel</FirstName>
<LastName>Garbow</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>R</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Joel R Garbow</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>garbow@wustl.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>3143629949</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000616134</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/29/2013</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Washington University</Name>
<CityName>Saint Louis</CityName>
<ZipCode>631304862</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>3147474134</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>CAMPUS BOX 1054</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[1 Brookings Drive]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Missouri</StateName>
<StateCode>MO</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MO01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>068552207</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>WASHINGTON UNIVERSITY, THE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>068552207</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Washington University]]></Name>
<CityName>St. Louis</CityName>
<StateCode>MO</StateCode>
<ZipCode>631304862</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Missouri</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MO01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1630</Code>
<Text>Mechanics of Materials and Str</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>022E</Code>
<Text>SOLID MECHANICS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>024E</Code>
<Text>MATERIALS DESIGN</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>027E</Code>
<Text>NANOMECHANICS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>116E</Code>
<Text>RESEARCH EXP FOR UNDERGRADS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8086</Code>
<Text>Natl Robotics Initiative (NRI)</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9131</Code>
<Text>CENTERS FOR RSCH EXCELL IN S&amp;T</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9161</Code>
<Text>SINGLE DIVISION/UNIVERSITY</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9178</Code>
<Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9231</Code>
<Text>SUPPL FOR UNDERGRAD RES ASSIST</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9251</Code>
<Text>REU SUPP-Res Exp for Ugrd Supp</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>AMPP</Code>
<Text>ADVANCED MATERIALS &amp; PROCESSING PROGRAM</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0113</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0114</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0115</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0116</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0117</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2013~429222</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~10000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2015~10000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2016~10000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2017~16000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Many biological tissues, like muscle or white matter in the brain, are composed of aligned fibers. As a result, the stiffness of the tissue, which determines how it responds to applied forces, depends on the direction of the loading. This directional dependence (&ldquo;anisotropy&rdquo;) may also be desirable in artificial biomaterials in order to replicate or improve upon the function of natural materials. It is important to be able to measure these properties non-destructively and non-invasively. Thus, the goal of the project was to develop a non-invasive method to measure the direction-dependent mechanical properties of fibrous soft tissues and biomaterials. To do so, the speeds of wave propagation were measured in these materials, in different directions, using a non-invasive imaging procedure, and used to estimate the material stiffness in corresponding orientations.</p> <p>In terms of intellectual merit, the study demonstrated that both &ldquo;slow&rdquo; (or &ldquo;pure transverse&rdquo;) and &ldquo;fast&rdquo; (or &ldquo;quasi-transverse&rdquo;) shear waves can be induced and imaged in fibrous soft tissues and biomaterials, using magnetic resonance elastography (MRE). &nbsp;These slow and fast shear waves were isolated by directional filtering, and their propagation speeds used to estimate anisotropic material parameters. Anisotropic wave propagation was demonstrated in muscle tissue, brain tissue, and a magnetically aligned fibrin gel. The study established that waves with multiple polarization and propagation directions relative to the dominant fiber axis must be measured in order to reliably estimate parameters.</p> <p>In terms of broader impact, students, both graduate and undergraduate, were involved in the project and learned research techniques at the interface of mechanical engineering, biophysics, and imaging. One graduate student, John Schmidt was supported by the project and plans to defend his PhD in Mechanical Engineering in November 2017. Seven undergraduate students (five female students, one under-represented minority student) participated in research on the project, all with support of REU supplements. The majority of the undergraduates attended national conferences and/or published technical papers. Thus this project provided significant benefits in terms of workforce development.&nbsp; One undergraduate student received 1<sup>st</sup> place in the undergraduate research poster competition at the national Summer Biomechanics, Bioengineering, and Biotransport Conference (SB3C).&nbsp; The principal investigator was recognized by his university for contributions to undergraduate research.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 10/04/2017<br>      Modified by: Philip&nbsp;V&nbsp;Bayly</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Image         </div> <div class="galControls onePhoto" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation onePhoto" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1332433/1332433_10255321_1507136392979_box_wave--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1332433/1332433_10255321_1507136392979_box_wave--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Figure 1."><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1332433/1332433_10255321_1507136392979_box_wave--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Figure 1."></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">(a) "Slow" and (b) "fast" shear waves in a fibrous material, showing fiber direction, a, polarization direction, m, and propagation direction, n.</div> <div class="imageCredit">D.J. Tweten et al. (2015), J Biomechanics 48(15):4002-9</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Philip&nbsp;V&nbsp;Bayly</div> <div class="imageTitle">Figure 1.</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Many biological tissues, like muscle or white matter in the brain, are composed of aligned fibers. As a result, the stiffness of the tissue, which determines how it responds to applied forces, depends on the direction of the loading. This directional dependence ("anisotropy") may also be desirable in artificial biomaterials in order to replicate or improve upon the function of natural materials. It is important to be able to measure these properties non-destructively and non-invasively. Thus, the goal of the project was to develop a non-invasive method to measure the direction-dependent mechanical properties of fibrous soft tissues and biomaterials. To do so, the speeds of wave propagation were measured in these materials, in different directions, using a non-invasive imaging procedure, and used to estimate the material stiffness in corresponding orientations.  In terms of intellectual merit, the study demonstrated that both "slow" (or "pure transverse") and "fast" (or "quasi-transverse") shear waves can be induced and imaged in fibrous soft tissues and biomaterials, using magnetic resonance elastography (MRE).  These slow and fast shear waves were isolated by directional filtering, and their propagation speeds used to estimate anisotropic material parameters. Anisotropic wave propagation was demonstrated in muscle tissue, brain tissue, and a magnetically aligned fibrin gel. The study established that waves with multiple polarization and propagation directions relative to the dominant fiber axis must be measured in order to reliably estimate parameters.  In terms of broader impact, students, both graduate and undergraduate, were involved in the project and learned research techniques at the interface of mechanical engineering, biophysics, and imaging. One graduate student, John Schmidt was supported by the project and plans to defend his PhD in Mechanical Engineering in November 2017. Seven undergraduate students (five female students, one under-represented minority student) participated in research on the project, all with support of REU supplements. The majority of the undergraduates attended national conferences and/or published technical papers. Thus this project provided significant benefits in terms of workforce development.  One undergraduate student received 1st place in the undergraduate research poster competition at the national Summer Biomechanics, Bioengineering, and Biotransport Conference (SB3C).  The principal investigator was recognized by his university for contributions to undergraduate research.          Last Modified: 10/04/2017       Submitted by: Philip V Bayly]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
