<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Integrated Hot-Phonon Harvesting Barriers in High-Power Circuit Devices</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2013</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>291175.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>291175</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07020000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CBET</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Chem, Bioeng, Env, &amp; Transp Sys</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Jose Lage</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>CBET 1332807&lt;br/&gt;PI: Massoud Kaviany (U. Michigan)&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The  proposed research aims to use (integrate) a novel hot phonon absorption barrier structure converting phonon energy to harvestable electric potential, in high-power electric circuits and devices. This electric potential barrier (barrier is formed by heterostructures, e.g., Al alloying, and its height matches optical phonon energy) allows only those electrons with high momentum/energy to pass through it, while the remaining electrons with lower energy will have a favorable phonon absorption condition. For the proposed example of GaN high electron mobility transistor, the expected reduction in the maximum operating temperature is as much as 40 degC at 5 W/mm Joule heating rate, and up to 20% of the phonons will be recycled corresponding to the same saving in power consumption (i.e., in-situ direct conversion of emitted phonons back to electric potential energy). The results are expected to also apply to light emitting diodes and other high-power electronics, and contribute to thermal management at atomic scale.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The use of a heterobarrier, or abrupt change in material composition, in a circuit allows electricity-generated heat to boost electric potential instead of draining efficiency. Using this architecture in high-power circuits lowers the device temperature and improves the device efficiency. Electrons in a circuit gain energy by absorbing phonons, the interatomic vibrations associated with heat. In a circuit, a ?heterobarrier? may be inserted to take advantage of these excited electrons, boosting them up in electrical potential.   The heterobarrier is engineered such that the increase in the band gap energy of the new material is equal to the energy given the electron by the phonons. Monte Carlo simulations based on interaction kinetics between electron and phonon show up to 19% of phonon energy converts to electric potential. This heterobarrier reverses the role of phonon from causing electric potential drop to causing potential gain.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/29/2013</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/29/2013</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1332807</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Massoud</FirstName>
<LastName>Kaviany</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME>MALE</PI_SUFX_NAME>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Massoud Kaviany</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>kaviany@umich.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>7349360402</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000305221</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/29/2013</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Regents of the University of Michigan - Ann Arbor</Name>
<CityName>Ann Arbor</CityName>
<ZipCode>481091274</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>7347636438</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>3003 South State St. Room 1062</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Michigan</StateName>
<StateCode>MI</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>12</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MI12</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>073133571</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>REGENTS OF THE UNIVERSITY OF MICHIGAN</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>073133571</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Michigan Ann Arbor]]></Name>
<CityName>Ann Arbor</CityName>
<StateCode>MI</StateCode>
<ZipCode>481092125</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[University of Michigan Ann arbor]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Michigan</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>12</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MI12</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1406</Code>
<Text>TTP-Thermal Transport Process</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>6892</Code>
<Text>CI REUSE</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>150E</Code>
<Text>Conduction/Diffusion</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7237</Code>
<Text>NANO NON-SOLIC SCI &amp; ENG AWD</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7433</Code>
<Text>CyberInfra Frmwrk 21st (CIF21)</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0113</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2013~291175</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><strong>Intellectual Merit: </strong>We used a graded heterobarrier placed along an electron channel, to in-situ recycle the phonons emitted in Joule heating, by increasing the entropy of phonon-absorbing electrons. The asymmetric electric potential distribution created by alloy grading separates the phonon absorption and emission regions, and emission in the larger effective-mass region causes momentum relaxation with smaller electron kinetic energy losses. These lead to smaller overall phonon emission and simultaneous potential-gain and self-cooling effects. Larger potential is gained with lower current and higher optical-phonon temperature. The self-consistent Monte Carlo simulations complying with the lateral momentum conservation combined with the entropy analysis as applied to a GaAs: Al electron channel with a graded heterobarrier, and under ideal lateral thermal isolation from surroundings, the phonon recycling efficiency reaches 25% of the reversible limit at 350 K, and it increases with temperature.A new heat harvester, the phonovoltaic (pV) cell, was introduced. The device converts optical phonons into power before they become heat. Due to the low entropy of a typical hot optical phonon population, the pV can operate at high fractions of the Carnot limit and harvest heat more efficiently than conventional heat harvesting technologies such as the thermoelectric generator. We use the bilayer graphene as a pV material. Our ab initio calculations show that bilayer graphene has a figure of merit exceeding 0.9, well above previously investigated materials. This allows a room-temperature pV to recycle 65% of a highly non-equilibrium, minimum entropy population of phonons. However, full-band Monte Carlo simulations of the electron and phonon dynamics in a bilayer graphene field-effect transistor (FET) show that the optical phonons emitted by field-accelerated electrons can only be recycled in situ with an efficiency of 50%, and this efficiency falls as the field strength grows. Still, a FET-pV can recycle the phonons produced in situ with a much higher efficiency than a thermoelectric generator can harvest heat produced by a FET ex situ.&nbsp;</p> <p><strong>Broader Impacts:</strong> We authored Wikipedia article on Heat Transfer Physics and this has becomes a source for quick review of the fundamentals/advances in this field (garnering more than 50 visits daily). We have authored a Wikipedia article phonovoltaic and continue to add animated/graphical and intuitive presentation of the atomic-level heat transfer processes, to make these accessible to undergraduates.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 08/01/2018<br>      Modified by: Massoud&nbsp;Kaviany</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Image         </div> <div class="galControls onePhoto" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation onePhoto" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1332807/1332807_10262159_1533131577716_Phonovoltaics--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1332807/1332807_10262159_1533131577716_Phonovoltaics--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Phonovoltaics"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1332807/1332807_10262159_1533131577716_Phonovoltaics--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Phonovoltaics"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Research has included simulation across a variety of scales,from quantum-mechanical, atomic scale ab initio simulations to semi-classical, meso-scalesimulations to classical, macroscale hydrodynamic simulation and analytical modeling.Comprehensive investigation</div> <div class="imageCredit">Massoud Kaviany</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Massoud&nbsp;Kaviany</div> <div class="imageTitle">Phonovoltaics</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Intellectual Merit: We used a graded heterobarrier placed along an electron channel, to in-situ recycle the phonons emitted in Joule heating, by increasing the entropy of phonon-absorbing electrons. The asymmetric electric potential distribution created by alloy grading separates the phonon absorption and emission regions, and emission in the larger effective-mass region causes momentum relaxation with smaller electron kinetic energy losses. These lead to smaller overall phonon emission and simultaneous potential-gain and self-cooling effects. Larger potential is gained with lower current and higher optical-phonon temperature. The self-consistent Monte Carlo simulations complying with the lateral momentum conservation combined with the entropy analysis as applied to a GaAs: Al electron channel with a graded heterobarrier, and under ideal lateral thermal isolation from surroundings, the phonon recycling efficiency reaches 25% of the reversible limit at 350 K, and it increases with temperature.A new heat harvester, the phonovoltaic (pV) cell, was introduced. The device converts optical phonons into power before they become heat. Due to the low entropy of a typical hot optical phonon population, the pV can operate at high fractions of the Carnot limit and harvest heat more efficiently than conventional heat harvesting technologies such as the thermoelectric generator. We use the bilayer graphene as a pV material. Our ab initio calculations show that bilayer graphene has a figure of merit exceeding 0.9, well above previously investigated materials. This allows a room-temperature pV to recycle 65% of a highly non-equilibrium, minimum entropy population of phonons. However, full-band Monte Carlo simulations of the electron and phonon dynamics in a bilayer graphene field-effect transistor (FET) show that the optical phonons emitted by field-accelerated electrons can only be recycled in situ with an efficiency of 50%, and this efficiency falls as the field strength grows. Still, a FET-pV can recycle the phonons produced in situ with a much higher efficiency than a thermoelectric generator can harvest heat produced by a FET ex situ.   Broader Impacts: We authored Wikipedia article on Heat Transfer Physics and this has becomes a source for quick review of the fundamentals/advances in this field (garnering more than 50 visits daily). We have authored a Wikipedia article phonovoltaic and continue to add animated/graphical and intuitive presentation of the atomic-level heat transfer processes, to make these accessible to undergraduates.       Last Modified: 08/01/2018       Submitted by: Massoud Kaviany]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
