<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Doctoral Dissertation Research: When Poverty Disappears: Investigating the Impact of a Universal Guaranteed Income</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/15/2013</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2015</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>11762.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>11762</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>04050000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>SBE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>SES</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Divn Of Social and Economic Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Patricia White</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>SES-1333623&lt;br/&gt;Erik O. Wright&lt;br/&gt;David Calnitsky&lt;br/&gt;University of Wisconsin&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;What would happen to a town if poverty were eliminated? What would happen if all residents suddenly could achieve genuine economic security in the form of substantial cash payments through a universal income transfer mechanism? This research examines the impact of an understudied quasi-experiment from the late 1970s called the Manitoba Basic Annual Income Experiment, or Mincome. Mincome, conducted by the Canadian and Manitoba Governments, tested a three-year universal basic annual income program. Participants in the program were able to secure guaranteed incomes equivalent to $18,725 CDN for a family of four. While Mincome took place in three main sites, the study focuses on the so-called "saturation" site located in the town of Dauphin, Manitoba, where all town residents were eligible for Mincome payments.  &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;There is a wide-ranging theoretical literature on the subject of basic income and its integration into a broadly capitalist economy. Debates focus primarily on the effects on the labor supply and work relations, and secondarily on gender and familial relations. There is an even bigger adjacent literature on poverty that remains relevant to the way a basic income might affect broad social outcomes from crime to the administration of the welfare state. This dissertation treats basic income in a small town as the independent variable, where work, gender and the family, education, crime and violence, and the stigma effects of social policy are treated as dependent variables.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Broader Impact&lt;br/&gt; &lt;br/&gt;While economic growth has been fairly steady since the 1990s, unlike the post-war decades it has been increasingly disconnected to employment growth. The challenge of the coming decades may be less about the search for new sources of employment than the distribution of a steadily expanding output. The contemporary economic bottleneck may not be due to people's willingness to work, but rather the dependable production of employment. Nonetheless, there is still little evidence on the various ways a guaranteed minimal income policy might operate.  Mincome was a unprecedented experiment and provides a rich source of information that should be further analyzed.  While no experiment can answer once and for all the deep questions posed by the broad reshaping of the work-income relationship, findings from the Dauphin experiment has the potential to contribute valuable knowledge on the subject.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>09/04/2013</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>09/04/2013</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.075</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1333623</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Erik</FirstName>
<LastName>Wright</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>O</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Erik O Wright</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>wright@ssc.wisc.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6082622921</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000407795</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/04/2013</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>David</FirstName>
<LastName>Calnitsky</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>David Calnitsky</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>calnitsky@wisc.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6082623822</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000629622</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/04/2013</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Wisconsin-Madison</Name>
<CityName>MADISON</CityName>
<ZipCode>537151218</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6082623822</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>21 North Park Street</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[Suite 6401]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Wisconsin</StateName>
<StateCode>WI</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>WI02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>161202122</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF WISCONSIN SYSTEM</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>041188822</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Wisconsin-Madison]]></Name>
<CityName>Madison</CityName>
<StateCode>WI</StateCode>
<ZipCode>537151218</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[21 North Park Street Suite 6401]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Wisconsin</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>WI02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1331</Code>
<Text>Sociology</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9179</Code>
<Text>GRADUATE INVOLVEMENT</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>SMET</Code>
<Text>SCIENCE, MATH, ENG &amp; TECH EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0113</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2013~11762</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>I examined the impact of a guaranteed annual income experiment from the 1970s called the Manitoba Basic Annual Income Experiment (Mincome). I examined Mincome&rsquo;s &lsquo;saturation&rsquo; site located in Dauphin, Manitoba, where all town residents were eligible for payments. My research&nbsp;analyzes a simple but elusive question: What would happen to a town if poverty were eliminated?&nbsp;</p> <p>Though the program came to an ignominious end&mdash;with no final report written and hundreds of boxes of raw data left unanalyzed in Archives Canada warehouses&mdash;at the outset it was designed as a model for the complete overhaul of Canadian social policy. Mincome was an unprecedented multi-million dollar experiment that was left largely unstudied. It provides a unique opportunity to understand the social realities of a transformative social policy. My research involved the digitization and analysis of archived quantitative panel data and qualitative surveys collected, but never studied, by original researchers. This raw survey data is held by&nbsp;Archives Canada. I supplement these surveys with census data and crime statistics.</p> <p>My first question is the following: Would people work less if their basic needs were guaranteed outside the market? A community-level experiment accounts for the fact that people make decisions in a social context, not in isolation. Using hitherto unanalyzed data I find an 11.3 percentage point reduction in labor market participation. Nearly 30 percent of that fall can be attributed to &lsquo;community context&rsquo; effects. Additionally, I show that withdrawals were driven disproportionately by young and single-headed households. Participants who provide qualitative explanations for work withdrawals typically cite care work, disability and illness, uneven employment opportunities, or educational investment.</p> <p>I also examined the question of social stigma. Drawing on archived qualitative participant accounts I found that the design and framing of Mincome led participants to view payments through a pragmatic lens, rather than the moralistic lens through which welfare is viewed. Consistent with prior theory I found that Mincome participation did not produce social stigma. The social meaning of Mincome was sufficiently powerful that even participants with particularly negative attitudes toward government assistance felt able to collect Mincome payments without a sense of contradiction. By obscuring the distinctions between the &ldquo;deserving&rdquo; and &ldquo;undeserving&rdquo; poor, universalistic income maintenance programs may weaken social stigmatization and strengthen program sustainability. &nbsp;</p> <p>Finally, using aggregate crime statistics data I find, in simple graphic trends, a fall in violent crime (as well as total crime) in Dauphin, during the Mincome years. I then merge annual crime data (i.e., annual town-level crime data from all Manitoba and Saskatchewan towns of similar size) with town-level Census variables to obtain controls. Using a fixed effects model to account for unobserved heterogeneity across towns and years, I find that Mincome (as a binary variable on town-years) is associated with a decline in the rate of violent crime and total crime. Adding in census controls destroys significance in the case of the total crime rate, but the violent crime rate remains very significant. What is the mechanism behind this fall in violence? To get at the mechanism I use an archived survey of "husbands" and "wives" in the treatment and control group, at the baseline and during the study period. The survey, which I digitized, focuses on various subjects including the domestic division of labor; power and decision-making in the home; and the frequency of disagreement and discussion of separation. I test a variety of mechanisms and find that Mincome reduced domestic assault by reducing financial stress and disagree...]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ I examined the impact of a guaranteed annual income experiment from the 1970s called the Manitoba Basic Annual Income Experiment (Mincome). I examined MincomeÆs æsaturationÆ site located in Dauphin, Manitoba, where all town residents were eligible for payments. My research analyzes a simple but elusive question: What would happen to a town if poverty were eliminated?   Though the program came to an ignominious end&mdash;with no final report written and hundreds of boxes of raw data left unanalyzed in Archives Canada warehouses&mdash;at the outset it was designed as a model for the complete overhaul of Canadian social policy. Mincome was an unprecedented multi-million dollar experiment that was left largely unstudied. It provides a unique opportunity to understand the social realities of a transformative social policy. My research involved the digitization and analysis of archived quantitative panel data and qualitative surveys collected, but never studied, by original researchers. This raw survey data is held by Archives Canada. I supplement these surveys with census data and crime statistics.  My first question is the following: Would people work less if their basic needs were guaranteed outside the market? A community-level experiment accounts for the fact that people make decisions in a social context, not in isolation. Using hitherto unanalyzed data I find an 11.3 percentage point reduction in labor market participation. Nearly 30 percent of that fall can be attributed to æcommunity contextÆ effects. Additionally, I show that withdrawals were driven disproportionately by young and single-headed households. Participants who provide qualitative explanations for work withdrawals typically cite care work, disability and illness, uneven employment opportunities, or educational investment.  I also examined the question of social stigma. Drawing on archived qualitative participant accounts I found that the design and framing of Mincome led participants to view payments through a pragmatic lens, rather than the moralistic lens through which welfare is viewed. Consistent with prior theory I found that Mincome participation did not produce social stigma. The social meaning of Mincome was sufficiently powerful that even participants with particularly negative attitudes toward government assistance felt able to collect Mincome payments without a sense of contradiction. By obscuring the distinctions between the "deserving" and "undeserving" poor, universalistic income maintenance programs may weaken social stigmatization and strengthen program sustainability.    Finally, using aggregate crime statistics data I find, in simple graphic trends, a fall in violent crime (as well as total crime) in Dauphin, during the Mincome years. I then merge annual crime data (i.e., annual town-level crime data from all Manitoba and Saskatchewan towns of similar size) with town-level Census variables to obtain controls. Using a fixed effects model to account for unobserved heterogeneity across towns and years, I find that Mincome (as a binary variable on town-years) is associated with a decline in the rate of violent crime and total crime. Adding in census controls destroys significance in the case of the total crime rate, but the violent crime rate remains very significant. What is the mechanism behind this fall in violence? To get at the mechanism I use an archived survey of "husbands" and "wives" in the treatment and control group, at the baseline and during the study period. The survey, which I digitized, focuses on various subjects including the domestic division of labor; power and decision-making in the home; and the frequency of disagreement and discussion of separation. I test a variety of mechanisms and find that Mincome reduced domestic assault by reducing financial stress and disagreement in families.           Last Modified: 09/30/2015       Submitted by: David Calnitsky]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
