<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Aspects of Quantum Computational Universality in the Measurement-Based Models</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2013</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>02/28/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>210000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>210000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03010000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>PHY</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Physics</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Bogdan Mihaila</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>bmihaila@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032928235</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This research will investigate important issues of quantum computational universality in measurement-based quantum computation (MBQC), explore connections of MBQC to ideas in statistical mechanics and condensed matter physics, and other quantum computational models. Specifically, the Affleck-Kennedy-Lieb-Tasaki (AKLT) models supply a rich playground for exploring new universal resource states and for understanding the intricate relations of quantum computational universality to percolation, spatial connectivity, magnetic order, and phase transitions in computational power. The long standing open question of the existence of a finite spectral of any two-dimensional rotationally symmetric (including AKLT) Hamiltonians is important also for the stability of generating related resource states by cooling. This will be studied with both analytic and numerical means. The research also includes searching for new types of resource states and developing model Hamiltonians whose thermal states can be used for quantum computation without the need to switch off interactions. Furthermore, this program studies how topological order can be of use to quantum computation, and conversely, how MBQC offers an efficient means to create a large class of topologically ordered states. &lt;br/&gt;Intellectual Merit: MBQC is one of the several models for building quantum computers. Essentially, all that is needed is a suitable highly entangled resource state to begin with and the ability to perform local measurements. This approach of realizing a quantum computer is promising with several physical systems, such as ultracold atoms in optical lattices and photons, complementing other approaches of implementing quantum computation. MBQC also provides a conceptual framework for answering fundamental questions in quantum computation and for bridging to other areas of research. The questions that will be addressed include: (1) What entangled states can qualify as an universal resource and can they arise as unique ground states of physically reasonable Hamiltonians? A complete understanding may lead to novel characterization of states of matter in terms of computational capability. (2) Is there a generalized Haldane conjecture in higher dimensions and how to test it? Tackling the long standing open question of the spectral gaps of two-dimensional AKLT Hamiltonians will give insight to a possible generalized Haldane conjecture in 2D and pave the road for probing richer phases in isotropic spin Hamiltonians in higher dimensions. (3) Can topological order provide insight to the quest of new resource states? (4) Are there advantages over others that the MBQC model offers? The research findings of MBQC from this program will not only advance our knowledge on various aspects of quantum computation and its connection to ideas in condensed matter physics and statistical mechanics, but also have potential impact on future quantum computer technology. &lt;br/&gt;Broader Impacts : The PI is taking the initiative in organizing a forum for discussing scientific results in quantum information science and stimulating collaboration across disciplines at Stony Brook University. He will integrate his research on quantum computation in the courses that he is currently and will be developing for both undergraduate and graduate students. This project will also include training of a graduate student and mentoring of a postoctoral researcher.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/29/2013</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/25/2015</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1333903</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Tzu-Chieh</FirstName>
<LastName>Wei</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Tzu-Chieh Wei</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>tzu-chieh.wei@stonybrook.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6316327966</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000602954</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/29/2013</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>SUNY at Stony Brook</Name>
<CityName>Stony Brook</CityName>
<ZipCode>117940001</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6316329949</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>WEST 5510 FRK MEL LIB</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NY01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>804878247</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>RESEARCH FOUNDATION FOR THE STATE UNIVERSITY OF NEW YORK, THE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>020657151</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[SUNY at Stony Brook]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<ZipCode>117943800</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NY01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1287</Code>
<Text>MATHEMATICAL PHYSICS</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>9134</Code>
<Text>Integrative Activities in Phys</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1287</Code>
<Text>MATHEMATICAL PHYSICS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0113</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0114</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0115</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2013~70000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~77063</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2015~62937</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Quantum computation has the potential of becoming the new technology in computation and it promises speedup for solving certain classes of problems over its classical counterpart. This project investigates one of the major models for quantum computation, i.e., the measurement-based approach (MBQC). It relies on a quantum feature called entanglement and the quantum computer consumes entanglement in order to run. Imagine that there are a two-dimensional array of "quantum coins" lying on a table and these quantum coins form some bizarre entangled network. The measured-based quantum computer runs by "looking" or "measuring" coins arranged in certain patterns and the entanglement of these quantum coins becomes less as a result of the measurement.&nbsp;</p> <p>First, the project explores what kind of quantum entanglement that the quantum coins can form such that they can be useful for computation. The complete catalog of such entanglement is not known. Only a limited number of cases were previously understood. This project found that a wide family of states known as the valence-bond states can indeed provide the resource for quantum computation, vastly expanding previously known territory. More detailed can be found at&nbsp;(1) Phys. Rev. A 88, 062307 (2013),<br />(2) Phys. Rev. A 90, 042333 (2014), and (3) Phys. Rev A 92, 012310 (2015).</p> <p>One important problem that this project contributed to solving is the so-called spectral gap in the above valence-bond states and their models (a.k.a. AKLT models). These valence-bond states appear to have the absolutely lowest energy and to break them requires a finite amount of external energy to be supplied. Such energy gap gives these valence-bond states some robustness against noise and perturbations. The project has produced strong numerical evidence that such a gap exists and gave an estimate of its value. More details can be found in the paper: (4) Phys. Rev. B 88, 245118 (2013).</p> <p>This project also examined how the above valence-bond models change their behavior if some kind of deformation is applied. This is useful for studying the gap properties and possible phases that emerge under deformation. Such phases are described by different entanglement patterns of the quantum coins. Rich phase diagrams were identified and their emergence depends on the underlying lattice structure and the "type of valence bonds". Moreover, an extended region was found that quantum computation is possible before some phase transition takes place. More details can be found in the paper:&nbsp;(5) Phys. Rev. B 94, 165130 (2016).</p> <p>To address whether quantum computation arises from some phases of matter, the project also investigates specific model constructions. In particular, it was found that even at finite nonzero temperature, the quantum entanglement survives and quantum computation is still possible. Even though the transitions may not coincide with the usual phase transitions of matter, the existence of such a quantum-computationally-useful region is encouraging for future technology. More details can be found in the paper: (6) Phys. Rev. A 89, 052315 (2014). &nbsp;&nbsp;</p> <p>In additional to the valence-bond type of entanglement, the project also found that a special type of entanglement, so-called Greenberger-Horne-Zeilinger states, forming some sort of loop-like structures, is also good for computation. In fact, these states appear as some prototypical states in the so-called symmetry-protected topological order (SPTO) in two and higher spatial dimensions, recently discovered by condensed-matter physicists. More details can be found in the paper: (7) Phys. Rev. A 92, 052309 (2015).&nbsp;</p> <p>In fact,&nbsp;the connection of such topological order and quantum computation was explored primarily in one dimension previously. This project also explores the possibility of different symmetry groups of SPTO in the natural protection of information processing. Furthermore, which phases can emerge from certain protected symmetry was also studied. More details can be found in the papers:&nbsp;(8) &nbsp;Phys. Rev. A 92, 022310 (2015) and (9)&nbsp;&nbsp;Phys. Rev. B 94, 045136 (2016).</p> <p><br />This project also provided crucial research training of students, including 3 Ph.D. students and as many as five master students, as well as a few undergraduate students. The PI had also mentored two postdoctoral researchers and both were successful in their subsequent career development and advancement. The PI had given physics lectures to high-school students in the summer and used demos and video showing to motivate their learning. Discussions included classical waves to quantum mechanical waves and quantum computation. These helped to plant seeds for students to engage careers in STEM. The PI also supervised high-school students in summer research activities. The students he had supervised all went on to universities to major in science. Such impact on students' career path choosing was more immediate. The PI had also developed his research outcomes and findings on quantum computation in course materials and workshop tutorials. The PI also participated in an undergraduate STEM summer institute and has been applying new scientific methods in his teaching.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 04/04/2017<br>      Modified by: Tzu-Chieh&nbsp;Wei</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Quantum computation has the potential of becoming the new technology in computation and it promises speedup for solving certain classes of problems over its classical counterpart. This project investigates one of the major models for quantum computation, i.e., the measurement-based approach (MBQC). It relies on a quantum feature called entanglement and the quantum computer consumes entanglement in order to run. Imagine that there are a two-dimensional array of "quantum coins" lying on a table and these quantum coins form some bizarre entangled network. The measured-based quantum computer runs by "looking" or "measuring" coins arranged in certain patterns and the entanglement of these quantum coins becomes less as a result of the measurement.   First, the project explores what kind of quantum entanglement that the quantum coins can form such that they can be useful for computation. The complete catalog of such entanglement is not known. Only a limited number of cases were previously understood. This project found that a wide family of states known as the valence-bond states can indeed provide the resource for quantum computation, vastly expanding previously known territory. More detailed can be found at (1) Phys. Rev. A 88, 062307 (2013), (2) Phys. Rev. A 90, 042333 (2014), and (3) Phys. Rev A 92, 012310 (2015).  One important problem that this project contributed to solving is the so-called spectral gap in the above valence-bond states and their models (a.k.a. AKLT models). These valence-bond states appear to have the absolutely lowest energy and to break them requires a finite amount of external energy to be supplied. Such energy gap gives these valence-bond states some robustness against noise and perturbations. The project has produced strong numerical evidence that such a gap exists and gave an estimate of its value. More details can be found in the paper: (4) Phys. Rev. B 88, 245118 (2013).  This project also examined how the above valence-bond models change their behavior if some kind of deformation is applied. This is useful for studying the gap properties and possible phases that emerge under deformation. Such phases are described by different entanglement patterns of the quantum coins. Rich phase diagrams were identified and their emergence depends on the underlying lattice structure and the "type of valence bonds". Moreover, an extended region was found that quantum computation is possible before some phase transition takes place. More details can be found in the paper: (5) Phys. Rev. B 94, 165130 (2016).  To address whether quantum computation arises from some phases of matter, the project also investigates specific model constructions. In particular, it was found that even at finite nonzero temperature, the quantum entanglement survives and quantum computation is still possible. Even though the transitions may not coincide with the usual phase transitions of matter, the existence of such a quantum-computationally-useful region is encouraging for future technology. More details can be found in the paper: (6) Phys. Rev. A 89, 052315 (2014).     In additional to the valence-bond type of entanglement, the project also found that a special type of entanglement, so-called Greenberger-Horne-Zeilinger states, forming some sort of loop-like structures, is also good for computation. In fact, these states appear as some prototypical states in the so-called symmetry-protected topological order (SPTO) in two and higher spatial dimensions, recently discovered by condensed-matter physicists. More details can be found in the paper: (7) Phys. Rev. A 92, 052309 (2015).   In fact, the connection of such topological order and quantum computation was explored primarily in one dimension previously. This project also explores the possibility of different symmetry groups of SPTO in the natural protection of information processing. Furthermore, which phases can emerge from certain protected symmetry was also studied. More details can be found in the papers: (8)  Phys. Rev. A 92, 022310 (2015) and (9)  Phys. Rev. B 94, 045136 (2016).   This project also provided crucial research training of students, including 3 Ph.D. students and as many as five master students, as well as a few undergraduate students. The PI had also mentored two postdoctoral researchers and both were successful in their subsequent career development and advancement. The PI had given physics lectures to high-school students in the summer and used demos and video showing to motivate their learning. Discussions included classical waves to quantum mechanical waves and quantum computation. These helped to plant seeds for students to engage careers in STEM. The PI also supervised high-school students in summer research activities. The students he had supervised all went on to universities to major in science. Such impact on students' career path choosing was more immediate. The PI had also developed his research outcomes and findings on quantum computation in course materials and workshop tutorials. The PI also participated in an undergraduate STEM summer institute and has been applying new scientific methods in his teaching.             Last Modified: 04/04/2017       Submitted by: Tzu-Chieh Wei]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
