<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Anticipating Bifurcations for Identifying Dynamic Characteristics of Nonlinear Systems</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2013</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>325251.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>325251</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CMMI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Civil, Mechanical, &amp; Manufact Inn</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Atul Kelkar</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The main goal of this research project is to create a novel method to quantitatively forecast bifurcations as well as the pre- and post-bifurcation dynamics of large dimensional nonlinear systems with a low dimensional inertial manifold. Dramatic changes in the dynamics of complex systems, from ecosystems to engineered systems, occur. Forecasting such events using advanced nonlinear techniques is of major importance. The behavior of such complex systems is commonly characterized by nonlinearities that can lead to regime shifts or bifurcations from a stable to an unstable dynamics. A method that can quantitatively predict bifurcations as well as the pre- and post-bifurcation dynamics for large dimensional nonlinear systems would have a significant impact in a variety of fields, from the analysis of nano-systems to the design of disease eradication campaigns. The three key tasks are to: (1) develop novel techniques to differentiate the dynamics along the inertial manifold from the overall dynamics and to handle noise using a robust signal processing methodology, (2) develop innovative methods to forecast stable/unstable branches of bifurcation diagrams, and (3) refine the general methods for application to complex nonlinear systems including population dynamics and aeroelastic systems. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project has broader impacts on the society at large. This effort will answer important scientific questions, and will impact applications spanning from computational dynamics to population dynamics. For example, there is an acute need for reliable methods to predict catastrophic events in populations of plants and/or animals because such events can lead to irreversible consequences such as extinction of species. The potential impact of this method is even higher when applied to disease eradication (populations of infectious diseases). While the dynamics of diseases is a very complex system and the method may not be perfect, it can prove to outperform most other methods because of its ability to filter out noise and the ability to provide forecasts without the need for an accurate model.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/26/2013</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/26/2013</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1334908</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Mercedes</FirstName>
<LastName>Pascual</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Mercedes Pascual</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>pascualmm@uchicago.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>7737952321</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000165801</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/26/2013</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Bogdan</FirstName>
<LastName>Epureanu</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>I</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Bogdan I Epureanu</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>epureanu@umich.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>7346476391</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000250672</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/26/2013</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Kiran</FirstName>
<LastName>D'Souza</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>X</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Kiran X D'Souza</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>kdsouza@umich.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2489256273</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000083404</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/26/2013</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Regents of the University of Michigan - Ann Arbor</Name>
<CityName>Ann Arbor</CityName>
<ZipCode>481091274</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>7347636438</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>3003 South State St. Room 1062</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Michigan</StateName>
<StateCode>MI</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>12</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MI12</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>073133571</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>REGENTS OF THE UNIVERSITY OF MICHIGAN</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>073133571</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Michigan Ann Arbor]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>MI</StateCode>
<ZipCode>481092125</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Michigan</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>12</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MI12</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7478</Code>
<Text>DYNAMICAL SYSTEMS</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>034E</Code>
<Text>Dynamical systems</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>035E</Code>
<Text>NOISE, ACOUSTICS, VIBRATIONS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>036E</Code>
<Text>CIVIL INFRASTRUCTURE</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1057</Code>
<Text>CIS BASE RESEARCH</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8024</Code>
<Text>Complex Systems</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>CVIS</Code>
<Text>CIVIL INFRASTRUCTURE</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0113</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2013~325251</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><strong>Summary</strong>: Dramatic changes in the dynamics of complex systems, from ecosystems to engineered systems, occur with catastrophic consequences. Thus, forecasting such events using nonlinear techniques is of major importance. The behavior of such complex systems is commonly characterized by nonlinearities that can lead to regime shifts from a stable to an unstable dynamics. Advancements in geometric methods have enabled the identification of the mechanisms responsible for regime shifts (bifurcations), i.e. qualitative and quantitative changes in the dynamics caused by parametric variations. These mechanisms have been discovered in a variety of engineered systems, biological systems, population dynamics, aeroelastic systems, and many others. Thus, methods for forecasting the dynamics of complex nonlinear systems have gained importance in a variety of fields. Such a method can be constructed by using invariants of the dynamics as developed in this project.</p> <p><strong>Intellectual Merit</strong>: The developed methods that can quantitatively and accurately predict bifurcations as well as the pre- and post-bifurcation dynamics for large dimensional nonlinear systems can have a significant impact in a variety of fields, from the analysis of nano-systems to the design of disease eradication campaigns. To create a method with such large applicability, invariants of the dynamics must be used. That is because they are pervasive in all systems and they remain the same no matter what kind of physical measurements are available. For example, measurements of populations may involve counting individuals, whereas measurements of brain activity may involve electrical fields. In all these systems, the remnants of the critical slowing down have the same manifestation, namely the tendency of the system to recover very slowly from perturbations. Thus, the grand challenge emerging is to discover how to use invariants of the dynamics to forecast bifurcations and to predict post-bifurcation regimes without placing the system in those regimes. An answer to this challenge was developed in this project.</p> <p>The <strong>goal and main achievement</strong> of this research is to create a novel model-less method to quantitatively forecast bifurcations as well as the pre- and post-bifurcation dynamics of large dimensional nonlinear systems with a low dimensional inertial manifold. The specific aims reached in this work are: (a) <em>novel methods</em>: by a unique use of invariants of the dynamics and by exploiting remnants of the critical slowing down phenomenon far from the bifurcation, novel methods will be developed to forecast the onset of (super- and sub-critical) bifurcations and to predict bifurcation diagrams without placing the system in the post-bifurcation dynamics (i.e., using time-series data from the pre-bifurcation regime only), (b) <em>novel solutions for specific applications</em>: the general methods developed will be applied to several systems, including ecosystems and population dynamics, and fluid-structural systems.</p> <p>The research has provided a unique method for early detection of qualitative and quantitative changes in the dynamics of complex systems such as ecosystems and population dynamics, flight structures, and fluid-structural systems. The novel method created in this project can be summarized as: (1) observe the dynamics in the normal pre-bifurcation regime, (2) collect measurements of the dynamics when the system recovers from a (naturally occurring or induced) perturbation, (3) repeat the data gathering after a period of time, when the parameters of the system have changed, (4) use the gathered data to forecast the bifurcation diagram for the system. An important advantage of the proposed approach is that the closer the system is to the bifurcation point, the more accurate the forecasting is.</p> <p><strong>Significance and Broader Impacts</strong>: This research has broader impacts on the society at large because it answers important scientific questions, and impacts applications spanning from computational dynamics to population dynamics. For example, there is an acute need for reliable methods to predict catastrophic events in populations of plants and/or animals because such events can lead to irreversible consequences such as extinction of species. The potential impact of the proposed method is even higher when applied to disease eradication (populations of infectious diseases). While forecasting the dynamics of diseases is a very complex problem, the proposed method has the potential to outperform most other methods because of its ability to filter out noise and the ability to provide quantitative forecasts without the need for an accurate model.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 09/29/2017<br>      Modified by: Bogdan&nbsp;I&nbsp;Epureanu</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Image         </div> <div class="galControls onePhoto" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation onePhoto" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1334908/1334908_10261725_1506700131162_figure-1--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1334908/1334908_10261725_1506700131162_figure-1--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Conceptual process of forecasting"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1334908/1334908_10261725_1506700131162_figure-1--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Conceptual process of forecasting"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Forecasting of bifurcation points from the region outside the danger zone. Measurements from locations A1, A2, or A1' and A2' are used to forecast bifurcation at A. Similarly, measurements from locations B1, B2, or B1' and B2' are used to forecast bifurcation at B.</div> <div class="imageCredit">PIs have created this figure, which appeared in a PLoS pubication</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Bogdan&nbsp;I&nbsp;Epureanu</div> <div class="imageTitle">Conceptual process of forecasting</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Summary: Dramatic changes in the dynamics of complex systems, from ecosystems to engineered systems, occur with catastrophic consequences. Thus, forecasting such events using nonlinear techniques is of major importance. The behavior of such complex systems is commonly characterized by nonlinearities that can lead to regime shifts from a stable to an unstable dynamics. Advancements in geometric methods have enabled the identification of the mechanisms responsible for regime shifts (bifurcations), i.e. qualitative and quantitative changes in the dynamics caused by parametric variations. These mechanisms have been discovered in a variety of engineered systems, biological systems, population dynamics, aeroelastic systems, and many others. Thus, methods for forecasting the dynamics of complex nonlinear systems have gained importance in a variety of fields. Such a method can be constructed by using invariants of the dynamics as developed in this project.  Intellectual Merit: The developed methods that can quantitatively and accurately predict bifurcations as well as the pre- and post-bifurcation dynamics for large dimensional nonlinear systems can have a significant impact in a variety of fields, from the analysis of nano-systems to the design of disease eradication campaigns. To create a method with such large applicability, invariants of the dynamics must be used. That is because they are pervasive in all systems and they remain the same no matter what kind of physical measurements are available. For example, measurements of populations may involve counting individuals, whereas measurements of brain activity may involve electrical fields. In all these systems, the remnants of the critical slowing down have the same manifestation, namely the tendency of the system to recover very slowly from perturbations. Thus, the grand challenge emerging is to discover how to use invariants of the dynamics to forecast bifurcations and to predict post-bifurcation regimes without placing the system in those regimes. An answer to this challenge was developed in this project.  The goal and main achievement of this research is to create a novel model-less method to quantitatively forecast bifurcations as well as the pre- and post-bifurcation dynamics of large dimensional nonlinear systems with a low dimensional inertial manifold. The specific aims reached in this work are: (a) novel methods: by a unique use of invariants of the dynamics and by exploiting remnants of the critical slowing down phenomenon far from the bifurcation, novel methods will be developed to forecast the onset of (super- and sub-critical) bifurcations and to predict bifurcation diagrams without placing the system in the post-bifurcation dynamics (i.e., using time-series data from the pre-bifurcation regime only), (b) novel solutions for specific applications: the general methods developed will be applied to several systems, including ecosystems and population dynamics, and fluid-structural systems.  The research has provided a unique method for early detection of qualitative and quantitative changes in the dynamics of complex systems such as ecosystems and population dynamics, flight structures, and fluid-structural systems. The novel method created in this project can be summarized as: (1) observe the dynamics in the normal pre-bifurcation regime, (2) collect measurements of the dynamics when the system recovers from a (naturally occurring or induced) perturbation, (3) repeat the data gathering after a period of time, when the parameters of the system have changed, (4) use the gathered data to forecast the bifurcation diagram for the system. An important advantage of the proposed approach is that the closer the system is to the bifurcation point, the more accurate the forecasting is.  Significance and Broader Impacts: This research has broader impacts on the society at large because it answers important scientific questions, and impacts applications spanning from computational dynamics to population dynamics. For example, there is an acute need for reliable methods to predict catastrophic events in populations of plants and/or animals because such events can lead to irreversible consequences such as extinction of species. The potential impact of the proposed method is even higher when applied to disease eradication (populations of infectious diseases). While forecasting the dynamics of diseases is a very complex problem, the proposed method has the potential to outperform most other methods because of its ability to filter out noise and the ability to provide quantitative forecasts without the need for an accurate model.       Last Modified: 09/29/2017       Submitted by: Bogdan I Epureanu]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
