<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Collaborative Research:  Investigating the Ecological Importance of Iron Storage in Diatoms</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2013</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>352664.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>352664</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>06040300</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>GEO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>OCE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Ocean Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>David Garrison</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Diatoms are responsible for a significant fraction of primary production in the ocean. They are associated with enhanced carbon export and usually dominate the response of phytoplankton to additions of the micronutrient iron in high-nutrient, low-chlorophyll (HNLC) regions. Diatoms, particularly those isolated from the open ocean, appear to have a significant capacity to store iron for later use, and in some groups of diatoms this ability is enabled by the iron storage protein ferritin. Such luxury uptake of iron has long been observed in laboratory cultures and hypothesized to provide diatoms with an ecological benefit in the low-iron waters that cover 40% of the global ocean. However iron storage has been difficult to observe in natural systems due to the methodological challenges of working with mixed plankton assemblages, and a physiological understanding of the impacts of iron on ocean diatoms is lacking. This project combines state-of-the-art high-throughput transcriptomic sequencing and single-cell element analysis with novel laboratory and field incubation experiments to quantify iron storage abilities of cultured and natural diatoms that either contain or lack ferritin and determine the ecological impacts of this process. The overall objective of this project is to examine the ecological importance of iron storage as a selective mechanism controlling the distributions of diatoms along iron gradients in marine ecosystems. The proposed research includes three specific objectives:&lt;br/&gt;A. Determine if there is a consistent physiological difference in the ability of pennate versus centric diatoms to store iron.&lt;br/&gt;B. Examine whether iron storage capacities across diverse diatom taxa consistently provide a mechanistic explanation for continued growth in the absence of iron.&lt;br/&gt;C. Determine whether enhanced iron storage provides diatoms with a competitive within natural phytoplankton assemblages in both coastal and oceanic regions.&lt;br/&gt;Transcriptomic sequencing on a variety of ecologically important pennate and centric diatoms will be used to survey for the presence of ferritin-like genes in order to establish biogeographical and/or phylogenetic patterns of occurrence of diatom ferritin. Laboratory culture experiments will be used to quantify the iron storage abilities of these diatoms, as well as the number of cell divisions that can be supported by the stored iron, providing valuable physiological data to inform the understanding of plankton ecology in iron-limited coastal and HNLC systems. The laboratory experiments will be complemented by measurements of ferritin expression and iron storage in coastal and ocean diatoms sampled across gradients of iron availability on two cruises-of-opportunity to the northeast Pacific Ocean.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Intellectual Merit: By characterizing the diversity in potential iron storage capacities of diatoms and elucidating the role ferritins play in enhancing iron storage and the iron-limitation response, this project will provide new insights into how this important group of primary producers has adapted to their environment, thus contributing to our knowledge of what factors influence their abundance and distributions. This knowledge is especially important in relation to predicting the future effects of climate change on these organisms that are responsible for significant primary production in marine ecosystems.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Broader Impacts: This project incorporates several activities that will directly contribute to education and training. The training of a graduate student, post-doctoral researcher and multiple undergraduates will be directly supported. Additionally, a broader impact goal of this project is to facilitate teaching and learning on marine science-related topics through translating our research objectives into widely distributed educational materials that can be used in the classroom. To accomplish this, a high-school teacher will participate in one of the cruises and convey her experiences at sea to her students as well as develop curricular materials for her class. These will be used for high-school earth and environmental science courses and also distributed to teachers in Maine as part of Bigelow Laboratories teacher training program, thus broadening the scope of the outreach activities.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/26/2013</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/26/2013</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.050</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1334632</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Benjamin</FirstName>
<LastName>Twining</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>S</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Benjamin S Twining</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>btwining@bigelow.org</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2073152567</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000090799</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/26/2013</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Bigelow Laboratory for Ocean Sciences</Name>
<CityName>East Boothbay</CityName>
<ZipCode>045440380</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2073152567</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>60 Bigelow Drive</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Maine</StateName>
<StateCode>ME</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>ME01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>077474757</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>BIGELOW LABORATORY FOR OCEAN SCIENCES</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Bigelow Laboratory for Ocean Sci]]></Name>
<CityName>East Boothbay</CityName>
<StateCode>ME</StateCode>
<ZipCode>045440380</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[60 Bigelow Drive]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Maine</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>ME01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1650</Code>
<Text>BIOLOGICAL OCEANOGRAPHY</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1389</Code>
<Text>CARBON CYCLE RESEARCH</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9117</Code>
<Text>MARINE BIOTECHNOLOGY</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0113</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2013~352664</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Iron is a nutrient required for the growth of phytoplankton (single-celled plants) in the ocean. In large regions of the ocean, the supply of iron -- mostly via airborne dust -- is very low, and iron availability limits the growth of phytoplankton in these areas. Because of the ability of phytoplankton to remove atmospheric carbon dioxide and sequester some of it on the bottom of the ocean, ocean iron limitation has implications for global climate. Hence, it is important to understand how phytoplankton compete for iron in the ocean. In this project we investigated the ability of various species of phytoplankton to store iron for use later, a behavior called 'luxury uptake'. We measured the iron contents of 14 different species of diatoms (a type of phytoplankton) grown in the laboratory at varying concentrations. Our collaborators at University of North Carolina measured levels of the iron-storage protein ferritin in the same species in order to determine if this protein gives cells an enhanced ability to store iron. We also conducted incubation experiments with natural phytoplankton communities collected at various locations along the California coast and further offshore from Vancouver Island to test for luxury iron storage and ferritin gene expression.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>From the laboratory work we learned that diatoms' ability to store iron is largely independent of the presence of ferritin. For the most part, species that contain ferritin were not significantly better at storing iron than species that lack ferritin. Furthermore, some species were found to contain multiple copies of the ferritin gene, which were expressed (or copied) in different ways. It appears that in some species ferritin may provide short-term 'buffering' of intracellular iron levels, allowing cells to control and maintain iron at beneficial concentrations inside the cell. From the experiments conducted on the research cruises, we documented significant occurrence of luxury iron uptake in natural phytoplankton populations growing along iron gradients. We also found that two groups of diatoms that either contain or lack ferritin did not vary notably in their ability to accumulate iron or respond to altered iron availability. This supports our findings from the laboratory experiments. Our results in this project greatly expand our knowledge of the upper bounds of iron that can be stored by phytoplankton. This information will be used to constrain global climate models that represent iron and phytoplankton behavior in the ocean. This will result in improved accuracy of these models' predictions of future climate conditions.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>The broader impacts of this work have been transferred to educational communities and the general public in several ways. Two post-doctoral researchers were trained at Bigelow through this research project, the first continuing on to a career in secondary school education. Additionally, two undergraduate researchers were trained by Bigelow scientists through this project. One student participated in the 3-week research cruise along the California Coast. The following year, a second undergraduate spent the summer working at Bigelow conducting diatom growth experiments. Additionally, Twining taught lectures and a laboratory exercise on iron limitation of diatoms during his ocean biogeochemistry course for undergraduates as part of Bigelow's fall semester program. Twining has given multiple outreach talks to the general public during the project, describing this research and the importance of iron and phytoplankton to global climate and ocean ecosystem health.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 10/30/2017<br>      Modified by: Benjamin&nbsp;S&nbsp;Twining</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Iron is a nutrient required for the growth of phytoplankton (single-celled plants) in the ocean. In large regions of the ocean, the supply of iron -- mostly via airborne dust -- is very low, and iron availability limits the growth of phytoplankton in these areas. Because of the ability of phytoplankton to remove atmospheric carbon dioxide and sequester some of it on the bottom of the ocean, ocean iron limitation has implications for global climate. Hence, it is important to understand how phytoplankton compete for iron in the ocean. In this project we investigated the ability of various species of phytoplankton to store iron for use later, a behavior called 'luxury uptake'. We measured the iron contents of 14 different species of diatoms (a type of phytoplankton) grown in the laboratory at varying concentrations. Our collaborators at University of North Carolina measured levels of the iron-storage protein ferritin in the same species in order to determine if this protein gives cells an enhanced ability to store iron. We also conducted incubation experiments with natural phytoplankton communities collected at various locations along the California coast and further offshore from Vancouver Island to test for luxury iron storage and ferritin gene expression.     From the laboratory work we learned that diatoms' ability to store iron is largely independent of the presence of ferritin. For the most part, species that contain ferritin were not significantly better at storing iron than species that lack ferritin. Furthermore, some species were found to contain multiple copies of the ferritin gene, which were expressed (or copied) in different ways. It appears that in some species ferritin may provide short-term 'buffering' of intracellular iron levels, allowing cells to control and maintain iron at beneficial concentrations inside the cell. From the experiments conducted on the research cruises, we documented significant occurrence of luxury iron uptake in natural phytoplankton populations growing along iron gradients. We also found that two groups of diatoms that either contain or lack ferritin did not vary notably in their ability to accumulate iron or respond to altered iron availability. This supports our findings from the laboratory experiments. Our results in this project greatly expand our knowledge of the upper bounds of iron that can be stored by phytoplankton. This information will be used to constrain global climate models that represent iron and phytoplankton behavior in the ocean. This will result in improved accuracy of these models' predictions of future climate conditions.     The broader impacts of this work have been transferred to educational communities and the general public in several ways. Two post-doctoral researchers were trained at Bigelow through this research project, the first continuing on to a career in secondary school education. Additionally, two undergraduate researchers were trained by Bigelow scientists through this project. One student participated in the 3-week research cruise along the California Coast. The following year, a second undergraduate spent the summer working at Bigelow conducting diatom growth experiments. Additionally, Twining taught lectures and a laboratory exercise on iron limitation of diatoms during his ocean biogeochemistry course for undergraduates as part of Bigelow's fall semester program. Twining has given multiple outreach talks to the general public during the project, describing this research and the importance of iron and phytoplankton to global climate and ocean ecosystem health.          Last Modified: 10/30/2017       Submitted by: Benjamin S Twining]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
