<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Resilient Steel Frame Systems through the Use of Non-Traditional Materials</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2013</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>289259.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>289259</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CMMI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Civil, Mechanical, &amp; Manufact Inn</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Yick Hsuan</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This project aims to enhance the performance of steel frame systems under seismic loads by incorporating non-traditional civil engineering materials into steel structural systems. Current design approaches for steel frame systems rely on damage to steel members in specific locations to dissipate energy. The use of non-traditional civil engineering materials, such as steel foam and honeycomb materials as fill-in, in steel systems is an important means to significantly reduce the impact of an earthquake on a structure. The use of these non-traditional materials provides an opportunity to better control structural response and the amount and location of damage. As a result, the need to repair both structural and non-structural damage after an extreme event is minimized and the economic integrity of the community is maintained. Such solutions are plausible for both new construction and retrofit of older steel frame systems. This work will provide a road map for more extensive use and integration of innovative materials in the design of structures.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Currently, steel frame systems dissipate earthquake input energy through inelastic behavior at 'fuses' or 'plastic hinges' in specified members limiting the sections that can be used for these members and leading to significant damage and downtime for repairs. The specific goal of this project is to enhance the resilience and robustness of seismic steel frame systems by employing non-traditional materials (high damping rubber, metal and polymer foams, and honeycomb materials) between the flanges of wide flange sections and the interior of hollow structural sections to increase energy dissipation and restrain local buckling. To achieve this goal, the behavior of the high damping materials will be characterized under large dynamic cyclic loads.  Mechanical behavior tests will be conducted on the non-traditional civil engineering materials and small-scale member tests will consider their behavior in a confined fill application. Finite element models will be used to evaluate the effect of different properties and configurations on the behavior and energy dissipation capacity of the void-filled members. Large-scale sub-assemblies of beam-column connections and bracing members utilizing the fill materials will be experimentally tested to determine detailing requirements and verify buckling mitigation. The confluence of non-traditional civil engineering materials, structural engineering, and earthquakes also provides an opportunity to motivate the next generation of students towards engineering; impress upon university students the need to think creatively; and educate structural engineering practitioners about non-traditional materials and their possible impact in structures.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/10/2013</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/10/2013</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1334272</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Jason</FirstName>
<LastName>McCormick</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Jason McCormick</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>jpmccorm@umich.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>7347644462</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000502052</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/10/2013</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Regents of the University of Michigan - Ann Arbor</Name>
<CityName>Ann Arbor</CityName>
<ZipCode>481091274</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>7347636438</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>3003 South State St. Room 1062</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Michigan</StateName>
<StateCode>MI</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>12</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MI12</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>073133571</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>REGENTS OF THE UNIVERSITY OF MICHIGAN</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>073133571</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Michigan Ann Arbor]]></Name>
<CityName>Ann Arbor</CityName>
<StateCode>MI</StateCode>
<ZipCode>481092125</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[2350 Hayward Street]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Michigan</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>12</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MI12</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1637</Code>
<Text>Structural and Architectural E</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>036E</Code>
<Text>CIVIL INFRASTRUCTURE</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>039E</Code>
<Text>STRUCTURAL SYSTEMS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>040E</Code>
<Text>Haz mitigation of structural sys</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>043E</Code>
<Text>EARTHQUAKE ENGINEERING</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1576</Code>
<Text>NATIONL EARTHQK HZRD REDCT PRG</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0113</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2013~289259</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Current design methodologies for steel frame systems rely on damage to steel members in specific locations to dissipate energy input into the system by an earthquake, which can lead to an unexpected performance under larger than expected loads and significant economic impact due to the need for extensive repairs prior to re-occupancy. The more pervasive use of non-traditional civil engineering materials in steel systems is an important means to significantly reduce the impact of an earthquake on a structure, but has been limited due to a lack of knowledge of the behavior of these materials under large cyclic loads and past reliance solely on traditional materials (steel, concrete, timber, and masonry). This project addressed this lack of knowledge and enhanced the use of hollow structural sections through the study of an innovative connection configuration and the use of expanding urethane foam in the voids of these sections.</p> <p>In meeting this goal, the outcomes associated with intellectual merit are the characterization of the behavior of expanding urethane foam under cyclic loads, the confirmation of the ability of lightweight, high energy dissipating materials to inhibit local buckling when applied to the voids of hollow structural section members undergoing bending loads expected during an earthquake, the defining of limiting width-thickness and depth-thickness ratios for the use of urethane foam filled HSS beams in bending application, and the optimization of a collar connection configuration that can allow for more reliable performance with increased quality control and construction speeds due to limited field welding. The results provide a road map for the more extensive use and integration of innovative materials in the design of structures. Interest in the findings extends to other fields of engineering, such as aerospace and mechanical engineering where lightweight, high energy dissipation systems can be valuable.</p> <p>Numerous project outcomes also are associated with the broader impacts resulting from the project. The project led to one female student completing her doctoral degree and successfully entering structural engineering practice, while an underrepresented undergraduate student from Puerto Rico spent a summer during his undergraduate studies working on the project at the University of Michigan and is now pursuing his own doctoral degree. Over the course of the project a total of three graduate students (1 Ph.D. and 2 Master&rsquo;s) and four undergraduate students worked on the project where five of these students were from underrepresented groups. The diversity of the research group had a positive impact on the project by continually providing unique perspectives as new challenges arose. Through dissemination and outreach efforts, a number of school age students, university students, and professionals were exposed for the first time to the use of non-traditional materials in structural systems and the potential benefits of thinking out of the box in regards to applications of these materials in hazard mitigation.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 02/27/2018<br>      Modified by: Jason&nbsp;Mccormick</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Image         </div> <div class="galControls onePhoto" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation onePhoto" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1334272/1334272_10265852_1519790145462_Figure1_ProjectOutcomes--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1334272/1334272_10265852_1519790145462_Figure1_ProjectOutcomes--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Project Outcomes Summary"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1334272/1334272_10265852_1519790145462_Figure1_ProjectOutcomes--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Project Outcomes Summary"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Summary of accomplishments and outcomes with respect to the application of non-traditional materials in the voids of hollow structural section members</div> <div class="imageCredit">Jason McCormick</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Jason&nbsp;Mccormick</div> <div class="imageTitle">Project Outcomes Summary</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Current design methodologies for steel frame systems rely on damage to steel members in specific locations to dissipate energy input into the system by an earthquake, which can lead to an unexpected performance under larger than expected loads and significant economic impact due to the need for extensive repairs prior to re-occupancy. The more pervasive use of non-traditional civil engineering materials in steel systems is an important means to significantly reduce the impact of an earthquake on a structure, but has been limited due to a lack of knowledge of the behavior of these materials under large cyclic loads and past reliance solely on traditional materials (steel, concrete, timber, and masonry). This project addressed this lack of knowledge and enhanced the use of hollow structural sections through the study of an innovative connection configuration and the use of expanding urethane foam in the voids of these sections.  In meeting this goal, the outcomes associated with intellectual merit are the characterization of the behavior of expanding urethane foam under cyclic loads, the confirmation of the ability of lightweight, high energy dissipating materials to inhibit local buckling when applied to the voids of hollow structural section members undergoing bending loads expected during an earthquake, the defining of limiting width-thickness and depth-thickness ratios for the use of urethane foam filled HSS beams in bending application, and the optimization of a collar connection configuration that can allow for more reliable performance with increased quality control and construction speeds due to limited field welding. The results provide a road map for the more extensive use and integration of innovative materials in the design of structures. Interest in the findings extends to other fields of engineering, such as aerospace and mechanical engineering where lightweight, high energy dissipation systems can be valuable.  Numerous project outcomes also are associated with the broader impacts resulting from the project. The project led to one female student completing her doctoral degree and successfully entering structural engineering practice, while an underrepresented undergraduate student from Puerto Rico spent a summer during his undergraduate studies working on the project at the University of Michigan and is now pursuing his own doctoral degree. Over the course of the project a total of three graduate students (1 Ph.D. and 2 Master?s) and four undergraduate students worked on the project where five of these students were from underrepresented groups. The diversity of the research group had a positive impact on the project by continually providing unique perspectives as new challenges arose. Through dissemination and outreach efforts, a number of school age students, university students, and professionals were exposed for the first time to the use of non-traditional materials in structural systems and the potential benefits of thinking out of the box in regards to applications of these materials in hazard mitigation.       Last Modified: 02/27/2018       Submitted by: Jason Mccormick]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
