<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Designing Multi-Level Incentives for Health Care Systems</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/15/2013</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2016</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>200000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>200000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CMMI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Civil, Mechanical, &amp; Manufact Inn</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Georgia-Ann Klutke</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>gaklutke@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922443</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The objective of this award is to analyze and improve multi-level incentive mechanisms in health care to benefit patients, physicians, hospitals and payers. A novel modeling approach based on multiscale decision theory will be developed that can account for the multi-level interdependencies between stakeholders, supports their decision processes and enables the re-design of incentive programs. The approach integrates a new graphical modeling technique with a modular mathematical formulation strategy to compute optimal decisions under uncertainty and to identify effective incentive structures. In a case study, the model will be applied to find mechanisms that can reduce the overuse of computed tomography (CT) scans.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;If successful, the results of this research will lead to improvements in the design of incentives in health care. Better alignment of incentives is one of the key mechanisms to lower costs while improving quality for the U.S. health care system. The benefits to society and economy will be an improvement in health care value, i.e., better health outcomes at lower costs. Fundamental research and advances in multiscale decision theory will lead to novel modeling and solution methods for complex socio-technical systems. The work will also contribute to the education of students and health care professionals on how to use incentives in organizational system design. An international collaboration with Germany will allow students to exchange ideas on health care system improvements from the perspective of their country and culture.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/29/2013</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/29/2013</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1335407</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Christian</FirstName>
<LastName>Wernz</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Christian Wernz</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>cwernz@vcu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>8048289468</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000520591</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/29/2013</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University</Name>
<CityName>BLACKSBURG</CityName>
<ZipCode>240610001</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5402315281</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>Sponsored Programs 0170</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[300 Turner Street NW, Suite 4200]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Virginia</StateName>
<StateCode>VA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>09</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>VA09</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>003137015</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>VIRGINIA POLYTECHNIC INSTITUTE AND STATE UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>003137015</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Virginia Polytechnic Institute]]></Name>
<CityName>Blacksburg</CityName>
<StateCode>VA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>240610001</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[250 Durham Hall]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Virginia</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>09</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>VA09</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1787</Code>
<Text>SERVICE ENTERPRISE SYSTEMS</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>076E</Code>
<Text>SERVICE ENTERPRISE SYSTEMS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>078E</Code>
<Text>ENTERPRISE DESIGN &amp; LOGISTICS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8023</Code>
<Text>Health Care Enterprise Systems</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9147</Code>
<Text>GENERIC TECHNOL FOR MANUFACTURING CELLS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>MANU</Code>
<Text>MANUFACTURING</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0113</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2013~200000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The goal of this project was to analyze payment models and incentives in health care accounting for the objectives and decisions of patients, physicians, hospitals and payers. Better alignment of incentives has been identified as a key mechanism to lower costs while improving quality for the U.S. health care system. One of the challenges in payment and incentive design has been the lack of mathematical models that can capture the complexities of the multi-level health care system and can provide decision insights for stakeholders, including policy makers.</p> <p>We applied and advanced a novel modeling approach called multiscale decision theory (MSDT) that can account for the multi-level interdependencies between stakeholders and enables the analysis of incentive mechanisms. Using MSDT, we conducted a case study on Accountable Care Organizations (ACOs) and the Medicare Shared Savings Programs (MSSP).</p> <p>Our findings show that the current practice of ACOs trying to negotiate for a higher, more lenient cost benchmark (i.e., greater incentives) may lead to higher health care costs <em>and</em> worse health outcomes. However, a too low and too stringent cost benchmark can result in too low utilization rates, and may jeopardize the willingness of the ACO to participate in the first place. The cost benchmark has to be set just right, and our model can be used to determine a benchmark that lowers costs and improves health outcomes.</p> <p>This finding highlights the importance and value of a model-driven and data-driven evaluation of payment and incentive mechanisms. In this research, we have developed the mathematical tools that make such analyses possible.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 10/24/2016<br>      Modified by: Christian&nbsp;Wernz</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The goal of this project was to analyze payment models and incentives in health care accounting for the objectives and decisions of patients, physicians, hospitals and payers. Better alignment of incentives has been identified as a key mechanism to lower costs while improving quality for the U.S. health care system. One of the challenges in payment and incentive design has been the lack of mathematical models that can capture the complexities of the multi-level health care system and can provide decision insights for stakeholders, including policy makers.  We applied and advanced a novel modeling approach called multiscale decision theory (MSDT) that can account for the multi-level interdependencies between stakeholders and enables the analysis of incentive mechanisms. Using MSDT, we conducted a case study on Accountable Care Organizations (ACOs) and the Medicare Shared Savings Programs (MSSP).  Our findings show that the current practice of ACOs trying to negotiate for a higher, more lenient cost benchmark (i.e., greater incentives) may lead to higher health care costs and worse health outcomes. However, a too low and too stringent cost benchmark can result in too low utilization rates, and may jeopardize the willingness of the ACO to participate in the first place. The cost benchmark has to be set just right, and our model can be used to determine a benchmark that lowers costs and improves health outcomes.  This finding highlights the importance and value of a model-driven and data-driven evaluation of payment and incentive mechanisms. In this research, we have developed the mathematical tools that make such analyses possible.       Last Modified: 10/24/2016       Submitted by: Christian Wernz]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
