<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Catastrophic transition to turbulence in rotation-dominated flows</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2013</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>263565.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>268565</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07020000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CBET</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Chem, Bioeng, Env, &amp; Transp Sys</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Ron Joslin</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>rjoslin@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927030</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Lopez, Juan &lt;br/&gt;1336410 &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;In floows with dominant background rotation, Coriolis accelerations provide restoring forces that can act to suppress radial motion, or lead to oscillatory behavior. Such flows are found in a wide range of applications in mechanical engineering (swirl burners, rotating machines), aerospace(vortex-generated lift, fuel tanks of spin-stabilized spacecraft), minerals processing (mixing, suspension and separation), to geophysics (molten planet cores, tropical cyclones). &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Intellectual Merit:&lt;br/&gt;The focus is on understanding the catastrophic transition from laminar to turbulent states in contained rotating &amp;#64258;ows. While there is experimental evidence for this phenomenon, no consensus exists as to the underlying physical mechanism. The two dominant interpretations are that the transition arises either from resonance of inviscid modes or directly as an instability of the basic state. &lt;br/&gt;The PI proposes to resolve this argument by using theoretical, numerical and experimental studies. Simulations and analysis at the PI's laboratory will be complemented with experiments conducted by international collaborators. Precessing rotating flows (where the driving mechanism is temporal variation of the rotation vector) and flows that generate large inertial wave responses through interaction of oscillatory Stokes layers with background rotation (rotation vector is &amp;#64257;xed) will be examined. The research approach will be based in direct numerical simulation and stability analysis of viscous &amp;#64258;ows, so that all the dynamics can be studied and directly matched to experiments.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Broader Impacts:&lt;br/&gt;The scientific problem to be investigated is a fundamental issue that has intrigued researchers for nearly 50 years, and has many potentially important applications, as already mentioned above.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project includes interdisciplinary training of graduate students by mentors who have decades of interdisciplinary research experience between them. Being a part of a larger international collaboration, there will be ample opportunities for exchange visits, providing a valuable training and mentoring experience for all involved. Our involvement with research experiences for undergraduates will be continued, where aspects of the &amp;#64258;ow problems will be isolated into projects suitable for undergraduates. For the broader community, all solvers developed in the project will be freely and readily available.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/16/2013</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/06/2015</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1336410</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Juan</FirstName>
<LastName>Lopez</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>M</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Juan M Lopez</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>jmlopez@asu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>4809658843</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000489211</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/16/2013</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Arizona State University</Name>
<CityName>TEMPE</CityName>
<ZipCode>852816011</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>4809655479</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>ORSPA</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[660 South Mill Avenue, Suite 310]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Arizona</StateName>
<StateCode>AZ</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>09</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>AZ09</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>943360412</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>ARIZONA STATE UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>806345658</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Arizona State University]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>AZ</StateCode>
<ZipCode>852871804</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Arizona</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>09</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>AZ09</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1443</Code>
<Text>FD-Fluid Dynamics</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>058E</Code>
<Text>Newtonian fluids</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9102</Code>
<Text>WOMEN, MINORITY, DISABLED, NEC</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9251</Code>
<Text>REU SUPP-Res Exp for Ugrd Supp</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0113</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0114</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0115</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2013~88526</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~90944</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2015~89095</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>In flows with dominant background rotation, Coriolis accelerations<br />provide restoring forces that can act to suppress radial motion, or<br />lead to oscillatory behavior. Such flows are found in a wide range of<br />applications in mechanical engineering (swirl burners, rotating<br />machines), aerospace (vortex-generated lift, fuel tanks of<br />spin-stabilized spacecraft), minerals processing (mixing, suspension<br />and separation), to geophysics (molten planet cores, tropical<br />cyclones).<br /><br />Strong rotation and weak forcing lead to two limits which in many ways<br />are contradictory. The strong rotation limit is usually taken to imply<br />that viscous dissipation can be neglected, and the weak forcing is<br />taken to imply that nonlinear processes are also negligible. But in<br />any practical sense, neither of these limits are valid and the effects<br />of viscous forces in the small Ekman number, large Reynolds number<br />regime, and the effects of nonlinear mode interactions (such as<br />resonances) in the small forcing amplitude regime, lead to behaviors<br />that are very different from those predicted on the basis of the<br />linear inviscid reduced models. The detailed numerical investigations<br />of the full problem in these challenging regimes considering several<br />distinct but interrelated rapidly rotating flows has shed significant<br />new insight into these problems, resolving many of the apparently<br />pathological results from the reduced models. A dozen papers have been<br />published in the top journals in the field, many more conference<br />presentations as well as invited seminars have been presented,<br />ensuring the widest possible dissemination of the results. An<br />undergraduate student was involve in some of the work. She has now<br />graduated and is working in a STEM field (actuary). A graduate student<br />based her thesis on an aspect of the project. She graduated this past<br />summer and is now a Krener Assistant Professor in the Department of<br />Mathematics at U. C. Davis.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 12/01/2017<br>      Modified by: Juan&nbsp;M&nbsp;Lopez</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ In flows with dominant background rotation, Coriolis accelerations provide restoring forces that can act to suppress radial motion, or lead to oscillatory behavior. Such flows are found in a wide range of applications in mechanical engineering (swirl burners, rotating machines), aerospace (vortex-generated lift, fuel tanks of spin-stabilized spacecraft), minerals processing (mixing, suspension and separation), to geophysics (molten planet cores, tropical cyclones).  Strong rotation and weak forcing lead to two limits which in many ways are contradictory. The strong rotation limit is usually taken to imply that viscous dissipation can be neglected, and the weak forcing is taken to imply that nonlinear processes are also negligible. But in any practical sense, neither of these limits are valid and the effects of viscous forces in the small Ekman number, large Reynolds number regime, and the effects of nonlinear mode interactions (such as resonances) in the small forcing amplitude regime, lead to behaviors that are very different from those predicted on the basis of the linear inviscid reduced models. The detailed numerical investigations of the full problem in these challenging regimes considering several distinct but interrelated rapidly rotating flows has shed significant new insight into these problems, resolving many of the apparently pathological results from the reduced models. A dozen papers have been published in the top journals in the field, many more conference presentations as well as invited seminars have been presented, ensuring the widest possible dissemination of the results. An undergraduate student was involve in some of the work. She has now graduated and is working in a STEM field (actuary). A graduate student based her thesis on an aspect of the project. She graduated this past summer and is now a Krener Assistant Professor in the Department of Mathematics at U. C. Davis.       Last Modified: 12/01/2017       Submitted by: Juan M Lopez]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
