<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Sustainable Co-generation of Hydrogen and Biochar from Biomass via a Novel Alkaline Thermal Treatment</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2013</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>300001.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>300001</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07020000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CBET</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Chem, Bioeng, Env, &amp; Transp Sys</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Carole Read</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>cread@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922418</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>PI: Park, Ah-Hyung&lt;br/&gt;Proposal Number: 1336567&lt;br/&gt;Institution: Columbia University&lt;br/&gt;Title: Sustainable Co-generation of Hydrogen and Biochar from Biomass via a Novel Alkaline Thermal Treatment&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project investigates biomass conversion to COx-free hydrogen (H2) with co-generation of biochar via a novel alkaline thermal treatment. CO and CO2, commonly produced during pyrolysis, will react with the alkali metal hydroxide to form stable metal carbonates leading to gaseous product that is free of carbon. Thus, the produced hydrogen can directly be used in fuel cells for electricity generation without subsequent gas cleanup/upgrade steps. In this study, both non-catalyzed and catalyzed reactions of biomass and hydroxide will be investigated to optimize and evaluate the overall sustainability of the proposed biomass conversion scheme. If successful, this transformative approach to biomass conversion will provide an important stepping stone for the development of a sustainable energy pathway based on carbon-neutral bioenergy.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The fundamental reaction kinetic and mechanistic studies will reveal important reaction pathways for forming a carbon-free hydrogen stream from various biomass feedstocks. The findings from this complex solid-solid reaction scheme involving in-situ carbon capture will not only provide the proof-of-concept of this novel biomass conversion technology but also the fundamental basis for other biomass conversion technologies. Ultimately, if successful, this technology will advance the field of sustainable energy generation by allowing the traditional energy consumers to be able to engage in the decision making process in energy production or even become energy producers themselves. The main technological benefits of the proposed biomass-to-H2 scheme include the co-generation of H2 and biochar, significant reduction in carbon emissions with the potential to be carbon-negative, no need for additional gas cleanup steps, and a simplified reactor design.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The team?s educational and outreach activities include: to promote the international research and educational collaborations in the proposed research area; to motivate K-12 students, particularly female and minority students, to pursue a career in science and engineering; to provide academic research experience for both graduate and undergraduate students; and to enable the development of a new curriculum reflecting an increasing interest in green energy and environmental issues.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/08/2013</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/08/2013</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1336567</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Jingguang</FirstName>
<LastName>Chen</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>G</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Jingguang G Chen</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>jgchen@columbia.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2128546166</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000205530</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/08/2013</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Ah-Hyung Alissa</FirstName>
<LastName>Park</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Ah-Hyung Alissa Park</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>ap2622@columbia.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2128548989</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000509281</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/08/2013</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Camille</FirstName>
<LastName>Petit</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Camille Petit</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>cp2577@columbia.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2128546851</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000642185</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/08/2013</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Columbia University</Name>
<CityName>NEW YORK</CityName>
<ZipCode>100276902</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2128546851</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>2960 Broadway</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>10</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NY10</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>049179401</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>TRUSTEES OF COLUMBIA UNIVERSITY IN THE CITY OF NEW YORK, THE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>049179401</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Columbia University]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<ZipCode>100277922</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>13</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NY13</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7644</Code>
<Text>EchemS-Electrochemical Systems</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>002E</Code>
<Text>Bio-energy</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0113</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2013~300001</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The need for energy is growing continuously with a large fraction of the demand stemming from the significant growth in emerging economies. Although fossil fuels are currently a viable energy source, they will have to be replaced by renewables in the future due supply limitations and the damaging effects of anthropogenic CO<sub>2</sub>. Biomass is one of the oldest renewable resources and is frequently used in developing countries, especially those with large rural communities. Since its carbon content is derived from CO<sub>2</sub>during photosynthesis, it is a carbon neutral feedstock and therefore environmentally benign.&nbsp;</p> <p>The centralized combustion of biomass is often energetically inefficient due to its high moisture content and low energy density. Furthermore, concerns over climate change and anthropogenic CO<sub>2</sub>require energy conversion pathways with a reduced carbon footprint. By integrating a carbon sequestration scheme into biomass conversion, the technology could not only be carbon-neutral, but potentially carbon-negative; such technologies are called BECCS (Bio-Energy with Carbon Capture and Storage).</p> <p>Thus, this project focused on the development of a biomass conversion reaction that can treat wet biomass with integrated carbon capture scheme. In order to eliminate the energy intensive transportation step, we searched for a reaction that can occur under mild pressure and temperature, which will allow the development of a reactor system that can be mass produced and installed even at households with an ease of operations.&nbsp;</p> <p>Our study showed that the Alkaline Thermal Treatment (ATT) reaction is capable of producing H<sub>2</sub>by reacting biomass (i.e., glucose, cellulose and hemicellulose) with a metal hydroxide at moderate temperatures, while simultaneously capturing the carbon as a thermodynamically stable carbonate.&nbsp;The focus of the research was to establish a comprehensive understanding of the biomass-hydroxide-water reactions in the presence of gas-phase and/or solid-phase catalysts. The role of hydroxide as well as the overall reaction mechanisms were investigated in details and the research findings provided valuable insights into the ATT of biomass and their potential as a BECCS technology.This study has shown that the conversion of biomass to H<sub>2</sub>with suppressed CO<sub>2</sub>formation can be achieved through the reforming of gaseous compounds in a fixed bed of Ca(OH)<sub>2</sub>and 10% Ni/ZrO<sub>2</sub>. Reforming occurs at low temperatures &le;773 K, which could allow improved process safety and sustainability.&nbsp;</p> <p class="ColorfulList-Accent11"><strong>Intellectual Merit&nbsp;</strong>-&nbsp;This study provided a valuable insight into a less studied biomass conversion reaction that is integrated with carbon capture and storage. Since this reaction scheme is developed for a distributed energy conversion system, our proposal on the deployment of the ATT reactors in household settings initiated interesting discussions on how to enable the traditional energy consumers to be able to engage in the decision-making process in energy production or even become energy producers themselves.</p> <p class="ColorfulList-Accent11"><strong>Broader Impact -</strong>As an integral part of this project, the team promoted the international research and educational collaborations in the area of BECCS via workshops attended by invited experts in various fields and student exchange efforts. We also worked with K-12, undergraduate and masters students, particularly female and minority students. They are now pursuing their careers in science and engineering and many of them are continuing their education in graduate schools.&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 05/27/2018<br>      Modified by: Ah-Hyung Alissa&nbsp;Park</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The need for energy is growing continuously with a large fraction of the demand stemming from the significant growth in emerging economies. Although fossil fuels are currently a viable energy source, they will have to be replaced by renewables in the future due supply limitations and the damaging effects of anthropogenic CO2. Biomass is one of the oldest renewable resources and is frequently used in developing countries, especially those with large rural communities. Since its carbon content is derived from CO2during photosynthesis, it is a carbon neutral feedstock and therefore environmentally benign.   The centralized combustion of biomass is often energetically inefficient due to its high moisture content and low energy density. Furthermore, concerns over climate change and anthropogenic CO2require energy conversion pathways with a reduced carbon footprint. By integrating a carbon sequestration scheme into biomass conversion, the technology could not only be carbon-neutral, but potentially carbon-negative; such technologies are called BECCS (Bio-Energy with Carbon Capture and Storage).  Thus, this project focused on the development of a biomass conversion reaction that can treat wet biomass with integrated carbon capture scheme. In order to eliminate the energy intensive transportation step, we searched for a reaction that can occur under mild pressure and temperature, which will allow the development of a reactor system that can be mass produced and installed even at households with an ease of operations.   Our study showed that the Alkaline Thermal Treatment (ATT) reaction is capable of producing H2by reacting biomass (i.e., glucose, cellulose and hemicellulose) with a metal hydroxide at moderate temperatures, while simultaneously capturing the carbon as a thermodynamically stable carbonate. The focus of the research was to establish a comprehensive understanding of the biomass-hydroxide-water reactions in the presence of gas-phase and/or solid-phase catalysts. The role of hydroxide as well as the overall reaction mechanisms were investigated in details and the research findings provided valuable insights into the ATT of biomass and their potential as a BECCS technology.This study has shown that the conversion of biomass to H2with suppressed CO2formation can be achieved through the reforming of gaseous compounds in a fixed bed of Ca(OH)2and 10% Ni/ZrO2. Reforming occurs at low temperatures &le;773 K, which could allow improved process safety and sustainability.  Intellectual Merit - This study provided a valuable insight into a less studied biomass conversion reaction that is integrated with carbon capture and storage. Since this reaction scheme is developed for a distributed energy conversion system, our proposal on the deployment of the ATT reactors in household settings initiated interesting discussions on how to enable the traditional energy consumers to be able to engage in the decision-making process in energy production or even become energy producers themselves. Broader Impact -As an integral part of this project, the team promoted the international research and educational collaborations in the area of BECCS via workshops attended by invited experts in various fields and student exchange efforts. We also worked with K-12, undergraduate and masters students, particularly female and minority students. They are now pursuing their careers in science and engineering and many of them are continuing their education in graduate schools.           Last Modified: 05/27/2018       Submitted by: Ah-Hyung Alissa Park]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
