<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>The effect of sociality on transmission and spread of a multi-host pathogen</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>11/01/2012</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>1647668.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>1647668</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>08010208</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>BIO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DEB</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Environmental Biology</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Deborah Winslow</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>White-Nose Syndrome is a fungal disease that affects bats hibernating in caves. Since it was first identified in the eastern United States in 2006, the disease has spread from cave to cave across the Northeast, as far south as Tennessee, and as far west as Oklahoma and Ontario.  Over a million bats have died from the fungus, called Geomyces destructans or Gd by scientists, which flourishes in the cool conditions of caves. The goal of this research project is to gain a better understanding how the disease is transmitted at local, regional, and continental scales. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The researchers will focus in particular on bat social behavior, such as the size of congregating groups and assortment within groups, which are known to vary both within and between bat species during different seasons. They hypothesize that disease transmission from bat to bat and cave to cave is affected by temporal and spatial variation in how bat social groups are organized. They will collect data to see if transmission increases with colony size and with how often and for how long bats are aroused during hibernation; if cave temperature and humidity affect the growth of the fungus; if the number of different bat species present in a region influences the prevalence of the disease; if some species are more susceptible than others; and if geographic latitude and having more places to hibernate in a given area promotes the development and spread of White-Nose Syndrome in local bat populations. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The researchers will use these data to create a predictive behavior-based model of disease transmission. Bats are significant in North American ecology because they control insects and pollinate plants. Understanding how this devastating disease develops and spreads is critical to protecting bat populations and the ecosystem services they provide. The researchers, who come from multiple disciplines and several universities (Boston University, the University of California-Santa Cruz, Northern Arizona University, and the University of Tennessee), also will train graduate and undergraduate students in the conduct of the research. They will share their results with resource managers and policy makers at state and federal levels, and will participate in Congressional briefings and in the United States Fish and Wildlife Service's White-Nose Syndrome National Plan.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>02/28/2013</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>01/22/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.074</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1336290</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Gary</FirstName>
<LastName>McCracken</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>F</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Gary F McCracken</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>gmccrack@utk.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>8659746194</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000185196</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/27/2013</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>A. Marm</FirstName>
<LastName>Kilpatrick</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>A. Marm Kilpatrick</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>akilpatr@ucsc.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>8314595070</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000455731</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>02/28/2013</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Winifred</FirstName>
<LastName>Frick</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>F</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Winifred F Frick</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>wfrick@batcon.org</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>8312473189</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000515870</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/07/2013</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Jeffrey</FirstName>
<LastName>Foster</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>T</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Jeffrey T Foster</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>jeff.foster@nau.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>9285234008</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000537025</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/27/2013</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of California-Santa Cruz</Name>
<CityName>Santa Cruz</CityName>
<ZipCode>950641077</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>8314595278</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1156 High Street</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>20</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CA20</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>125084723</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF CALIFORNIA, SANTA CRUZ</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>071549000</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of California-Santa Cruz]]></Name>
<CityName>Santa Cruz</CityName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>950641077</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[1156 High Street]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>20</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CA20</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7242</Code>
<Text>Ecology of Infectious Diseases</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7242</Code>
<Text>ECOLOGY OF INFECTIOUS DISEASES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0111</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2011~1647666</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p class="MsoNormal" style="margin-bottom: 7.5pt; line-height: normal;"><span style="font-size: 9pt; font-family: Arial, sans-serif;">Transmission of pathogens that cause infectious diseases is inherently a social process. How social groups are organized in space and time determine how transmission among individuals scales up to the spread of disease across populations and landscapes. However, the influence of variation in sociality on pathogen spread in wildlife remains a critical gap in our knowledge. We examined the influence of sociality on the ecology of white-nose syndrome (WNS), an emerging infectious disease of hibernating bats caused by the fungus <em>Pseudogymnoascus destructans&nbsp;</em>(<em>Pd</em>). WNS was first detected in NY in 2006 and has since spread rapidly across North America. Some key findings from our research include:</span></p> <p class="MsoNormal" style="margin-bottom: 7.5pt; line-height: normal;"><strong><span style="font-size: 9pt; font-family: Arial, sans-serif;">- Pd infection is seasonal, and is jointly determined by contact with environmental reservoirs and bat hibernation behavior.</span></strong><span style="font-size: 9pt; font-family: Arial, sans-serif;">&nbsp;Bats initially become exposed to Pd during fall when they return to hibernacula to mate, but infection levels remain low when bats are active. However, Pd loads on bats increase approximately 100-fold during winter when bats hibernate. Bats that survive WNS clear infection from the surface of their skin over the summer, but get re-infected each fall.</span></p> <p class="MsoNormal" style="margin-bottom: 7.5pt; line-height: normal;"><strong><span style="font-size: 9pt; font-family: Arial, sans-serif;">- Pd contamination of caves and mines where bats hibernate plays a key role in re-infecting bats early in winter and contributes to the severe mortality observed.</span></strong><span style="font-size: 9pt; font-family: Arial, sans-serif;">&nbsp;Long term persistence of Pd, which occurs even in the absence of bats, results in most bats in six different species becoming infected each winter. Saturation of infection in bats begins two years after Pd invasion and persists for at least a decade subsequently.</span></p> <p class="MsoNormal" style="margin-bottom: 7.5pt; line-height: normal;"><strong><span style="font-size: 9pt; font-family: Arial, sans-serif;">- WNS has killed millions of bats, including tens of thousands of bats in individual colonies. However, impacts have been variable among species and populations.</span></strong><span style="font-size: 9pt; font-family: Arial, sans-serif;">&nbsp;WNS has had regional population impacts on six species of hibernating bats, with three species declining sharply (&gt;65%) in the initial year following WNS detection, and three species suffering moderate impacts (30-40% reductions in population growth rates).&nbsp; Initial population declines were equally severe across a wide range of colony sizes (100-100,000 bats) for two social bat species but were less severe in smaller colonies than in larger colonies for two solitary species. Declines of two social species were more severe in warmer and more humid sites. The two social species became more solitary as colonies declined in size.</span></p> <p class="MsoNormal" style="margin-bottom: 7.5pt; line-height: normal;"><strong><span style="font-size: 9pt; font-family: Arial, sans-serif;">- Species roosting at warmer temperatures have the highest fungal loads and suffer the greatest population impacts from WNS.</span></strong><span style="font-size: 9pt; font-family: Arial, sans-serif;">&nbsp;One species, the northern long-eared bat, is on a trajectory towards extinction.</span></p> <p class="MsoNormal" style="margin-bottom: 7.5pt; line-height: normal;"><strong><span style="font-size: 9pt; font-family: Arial, sans-serif;">- WNS has extirpated many bat colonies and reduced colony sizes of bats in eastern North America by an order of magnitude, but some colonies persist, apparently by multiple mechanisms.&nbsp;</span></strong><span style="font-size: 9pt; font-family: Arial, sans-serif;">North American bat colonies are now similar in size to the much smaller colonies of bat species in Europe. WNS has extirpated 6-69% of colonies of six species of bats, with larger colonies usually being less likely to be extirpated. Some colonies of one species, little brown bats, are now persisting with the fungus. In some of these colonies fungal growth is limited whereas in others bats appear to be tolerating high fungal loads. Some persisting colonies also now have higher fat stores than during WNS invasion which allows them to partly tolerate the physiological impacts WNS.</span></p> <p class="MsoNormal" style="margin-bottom: 7.5pt; line-height: normal;"><strong><span style="font-size: 9pt; font-family: Arial, sans-serif;">- Pd is widespread throughout Eurasia, but fungal loads on Eurasian bats are orders of magnitude lower than in declining populations in North America.</span></strong><span style="font-size: 9pt; font-family: Arial, sans-serif;">&nbsp;Colony size, winter severity and temperature could not explain these differences in fungal loads.</span></p> <p class="MsoNormal" style="margin-bottom: 7.5pt; line-height: normal;"><strong><span style="font-size: 9pt; font-family: Arial, sans-serif;">- Bacteria isolated from bats&rsquo; skin microbiome reduced Pd growth in vitro, reduced WNS lesions in a laboratory challenge study, and increased survival in lab and field trials.&nbsp;</span></strong><span style="font-size: 9pt; font-family: Arial, sans-serif;">Unfortunately, survival of treated bats was still insufficient to support a stable population, so a multi-pronged approach is required.</span></p> <p class="MsoNormal" style="margin-bottom: 7.5pt; line-height: normal;"><strong><span style="font-size: 9pt; font-family: Arial, sans-serif;">- We developed a management framework for combating wildlife diseases and conserving species threatened by disease.</span></strong><span style="font-size: 9pt; font-family: Arial, sans-serif;">&nbsp; Conservation of wildlife populations impacted by wildlife disease should be tailored to the stage of pathogen invasion with riskier strategies employed earlier and supportive strategies later. This framework informed the USFWS management plan for WNS, and the management of an emerging disease of salamanders in Europe.</span></p> <p class="MsoNormal" style="margin-bottom: 7.5pt; line-height: normal;"><strong><span style="font-size: 9pt; font-family: Arial, sans-serif;">- We trained 13 graduate students, 32 undergraduate students, four high school students, and three post-doctoral scholars.</span></strong></p> <p class="MsoNormal" style="margin-bottom: 7.5pt; line-height: normal;"><strong><span style="font-size: 9pt; font-family: Arial, sans-serif;">- The findings from this work were widely disseminated</span></strong><span style="font-size: 9pt; font-family: Arial, sans-serif;">, including: a) 119 presentations at conferences, invited university conferences, and other venues; b) congressional briefings with four members of congress; c) coverage by the popular press including New York Times, Washington Post, Newsweek, BBC, NPR, Quirks and quarks, Reuters, Associated Press, Aljazeera News, USA Today, IFLScience!, Discovery News, Nature News, Science News, Scientific American, Breitbart News, NBC News, San Francisco Chronicle; d) Undergraduate courses taught at four universities; e) the white-nose syndrome Wikipedia page (<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/White-nose_syndrome">https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/White-nose_syndrome</a>).</span></p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 12/14/2017<br>      Modified by: A. Marm&nbsp;Kilpatrick</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Images (<span id="selectedPhoto0">1</span> of <span class="totalNumber"></span>)           </div> <div class="galControls" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1336290/1336290_10132545_1513017391610_InfectedPESUMYLU--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1336290/1336290_10132545_1513017391610_InfectedPESUMYLU--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Infected bats"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1336290/1336290_10132545_1513017391610_InfectedPESUMYLU--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Infected bats"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Little brown bat (Myotis lucifugus) and tri-colored bat (Perimyotis subflavus) infected with Pseudogymnoascus destructans, the fungus that causes white-nose syndrome.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Joseph Hoyt</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">A. Marm&nbsp;Kilpatrick</div> <div class="imageTitle">Infected bats</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1336290/1336290_10132545_1513015641520_LangwigetalPhilTransFig1--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1336290/1336290_10132545_1513015641520_LangwigetalPhilTransFig1--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Langwig et al 2016 Fig 1"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1336290/1336290_10132545_1513015641520_LangwigetalPhilTransFig1--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Langwig et al 2016 Fig 1"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">White-nose syndrome (WNS) extent, March 2016 (hatched), and distributions of 6 bat species (colours). Insets show counts of colonies, 1979 to 2011, with mean 1st year WNS declines in percent. Phil. Trans. R. Soc. B 371: 20150456 dx.doi.org/10.1098/rstb.2015.0456 Fig 1</div> <div class="imageCredit">Kate Langwig</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">A. Marm&nbsp;Kilpatrick</div> <div class="imageTitle">Langwig et al 2016 Fig 1</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1336290/1336290_10132545_1513016145860_FricketalGEBFigure1--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1336290/1336290_10132545_1513016145860_FricketalGEBFigure1--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Frick et al 2015 GEB Fig 1"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1336290/1336290_10132545_1513016145860_FricketalGEBFigure1--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Frick et al 2015 GEB Fig 1"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Impacts of white-nose syndrome (WNS) on colony sizes of hibernating bats in North America, before and after the emergence of WNS, compared to Europe. Bat photos by Al Hicks and Ivan Horacek. Glob Ecol Biog (2015) 24: 741?749 DOI: 10.1111/geb.12290 Fig 1</div> <div class="imageCredit">Winifred Frick</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">A. Marm&nbsp;Kilpatrick</div> <div class="imageTitle">Frick et al 2015 GEB Fig 1</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1336290/1336290_10132545_1513016845828_globalpd--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1336290/1336290_10132545_1513016845828_globalpd--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Hoyt et al 2016 EID Fig 1"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1336290/1336290_10132545_1513016845828_globalpd--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Hoyt et al 2016 EID Fig 1"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Global distribution of white-nose syndrome (WNS). Distribution in central Asia based on distributions of bat species found infected. Extent of WNS in North America as of 2016. Emerg Inf Diseases (2016) 22 140-2 dx.doi.org/10.3201/eid2201.151314 Fig 1</div> <div class="imageCredit">Joseph Hoyt</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">A. Marm&nbsp;Kilpatrick</div> <div class="imageTitle">Hoyt et al 2016 EID Fig 1</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1336290/1336290_10132545_1513017574292_Rowoflittlebrownbats--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1336290/1336290_10132545_1513017574292_Rowoflittlebrownbats--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Myotis lucifugus cluster"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1336290/1336290_10132545_1513017574292_Rowoflittlebrownbats--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Myotis lucifugus cluster"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Cluster of little brown bats (Myotis lucifugus) hibernating in a cave in Wisconsin. This highly social species has been heavily impacted by white-nose syndrome.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Marm Kilpatrick</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">A. Marm&nbsp;Kilpatrick</div> <div class="imageTitle">Myotis lucifugus cluster</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1336290/1336290_10132545_1513015008174_FricketalEcologyFig3--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1336290/1336290_10132545_1513015008174_FricketalEcologyFig3--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Frick et al 2017 Ecology Fig 3"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1336290/1336290_10132545_1513015008174_FricketalEcologyFig3--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Frick et al 2017 Ecology Fig 3"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Pathogen spread, population declines, and fungal loads. Map colors show time since Pseudogymnoascus destructans (Pd) arrival. Panels show population trajectories and fungal loads for 8 colonies of Myotis lucifugus and Perimyotis subflavus. Ecology, 98(3), 2017, pp. 624?631 doi/10.1002/ecy.1706 Fig 3</div> <div class="imageCredit">Winifred Frick</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">A. Marm&nbsp;Kilpatrick</div> <div class="imageTitle">Frick et al 2017 Ecology Fig 3</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[Transmission of pathogens that cause infectious diseases is inherently a social process. How social groups are organized in space and time determine how transmission among individuals scales up to the spread of disease across populations and landscapes. However, the influence of variation in sociality on pathogen spread in wildlife remains a critical gap in our knowledge. We examined the influence of sociality on the ecology of white-nose syndrome (WNS), an emerging infectious disease of hibernating bats caused by the fungus Pseudogymnoascus destructans (Pd). WNS was first detected in NY in 2006 and has since spread rapidly across North America. Some key findings from our research include: - Pd infection is seasonal, and is jointly determined by contact with environmental reservoirs and bat hibernation behavior. Bats initially become exposed to Pd during fall when they return to hibernacula to mate, but infection levels remain low when bats are active. However, Pd loads on bats increase approximately 100-fold during winter when bats hibernate. Bats that survive WNS clear infection from the surface of their skin over the summer, but get re-infected each fall. - Pd contamination of caves and mines where bats hibernate plays a key role in re-infecting bats early in winter and contributes to the severe mortality observed. Long term persistence of Pd, which occurs even in the absence of bats, results in most bats in six different species becoming infected each winter. Saturation of infection in bats begins two years after Pd invasion and persists for at least a decade subsequently. - WNS has killed millions of bats, including tens of thousands of bats in individual colonies. However, impacts have been variable among species and populations. WNS has had regional population impacts on six species of hibernating bats, with three species declining sharply (&gt;65%) in the initial year following WNS detection, and three species suffering moderate impacts (30-40% reductions in population growth rates).  Initial population declines were equally severe across a wide range of colony sizes (100-100,000 bats) for two social bat species but were less severe in smaller colonies than in larger colonies for two solitary species. Declines of two social species were more severe in warmer and more humid sites. The two social species became more solitary as colonies declined in size. - Species roosting at warmer temperatures have the highest fungal loads and suffer the greatest population impacts from WNS. One species, the northern long-eared bat, is on a trajectory towards extinction. - WNS has extirpated many bat colonies and reduced colony sizes of bats in eastern North America by an order of magnitude, but some colonies persist, apparently by multiple mechanisms. North American bat colonies are now similar in size to the much smaller colonies of bat species in Europe. WNS has extirpated 6-69% of colonies of six species of bats, with larger colonies usually being less likely to be extirpated. Some colonies of one species, little brown bats, are now persisting with the fungus. In some of these colonies fungal growth is limited whereas in others bats appear to be tolerating high fungal loads. Some persisting colonies also now have higher fat stores than during WNS invasion which allows them to partly tolerate the physiological impacts WNS. - Pd is widespread throughout Eurasia, but fungal loads on Eurasian bats are orders of magnitude lower than in declining populations in North America. Colony size, winter severity and temperature could not explain these differences in fungal loads. - Bacteria isolated from bats? skin microbiome reduced Pd growth in vitro, reduced WNS lesions in a laboratory challenge study, and increased survival in lab and field trials. Unfortunately, survival of treated bats was still insufficient to support a stable population, so a multi-pronged approach is required. - We developed a management framework for combating wildlife diseases and conserving species threatened by disease.  Conservation of wildlife populations impacted by wildlife disease should be tailored to the stage of pathogen invasion with riskier strategies employed earlier and supportive strategies later. This framework informed the USFWS management plan for WNS, and the management of an emerging disease of salamanders in Europe. - We trained 13 graduate students, 32 undergraduate students, four high school students, and three post-doctoral scholars. - The findings from this work were widely disseminated, including: a) 119 presentations at conferences, invited university conferences, and other venues; b) congressional briefings with four members of congress; c) coverage by the popular press including New York Times, Washington Post, Newsweek, BBC, NPR, Quirks and quarks, Reuters, Associated Press, Aljazeera News, USA Today, IFLScience!, Discovery News, Nature News, Science News, Scientific American, Breitbart News, NBC News, San Francisco Chronicle; d) Undergraduate courses taught at four universities; e) the white-nose syndrome Wikipedia page (https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/White-nose_syndrome).       Last Modified: 12/14/2017       Submitted by: A. Marm Kilpatrick]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
