<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Collaborative Research: High Temperature and Pressure Char Kinetics - Diagnostic development, Gasifier experiments, and Modeling</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2013</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>02/28/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>154993.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>184023</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07020000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CBET</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Chem, Bioeng, Env, &amp; Transp Sys</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Song-Charng Kong</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>1336364/1336643&lt;br/&gt;Rieker/Porter&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Current water treatment methodologies are not designed to handle emerging contamination threats derived from agricultural run-off, volatile organic compounds, and pharmaceutical residues?advanced methods are therefore needed. Plasma production in liquid water produces a host of advanced oxidation agents that have the capacity to rapidly decompose organic contaminants. The proposed effort investigates a novel method of producing plasma in bubbles immersed in water by driving them at resonance in the presence of an electric field. This effort studies the ignition physics of resonantly driven bubbles, the time evolution of plasma formation in such bubbles, and the chemistry of the active interfacial layer separating the plasma bubble and the liquid water.  The understanding gained from these studies will be used to design and build a plasma reactor for the purpose of water purification. As part of the educational outreach thrust of this effort, lab tours and demonstrations will be given to visiting grade school students from programs such as the Detroit Area Pre-College Engineering Program and those sponsored by Women in Science and Engineering, using in-house fabricated plasma demonstration experiments.  In addition to sponsoring a student from the Summer Research Opportunity Program (SROP), a program aimed at encouraging underrepresented students to attend graduate school, we will also integrate plasma demonstrations into the existing educational outreach effort led by the National Society of Black Engineers, which involves actually visiting at risk schools in the area for the purpose of inspiring students with hands on experiments, mini-lessons, and mentorship.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/03/2013</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>09/06/2017</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1336364</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Jason</FirstName>
<LastName>Porter</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>M</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Jason M Porter</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>jporter@mines.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>3032733683</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000625664</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/03/2013</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Colorado School of Mines</Name>
<CityName>Golden</CityName>
<ZipCode>804011887</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>3032733000</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1500 Illinois</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Colorado</StateName>
<StateCode>CO</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CO07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>010628170</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>TRUSTEES OF THE COLORADO SCHOOL OF MINES</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>010628170</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Colorado School of Mines]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>CO</StateCode>
<ZipCode>804011887</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Colorado</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CO07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1407</Code>
<Text>CFS-Combustion &amp; Fire Systems</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>5761</Code>
<Text>IUCRC-Indust-Univ Coop Res Ctr</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>018Z</Code>
<Text>Grad Prep APG:Enhan. Activities</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>061E</Code>
<Text>Fire</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0113</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0117</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2013~154993</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2017~29030</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Educational outcomes</p> <p>One PhD student, Madison Kelley (Spring 2013 &ndash; Fall 2017) and four undergraduate researchers were supported under this grant.&nbsp;&nbsp;Andrew Potter (Fall 2013 &ndash; Spring 2014),&nbsp;Alex Lampe (Fall 2014 &ndash; Spring 2015), and Kit Lewis (Fall 2014)&nbsp;designed and built a new coal powder feeding system for the gasifier.&nbsp;&nbsp;Alex also designed and built custom dropout tanks for condensed water and particle separation. &nbsp;</p> <p>As part of this program, an outreach program with Red Rocks Community College students to participate in an 8-week summer research experience was developed. In 2015, I collaborated with Liz Cox (RRCC STEM Director) and Chuck Stone (REMRSEC REU Director) to integrate the RRCC program into the existing REU activities.&nbsp;&nbsp;This program supported one RRCC student to do work in my lab in the summer of 2015 under the supervision of the PhD student supported by this grant, Madison Kelley.&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;Sean is co-author on two conference papers.</p> <p>Infrastructure outcomes</p> <p>This grant supported the recommissioning and modification of a laboratory-scale gasifier for single-particle experiments.&nbsp;&nbsp;A new particle feeding system was designed and fabricated for entrained flow studies.&nbsp;This configuration is reported in one journal paper and one conference paper:&nbsp;</p> <p>M. A. Kelley, et al., System overview and characterization of a high-temperature, high-pressure, entrained-flow, laboratory-scale gasifier, Review of Scientific Instruments, (2015) vol. 86, no. 5, p. 055106.</p> <p>M. Kelley, J. Porter, System overview and preliminary characterization of the high-temperature and pressure entrained-flow lab-scale gasifier at CSM, Thirty-First Annual Pittsburgh Coal Conference, Oct 6-9, (2014), Pittsburgh, PA.</p> <p>The internal reactor column was modified to allow for line-of-sight optical access to the high pressure and temperature flow.&nbsp;&nbsp;In collaboration with researchers at CU Boulder in Dr. Greg Rieker&rsquo;s group, we demonstrated frequency-comb measurements of water vapor concentration and temperature at the conditions of the study.&nbsp;&nbsp;(Manuscript in preparation)&nbsp;</p> <p>A new steam injection system and single-particle extraction probe was designed and fabricated for the single particle char kinetics studies.&nbsp;&nbsp;This system allowed for precise particle reaction times and direct measurements of carbon conversion rates. &nbsp;</p> <p>Scholarly outcomes</p> <p>Activated carbon was selected as a char surrogate for the study.&nbsp;&nbsp;Several activate carbon samples were selected and thoroughly characterized including samples from biomass and coal feedstocks.&nbsp;&nbsp;This characterization of the initial char was an essential contribution of this study, as there is a lack of conversion studies with well-characterized initial feedstocks.&nbsp;&nbsp;This characterization is reported in one conference paper:</p> <p>M. A. Kelley, et al., Activated carbon as a potential char surrogate in char kinetics studies, Western States Section of Combustion Institute, October 5-6, (2015), Provo, UT</p> <p>A coal-derived activated carbon was selected for high temperature and pressure steam gasification studies.&nbsp;&nbsp;Single particles on the order of 2 mm were selected for reaction in the gasifier.&nbsp;These experiments were conducted under regime II conditions (neither kinetics nor mass transfer are rate limiting); this is the typical condition experienced in commercial gasification.&nbsp;The resulting dataset is being published as:</p> <p>M. A. Kelley, et al., A novel single particle study of steam gasification kinetics of a coal-derived char at high temperatures and pressures, 37<sup>th</sup>International Symposium on Combustion, Dublin, IR, July 29-Aug 3, 2018. (Accepted)</p> <p>This dataset provides a rare complete characterization and reaction study at temperatures to 1400C and 15 atm and will provide valuable validation data for gasification modelers.&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 06/26/2018<br>      Modified by: Jason&nbsp;M&nbsp;Porter</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Image         </div> <div class="galControls onePhoto" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation onePhoto" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1336364/1336364_10255922_1529988485491_Single_particle--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1336364/1336364_10255922_1529988485491_Single_particle--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Steam-char gasification"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1336364/1336364_10255922_1529988485491_Single_particle--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Steam-char gasification"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">A single 2mm char particle supported in a flow of pure steam at 1200C and 1 bar.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Madison Kelley</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Royalty-free (restricted use - cannot be shared)</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Jason&nbsp;M&nbsp;Porter</div> <div class="imageTitle">Steam-char gasification</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Educational outcomes  One PhD student, Madison Kelley (Spring 2013 &ndash; Fall 2017) and four undergraduate researchers were supported under this grant.  Andrew Potter (Fall 2013 &ndash; Spring 2014), Alex Lampe (Fall 2014 &ndash; Spring 2015), and Kit Lewis (Fall 2014) designed and built a new coal powder feeding system for the gasifier.  Alex also designed and built custom dropout tanks for condensed water and particle separation.    As part of this program, an outreach program with Red Rocks Community College students to participate in an 8-week summer research experience was developed. In 2015, I collaborated with Liz Cox (RRCC STEM Director) and Chuck Stone (REMRSEC REU Director) to integrate the RRCC program into the existing REU activities.  This program supported one RRCC student to do work in my lab in the summer of 2015 under the supervision of the PhD student supported by this grant, Madison Kelley.   Sean is co-author on two conference papers.  Infrastructure outcomes  This grant supported the recommissioning and modification of a laboratory-scale gasifier for single-particle experiments.  A new particle feeding system was designed and fabricated for entrained flow studies. This configuration is reported in one journal paper and one conference paper:   M. A. Kelley, et al., System overview and characterization of a high-temperature, high-pressure, entrained-flow, laboratory-scale gasifier, Review of Scientific Instruments, (2015) vol. 86, no. 5, p. 055106.  M. Kelley, J. Porter, System overview and preliminary characterization of the high-temperature and pressure entrained-flow lab-scale gasifier at CSM, Thirty-First Annual Pittsburgh Coal Conference, Oct 6-9, (2014), Pittsburgh, PA.  The internal reactor column was modified to allow for line-of-sight optical access to the high pressure and temperature flow.  In collaboration with researchers at CU Boulder in Dr. Greg Rieker?s group, we demonstrated frequency-comb measurements of water vapor concentration and temperature at the conditions of the study.  (Manuscript in preparation)   A new steam injection system and single-particle extraction probe was designed and fabricated for the single particle char kinetics studies.  This system allowed for precise particle reaction times and direct measurements of carbon conversion rates.    Scholarly outcomes  Activated carbon was selected as a char surrogate for the study.  Several activate carbon samples were selected and thoroughly characterized including samples from biomass and coal feedstocks.  This characterization of the initial char was an essential contribution of this study, as there is a lack of conversion studies with well-characterized initial feedstocks.  This characterization is reported in one conference paper:  M. A. Kelley, et al., Activated carbon as a potential char surrogate in char kinetics studies, Western States Section of Combustion Institute, October 5-6, (2015), Provo, UT  A coal-derived activated carbon was selected for high temperature and pressure steam gasification studies.  Single particles on the order of 2 mm were selected for reaction in the gasifier. These experiments were conducted under regime II conditions (neither kinetics nor mass transfer are rate limiting); this is the typical condition experienced in commercial gasification. The resulting dataset is being published as:  M. A. Kelley, et al., A novel single particle study of steam gasification kinetics of a coal-derived char at high temperatures and pressures, 37thInternational Symposium on Combustion, Dublin, IR, July 29-Aug 3, 2018. (Accepted)  This dataset provides a rare complete characterization and reaction study at temperatures to 1400C and 15 atm and will provide valuable validation data for gasification modelers.           Last Modified: 06/26/2018       Submitted by: Jason M Porter]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
