<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>MRI:   Acquisition of an Environmental Transmission Electron Microscope for Research and Education in Materials Chemistry</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/15/2013</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2016</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>1155034.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>1155034</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03070000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DMR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Materials Research</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Leonard Spinu</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>lspinu@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922665</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>1337731&lt;br/&gt;Yang&lt;br/&gt;Technical Abstract&lt;br/&gt;This Major Research Instrumentation Award supports the acquisition of an environmental transmission electron microscope (ETEM), a high-resolution electron microscope with a simplified differential pumping system that permits gas introduction directly into the column.  As a conventional TEM the instrument will enhance the current electron microscopy capabilities in teaching, user training and research. The capability to visualize structural changes at the sub-nanoscale level under operational environmental conditions will bring essential insights to many materials issues, such as the effect of dopants and impurities on processing and corrosion, defect (dislocation, grain boundaries and interface) migrations, thermally induced phase transformations, heterogeneous catalyses, nano-scale functional materials, and the environmental stability of materials in general.  The low accelerating voltage minimizes damage of oxide species and soft materials, thereby providing the ability to visualize the dynamics of polymers, tissue engineering, drug delivery, biomaterials and biomineralization.  This will be the first ETEM in the greater Western Pennsylvania area.  It will be housed at the University of Pittsburgh in the Swanson School of Engineering (SSoE) and will be a part of the Nanofabrication and Characterization Facility (NFCF) in the Peterson Institute of NanoScience and Engineering (PINSE). It will be linked to the electron microscopy facility in the Structural Biology department, School of Medicine. The NFCF is a user facility available to all national and international researchers.  The broad visibility and access to this instrument will contribute to nano- and meso-scale science and technology, biology, energy and sustainability research and to the training of post-docs, graduate students and undergraduate students. This instrument will also be used in teaching courses in Electron Microscopy, Nano-characterization, Thin Films, Biomaterials, Nanomaterials and Nanotechnology. As a part of PINSE, it will contribute to the education of high school students and under-represented groups, especially African-American, as part of the NSF-Nanotechnology Undergraduate Education (NUE) outreach program and Pitt Engineering Career Access Program (PECAP) program, respectively. &lt;br/&gt;******&lt;br/&gt;This award from the Major Instrumentation program will support the installation of the first Environmental Transmission Electron Microscope (ETEM) in the greater Western Pennsylvania area. The instrument will be housed at the University of Pittsburgh in the Swanson School of Engineering (SSoE) as part of the Nanofabrication and Characterization Facility (NFCF), a user facility available to all national and international researchers. TEM is a powerful tool to visualize materials at the nanoscale and below. ETEM enables unique insights on the dynamic processing/structure/property relationships of nanomaterials  with impact in a broad spectrum of science and engineering areas, such as oxidation, corrosion, catalysis, nano-processing, bio-mineralization, tissue engineering and drug delivery.  The broad visibility and access to this instrument will contribute to nano- and meso-scale science and technology, biology, energy and sustainability research and education of post-docs, graduate students and undergraduate students. This instrumentation will also be used in teaching Electron Microscopy, Nano-characterization, Thin Films, Biomaterials, Nanomaterials and Nanotechnology courses.  It will contribute to the education of high school students and under-represented groups, especially African-American, as part of the NSF-Nanotechnology Undergraduate Education outreach program and Pitt Engineering Career Access Program, respectively.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>09/20/2013</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>09/20/2013</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1337731</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Judith</FirstName>
<LastName>Yang</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>C</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Judith C Yang</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>judyyang@pitt.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>4126248613</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000470642</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/20/2013</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Jorg</FirstName>
<LastName>Wiezorek</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>M</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Jorg M Wiezorek</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>wiezorek@pitt.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>4126240122</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000284199</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/20/2013</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Peijun</FirstName>
<LastName>Zhang</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Peijun Zhang</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>pez7@pitt.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>4123835907</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000243809</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/20/2013</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Pittsburgh</Name>
<CityName>Pittsburgh</CityName>
<ZipCode>152133203</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>4126247400</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>300 Murdoch Building</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[3420 Forbes Avenue]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Pennsylvania</StateName>
<StateCode>PA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>18</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>PA18</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>004514360</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF PITTSBURGH, THE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>004514360</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Pittsburgh]]></Name>
<CityName>Pittsburgh</CityName>
<StateCode>PA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>152132303</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[University Club]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Pennsylvania</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>18</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>PA18</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1189</Code>
<Text>Major Research Instrumentation</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1189</Code>
<Text>MAJOR RESEARCH INSTRUMENTATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7237</Code>
<Text>NANO NON-SOLIC SCI &amp; ENG AWD</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0113</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2013~1155034</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>An environmental transmission electron microscope (ETEM) is a powerful analytical tool that can enable the direct atomic-resolution observation, in real time, of the physical and chemical changes that materials undergo in thermal, gaseous, and liquid environments. This MRI allowed the purchase and installation of an Hitachi H9500 ETEM in the shared user Nanofabrication and Characterization Facility (NFCF) at the University of Pittsburgh.&nbsp; This tool allows for examining materials&rsquo; performance and chemical reactivity under a variety of gas environments (oxygen, methanol, hydrogen, methane and carbon monoxide) and temperatures (up to 1000 &deg;C). This is the first ETEM in the greater Western Pennsylvania area.&nbsp;</p> <p><strong>Intellectual Merit.</strong>&nbsp; An ETEM provides researchers with a powerful tool to visualize the impact of chemical processes in real-time and on the nanoscale.&nbsp; This invaluable tool allows for a more precise understanding of amaterials&rsquo; chemical sensitivities or robustness over a variety of length scales, temperatures, and gas environments. We have (and will continue) to foster much-needed research activities related to the dynamics of materials-related processes under various conditions <em>in situ</em> and establish a fundamental understanding of materials in ambient to extreme conditions of temperature and environments. Many materials systems have been characterized dynamically using this ETEM, a Hitachi H9500, at the University of Pittsburgh.&nbsp; Some examples include the early stages of metal and metal alloy oxidation for fundamental understanding of corrosion needed to design corrosion resistant coating materials. The ETEM allows us to see catalysts under environmental conditions to gain essential insights into the structure-catalytic property relationship as well as to determine the range of environmental conditions (temperature and gas pressure) where the catalyst structure is stable and thus efficient.&nbsp; In addition, this instrument is routinely used for the characterization of DNA based nanostructures as it can be operated at low electron volt energy to minimize the damage to light materials, such as DNA. Two projects are highlighted (images). ETEM was used to determine under what conditions (oxygen pressures and temperatures) would initiate the "un-corking" mechanism of gold nanoparticles from sealed carbon nanotubes. These observations will help to develop these materials for the controlled delivery of cargo to biological targets of interest.&nbsp; Another example is the early stage oxidation of copper oxidation where its progression can be followed at the atomic scale.</p> <p><strong>Broader Impacts.</strong> The ETEM is part of the NFCF which is a user facility available to all national and international researchers as well as industrial customers.&nbsp; The broad visibility and access to this instrument has and will continue to contribute to nano- and meso-scale science and technology, biology, energy and sustainability research .&nbsp; In addition, the students and postdoctoral researchers &nbsp;that are trained and using the ETEM will have cutting edge experience to lead to future in situ ETEM developments and research as their careers progress.&nbsp; This instrument also contributes to the education of post-docs, graduate students and undergraduate students. This instrumentation was used as the hands-on demonstration for graduate level Electron Microscopy course. The Hitachi H9500 ETEM has also been used as a teaching platform in two separate outreach events in 2016 to groups of school and middle school students, and will continue this outreach activities. The ETEM was showcased remotely as part of Hewlett Packard Enterprise&rsquo;s &ldquo;Take Our Children to Work Day&rdquo; in Plano, Texas via Skype on July 15th, 2016.&nbsp; The instrument was again featured as a demonstration tool to an English as a second language program focused on STEM which occurs on site at the University of Pittsburgh on July 22nd, 2016.&nbsp; A third outreach event for junior and high school students through the Pennsylvania Junior Academy of Science (PJAS) Nano-day on November 19, 2016 featured the ETEM. This advanced ETEM system that can achieve sub-nanoscale resolution under a broad range of environmental conditions benefits research and education in nano- and bio-sciences, as well as at their intersection, and energy and sustainability.&nbsp;&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 11/29/2016<br>      Modified by: Judith&nbsp;C&nbsp;Yang</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Images (<span id="selectedPhoto0">1</span> of <span class="totalNumber"></span>)           </div> <div class="galControls" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2016/1337731/1337731_10283221_1480399091779_Copperoxidation--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2016/1337731/1337731_10283221_1480399091779_Copperoxidation--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Copper Oxidation"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2016/1337731/1337731_10283221_1480399091779_Copperoxidation--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Copper Oxidation"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">ETEM in situ oxidation of a thin copper film. A ?saw tooth? pattern (surfacereconstruction) forms on the surface of the Cu facet when exposed to oxygen.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Judith Yang</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Judith&nbsp;C&nbsp;Yang</div> <div class="imageTitle">Copper Oxidation</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2016/1337731/1337731_10283221_1480399304555_Untitled--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2016/1337731/1337731_10283221_1480399304555_Untitled--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Nanotube"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2016/1337731/1337731_10283221_1480399304555_Untitled--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Nanotube"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Under oxygen, as temperature increases, the gold plugs withdraw into the caps, which themselves round out. This is followed by the thinning and eventual rupture of the carbon nanotubes.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Judith Yang</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Judith&nbsp;C&nbsp;Yang</div> <div class="imageTitle">Nanotube</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2016/1337731/1337731_10283221_1480399479519_outreach--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2016/1337731/1337731_10283221_1480399479519_outreach--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Outreach"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2016/1337731/1337731_10283221_1480399479519_outreach--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Outreach"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Remote outreach event with High School students in Texas using the H9500 Hitachi environmental TEM at the University of Pittsburgh to see copper oxidation dynamically.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Judith Yang</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Judith&nbsp;C&nbsp;Yang</div> <div class="imageTitle">Outreach</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ An environmental transmission electron microscope (ETEM) is a powerful analytical tool that can enable the direct atomic-resolution observation, in real time, of the physical and chemical changes that materials undergo in thermal, gaseous, and liquid environments. This MRI allowed the purchase and installation of an Hitachi H9500 ETEM in the shared user Nanofabrication and Characterization Facility (NFCF) at the University of Pittsburgh.  This tool allows for examining materials? performance and chemical reactivity under a variety of gas environments (oxygen, methanol, hydrogen, methane and carbon monoxide) and temperatures (up to 1000 &deg;C). This is the first ETEM in the greater Western Pennsylvania area.   Intellectual Merit.  An ETEM provides researchers with a powerful tool to visualize the impact of chemical processes in real-time and on the nanoscale.  This invaluable tool allows for a more precise understanding of amaterials? chemical sensitivities or robustness over a variety of length scales, temperatures, and gas environments. We have (and will continue) to foster much-needed research activities related to the dynamics of materials-related processes under various conditions in situ and establish a fundamental understanding of materials in ambient to extreme conditions of temperature and environments. Many materials systems have been characterized dynamically using this ETEM, a Hitachi H9500, at the University of Pittsburgh.  Some examples include the early stages of metal and metal alloy oxidation for fundamental understanding of corrosion needed to design corrosion resistant coating materials. The ETEM allows us to see catalysts under environmental conditions to gain essential insights into the structure-catalytic property relationship as well as to determine the range of environmental conditions (temperature and gas pressure) where the catalyst structure is stable and thus efficient.  In addition, this instrument is routinely used for the characterization of DNA based nanostructures as it can be operated at low electron volt energy to minimize the damage to light materials, such as DNA. Two projects are highlighted (images). ETEM was used to determine under what conditions (oxygen pressures and temperatures) would initiate the "un-corking" mechanism of gold nanoparticles from sealed carbon nanotubes. These observations will help to develop these materials for the controlled delivery of cargo to biological targets of interest.  Another example is the early stage oxidation of copper oxidation where its progression can be followed at the atomic scale.  Broader Impacts. The ETEM is part of the NFCF which is a user facility available to all national and international researchers as well as industrial customers.  The broad visibility and access to this instrument has and will continue to contribute to nano- and meso-scale science and technology, biology, energy and sustainability research .  In addition, the students and postdoctoral researchers  that are trained and using the ETEM will have cutting edge experience to lead to future in situ ETEM developments and research as their careers progress.  This instrument also contributes to the education of post-docs, graduate students and undergraduate students. This instrumentation was used as the hands-on demonstration for graduate level Electron Microscopy course. The Hitachi H9500 ETEM has also been used as a teaching platform in two separate outreach events in 2016 to groups of school and middle school students, and will continue this outreach activities. The ETEM was showcased remotely as part of Hewlett Packard Enterprise?s "Take Our Children to Work Day" in Plano, Texas via Skype on July 15th, 2016.  The instrument was again featured as a demonstration tool to an English as a second language program focused on STEM which occurs on site at the University of Pittsburgh on July 22nd, 2016.  A third outreach event for junior and high school students through the Pennsylvania Junior Academy of Science (PJAS) Nano-day on November 19, 2016 featured the ETEM. This advanced ETEM system that can achieve sub-nanoscale resolution under a broad range of environmental conditions benefits research and education in nano- and bio-sciences, as well as at their intersection, and energy and sustainability.            Last Modified: 11/29/2016       Submitted by: Judith C Yang]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
