<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>MRI: Acquisition of a Next-Generation Sequencer for Biological Research at a Hispanic Serving Institution in South Texas</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2013</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2016</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>158420.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>158420</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>08080000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>BIO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DBI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Biological Infrastructure</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Christopher Sanford</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>An award is made to the University of Texas Pan American, a Hispanic Serving Institution in South Texas, to acquire a next-generation DNA sequencer to advance and promote biological research. Next-generation sequencing refers to DNA sequencing techniques and analyses that are faster and more robust than the traditional Sanger Method for sequencing DNA. Next-generation sequencing allows for thousands to billions of short sequencing reactions to occur simultaneously and large amounts of sequence data to be generated. The research team will include a diverse group of faculty (tenured and tenure-track) from complementary biological disciplines that will incorporate next-generation sequencing into their research to address major biological questions in microbiology, plant science, zoology, genetics, physiology, ecology, and for educational purposes in laboratory classes. Example projects include: (i) Genomics-based evolutionary studies of microbial arsenic detoxification pathways; (ii) Comparative genomics of plant pathogens; (iii) Plant systematic studies of Tropical and New World morning glories; (iv) Transcriptome analyses of plant responses to environmental stressors; (v) Speciation and phylogenetic studies of sand crabs; (vi) Developmental genomics of insects; (vii) Species distribution studies of insect that serves as vectors for Chagas Disease; and (viii) Classroom-based projects in upper-division Biology courses. The breadth of projects, along with future projects and collaborations, will advance and expand the department's and university's research and education capabilities.&lt;br/&gt; &lt;br/&gt; Researchers and research students will use the instrument directly; thus, research and learning will be positively impacted due to the ability of users to directly access the technology. Acquiring a next-generation sequencer will allow researchers at UTPA, their Hispanic students, and collaborators at nearby institutions to perform cutting-edge research that is currently not available to them. A next-generation sequencer will allow faculty mentors to train new student researchers and use the technology in upper-division Biology courses. This has the potential to not only transform research and education for the University of Texas Pan American, but transform research and education for the entire South Texas region. The research team includes four women, one of whom is Hispanic and one that has a disability. A next-generation sequencer will increase the number of Hispanics, women, and disabled persons conducting biological research in South Texas and in the USA.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/13/2013</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/13/2013</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.074</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1337362</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Kristine</FirstName>
<LastName>Lowe</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>L</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Kristine L Lowe</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>kristine.lowe@utrgv.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>9566658749</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000303238</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/13/2013</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Erin</FirstName>
<LastName>Schuenzel</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>L</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Erin L Schuenzel</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>schuenzelel@utpa.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>9563812011</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000600162</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/13/2013</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>The University of Texas Rio Grande Valley</Name>
<CityName>Edinburg</CityName>
<ZipCode>785392909</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>9566652889</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1201 West University Dr</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Texas</StateName>
<StateCode>TX</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>15</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>TX15</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>069444511</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF TEXAS RIO GRANDE VALLEY, THE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>042000273</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Texas - Pan American]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>TX</StateCode>
<ZipCode>785412999</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Texas</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>15</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>TX15</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1189</Code>
<Text>Major Research Instrumentation</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0113</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2013~158420</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><strong>Intellectual Merit.</strong> The Department of Biology at The University of Texas Rio Grande Valley (formally The University of Texas &ndash; Pan American) acquired a MiSeq next-generation sequencer to advance the biological research capabilities at a Hispanic Serving Institution in Texas. Next-generation sequencing refers to DNA and RNA sequencing techniques and analyses that are faster and more robust than traditional sequencing methods. In next-generation sequencing, only a small amount of DNA or RNA is needed, which may be extracted directly from the source. Next-generation sequencing allows for thousands to billions of short sequencing reactions to occur simultaneously and large amounts of sequence data to be generated. Research performed using the instrument included profiling of prokaryotic microbial communities from a rare ecosystem; profiling microbes that are commensal with aquatic plants; gene expression studies of agricultural pests, including cattle ticks; determining the microbiomes of insects; and other studies. Conference presentations, technical reports and peer-reviewed scientific publications based on research using the next-generation sequencer were submitted and/presented by students and faculty members at The University of Texas Rio Grande Valley (UTRGV). Presentations were at state, national and international conferences.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p><strong>Broader Impacts.</strong> The MiSeq instrument was preferred because of its compact size; its ability to perform several applications; and for its ease-of-use compared to other instruments. Due to those characteristics, the instrument was used by undergraduate students, graduate students and faculty members conducting research. The PI and Co-PI of the grant were both female and the PI had a documented disability. The instrument was also used in advanced undergraduate courses and graduate-level courses within the Department of Biology. First-hand use by students in research and in class greatly expanded the number of young researchers who were trained and proficient using the instrument. As UTRGV is a Hispanic Serving Institution, the majority of the new researchers were Hispanic and most were female. Several new research collaborations were initiated with faculty within the institution and with international researchers outside of the institution. Therefore, the acquisition of the next-generation sequencer increased the number of women, Hispanics and disabled persons conducting next-generation sequencing research and also transformed the educational and research capabilities of UTRGV and the local community in the Rio Grande Valley of Texas.&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 12/01/2016<br>      Modified by: Kristine&nbsp;L&nbsp;Lowe</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Intellectual Merit. The Department of Biology at The University of Texas Rio Grande Valley (formally The University of Texas &ndash; Pan American) acquired a MiSeq next-generation sequencer to advance the biological research capabilities at a Hispanic Serving Institution in Texas. Next-generation sequencing refers to DNA and RNA sequencing techniques and analyses that are faster and more robust than traditional sequencing methods. In next-generation sequencing, only a small amount of DNA or RNA is needed, which may be extracted directly from the source. Next-generation sequencing allows for thousands to billions of short sequencing reactions to occur simultaneously and large amounts of sequence data to be generated. Research performed using the instrument included profiling of prokaryotic microbial communities from a rare ecosystem; profiling microbes that are commensal with aquatic plants; gene expression studies of agricultural pests, including cattle ticks; determining the microbiomes of insects; and other studies. Conference presentations, technical reports and peer-reviewed scientific publications based on research using the next-generation sequencer were submitted and/presented by students and faculty members at The University of Texas Rio Grande Valley (UTRGV). Presentations were at state, national and international conferences.     Broader Impacts. The MiSeq instrument was preferred because of its compact size; its ability to perform several applications; and for its ease-of-use compared to other instruments. Due to those characteristics, the instrument was used by undergraduate students, graduate students and faculty members conducting research. The PI and Co-PI of the grant were both female and the PI had a documented disability. The instrument was also used in advanced undergraduate courses and graduate-level courses within the Department of Biology. First-hand use by students in research and in class greatly expanded the number of young researchers who were trained and proficient using the instrument. As UTRGV is a Hispanic Serving Institution, the majority of the new researchers were Hispanic and most were female. Several new research collaborations were initiated with faculty within the institution and with international researchers outside of the institution. Therefore, the acquisition of the next-generation sequencer increased the number of women, Hispanics and disabled persons conducting next-generation sequencing research and also transformed the educational and research capabilities of UTRGV and the local community in the Rio Grande Valley of Texas.           Last Modified: 12/01/2016       Submitted by: Kristine L Lowe]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
