<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Sedimenting Particulate Suspensions in Viscoelastic Fluids Under Shear</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>10/01/2013</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>09/30/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>359389.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>359389</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07020000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CBET</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Chem, Bioeng, Env, &amp; Transp Sys</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Ron Joslin</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>rjoslin@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927030</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>1337051&lt;br/&gt;PI: Shaqfeh&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Suspensions of rigid particles in viscoelastic fluids play key roles in many energy applications, materials design applications, and consumer product applications. For example, in oil drilling the so-called drilling mud is a very viscous, viscoelastic fluid designed to shear-thin during drilling, but thicken at stoppage so that the cuttings can remain suspended. In a related application known as hydraulic fracturing (an operation used to stimulate petroleum and gas production) suspensions of solids called proppant are used to prop open the fracture by pumping them into the well.  Quality performance of the proppant demands placement deep into the fracture requiring that the excess weight of the solids be supported during the flow. A commonly used proppant-transport liquid is an aqueous guar polymer solution, transiently cross-linked with borate ion, such that it is highly elastic. It is well known that the sedimentation of particles in a  viscoelastic fluid can be quite different from that which is observed in Newtonian fluids, especially under shear. For example, in a non-Newtonian liquid, the complex rheological properties induce a nonlinear coupling between the sedimentation and shear flow which is not found in Newtonian liquids and which is critical to the function of the aforementioned drilling and fracking fluids.  In a related materials application, the cleaning of particulate matter from surfaces, particularly in applications associated with etching of silicon wafers is often done by a post processing known as rinse. Most recently, it has been shown that a viscoelastic solution becomes a far more effective rinse agent than a Newtonian solution, even at the same viscosity. Again, in this application, the elasticity in a flowing, sheared fluid seems to change, in a manner as yet unknown, the forces on particulates subject to gravity in directions orthogonal to the shear flow, creating thereby an enhanced lift force that cleans the surface. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;In this project, the research team will develop large scale, computer simulations of particle suspensions at finite concentration in viscoelastic fluids. The focus will be on particles acted on by a body force (i.e. gravity) as well as an applied shear flow in a direction orthogonal to gravity with the goal of understanding the applications described above. The computer simulations will be unique, first of their kind, combining unstructured, finite volume technology with immersed boundary techniques in elastic liquids. Such simulations are, in the authors view, the only known way to understand the nonlinear physics in these highly nonequilibrium flow applications and thus to engineer these fluids rather than develop them based on historical precedent.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/10/2013</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/10/2013</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1337051</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Eric Stefan</FirstName>
<LastName>Shaqfeh</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>G</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Eric Stefan G Shaqfeh</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>esgs@stanford.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6507233764</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000208548</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/10/2013</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Gianluca</FirstName>
<LastName>Iaccarino</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Gianluca Iaccarino</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>jops@stanford.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6509060302</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000486250</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/10/2013</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Stanford University</Name>
<CityName>Stanford</CityName>
<ZipCode>943052004</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6507232300</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>450 Jane Stanford Way</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>18</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CA18</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>009214214</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>LELAND STANFORD JUNIOR UNIVERSITY, THE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>009214214</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Stanford University]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>943054100</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>18</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CA18</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1415</Code>
<Text>PMP-Particul&amp;MultiphaseProcess</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>056E</Code>
<Text>Multiphase flow</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0113</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2013~359389</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Suspensions of rigid particles are omnipresent in every day life from silt in the ocean to milk in your coffee. In many industrial and biological applications, the suspending fluids themselves are not "small molecule fluids" like air or water. They are indeed fluids with large macromolecules embedded in the fluid -- so called viscoleastic fluids. For example, in your body, mucous and blood plasma are viscoelastic and they typically have particles (e.g. bacteria, cilia, or red blood cells) suspended in them. The fundamental understanding of these suspensions containing viscoelastic suspending fluids is in its infancy, even though they have broad application. For example, in the operation of frac'ing, sand is used as a proppant to hold open the cracks after the pressure in the well is reduced. The fluid that supports the proppant during injection is indeed a highly elastic guar gum (guar being usually culled from sea weed). The physical mechanism of how the guar gum helped support the sand was, prior to the present research, simply not understood. Note that such suspensions often behave in a qualitatively different manner than if the suspending fluid was made of small molecules.&nbsp; The main hurdle in understanding these complex suspensions is the development of computer simulation tools to simulate the suspension. Note that in suspensions of rigid particle in small molecule fluids, simulations play a key role. In this research, we have developed, for the first time, a massively parallel computer code capable of simulating a large number of particles flowing in a viscoelastic fluid such that suspension properties can be understood. These include the sedimentation rate of the particles in the fluid under shear (key to the frac'ing application discussed above). Moreover, we have examined also how the suspensions, when viewed themselves as an "effective fluid" with new properites, might be described. This research then opens the door to a new field of inquiry that has been stymied heretofore.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 01/05/2018<br>      Modified by: Eric Stefan&nbsp;G&nbsp;Shaqfeh</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Suspensions of rigid particles are omnipresent in every day life from silt in the ocean to milk in your coffee. In many industrial and biological applications, the suspending fluids themselves are not "small molecule fluids" like air or water. They are indeed fluids with large macromolecules embedded in the fluid -- so called viscoleastic fluids. For example, in your body, mucous and blood plasma are viscoelastic and they typically have particles (e.g. bacteria, cilia, or red blood cells) suspended in them. The fundamental understanding of these suspensions containing viscoelastic suspending fluids is in its infancy, even though they have broad application. For example, in the operation of frac'ing, sand is used as a proppant to hold open the cracks after the pressure in the well is reduced. The fluid that supports the proppant during injection is indeed a highly elastic guar gum (guar being usually culled from sea weed). The physical mechanism of how the guar gum helped support the sand was, prior to the present research, simply not understood. Note that such suspensions often behave in a qualitatively different manner than if the suspending fluid was made of small molecules.  The main hurdle in understanding these complex suspensions is the development of computer simulation tools to simulate the suspension. Note that in suspensions of rigid particle in small molecule fluids, simulations play a key role. In this research, we have developed, for the first time, a massively parallel computer code capable of simulating a large number of particles flowing in a viscoelastic fluid such that suspension properties can be understood. These include the sedimentation rate of the particles in the fluid under shear (key to the frac'ing application discussed above). Moreover, we have examined also how the suspensions, when viewed themselves as an "effective fluid" with new properites, might be described. This research then opens the door to a new field of inquiry that has been stymied heretofore.                   Last Modified: 01/05/2018       Submitted by: Eric Stefan G Shaqfeh]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
