<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>MRI: Acquisition of an Infrared Eye Tracker to Study the Emergence, Use, Loss and Reacquisition of Communication Skills</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2013</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2016</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>41575.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>41575</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>04040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>SBE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>BCS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Behavioral and Cognitive Sci</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>John Yellen</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>jyellen@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032928759</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Using a Major Instrumentation award from the National Science Foundation, Dr. Rhiannon Luyster and three co-investigators at Emerson College will purchase a Remote Eye Tracking (RED) System from Sensomotoric Instruments.  By using infrared light, the RED system allows users to record eye movements and fixations to images or videos; this technology has been used across a wide range of disciplines to learn about what aspects of visual images attract a viewer's attention.  &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The four collaborating investigators are faculty in the Department of Communication Sciences and Disorders and plan to use this advanced technology to study the emergence, use, loss and reacquisition of communication skills across the lifespan.  One study explores the role of visual attention to speaking faces in early childhood language learning and language deficits.  A second study addresses how children visually scan the facial expressions of peers with and without autism and how these visual scan patterns relate to the perception of awkwardness in the social communication attempts of children with autism.  A final set of projects studies how adults with aphasia attend to verbal and non-verbal communication channels when trying to understand messages and how potential communication partners of adults with aphasia rely on verbal and non-verbal channels to understand people with aphasia. Together, this program of research has the potential to reveal new insights into the role of communication across the lifespan, from young children to adults.  The goal is to answer core questions about the value of communicative cues, and how variations in the use of communicative cues might be associated with deficits, or, conversely, support healthy development.      &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This equipment will have broad benefits for faculty scholarship, student learning and community engagement at Emerson College.  First, in addition to the four faculty associated with the present proposal, several faculty members throughout the college have expressed an interest in incorporating eye-tracking technology into their own work, covering topics from cross-cultural consumer behavior to the role of media in journalism.  Second, the equipment will be made available to undergraduate and masters students from any college department, many of which (Marketing, for instance) produce graduates who will encounter eye-tracking technology in the professional world.  Finally, the acquisition of this equipment will strengthen current Emerson College outreach programs, including an existing partnership with the Boston-area Science Club for Girls (connecting college students in the sciences with elementary and middle-school aged girls from underrepresented groups), the Boston Museum of Science, and the Cambridge Science Festival, where our students present pieces on science and science education to a large and diverse audience.  Finally, the School of Communication at Emerson recently began recording a series of podcasts to showcase the research programs and innovations of its faculty.  These podcasts are aired in a variety of contexts, including on WERS  - the Emerson-owned radio station - thus disseminating information about Emerson's eye-tracking research, recent findings and the value of science in our society.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/05/2013</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/05/2013</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.075</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1337120</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Rhiannon</FirstName>
<LastName>Luyster</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Rhiannon Luyster</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>rhiannon_luyster@emerson.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6178248354</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000642490</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/05/2013</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Joanne</FirstName>
<LastName>Lasker</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Joanne Lasker</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>joanne_lasker@emerson.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6178248354</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000642957</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/05/2013</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Daniel</FirstName>
<LastName>Kempler</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Daniel Kempler</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>daniel_kempler@emerson.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6178248354</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000642959</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/05/2013</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Ruth</FirstName>
<LastName>Grossman</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Ruth Grossman</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>ruth_grossman@emerson.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6178248354</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000642960</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/05/2013</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Emerson College</Name>
<CityName>Boston</CityName>
<ZipCode>021161523</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6178243075</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>120 Boylston Street</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
<StateCode>MA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MA07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>043411438</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>EMERSON COLLEGE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>043411438</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Emerson College]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>MA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>021161523</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MA07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1189</Code>
<Text>Major Research Instrumentation</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1189</Code>
<Text>MAJOR RESEARCH INSTRUMENTATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0113</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2013~41575</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>This award provided funding to acquire an infrared eye-tracker for four co-PIs at Emerson College to study the emergence, use, loss and reacquisition of communication skills across the lifespan.&nbsp; Research questions of interest included: (1) the role of visual attention to faces in young children with autism spectrum disorder; (2) how children visually scan facial expressions and how these visual scan patterns relate to the perception of awkwardness in the social communication attempts of children with autism; and (3) how adults with aphasia attend to verbal and non-verbal communication channels when trying to understand messages and how potential communication partners of adults with aphasia rely on verbal and non-verbal channels to understand people with aphasia. Overall, we aimed to address core questions about the value of seeking communicative cues (particularly nonverbal ones, like facial expressions/movements and gestures), and how variations in the use of communicative cues might be associated with deficits, or, conversely, support healthy development.&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;</p> <p><strong>&nbsp;</strong></p> <p><strong><span style="text-decoration: underline;">Outcomes</span></strong></p> <p><strong>Intellectual Merit</strong></p> <p>Outcomes from the three separate threads of research will be reported separately.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p><em>Question 1: &nbsp;The role of visual attention to faces in young children with autism spectrum disorder. </em>In the first year of this project, the original research plan was modified because of new publications in the field that greatly overlapped with our research plan and questions. &nbsp;An altered set of research questions were generated, focusing on within-group variability on attention to eyes versus mouth across a range of stimuli in order to explore the potential effect of stimulus type on visual attention to faces.&nbsp; In the second year of the award, we compiled a comprehensive set of stimuli that reflect the range of stimuli previously used in eye-tracking research with infants and toddlers with/at risk for ASD, and we began collecting data focusing on within group-variability in social attention. &nbsp;By the end of the award, we have seen 42 typically developing toddlers. We plan to continue enrolling typically developing toddlers, as well as a comparison sample of toddler with ASD. &nbsp;Additionally, we have begun a new study looking at the robustness of noun and verb learning in children with ASD across in-person and recorded conditions; to date, we have enrolled 30 participants for piloting and data collection.&nbsp; These data were presenting at the 2016 meeting of the International Meeting for Autism Research.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p><em>Question 2: </em><em>How children visually scan facial expressions and how these visual scan patterns relate to the perception of awkwardness in the social communication attempts of children with autism. </em>We collected data for a master&rsquo;s thesis focusing on gaze patterns to human and computer animated faces. &nbsp;In the second year, we completed data analysis and our student defended her thesis. &nbsp;We also presented this work at the American Speech Language and Hearing Association Convention in November 2015. &nbsp;We are currently analyzing data for a follow-up study based on these data and hope to present them at the International Meeting for Autism Research in May 2017.</p> <p><em>&nbsp;</em></p> <p><em>Question 3: How adults with aphasia attend to verbal and non-verbal communication channels when trying to understand messages and how potential communication partners of adults with aphasia rely on verbal and non-verbal channels to understand people with aphasia.</em> We collected eye tracking data on visual attention to hands vs. face in people with aphasia and typical communicators. &nbsp;We completed data analysis, submitted a presentation to Clinical Aphasiology Conference (presented in May 2015) and the American-Speech-Language-Hearing Association (presented in November, 2015). To investigate differences between gaze patterns towards communicators with aphasia and typical communicators, we developed controlled stimuli involving an actor completing daily activities in three conditions - typical speech with gesture, degraded speech with gesture, and gesture only. Our initial data suggest that unfamiliar viewers attend to faces, regardless of degradation of the speech signal. Therefore, clinically, it would be important to overtly draw listeners&rsquo; attention to the hands, for gesture to be maximally useful in communication.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p><strong>Broader Impacts</strong></p> <p>We have been pleased to see the broader impacts of this award, including:</p> <ul> <li>One graduate master&rsquo;s thesis for an Emerson College student</li> <li>One undergraduate honors thesis for a student at the University of Bath</li> <li>Extensive hands on training for more than 10 graduate students at Emerson College</li> <li>Extensive hands on training for 2 undergraduate students from the University of Bath</li> <li>Extensive hands on training for three high-school interns through the Science Club for Girls </li> </ul> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 11/30/2016<br>      Modified by: Rhiannon&nbsp;Luyster</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ This award provided funding to acquire an infrared eye-tracker for four co-PIs at Emerson College to study the emergence, use, loss and reacquisition of communication skills across the lifespan.  Research questions of interest included: (1) the role of visual attention to faces in young children with autism spectrum disorder; (2) how children visually scan facial expressions and how these visual scan patterns relate to the perception of awkwardness in the social communication attempts of children with autism; and (3) how adults with aphasia attend to verbal and non-verbal communication channels when trying to understand messages and how potential communication partners of adults with aphasia rely on verbal and non-verbal channels to understand people with aphasia. Overall, we aimed to address core questions about the value of seeking communicative cues (particularly nonverbal ones, like facial expressions/movements and gestures), and how variations in the use of communicative cues might be associated with deficits, or, conversely, support healthy development.          Outcomes  Intellectual Merit  Outcomes from the three separate threads of research will be reported separately.     Question 1:  The role of visual attention to faces in young children with autism spectrum disorder. In the first year of this project, the original research plan was modified because of new publications in the field that greatly overlapped with our research plan and questions.  An altered set of research questions were generated, focusing on within-group variability on attention to eyes versus mouth across a range of stimuli in order to explore the potential effect of stimulus type on visual attention to faces.  In the second year of the award, we compiled a comprehensive set of stimuli that reflect the range of stimuli previously used in eye-tracking research with infants and toddlers with/at risk for ASD, and we began collecting data focusing on within group-variability in social attention.  By the end of the award, we have seen 42 typically developing toddlers. We plan to continue enrolling typically developing toddlers, as well as a comparison sample of toddler with ASD.  Additionally, we have begun a new study looking at the robustness of noun and verb learning in children with ASD across in-person and recorded conditions; to date, we have enrolled 30 participants for piloting and data collection.  These data were presenting at the 2016 meeting of the International Meeting for Autism Research.     Question 2: How children visually scan facial expressions and how these visual scan patterns relate to the perception of awkwardness in the social communication attempts of children with autism. We collected data for a master?s thesis focusing on gaze patterns to human and computer animated faces.  In the second year, we completed data analysis and our student defended her thesis.  We also presented this work at the American Speech Language and Hearing Association Convention in November 2015.  We are currently analyzing data for a follow-up study based on these data and hope to present them at the International Meeting for Autism Research in May 2017.     Question 3: How adults with aphasia attend to verbal and non-verbal communication channels when trying to understand messages and how potential communication partners of adults with aphasia rely on verbal and non-verbal channels to understand people with aphasia. We collected eye tracking data on visual attention to hands vs. face in people with aphasia and typical communicators.  We completed data analysis, submitted a presentation to Clinical Aphasiology Conference (presented in May 2015) and the American-Speech-Language-Hearing Association (presented in November, 2015). To investigate differences between gaze patterns towards communicators with aphasia and typical communicators, we developed controlled stimuli involving an actor completing daily activities in three conditions - typical speech with gesture, degraded speech with gesture, and gesture only. Our initial data suggest that unfamiliar viewers attend to faces, regardless of degradation of the speech signal. Therefore, clinically, it would be important to overtly draw listeners? attention to the hands, for gesture to be maximally useful in communication.     Broader Impacts  We have been pleased to see the broader impacts of this award, including:  One graduate master?s thesis for an Emerson College student One undergraduate honors thesis for a student at the University of Bath Extensive hands on training for more than 10 graduate students at Emerson College Extensive hands on training for 2 undergraduate students from the University of Bath Extensive hands on training for three high-school interns through the Science Club for Girls                  Last Modified: 11/30/2016       Submitted by: Rhiannon Luyster]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
