<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Suspension Rheology at Constant Pressure</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2013</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2016</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>300000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>300000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07020000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CBET</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Chem, Bioeng, Env, &amp; Transp Sys</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>William Olbricht</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>1337097&lt;br/&gt;PI: Brady&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Colloidal suspensions are widely used in industry, medicine and in natural environments, and encompass systems as diverse as toothpaste, paints, the interior of a cell and sprayable solar panels. Understanding the rheological properties of suspensions is critical to their processing, dispensing, durability and performance. Most studies of suspension rheology have been at fixed volume (or fixed volume fraction). While this may be adequate for many applications, often suspension flows are not at fixed volume but rather at fixed stress (or fixed pressure or pressure drop). Is the flow behavior the same at fixed volume and fixed pressure? If the volume fraction of suspended particles is low enough it should be possible to covert one measurement into the other. But as the maximum flowing fraction is approached, it is no longer clear that the two conditions will lead to the same flow behavior. A simulation study of colloidal suspensions at fixed pressure, allowing the system to dilate or contract and the volume fraction fluctuate as necessary, is proposed. The Accelerated Stokesian dynamics simulation methodology will be adapted to permit the simulation volume to change and used to study the flow behavior of Brownian hard-sphere suspensions as the strength of the shearing forces compared to thermal Brownian forces is varied over a wide range. Complete microscale detail is available from simulation, including particle distribution functions, order parameters, short- and long-time particle displacements, etc., and will connect the observed macroscopic behavior to the underlying particle dynamics. Particular attention will be focused on the flow behavior as the maximum flowing fraction is approached and the scaling of the flow properties near this point.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Understanding suspension rheology is an important subject in its own right, but examining the flow behavior as the maximum flowing fraction is approached may have important implications for glassy and jammed systems. Colloidal dispersions at rest are known to form a glass at volume fractions near 0.58, well below random close packing (0.64 for monodisperse spheres). Experiment on both rapid granular flows and viscous non-Brownian suspensions at fixed pressure and shear stress have shown very similar behaviors: the ratio of shear to normal stress - the friction coefficient - is the same in the two systems, as is the maximum flowing volume fraction, despite the very different microscale physics - inertial dynamics versus viscous forces. It is quite possible that Brownian colloidal dispersions will display a similar behavior, which would then make an important link between jammed granular media and colloidal glasses. If demonstrated, such a connection would transform our understanding of glasses and jammed systems, and possibly provide a universal understanding of jamming.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This research will enable the design, at the particle scale, of colloidal dispersions to meet the flow requirements of specific applications in, for example, the paints and coatings industry, thus reducing energy consumption and product waste. Contributing to the understanding of glasses and glass-forming systems, and particular their dynamic properties, would have broad impact across disciplines from fundamental physics and chemistry to biology - the motion of proteins and protein complexes in the crowded interior of a cell has strong similarities  with the hindered and heterogeneous motion in colloidal glasses. Finally, the graduate student supported by this research will be well-trained in continuum and statistical mechanics, colloidal physics and computational science, and will join the scientific workforce of the nation.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/22/2013</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/22/2013</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1337097</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>John</FirstName>
<LastName>Brady</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>F</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>John F Brady</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>jfbrady@caltech.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6263954183</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000212238</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/22/2013</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>California Institute of Technology</Name>
<CityName>PASADENA</CityName>
<ZipCode>911250600</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6263956219</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1200 E California Blvd</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[Mail Code 273-6]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>27</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CA27</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>009584210</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>CALIFORNIA INSTITUTE OF TECHNOLOGY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>009584210</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[California Institute of Technology]]></Name>
<CityName>Pasadena</CityName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>911250600</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[1200 E. California Blvd.]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>27</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CA27</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1415</Code>
<Text>PMP-Particul&amp;MultiphaseProcess</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>056E</Code>
<Text>Multiphase flow</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0113</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2013~300000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>How are paint, milk and blood related? &nbsp;They are all suspensions of small particles dispersed in a fluid. &nbsp;Indeed many of our everyday personal care products -- toothpaste, shampoo, deodorant, detergent, etc. -- are suspensions. &nbsp;Understanding the flow behavior of these materials is critical for their manufacture and for their function. &nbsp;Most studies of colloidal suspensions have been carried under conditions of controlled volume as might occur for flow in a pipe. &nbsp;However, in many processes, such as film coating, material flow occurs under conditions of fixed pressure, not volume. &nbsp;Up to now, there has been no method to determine the flow behavior, or rheology, of suspensions at fixed pressure. &nbsp;In ehe research sponsored by this NSF grant we developed a new approach to simulate suspension flow behavior at controlled pressure and thus has opened a new window into suspension behavior. &nbsp;Through this new approach we have been able to understand the microstructures formed in the colloidal film drying process, and discovered a regime of fast drying and controlled structure that was not anticipated by conventional theories. &nbsp;We have also been able to shed new light on the colloidal glass formation process, relating for the first time the connection between a particulate glass and a jammed granular packing.&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 06/05/2017<br>      Modified by: John&nbsp;F&nbsp;Brady</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Images (<span id="selectedPhoto0">1</span> of <span class="totalNumber"></span>)           </div> <div class="galControls" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1337097/1337097_10259831_1496688394661_b01_mu-Iv-all--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1337097/1337097_10259831_1496688394661_b01_mu-Iv-all--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Friction coefficient vs. viscous number"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1337097/1337097_10259831_1496688394661_b01_mu-Iv-all--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Friction coefficient vs. viscous number"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">The steady shear rheology of hard-sphere colloidal suspensions with constant shear stress and pressure.  The ratio of the shear to confining pressure, \mu, as a function of the scaled shear rate, I_v.  The confining pressures \Pi a^3/k_BT, are scaled by the thermal energy and the particle size a.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Wang & Brady, PRL (2015)</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">John&nbsp;F&nbsp;Brady</div> <div class="imageTitle">Friction coefficient vs. viscous number</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1337097/1337097_10259831_1496688672131_b02_mu-phi-0--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1337097/1337097_10259831_1496688672131_b02_mu-phi-0--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Friction coefficient vs. volume fraction"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1337097/1337097_10259831_1496688672131_b02_mu-phi-0--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Friction coefficient vs. volume fraction"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">The steady shear rheology of hard-sphere colloidal suspensions with constant shear stress and pressure. The ratio of the shear to confining pressure, \mu, as a function of the volume fraction showing the shear arrest point. The scaled confining pressures are \Pi a^3/k_BT.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Wang & Brady, PRL (2015)</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">John&nbsp;F&nbsp;Brady</div> <div class="imageTitle">Friction coefficient vs. volume fraction</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ How are paint, milk and blood related?  They are all suspensions of small particles dispersed in a fluid.  Indeed many of our everyday personal care products -- toothpaste, shampoo, deodorant, detergent, etc. -- are suspensions.  Understanding the flow behavior of these materials is critical for their manufacture and for their function.  Most studies of colloidal suspensions have been carried under conditions of controlled volume as might occur for flow in a pipe.  However, in many processes, such as film coating, material flow occurs under conditions of fixed pressure, not volume.  Up to now, there has been no method to determine the flow behavior, or rheology, of suspensions at fixed pressure.  In ehe research sponsored by this NSF grant we developed a new approach to simulate suspension flow behavior at controlled pressure and thus has opened a new window into suspension behavior.  Through this new approach we have been able to understand the microstructures formed in the colloidal film drying process, and discovered a regime of fast drying and controlled structure that was not anticipated by conventional theories.  We have also been able to shed new light on the colloidal glass formation process, relating for the first time the connection between a particulate glass and a jammed granular packing.        Last Modified: 06/05/2017       Submitted by: John F Brady]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
