<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>I/UCRC:  Collaborative Research: Center for Arthropod Management Technologies (CAMTech)</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2013</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>482500.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>532497</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07070000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>IIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Industrial Innovation &amp; Partnersh</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Prakash Balan</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>pbalan@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032925341</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>1338775 Iowa State University; Byrony Bonning &lt;br/&gt;13387667 University of Kentucky; Subba Palli &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The proposed Center for Arthropod Management Technologies (CAMTech) will streamline and link the efforts of industry and academia toward effective management of arthropod and nematode pests through a formalized and extended research partnership. The research efforts will be anchored by Iowa State University (ISU) as the lead institution, partnered with the University of Kentucky (UKY). &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The proposed Center comprised of Iowa State University and the University of Kentucky will serve as an incubator for novel technologies. CAMTech will provide the basic research foundation necessary for the applied research goals of industry and will extend the utility of current arthropod management practices. The goals of CAMTech will be to (i) conduct pre-competitive research and transfer knowledge to industrial partners for in house development, (ii) optimize and extend the versatility of current technologies, and (iii) train undergraduate and graduate students as well as postdoctoral scholars for potential future employment within industry. An interdisciplinary team has been assembled with UKY researchers extending and complementing the skills and expertise of ISU researchers. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Establishment of this Center will enable a cohesive industry-university alliance that will allow industry to communicate their needs to academia toward a common goal, and to facilitate collaboration amongst companies. The diverse team of researchers will provide knowledge of fundamental systems relevant to arthropod management, allowing Center members to derive value from fundamental research and to expand the utility of current approaches. Students and postdoctoral researchers within the proposed Center will receive outstanding professional development training at both ISU and UKY. The commitment of ISU and UK to develop the academic potential of underrepresented groups in STEM fields will be further enhanced by informal mentorships, internships and career options with CAMTech industrial partners.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/16/2013</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/25/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1338775</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Bryony</FirstName>
<LastName>Bonning</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>C</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Bryony C Bonning</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>bbonning@ufl.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>3522733984</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000490112</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/16/2013</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Iowa State University</Name>
<CityName>AMES</CityName>
<ZipCode>500112207</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5152945225</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1138 Pearson</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Iowa</StateName>
<StateCode>IA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>IA04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>005309844</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>IOWA STATE UNIVERSITY OF SCIENCE AND TECHNOLOGY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>005309844</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Iowa State University]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>IA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>500112207</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Iowa</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>IA04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>5761</Code>
<Text>IUCRC-Indust-Univ Coop Res Ctr</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1049</Code>
<Text>INDUSTRY-UNIV COOPERATIVE RSCH PROJECTS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>5761</Code>
<Text>INDUSTRY/UNIV COOP RES CENTERS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8042</Code>
<Text>Health and Safety</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0113</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0114</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2013~482500</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~49997</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The Center for Arthropod Management Technologies (CAMTech), established in 2013, focuses on linking the efforts of industry, government and academia toward effective management of arthropod and nematode pests. Through precompetitive research, the center develops new tools and provides the knowledge necessary to effectively translate and apply novel pest management strategies to the field. During the Phase I funding period, the center was led by Iowa State University, Ames, IA with a second university site at the University of Kentucky in Lexington, KY. The Center and Site Directors, along with the Industry Advisory Board set the direction for the Center and select research projects to be funded.&nbsp;</p> <p>During the five year Phase I funding period, the center made key advances through state of the art research with 21 research projects funded. The technical focus of the center is aligned with industry needs, with an emphasis on genomics, physiology, insect resistance, integrated pest management, and the development of new methods and tools. Eleven companies participated as center members during Phase I, with 100% member retention reflecting the high value gained from center participation. Member companies gained valuable insights into pest genomics and physiology that will facilitate development of new pest management tools for protection of agricultural and forestry crops and for the management of insects of public health importance. In addition to center supported research, interactions between faculty members at the two sites with industry representatives resulted in eight projects totaling around $3 million being funded directly to individual laboratories to build on faculty expertise toward pest management solutions. These projects involved more than half of the Phase I CAMTech members.&nbsp;</p> <p>The center made valuable contributions through training of graduate students and postdoctoral researchers for potential employment within the industrial sector. A total of 14 graduate students and 18 postdoctoral researchers drawn from diverse ethnic backgrounds were trained with support from CAMTech including multiple professional development activities coordinated by the center. Of these trainees, approximately one-third now work within the industrial sector. As one of the few women I/UCRC directors, Bonning provides a role model as a female leader within the biological sciences, and actively mentors CAMTech trainees.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 02/15/2019<br>      Modified by: Bryony&nbsp;C&nbsp;Bonning</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Image         </div> <div class="galControls onePhoto" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation onePhoto" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1338775/1338775_10258377_1550246759613_Slide1--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1338775/1338775_10258377_1550246759613_Slide1--rgov-800width.jpg" title="CAMTech logo"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1338775/1338775_10258377_1550246759613_Slide1--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="CAMTech logo"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">CAMTech</div> <div class="imageCredit">Jordan Miller</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Bryony&nbsp;C&nbsp;Bonning</div> <div class="imageTitle">CAMTech logo</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The Center for Arthropod Management Technologies (CAMTech), established in 2013, focuses on linking the efforts of industry, government and academia toward effective management of arthropod and nematode pests. Through precompetitive research, the center develops new tools and provides the knowledge necessary to effectively translate and apply novel pest management strategies to the field. During the Phase I funding period, the center was led by Iowa State University, Ames, IA with a second university site at the University of Kentucky in Lexington, KY. The Center and Site Directors, along with the Industry Advisory Board set the direction for the Center and select research projects to be funded.   During the five year Phase I funding period, the center made key advances through state of the art research with 21 research projects funded. The technical focus of the center is aligned with industry needs, with an emphasis on genomics, physiology, insect resistance, integrated pest management, and the development of new methods and tools. Eleven companies participated as center members during Phase I, with 100% member retention reflecting the high value gained from center participation. Member companies gained valuable insights into pest genomics and physiology that will facilitate development of new pest management tools for protection of agricultural and forestry crops and for the management of insects of public health importance. In addition to center supported research, interactions between faculty members at the two sites with industry representatives resulted in eight projects totaling around $3 million being funded directly to individual laboratories to build on faculty expertise toward pest management solutions. These projects involved more than half of the Phase I CAMTech members.   The center made valuable contributions through training of graduate students and postdoctoral researchers for potential employment within the industrial sector. A total of 14 graduate students and 18 postdoctoral researchers drawn from diverse ethnic backgrounds were trained with support from CAMTech including multiple professional development activities coordinated by the center. Of these trainees, approximately one-third now work within the industrial sector. As one of the few women I/UCRC directors, Bonning provides a role model as a female leader within the biological sciences, and actively mentors CAMTech trainees.       Last Modified: 02/15/2019       Submitted by: Bryony C Bonning]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
