<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>MRI Acquisition: An integrated platform for combined multi-scale mechanical and chemical analysis to inform functional materials design</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2013</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2015</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>434112.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>434112</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07020000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CBET</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Chem, Bioeng, Env, &amp; Transp Sys</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Leon Esterowitz</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>lesterow@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927942</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>1338154&lt;br/&gt;Ferguson&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The proposed system facilitates multimodal analysis of a single ROI on one modular platform by integrating an Atomic Force Microscope, an Ultra Nanoindentation Tester (max depth = 100 ìm; load = 50 mN), a Nanoindentation Tester (1000 ìm; 500 mN), and an optical microscope through which 2-D Raman microscopy (514 or 785 nm lasers) is performed. A high precision translation stage moves samples between modules. This proposed instrument will facilitate combined mechanical analysis, across multiple small length-scales, with determination of chemical composition at a single ROI. AFM and nanoindentation are well-established techniques for assessing stiff, conventional engineering materials. Yet most commercially available nanoindenters fail to accurately test materials that are hydrated, soft, or subjected to thermal changes. The CSM Instruments platform adeptly overcomes limitations of existing indenter systems by using one independent probe to find a sample's surface and continuously monitor thermal drift while a second probe indents the sample - critical for soft or fluid-like surfaces. Integration with a Raman microscope will facilitate combined analysis of mechanical behavior and materials chemistry in one exact ROI. Acquisition of this system at CU Boulder will inform design of cutting-edge materials in an unparalleled fashion and enhance our activities in world-class materials research.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/16/2013</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/16/2013</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1338154</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Richard</FirstName>
<LastName>Noble</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>D</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Richard D Noble</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>nobler@colorado.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>3034926100</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000200792</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/16/2013</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Steven</FirstName>
<LastName>George</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>M</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Steven M George</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>Steven.George@Colorado.Edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>3034923398</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000390861</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/16/2013</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Christopher</FirstName>
<LastName>Bowman</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>N</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Christopher N Bowman</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>christopher.bowman@colorado.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>3034923247</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000291917</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/16/2013</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Virginia</FirstName>
<LastName>Ferguson</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>L</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Virginia L Ferguson</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>virginia.ferguson@colorado.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>3037355232</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000220888</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/16/2013</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Daria</FirstName>
<LastName>Kotys-Schwartz</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>A</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Daria A Kotys-Schwartz</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>daria.kotys@colorado.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>3034923174</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000331350</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/16/2013</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Colorado at Boulder</Name>
<CityName>Boulder</CityName>
<ZipCode>803031058</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>3034926221</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>3100 Marine Street, Room 481</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[572 UCB]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Colorado</StateName>
<StateCode>CO</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CO02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>007431505</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>REGENTS OF THE UNIVERSITY OF COLORADO, THE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>007431505</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Colorado at Boulder]]></Name>
<CityName>Boulder</CityName>
<StateCode>CO</StateCode>
<ZipCode>803090427</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[1111 Engineering Dr]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Colorado</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CO02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1189</Code>
<Text>Major Research Instrumentation</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>065E</Code>
<Text>Radiation heat transfer</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0113</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2013~434112</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><strong><span style="text-decoration: underline;">Intellectual Merit Outcomes</span></strong>:&nbsp; University of Colorado at Boulder (CU) researchers are highly recognized for characterization and development of materials in key application areas that include: biological and tissue engineering, advanced functional materials, membranes and filtration, microsystems and energy storage, and study of natural (<em>e.g., </em>geologic) materials. Often, the functionality of these materials depends on complex composition (chemistry) and/or structure at small (nm to &mu;m) length-scales.&nbsp; In biological and natural materials, we often study fundamental questions such as how the variations in structure and chemistry contribute to the material&rsquo;s function and behavior. In engineered materials, we can utilize mechanics and chemistry measurements to inform the design of products that have vastly improved mechanical function and performance. Yet in the current materials environment, materials evaluation at small micrometer-sized length scales predominately relies on using separate instruments for mechanical property and chemical analyses. Yet tremendous benefits arise from co-locating the same exact region of interest (ROI) on a single sample.&nbsp; While such combined measurements are invaluable, they are seldom performed as the process is often complicated by: 1) locating exact ROIs using two separate instruments and 2) the difficult and time-consuming task of registering multiple images (and data sets) that often differ in length scale, aspect ratio, and rotation.&nbsp;</p> <p>Through this funded Major Research Instrumentation grant we acquired and linked together two independent instruments: a Hysitron TI-950 nanoindenter to evaluate mechanical stiffness and other properties and a Renishaw InVia Raman spectroscopy system and microscope to enable assessment of chemistry of a material&rsquo;s surface. These two instruments are linked via fiber optic lines and fiber optic probes that are mounted on the objective within the nanoindenter to enable collection of Raman spectra from samples mounted within the nanoindenter. While these two instruments are quite valuable as standalone tools, together they uniquely enable us to perform direct analysis of material chemistry at sites or regions where indentations, scratch testing, or wear testing has been performed. Use of these tools for research will uniquely will enable direct correlation between: 1) nanomechanical properties/behavior and material chemistry and/or 2) materials chemistry alterations prior to and following indentation, scratching, and wearing of surfaces. &nbsp;For example in the latter case, this unique capability is essential for understanding how pressure-induced phase transformations (following nanoindentation, as an example) cause phase changes or alter crystallinity.</p> <p>Through this newly installed and operational combined instrument, we seek to vastly improve assessment of how a material&rsquo;s chemistry and microstructure contribute to its mechanical function and application performance. We will improve our ability to analyze small length-scale phenomena in natural and engineered materials, and also to utilize this same information to advance materials design efforts via the typical iterative design cycle: design &ndash; implement &ndash; evaluate &ndash; redesign &ndash; reimplement &ndash; revaluate&hellip; &nbsp;Thus with this tool, we can make tremendous improvements in our ability to characterize and synthesize new materials.&nbsp; We will thus greatly enhance ongoing leading-edge materials research at CU Boulder.&nbsp;</p> <p><strong><span style="text-decoration: underline;">Broader Impact Outcomes</span></strong>:&nbsp; This project has enabled two postdocs and over ten PhD students at CU Boulder (across four departments and two different Colleges), and one PhD student from the Colorado Sc...]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Intellectual Merit Outcomes:  University of Colorado at Boulder (CU) researchers are highly recognized for characterization and development of materials in key application areas that include: biological and tissue engineering, advanced functional materials, membranes and filtration, microsystems and energy storage, and study of natural (e.g., geologic) materials. Often, the functionality of these materials depends on complex composition (chemistry) and/or structure at small (nm to &mu;m) length-scales.  In biological and natural materials, we often study fundamental questions such as how the variations in structure and chemistry contribute to the materialÆs function and behavior. In engineered materials, we can utilize mechanics and chemistry measurements to inform the design of products that have vastly improved mechanical function and performance. Yet in the current materials environment, materials evaluation at small micrometer-sized length scales predominately relies on using separate instruments for mechanical property and chemical analyses. Yet tremendous benefits arise from co-locating the same exact region of interest (ROI) on a single sample.  While such combined measurements are invaluable, they are seldom performed as the process is often complicated by: 1) locating exact ROIs using two separate instruments and 2) the difficult and time-consuming task of registering multiple images (and data sets) that often differ in length scale, aspect ratio, and rotation.   Through this funded Major Research Instrumentation grant we acquired and linked together two independent instruments: a Hysitron TI-950 nanoindenter to evaluate mechanical stiffness and other properties and a Renishaw InVia Raman spectroscopy system and microscope to enable assessment of chemistry of a materialÆs surface. These two instruments are linked via fiber optic lines and fiber optic probes that are mounted on the objective within the nanoindenter to enable collection of Raman spectra from samples mounted within the nanoindenter. While these two instruments are quite valuable as standalone tools, together they uniquely enable us to perform direct analysis of material chemistry at sites or regions where indentations, scratch testing, or wear testing has been performed. Use of these tools for research will uniquely will enable direct correlation between: 1) nanomechanical properties/behavior and material chemistry and/or 2) materials chemistry alterations prior to and following indentation, scratching, and wearing of surfaces.  For example in the latter case, this unique capability is essential for understanding how pressure-induced phase transformations (following nanoindentation, as an example) cause phase changes or alter crystallinity.  Through this newly installed and operational combined instrument, we seek to vastly improve assessment of how a materialÆs chemistry and microstructure contribute to its mechanical function and application performance. We will improve our ability to analyze small length-scale phenomena in natural and engineered materials, and also to utilize this same information to advance materials design efforts via the typical iterative design cycle: design &ndash; implement &ndash; evaluate &ndash; redesign &ndash; reimplement &ndash; revaluate&hellip;  Thus with this tool, we can make tremendous improvements in our ability to characterize and synthesize new materials.  We will thus greatly enhance ongoing leading-edge materials research at CU Boulder.   Broader Impact Outcomes:  This project has enabled two postdocs and over ten PhD students at CU Boulder (across four departments and two different Colleges), and one PhD student from the Colorado School of Mines, to train on and begin to collect data from the Hysitron nanoindenter and/or the Raman spectroscopy system within the first year of instrument operation.  Of these individuals, four are now considered proficient at performing combined measurements of nanoindentation and...]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
