<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Collaborative Research: Adaptable life history strategy of a migratory large predator in response to El Nino and climate change</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2013</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2014</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>75993.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>75993</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>06040300</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>GEO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>OCE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Ocean Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>David Garrison</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This project will examine the response of Dosidicus gigas (Humboldt squid) to an El Niño event in 2009-2010 that was accompanied by a collapse of the commercial fishery for this squid in the Guaymas Basin within the Gulf of California. This large squid is a major predator of great ecological and economic importance in the Gulf of California, the California Current, and Peru Current systems. In early 2010, these squid abandoned their normal coastal-shelf habitats in the Guaymas Basin and instead were found in the Salsipuedes Basin to the north, an area buffered from the effects of El Niño by the upwelling of colder water. The commercial fishery also relocated to this region and large squid were not found in the Guaymas Basin from 2010-2012, instead animals that matured at an unusually small size and young age were abundant.  A return to the large size-at-maturity condition has still not occurred, despite the apparent return of normal oceanographic conditions. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The El Niño of 2009-2010 presented an unforeseen opportunity to reveal an important feature of adaptability of Dosidicus gigas to an acute climatic anomaly, namely a large decrease in size and age at maturity. Now these investigators will have the opportunity to document recovery to the normal large size-at-maturity condition. The specific aims of this project are: 1) continue a program of acoustic surveys and direct sampling of squid that has already been established in the Gulf of California in order to assess distribution, biomass, life history strategy diet, and migratory and foraging behaviors relative to pre-El Niño conditions and 2) conduct analogous surveys in Monterey Bay, California in conjunction with long-term remote operated vehicle surveys of squid abundance.  The data from these studies will provide a comparison of recovery in the two different squid populations and yield valuable insights into what ecological effects an area is expected to experience with an invasion of either small or large Humboldt squid. As long-term climate change progresses, squid of both forms may expand northward into the California Current System.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Training will be provided for participating graduate and undergraduate students and an established collaboration will be continued with a technical college in Mexico that involves Mexican undergraduates in local sampling and developing public outreach aimed at the local squid fishing community. Squid abundance (biomass) and foraging (diet) data will be incorporated into NOAA fishery-management models being developed for Humboldt squid.  Findings of the project concerning El Niño, climate change, and squid fisheries will be incorporated into an established outreach program with NOAA (Squids4Kids), the Google Science Fair Science Hangouts program, and a NEH Summer Institute on John Steinbeck at Hopkins Marine Station. The investigators will continue to contribute exhibits being developed on squid at both the Monterey Bay Aquarium and Hatfield Marine Science Center.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/26/2013</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/26/2013</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.050</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1338432</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Kelly</FirstName>
<LastName>Benoit-Bird</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>J</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Kelly J Benoit-Bird</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>kbb@mbari.org</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>8317751833</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000118720</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/26/2013</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Oregon State University</Name>
<CityName>Corvallis</CityName>
<ZipCode>973318507</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5417374933</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>OREGON STATE UNIVERSITY</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Oregon</StateName>
<StateCode>OR</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>OR04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>053599908</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>OREGON STATE UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>053599908</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Oregon State University]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>OR</StateCode>
<ZipCode>973318507</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Oregon</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>OR04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1650</Code>
<Text>BIOLOGICAL OCEANOGRAPHY</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>0000</Code>
<Text>UNASSIGNED</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7914</Code>
<Text>RAPID</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0113</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2013~75993</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Understanding how large predators cope with short- and long-term environmental change is critical to evaluating the interacting effects of fisheries and climate change on marine ecosystem services. A difficulty in elucidating how these predators will respond is the long lifespan of most top predators, which necessitates long-term datasets. Dosidicus gigas (Humboldt or jumbo) squid, however, is an ecologically and commercially important large predator that is distributed throughout much of the eastern Pacific. This squid has a flexible diet, high fecundity, rapid growth rate, and short life span. 2001). Moreover, individuals can tolerate a broad range of temperature and oxygen concentrations, and they can rapidly migrate long distances. These life history traits and physiological capabilities suggest that Dosidicus can respond quickly, on both an individual and population level, to climatic change.</p> <p><br />An El Ni&ntilde;o event in 2009-2010 was accompanied by a collapse of the important commercial fishery for jumbo squid in the Guaymas Basin within the Gulf of California. As part of our NSF funded project &ldquo;Physiological limits to vertical migrations of the pelagic, jumbo squid, Dosidicus gigas, in the Gulf of California&rdquo;, we documented major changes in distribution, diet and reproductive strategy of these squid. In early 2010, large, mature squid abandoned their normal coastal-shelf habitats in the Guaymas Basin and instead were found in the Salsipuedes Basin to the north, an area buffered from the effects of El Ni&ntilde;o by tidal upwelling and a well-mixed water column. The commercial fishery also relocated to this region. Although large squid were not found in the Guaymas Basin from 2010-2012, much smaller squid were abundant and matured at an unusually small mantle-length (&lt;30 cm) and young age (~6 months). This corresponds to an order of magnitude decrease in body mass at maturity and a roughly proportionate decrease in fecundity. This project continued our time-series, following the biomass and life-history traits of squid after the recovery from El Ni&ntilde;o. We found no evidence of a return to pre-El Ni&ntilde;o conditions during the study.</p> <p>We hypothesize that juvenile squid in the Gulf of California responded to El Ni&ntilde;o with an alternative life-history trajectory in which gigantism and high fecundity in normally productive coastal-shelf habitats were traded for greatly accelerated reproduction at small size in an offshore environment that is less impacted by El Ni&ntilde;o. During 2011, both small and large mature squid were present in the Salsipuedes Basin, indicating that both life-history strategies can coexist. Hydro-acoustic data revealed that squid biomass in the study area nearly doubled between 2010 and 2011, primarily due to a large increase in small squid that were not susceptible to the fishery because of gear limitations. Large squid have still not returned to the traditional fishing grounds in the Guaymas Basin based on a sampling we carried out in Sept 2012 and 2013 and into summer 2014. These observations suggest that a population-level benefit for Dosidicus in the Guaymas Basin may have resulted from El Ni&ntilde;o and that the long-term persistence (through the end of the NSF funded field efforts) of the small size-at-maturity is an important element of this squid&rsquo;s life history strategy. Such a climate-driven switch in size-at-maturity allows Dosidicus to rapidly adapt to El Ni&ntilde;o, and potentially to also optimize adaptation to longer-term climate-change involving factors, particularly global-scale warming, expanding oxygen minimum zones and<br />changing&nbsp;productivity.</p> <p><br />As part of this effort, training was provided for participating graduate and undergraduate students. The established collaboration (SURMAR, Sustainable Utilization and Research in the Central Mar de Cort&ea...]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Understanding how large predators cope with short- and long-term environmental change is critical to evaluating the interacting effects of fisheries and climate change on marine ecosystem services. A difficulty in elucidating how these predators will respond is the long lifespan of most top predators, which necessitates long-term datasets. Dosidicus gigas (Humboldt or jumbo) squid, however, is an ecologically and commercially important large predator that is distributed throughout much of the eastern Pacific. This squid has a flexible diet, high fecundity, rapid growth rate, and short life span. 2001). Moreover, individuals can tolerate a broad range of temperature and oxygen concentrations, and they can rapidly migrate long distances. These life history traits and physiological capabilities suggest that Dosidicus can respond quickly, on both an individual and population level, to climatic change.   An El Ni&ntilde;o event in 2009-2010 was accompanied by a collapse of the important commercial fishery for jumbo squid in the Guaymas Basin within the Gulf of California. As part of our NSF funded project "Physiological limits to vertical migrations of the pelagic, jumbo squid, Dosidicus gigas, in the Gulf of California", we documented major changes in distribution, diet and reproductive strategy of these squid. In early 2010, large, mature squid abandoned their normal coastal-shelf habitats in the Guaymas Basin and instead were found in the Salsipuedes Basin to the north, an area buffered from the effects of El Ni&ntilde;o by tidal upwelling and a well-mixed water column. The commercial fishery also relocated to this region. Although large squid were not found in the Guaymas Basin from 2010-2012, much smaller squid were abundant and matured at an unusually small mantle-length (&lt;30 cm) and young age (~6 months). This corresponds to an order of magnitude decrease in body mass at maturity and a roughly proportionate decrease in fecundity. This project continued our time-series, following the biomass and life-history traits of squid after the recovery from El Ni&ntilde;o. We found no evidence of a return to pre-El Ni&ntilde;o conditions during the study.  We hypothesize that juvenile squid in the Gulf of California responded to El Ni&ntilde;o with an alternative life-history trajectory in which gigantism and high fecundity in normally productive coastal-shelf habitats were traded for greatly accelerated reproduction at small size in an offshore environment that is less impacted by El Ni&ntilde;o. During 2011, both small and large mature squid were present in the Salsipuedes Basin, indicating that both life-history strategies can coexist. Hydro-acoustic data revealed that squid biomass in the study area nearly doubled between 2010 and 2011, primarily due to a large increase in small squid that were not susceptible to the fishery because of gear limitations. Large squid have still not returned to the traditional fishing grounds in the Guaymas Basin based on a sampling we carried out in Sept 2012 and 2013 and into summer 2014. These observations suggest that a population-level benefit for Dosidicus in the Guaymas Basin may have resulted from El Ni&ntilde;o and that the long-term persistence (through the end of the NSF funded field efforts) of the small size-at-maturity is an important element of this squidÆs life history strategy. Such a climate-driven switch in size-at-maturity allows Dosidicus to rapidly adapt to El Ni&ntilde;o, and potentially to also optimize adaptation to longer-term climate-change involving factors, particularly global-scale warming, expanding oxygen minimum zones and changing productivity.   As part of this effort, training was provided for participating graduate and undergraduate students. The established collaboration (SURMAR, Sustainable Utilization and Research in the Central Mar de Cort&eacute;s, under auspices of The Ocean Foundation) was continued with a technical college in Mexico and involved Mexican ...]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
