<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>FESD Type I: The Dynamics of Mountains, Landscapes and Climate in the Distribution and Generation of Biodiversity of the Amazon/Andean Forest</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2013</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2020</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>4430000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>4430000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>06030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>GEO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>EAR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Earth Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Justin Lawrence</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>jlawrenc@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922425</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The forests of tropical South America host some of the highest biodiversity on Earth. In this project, an interdisciplinary team of geologists, climatologists, and biologists will take advantage of recent advances in their respective disciplines to develop an integrated understanding of how climate and geology interact to shape the distribution and generation of biodiversity in these Amazon/Andean forests through time. The Amazon and Andes are a dynamically linked highly interactive system. On long timescales, uplift of the Andes affects Amazon climate and hydrology. Andean uplift also generates the sediment fill, nutrient supply, river routing, and soil composition of the adjacent lowland basin of the Amazon and hence affects the productivity of its forests. But the interactions are bi-directional, because changes in climate, hydrology, and sediment supply influence rates of uplift through isostatic (buoyancy) effects produced by weathering and erosion. Together the multiple system components interact in complex ways to effect the origin and demise of new species and thus determine biodiversity. Today, this biodiversity is threatened by global climate change and other human activities. For example, a major emerging threat is the planned construction of headwater dams that will sever the transfer of nutrients from the Andes to the Amazon and impact the productivity and diversity of its forests and waterways. Thus, more than ever, there is a need for better understanding of the factors that foster the evolution and maintenance of biodiversity. The project is an interdisciplinary effort that unites scientists from both North and South America. It will support the education, training, and mentoring of undergraduate students, graduate students, and postdoctoral scientists at this exciting new frontier through the integration of fieldwork, laboratory studies, and modeling.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Before it is possible to quantify relationships between extrinsic forcings (e.g. climate, tectonics, hydrology) and the observed distribution of species through time, it is first necessary to generate accurately dated histories of the underlying geologic and climatic processes and to explore the governing rules for how environment influences diversity. The interdisciplinary team will undertake new detailed field and laboratory investigations of key aspects of the system components of the linked Andes-Amazon system, emphasizing: (1) determination of the history of Andean uplift, particularly in the oft-overlooked Western Cordillera; (2) a first attempt at reconstruction of a complete history of Cenozoic paleoclimate in the western Amazon lowlands; (3) isotope-enabled ocean-atmosphere climate modeling at key Cenozoic time slices; (4) molecular genetics of woody plant taxa carefully chosen to test several fundamental hypotheses about the role of uplift and climate in generation of diversity; (5) construction of an over-arching modeling framework (that incorporates new data on uplift, climate, and biota) linking paleo-topography, climate, hydrology, and nutrient cycling to plant traits, productivity, ecologic niche, and species distribution. The ultimate goal is to understand the role of environment and environmental history in genetic differentiation of populations and the origins of new species. By deciphering how environment affects biodiversity and, conversely, how genetic sequences of plant species encode the history of the physical environment, it is envisioned that molecular phylogenetics will inform geological history, much like paleontology informs stratigraphic and paleoenvironmental interpretation, and a new field of "geo-genomics" will emerge.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/02/2013</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/23/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.050</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1338694</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Sherilyn</FirstName>
<LastName>Fritz</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>C</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Sherilyn C Fritz</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>sfritz2@unl.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>4024726431</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000233533</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/02/2013</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Paul</FirstName>
<LastName>Baker</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>A</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Paul A Baker</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>pbaker@duke.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>9196846450</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000298735</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/02/2013</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>David</FirstName>
<LastName>Battisti</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>S</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>David S Battisti</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>david@atmos.washington.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2065432019</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000107020</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/02/2013</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Christopher</FirstName>
<LastName>Dick</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>W</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Christopher W Dick</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>cwdick@umich.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>7347649408</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000219641</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/02/2013</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Brian</FirstName>
<LastName>Horton</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>K</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Brian K Horton</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>horton@jsg.utexas.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5124711869</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000316264</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/02/2013</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Duke University</Name>
<CityName>Durham</CityName>
<ZipCode>277054010</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>9196843030</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>2200 W. Main St, Suite 710</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[Erwin Square]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>North Carolina</StateName>
<StateCode>NC</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NC01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>044387793</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>DUKE UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>044387793</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Duke University]]></Name>
<CityName>Durham</CityName>
<StateCode>NC</StateCode>
<ZipCode>277080227</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[103 Old Chem Bldg]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>North Carolina</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NC04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>8016</Code>
<Text>Front in Earth Sys Dynamics</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0113</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0114</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2013~2440000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~1990000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The landscape of South America at the end of the Cretaceous, about 65 million years ago, was very different from the continent that we know today. In this project, an interdisciplinary team of geologists, climatologists, and biologists explored how long-term geological changes, such as increasing width of the Atlantic Ocean, the punctuated uplift of the Andean Cordilleras, and the development of the now trans-continental Amazon river system, influenced the climate and biota of tropical South America through the late Mesozoic and Cenozoic, including the evolution of biodiversity in the neotropical forests, which today are the most biodiverse on Earth. Using climate models, we found that when the Atlantic Ocean was approximately half its current width, about 55 million years ago, the lowland regions of the continent were significantly drier relative to modern climate. By study of outcropping sediments in the Andes of Ecuador, Peru, and Bolivia, we unraveled the complex uplift history of both the eastern and western cordilleras over the last 80 million years. We found that the climate of the tropical Andes was wetter than today before the eastern Cordillera reached its current elevation. In the adjoining Amazon lowlands, progressive wetting due to the widening Atlantic and the rising Andes, only partly offset by decreasing global atmospheric CO2 concentrations, may have contributed to the accumulating biodiversity of the Amazon forests. We also developed geochemical tools to fingerprint the sources of sediments deposited in different basins at different periods of time, a tool that can be used to track how the uplift and subsequent erosion of the Andes affected the flow of water and sediments and the resultant topography.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>We compared the genetic composition of specific groups of modern plant species, both in the Andes and in the Amazon, to infer their evolutionary history, a sub-discipline called phylogenetics. For example, we compared the genetics of the majority of species in the brazil nut family (Lecythidaceae) across Brazil, Ecuador, and Panama. These results show that the initial colonization of tropical America was accomplished via long-distance oceanic dispersal from the Old World tropics and also that the most diverse groups in the family originated in the Guiana Shield region, before expanding across the Amazon basin. In addition, we studied woody plants on opposite sides of the modern Amazon River to evaluate their degree of genetic similarity, which reflects how much gene flow (mixing and interbreeding) occurs between populations. The analysis indicates that the level of gene flow is dependent upon the distance between opposite river banks. Thus, as rivers evolve and widen over time, they may become more substantive barriers to plant dispersal. In the Andes, we compared the genetics of high-elevation (p&aacute;ramo) plants in multiple localities from north to south. For some key p&aacute;ramo species, the results suggest that they first colonized the central Andean cordillera of Colombia and later spread south, at a time much earlier than has been assumed previously for the origins of this distinctive high-elevation grassland habitat.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>Team members also contributed to the maintenance and expansion of a network of forest inventory plots that span the elevational and climatic gradient from the lowland Amazon into the adjacent Andean highlands. These plots, which are consistently monitored and inventoried for species composition and a number of environmental conditions, contribute to an understanding of how forest communities change in response to changes in temperature and moisture along the Andes-Amazon gradient, thus, providing insight into modern biodiversity responses to ongoing and future environmental change.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>The scientific team mentored multiple undergraduate students, graduate students, and postdoctoral fellows from both US and South American universities, who received training in interdisciplinary sciences across a broad spectrum of geoscience and bioscience disciplines, as well as experience working together in collaborative international teams to address large-scale scientific questions. The project also has contributed to development of the human infrastructure needed to understand and conserve the diverse forests and landscapes of the Andes and Amazon.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 10/02/2020<br>      Modified by: Paul&nbsp;A&nbsp;Baker</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The landscape of South America at the end of the Cretaceous, about 65 million years ago, was very different from the continent that we know today. In this project, an interdisciplinary team of geologists, climatologists, and biologists explored how long-term geological changes, such as increasing width of the Atlantic Ocean, the punctuated uplift of the Andean Cordilleras, and the development of the now trans-continental Amazon river system, influenced the climate and biota of tropical South America through the late Mesozoic and Cenozoic, including the evolution of biodiversity in the neotropical forests, which today are the most biodiverse on Earth. Using climate models, we found that when the Atlantic Ocean was approximately half its current width, about 55 million years ago, the lowland regions of the continent were significantly drier relative to modern climate. By study of outcropping sediments in the Andes of Ecuador, Peru, and Bolivia, we unraveled the complex uplift history of both the eastern and western cordilleras over the last 80 million years. We found that the climate of the tropical Andes was wetter than today before the eastern Cordillera reached its current elevation. In the adjoining Amazon lowlands, progressive wetting due to the widening Atlantic and the rising Andes, only partly offset by decreasing global atmospheric CO2 concentrations, may have contributed to the accumulating biodiversity of the Amazon forests. We also developed geochemical tools to fingerprint the sources of sediments deposited in different basins at different periods of time, a tool that can be used to track how the uplift and subsequent erosion of the Andes affected the flow of water and sediments and the resultant topography.     We compared the genetic composition of specific groups of modern plant species, both in the Andes and in the Amazon, to infer their evolutionary history, a sub-discipline called phylogenetics. For example, we compared the genetics of the majority of species in the brazil nut family (Lecythidaceae) across Brazil, Ecuador, and Panama. These results show that the initial colonization of tropical America was accomplished via long-distance oceanic dispersal from the Old World tropics and also that the most diverse groups in the family originated in the Guiana Shield region, before expanding across the Amazon basin. In addition, we studied woody plants on opposite sides of the modern Amazon River to evaluate their degree of genetic similarity, which reflects how much gene flow (mixing and interbreeding) occurs between populations. The analysis indicates that the level of gene flow is dependent upon the distance between opposite river banks. Thus, as rivers evolve and widen over time, they may become more substantive barriers to plant dispersal. In the Andes, we compared the genetics of high-elevation (p&aacute;ramo) plants in multiple localities from north to south. For some key p&aacute;ramo species, the results suggest that they first colonized the central Andean cordillera of Colombia and later spread south, at a time much earlier than has been assumed previously for the origins of this distinctive high-elevation grassland habitat.     Team members also contributed to the maintenance and expansion of a network of forest inventory plots that span the elevational and climatic gradient from the lowland Amazon into the adjacent Andean highlands. These plots, which are consistently monitored and inventoried for species composition and a number of environmental conditions, contribute to an understanding of how forest communities change in response to changes in temperature and moisture along the Andes-Amazon gradient, thus, providing insight into modern biodiversity responses to ongoing and future environmental change.     The scientific team mentored multiple undergraduate students, graduate students, and postdoctoral fellows from both US and South American universities, who received training in interdisciplinary sciences across a broad spectrum of geoscience and bioscience disciplines, as well as experience working together in collaborative international teams to address large-scale scientific questions. The project also has contributed to development of the human infrastructure needed to understand and conserve the diverse forests and landscapes of the Andes and Amazon.       Last Modified: 10/02/2020       Submitted by: Paul A Baker]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
