<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>US-Based Students Support to Attend the IEEE International Conference on Mobile Data Management 2013 (IEEE MDM 2013)</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>04/15/2013</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>03/31/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>20000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>20000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>05020000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>CSE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>IIS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Information &amp; Intelligent Systems</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Sylvia Spengler</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>sspengle@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032928930</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This proposal seeks support in the form of travel awards for U.S.-based graduate and undergraduate students to participate in the 14th IEEE MDM 2013 Conference, which will be held in Milan, Italy, June 3-6, 2013. The MDM series of conferences, annually organized by the IEEE society since 1999, has established itself as a prestigious forum for the exchange of innovative and significant research results in mobile data management. The conference provides unique opportunities for researchers, engineers, practitioners, developers, and users to explore new ideas, techniques, and tools, and to exchange experiences in mobile data management. Attendees will participate interactions via lively presentations of accepted technical papers, posters and demos, and invited talks given by leading academics and industry professionals of related fields. The participation of US based graduate and promising undergraduate students will result in the intellectual simulation of young minds to pursue advanced research and development activities in this area that has huge technical and societal impact, and helps U.S. keep the leading position in this vital field. To ensure a broader impact in disseminating the results of the conference, and to garner interest among young researchers in the fields of mobile data management, this award is for travel grants enabling student travel to attend IEEE MDM 2013 and the workshops to be held in conjunction with the MDM 2013. The purpose is to encourage the attendance of students who otherwise would not have the opportunity to participate in such a conference.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The allocation of the grants will be based on need and impact of the applicant?s attendance in increasing the diversity of conference participation.  Minority students, students from underrepresented institutions, and students in financial need will be given higher priority.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>04/10/2013</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>04/12/2017</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.070</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1338260</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Ouri</FirstName>
<LastName>Wolfson</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Ouri Wolfson</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>wolfson@uic.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>3129966770</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000148177</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/10/2013</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Illinois at Chicago</Name>
<CityName>Chicago</CityName>
<ZipCode>606124305</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>3129962862</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>809 S. Marshfield Avenue</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[MB 502, M/C 551]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Illinois</StateName>
<StateCode>IL</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>IL07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>098987217</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF ILLINOIS</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>041544081</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Illinois at Chicago]]></Name>
<CityName>Chicago</CityName>
<StateCode>IL</StateCode>
<ZipCode>606077042</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[851 S. Morgan Steet]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Illinois</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>IL07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7364</Code>
<Text>Info Integration &amp; Informatics</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7484</Code>
<Text>IIS SPECIAL PROJECTS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7556</Code>
<Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0113</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2013~20000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><span><span style="font-size: small;">This project provided travel awards for about 10 U.S.-based students to participate in conferences related to spatial/temporal data and mobility, such as the IEEE MDM Conference. The MDM series of conferences, annually organized by the IEEE society since 1999,</span></span><span> </span><span><span style="font-size: small;">has established itself as a prestigious forum for the exchange of innovative and significant research results in mobile data management. The conference provides unique opportunities for researchers, engineers, practitioners, developers, and users to explore new ideas, techniques, and tools, and to exchange experiences in mobile data management. Attendees participated in interactions via lively presentations of accepted technical papers, posters and demos, and invited talks given by leading academics and industry professionals of related fields.<span>&nbsp; </span>The participation of US based students resulted in the intellectual simulation of young minds to pursue advanced research and development activities in this area that has huge technical and societal impact, and helps U.S. keep the leading position in this vital field.</span></span></p> <p><span>To garner interest among young researchers in the fields of mobile and spatio-temporal data management, this award enabled student travel to attend conferences and workshops. <span>&nbsp;</span>It enabled the attendance of students who otherwise would not have the opportunity to participate in such conferences. The effort was directed at promoting student exposure to research and enhancing the integration of research and education, pursuant to NSF policy. </span><strong>&nbsp;</strong><em></em><span><span style="font-size: small;"><br /></span></span></p> <p><strong>&nbsp;</strong><em>&nbsp;</em></p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 05/09/2018<br>      Modified by: Ouri&nbsp;Wolfson</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ This project provided travel awards for about 10 U.S.-based students to participate in conferences related to spatial/temporal data and mobility, such as the IEEE MDM Conference. The MDM series of conferences, annually organized by the IEEE society since 1999, has established itself as a prestigious forum for the exchange of innovative and significant research results in mobile data management. The conference provides unique opportunities for researchers, engineers, practitioners, developers, and users to explore new ideas, techniques, and tools, and to exchange experiences in mobile data management. Attendees participated in interactions via lively presentations of accepted technical papers, posters and demos, and invited talks given by leading academics and industry professionals of related fields.  The participation of US based students resulted in the intellectual simulation of young minds to pursue advanced research and development activities in this area that has huge technical and societal impact, and helps U.S. keep the leading position in this vital field.  To garner interest among young researchers in the fields of mobile and spatio-temporal data management, this award enabled student travel to attend conferences and workshops.  It enabled the attendance of students who otherwise would not have the opportunity to participate in such conferences. The effort was directed at promoting student exposure to research and enhancing the integration of research and education, pursuant to NSF policy.                 Last Modified: 05/09/2018       Submitted by: Ouri Wolfson]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
