<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>MRI: Acquisition of a Multi-beam (Ga, Ne, He,) Microscope for Nanomaterials Modification and Investigation</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2013</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2016</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>1525503.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>1525503</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03070000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DMR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Materials Research</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Leonard Spinu</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>lspinu@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922665</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>1338139&lt;br/&gt;Hosemann&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Technical Abstract:&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The acquisition of the ORION Nanofab, a Multi-beam (Ga, Ne, He,) Ion Microscope for Nanomaterials Modification and Investigation, will significantly upgrade the capabilities at the University of Californian Berkeley campus and to outside users interested in ion microscopy. The instrument will be housed at a multiuser facility on campus as a multi-user device. The three ion beams Ga, Ne and He will allow for not just high resolution ion imaging but also virtually damage-free nanofabrication and ion patterning while also enabling direct He or Ne implantation studies. This instrument combines fast ion milling using the Ga beam with a precise fine milling utilizing either Ne or the He beam while being usable as helium ion microscope (HIM) for  high resolution imaging. The instrument will be used for patterning in polymers, imaging of biomaterials, fabrication of optical antennas, imaging cell structures, modifying grapheme structures, enabling nano-scale heat transfer studies, quantitative characterization of near-field energy transfer, in-situ He implantation, or for the manufacturing of damage-free and site-specific TEM (transmission electron microscopy), APT (atom probe tomography) and nanoscale specimens for further investigation. The device marks a new generation of nanofabrication tools with wide applicability and unprecedented resolution and accuracy. The novelty of this device will also have a substantial impact on teaching at U.C. Berkeley as well as cutting-edge demonstrations for students and outside interested personnel.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Non-Technical Abstract:&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This Major Research Instrumentation (MRI) Program grant supports the acquisition of a Multi-beam (Ga, Ne, He,) Microscope for Nanomaterials Modification and Investigation at the University of California at Berkeley. This tool will allow for advanced characterization of nanoscale structures ranging from Biology, Chemistry, Geoscience, Materials Science, Physics and Mechanical, Electrical, Mining and Nuclear Engineering. In addition, the instrument will allow for materials modification at the nanoscale with unprecedented precision and little damage to the material. The instrument utilizes three different beams of ions allowing the user to select the right beam for the right application and material. The instrument has extremely wide applicability and will be installed as a multi-user tool incorporated into a UC Berkeley user center accessible to scientists, engineers and interested personnel nationwide. This instrument marks a new generation of ion beam microscopes and nanofabrication tools allowing for the investigation and modification of matter at the smallest scales. The tool will also be used to demonstrate to the general public cutting-edge applications of nanoscale science and technology using a "seeing is believing" approach. This instrument will also have be used in teaching to students in the areas mentioned above by incorporation of real life examples and demonstrations.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>09/06/2013</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>09/06/2013</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1338139</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Nipam</FirstName>
<LastName>Patel</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>H</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Nipam H Patel</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>npatel@mbl.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5104954133</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000372107</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/06/2013</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Jeffrey</FirstName>
<LastName>Bokor</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Jeffrey Bokor</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>jbokor@eecs.berkeley.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5106424134</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000173149</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/06/2013</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Michael</FirstName>
<LastName>Crommie</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>F</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Michael F Crommie</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>crommie@berkeley.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5106429392</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000449302</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/06/2013</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Andrew</FirstName>
<LastName>Minor</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>M</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Andrew M Minor</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>aminor@berkeley.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5104952749</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000513140</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/06/2013</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Peter</FirstName>
<LastName>Hosemann</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Peter Hosemann</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>peterh@berkeley.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5106428109</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000567975</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/06/2013</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of California-Berkeley</Name>
<CityName>BERKELEY</CityName>
<ZipCode>947101749</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5106433891</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>Sponsored Projects Office</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[1608 Fourth Street, Suite 220]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>13</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CA13</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>124726725</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>REGENTS OF THE UNIVERSITY OF CALIFORNIA, THE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>071549000</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of California-Berkeley]]></Name>
<CityName>Berkeley</CityName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>947201730</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[1107 Etcheverry Hall]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>13</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CA13</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1189</Code>
<Text>Major Research Instrumentation</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1189</Code>
<Text>MAJOR RESEARCH INSTRUMENTATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7237</Code>
<Text>NANO NON-SOLIC SCI &amp; ENG AWD</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7573</Code>
<Text>BIO-RELATED MATERIALS RESEARCH</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0113</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2013~1525503</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>This Major Research Instrumentation Program grant supported the acquisition of a multi-ion-beam microscope that enables nanomaterial modification and investigation using helium, neon and gallium focused ion beams. The microscope is a Zeiss Orion NanoFab and has been installed at the University of California, Berkeley, at the Biomolecular Nanotechnology Center, where it is open for full-community access. The tool is used by students from a range of departments at UC Berkeley and beyond (e.g. Materials Science, Nuclear Engineering, Electrical Engineering, Physics, Biology) for a wide range of research projects. For example, the helium ion beam, which is the most finely focused of the three beams, is used to create and image nano-sized structures that have applications in optical sensing. It is also used in irradiation studies to form nano-sized gas bubbles in materials thus simulating processes occurring in nuclear fusion applications. In conjunction with a charge neutralization functionality, researchers can image non-conductive (e.g. biological) samples without needing to coat the sample with a conductive layer first. The neon and gallium beams are used in fabrication applications in which larger amounts of material need to be removed (the higher the mass of the ion, the higher the sputtering rate). By using all three beams sequentially (Ga, Ne, then He) rather intricate structures can be made. In addition, a metal and insulator deposition system enhances the capabilities of the tool even further. In summary, the tool is highly versatile lending itself to a wide range of research in the field of nanomaterials generating very visual feedback through the spectacular images it can acquire that can be used to help explain new science and technology concepts and motivate the next generation of scientists.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 09/04/2016<br>      Modified by: Peter&nbsp;Hosemann</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ This Major Research Instrumentation Program grant supported the acquisition of a multi-ion-beam microscope that enables nanomaterial modification and investigation using helium, neon and gallium focused ion beams. The microscope is a Zeiss Orion NanoFab and has been installed at the University of California, Berkeley, at the Biomolecular Nanotechnology Center, where it is open for full-community access. The tool is used by students from a range of departments at UC Berkeley and beyond (e.g. Materials Science, Nuclear Engineering, Electrical Engineering, Physics, Biology) for a wide range of research projects. For example, the helium ion beam, which is the most finely focused of the three beams, is used to create and image nano-sized structures that have applications in optical sensing. It is also used in irradiation studies to form nano-sized gas bubbles in materials thus simulating processes occurring in nuclear fusion applications. In conjunction with a charge neutralization functionality, researchers can image non-conductive (e.g. biological) samples without needing to coat the sample with a conductive layer first. The neon and gallium beams are used in fabrication applications in which larger amounts of material need to be removed (the higher the mass of the ion, the higher the sputtering rate). By using all three beams sequentially (Ga, Ne, then He) rather intricate structures can be made. In addition, a metal and insulator deposition system enhances the capabilities of the tool even further. In summary, the tool is highly versatile lending itself to a wide range of research in the field of nanomaterials generating very visual feedback through the spectacular images it can acquire that can be used to help explain new science and technology concepts and motivate the next generation of scientists.       Last Modified: 09/04/2016       Submitted by: Peter Hosemann]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
