<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Collaborative Research: CC-NIE Integration: Developing Applications with Networking Capabilities via End-to-End SDN (DANCES)</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>01/01/2014</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2015</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>225000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>225000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>05090000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>CSE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>OAC</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Office of Advanced Cyberinfrastructure (OAC)</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Kevin Thompson</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>kthompso@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924220</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The DANCES project team of network engineers, application developers, and research scientists is implementing a software-defined networking (SDN)-enabled end-to-end environment to optimize support for scientific data transfer.  DANCES accomplishes this optimization by integrating high performance computing job scheduling, network control capabilities offered by SDN along with data movement applications in an end-to-end network infrastructure.  This integration provides access to control mechanisms for managing network bandwidth. The control of network resources enabled by SDN enhances application stability, predictability and performance, thereby improving overall network utilization. Motivation for the DANCES project is to apply the advantages of advanced network services to the problem of congested metropolitan and campus networks.  DANCES uses XSEDENet across Internet2 in conjunction with OpenFlow-enabled network switches installed at the collaborating sites as the end-to-end hardware and software substrate.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Knowledge gained through DANCES is being disseminated through educational programs offered by the participating institutions and at existing community workshops, meetings, and conferences.  The insights and experience obtained through DANCES will promote a better understanding of the technical requirements for supporting end-to-end SDN across wide area and campus cyberinfrastructure.  The resulting SDN-enabled applications will make the request and configuration of high bandwidth connections easily accessible to end users and improve network performance and predictability for supporting a wide range of applications.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>09/20/2013</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>09/20/2013</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.070</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1340981</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Gregory</FirstName>
<LastName>Peterson</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>D</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Gregory D Peterson</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>gdp@utk.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>8659746352</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000473243</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/20/2013</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Victor</FirstName>
<LastName>Hazlewood</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>G</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Victor G Hazlewood</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>victor@utk.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>8657760770</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000620876</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/20/2013</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Tennessee Knoxville</Name>
<CityName>Knoxville</CityName>
<ZipCode>379163801</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>8659743466</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1331 CIR PARK DR</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Tennessee</StateName>
<StateCode>TN</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>TN02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>003387891</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF TENNESSEE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>003387891</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Tennessee Knoxville]]></Name>
<CityName>Knoxville</CityName>
<StateCode>TN</StateCode>
<ZipCode>379163801</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[1 Circle Park]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Tennessee</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>TN02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>8080</Code>
<Text>Campus Cyberinfrastructure</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7433</Code>
<Text>CyberInfra Frmwrk 21st (CIF21)</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0113</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2013~225000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The Developing Applications with Networking Capabilities via End-to-End SDN (DANCES) project was a collaboration between The University of Tennessee's National Institute for Computational Sciences (UT-NICS), Pittsburgh Supercomputing Center (PSC), Pennsylvania State University (Penn State), the National Center for Supercomputing Applications (NCSA), Texas Advanced Computing Center (TACC), Georgia Institute of Technology (Georgia Tech), the Extreme Science and Engineering Discovery Environment (XSEDE), and Internet2 to investigate and develop a capability to add network bandwidth scheduling capability via software-defined networking (SDN) programmability to selected cyberinfrastructure services and applications. DANCES, funded by the National Science Foundation's Campus Cyberinfrastructure - Network Infrastructure and Engineering (CC-NIE) program award numbers 1341005, 1340953, and1340981, has investigated three vendor network devices in order to determine which implements the OpenFlow 1.3 standard with DANCES requirements of meters and per-port queueing in order to provide a network reservation and rate-limiting capability desired to implement the goals of DANCES.&nbsp; Of the devices tested the DANCES project determined that the Corsa DP6410 met the requirements of OpenFlow 1.3 especially the implementation of features of metering and per port queueing which allow complex quality of service configuration for network flows.&nbsp; After selection of the network device a test environment was setup between the University of Tennessee and PSC (see attached figure).&nbsp; Tests were performed across the test environment including: (1) networking and network performance with iperf3; (2) GridFTP and GridFTP performance; (3) performance with and without Corsa OpenFlow rate limiting metering configured;&nbsp; (4) a resource management capability with Torque and Moab simulating a batch queuing and scheduling capability; (5) installation, configuration and use of a Ryu OpenFlow controller; and (6) submission of a test job using all the previously mentioned services to simulate a data transfer batch job employing network scheduling and network bandwidth reservation using OpenFlow to reserve network bandwidth between UT-NICS and PSC across the WAN.&nbsp;&nbsp; Results of the DANCES work by University of Tennessee included: two reports evaluating the Juniper and Corsa network devices and their suitability for DANCES which were prepared and submitted to the XSEDE Technology Investigation Service for inclusion in the XSEDE Technology Evaluation Database (XTED); and a paper describing the DANCES project, environment, and results which has been developed and is to be submitted for review for acceptance to the XSEDE16 conference.</p> <p>With the knowledge gained by the implementation of the DANCES project, the DANCES collaborators including XSEDE have a strong foundation for implementing scheduling of network resources utilizing OpenFlow 1.3 feature sets with a Corsa DP6410 device to provide network performance reservation and network quality of service rate limiting on specific network flows within the datacenter and across the WAN.&nbsp; Armed with this information network engineers and system administrators can configure environments that can significantly impact overall researcher workflows including the network data flows between data transfer resources at separate organizations across the WAN.&nbsp; The test environment at UT-NICS will remain active through 2016 for use by the PSC DANCES project and to demonstrate this capability with other organizations who want to participate in scheduling of network resources and network bandwidth reservation capabilities between UT-NICS and data transfer resources at their organization.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 03/31/2016<br>      Modified by: Victor&nbsp;G&nbsp;Hazlewood</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gal...]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The Developing Applications with Networking Capabilities via End-to-End SDN (DANCES) project was a collaboration between The University of Tennessee's National Institute for Computational Sciences (UT-NICS), Pittsburgh Supercomputing Center (PSC), Pennsylvania State University (Penn State), the National Center for Supercomputing Applications (NCSA), Texas Advanced Computing Center (TACC), Georgia Institute of Technology (Georgia Tech), the Extreme Science and Engineering Discovery Environment (XSEDE), and Internet2 to investigate and develop a capability to add network bandwidth scheduling capability via software-defined networking (SDN) programmability to selected cyberinfrastructure services and applications. DANCES, funded by the National Science Foundation's Campus Cyberinfrastructure - Network Infrastructure and Engineering (CC-NIE) program award numbers 1341005, 1340953, and1340981, has investigated three vendor network devices in order to determine which implements the OpenFlow 1.3 standard with DANCES requirements of meters and per-port queueing in order to provide a network reservation and rate-limiting capability desired to implement the goals of DANCES.  Of the devices tested the DANCES project determined that the Corsa DP6410 met the requirements of OpenFlow 1.3 especially the implementation of features of metering and per port queueing which allow complex quality of service configuration for network flows.  After selection of the network device a test environment was setup between the University of Tennessee and PSC (see attached figure).  Tests were performed across the test environment including: (1) networking and network performance with iperf3; (2) GridFTP and GridFTP performance; (3) performance with and without Corsa OpenFlow rate limiting metering configured;  (4) a resource management capability with Torque and Moab simulating a batch queuing and scheduling capability; (5) installation, configuration and use of a Ryu OpenFlow controller; and (6) submission of a test job using all the previously mentioned services to simulate a data transfer batch job employing network scheduling and network bandwidth reservation using OpenFlow to reserve network bandwidth between UT-NICS and PSC across the WAN.   Results of the DANCES work by University of Tennessee included: two reports evaluating the Juniper and Corsa network devices and their suitability for DANCES which were prepared and submitted to the XSEDE Technology Investigation Service for inclusion in the XSEDE Technology Evaluation Database (XTED); and a paper describing the DANCES project, environment, and results which has been developed and is to be submitted for review for acceptance to the XSEDE16 conference.  With the knowledge gained by the implementation of the DANCES project, the DANCES collaborators including XSEDE have a strong foundation for implementing scheduling of network resources utilizing OpenFlow 1.3 feature sets with a Corsa DP6410 device to provide network performance reservation and network quality of service rate limiting on specific network flows within the datacenter and across the WAN.  Armed with this information network engineers and system administrators can configure environments that can significantly impact overall researcher workflows including the network data flows between data transfer resources at separate organizations across the WAN.  The test environment at UT-NICS will remain active through 2016 for use by the PSC DANCES project and to demonstrate this capability with other organizations who want to participate in scheduling of network resources and network bandwidth reservation capabilities between UT-NICS and data transfer resources at their organization.       Last Modified: 03/31/2016       Submitted by: Victor G Hazlewood]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
