<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Research Initiation Grant: Writing to Learn Engineering: Identifying Effective Techniques for the Integration of Written Communication  Into Engineering Classes and Curricula</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>01/01/2014</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>150000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>150000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07050000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>EEC</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Engineering Education and Centers</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Elliot Douglas</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Proficiency in technical writing is a highly desirable attribute for engineering graduates, and improvement of communication skills among undergraduate engineering students can help enhance the competitiveness of U.S. technical talent in an increasingly global engineering market. This project responds to the need for improved communication skills in engineering by directly addressing challenges associated with incorporating writing-based instructional techniques in traditional technical classes. More specifically, the goals of this project are to develop, validate, and disseminate high-impact, scalable techniques for integrating writing in existing engineering courses and curricula. The project particularly seeks to address common instructor-level challenges that often preclude the inclusion of writing in engineering coursework. This project is primarily focused on required, large-lecture engineering courses where writing typically does not occur, and where ample opportunities exist to train faculty to implement simple, scalable writing activities, exercises, and related assessments. This study will involve systematic investigation of how such activities can potentially enhance student learning of both writing and course-specific technical skills. The project will also survey faculty and staff at multiple institutions to evaluate current attitudes toward writing in engineering, while identifying the most scalable and sustainable writing interventions from the standpoint of instructors and institutions. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The proposed project brings together an interdisciplinary team with highly complementary expertise spanning multiple disciplines and areas of activity, including engineering (civil and electrical/computer), technical communication, active and experiential learning, and engineering education research. The project proposes innovative application of writing interventions that have been proven effective in other contexts, with the goal of transforming core courses in engineering to enhance the technical capabilities and writing skills of participating students. Increased emphasis on writing in engineering education may also broaden participation and increase retention of underrepresented groups (particularly women and linguistic minorities), including by helping to contextualize and make more relevant the technical courses and topics that comprise much of current engineering curricula.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/16/2013</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/16/2013</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1340491</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Joshua</FirstName>
<LastName>Boyd</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Joshua Boyd</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>boyd@purdue.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>7654944600</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000342731</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/16/2013</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Brent</FirstName>
<LastName>Jesiek</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>K</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Brent K Jesiek</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>bjesiek@purdue.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>7654961531</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000332534</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/16/2013</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Cary</FirstName>
<LastName>Troy</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Cary Troy</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>troy@purdue.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>7654944600</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000306706</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/16/2013</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Purdue University</Name>
<CityName>West Lafayette</CityName>
<ZipCode>479072114</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>7654941055</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>Young Hall</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[155 S Grant Street]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Indiana</StateName>
<StateCode>IN</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>IN04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>072051394</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>PURDUE UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>072051394</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Purdue University]]></Name>
<CityName>West Lafayette</CityName>
<StateCode>IN</StateCode>
<ZipCode>479072051</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[550 Stadium Mall Drive]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Indiana</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>IN04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1340</Code>
<Text>EngEd-Engineering Education</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>110E</Code>
<Text>EDUCATION RESEARCH</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0113</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2013~150000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p style="text-align: left;"><strong>Background&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; </strong>This project examined the use of writing exercises in core engineering subjects in order to promote student learning.&nbsp; This technique, sometimes termed &ldquo;write to learn&rdquo;, leverages the cognitive process associated with writing in order to cause students to think more deeply about their calculations and equations.&nbsp; However, in spite of the benefits of using writing in university engineering classes to promote technical learning, substantial hurdles exist for instructors looking to implement writing in engineering classes, particularly in large classes.&nbsp;</p> <p style="text-align: left;"><strong>Purpose&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; </strong>To address these gaps, the project had three main goals: (1) Identification of faculty-level barriers that inhibit the inclusion of writing in engineering courses; (2) Development of transferrable techniques that employ writing in engineering and STEM courses; (3) Assessment of these techniques; (4) Development of dissemination materials to transfer these writing techniques.</p> <p style="text-align: left;"><strong>Approach and findings&nbsp;&nbsp; </strong>The project had several phases.&nbsp; The first phase of the project focused on the surveying of engineering instructors.&nbsp; Our project surveyed faculty at large universities and found that while most instructors appreciated the role writing can play in a technical education, time and resource limitations often limited their ability and willingness to use more writing exercises.&nbsp; The project also found that when writing was included, the anticipated outcomes weren't always clear; while most faculty said they used rubrics to grade writing, a much smaller number actually revealed to students what those rubrics were before applying them. &nbsp;Additionally, engineering instructors cited the time and expertise required for grading to be a difficult challenge to overcome when using writing exercises in their classes. &nbsp;</p> <p style="text-align: left;">A second phase of our project carried out and analyzed an extensive survey of engineering textbooks used in core engineering subjects at major engineering universities.&nbsp; The purpose of this survey was to determine instructor needs as well as to develop transferrable writing techniques for engineering instructors.&nbsp; From this survey we determined that textbooks in general did not leverage writing in the learning process, which was additionally suggestive of a lack of use of writing by instructors using these books (and a lack of resources to help instructors assess the writing-related questions that we did find).&nbsp;</p> <p style="text-align: left;">The final phase of the project focused on the development and dissemination of materials to transfer writing techniques across engineering disciplines. &nbsp;The findings from the instructor and textbook surveys were used to address some of the challenges associated with including writing exercises.&nbsp; The project team developed a writing prompt classification scheme that allows instructors to easily craft writing questions from standard textbook problems, again to support writing in the learning of technical material.&nbsp; This scheme includes linkages to Bloom&rsquo;s taxonomy, which allows instructors to target certain types and levels of learning objectives with their writing questions.&nbsp; Additionally, simple and adaptable grading rubrics were developed to aid instructors in the timely assessment of student writing.&nbsp; All of these techniques are being developed into an instructor-focused website that will be housed on the Purdue Online Writing Lab (OWL) website, a very popular website used by both students and instructors.</p> <p style="text-align: left;"><strong>Conclusions&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; </strong>Taken in sum, the developments and outcomes from this project serve to increase the amount and quality of writing used in the education of undergraduate engineers, which in turn is expected to produce more highly trained engineers for the workforce, as well as engineers and scientists more capable of communicating their ideas with a broader audience.&nbsp; As part of the project a multi-disciplinary team was formed that included experts from civil engineering, engineering education, and communication, as well as several graduate students who received training in scientific research methods.&nbsp; These graduate students, both female, have both obtained faculty positions at universities, thus increasing the number of female engineering faculty.</p> <p style="text-align: left;">&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 10/16/2017<br>      Modified by: Cary&nbsp;Troy</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[Background           This project examined the use of writing exercises in core engineering subjects in order to promote student learning.  This technique, sometimes termed "write to learn", leverages the cognitive process associated with writing in order to cause students to think more deeply about their calculations and equations.  However, in spite of the benefits of using writing in university engineering classes to promote technical learning, substantial hurdles exist for instructors looking to implement writing in engineering classes, particularly in large classes.  Purpose       To address these gaps, the project had three main goals: (1) Identification of faculty-level barriers that inhibit the inclusion of writing in engineering courses; (2) Development of transferrable techniques that employ writing in engineering and STEM courses; (3) Assessment of these techniques; (4) Development of dissemination materials to transfer these writing techniques. Approach and findings   The project had several phases.  The first phase of the project focused on the surveying of engineering instructors.  Our project surveyed faculty at large universities and found that while most instructors appreciated the role writing can play in a technical education, time and resource limitations often limited their ability and willingness to use more writing exercises.  The project also found that when writing was included, the anticipated outcomes weren't always clear; while most faculty said they used rubrics to grade writing, a much smaller number actually revealed to students what those rubrics were before applying them.  Additionally, engineering instructors cited the time and expertise required for grading to be a difficult challenge to overcome when using writing exercises in their classes.   A second phase of our project carried out and analyzed an extensive survey of engineering textbooks used in core engineering subjects at major engineering universities.  The purpose of this survey was to determine instructor needs as well as to develop transferrable writing techniques for engineering instructors.  From this survey we determined that textbooks in general did not leverage writing in the learning process, which was additionally suggestive of a lack of use of writing by instructors using these books (and a lack of resources to help instructors assess the writing-related questions that we did find).  The final phase of the project focused on the development and dissemination of materials to transfer writing techniques across engineering disciplines.  The findings from the instructor and textbook surveys were used to address some of the challenges associated with including writing exercises.  The project team developed a writing prompt classification scheme that allows instructors to easily craft writing questions from standard textbook problems, again to support writing in the learning of technical material.  This scheme includes linkages to Bloom?s taxonomy, which allows instructors to target certain types and levels of learning objectives with their writing questions.  Additionally, simple and adaptable grading rubrics were developed to aid instructors in the timely assessment of student writing.  All of these techniques are being developed into an instructor-focused website that will be housed on the Purdue Online Writing Lab (OWL) website, a very popular website used by both students and instructors. Conclusions           Taken in sum, the developments and outcomes from this project serve to increase the amount and quality of writing used in the education of undergraduate engineers, which in turn is expected to produce more highly trained engineers for the workforce, as well as engineers and scientists more capable of communicating their ideas with a broader audience.  As part of the project a multi-disciplinary team was formed that included experts from civil engineering, engineering education, and communication, as well as several graduate students who received training in scientific research methods.  These graduate students, both female, have both obtained faculty positions at universities, thus increasing the number of female engineering faculty.         Last Modified: 10/16/2017       Submitted by: Cary Troy]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
