<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>The seasonal cycle of export production in an Antarctic coastal marine ecosystem</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>04/01/2012</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2015</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>257280.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>257280</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>06090300</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>GEO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>OPP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Office of Polar Programs (OPP)</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Lisa Clough</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>lclough@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924746</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The research project will obtain a comprehensive data set on the seasonal cycles of new, export and net community production, and lead to a better understanding of the production and export of organic matter (C and N) in a coastal Antarctic marine ecosystem.  There have been relatively few measurements of these three processes in polar regions, and even fewer systematic time-series investigations conducted at the proper scales to uncover mechanisms. In consequence, the physical, ecological and biogeochemical mechanisms regulating new production, NCP and export production remain poorly-characterized.  We propose to conduct a detailed, season- long study of export production as determined from water column 238U:234Th disequilibrium. New production will be measured by 15NO3 uptake. Net community production will be estimated from measurements of the O2:Ar ratio in seawater. Sampling will be carried out weekly from October to April at a regularly-occupied and long-studied (since 1993) site 5 km from Palmer Station, in close conjunction with ongoing research by the Palmer, Antarctica Long Term Ecological Research project (PAL). Sediment traps will be deployed weekly at two depths to collect particles for determination of the ratios of C:N:234Th on sinking particles.  This study will be among the first to obtain detailed concurrent time series of new, export and net community production.  Current estimates of particle export in coastal Antarctica are limited to a few offshore sites and may underestimate the true export by an order of magnitude. In addition, seasonal and interannual variability are not quantitatively related to corresponding variations in primary production, sea ice cover nor zooplankton stocks. These shortcomings may result from sediment trap collection deficiencies and a spatiotemporal disconnect between sampling the plankton community and particle flux that blurs relationships. If these suppositions are correct, the project will provide a new, robust estimate of export production in the Antarctic marine environment, and a new explanation of how and why it varies during the Austral summer growing season. This project will support a postdoctoral fellow and take advantage of the well-developed infrastructure of the MBL and PAL-LTER Education and Outreach programs, to inform two of the most influential groups for public education, K12 teachers and science journalists, about the ocean carbon cycle and climate change in one of the world's most captivating and rapidly changing ecosystems.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>04/12/2013</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>04/12/2013</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.078</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1340886</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Hugh</FirstName>
<LastName>Ducklow</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>W</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Hugh W Ducklow</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>hducklow@ldeo.columbia.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>7578762590</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000336686</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/12/2013</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Columbia University</Name>
<CityName>NEW YORK</CityName>
<ZipCode>100276902</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2128546851</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>2960 Broadway</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>10</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NY10</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>049179401</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>TRUSTEES OF COLUMBIA UNIVERSITY IN THE CITY OF NEW YORK, THE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>049179401</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Lamont-Doherty Earth Observatory]]></Name>
<CityName>Palisades</CityName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<ZipCode>109648000</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[61 Route 9W]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>17</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NY17</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>5111</Code>
<Text>ANT Organisms &amp; Ecosystems</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<Appropriation>
<Code>02XX</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2011~257280</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Photosynthesis by phytoplankton (tiny plants floating in the surface ocean) is responsible for roughly half of the earth&rsquo;s biological carbon dioxide utilization, and hence is a major sink for fossil fuel-produced CO<sub>2</sub>.&nbsp; However, most of the CO<sub>2</sub> taken up by phytoplankton will be respired by bacteria or zooplankton grazers and hence re-released into the atmosphere.&nbsp; For this carbon to be removed from the atmosphere for time periods of longer than a season, it must be transported from the surface ocean into the deep ocean.&nbsp; One of the primary mechanisms for export of carbon into the ocean interior is sinking of biological particles including large phytoplankton, zooplankton fecal pellets, and aggregates.&nbsp; Despite the importance of this process in the global carbon cycle, we still lack a mechanistic understanding capable of predicting how carbon export rates will respond to a changing ocean.&nbsp;</p> <p>The Southern Ocean is believed to take up a significant fraction of atmospheric CO2, so it is especially critical to understand these processes around Antarctica.&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; One of the basic theories governing our understanding of carbon export is the balance between &ldquo;new production&rdquo; and export.&nbsp; In most regions, the surface ocean is limited by the availability of inorganic nitrogen.&nbsp; Thus the input of &ldquo;new&rdquo; nitrogen (primarily introduced when deep, nutrient rich waters are brought to the surface) to the upper ocean will stimulate phytoplankton productivity.&nbsp; Over long time periods and large spatial scales, the surface ocean retains a relatively constant nitrogen concentration.&nbsp; Thus, it is expected that the export of nitrogen to the deep ocean on biological particles must be balanced by the input of new nitrogen and its utilization by phytoplankton.&nbsp; Basically, you can envision the surface ocean as a cornfield.&nbsp; If corn is removed from the farm (export) but no fertilizer is added (new nitrogen) the farm will become depleted and nothing will grow.&nbsp; The addition of fertilizer is equivalent to the new production that happens when currents bring nutrients in deep water to the surface.</p> <p>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; While the simplicity of this theory is attractive, it is difficult to test because new production and export typically do not occur on the same scales.&nbsp; Often new production happens early in the phytoplankton growing season, leading to an increase in phytoplankton populations, which are exported at the end of the growing season.&nbsp; Furthermore, the constantly swirling ocean currents often transport communities long distances, leading to a spatial decoupling of new production and export.&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; In order to test the equivalence of new production and export, we conducted a program to measure new production and export at a site near Palmer Station Antarctica, during the full phytoplankton growth season (Antarctic summer).&nbsp; We used three independent methods to measure new production and net community production, which agreed well and suggested fairly high new production as would be expected for summer in the nutrient-rich Southern Ocean.&nbsp; We also used two independent methods to measure export and found that while these two methods agreed with each other, they showed much lower export than new production.&nbsp; Our results thus suggest that, contrary to prior expectations, new production is not balanced by the sinking of particles out of the surface ocean in the region near Palmer Station.&nbsp; In fact, the biological pump was substantially weaker than expected.</p> <p>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; Nevertheless, this new produ...]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Photosynthesis by phytoplankton (tiny plants floating in the surface ocean) is responsible for roughly half of the earthÆs biological carbon dioxide utilization, and hence is a major sink for fossil fuel-produced CO2.  However, most of the CO2 taken up by phytoplankton will be respired by bacteria or zooplankton grazers and hence re-released into the atmosphere.  For this carbon to be removed from the atmosphere for time periods of longer than a season, it must be transported from the surface ocean into the deep ocean.  One of the primary mechanisms for export of carbon into the ocean interior is sinking of biological particles including large phytoplankton, zooplankton fecal pellets, and aggregates.  Despite the importance of this process in the global carbon cycle, we still lack a mechanistic understanding capable of predicting how carbon export rates will respond to a changing ocean.   The Southern Ocean is believed to take up a significant fraction of atmospheric CO2, so it is especially critical to understand these processes around Antarctica.               One of the basic theories governing our understanding of carbon export is the balance between "new production" and export.  In most regions, the surface ocean is limited by the availability of inorganic nitrogen.  Thus the input of "new" nitrogen (primarily introduced when deep, nutrient rich waters are brought to the surface) to the upper ocean will stimulate phytoplankton productivity.  Over long time periods and large spatial scales, the surface ocean retains a relatively constant nitrogen concentration.  Thus, it is expected that the export of nitrogen to the deep ocean on biological particles must be balanced by the input of new nitrogen and its utilization by phytoplankton.  Basically, you can envision the surface ocean as a cornfield.  If corn is removed from the farm (export) but no fertilizer is added (new nitrogen) the farm will become depleted and nothing will grow.  The addition of fertilizer is equivalent to the new production that happens when currents bring nutrients in deep water to the surface.              While the simplicity of this theory is attractive, it is difficult to test because new production and export typically do not occur on the same scales.  Often new production happens early in the phytoplankton growing season, leading to an increase in phytoplankton populations, which are exported at the end of the growing season.  Furthermore, the constantly swirling ocean currents often transport communities long distances, leading to a spatial decoupling of new production and export.               In order to test the equivalence of new production and export, we conducted a program to measure new production and export at a site near Palmer Station Antarctica, during the full phytoplankton growth season (Antarctic summer).  We used three independent methods to measure new production and net community production, which agreed well and suggested fairly high new production as would be expected for summer in the nutrient-rich Southern Ocean.  We also used two independent methods to measure export and found that while these two methods agreed with each other, they showed much lower export than new production.  Our results thus suggest that, contrary to prior expectations, new production is not balanced by the sinking of particles out of the surface ocean in the region near Palmer Station.  In fact, the biological pump was substantially weaker than expected.              Nevertheless, this new production, must somehow leave the ecosystem (or biomass would continually accumulate).  By analyzing nitrate and thorium data, along with physical profiles of the water column, we determined that persistent physically-driven vertical mixing (which may be much higher in the Southern Ocean than in other regions due to the cold surface temperatures) of particles to depth may be responsible for much of the imbalance.  This has profound implications for the mechanisms ...]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
