<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Collaborative Research: RUI: The Pulse-Shunt Concept: A Conceptual Framework for Quantifying and Forecasting Watershed DOM Fluxes and Transformations at the MacroSystem Scale</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>06/01/2014</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>09/30/2020</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>278579.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>278579</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>08010000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>BIO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DEB</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Environmental Biology</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Elizabeth Blood</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>eblood@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924349</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The transfers of carbon, nutrients and pollutants from the land to streams and their changes as they move through river networks are issues that motivate environmental scientists and water resource managers.  Dissolved organic matter (DOM) is a central chemical in streams and rivers that affects the forms and movements of contaminants, light penetration through the water, metabolism of life in the streams, pH, and the efficiency of water treatments by municipalities.  This study aims to improve predictions of DOM formation and movement from small headwater streams and our understanding of the factors that change the amount and forms of DOM during as it moves downstream.  One goal of this research is to greatly improve a computer model of DOM transport and transformation as it moves through a watershed and into the headwater streams.  This model links rainfall and runoff that generate streamflow to the biological and chemical processes that lead to changes in the amount and forms of DOM.   The model will be tested against actual measurements of DOM made in several headwater streams of the Connecticut River along its length.  Measurements will then also be made in larger parts of the Connecticut River downriver that will help explain how DOM changes along the entire drainage network.  This project challenges a long standing picture of how streams and rivers work, called the River Continuum Concept, proposing that a newer view may be required, referred to as the Pulse-Shunt Concept.  &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project will involve graduate students and a post-doctoral associate in the laboratory, field, and modeling ends of the research.  It will also build on a partnership with the Connecticut Science Museum to construct educational activities and displays related to watershed ecology and management for the general public.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>04/07/2014</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>04/07/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.074</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1340707</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>William</FirstName>
<LastName>Sobczak</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>V</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>William V Sobczak</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>wsobczak@holycross.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5087933752</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000228294</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/07/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>College of the Holy Cross</Name>
<CityName>Worcester</CityName>
<ZipCode>016102395</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5087932741</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1 College Street</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
<StateCode>MA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MA02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>041509506</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>COLLEGE OF THE HOLY CROSS</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>041509506</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[College of the Holy Cross]]></Name>
<CityName>Worcester</CityName>
<StateCode>MA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>016102395</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[1 College Street]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MA02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7959</Code>
<Text>MacroSysBIO &amp; NEON-Enabled Sci</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7959</Code>
<Text>MACROSYSTEM BIOLOGY</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9229</Code>
<Text>RES IN UNDERGRAD INST-RESEARCH</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0114</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~278579</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Understanding global carbon (C) cycling requires advances in knowledge of how terrestrial and marine environments are linked by continental drainage basins. &nbsp;Recognition has grown that freshwater dissolved organic matter (DOM)-cycling processes may be as important as terrestrial and open-ocean processes, but great uncertainty remains about how increases in the intensity of event-driven discharge in headwater streams regulates the export (and composition and bioreactivity) of DOM to downstream freshwater and estuarine ecosystems. Furthermore, global climate change will influence the characteristics of regional hydrologic events and precipitation patterns throughout the planet, thus altering watershed biota, biogeochemistry, and hydrology in highly variable ways. Terrestrial DOM export and accompanying transformations in the continents? fluvial networks and freshwater ecosystems must be examined across spatial and temporal scales and viewed as an integral and highly dynamic component of the global C cycle.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>The ?Pulse-shunt Concept? (PSC) highlights the importance of large rivers for the processing of terrestrial DOM.&nbsp; Due to the increase in concentration and decrease in residence time with hydrological events, both the ?pulse? of fresh DOM and the ?shunt? downstream are accentuated compounding the importance of big rivers for the removal of terrestrial DOM at annual time scales. The PSC predicts that the annual frequency of large rainfall events is arguably equally important to overall annual rainfall magnitude when determining fluxes from drainage networks. &nbsp;Sampling and modeling approaches need to account for rainfall frequency, intensity, and timing when estimating and forecasting DOM export, particularly when targeting the response of export to global climate change.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>The PSC, like other conceptual models before it, underscores the need for integrating multiple environmental science disciplines and spatial scaling into watershed biogeochemistry research.&nbsp; Advances in remote sampling and remote sensing products will greatly accelerate and strengthen our ability to integrate landscape scaling into drainage network biogeochemistry.&nbsp; The PSC formalizes the need for a better understanding of decomposition rates, hydrologic residence times, and photolysis.&nbsp; These parameters are highly dynamic yet poorly resolved, thus highlighting critical frontier research areas in the hydrological and biogeochemical sciences.&nbsp; Overall, the PSC improves how we conceptualize and quantify the role of stream and river networks at annual and decadal time scales, thus providing a more accurate depiction of the important role of large watersheds in the global C-cycle.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 04/02/2021<br>      Modified by: William&nbsp;V&nbsp;Sobczak</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Understanding global carbon (C) cycling requires advances in knowledge of how terrestrial and marine environments are linked by continental drainage basins.  Recognition has grown that freshwater dissolved organic matter (DOM)-cycling processes may be as important as terrestrial and open-ocean processes, but great uncertainty remains about how increases in the intensity of event-driven discharge in headwater streams regulates the export (and composition and bioreactivity) of DOM to downstream freshwater and estuarine ecosystems. Furthermore, global climate change will influence the characteristics of regional hydrologic events and precipitation patterns throughout the planet, thus altering watershed biota, biogeochemistry, and hydrology in highly variable ways. Terrestrial DOM export and accompanying transformations in the continents? fluvial networks and freshwater ecosystems must be examined across spatial and temporal scales and viewed as an integral and highly dynamic component of the global C cycle.     The ?Pulse-shunt Concept? (PSC) highlights the importance of large rivers for the processing of terrestrial DOM.  Due to the increase in concentration and decrease in residence time with hydrological events, both the ?pulse? of fresh DOM and the ?shunt? downstream are accentuated compounding the importance of big rivers for the removal of terrestrial DOM at annual time scales. The PSC predicts that the annual frequency of large rainfall events is arguably equally important to overall annual rainfall magnitude when determining fluxes from drainage networks.  Sampling and modeling approaches need to account for rainfall frequency, intensity, and timing when estimating and forecasting DOM export, particularly when targeting the response of export to global climate change.     The PSC, like other conceptual models before it, underscores the need for integrating multiple environmental science disciplines and spatial scaling into watershed biogeochemistry research.  Advances in remote sampling and remote sensing products will greatly accelerate and strengthen our ability to integrate landscape scaling into drainage network biogeochemistry.  The PSC formalizes the need for a better understanding of decomposition rates, hydrologic residence times, and photolysis.  These parameters are highly dynamic yet poorly resolved, thus highlighting critical frontier research areas in the hydrological and biogeochemical sciences.  Overall, the PSC improves how we conceptualize and quantify the role of stream and river networks at annual and decadal time scales, thus providing a more accurate depiction of the important role of large watersheds in the global C-cycle.       Last Modified: 04/02/2021       Submitted by: William V Sobczak]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
