<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>CAREER: Spin-Torque Oscillator Arrays</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>12/23/2012</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2016</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>326316.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>326316</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07010000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>ECCS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Electrical, Commun &amp; Cyber Sys</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Usha Varshney</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>uvarshne@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032925385</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This research investigates magnetostatic spin-wave generation, propagation, interaction and absorption in multi-layer Giant magnetoresistance (GMR) and Tunnel magnetoresistance (TMR) spin-torque oscillator (STO) arrays.  With the recent demonstration of spin-torque transfer and self-sustained oscillators, a new class of oscillator has emerged with extreme tunability and potential for excellent RF performance.  Recent results have shown, however, that the potential of these new devices is limited by the large phase noise of individual devices due to the small amount of energy stored in a single device.  A potential solution is the phase-locking of many STOs in a large array. This research focuses on the fundamental science of STO-STO interaction in multi-device arrays with the goal of laying the foundation for controllable, scalable arrays of STO oscillators. Specifically, this research proposal focuses on three tasks investigating fundamental science of spin-wave STO interaction: 1) Study of magnetostatic surface wave dynamics on multi-layer STO stacks, 2) Study of magnetostatic surface wave stimulated emission by an STO, and  3) Spatial dependence and scaling of STO-STO interactions. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Intellectual merit: This research will develop fundamental knowledge about magnetostatic spin wave propagation in multi-layer GMR/TMR stacks such as dependence of wavenumber, decay, directionality on various parameters and also the best possible film configuration for transferring spin wave energy to adjacent STOs. In addition the proposed study on STO-wave interaction will develop new understanding about spin wave emission efficiency of a single STO, spin wave scattering/absorption/amplification by a single STO, frequency pulling effect of a STO under spin wave field as well as non-linear interaction of an excited particle (STO) with a continuous plane wave. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Broader impacts:  This research will develop STO arrays, with low phase noise oscillators and high tunability for spectrum-agile RF systems. Combined with these research programs is an integrated effort for the development of new interdisciplinary courses that focus on the fundamentals of device physics and their applications, the creation of virtual laboratories that enable students around the globe to explore these fundamental concepts, and the introduction of elementary and high school students in local communities to the exciting field of magnetics and electronics. Furthermore, an integrated research and educational program will provide direct access for students, in local communities and around the globe, to investigate fundamentals of nanoscale devices through web-deployed virtual laboratories and educational tutorials. The educational efforts will focus on developing experiential learning activities for students via virtual labs to enable students to learn concepts through experimentation and exploration, complimenting traditional lecture based educational methods.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>05/31/2013</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/31/2013</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1341990</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>David</FirstName>
<LastName>Ricketts</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>S</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>David S Ricketts</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>david.ricketts@ncsu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>9195137361</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000508959</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/31/2013</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>North Carolina State University</Name>
<CityName>Raleigh</CityName>
<ZipCode>276957514</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>9195152444</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>2601 Wolf Village Way</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[Admin. III, STE 240]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>North Carolina</StateName>
<StateCode>NC</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NC04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>042092122</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>NORTH CAROLINA STATE UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>142363428</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[North Carolina State University]]></Name>
<CityName>Raleigh</CityName>
<StateCode>NC</StateCode>
<ZipCode>276957103</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[2701 Sullivan Drive]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>North Carolina</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NC02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1504</Code>
<Text>GOALI-Grnt Opp Acad Lia wIndus</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1517</Code>
<Text>EPMD-ElectrnPhoton&amp;MagnDevices</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1045</Code>
<Text>CAREER-Faculty Erly Career Dev</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>107E</Code>
<Text>Magnetics and spin electronics</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1187</Code>
<Text>PECASE- eligible</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1504</Code>
<Text>GRANT OPP FOR ACAD LIA W/INDUS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0111</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2011~326315</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>In this research, we investigated the oscillation dynamics of spin-torque oscillators (STOs), a nanoscale magnetic-electronic device that has the potential to replace many larger (micron scale) electrical oscillators. Our work centered on understanding frequency and phase fluctuations and on output power, all of which are well below the comparable electronic oscillators.</p> <p>In our work we investigated the STO directly as well as spin-wave dynamics, a key potential method for interaction between STOs, and precision measurement techniques to better understand true STO performance.</p> <p>We developed a Green&rsquo;s function formalism for magnetostatic surface waves that enables an analytically modeling of the diffraction patterns made by spin waves in magnetic materials. This research was enabled using a custom spatially resolved ferromagnetic resonance scanning Kerr effect microscopy, which uses an optical effect to measure the amplitude and phase of spin waves. The outcomes of this work can be used to better understand, model and in the future design, spin-wave devices. Together with collaborators at the University of Texas, we investigated spin waves excited from co-planer waveguide antennas using micro-Brillouin light scattering measurement technique. This work showed that we could measure the spin-wave propagation length and the spin-wave vector, two important quantities for understanding spin-waves in magnetic materials.</p> <p>To understand the oscillation fluctuation and variations between STOs, we investigated point-contact-based STOs, using a custom apparatus that could vary the bias field azimuthally at a fixed altitude angle. This is significant, as point-contact STOs should be uniform in the azimuthal bias and produce symmetric results.&nbsp; Our results showed that both the power and frequency were significantly altered by the azimuthal variation, such that the two identical STOs with different azimuthal biases would oscillate very differently. This observation furthered the realization that variation in STOs may be more significant that at first thought and be highly dependent on fabrication and bias conditions, even if the device materials and electrical biasing are identical.</p> <p>Our work in spin-waves and STO fluctuations also led to the development of a new measurement techniques. One of the challenges with STO measurements is their low power. To ensure a high signal-to-noise ratio, measurements need sufficient time to average thermal excitations (noise) &ndash; requiring long measurement times. During these measurements the measurement device itself can change making it extremely difficult to accurately measure. We created an adaptive-drift cancellation measurement technique for STO measurement that enables high-precision frequency and noise measurements at very low powers.</p> <p>Finally, in our collaboration with the National Institute of Advanced Technology (AIST) Japan, we investigated the output power of STOs, particularly in the methods to maximize power from STOs. In our work, we developed a complete de-embedding methodology to remove parasitic and insertion loss of measurement structures to accurately measured STO power.&nbsp; In addition, our analysis revealed that substrate interaction with STOs can significantly increase loss. The insights of our work were used to design a new set of STOs that have some of the highest reported power to date.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 03/13/2017<br>      Modified by: David&nbsp;S&nbsp;Ricketts</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ In this research, we investigated the oscillation dynamics of spin-torque oscillators (STOs), a nanoscale magnetic-electronic device that has the potential to replace many larger (micron scale) electrical oscillators. Our work centered on understanding frequency and phase fluctuations and on output power, all of which are well below the comparable electronic oscillators.  In our work we investigated the STO directly as well as spin-wave dynamics, a key potential method for interaction between STOs, and precision measurement techniques to better understand true STO performance.  We developed a Green?s function formalism for magnetostatic surface waves that enables an analytically modeling of the diffraction patterns made by spin waves in magnetic materials. This research was enabled using a custom spatially resolved ferromagnetic resonance scanning Kerr effect microscopy, which uses an optical effect to measure the amplitude and phase of spin waves. The outcomes of this work can be used to better understand, model and in the future design, spin-wave devices. Together with collaborators at the University of Texas, we investigated spin waves excited from co-planer waveguide antennas using micro-Brillouin light scattering measurement technique. This work showed that we could measure the spin-wave propagation length and the spin-wave vector, two important quantities for understanding spin-waves in magnetic materials.  To understand the oscillation fluctuation and variations between STOs, we investigated point-contact-based STOs, using a custom apparatus that could vary the bias field azimuthally at a fixed altitude angle. This is significant, as point-contact STOs should be uniform in the azimuthal bias and produce symmetric results.  Our results showed that both the power and frequency were significantly altered by the azimuthal variation, such that the two identical STOs with different azimuthal biases would oscillate very differently. This observation furthered the realization that variation in STOs may be more significant that at first thought and be highly dependent on fabrication and bias conditions, even if the device materials and electrical biasing are identical.  Our work in spin-waves and STO fluctuations also led to the development of a new measurement techniques. One of the challenges with STO measurements is their low power. To ensure a high signal-to-noise ratio, measurements need sufficient time to average thermal excitations (noise) &ndash; requiring long measurement times. During these measurements the measurement device itself can change making it extremely difficult to accurately measure. We created an adaptive-drift cancellation measurement technique for STO measurement that enables high-precision frequency and noise measurements at very low powers.  Finally, in our collaboration with the National Institute of Advanced Technology (AIST) Japan, we investigated the output power of STOs, particularly in the methods to maximize power from STOs. In our work, we developed a complete de-embedding methodology to remove parasitic and insertion loss of measurement structures to accurately measured STO power.  In addition, our analysis revealed that substrate interaction with STOs can significantly increase loss. The insights of our work were used to design a new set of STOs that have some of the highest reported power to date.             Last Modified: 03/13/2017       Submitted by: David S Ricketts]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
