<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Noyce Northeast Regional Conferences in 2013 and 2014</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2013</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2016</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>715398.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>715398</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>11040100</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>EHR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DUE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Undergraduate Education</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Keith Sverdrup</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>ksverdru@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924671</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Drexel University, the State University of New York College at Cortland, and the University of Massachusetts Boston are organizing two annual conferences for Noyce Scholars, Fellows and faculty from Noyce programs located in the Northeast United States.  The conferences are designed to advance the content knowledge and pedagogical practices of STEM teachers with a focus on teaching in high-need schools.  Successful teaching in high need schools is dependent upon STEM teachers who have a wide repertoire of pedagogical practices for teaching conceptually difficult content. The conferences are enabling participants to learn about, discuss and practice the latest methods for teaching STEM content to students who face the challenges common in high-need schools. To this end, the conference aims to integrate the intellectual and conceptual aspects of STEM teaching with the practical application of STEM concepts in the classroom.  Noyce programs from the Northeast region are coming together to learn about and share the latest content from STEM fields and the best teaching practices. The conferences provide a platform for them to inspire one another, to address the national needs of supporting high quality, innovative and transformative mathematics and science teaching and to advance education in high need schools. Noyce scholars and teachers receive professional development that directly impacts their teaching. The conferences are providing opportunities for Noyce scholars and teachers to collaborate, share experiences, expertise, and skills with peers and colleagues and to continue to maintain the connections beyond the conference through on-going networking. The goal is to advocate for strong content knowledge and teaching practices in mathematics and science and include researchers, teacher educators, K-12 educators, school administrators, and policy makers who can support teachers and work to positively transform practices and policies to better support science and mathematics learning for students in high need schools.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/24/2013</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/06/2015</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.076</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1341207</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Sheila</FirstName>
<LastName>Vaidya</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>R</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Sheila R Vaidya</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>vaidyasr@drexel.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2158956690</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000193647</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/24/2013</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Lisa</FirstName>
<LastName>Gonsalves</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>M</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Lisa M Gonsalves</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>lisa.gonsalves@umb.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6172877642</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000103867</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/24/2013</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Gregory</FirstName>
<LastName>Phelan</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>D</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Gregory D Phelan</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>gregory.phelan@cortland.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6077532905</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000525005</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/24/2013</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>SUNY College at Cortland</Name>
<CityName>Cortland</CityName>
<ZipCode>130452000</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6077532511</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>Research Foundation for SUNY</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[PO Box 2000]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>22</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NY22</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>090190591</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>RESEARCH FOUNDATION FOR THE STATE UNIVERSITY OF NEW YORK, THE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>020657151</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[SUNY Cortland]]></Name>
<CityName>Cortalnd</CityName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<ZipCode>130452000</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[402 Miller, Graham Avenue]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>22</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NY22</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1795</Code>
<Text>Robert Noyce Scholarship Pgm</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1795</Code>
<Text>ROBERT NOYCE SCHOLARSHIP PGM</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9178</Code>
<Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>SMET</Code>
<Text>SCIENCE, MATH, ENG &amp; TECH EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>04XX</Code>
<Name>NSF Education &amp; Human Resource</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040106</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2013~715398</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p class="Default">The Noyce Northeast Regional Conferences in 2013 and 2014 grant was proposed to bring people from 76 different National Science Foundation funded Robert Noyce Teacher Scholarship Program together at a series of conferences.&nbsp; These conferences were designed to help identify challenges and best practices for preparing the next generation of STEM teachers.&nbsp; The participants included college students studying STEM, teachers and administrators from K-12 schools, and faculty and administrators from colleges and universities that had received the Robert Noyce grants. &nbsp;&nbsp;</p> <p class="Default">Conferences were held in the spring of 2014 in Philadelphia and the spring of 2015 in Boston. At each conference event there were a variety of events including large seminars, small workshops, and hands-on field trips to local museums and science centers. More than 500 participants attended the two conferences.</p> <p class="Default">Additionally, the personnel supported by this grant worked with an outside evaluation group to determine how effective the conferences were.&nbsp; A new tool was developed to measure both quantitative (numerical) and qualitative (conceptual/opinion based/descriptive) outcomes of the conferences.&nbsp; Key findings from this work include:</p> <p class="Default">79% of students and K-12 teachers attending believe they successfully applied teaching strategies learned at the conference into their career.</p> <p class="Default">92% of students and K-12 teachers attending and 85% of college faculty believe the conference improved their skills as a STEM professional.</p> <p class="Default">87% of students and K-12 teachers attending report the conference inspired them to pursue additional professional development.</p> <p class="Default">84% of students and K-12 teachers attending and 87% of college faculty felt part of the Noyce community.</p> <p class="Default">76% of attendees said the conference re-energized them about working in a high-need school.</p> <p class="Default">96% of attendees expressed satisfaction with the conference.</p> <p class="Default">More than 50% of attendees stayed in contact with other attendees after the conference.</p> <p class="Default">Additionally, attendees reported that the conference helped enhance their existing interactions with other teachers and students, re-energized them, helped them identify new things to try in their classrooms, and helped everyone identify future professional development opportunities.&nbsp; Finally, it helped Robert Noyce Scholarship Program administrators identify key challenges facing them and some strategies to address these challenges. &nbsp;These challenges included (a) recruitment of STEM teachers and students into STEM disciplines, (b) obtaining more diversity in STEM, (c) keeping teachers motivated while working in a high-needs schools, (d) preparing future teachers to be successful in a politically charged environment, and (e) identifying funding for STEM programs and students.&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 11/29/2016<br>      Modified by: Gregory&nbsp;D&nbsp;Phelan</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[The Noyce Northeast Regional Conferences in 2013 and 2014 grant was proposed to bring people from 76 different National Science Foundation funded Robert Noyce Teacher Scholarship Program together at a series of conferences.  These conferences were designed to help identify challenges and best practices for preparing the next generation of STEM teachers.  The participants included college students studying STEM, teachers and administrators from K-12 schools, and faculty and administrators from colleges and universities that had received the Robert Noyce grants.    Conferences were held in the spring of 2014 in Philadelphia and the spring of 2015 in Boston. At each conference event there were a variety of events including large seminars, small workshops, and hands-on field trips to local museums and science centers. More than 500 participants attended the two conferences. Additionally, the personnel supported by this grant worked with an outside evaluation group to determine how effective the conferences were.  A new tool was developed to measure both quantitative (numerical) and qualitative (conceptual/opinion based/descriptive) outcomes of the conferences.  Key findings from this work include: 79% of students and K-12 teachers attending believe they successfully applied teaching strategies learned at the conference into their career. 92% of students and K-12 teachers attending and 85% of college faculty believe the conference improved their skills as a STEM professional. 87% of students and K-12 teachers attending report the conference inspired them to pursue additional professional development. 84% of students and K-12 teachers attending and 87% of college faculty felt part of the Noyce community. 76% of attendees said the conference re-energized them about working in a high-need school. 96% of attendees expressed satisfaction with the conference. More than 50% of attendees stayed in contact with other attendees after the conference. Additionally, attendees reported that the conference helped enhance their existing interactions with other teachers and students, re-energized them, helped them identify new things to try in their classrooms, and helped everyone identify future professional development opportunities.  Finally, it helped Robert Noyce Scholarship Program administrators identify key challenges facing them and some strategies to address these challenges.  These challenges included (a) recruitment of STEM teachers and students into STEM disciplines, (b) obtaining more diversity in STEM, (c) keeping teachers motivated while working in a high-needs schools, (d) preparing future teachers to be successful in a politically charged environment, and (e) identifying funding for STEM programs and students.           Last Modified: 11/29/2016       Submitted by: Gregory D Phelan]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
