<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>NSF/FDA SIR:  Isolation of cancer stem cells and the determination of the role of microRNA in B cell differentiation by flow cytometric techniques</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2013</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2014</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>114534.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>114534</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07020000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CBET</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Chem, Bioeng, Env, &amp; Transp Sys</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Leon Esterowitz</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>lesterow@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927942</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Abstract&lt;br/&gt;#1343519&lt;br/&gt;Raveche, Elizabeth&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This proposal employs multiparameter analysis of individual cells using markers with specific fluorescence tags that upon laser excitation emit a signal that can be distinguished from all other signals and background. Through this multi-color analysis exquisitely small samples can be identified and ultimately sorted and employed in molecular and functional assays. . This proposed research will test the ability of this technology to define unique malignant precursor cells that will be important for future scientific breakthroughs. This proposal initially takes advantage of the engineering advancements that have allowed fluorescent dyes with unique excitation and emission profiles to result in the ability to differentially excite and collect these emissions. The analysis of individual cells (or particles) rather than the whole population allows for detection of multiple properties measured on the same cell. The detection is rapid (as fast as the cell in the fluid sheath passes through the laser beam). In addition to analysis of individual cells, some types of flow cytometers can physically sort cells based on signals associated with the parameters being detected. and scientific research.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/21/2013</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/21/2013</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1343519</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Elizabeth</FirstName>
<LastName>Raveche</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Elizabeth Raveche</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>raveches@umdnj.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>9739725240</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000614655</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/21/2013</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Rutgers, The State University of New Jersey-RBHS-New Jersey Med</Name>
<CityName>Newark</CityName>
<ZipCode>071032403</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>9739720281</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>New Jersey Medical School, MSB C</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[65 Bergen Street, Suite 538]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New Jersey</StateName>
<StateCode>NJ</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>10</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NJ10</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>078795851</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>RUTGERS, THE STATE UNIVERSITY OF NEW JERSEY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>001912864</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[FDA White Oak]]></Name>
<CityName>Silver Spring</CityName>
<StateCode>MD</StateCode>
<ZipCode>209031058</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[10903 New Hampshire AVe]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Maryland</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>08</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MD08</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7236</Code>
<Text>BioP-Biophotonics</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>004E</Code>
<Text>BIOMEDICAL ENG AND DIAGNOSTICS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0113</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2013~114534</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The major outcome was to develop a systems immunology approach to disease development.&nbsp; The objective was to develop advanced flow-cytometry-based methods to identify and isolate the earliest cancer progenitor cell.&nbsp; The human disease modeled was chronic lymphocytic leukemia (CLL).&nbsp;&nbsp;A&nbsp;scientific outcome was the development and employment of congenic mice, which had a mutation in the loci containing the microRNAs miR-15a/16. Abnormalities in this microRNA had profound effects on the level and type of messenger RNA that a cell employs.&nbsp; Another major outcome was the production of induced pluripotent stem cells (iPS cells) and embryonic stem cells.&nbsp; These tools were invaluable for the dissection of the role of microRNA miR15a/16 in stem cell commitment to malignancy.&nbsp; Flow cytometrically sorted subpopulations of cells, sorted on the basis of differential expression of surface markers, were tested for their ability to give rise to the B1 lineage.&nbsp; Because the sources of cells came from mice with either the normal wild-type levels of miR-15a/16 or the decreased levels of miR15a/16 (due to the presence of the NZB mutation/deletion), the contribution and the role of miR-15a in the origin of CLL could be determined.&nbsp; NZB and DBA/2 congenic mice with replaced <em>mir-15a/16&nbsp; </em>loci (referred to as DBA-/-) were employed to study the capacity of early progenitors to recapitulate the disease both <em>in vitro </em>and <em>in vivo</em> using the bone marrow stromal OP9 system and immunodeficient mice.&nbsp; B1 progenitors from both NZB and DBA-/- mice had increased c-myb and Pax5 and decreased PU.1 (genes critical for B lymphocyte development).&nbsp; They are capable of repopulating irradiated recipients and produce significantly higher numbers of B1 cells than sources with normal miR-15a/16 levels.&nbsp;Furthermore, induced pluripotent stem (iPS) cells derived for the first time from the NZB provided insights into the B cell differentiation roadblock inherent in the NZB strain.&nbsp; In addition, exogenously delivered miR-15a/16-1 into the NZB derived B cell line led to downregulation of c-myb and Pax5, as well as upregulation of PU.1 gene expression, which is known to be critical for B2 cell development.&nbsp; This data support the hypothesis that microRNA miR-15a/16 deficient B progenitors experience a maturation blockage resulting from the increased expression of c-Myb and that B1 progenitors could be the cells of origin for CLL.</p> <p>The Investigators&nbsp;were involved in identification of the precursor state of CLL, monoclonal B lymphocytosis (MBL).&nbsp; Only a subpopulation of individuals with MLB develops CLL.&nbsp; There is potential for early intervention and, since this is a blood disease with malignant cells in the bone marrow as well, the early identification of a disease state might eliminate the potential to transfer disease via blood or marrow transfers.&nbsp; This proposal employed multiparameter analysis of individual cells using markers with specific flourescence tags that upon laser excitation emit a signal that can be distinguished from all other signals and background.&nbsp; Through this multi-color analysis exquisitely small smaples can be identified and ultimately sorted and employed in molecular and functional assays.&nbsp; The flow cytometer is the "go-to" technology employed in pharma, clinical labs, research and university settings.</p> <p>This work involved meaningful collaborations between the Raveche lab and the FDA.&nbsp; The major scientific interaction occurred with Dr. Heba Degheidy at OSEL/CDRH now at CBER.&nbsp;&nbsp; Raveche lab personnel, Chingiz Underbayev and Siddah Kasar, spent rotating time at the FDA and performed detailed sorting experiments at the CDRH and CBR flow cytomertry facility.&nbsp; The interaction lead to fruitful collaborative studies, and both students successfully received doctoral degrees and post-doctoral positions at prestigious institutions (NIH and Harvard) where they will continue the work initiated with the NSF grant.&nbsp; Several manuscripts and a book chapter resulted from these studies and two more manuscripts are ready for submission.&nbsp; Abstracts were presented at national meetings and the PI of this NSF grant, Raveche, gave a plenary international talk at the 36th Annual Meeting of the United Kingdom Environmental Mutagenesis Society (UKEMS) in which aspects of research funded by the NSF grant were presented.</p> <p>We&nbsp;were fully engaged in FDA activities, both offering our expertise and learning from FDA experts. Our lab attended Workshops on Minimal Residual Disease in CLL and a Workshop on Clinical Flow Cytometry in Hematologic Malignancies both of which took place at the FDA.&nbsp; This highlighted the role of cutting edge technology in the development of assays, which are both employed as diagnostics and&nbsp;monitoring devices for the detection of efficacy or adverse effects of investigational new drugs being submitted to the FDA for approval.&nbsp; Raveche participated in a technical review panel of the FDA.&nbsp; Based on Raveche's scientific expertise in microRNAs, she presented a talk:&nbsp; "MicroRNAs: prognostic, diagnostic and therapeutic implications" at OSEL/CDRH/FDA.&nbsp; The Raveche lab continued outreach programs to encourage students at high schools serving under-represented minorities to enter careers in science and engineering.&nbsp; Overall this project had scocial, technological and scientific impact.</p> <p><em><br /></em></p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 12/12/2016<br>      Modified by: Elizabeth&nbsp;Raveche</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The major outcome was to develop a systems immunology approach to disease development.  The objective was to develop advanced flow-cytometry-based methods to identify and isolate the earliest cancer progenitor cell.  The human disease modeled was chronic lymphocytic leukemia (CLL).  A scientific outcome was the development and employment of congenic mice, which had a mutation in the loci containing the microRNAs miR-15a/16. Abnormalities in this microRNA had profound effects on the level and type of messenger RNA that a cell employs.  Another major outcome was the production of induced pluripotent stem cells (iPS cells) and embryonic stem cells.  These tools were invaluable for the dissection of the role of microRNA miR15a/16 in stem cell commitment to malignancy.  Flow cytometrically sorted subpopulations of cells, sorted on the basis of differential expression of surface markers, were tested for their ability to give rise to the B1 lineage.  Because the sources of cells came from mice with either the normal wild-type levels of miR-15a/16 or the decreased levels of miR15a/16 (due to the presence of the NZB mutation/deletion), the contribution and the role of miR-15a in the origin of CLL could be determined.  NZB and DBA/2 congenic mice with replaced mir-15a/16  loci (referred to as DBA-/-) were employed to study the capacity of early progenitors to recapitulate the disease both in vitro and in vivo using the bone marrow stromal OP9 system and immunodeficient mice.  B1 progenitors from both NZB and DBA-/- mice had increased c-myb and Pax5 and decreased PU.1 (genes critical for B lymphocyte development).  They are capable of repopulating irradiated recipients and produce significantly higher numbers of B1 cells than sources with normal miR-15a/16 levels. Furthermore, induced pluripotent stem (iPS) cells derived for the first time from the NZB provided insights into the B cell differentiation roadblock inherent in the NZB strain.  In addition, exogenously delivered miR-15a/16-1 into the NZB derived B cell line led to downregulation of c-myb and Pax5, as well as upregulation of PU.1 gene expression, which is known to be critical for B2 cell development.  This data support the hypothesis that microRNA miR-15a/16 deficient B progenitors experience a maturation blockage resulting from the increased expression of c-Myb and that B1 progenitors could be the cells of origin for CLL.  The Investigators were involved in identification of the precursor state of CLL, monoclonal B lymphocytosis (MBL).  Only a subpopulation of individuals with MLB develops CLL.  There is potential for early intervention and, since this is a blood disease with malignant cells in the bone marrow as well, the early identification of a disease state might eliminate the potential to transfer disease via blood or marrow transfers.  This proposal employed multiparameter analysis of individual cells using markers with specific flourescence tags that upon laser excitation emit a signal that can be distinguished from all other signals and background.  Through this multi-color analysis exquisitely small smaples can be identified and ultimately sorted and employed in molecular and functional assays.  The flow cytometer is the "go-to" technology employed in pharma, clinical labs, research and university settings.  This work involved meaningful collaborations between the Raveche lab and the FDA.  The major scientific interaction occurred with Dr. Heba Degheidy at OSEL/CDRH now at CBER.   Raveche lab personnel, Chingiz Underbayev and Siddah Kasar, spent rotating time at the FDA and performed detailed sorting experiments at the CDRH and CBR flow cytomertry facility.  The interaction lead to fruitful collaborative studies, and both students successfully received doctoral degrees and post-doctoral positions at prestigious institutions (NIH and Harvard) where they will continue the work initiated with the NSF grant.  Several manuscripts and a book chapter resulted from these studies and two more manuscripts are ready for submission.  Abstracts were presented at national meetings and the PI of this NSF grant, Raveche, gave a plenary international talk at the 36th Annual Meeting of the United Kingdom Environmental Mutagenesis Society (UKEMS) in which aspects of research funded by the NSF grant were presented.  We were fully engaged in FDA activities, both offering our expertise and learning from FDA experts. Our lab attended Workshops on Minimal Residual Disease in CLL and a Workshop on Clinical Flow Cytometry in Hematologic Malignancies both of which took place at the FDA.  This highlighted the role of cutting edge technology in the development of assays, which are both employed as diagnostics and monitoring devices for the detection of efficacy or adverse effects of investigational new drugs being submitted to the FDA for approval.  Raveche participated in a technical review panel of the FDA.  Based on Raveche's scientific expertise in microRNAs, she presented a talk:  "MicroRNAs: prognostic, diagnostic and therapeutic implications" at OSEL/CDRH/FDA.  The Raveche lab continued outreach programs to encourage students at high schools serving under-represented minorities to enter careers in science and engineering.  Overall this project had scocial, technological and scientific impact.             Last Modified: 12/12/2016       Submitted by: Elizabeth Raveche]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
