<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Early Career: Upgrade of an X-ray Diffractometer with Capillary &amp; Humidity-Temperature Stages for Suspension &amp; Hydrated Powder Measurements, and Outreach for Geochemistry R</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/15/2014</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2016</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>133640.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>133640</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>06030202</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>GEO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>EAR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Earth Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>David Lambert</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>dlambert@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924736</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Clay minerals play an important role in biological, chemical and physical processes in soils and influence the physical and biological availability of contaminants, macromolecules, and organic matter. This award funds equipment that will enable the researchers to examine the interactions of organic molecules with certain clay minerals. The research enabled by this equipment has important relevance to the formation of porous soil aggregates, the dynamics of water movement through soils, sequestration and biogeochemical cycling of soil organic matter, and the fate and transport of contaminants in soils. Thus, it is expected that the research findings will be of interest to scientists across various disciplines. The principal investigator is also developing new curricula to engage undergraduates in using nanoscale techniques in aqueous geochemistry research and is active in recruiting undergraduates from underrepresented groups as active participants in her research team. This award will provide funding for additional undergraduate researchers to gain hands-on experience in state-of-the-art techniques provided by the instrumentation to be purchased.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Specifically, this award funds the purchase of two accessories to upgrade an X-ray diffraction system with the capabilities to conduct liquid-state suspension and temperature- and humidity-dependent&lt;br/&gt;X-ray diffraction measurements. Additional support will be provided for outreach activities to engage underrepresented undergraduates in this research. The response of the structural dynamics within clay minerals to interactions with organic guest molecules can be probed by monitoring changes in the clay structures via X-ray diffraction techniques. Traditional powder X-ray diffraction measurements provide no information about the organic-clay mineral interaction in suspension or as a function of moisture content and temperature. The accessory stages to be purchased will enable the researchers to conduct such experiments to obtain such information. Using a combination of computational techniques and these experimental X-ray diffraction and other spectroscopic techniques, the researchers will investigate the structural dynamics responsible for the binding interactions and mechanisms of sequestration of organic contaminants and natural organic molecules within hydrated smectite-type clay particles at different temperatures. These structural insights will contribute to elucidating the influence of clay minerals on the storage and stability of organic carbon in soils, which have important implications for understanding how the global carbon cycle will respond to projected climate change.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/11/2014</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/11/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.050</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1343063</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Ludmilla</FirstName>
<LastName>Aristilde</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Ludmilla Aristilde</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>ludmilla.aristilde@northwestern.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>8474913257</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000635646</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/11/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Cornell University</Name>
<CityName>Ithaca</CityName>
<ZipCode>148502820</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6072555014</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>373 Pine Tree Road</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>23</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NY23</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>872612445</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>CORNELL UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>002254837</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Cornell University]]></Name>
<CityName>Ithaca</CityName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<ZipCode>148502820</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>23</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NY23</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1580</Code>
<Text>Instrumentation &amp; Facilities</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0114</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~133640</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>We have achieved both the&nbsp;technical and outreach objectives of this project. The primary tehcnical objective&nbsp;was to equip our X-ry diffractometer with two stages to enable moisture-dependent and suspension X-ray diffraction measuremnts. The primary outreach objective was to train and engage undergraduate students in aqueous geochemistry research pertaining to the environmental chemistry and engineering of organo-mineral composites with relvance to the fate of both natural and cotnaminants organics. A total of three undergraduate researchers (including one female and two of underrepresente minority groups) participated in the research activities in this project.&nbsp;The&nbsp;research findings obtained by these&nbsp;undergraduate researchers have shed light on the role of water-bridges and cation bridges in stabilizing contmainant-mineral interactions and in water diffusion influenced by organics in clay mineral nanopores. A major outcome of these findings is three publicaitons, which invovled a total of five co-authorships from undergraduate researchers.The following results were highlighted in the published findings: (1) the conformaitonal arrangment of contamiants structures works in concert with the existence of specific functional groups to facilitate binding at mineral interfaces; (2) glucose-occupied mineral naopores have&nbsp;decreased water and solute diffusion coefficiences; and (3) distinct biologically-derived structures with relevance to mineral dissolution persist in the low-molecular-weight fractions of dissolved organic matter.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 06/21/2017<br>      Modified by: Ludmilla&nbsp;Aristilde</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Image         </div> <div class="galControls onePhoto" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation onePhoto" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1343063/1343063_10317932_1498101987800_Figure7--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1343063/1343063_10317932_1498101987800_Figure7--rgov-800width.jpg" title="X-ray diffraction patterns of montmorillonite layers in the absence and presence of glucose"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1343063/1343063_10317932_1498101987800_Figure7--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="X-ray diffraction patterns of montmorillonite layers in the absence and presence of glucose"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Measurements were made following reactions with glucose solutions at different concentrations: 0 mM (A), 0.5 mM (B), 2 mM (C), and 20 mM (D). The oriented clay layers were equilibrated at different relative humidity (RH): 90% (black symbols), 50% (light blue symbols), and 20% (white symbols).</div> <div class="imageCredit">Sbarina Kelch and Ludmilla Aristilde</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Ludmilla&nbsp;Aristilde</div> <div class="imageTitle">X-ray diffraction patterns of montmorillonite layers in the absence and presence of glucose</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ We have achieved both the technical and outreach objectives of this project. The primary tehcnical objective was to equip our X-ry diffractometer with two stages to enable moisture-dependent and suspension X-ray diffraction measuremnts. The primary outreach objective was to train and engage undergraduate students in aqueous geochemistry research pertaining to the environmental chemistry and engineering of organo-mineral composites with relvance to the fate of both natural and cotnaminants organics. A total of three undergraduate researchers (including one female and two of underrepresente minority groups) participated in the research activities in this project. The research findings obtained by these undergraduate researchers have shed light on the role of water-bridges and cation bridges in stabilizing contmainant-mineral interactions and in water diffusion influenced by organics in clay mineral nanopores. A major outcome of these findings is three publicaitons, which invovled a total of five co-authorships from undergraduate researchers.The following results were highlighted in the published findings: (1) the conformaitonal arrangment of contamiants structures works in concert with the existence of specific functional groups to facilitate binding at mineral interfaces; (2) glucose-occupied mineral naopores have decreased water and solute diffusion coefficiences; and (3) distinct biologically-derived structures with relevance to mineral dissolution persist in the low-molecular-weight fractions of dissolved organic matter.       Last Modified: 06/21/2017       Submitted by: Ludmilla Aristilde]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
