<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>EAGER: An Innovative High Specific Energy Li-air battery</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2013</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2015</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>102178.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>102178</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07020000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CBET</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Chem, Bioeng, Env, &amp; Transp Sys</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Jose Lage</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>CBET-134187&lt;br/&gt;PI: Faghri&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Li-air batteries are promising alternatives to current Li-ion batteries due to the high specific energy of lithium metal (12 kWh kg-1) and the infinite oxygen for the cathode available from the ambient. However, even if the specific energy achieved in practice is much lower than the theoretical value (less than 10% of its theoretical value), the specific energy of Li-air batteries achieved in laboratory studies is at least 2-5 times higher than that of Li-ion batteries. Thus, developing the science and the technology to achieve values closer to the maximum achievable is an important objective. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The low values achieved for the specific energy of a Li-air battery is partly related to the low mass transfer coefficient of the porous cathode electrode. In the proposed effort, an innovative and active Li-air battery is proposed that has a much higher specific energy and power. The innovation lies in the development of an inter-digitated micro channel system adjacent to the cathode through which electrolyte and oxygen mixture is circulated. The hypothesis is that the specific energy and power of Li-air batteries is enhanced because the convection of electrolyte in the porous electrode can increase the mass flux of oxygen and lithium ion in the electrode. &lt;br/&gt;In addition, an improved thermal management system with the circulation of electrolyte, within and outside the battery electrode is proposed enabling the battery system to operate under extreme environmental conditions &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The newly proposed battery is expected to have a specific energy as high as 600 Wh kg-1, and a specific power as high as 25 W kg-1. &lt;br/&gt;Thus, the project will lead to Li-air batteries with enhanced specific energy and power. The application domains include automotive, energy-storage, aerospace and others.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/29/2013</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/29/2013</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1343187</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Amir</FirstName>
<LastName>Faghri</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Amir Faghri</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>faghri@engr.uconn.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>8604860419</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000454187</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/29/2013</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Connecticut</Name>
<CityName>Storrs</CityName>
<ZipCode>062691133</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>8604863622</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>438 Whitney Road Ext.</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[Unit 1133]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Connecticut</StateName>
<StateCode>CT</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CT02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>614209054</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF CONNECTICUT</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>004534830</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Connecticut]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>CT</StateCode>
<ZipCode>062691133</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Connecticut</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CT02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1406</Code>
<Text>TTP-Thermal Transport Process</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>064E</Code>
<Text>Convection heat and mass transfer</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>150E</Code>
<Text>Conduction/Diffusion</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7237</Code>
<Text>NANO NON-SOLIC SCI &amp; ENG AWD</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7916</Code>
<Text>EAGER</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0113</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2013~102178</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>&nbsp;</p> <p>Insoluble lithium peroxide, generated during the discharging of organic electrolyte lithium air batteries, blocks the porous electrode and limits the energy density. In this study, an active cathode structure is proposed to enhance the discharge capacity of the lithium air battery using an organic electrolyte. The electrolyte is forced to recirculate through the cathode and then is saturated with oxygen in a tank outside of the battery. The forced convection enhances oxygen transport and electrode utilization. A two dimensional, transient, and non-isothermal simulation model is developed to simulate the heat and mass transfer within the battery.</p> <p>Results show that this novel active cathode design improves the battery capacity at all discharge current densities.&nbsp;The capacity of the Li-air battery is increased by 11.7 times (from 11.6&nbsp;mAh g&minus;1&nbsp;to 147.8&nbsp;mAh g&minus;1) at the discharge current of 2.0&nbsp;mA cm&minus;2&nbsp;when the conventional passive electrode is replaced by the newly designed active electrode. Furthermore, a cathode electrode with non-uniform porosity is suggested and simulation results show that it can reach a higher discharge capacity without decreasing its power density.</p> <p>Based on the analysis, two methods, dual layer cathode and alternating electrolyte flow, are proposed to enhance battery capacity. The dual layer cathode has 105% higher capacity than a single layer cathode at the current density of 1.5 mA cm-2. Alternating electrolyte flow can increase the cathode capacity by 3.7% at the current density of 0.2 mA cm-2.&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 11/16/2015<br>      Modified by: Amir&nbsp;Faghri</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[    Insoluble lithium peroxide, generated during the discharging of organic electrolyte lithium air batteries, blocks the porous electrode and limits the energy density. In this study, an active cathode structure is proposed to enhance the discharge capacity of the lithium air battery using an organic electrolyte. The electrolyte is forced to recirculate through the cathode and then is saturated with oxygen in a tank outside of the battery. The forced convection enhances oxygen transport and electrode utilization. A two dimensional, transient, and non-isothermal simulation model is developed to simulate the heat and mass transfer within the battery.  Results show that this novel active cathode design improves the battery capacity at all discharge current densities. The capacity of the Li-air battery is increased by 11.7 times (from 11.6 mAh g&minus;1 to 147.8 mAh g&minus;1) at the discharge current of 2.0 mA cm&minus;2 when the conventional passive electrode is replaced by the newly designed active electrode. Furthermore, a cathode electrode with non-uniform porosity is suggested and simulation results show that it can reach a higher discharge capacity without decreasing its power density.  Based on the analysis, two methods, dual layer cathode and alternating electrolyte flow, are proposed to enhance battery capacity. The dual layer cathode has 105% higher capacity than a single layer cathode at the current density of 1.5 mA cm-2. Alternating electrolyte flow can increase the cathode capacity by 3.7% at the current density of 0.2 mA cm-2.              Last Modified: 11/16/2015       Submitted by: Amir Faghri]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
