<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>INSPIRE Track 1: Understanding the Engineering Education--Workforce Continuum</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>10/01/2013</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>799591.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>954562</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>11040200</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>EHR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DUE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Undergraduate Education</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Myles Boylan</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>mboylan@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032928670</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This INSPIRE award is partially funded by Transforming Undergraduate Education in STEM Program in the Division of Undergraduate Education in the Directorate for Education and Human Resources and by the Division of Engineering Education and Centers in the Directorate for Engineering.  The project is using a rigorous process of data gathering and analysis, overseen by a committee of national experts, to explore a set of questions about the career choices of those who are trained as engineers or are employed as engineers (without earning a degree in engineering) in the United States. The National Academy of Engineering, part of the National Academies, has a long track record of providing independent and trustworthy advice on matters of national interest. As globalization and economic readjustments continue to affect the ability of the United States to remain technologically competitive, the roles of engineering education and of engineers will become even more critical than they are today. A fresh look at this vital segment of the nation's innovation capability is useful for a variety of policy-making purposes.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>09/16/2013</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/27/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.076</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1344190</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Proctor</FirstName>
<LastName>Reid</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>P</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Proctor P Reid</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>preid@nae.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2023342467</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000089232</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/16/2013</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Elizabeth</FirstName>
<LastName>Cady</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>T</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Elizabeth T Cady</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>ecady@nae.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2023342064</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000247531</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/16/2013</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>National Academy of Sciences</Name>
<CityName>Washington</CityName>
<ZipCode>200012721</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2023342254</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>500 FIFTH STREET NW</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>District of Columbia</StateName>
<StateCode>DC</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>00</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>DC00</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>041964057</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>NATIONAL ACADEMY OF SCIENCES</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>041964057</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[National Academy of Sciences]]></Name>
<CityName>WASHINGTON</CityName>
<StateCode>DC</StateCode>
<ZipCode>200012721</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[500 FIFTH STREET, NW]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>District of Columbia</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>00</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>DC00</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1340</Code>
<Text>EngEd-Engineering Education</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1385</Code>
<Text>SSA-Special Studies &amp; Analysis</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1998</Code>
<Text>IUSE</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>8078</Code>
<Text>INSPIRE</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1340</Code>
<Text>ENGINEERING EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1385</Code>
<Text>SPECIAL STUDIES AND ANALYSES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1666</Code>
<Text>RESEARCH ON LEARNING &amp; EDUCATI</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8209</Code>
<Text>Improv Undergrad STEM Ed(IUSE)</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8653</Code>
<Text>INSPIRE Track-1 Creative</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9178</Code>
<Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>SMET</Code>
<Text>SCIENCE, MATH, ENG &amp; TECH EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0113</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0114</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0116</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0413</Code>
<Name>NSF Education &amp; Human Resource</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040106</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0416</Code>
<Name>NSF Education &amp; Human Resource</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040106</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2013~759904</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~39687</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2016~154971</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>By assessing the expectations, training, employment options, and employment choices of those trained or employed as engineers in the United States, this project aimed to broaden the thinking of engineering students, educators, employers, and policy makers about the connections between engineering education and the workforce. The resulting consensus report will identify opportunities, challenges, and potential actions for all stakeholders to strengthen the nation&rsquo;s engineering workforce and the education enterprise that supports it.</p> <p>A committee of experts at the National Academy of Engineering gathered and analyzed data in order to explore a set of questions about the career choices of engineering graduates and those employed as engineers with non-engineering degrees in the United States. The project addressed three objectives and related questions:</p> <p><span style="text-decoration: underline;">Objective 1</span>: Collect and synthesize data from existing sources that shed light on the characteristics of those working as engineers in the US, including age, gender, educational background, occupational sector, job category (e.g., management, nonmanagement), compensation, and job-related competencies. Questions included:</p> <p>1)&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; &nbsp;What kinds of occupations/jobs do engineering graduates have in engineering and non-engineering fields; what do we know about the competencies they bring to the workplace and the tasks they perform; and how has the type of work performed by engineers in and outside of engineering occupations changed over time ?</p> <p>2)&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; &nbsp;How do compensation levels differ among engineering graduates working as engineers, engineering graduates working in non-STEM fields, and those without engineering degrees working as engineers? To what extent are these compensation levels influencing the career paths of recent graduates?</p> <p><span style="text-decoration: underline;">Objective 2</span>: Collect and synthesize existing data that shed light on factors that influence the career decisions of those working as engineers and those trained as engineers who are not working in engineering, including individual characteristics, personal values and beliefs, motivation, self-efficacy, educational experience, economic incentives, job satisfaction, and job mobility.</p> <p>1)&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; &nbsp;What factor or factors most explain BS engineering graduates&rsquo; choice of occupation (engineering, engineering-related, or non-engineering related), and how do these factors and their influence change over time?&nbsp;&nbsp;</p> <p>2)&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; &nbsp;Are those with engineering degrees choosing willingly or being diverted unwillingly to STEM-related and non-STEM related work?</p> <p>3)&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; &nbsp;How if at all does the specific engineering discipline influence or align with occupational choice and career development?&nbsp;</p> <p>4)&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; Do these factors differ across groups that are traditionally underrepresented in engineering (e.g., women, underrepresented minorities)?</p> <p><span style="text-decoration: underline;">Objective 3</span>: Based on the data reviewed and/or collected, consider the implications of current career pathways to and through engineering for: undergraduate engineering students, post-secondary engineering programs, continuing engineering education initiatives, employers of engineering talent (e.g., on-the-job training), and US national interests.</p> <p>1)&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; &nbsp;How should what we are learning about career pathways in engineering affect the curriculum in engineering programs, engineering pedagogy, and the criteria schools use to matriculate students into these programs?</p> <p>2)&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; &nbsp;How should continuing and on-the-job engineering education efforts leverage information about career pathways to better align the competencies of engineers with the needs of employers?</p> <p>3)&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; &nbsp;How well aligned are the skills and knowledge acquired in formal engineering education with the skills and knowledge needed on the job?<strong></strong></p> <p>4)&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; How should the engineering enterprise increase representation of women, underrepresented minorities, and other marginalized groups? <strong></strong></p> <p>The project&rsquo;s study committee brought expertise and perspectives from several disciplines, including engineering occupations, engineering education, engineering education research, social sciences, labor economics, and statistics. This breadth of knowledge and viewpoints provides a different, more complex, and potentially more useful view of the engineering education-workforce continuum. By assessing the expectations, training, employment options, and employment choices of those educated or employed as engineers in the United States, this project aims to broaden the thinking of engineering educators and policy makers about the connection between engineering education and the workforce and presents opportunities and also raises challenges for the engineering education community and policy makers. <strong></strong></p> <p>The final report is expected to reshape thinking regarding the &ldquo;value proposition&rdquo; for engineering, with resulting impacts within engineering education and the STEM, R&amp;D, and industrial policy communities. By critically evaluating the range of data sources relevant to engineering career pathways, the project challenges some long-held assumptions about not only what engineers do but also what education and training is needed to do engineering. This can provide a fruitful opening for more productive discussions within engineering education and among engineering education leaders, policy makers, and industry about the training and employment of engineering talent in the United States. Over the longer term, the project will encourage potentially transformative efforts to make these pathways more viable, including changes to engineering education that provide undergraduate students with the experiences and tools they need to navigate and succeed in their first job and changes to the entire engineering education and workforce continuum that create a more inclusive environment for capable engineers from a variety of backgrounds.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 06/22/2017<br>      Modified by: Elizabeth&nbsp;T&nbsp;Cady</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ By assessing the expectations, training, employment options, and employment choices of those trained or employed as engineers in the United States, this project aimed to broaden the thinking of engineering students, educators, employers, and policy makers about the connections between engineering education and the workforce. The resulting consensus report will identify opportunities, challenges, and potential actions for all stakeholders to strengthen the nation?s engineering workforce and the education enterprise that supports it.  A committee of experts at the National Academy of Engineering gathered and analyzed data in order to explore a set of questions about the career choices of engineering graduates and those employed as engineers with non-engineering degrees in the United States. The project addressed three objectives and related questions:  Objective 1: Collect and synthesize data from existing sources that shed light on the characteristics of those working as engineers in the US, including age, gender, educational background, occupational sector, job category (e.g., management, nonmanagement), compensation, and job-related competencies. Questions included:  1)      What kinds of occupations/jobs do engineering graduates have in engineering and non-engineering fields; what do we know about the competencies they bring to the workplace and the tasks they perform; and how has the type of work performed by engineers in and outside of engineering occupations changed over time ?  2)      How do compensation levels differ among engineering graduates working as engineers, engineering graduates working in non-STEM fields, and those without engineering degrees working as engineers? To what extent are these compensation levels influencing the career paths of recent graduates?  Objective 2: Collect and synthesize existing data that shed light on factors that influence the career decisions of those working as engineers and those trained as engineers who are not working in engineering, including individual characteristics, personal values and beliefs, motivation, self-efficacy, educational experience, economic incentives, job satisfaction, and job mobility.  1)      What factor or factors most explain BS engineering graduates? choice of occupation (engineering, engineering-related, or non-engineering related), and how do these factors and their influence change over time?    2)      Are those with engineering degrees choosing willingly or being diverted unwillingly to STEM-related and non-STEM related work?  3)      How if at all does the specific engineering discipline influence or align with occupational choice and career development?   4)     Do these factors differ across groups that are traditionally underrepresented in engineering (e.g., women, underrepresented minorities)?  Objective 3: Based on the data reviewed and/or collected, consider the implications of current career pathways to and through engineering for: undergraduate engineering students, post-secondary engineering programs, continuing engineering education initiatives, employers of engineering talent (e.g., on-the-job training), and US national interests.  1)      How should what we are learning about career pathways in engineering affect the curriculum in engineering programs, engineering pedagogy, and the criteria schools use to matriculate students into these programs?  2)      How should continuing and on-the-job engineering education efforts leverage information about career pathways to better align the competencies of engineers with the needs of employers?  3)      How well aligned are the skills and knowledge acquired in formal engineering education with the skills and knowledge needed on the job?  4)     How should the engineering enterprise increase representation of women, underrepresented minorities, and other marginalized groups?   The project?s study committee brought expertise and perspectives from several disciplines, including engineering occupations, engineering education, engineering education research, social sciences, labor economics, and statistics. This breadth of knowledge and viewpoints provides a different, more complex, and potentially more useful view of the engineering education-workforce continuum. By assessing the expectations, training, employment options, and employment choices of those educated or employed as engineers in the United States, this project aims to broaden the thinking of engineering educators and policy makers about the connection between engineering education and the workforce and presents opportunities and also raises challenges for the engineering education community and policy makers.   The final report is expected to reshape thinking regarding the "value proposition" for engineering, with resulting impacts within engineering education and the STEM, R&amp;D, and industrial policy communities. By critically evaluating the range of data sources relevant to engineering career pathways, the project challenges some long-held assumptions about not only what engineers do but also what education and training is needed to do engineering. This can provide a fruitful opening for more productive discussions within engineering education and among engineering education leaders, policy makers, and industry about the training and employment of engineering talent in the United States. Over the longer term, the project will encourage potentially transformative efforts to make these pathways more viable, including changes to engineering education that provide undergraduate students with the experiences and tools they need to navigate and succeed in their first job and changes to the entire engineering education and workforce continuum that create a more inclusive environment for capable engineers from a variety of backgrounds.       Last Modified: 06/22/2017       Submitted by: Elizabeth T Cady]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
