<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>NEESR Planning/Collaborative Research: Engineered Timber Structural Systems for Seismically Resilient Tall Buildings</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>10/01/2013</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>09/30/2015</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>70000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>70000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CMMI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Civil, Mechanical, &amp; Manufact Inn</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Joy Pauschke</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>jpauschk@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927024</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>To enable resilient, eight to fourteen story, timber buildings in regions of high seismicity in the United States, this planning grant combines innovative concepts in seismic load resisting systems with a new form of a mass timber structural component, called cross laminated timber (CLT), to research three potential structural systems for resilient, tall CLT building construction: (a) single-story, pre-stressed re-centering walls, (b) multi-story, segmental rocking walls, and (c) deformable floor diaphragms with supplemental damping devices. These systems will be distributed vertically along the height of the building, combining deformable panels or layers with relatively rigid and stiff ones, to leverage CLT behavior, enable rapid construction, and limit the impact of higher modes. Based on their performance in component-level testing and system-level simulation conducted as part of this research, promising systems that are economically competitive will be selected for full-scale experimental investigation in follow-on research.  This planning phase research will generate fundamental knowledge on resilient, multi-story panelized systems that have the potential to transform the seismic design of taller buildings in general. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;As urban densification occurs in U.S. regions of high seismicity, there is a natural demand for tall buildings that can survive large earthquakes with minimal damage and interruption. CLT is a naturally sustainable material that has been used in Europe and Australia to rapidly construct multi-story buildings. However, existing multi-story CLT constructions were limited to regions of low seismicity because there is no seismic design methodology for tall CLT buildings worldwide.  In the U.S. Pacific Northwest, there is significant interest in utilizing CLT in eight to fourteen story residential and commercial buildings due to its appeal as a potential locally sourced, sustainable, and economically competitive building material. With combined expertise from the research and design community, this project will address this societal need by prototyping three potential structural systems that are suitable for tall CLT buildings in high seismicity regions, comparing their performance through experimentation and simulation, and developing performance-based seismic design methods for their implementation. Once the optimal systems are selected in this study and verified at full-scale in subsequent research, it is envisioned that a resilient, tall CLT building will become an option for west coast cities in about six to eight years. In addition to providing research training for students working on the project, the project will deliver educational resources to introduce this new sustainable building type to students, stakeholders, and the general public.  Data from this project will be archived and made available to the public through the NEES data repository.  This award is part of the National Earthquake Hazards Reduction Program (NEHRP).</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/21/2013</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/21/2013</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1344621</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Jeffrey</FirstName>
<LastName>Berman</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>W</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Jeffrey W Berman</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>jwberman@u.washington.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2066163530</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000186668</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/21/2013</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Washington</Name>
<CityName>Seattle</CityName>
<ZipCode>981950001</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2065434043</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>4333 Brooklyn Ave NE</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Washington</StateName>
<StateCode>WA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>WA07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>605799469</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF WASHINGTON</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>042803536</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Washington]]></Name>
<CityName>Seattle</CityName>
<StateCode>WA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>981952700</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[4333 Brooklyn Ave NE]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Washington</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>WA07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7396</Code>
<Text>NEES RESEARCH</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>036E</Code>
<Text>CIVIL INFRASTRUCTURE</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>039E</Code>
<Text>STRUCTURAL SYSTEMS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>043E</Code>
<Text>EARTHQUAKE ENGINEERING</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1576</Code>
<Text>NATIONL EARTHQK HZRD REDCT PRG</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7231</Code>
<Text>CYBERINFRASTRUCTURE</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0113</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2013~70000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The research project has developed a new concept for a low-damage seismic force resisting system for tall timber buildings. The system utilizes cross-laminated timber (CLT) walls which is a new technology just becoming available in the United States and one that has enabled the design and construction of timber buildings in regions with no seismic hazard in Europe and Australia of up to 13 stories. Such buildings have been shown to have significantly smaller environmental impacts relative to steel and concrete construction but until now there have been now options for seismic load resisting systems that are necessary for implementation of the technology in the regions of high seismic hazard on the west coast of the U.S.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>The new seismic load resisting system allows the CLT walls to rock at their base and utilizes post-tensioning to ensure stability, post-earthquake recentering and low and easily repaired damage in even large earthquakes. The research performed with this grant consisted of large-scale experiments on rocking CLT walls, development of numerical models to simulate their seismic behavior in tall building applications, and design methods for implementation in practice. The experiments and analyses demonstrated that the system is capable of achieving the desired high level of seismic performance.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>Intellectual Merit:</p> <p>The research project first developed rocking CLT wall system concept in collaboration with structural engineering and architecture practitioners through a workshop held in Seattle. The concept was then applied to prototype tall timber buildings designed for Seattle. From these prototype designs, large-scale rocking CLT wall experiments to investigate the behavior of the system. Data from the experiments were interpreted and used to develop and calibrate numerical models to support design and analyses of the system. Numerical simulations of the prototype buildings under earthquake loading were conducted to investigate their seismic performance. Finally, project results were used to develop design methods for practitioners. The project was a collaboration between researchers with expertise in timber design, rocking system design for low-damage in seismic events, and large-scale testing. Development of this technology will enable the design and construction of tall timber buildings in high seismic regions of the U.S.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>Broader Impacts:</p> <p>The project results will advance the use of sustainable building construction techniques in the U.S., reducing the environmental impacts of building construction and increasing the use of U.S. timber which support rural economies. Additionally, by focusing on low-damage solutions for seismic load resisting systems, the project will improve the seismic resilience of communities where the technology is implemented. There is already a 12 story building under design in Portland, OR that is utilizing the system. This project was a winner of a USDA competition to promote tall timber buildings in the U.S. and would not be possible without the research results that demonstrate to building code officials the excellent seismic performance of the system. &nbsp;</p> <p><strong>&nbsp;</strong><em>&nbsp;</em></p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 12/13/2015<br>      Modified by: Jeffrey&nbsp;W&nbsp;Berman</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The research project has developed a new concept for a low-damage seismic force resisting system for tall timber buildings. The system utilizes cross-laminated timber (CLT) walls which is a new technology just becoming available in the United States and one that has enabled the design and construction of timber buildings in regions with no seismic hazard in Europe and Australia of up to 13 stories. Such buildings have been shown to have significantly smaller environmental impacts relative to steel and concrete construction but until now there have been now options for seismic load resisting systems that are necessary for implementation of the technology in the regions of high seismic hazard on the west coast of the U.S.     The new seismic load resisting system allows the CLT walls to rock at their base and utilizes post-tensioning to ensure stability, post-earthquake recentering and low and easily repaired damage in even large earthquakes. The research performed with this grant consisted of large-scale experiments on rocking CLT walls, development of numerical models to simulate their seismic behavior in tall building applications, and design methods for implementation in practice. The experiments and analyses demonstrated that the system is capable of achieving the desired high level of seismic performance.     Intellectual Merit:  The research project first developed rocking CLT wall system concept in collaboration with structural engineering and architecture practitioners through a workshop held in Seattle. The concept was then applied to prototype tall timber buildings designed for Seattle. From these prototype designs, large-scale rocking CLT wall experiments to investigate the behavior of the system. Data from the experiments were interpreted and used to develop and calibrate numerical models to support design and analyses of the system. Numerical simulations of the prototype buildings under earthquake loading were conducted to investigate their seismic performance. Finally, project results were used to develop design methods for practitioners. The project was a collaboration between researchers with expertise in timber design, rocking system design for low-damage in seismic events, and large-scale testing. Development of this technology will enable the design and construction of tall timber buildings in high seismic regions of the U.S.     Broader Impacts:  The project results will advance the use of sustainable building construction techniques in the U.S., reducing the environmental impacts of building construction and increasing the use of U.S. timber which support rural economies. Additionally, by focusing on low-damage solutions for seismic load resisting systems, the project will improve the seismic resilience of communities where the technology is implemented. There is already a 12 story building under design in Portland, OR that is utilizing the system. This project was a winner of a USDA competition to promote tall timber buildings in the U.S. and would not be possible without the research results that demonstrate to building code officials the excellent seismic performance of the system.                Last Modified: 12/13/2015       Submitted by: Jeffrey W Berman]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
