<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>SCH: INT: Collaborative Research: Physiological Studies of Brain Signals using a Wireless Neuro-Sensing-Diagnostic System</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>12/01/2013</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>11/30/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>887232.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>887232</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>05020000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>CSE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>IIS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Information &amp; Intelligent Systems</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Wendy Nilsen</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>wnilsen@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922568</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The goal of this project is to develop a fully-passive intra cranial sensing system. This novel electronic brain-machine interface utilizes an implantable miniaturized neurosensor based on microwave back-scattering, a miniature textile antenna, and RF circuits on flexible polymer substrate. It has the unique properties of only minor heating, thus, minimizing injury and trauma to the brain, eliminating the need for wires through the cranium, and preserving natural lifestyle and comfort. The acquired neurosignals are collected by a self-powered wearable body area network for continuous real-time monitoring and subsequent physiological interpretation. The project includes physiological studies of the acquired brain signals. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;While conceived initially as a tool for long-term monitoring of brain signals, this sensing technology has a very wide range of potential applications in health, including control of prosthetics and early detection of seizures. Overcoming the challenges in safety and long-term reliability presented by conventional neurosensor technology could transform healthcare for people suffering from severe chronic neurological disorders. Results of the physiological studies are disseminated through a data repository for understanding brain disorders. Research is integrated with education through several activities, including hands-on experience for students in this new area, summer camps, and a variety of outreach activities to attract women and minorities in engineering.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>09/16/2013</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>09/16/2013</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.070</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1344928</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Junseok</FirstName>
<LastName>Chae</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Junseok Chae</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>junseok.chae@asu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>4809652082</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000320161</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/16/2013</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Arizona State University</Name>
<CityName>TEMPE</CityName>
<ZipCode>852816011</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>4809655479</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>ORSPA</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[660 South Mill Avenue, Suite 310]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Arizona</StateName>
<StateCode>AZ</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>09</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>AZ09</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>943360412</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>ARIZONA STATE UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>806345658</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Arizona State University]]></Name>
<CityName>Tempe</CityName>
<StateCode>AZ</StateCode>
<ZipCode>852876011</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[PO Box 876011]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Arizona</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>09</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>AZ09</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>8018</Code>
<Text>Smart and Connected Health</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8018</Code>
<Text>Smart and Connected Health</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8062</Code>
<Text>SCH Type II: INT</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0113</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2013~887232</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>This NSF SCH project has been very highly successful in providing innovations for unobtrusive deep-brain neuro-sensing and in educating many graduate/undergraduate students and post-docs. Over the course of the project, 11 graduate students, 4 undergraduate students, and 1 post-doc were involved at the Ohio State and Arizona State sites. The PIs, students, and post-docs generated 6 journal papers and 15 conference papers, 3 of which were awarded with 'Best Student Paper Award', 'IEEE EMB-S Young Investigator Award', and 'Honorable Mention', respectively.</p> <p>A sampling of 6 high-impact outcomes are listed below</p> <p>1)&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; Designed, fabricated, and tested <em>in-vitro </em>a wireless and fully-passive neural recorder with a miniature footprint of only 10mm x 8.9mm. Benchtop measurements showed that this sensor can read &gt;15&mu;Vpp emulated neuropotentials. This implies a 33 times sensitivity improvement as compared to the neurosensing system developed at the beginning of this project.</p> <p>2)&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; Developed novel models to accurately represent the deep-brain electrode impedance as a function of frequency. Previous implementations used a 50&Omega; function generator to emulate the brain signals. Instead, our new electrode models provide much more realistic results in both simulations and measurements. This is a critical step towards future realistic <em>in-vivo </em>studies. Indeed preliminary <em>in-vivo</em> measurements in rats have demonstrated that our implant can detect neurosignals at the purported levels.</p> <p>3)&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; Developed a manufacturing process for fabricating wireless fully-passive neural implants on a flexible polyimide substrate. This flexible form can potentially lead to ?injectable? implants for practical use in surgical procedures without a need for open-skull surgery.</p> <p>4)&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; Designed and demonstrated a wireless passive stimulator on a flexible substrate, featuring high current delivery, up to 60 mA. This stimulator was initially used to stimulate engineered cardiac tissues and shown to provide synchronous contractions within 0.5-2 Hz. Importantly, to the authors' knowledge, this is the first successful attempt to regulate synchronous contraction of cardiac cells using a wireless stimulator.</p> <p>5)&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; Reviewed the literature to identify an algorithm to estimate the level of consciousness based on a non-perturbational approach, and identified an appropriate algorithm for analysis of ECoG data without the need for a perturbation signal.</p> <p>6)&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; Attempted to acquire <em>in-vivo</em> neural signals from a rat model. The flexible wireless fully-passive neural implant was placed in between the skelp and skull to record stimulation-evoked signals as well as interictal epileptiform discharges (IEDs). Direct side-by-side comparison of wired vs wireless data show good agreement, concluding that the wireless fully-passive sensor is capable of acquiring neural signals from a rat model.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 01/09/2019<br>      Modified by: Junseok&nbsp;Chae</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ This NSF SCH project has been very highly successful in providing innovations for unobtrusive deep-brain neuro-sensing and in educating many graduate/undergraduate students and post-docs. Over the course of the project, 11 graduate students, 4 undergraduate students, and 1 post-doc were involved at the Ohio State and Arizona State sites. The PIs, students, and post-docs generated 6 journal papers and 15 conference papers, 3 of which were awarded with 'Best Student Paper Award', 'IEEE EMB-S Young Investigator Award', and 'Honorable Mention', respectively.  A sampling of 6 high-impact outcomes are listed below  1)    Designed, fabricated, and tested in-vitro a wireless and fully-passive neural recorder with a miniature footprint of only 10mm x 8.9mm. Benchtop measurements showed that this sensor can read &gt;15&mu;Vpp emulated neuropotentials. This implies a 33 times sensitivity improvement as compared to the neurosensing system developed at the beginning of this project.  2)    Developed novel models to accurately represent the deep-brain electrode impedance as a function of frequency. Previous implementations used a 50&Omega; function generator to emulate the brain signals. Instead, our new electrode models provide much more realistic results in both simulations and measurements. This is a critical step towards future realistic in-vivo studies. Indeed preliminary in-vivo measurements in rats have demonstrated that our implant can detect neurosignals at the purported levels.  3)    Developed a manufacturing process for fabricating wireless fully-passive neural implants on a flexible polyimide substrate. This flexible form can potentially lead to ?injectable? implants for practical use in surgical procedures without a need for open-skull surgery.  4)    Designed and demonstrated a wireless passive stimulator on a flexible substrate, featuring high current delivery, up to 60 mA. This stimulator was initially used to stimulate engineered cardiac tissues and shown to provide synchronous contractions within 0.5-2 Hz. Importantly, to the authors' knowledge, this is the first successful attempt to regulate synchronous contraction of cardiac cells using a wireless stimulator.  5)    Reviewed the literature to identify an algorithm to estimate the level of consciousness based on a non-perturbational approach, and identified an appropriate algorithm for analysis of ECoG data without the need for a perturbation signal.  6)    Attempted to acquire in-vivo neural signals from a rat model. The flexible wireless fully-passive neural implant was placed in between the skelp and skull to record stimulation-evoked signals as well as interictal epileptiform discharges (IEDs). Direct side-by-side comparison of wired vs wireless data show good agreement, concluding that the wireless fully-passive sensor is capable of acquiring neural signals from a rat model.       Last Modified: 01/09/2019       Submitted by: Junseok Chae]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
