<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>INSPIRE Track 1: Primary School Organizations as Open Systems: Strategic External Relationship Development to Promote Student Engagement in STEM Topics</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>10/01/2013</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>09/30/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>707299.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>714599</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>11090000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>EHR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DRL</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Research On Learning</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Amy Baylor</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>abaylor@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032925126</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This INSPIRE award is partially funded by the Science of Organization Program in the Division of Social and Economic Sciences in the Social, Behavioral and Economic Sciences Directorate, and the Math and Science Partnership Program and the Discovery Research K-12 program in the Division of Research on Learning in the Education and Human Resources Directorate.  &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Our country faces a decline in student engagement, particularly in Science, Technology, Engineering, and Mathematics (STEM) disciplines and among underrepresented minority groups. Most often this problem is discussed in the context of an achievement gap, where racial and socioeconomic groups perform unequally on academic assessments. To understand what creates the achievement gap, researchers must understand the STEM "opportunity gap" that exists between students from different backgrounds, where these same students achieve differently because of varying exposure to out-of-school enrichment and learning experiences. The STEM opportunity gap arises from the inequity of out-of-school learning experiences for children. Therefore, efforts to engage minorities and women in STEM in primary schools will only succeed if we consider the complex organizational environment in which primary schools operate. The focus of this study is on what interorganizational relationships are necessary for schools to maintain to ensure equitable, efficient, and effective opportunities for students to engage in STEM. External relationships require schools to commit time and resources, and schools must decide which relationships to develop and maintain. Understanding what kinds of relationships particular school types invest in and what level of effort to commit to maintaining those relationships is important for improving student engagement opportunities in STEM. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Specifically, the study explores the following issues in 9 schools across 3 neighborhoods in Chicago, IL: &lt;br/&gt;     (1) How student engagement in STEM is enabled and constrained by the school's relations with its external community. &lt;br/&gt;     (2) The similarities and differences in partnerships, particularly STEM-related partnerships, across different types of schools in three different urban neighborhoods by mapping networks, and assessing the costs and benefits of creating, maintaining, and dissolving network ties.&lt;br/&gt;     (3) How to model school and network decisions, relations, and resources using an operations research framework. The model prescribes network configurations that address strategic, tactical, and operational concerns, to ensure the school will equitably, efficiently, and effectively utilize partners to improve student engagement in STEM.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>09/18/2013</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>01/06/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.076</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1344266</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>James</FirstName>
<LastName>Spillane</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>P</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>James P Spillane</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>j-spillane@northwestern.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>8474675577</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000455244</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/18/2013</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Karen</FirstName>
<LastName>Smilowitz</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>R</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Karen R Smilowitz</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>ksmilowitz@northwestern.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>8474914693</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000178418</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>01/06/2016</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Karen</FirstName>
<LastName>Smilowitz</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>R</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Karen R Smilowitz</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>ksmilowitz@northwestern.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>8474914693</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000178418</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/18/2013</StartDate>
<EndDate>06/04/2014</EndDate>
<RoleCode>Former Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Paul</FirstName>
<LastName>Leonardi</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>M</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Paul M Leonardi</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>leonardi@tmp.ucsb.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>8058935414</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000528770</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/18/2013</StartDate>
<EndDate>06/04/2014</EndDate>
<RoleCode>Former Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Northwestern University</Name>
<CityName>Chicago</CityName>
<ZipCode>606114579</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>3125037955</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>750 N. Lake Shore Drive</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[Rubloff 7th Floor]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Illinois</StateName>
<StateCode>IL</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>IL07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>160079455</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>NORTHWESTERN UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>005436803</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Northwestern University]]></Name>
<CityName>Evanston</CityName>
<StateCode>IL</StateCode>
<ZipCode>602080834</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[2145 Sheridan Rd]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Illinois</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>09</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>IL09</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7645</Code>
<Text>Discovery Research K-12</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>8078</Code>
<Text>INSPIRE</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8653</Code>
<Text>INSPIRE Track-1 Creative</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9251</Code>
<Text>REU SUPP-Res Exp for Ugrd Supp</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0113</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0114</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0413</Code>
<Name>NSF Education &amp; Human Resource</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040106</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0414</Code>
<Name>NSF Education &amp; Human Resource</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040106</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2013~437299</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~277300</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>There is concern over a decline in student engagement, particularly in Science, Technology, Engineering, and Mathematics (STEM) disciplines and among underrepresented minority groups in the United States.&nbsp; Often this problem is discussed in the context of an achievement gap, where racial and socioeconomic groups perform unequally on academic assessments. To understand what creates the achievement gap, researchers must understand the STEM "opportunity gap" that exists between students from different backgrounds, where these same students achieve differently because of varying exposure to out-of-school enrichment and learning experiences. The STEM opportunity gap arises from the inequity of out-of-school learning experiences for children. Therefore, efforts to engage minorities and women in STEM in primary schools will only succeed if we consider the complex organizational environment in which primary schools operate. The focus of this study is on what interorganizational relationships are necessary for schools to maintain to ensure equitable, efficient, and effective opportunities for students to engage in STEM. External relationships require schools to commit time and resources, and schools must decide which relationships to develop and maintain. Understanding what kinds of relationships particular school types invest in and what level of effort to commit to maintaining those relationships is important for improving student engagement opportunities in STEM.&nbsp; Specifically, the study explores these issues in the context of nine schools strategically chosen across three neighborhoods and three school types in a major urban setting.&nbsp;</p> <p><strong>Intellectual merit</strong></p> <p>The study of the factors that influence student engagement in school and in STEM, with a particular focus on each school's relationship with its external community, led to several key findings.&nbsp; The researchers found through extensive interviews with school employees that neighborhood organizations can play a unique role in brokering relationships between the school and the community. However, STEM brokers are scarce compared to other types of organizations (literacy, arts, etc.), evidencing a policy need to focus on organizations that connect schools to STEM resources and opportunities.&nbsp; Researchers were also able to characterize the variation in STEM-related partnerships across schools of different types and in different urban neighborhoods by mapping communication and partnership networks, and assessing the costs and benefits of creating, maintaining, and dissolving network ties.&nbsp; The team found that the distribution of resource relationships to external organizations is uneven across employees. Specifically, the trade-off is such that some people have many relationships, but each relationship involves minimal resources, and some other people have few relationships, but each involves many resources. This depth-versus-breadth trade off maps to how employees perceive the importance of the relationship to themselves, and their school more broadly.&nbsp; Furthermore, by comparing schools of different institutional types in different resource environments, the researchers were able to advance both resource dependence and institutional theories of organizations. &nbsp;Lastly, findings indicate a complex multi-dimensionality of resources that move through the school's network including knowledge, money, non-material resources, political support, community support, reputational benefits, time-saving benefits (volunteers), and even more informal social support. &nbsp;The massive amount of network data with multiplex ties enabled the team to explore topics around costs of multiplex resource acquisition under different communication conditions, which had been difficult to test without such complex data.</p> <p><strong>Broader impacts</strong></p> <p>Throughout the project, the team worked closely with the nine schools in the study to communicate results.&nbsp; This led to the creation of the School Supply Chain Website (<a href="https://theschoolsupplychainproject.weebly.com/">https://theschoolsupplychainproject.weebly.com/</a>).&nbsp; This interactive website allows schools to interactively explore how organizations can visualize their supply chains. This project has included significant training and professional development for undergraduate and graduate students.&nbsp; Students have learned about research design, collection, and data analysis, and helped in the development of reports and dissemination of the data.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 01/07/2019<br>      Modified by: Karen&nbsp;R&nbsp;Smilowitz</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ There is concern over a decline in student engagement, particularly in Science, Technology, Engineering, and Mathematics (STEM) disciplines and among underrepresented minority groups in the United States.  Often this problem is discussed in the context of an achievement gap, where racial and socioeconomic groups perform unequally on academic assessments. To understand what creates the achievement gap, researchers must understand the STEM "opportunity gap" that exists between students from different backgrounds, where these same students achieve differently because of varying exposure to out-of-school enrichment and learning experiences. The STEM opportunity gap arises from the inequity of out-of-school learning experiences for children. Therefore, efforts to engage minorities and women in STEM in primary schools will only succeed if we consider the complex organizational environment in which primary schools operate. The focus of this study is on what interorganizational relationships are necessary for schools to maintain to ensure equitable, efficient, and effective opportunities for students to engage in STEM. External relationships require schools to commit time and resources, and schools must decide which relationships to develop and maintain. Understanding what kinds of relationships particular school types invest in and what level of effort to commit to maintaining those relationships is important for improving student engagement opportunities in STEM.  Specifically, the study explores these issues in the context of nine schools strategically chosen across three neighborhoods and three school types in a major urban setting.   Intellectual merit  The study of the factors that influence student engagement in school and in STEM, with a particular focus on each school's relationship with its external community, led to several key findings.  The researchers found through extensive interviews with school employees that neighborhood organizations can play a unique role in brokering relationships between the school and the community. However, STEM brokers are scarce compared to other types of organizations (literacy, arts, etc.), evidencing a policy need to focus on organizations that connect schools to STEM resources and opportunities.  Researchers were also able to characterize the variation in STEM-related partnerships across schools of different types and in different urban neighborhoods by mapping communication and partnership networks, and assessing the costs and benefits of creating, maintaining, and dissolving network ties.  The team found that the distribution of resource relationships to external organizations is uneven across employees. Specifically, the trade-off is such that some people have many relationships, but each relationship involves minimal resources, and some other people have few relationships, but each involves many resources. This depth-versus-breadth trade off maps to how employees perceive the importance of the relationship to themselves, and their school more broadly.  Furthermore, by comparing schools of different institutional types in different resource environments, the researchers were able to advance both resource dependence and institutional theories of organizations.  Lastly, findings indicate a complex multi-dimensionality of resources that move through the school's network including knowledge, money, non-material resources, political support, community support, reputational benefits, time-saving benefits (volunteers), and even more informal social support.  The massive amount of network data with multiplex ties enabled the team to explore topics around costs of multiplex resource acquisition under different communication conditions, which had been difficult to test without such complex data.  Broader impacts  Throughout the project, the team worked closely with the nine schools in the study to communicate results.  This led to the creation of the School Supply Chain Website (https://theschoolsupplychainproject.weebly.com/).  This interactive website allows schools to interactively explore how organizations can visualize their supply chains. This project has included significant training and professional development for undergraduate and graduate students.  Students have learned about research design, collection, and data analysis, and helped in the development of reports and dissemination of the data.       Last Modified: 01/07/2019       Submitted by: Karen R Smilowitz]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
