<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>CSR: EAGER: Design and Implementation of a Fine-Grained Appliance Energy Profiling System for Green Building</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2013</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2015</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>258040.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>290040</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>05050000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>CSE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CNS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Computer and Network Systems</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Marilyn McClure</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>mmcclure@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032925197</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Green building applications need efficient and fine-grained determination of power consumption pattern of a wide variety of consumer-grade appliances through non-intrusive load monitoring (NILM) techniques for an effective adaptation and percolation of demand response model down to the consumer level appliances. A key inhibitor to the widespread adoption of such demand response policy at the consumer grade appliances for intelligent building energy management, is the inability of smart plug to efficiently determine, control or infer the power consumption pattern of multiple devices in tandem.  In practice, deploying smart plug based NILM and acquiring the low-level power measures of a large number of devices is often difficult or impossible due to the deployment complexity and varying characteristics of devices and thus must instead be employed at the circuit-level and inferred through the incorporation of novel usage-based measurement and probabilistic level-based disaggregation algorithm. But the challenges in deploying non-intrusive load monitoring algorithm involve disaggregating individual device?s consumption from the aggregate power measurement, as well as modeling and incorporating the usage based prediction. Thus in this project we will focus on advanced machine learning and data analytics algorithms that capture the measurement based approach and circuit level NILM with the autonomous profiling and prediction logic to enable the deployment of flexible and fungible smart plug and the evolvability of future DR model in green building applications.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/31/2013</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>02/06/2015</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.070</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1344990</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Nirmalya</FirstName>
<LastName>Roy</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Nirmalya Roy</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>nroy@umbc.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>4104553182</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000615120</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/31/2013</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Maryland Baltimore County</Name>
<CityName>Baltimore</CityName>
<ZipCode>212500002</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>4104553140</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1000 Hilltop Circle</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Maryland</StateName>
<StateCode>MD</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MD07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>061364808</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF MARYLAND BALTIMORE COUNTY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>003256088</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Maryland Baltimore County]]></Name>
<CityName>Baltimore</CityName>
<StateCode>MD</StateCode>
<ZipCode>212500002</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[1000 Hilltop Circle]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Maryland</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MD07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1714</Code>
<Text>Special Projects - CNS</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7354</Code>
<Text>CSR-Computer Systems Research</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7916</Code>
<Text>EAGER</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9178</Code>
<Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9251</Code>
<Text>REU SUPP-Res Exp for Ugrd Supp</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0112</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0114</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0115</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2012~258040</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~16000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2015~16000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Green building applications need efficient and fine-grained determination of power consumption pattern of a wide variety of consumer-grade appliances through non-intrusive load monitoring (NILM) techniques. Inspired by this, we developed circuit-level non-intrusive load monitoring algorithms, measurements based usage model, probabilistic level based disaggregation algorithm and power-line communications and control that support green building applications&rsquo; requirements. We elicited an autonomous discovery, profiling and predictive model in the unique setting of green building, which captures the relationship between disaggregated power measures and a device&rsquo;s actual usage characteristics. This model is complicated by the fact that multiple devices would simultaneously generate a single power measure, which must be disaggregated from an aggregate measurement. To support accurate identification of such consumer-scale devices, we combined NILM techniques with usage-based predictors about the likely patterns of different devices.</p> <p>This Green Building energy analytics project provided the UMBC graduate and undergraduate students with the opportunity to be involved with cutting-edge energy efficiency and conservation research and state-of-the-art energy related technologies. This helped students to gain a greater sense of social awareness and deeper understanding of energy system technologies. The amalgamation of&nbsp; fundamental energy metering and disaggregation research and incubation of appliance specific itemized energy consumption visualization and database development tasks from our everyday smart environments have made this project efforts unique and interesting both among the graduate and undergraduate students while raising the public awareness on energy sustainability. We have interacted with close to 300 students by giving them the opportunity to work on an energy education research and development project. This has not only helped to increase energy awareness among the students, but also made them prepared for handling practical research projects, public demonstration and talks in front of industrial personnel and in any regional or international conferences. It has also prepared them for graduate studies, professional careers in energy related companies and information technology. The project has also disseminated sustainable behavior and practices among the students, the community and beyond. Students have used real datasets in their research and development projects that help solidified their analysis, and submitted the project report articulating the challenges, motivation and quantifying the behavioral changes in terms of carbon footprint. The datasets have been made available to our Green Building project website <a href="http://mpsc.umbc.edu/softwaredata/">http://mpsc.umbc.edu/softwaredata/</a> to advance the research in this field.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 02/05/2016<br>      Modified by: Nirmalya&nbsp;Roy</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Green building applications need efficient and fine-grained determination of power consumption pattern of a wide variety of consumer-grade appliances through non-intrusive load monitoring (NILM) techniques. Inspired by this, we developed circuit-level non-intrusive load monitoring algorithms, measurements based usage model, probabilistic level based disaggregation algorithm and power-line communications and control that support green building applicationsÆ requirements. We elicited an autonomous discovery, profiling and predictive model in the unique setting of green building, which captures the relationship between disaggregated power measures and a deviceÆs actual usage characteristics. This model is complicated by the fact that multiple devices would simultaneously generate a single power measure, which must be disaggregated from an aggregate measurement. To support accurate identification of such consumer-scale devices, we combined NILM techniques with usage-based predictors about the likely patterns of different devices.  This Green Building energy analytics project provided the UMBC graduate and undergraduate students with the opportunity to be involved with cutting-edge energy efficiency and conservation research and state-of-the-art energy related technologies. This helped students to gain a greater sense of social awareness and deeper understanding of energy system technologies. The amalgamation of  fundamental energy metering and disaggregation research and incubation of appliance specific itemized energy consumption visualization and database development tasks from our everyday smart environments have made this project efforts unique and interesting both among the graduate and undergraduate students while raising the public awareness on energy sustainability. We have interacted with close to 300 students by giving them the opportunity to work on an energy education research and development project. This has not only helped to increase energy awareness among the students, but also made them prepared for handling practical research projects, public demonstration and talks in front of industrial personnel and in any regional or international conferences. It has also prepared them for graduate studies, professional careers in energy related companies and information technology. The project has also disseminated sustainable behavior and practices among the students, the community and beyond. Students have used real datasets in their research and development projects that help solidified their analysis, and submitted the project report articulating the challenges, motivation and quantifying the behavioral changes in terms of carbon footprint. The datasets have been made available to our Green Building project website http://mpsc.umbc.edu/softwaredata/ to advance the research in this field.       Last Modified: 02/05/2016       Submitted by: Nirmalya Roy]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
