<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Painting Between the Ice: Antarctic Biodiversity from the Dry Valleys to the Sea Floor</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>06/01/2014</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>11/30/2014</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>1.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>1</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>06090300</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>GEO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>OPP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Office of Polar Programs (OPP)</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Peter West</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The PI proposes to collaborate with three field teams to study and create paintings focused on biodiversity&amp;#8232;in the McMurdo Dry Valleys and Ross Sea. She proposes to create a series of mural-size paintings based on organisms native to the Southern Ocean?s sea floor and the soil of the Dry Valleys. The paintings will explore uniquely adapted Antarctic invertebrates and their habitats &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The PI proposes to explore the benthic communities in the Ross Sea, either first-hand or through the observations of specimens gathered by scientifc divers. She proposes, if possible, ?to study, draw, and paint the organisms while they are still ?alive, flush with natural pigment, and illuminated by the unique&amp;#8232;blue glow of sunlight filtered through the ice covering the ocean?s surface.? &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Painting en plain air, she also proposes to subsequently work with field teams to investigate and capture on canvas the complex soil ecosystems of Taylor Valley. She will observe and paint nematodes, tardigrades, and rotifers extracted from the soil in and around the Valleys? network of water&amp;#8232;tracks. &lt;br/&gt;</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/08/2014</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/08/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.078</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1344504</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Lily</FirstName>
<LastName>Simonson</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Lily Simonson</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress/>
<PI_PHON>5106846566</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000645415</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/08/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Simonson                Lily</Name>
<CityName>Los Angeles</CityName>
<ZipCode>900682708</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber/>
<StreetAddress/>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>28</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CA28</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM/>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME/>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Simonson                Lily]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>900682708</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>28</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CA28</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>5294</Code>
<Text>Antarctic Education</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<Appropriation>
<Code>02XX</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~1</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p class="vert-spacing">As research technologies advance, our understanding of life in Antarctica, especially at the microscopic level, has deepened tremendously. These more refined tools and important new discoveries offer rich subjects for artistic interpretation. Through painting, I aim to share these new discoveries with a broader audience, and help them understand both the advancements in research technologies, and the richness of Antarctica&rsquo;s distinctive ecosystem.</p> <p>I collaborated with four research groups to study and paint the rich biodiversity of the McMurdo Dry Valleys, the McMurdo Sound, and Mount Erebus. The resulting series of paintings explore these unique habitats as microcosmic indexes of global change. Once characterized by isolation, these specialized ecosystems face increased connectivity as a result of human activities and natural geological shifts.</p> <p>In October and November of 2014, I SCUBA dove 25 times in the McMurdo Sound to explore the benthic communities of shimmering polychaetes, vibrant sea stars, unusual crustaceans, and other invertebrates flourishing on the volcanically-formed seafloor. During these dives, I took video, photographs, and collected a handful of specimens. With the assistance of Crary Lab staff, I kept the animals alive in the touch tank. I used the animals, alongside my video and photo, as models while I painted in the studio that we set up the second flight of Crary.</p> <p>In mid-December, I joined the MEVO group at Fang Camp and at Lower Erebus Hut. I created drawings and paintings based my own observations, and on data they collected from their research. This leg of my project seeks to tie together the impact of geothermal activity on the formation of Ross Island and the Ross Sea Floor, and ties this landscape to the ancient volcanic footprints throughout the McMurdo Dry Valleys.</p> <p>From December 22-February 1, I collaborated with science groups led by Joseph Levy and Diana Wall to study and paint the ecosystems within the soil of the Dry Valleys. Embedded in Levy&rsquo;s group, I assisted with field work and created drawings and paintings inspired by the Valleys&rsquo; hydrology. Working en plein air, I made paintings and drawings capturing the intricacies of these channels of moisture. Formed in the seasonally active layer of permafrost soil, these water tracks are likely to expand as the climate warms. The expansion of moisture in turn impacts the diversity of invertebrates, which are studied by Wall&rsquo;s team. Working both in the field and at the lab on station, I was able to observe and depict the nematodes, tardigrades, and rotifers collected from the soil in Taylor Valley.</p> <p>These sites may be on the verge of experiencing dramatic changes as a result of subtle global shifts. Reinterpreting these small organisms and their surroundings through magnified, dramatic compositions, my paintings and the discourse around them position these ecosystems as symbols of both isolation and connectivity. My work highlights the importance of studying these seemingly remote areas, and illuminates the ways in which human actions affect the Antarctic.</p> <p>Combining tropes of zoological illustration, Renaissance glazing, and abstract expressionism, these paintings mine the complex morphologies of my subjects to explore new modes of representation, in addition to conveying current ecological concerns.</p> <p>Throughout my deployment, I posted images and updates to a range of blogs and social media platforms, sharing my art and discussing the science that inspires the work. In addition, I am currently compiling short videos highlighting my process of collaborating with Antarctic scientists and diving beneath the ice. I am now designing and courses inspired by current Antarctic research, aimed at guiding students in translating complex research into compelling visual images. Implemented through the Norto...]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[As research technologies advance, our understanding of life in Antarctica, especially at the microscopic level, has deepened tremendously. These more refined tools and important new discoveries offer rich subjects for artistic interpretation. Through painting, I aim to share these new discoveries with a broader audience, and help them understand both the advancements in research technologies, and the richness of AntarcticaÆs distinctive ecosystem.  I collaborated with four research groups to study and paint the rich biodiversity of the McMurdo Dry Valleys, the McMurdo Sound, and Mount Erebus. The resulting series of paintings explore these unique habitats as microcosmic indexes of global change. Once characterized by isolation, these specialized ecosystems face increased connectivity as a result of human activities and natural geological shifts.  In October and November of 2014, I SCUBA dove 25 times in the McMurdo Sound to explore the benthic communities of shimmering polychaetes, vibrant sea stars, unusual crustaceans, and other invertebrates flourishing on the volcanically-formed seafloor. During these dives, I took video, photographs, and collected a handful of specimens. With the assistance of Crary Lab staff, I kept the animals alive in the touch tank. I used the animals, alongside my video and photo, as models while I painted in the studio that we set up the second flight of Crary.  In mid-December, I joined the MEVO group at Fang Camp and at Lower Erebus Hut. I created drawings and paintings based my own observations, and on data they collected from their research. This leg of my project seeks to tie together the impact of geothermal activity on the formation of Ross Island and the Ross Sea Floor, and ties this landscape to the ancient volcanic footprints throughout the McMurdo Dry Valleys.  From December 22-February 1, I collaborated with science groups led by Joseph Levy and Diana Wall to study and paint the ecosystems within the soil of the Dry Valleys. Embedded in LevyÆs group, I assisted with field work and created drawings and paintings inspired by the ValleysÆ hydrology. Working en plein air, I made paintings and drawings capturing the intricacies of these channels of moisture. Formed in the seasonally active layer of permafrost soil, these water tracks are likely to expand as the climate warms. The expansion of moisture in turn impacts the diversity of invertebrates, which are studied by WallÆs team. Working both in the field and at the lab on station, I was able to observe and depict the nematodes, tardigrades, and rotifers collected from the soil in Taylor Valley.  These sites may be on the verge of experiencing dramatic changes as a result of subtle global shifts. Reinterpreting these small organisms and their surroundings through magnified, dramatic compositions, my paintings and the discourse around them position these ecosystems as symbols of both isolation and connectivity. My work highlights the importance of studying these seemingly remote areas, and illuminates the ways in which human actions affect the Antarctic.  Combining tropes of zoological illustration, Renaissance glazing, and abstract expressionism, these paintings mine the complex morphologies of my subjects to explore new modes of representation, in addition to conveying current ecological concerns.  Throughout my deployment, I posted images and updates to a range of blogs and social media platforms, sharing my art and discussing the science that inspires the work. In addition, I am currently compiling short videos highlighting my process of collaborating with Antarctic scientists and diving beneath the ice. I am now designing and courses inspired by current Antarctic research, aimed at guiding students in translating complex research into compelling visual images. Implemented through the Norton Simon Teen Arts Academy and Adult Drawing Classes. The paintings generated from my time on the ice will be exhibited at CB1 Gallery in Los Angeles a...]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
