<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Special Semester on Evolutionary Problems at the Mittag-Leffler Institute - support for US participants</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>10/01/2013</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>09/30/2014</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>23800.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>23800</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DMS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Bruce P. Palka</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Abstract (Manfredi, 1344316): &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award provides funding to help defray the expenses of graduate students and young mathematicians to participate in the Special Semester on "Evolutionary Problems" on December 2-4 2013, at the Mittag-Leffler Institute of Mathematical Sciences.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The Special Semester aims to bring together leading experts and researchers in nonlinear partial differential equations (both on the applied and theoretical sides). This proposal support US participants who will get involved in the institute activities during December 02-04. The list of speakers includes young mathematicians such as S. Amrstrong and C. Smart.  During that period, the activities will revolve around the theory of nonlinear PDEs  and related evolutionary equations. The one semester program at the institute focuses on some important classes of equations which among other things, are of importance in mathematical modeling. Between seventeen and twenty participants will travel from the US, and the majority of the participants to be supported are minorities. This proposal contains a letter of commitment from the Mittag-Leffler Institute to support the local expenses of up to twenty US participants.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/12/2013</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/12/2013</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1344316</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Juan</FirstName>
<LastName>Manfredi</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>J</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Juan J Manfredi</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>manfredi@pitt.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>4126248374</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000394692</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/12/2013</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Pittsburgh</Name>
<CityName>Pittsburgh</CityName>
<ZipCode>152133203</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>4126247400</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>300 Murdoch Building</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[3420 Forbes Avenue]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Pennsylvania</StateName>
<StateCode>PA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>18</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>PA18</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>004514360</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF PITTSBURGH, THE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>004514360</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Pittsburgh]]></Name>
<CityName>Pittsburgh</CityName>
<StateCode>PA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>152132303</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[University Club]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Pennsylvania</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>18</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>PA18</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1281</Code>
<Text>ANALYSIS PROGRAM</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7556</Code>
<Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0113</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2013~23800</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>This project facilitated the visit a group of US mathematicians to the Mittag-Leffler Institute of Mathematical Sciences in Stockholm (Sweden) to participate in the Special Semester on <em>Evolutionary Problems</em> and to attend the conference <em>Quasilinear PDES and Game Theory</em>, at Uppsala University, December 2-4, 2103. &nbsp;</p> <p>Funds for this projects were used to pay for travel expenses to Sweden. The Mittag-Leffler Institute covered the local expenses of the participants supported by this award.</p> <p>Eighteen (18) US mathematicians (seven (7) faculty members, two (2) of them Assistant Professors, four (4) postdoctoral scholars, and seven (7) graduate students) &nbsp;from US institutions participated in the Special Semester on <em>Evolutionary Problems</em>&nbsp;at the Mittag Leffler Institute. Fourteen of them (14) attended the conference&nbsp;<em>Quasilinear PDES and Game Theory</em>, at Uppsala University. Four (4) of them were invited speakers at this conference.&nbsp;</p> <p>They were &nbsp;a diverse group of mathematicians, including &nbsp;two (2) &nbsp;women, three (3) African-American mathematicians, and one student veteran.&nbsp;</p> <p>In the unique informal atmosphere at the Mittag-Leffler institute, participants in this project, particularly graduate students, postdoctoral scholars, and assistant professors, enjoyed many opportunities for meaningful, interactions with senior investigators, without time constraints. &nbsp;The few traditional offices assigned to senior investigators are always open, and the many open spaces and the library, provided good places for mathematical discussions.&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 11/27/2015<br>      Modified by: Juan&nbsp;J&nbsp;Manfredi</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ This project facilitated the visit a group of US mathematicians to the Mittag-Leffler Institute of Mathematical Sciences in Stockholm (Sweden) to participate in the Special Semester on Evolutionary Problems and to attend the conference Quasilinear PDES and Game Theory, at Uppsala University, December 2-4, 2103.    Funds for this projects were used to pay for travel expenses to Sweden. The Mittag-Leffler Institute covered the local expenses of the participants supported by this award.  Eighteen (18) US mathematicians (seven (7) faculty members, two (2) of them Assistant Professors, four (4) postdoctoral scholars, and seven (7) graduate students)  from US institutions participated in the Special Semester on Evolutionary Problems at the Mittag Leffler Institute. Fourteen of them (14) attended the conference Quasilinear PDES and Game Theory, at Uppsala University. Four (4) of them were invited speakers at this conference.   They were  a diverse group of mathematicians, including  two (2)  women, three (3) African-American mathematicians, and one student veteran.   In the unique informal atmosphere at the Mittag-Leffler institute, participants in this project, particularly graduate students, postdoctoral scholars, and assistant professors, enjoyed many opportunities for meaningful, interactions with senior investigators, without time constraints.  The few traditional offices assigned to senior investigators are always open, and the many open spaces and the library, provided good places for mathematical discussions.              Last Modified: 11/27/2015       Submitted by: Juan J Manfredi]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
