<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>SNM: Large Scale Manufacturing of Low-Cost Functionalized Carbon Nanomaterials for Energy Storage and Biosensor Applications</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>12/01/2013</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>11/30/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>1497905.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>1497905</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CMMI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Civil, Mechanical, &amp; Manufact Inn</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Khershed Cooper</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>khcooper@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927017</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The benefits of graphene nano-petal structures are high surface area-to-volume ratio and high thermal and electrical conductivities. Graphene nano-petals can be functionalized for specific applications such as sensors, power and energy and lightweight materials. This grant provides funding to boost the throughput and yield of coated graphene nano-petal structures by ~5 orders of magnitude to 10m2/h from  the current lab-scale throughput thus opening the door to their commercial viability in diverse application areas such as biosensing, electrochemical energy storage to high strength, lightweight carbon fiber composites. This major breakthrough will arise from comprehensive research proposed in five thrust areas, namely the design of continuous, roll-to-roll  processing systems for large scale graphene nano-petal growth; fundamental understanding of graphene nano-petal growth mechanisms in a novel high energy plasma-enhanced chemical vapor deposition reactor; understanding of vibrations and stability of the transported web based on coarse-grain simulation models; scalable functionalization of the nano-petals in an ambient environment; and study of new in-line and offline metrology tools for quality control of devices based on the functionalized nano-petal structures.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Graphene nano-petal based surfaces could find wide commercial use in detection of glucose in ultra-low concentrations, supercapacitors with concurrent high power and energy densities with high cycle stability, and in high-performance carbon fiber composites and new thermal interfacial materials. The breakthrough technologies that will be developed in this project will find direct commercial outlet through strong collaboration with start-up companies. Many results and methods from this research are likely to be applicable to a wide variety of low-pressure and ambient roll-to-roll nanomanufacturing processes such as for flexible electronics and membrane technology.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>09/24/2013</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>09/24/2013</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1344654</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Alexander</FirstName>
<LastName>Wei</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Alexander Wei</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>alexwei@purdue.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>7654945257</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000450748</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/24/2013</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Timothy</FirstName>
<LastName>Fisher</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>S</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Timothy S Fisher</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>tsfisher@ucla.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>3102068113</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000316158</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/24/2013</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Arvind</FirstName>
<LastName>Raman</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Arvind Raman</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>raman@ecn.purdue.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>7654945733</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000287939</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/24/2013</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Alina</FirstName>
<LastName>Alexeenko</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>A</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Alina A Alexeenko</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>alexeenk@purdue.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>7654961864</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000239501</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/24/2013</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Ernesto</FirstName>
<LastName>Marinero</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>E</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Ernesto E Marinero</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>eemarinero@purdue.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON/>
<NSF_ID>000646810</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/24/2013</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Purdue University</Name>
<CityName>West Lafayette</CityName>
<ZipCode>479072114</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>7654941055</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>Young Hall</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[155 S Grant Street]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Indiana</StateName>
<StateCode>IN</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>IN04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>072051394</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>PURDUE UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>072051394</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Purdue University]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>IN</StateCode>
<ZipCode>479072017</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Indiana</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>IN04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1674</Code>
<Text>NANOSCALE: INTRDISCPL RESRCH T</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>082E</Code>
<Text>MFG MACHINES &amp; METROLOGY</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>083E</Code>
<Text>MATERIAL TRANSFORMATION PROC</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>084E</Code>
<Text>NANOMANUFACTURING</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1674</Code>
<Text>NANOSCALE: INTRDISCPL RESRCH T</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0113</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2013~1497905</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Graphitic nanopetals are critical to enhancing material performance in a variety of engineered applications. These nanostructures have been fabricated extensively in batch-style processes on both flat and flexible substrates, but have yet to be produced in a&nbsp;&nbsp;continuous&nbsp;&nbsp;fashion.&nbsp;A roll-to-roll radio-frequency (80 kHz, 5 kW) plasma chemical vapor deposition (CVD) system was developed to deposit, in a continuous fashion, carbon nanomaterials, such as planar graphene, graphitic petals, and carbon nanotubes. Eight processing parameters can be varied including plasma power, chamber pressure, material speed, and the ratio of gases entering the chamber (Ar:H2:CH4:N2:O2). A plasma diagnostic technique capable of real-time process monitoring has been developed based on optical emission spectroscopy (OES).&nbsp;&nbsp;A custom R2R CVD system was designed, built and then installed in Birck Nanotechnology Center and made available to users.&nbsp;&nbsp;Plasma CVD and optical emission simulations have been developed based on electromagnetic, fluid/thermal and plasma chemistry modeling and applied for better process understanding and design. Beyond carbon nanopetals, the modeling framework is applicable to CVD of graphene and diamond coatings for high-temperature extreme hardness requirements and other plasma-based reactors. A statistical approach to scale up graphene production in the R2R RF plasma CVD was developed. Based on statistical surrogate models, the deposited graphene quality is largely influenced by gas pressure, nitrogen, oxygen, and plasma power. A sequential optimization technique was applied to suggest experiments that minimize the uncertainty of the model while increasing the quality of graphene. Moreover, the results from OES suggest correlations of CH species to low defects, while the presence of Ar+, C2, H&alpha;, and O correlate to high defects. The reported approach can be utilized in scaling up other 2D materials and other roll-to-roll manufacturing processes.</p> <p>The project resulted in new knowledge and methods to characterize, model and optimize plasma-based chemical vapor deposition (CVD) processes for roll-to-roll manufacturing graphitic petals and other carbon nanomaterials. In addition to the development of scalable nanomanufacturing techniques, we have participated in related studies on the mechanics and application of the materials towards (1) understanding the manufactured material characteristics required for function, and (2) creating future manufacturing demand. Such applications include nanopetal-based flexible wire supercapacitors, mechanics of nanoparticle assemblies, scalable functional coatings on graphene and nanopetals, graphene nanoparticle assemblies for thermal applications, and cell culture on nanopetals. Additionally we characterized MEMS device concepts utilizing nanopetal field-emitters for enabling microreactors.&nbsp;</p> <p>During the development of R2R processes for the continuous production of electroactive carbon films, we identified an opportunity to adapt this method toward the scalable preparation of macroporous thin films, using a laser-based process under dry, ambient conditions and magnetic gold nanoclusters (MGNCs) as etchants. This approach is compatible with continuous manufacturing processes, and offers a potentially low-cost alternative to batch methods based on reactive ion-track etching. A scalable synthesis of MGNCs (dav 100 nm) was developed using aqueous solutions and chemical reagents with low environmental impact. MGNCs were deposited onto thermoplastic roll films (50-75 micron thickness) using a simple gravure process, then exposed to nanosecond laser pulses in the presence of a coaxial magnetic field gradient to produce submicron channels with aspect ratios up to 1000, as characterized by three-dimensional confocal imaging. This dry-etching process can be performed in air and is applicable to a substrates ranging from fluoropolymers to borosilicate glass, with etch rates in excess of 1 microm/s. Finite-element modeling suggests that the absorption of laser pulses by MGNCs produces temperature spikes of nearly 1000 deg C, which can produce photoacoustic responses that drive particles into the medium while being guided by magnetomotive force.</p> <p>Results of the project have been published and presented in scientific conferences and workshops. This includes 23 articles in peer-reviewed journals and a patent application. Several graduate students completed their PhD dissertations based on this project, and one student participated in entrepreneurship training through NSF/DOD I-Corps.&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 04/01/2019<br>      Modified by: Alina&nbsp;A&nbsp;Alexeenko</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Images (<span id="selectedPhoto0">1</span> of <span class="totalNumber"></span>)           </div> <div class="galControls" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1344654/1344654_10283610_1554091500198_SNM_Outcomes_images_r2r--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1344654/1344654_10283610_1554091500198_SNM_Outcomes_images_r2r--rgov-800width.jpg" title="R2R Plasma CVD System"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1344654/1344654_10283610_1554091500198_SNM_Outcomes_images_r2r--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="R2R Plasma CVD System"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Roll-to-roll radio-frequency plasma chemical vapor deposition equipment. View of a) full equipment, b) inside vacuum chamber, c) electrodearea, and d) active plasma through the quartz window.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Kimberly Saviers</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Alina&nbsp;A&nbsp;Alexeenko</div> <div class="imageTitle">R2R Plasma CVD System</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1344654/1344654_10283610_1554090471569_SNM_Outcomes_images--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1344654/1344654_10283610_1554090471569_SNM_Outcomes_images--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Scalable synthesis of macroporous thin films"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1344654/1344654_10283610_1554090471569_SNM_Outcomes_images--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Scalable synthesis of macroporous thin films"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">(a) Dry-etching process of nanopores in thermoplastic films under ambient conditions, by pulsed laser irradiation of magnetic gold nanoclusters (MGNCs) aided by a coaxial magnetic field gradient. (b) 3D confocal image of nanoporous PTFE film (50 &#956;m) with infiltrated dye solution.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Alexander Wei</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Alina&nbsp;A&nbsp;Alexeenko</div> <div class="imageTitle">Scalable synthesis of macroporous thin films</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1344654/1344654_10283610_1554091931936_SNM_Outcomes_images_petals--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1344654/1344654_10283610_1554091931936_SNM_Outcomes_images_petals--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Deposited structures on 1-m tow"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1344654/1344654_10283610_1554091931936_SNM_Outcomes_images_petals--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Deposited structures on 1-m tow"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">SEM images along the length of the carbon fiber tow, captured at intervals of 4.6 cm. Distinct morphologies include a) standalone nanowalls,b) light coverage of GPs, c) unstructured carbon, and d) copious coverage of well-defined GPs.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Majed Alrefae</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Alina&nbsp;A&nbsp;Alexeenko</div> <div class="imageTitle">Deposited structures on 1-m tow</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1344654/1344654_10283610_1554093078213_SNM_Outcomes_images_OES--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1344654/1344654_10283610_1554093078213_SNM_Outcomes_images_OES--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Plasma modeling vs OES"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1344654/1344654_10283610_1554093078213_SNM_Outcomes_images_OES--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Plasma modeling vs OES"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">(left) Locations in the discharge gap at which the emission intensities are modeled. Plasmaimage shown for Vamp = 186 V, Pg = 9.5 mbar, fcycle = 80 kHz square wave input. (right) Comparison of emission intensity from the CRM with OES measurements at locations 1 and 3.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Gayathri Shivkumar</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Public Domain</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Alina&nbsp;A&nbsp;Alexeenko</div> <div class="imageTitle">Plasma modeling vs OES</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Graphitic nanopetals are critical to enhancing material performance in a variety of engineered applications. These nanostructures have been fabricated extensively in batch-style processes on both flat and flexible substrates, but have yet to be produced in a  continuous  fashion. A roll-to-roll radio-frequency (80 kHz, 5 kW) plasma chemical vapor deposition (CVD) system was developed to deposit, in a continuous fashion, carbon nanomaterials, such as planar graphene, graphitic petals, and carbon nanotubes. Eight processing parameters can be varied including plasma power, chamber pressure, material speed, and the ratio of gases entering the chamber (Ar:H2:CH4:N2:O2). A plasma diagnostic technique capable of real-time process monitoring has been developed based on optical emission spectroscopy (OES).  A custom R2R CVD system was designed, built and then installed in Birck Nanotechnology Center and made available to users.  Plasma CVD and optical emission simulations have been developed based on electromagnetic, fluid/thermal and plasma chemistry modeling and applied for better process understanding and design. Beyond carbon nanopetals, the modeling framework is applicable to CVD of graphene and diamond coatings for high-temperature extreme hardness requirements and other plasma-based reactors. A statistical approach to scale up graphene production in the R2R RF plasma CVD was developed. Based on statistical surrogate models, the deposited graphene quality is largely influenced by gas pressure, nitrogen, oxygen, and plasma power. A sequential optimization technique was applied to suggest experiments that minimize the uncertainty of the model while increasing the quality of graphene. Moreover, the results from OES suggest correlations of CH species to low defects, while the presence of Ar+, C2, H&alpha;, and O correlate to high defects. The reported approach can be utilized in scaling up other 2D materials and other roll-to-roll manufacturing processes.  The project resulted in new knowledge and methods to characterize, model and optimize plasma-based chemical vapor deposition (CVD) processes for roll-to-roll manufacturing graphitic petals and other carbon nanomaterials. In addition to the development of scalable nanomanufacturing techniques, we have participated in related studies on the mechanics and application of the materials towards (1) understanding the manufactured material characteristics required for function, and (2) creating future manufacturing demand. Such applications include nanopetal-based flexible wire supercapacitors, mechanics of nanoparticle assemblies, scalable functional coatings on graphene and nanopetals, graphene nanoparticle assemblies for thermal applications, and cell culture on nanopetals. Additionally we characterized MEMS device concepts utilizing nanopetal field-emitters for enabling microreactors.   During the development of R2R processes for the continuous production of electroactive carbon films, we identified an opportunity to adapt this method toward the scalable preparation of macroporous thin films, using a laser-based process under dry, ambient conditions and magnetic gold nanoclusters (MGNCs) as etchants. This approach is compatible with continuous manufacturing processes, and offers a potentially low-cost alternative to batch methods based on reactive ion-track etching. A scalable synthesis of MGNCs (dav 100 nm) was developed using aqueous solutions and chemical reagents with low environmental impact. MGNCs were deposited onto thermoplastic roll films (50-75 micron thickness) using a simple gravure process, then exposed to nanosecond laser pulses in the presence of a coaxial magnetic field gradient to produce submicron channels with aspect ratios up to 1000, as characterized by three-dimensional confocal imaging. This dry-etching process can be performed in air and is applicable to a substrates ranging from fluoropolymers to borosilicate glass, with etch rates in excess of 1 microm/s. Finite-element modeling suggests that the absorption of laser pulses by MGNCs produces temperature spikes of nearly 1000 deg C, which can produce photoacoustic responses that drive particles into the medium while being guided by magnetomotive force.  Results of the project have been published and presented in scientific conferences and workshops. This includes 23 articles in peer-reviewed journals and a patent application. Several graduate students completed their PhD dissertations based on this project, and one student participated in entrepreneurship training through NSF/DOD I-Corps.                    Last Modified: 04/01/2019       Submitted by: Alina A Alexeenko]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
