<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Collaborative Research:   Statistical Physics of Fault Behavior - Dynamic Friction, Strain Localization, Comminution, Heat Transfer, and Compaction</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2014</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>230000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>230000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>06030204</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>GEO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>EAR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Earth Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Eva Zanzerkia</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>ezanzerk@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924734</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Earthquakes, landslides, volcanoes, and other natural disasters are costly public reminders that geophysical processes underlying the beauty of landscapes and coastlines are also capable of massive destruction through the sudden release of stored energy. The dynamical instabilities responsible for the onset and ensuing propagation of these events are linked to fundamental physics?friction, fracture, heating, and compaction-- of granular materials subject to extreme geophysical conditions present in earthquake faults, hillsides, and volcanoes. This project aims to develop quantitative, predictive models of granular materials under stress. The physics-based approach enables the project to span scales in a manner that is inaccessible based on previous phenomenological methods. While granular materials are ubiquitous, in both nature and technology, the fundamental physics of these systems is not well understood. Development of a precise, physical description for these materials, motivated by geophysical variables and laboratory observables, will contribute to development of predictive models for natural phenomena, such as earthquakes and landslides, as well as technological processes, including granular flow, transportation, jamming, and packing, that arise in food, pharmaceutical, and construction industries. The incomplete understanding of friction, deformation, and failure in these systems limits progress in manufacturing technologies as well as forecasting natural hazards. Integrating perspectives from mechanics, statistical physics, civil engineering, and geophysics provides a wide range of scientific and educational opportunities, with impact on natural hazards policy and preparedness as well as technical training of the workforce. Central to the project is development of parallel pipelines at the sponsored institutions, aimed at broadening and supporting participation of underrepresented groups in STEM fields. Activities include K-12 outreach, collaboration with local community colleges (Santa Barbara City College and Parkland College in Champaign), and scientific, educational, and professional mentoring of undergraduate and graduate students. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project establishes a quantitative, predictive theoretical framework, based on non-equilibrium statistical thermodynamics, for modeling the influence of grain breakage, temperature variations, and grain shape on the frictional response of sheared gouge layers spanning a wide range of velocities and normal stresses. The theoretical framework is validated by quantitative fits to experimental data on sand and fault gouge obtained in the rock mechanics and geophysics communities. Target investigations include, but are not limited to the following: strain localization patterns (Riedel, boundary, Y-band) at laboratory and fault scales and partitioning of slip between these different modes; dynamics of grain breakage and its role in fault weakening and the evolution of fault zone fabric; effects of thermally-varying material properties and flash processes at the grain scale on transient and steady state frictional response; effect of grain angularity on volume changes and rheology of sheared gouge layers. The project links quantitative physical parameters to phenomenological rate-and-state laws involving porosity, temperature, pore fluid pressure, and friction. Microscopic mechanisms underlying macroscopic dynamic processes, including stick slip, and dynamic triggering will be identified.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/30/2014</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/29/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.050</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1345074</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Jean</FirstName>
<LastName>Carlson</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>M</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Jean M Carlson</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>carlson@physics.ucsb.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>8058938345</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000288345</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/30/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of California-Santa Barbara</Name>
<CityName>Santa Barbara</CityName>
<ZipCode>931062050</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>8058934188</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>Office of Research</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[Rm 3227 Cheadle Hall]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>24</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CA24</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>094878394</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF CALIFORNIA, SANTA BARBARA</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>071549000</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of California-Santa Barbara]]></Name>
<CityName>Santa Barbara</CityName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>931069530</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[6123 Broida]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>24</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CA24</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1574</Code>
<Text>Geophysics</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0114</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0115</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0116</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~77880</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2015~74479</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2016~77641</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>This project established a theoretical and computational framework, based on principles of non-equilibrium statistical thermodynamics, for modeling the influence of grain breakage, temperature variations and grain shape on the frictional response of sheared gouge layers at a wide range of velocities and normal stresses. The framework was validated by developing quantitative fits to experimental data on sand and fault gouge obtained in the rock mechanics community. Advances included analysis of shear band formation and stick slip instabilities, deformation and strength in heterogeneous materials, models of autoacoustic compaction and the implications for stick slip and clock advance and slow slip. This correspondence enabled the investigators to extrapolate their predictions to geophysically-relevant regimes that are presently beyond reach of laboratory experiments, thereby offering experimentalists and field workers insights on what features to explore in their future work. This physics-based approach to constitutive laws bridges the gap between microscopic dynamics and large-scale phenomena such as stick-slip instabilities and dynamic rupture. The dynamic rupture models thus developed possess a predictive capability that the classical phenomenological approaches were otherwise lacking.</p> <p>This project also developed computational methods for complex heterogeneous, multiscale materials. Methods emphasizing the interplay between stress, contact, and connectivity networks characteristic of geo-materials are relevant to wide range of other complex, hierarchical materials. Modeling earthquake ruptures is a complex challenge due to the wide range of spatio-temporal scales contributing to the dynamic instability, ensuing propagation, and slow inter-seismic deformation. New numerical schemes based on efficient domain decomposition, or adaptive mesh refinement, are thus required to address this conundrum of scales and resolve the correct physics. The project developed a hybrid finite element-spectral boundary integral approach with applications to dynamic rupture modeling in unbounded domains. The project also identified mesoscale signatures of material fragility using network models to link structural characteristics with mechanical properties with applications to geo-materials, bio-materials, and bio-inspired materials.</p> <p>This project supported research and education of numerous graduate and undergraduate students, including community college students, who successfully transferred to four-year universities, and later to PhD programs. Members of this project were actively engaged in K-12 outreach and initiatives that target increased diversity in STEM fields. Our project team participated in the UCSB K-12 Physics Circus Outreach Program, the UCSB Women in Physics, and the Santa Barbara City College STEM transfer program. The Physics Circus brings hands on demonstrations of scientific concepts to local classrooms. The Women in Physics group recruits and supports increasing the representation of women in science through a wide variety of professional development events, as well as outreach to schools and colleges. The STEM Transfer Program provides support for community college students to complete associate degree programs and transfer to Universities in STEM fields.&nbsp;</p> <p>Results of this project contribute to our understanding of the physical mechanisms that underlie seismic hazards, including dynamic triggering of seismicity, radiation of seismic waves, and high variability in spatial and temporal patterns of seismicity. Earthquake occurrence is highly variable and uncertain. Insights obtained from the underlying physics reduce this uncertainty, providing sharper constraints on hazards. Additionally, our outreach efforts aim to increase public awareness and preparation, thus increasing public safety and communication during earthquakes.&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 12/06/2018<br>      Modified by: Jean&nbsp;M&nbsp;Carlson</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ This project established a theoretical and computational framework, based on principles of non-equilibrium statistical thermodynamics, for modeling the influence of grain breakage, temperature variations and grain shape on the frictional response of sheared gouge layers at a wide range of velocities and normal stresses. The framework was validated by developing quantitative fits to experimental data on sand and fault gouge obtained in the rock mechanics community. Advances included analysis of shear band formation and stick slip instabilities, deformation and strength in heterogeneous materials, models of autoacoustic compaction and the implications for stick slip and clock advance and slow slip. This correspondence enabled the investigators to extrapolate their predictions to geophysically-relevant regimes that are presently beyond reach of laboratory experiments, thereby offering experimentalists and field workers insights on what features to explore in their future work. This physics-based approach to constitutive laws bridges the gap between microscopic dynamics and large-scale phenomena such as stick-slip instabilities and dynamic rupture. The dynamic rupture models thus developed possess a predictive capability that the classical phenomenological approaches were otherwise lacking.  This project also developed computational methods for complex heterogeneous, multiscale materials. Methods emphasizing the interplay between stress, contact, and connectivity networks characteristic of geo-materials are relevant to wide range of other complex, hierarchical materials. Modeling earthquake ruptures is a complex challenge due to the wide range of spatio-temporal scales contributing to the dynamic instability, ensuing propagation, and slow inter-seismic deformation. New numerical schemes based on efficient domain decomposition, or adaptive mesh refinement, are thus required to address this conundrum of scales and resolve the correct physics. The project developed a hybrid finite element-spectral boundary integral approach with applications to dynamic rupture modeling in unbounded domains. The project also identified mesoscale signatures of material fragility using network models to link structural characteristics with mechanical properties with applications to geo-materials, bio-materials, and bio-inspired materials.  This project supported research and education of numerous graduate and undergraduate students, including community college students, who successfully transferred to four-year universities, and later to PhD programs. Members of this project were actively engaged in K-12 outreach and initiatives that target increased diversity in STEM fields. Our project team participated in the UCSB K-12 Physics Circus Outreach Program, the UCSB Women in Physics, and the Santa Barbara City College STEM transfer program. The Physics Circus brings hands on demonstrations of scientific concepts to local classrooms. The Women in Physics group recruits and supports increasing the representation of women in science through a wide variety of professional development events, as well as outreach to schools and colleges. The STEM Transfer Program provides support for community college students to complete associate degree programs and transfer to Universities in STEM fields.   Results of this project contribute to our understanding of the physical mechanisms that underlie seismic hazards, including dynamic triggering of seismicity, radiation of seismic waves, and high variability in spatial and temporal patterns of seismicity. Earthquake occurrence is highly variable and uncertain. Insights obtained from the underlying physics reduce this uncertainty, providing sharper constraints on hazards. Additionally, our outreach efforts aim to increase public awareness and preparation, thus increasing public safety and communication during earthquakes.           Last Modified: 12/06/2018       Submitted by: Jean M Carlson]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
