<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>An Ideas Lab to Foster Transformative Approaches to Teaching and Learning</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2013</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2016</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>297047.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>297047</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>11090000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>EHR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DRL</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Research On Learning</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Gregg Solomon</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>gesolomo@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032928333</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This project provides the infrastructure, support and facilitation for the EHR Data-Intensive Research to Improve Teaching and Learning - An Ideas Lab to Foster Transformative Approaches to Teaching and Learning. The project secures a venue and coordinates the travel and accommodations for the participants. In addition, the project will help structure the work of the Ideas Lab mentors.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/28/2013</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/28/2013</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.076</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1345385</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Andrew</FirstName>
<LastName>Bernat</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Andrew Bernat</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>abernat@cra.org</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2022662949</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000374812</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/28/2013</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Computing Research Association</Name>
<CityName>Washington</CityName>
<ZipCode>200360000</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2022662949</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1828 L St., NW</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[Suite 800]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>District of Columbia</StateName>
<StateCode>DC</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>00</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>DC00</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>604064386</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>COMPUTING RESEARCH ASSOCIATION, INC.</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Computing Research Association]]></Name>
<CityName>Washington</CityName>
<StateCode>DC</StateCode>
<ZipCode>200365104</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[1828 L St, NW, Suite 800]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>District of Columbia</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>00</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>DC00</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7625</Code>
<Text>REAL</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7556</Code>
<Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7916</Code>
<Text>EAGER</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0413</Code>
<Name>NSF Education &amp; Human Resource</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040106</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2013~297047</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><div class="page" title="Page 6"> <div class="layoutArea"> <div class="column"> <p><span>A confluence of advances in the computer and mathematical sciences has unleashed an unprecedented capability for enabling true evidence-based decision making. The&nbsp;application of data analytics, or techniques of so-called big data, to education&nbsp;needs attention because the resultant data-informed instructional methods offer tremendous&nbsp;</span>promise for transforming education within the U.S., a system under considerable stress. Educational innovations and improvements are greatly hampered by the lack of sufficient quantitative data to properly assess their effectiveness and optimize their use. Understanding how to create and make use of such "big data" offers tremendous promise for transforming education within the U.S.</p> <p>But the collection and use of such data is quite novel within the educational sphere so we need new approaches for the collection, curation and use of these potentially very large data sets. Thus we need new approaches that are difficult to generate via the traditional academic approach to research - that of a single or small group of investigators from one discipline proposing a project focused on their understanding of the issues. We need far more broad-based approaches combining the intellectual contributions across a number of relevant disciplines.</p> <p><span>The workshop sought to foster novel, transformative, multidisciplinary approaches that address the use of large data sets to improve teaching and learning environments. To create the new collaborations desired, the workshop used the Ideas Lab approach which brings together researchers/specialists across a broad spectrum of specialities and creates the environment for truly innovative proposals. A number of innovative ideas were generated over the course of the workshop and a number of these resulted in concrete proposals submitted to NSF.</span></p> </div> </div> </div><br> <p>            Last Modified: 09/01/2016<br>      Modified by: Andrew&nbsp;Bernat</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[    A confluence of advances in the computer and mathematical sciences has unleashed an unprecedented capability for enabling true evidence-based decision making. The application of data analytics, or techniques of so-called big data, to education needs attention because the resultant data-informed instructional methods offer tremendous promise for transforming education within the U.S., a system under considerable stress. Educational innovations and improvements are greatly hampered by the lack of sufficient quantitative data to properly assess their effectiveness and optimize their use. Understanding how to create and make use of such "big data" offers tremendous promise for transforming education within the U.S.  But the collection and use of such data is quite novel within the educational sphere so we need new approaches for the collection, curation and use of these potentially very large data sets. Thus we need new approaches that are difficult to generate via the traditional academic approach to research - that of a single or small group of investigators from one discipline proposing a project focused on their understanding of the issues. We need far more broad-based approaches combining the intellectual contributions across a number of relevant disciplines.  The workshop sought to foster novel, transformative, multidisciplinary approaches that address the use of large data sets to improve teaching and learning environments. To create the new collaborations desired, the workshop used the Ideas Lab approach which brings together researchers/specialists across a broad spectrum of specialities and creates the environment for truly innovative proposals. A number of innovative ideas were generated over the course of the workshop and a number of these resulted in concrete proposals submitted to NSF.          Last Modified: 09/01/2016       Submitted by: Andrew Bernat]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
