<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Climatic and Tectonic Insights from Low-Temperature Thermochronometry Across the Himalayan Rain Shadow, Everest Region, Nepal and Tibet</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>04/01/2014</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>03/31/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>245808.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>245808</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>06030103</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>GEO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>EAR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Earth Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Stephen Harlan</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>sharlan@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927707</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The physiographic transition from the Gangetic Plains to the Tibetan Plateau corresponds in space to one of our planet's most profound climate transitions. Several popular geodynamic models for the late Cenozoic evolution of the Himalaya feature a strong feedback relationship between precipitation, erosional rock exhumation, and deformation. If valid, these models predict that the extreme precipitation gradient across the Himalaya should be accompanied by variations in denudation rate and deformational patterns. Previous studies along the southern Himalayan flank conducted to verify these predictions have had mixed results, partly because they were done along the valleys of major rivers that cut across the Himalaya. These 'Transhimalayan' river valleys serve as pathways for northern penetration of monsoon storms, such that erosion rates on either side of the range crest may not truly reflect potential effects of the rain shadow. In addition, extreme incision of the Transhimalayan rivers during uplift of the Himalaya may focus exhumation and obscure broader patterns related to climate and regional tectonics.  We endeavor to learn more about exhumation patterns across the rain shadow by applying the (Uranium-Thorium)/Helium thermochronometer to rocks collected along a transect that does not follow a Transhimalayan river. Nearly three decades of research in in the Everest region of central Nepal and southern Tibet by several researcher groups has resulted in an unusually good understanding of the basic structural geology of the region, permitting interpretation of the data obtained in appropriate structural context. Our goal is a comprehensive dataset suitable for thermal-kinematic modeling aimed at providing an improved understanding of the coupled influence of precipitation and dynamics of Himalayan orogenic wedge. We are also taking advantage of a portion of the data produced to explore the timing and slip history of the Lhotse and Qomolangma detachments in the Rongbuk Valley north of Mount Everest. These are two of the best studied of all strands of the South Tibetan detachment system, a major tectonic feature in the Himalaya. While the South Tibetan detachment system is known to have been active throughout the Himalaya in Early to Middle Miocene time, the actual age of youngest movement is poorly constrained in most areas, including the Rongbuk Valley. We are providing new constraints on the low-temperature thermal structure of the footwalls of the two detachments here through (Uranium-Thorium)/Helium and fission track work on accessory minerals. Exposures of the detachments in the Rongbuk Valley are unusual: shallow fault dip angles and high relief conspire to provide sampling opportunities over as distance of greater than 35 kilometers in the direction of transport in the immediate footwall of the South Tibetan detachment system. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;While much research focuses on the global impacts of climate variations in space and time, some of the greatest frontiers for research are at smaller, regional scales. On those scales, we are addressing questions about how climate variations relate to other natural earth system processes. Of particular interest for this study is how mountain ranges affect local climate and, conversely, how local climate can influence the erosional history of a mountain range. The high mountain ranges of the Himalaya retard the northward track of the South Asian monsoon system, creating two very different landscapes: the heavily forested slopes of the southern Himalayan flank, which receive some of the highest recorded annual rainfall totals on earth, and the high deserts of the southern Tibetan Plateau.  Our work is aimed at understanding how far back in time this climatic pattern may have extended and how it might cause variations in erosion rate north and south of the Himalayan crest. The lessons learned here will inform perceptions of the role of regional climate variation in the erosional process both in the United States and abroad. The project is supporting a talented female Ph.D. candidate, thereby contributing to on-going efforts to reduce the gender disparity between male and female doctoral level scientists, a problem that is particularly acute in the physical sciences.  In addition, special multimedia displays are being created for public museum exhibitions exploring the science of climate variations in mountainous landscapes.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>03/20/2014</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>02/26/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.050</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1346360</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Kip</FirstName>
<LastName>Hodges</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>V</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Kip V Hodges</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>kvhodges@asu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>4809655331</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000250818</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>03/20/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Arizona State University</Name>
<CityName>TEMPE</CityName>
<ZipCode>852816011</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>4809655479</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>ORSPA</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[660 South Mill Avenue, Suite 310]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Arizona</StateName>
<StateCode>AZ</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>09</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>AZ09</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>943360412</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>ARIZONA STATE UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>806345658</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Arizona State University]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>AZ</StateCode>
<ZipCode>852876004</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Arizona</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>09</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>AZ09</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1572</Code>
<Text>Tectonics</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0114</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0115</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0116</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~91216</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2015~75958</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2016~78634</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>This project was designed to explore long-term relationships between rainfall and erosion across the Himalaya of central Nepal at the longitude of Mount Everest, the highest mountain in the world. The high mountains of the Himalaya create one of the world&rsquo;s most dramatic rain shadows, separating high rainfall regions on the southern flank from arid regions to the north within the Tibetan Plateau. It stands to reason that modern erosion rates on the north and south sides of the Himalaya differ, but an important question for both climate science and tectonics is how long the current pattern of rainfall has persisted. We addressed that question by collecting rock samples along the transect across the Himalaya and determining the isotopic ages of minerals separated from those rocks in the laboratory back in the United States. For each sample, dates for multiple minerals establish the time at which the sample passed through a range of temperatures during erosional exhumation from deeper levels. Numerical modeling of those dates, after making some assumptions about the thermal and physical environment of the samples at different structural levels, permitted us to establish the likely erosional histories of the entire suite. Our work shows that the current pattern of erosion across the range is mimicked by the pattern of erosion (as derived from isotopic dates of minerals from rocks along the transect) on a multi-million-year timescale. This implies that the rain shadow has persisted for at least 2-3 million years. In turn, this finding implies that construction of high mountain ranges through tectonic activity establishes long-term regional variations in climate.&nbsp;&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 10/04/2019<br>      Modified by: Kip&nbsp;V&nbsp;Hodges</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ This project was designed to explore long-term relationships between rainfall and erosion across the Himalaya of central Nepal at the longitude of Mount Everest, the highest mountain in the world. The high mountains of the Himalaya create one of the world?s most dramatic rain shadows, separating high rainfall regions on the southern flank from arid regions to the north within the Tibetan Plateau. It stands to reason that modern erosion rates on the north and south sides of the Himalaya differ, but an important question for both climate science and tectonics is how long the current pattern of rainfall has persisted. We addressed that question by collecting rock samples along the transect across the Himalaya and determining the isotopic ages of minerals separated from those rocks in the laboratory back in the United States. For each sample, dates for multiple minerals establish the time at which the sample passed through a range of temperatures during erosional exhumation from deeper levels. Numerical modeling of those dates, after making some assumptions about the thermal and physical environment of the samples at different structural levels, permitted us to establish the likely erosional histories of the entire suite. Our work shows that the current pattern of erosion across the range is mimicked by the pattern of erosion (as derived from isotopic dates of minerals from rocks along the transect) on a multi-million-year timescale. This implies that the rain shadow has persisted for at least 2-3 million years. In turn, this finding implies that construction of high mountain ranges through tectonic activity establishes long-term regional variations in climate.            Last Modified: 10/04/2019       Submitted by: Kip V Hodges]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
