<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>CAREER: Explicit Methods in Arithmetic Geometry</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2013</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>282209.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>282209</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DMS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>James Matthew Douglass</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>mdouglas@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922467</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The PI proposes to research algorithms for cohomological automorphic forms and the arithmetic of curves parametrized by congruence semi-arithmetic groups.  This proposal interrelates abstract theory and practical computation, linking research with the development of tools and concrete projects which will be integrated into undergraduate and graduate education.  In the first proposed activity, the PI will prove that there exists an algorithm to compute the cohomology of an arithmetic group as a Hecke module.  The PI will implement the proposed algorithm robustly in a computer algebra system, collect and analyze data, and conjecture and prove results based on the discovered phenomena.  In the second activity, the PI will study arithmetic applications of Galois Belyi covers that arise from a modular embedding of a triangle group into a quaternionic unit group.  The PI will investigate questions of modularity, parametrization of elliptic curves, and special points arising from this construction.  The proposed research will allow explicit investigation of the Langlands correspondence--the deep connection between automorphic forms, algebraic groups, and Galois representations--in both classical and novel settings, exploring exciting new ground.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Classical unsolved problems often serve as the genesis for the formulation of a rich and unified mathematical fabric.  Diophantus of Alexandria first sought solutions to algebraic equations in integers almost two thousand years ago.  Today, mathematicians recognize that geometric properties often govern the behavior of arithmetic objects.&lt;br/&gt;Furthermore, computational tools provide a means to test conjectures and can sometimes furnish partial solutions; at the same time, theoretical advances fuel dramatic improvements in computation.  The theory, design, and implementation of algorithms in arithmetic geometry is a burgeoning area, and there are many exciting applications of these methods to diverse fields.  The PI further proposes many specific projects at the undergraduate and graduate level, and the proposed algorithmic tools will be integrated into teaching, training, and learning.  The PI will continue undergraduate outreach, mentoring of undergraduate and graduate students, and expository writing and extensive lectures aimed at communicating high level mathematics to a student audience.  Finally, the PI will design a course on the mathematics of cryptography for teacher leaders who have graduated from the Vermont Mathematics Initiative (VMI)</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>09/24/2013</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/08/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1346894</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>John</FirstName>
<LastName>Voight</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>M</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>John M Voight</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>jvoight@gmail.com</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6127023448</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000256583</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/24/2013</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Dartmouth College</Name>
<CityName>HANOVER</CityName>
<ZipCode>037551421</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6036463007</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>OFFICE OF SPONSORED PROJECTS</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[11 ROPE FERRY RD #6210]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New Hampshire</StateName>
<StateCode>NH</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NH02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>041027822</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>TRUSTEES OF DARTMOUTH COLLEGE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>041027822</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Dartmouth College]]></Name>
<CityName>Hanover</CityName>
<StateCode>NH</StateCode>
<ZipCode>037551404</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[11 Rope Ferry Rd #6210]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New Hampshire</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NH02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1264</Code>
<Text>ALGEBRA,NUMBER THEORY,AND COM</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EPSCoR Co-Funding</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1045</Code>
<Text>CAREER-Faculty Erly Career Dev</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0112</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0114</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0115</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0116</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2012~82209</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~66667</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2015~66667</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2016~66666</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Since the time of Diophantus of Alexandria, mathematicians have sought to understand solutions to algebraic equations in whole and rational numbers, and many fascinating questions remain unanswered.&nbsp; Today, mathematicians recognize that geometric properties often govern the behavior of arithmetic objects.&nbsp; Moreover, the dynamic interplay between experiment, theory, and computation has played a pivotal role in the development of number theory.&nbsp; Computational tools provide a means to test conjectures and can sometimes furnish partial solutions; at the same time, theoretical advances fuel dramatic improvements in computation.</p> <p>To this end, in this project we have pursued research in explicit methods in arithmetic geometry.&nbsp; This proposal interrelated both abstract theory and practical computation, linking research with the development of tools and concrete projects amenable for integration into graduate and undergraduate education.</p> <p>In brief, this project developed algorithms for cohomological automorphic forms on arithmetic groups and studied the arithmetic of curves parametrized by congruence semi-arithmetic groups.&nbsp; The intellectual merit of the proposed research comes from explicit investigation of the Langlands correspondence--the deep connection between automorphic forms, algebraic groups, and Galois representations--in both classical and novel settings.&nbsp;&nbsp;</p> <p>The results of this project have been broadly disseminated: beyond publication in journals, the PI gave extensive lectures aimed at communicating high-level mathematics to a broad audience and authored a graduate textbook on quaternion algebras (http://quatalg.org).&nbsp; This project advanced the training and professional development of several undergraduate and graduate students in creative mathematical research, writing, and explicit computation.&nbsp; Finally, the project enhanced mathematical infrastructure by development of the L-Functions and Modular Forms DataBase (http://www.lmfdb.org), a publicly browsable catalogue of mathematical objects and the connections between them.</p> <p>The theory, design, and implementation of algorithms in arithmetic geometry is a burgeoning area, and there are many exciting applications of these methods to diverse fields.&nbsp; Our investigations have exhibited the tight interplay between theory and computation, and in this project we have pursued several new directions to further develop this exciting field.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 11/27/2018<br>      Modified by: John&nbsp;M&nbsp;Voight</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Since the time of Diophantus of Alexandria, mathematicians have sought to understand solutions to algebraic equations in whole and rational numbers, and many fascinating questions remain unanswered.  Today, mathematicians recognize that geometric properties often govern the behavior of arithmetic objects.  Moreover, the dynamic interplay between experiment, theory, and computation has played a pivotal role in the development of number theory.  Computational tools provide a means to test conjectures and can sometimes furnish partial solutions; at the same time, theoretical advances fuel dramatic improvements in computation.  To this end, in this project we have pursued research in explicit methods in arithmetic geometry.  This proposal interrelated both abstract theory and practical computation, linking research with the development of tools and concrete projects amenable for integration into graduate and undergraduate education.  In brief, this project developed algorithms for cohomological automorphic forms on arithmetic groups and studied the arithmetic of curves parametrized by congruence semi-arithmetic groups.  The intellectual merit of the proposed research comes from explicit investigation of the Langlands correspondence--the deep connection between automorphic forms, algebraic groups, and Galois representations--in both classical and novel settings.    The results of this project have been broadly disseminated: beyond publication in journals, the PI gave extensive lectures aimed at communicating high-level mathematics to a broad audience and authored a graduate textbook on quaternion algebras (http://quatalg.org).  This project advanced the training and professional development of several undergraduate and graduate students in creative mathematical research, writing, and explicit computation.  Finally, the project enhanced mathematical infrastructure by development of the L-Functions and Modular Forms DataBase (http://www.lmfdb.org), a publicly browsable catalogue of mathematical objects and the connections between them.  The theory, design, and implementation of algorithms in arithmetic geometry is a burgeoning area, and there are many exciting applications of these methods to diverse fields.  Our investigations have exhibited the tight interplay between theory and computation, and in this project we have pursued several new directions to further develop this exciting field.          Last Modified: 11/27/2018       Submitted by: John M Voight]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
