<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>CAREER: Survivability and Selfcoexistence in the Battle of Cognitive Radio Network Societies</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2013</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>02/28/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>362113.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>388113</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>05050000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>CSE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CNS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Computer and Network Systems</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Monisha Ghosh</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Dynamic spectrum access (DSA) based on cognitive radio (CR) allows unused licensed bands to be used by unlicensed (secondary) networks in an opportunistic/dynamic manner under the provision that they would vacate upon the return of the licensed users.  DSA allows unlicensed users to share frequencies, but the paradigm does not provide good protection from interference. This raises serious challenge of self-coexistence among the secondary networks as well as risks of disruption from malicious CR devices/networks through various non-traditional spectrum attacks. This project studies the self-coexistence challenges of CR networks under adversarial conditions and investigates inter-disciplinary methodologies based on game theory, behavioral adaptation, stochastic learning and network forensics that aid survivability of these networks. To assess effectiveness, the mechanisms are implemented on CR prototype testbed. The intellectual merit of this project lies in: 1) constructing behavioral frameworks studying the evolutionary dynamics of spectrum conflict, 2) systematically understanding the unique shadow-disruptive nature of the malicious CRs exploiting the finest granularity of spectrum agility, and 3) developing a suite of survival mechanisms against cognitive disruptions and exploring their effectiveness. The project has broader impact on wireless technologies/policies and is expected to help in the efficient and secure design of future cognitive radios. This project is committed to tightly integrate research and educational plans which revolve around student mentoring, graduate/undergraduate curriculum enhancement and hands-on project based learning taking feedback from research findings and K-12 outreach. Research results will be disseminated through publications, seminars, and tutorials.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/29/2013</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>03/23/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.070</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1346600</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Shamik</FirstName>
<LastName>Sengupta</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Shamik Sengupta</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>ssengupta@unr.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>7757846953</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000540898</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/29/2013</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Board of Regents, NSHE, obo University of Nevada, Reno</Name>
<CityName>Reno</CityName>
<ZipCode>895570001</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>7757844040</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1664 North Virginia Street</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[Sponsored Projects / MS 325]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Nevada</StateName>
<StateCode>NV</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NV02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>146515460</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>NEVADA SYSTEM OF HIGHER EDUCATION</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>067808063</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Nevada Reno]]></Name>
<CityName>Reno</CityName>
<StateCode>NV</StateCode>
<ZipCode>895570001</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[1664 North Virginia Street]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Nevada</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NV02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1714</Code>
<Text>Special Projects - CNS</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7363</Code>
<Text>Networking Technology and Syst</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1045</Code>
<Text>CAREER-Faculty Erly Career Dev</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7363</Code>
<Text>RES IN NETWORKING TECH &amp; SYS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9251</Code>
<Text>REU SUPP-Res Exp for Ugrd Supp</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0112</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0113</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0114</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0115</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0116</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2012~54113</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2013~77000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~89000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2015~77000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2016~91000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Cognitive radio networks are envisioned to be autonomous, rational and intelligent through their sensing, learning, self-configuration and adaptation capabilities just like human societies. As the conflict among the cognitive radio networks affect efficient and fair spectrum access, similar to the human behavior, the behavior of cognitive radio nodes also gets affected which can be characterized roughly into two classes: (a) the individual behavior and (b) the societal behavior. In light of the above observations, a major challenge is understanding the fundamental vulnerabilities threatening the coexistence of recently emerging CR network societies and based on this understanding, devising mechanisms such that cognitive radio networks can operate efficiently. To address the unique challenges, we advance ideas from evolutionary behavioral models, game theory, and cognitive radio to optimize decisions under uncertainty.</p> <p>This research work has contributed to studying different aspects of evolutionary dynamics in wireless networking and advance the comprehensive framework of inter-disciplinary systems, e.g., the principles of game theories, microeconomics, social networks, anthropologies to the understanding of evolution of wireless networks, and in general, any communications systems.</p> <p>The "open access" philosophy of the FCC-proposed DSA paradigm also makes cognitive radio networks susceptible to various unforeseen attacks by smart malicious societies. Malicious attacker societies can be one or multiple malicious radios or compromised radio(s) from inside the secondary networks aiming to disrupt the operation of the secondary networks in the DSA networks. To defend against such smart&nbsp; disruptions, it is absolutely critical to understand the uniqueness of the attack models/strategies in exploiting the finest granularity of spectrum agility and the shadow-disruptive nature of the malicious societies.</p> <p>The examination of conflicts present in any network architecture (May it be cognitive, cellular, sensor or ad hoc) can be attributed easily through the game theoretic formalizations and the theory of economics. The wireless networks systems can take advantage of micro and macro economics to understand the behavioral aspects among the rational agents, which can be created easily or refined through techniques from economics principles. The synergy of wireless networking, security, economics and anthropology allow us to provide adaptation at all levels of modern systems and to achieve the necessary vertical integration.</p> <p>The findings of the project has contributed to understand and analyze: (a) Benefits of inter-operability of wireless cognitive radio networks across spectrum bands and geographical regions; (b) Security vulnerabilities and implications; (c) Network availability/survivability and self-coexistence under disruptions; (d) Network reliability over frequency selective, fast fading channels; (e) Spectrum agility and open access flexibility.</p> <p>More specifically, the key impacts have been:</p> <p>1) Presenting a game-theoretic framework where the dynamicity of the environment in this game demands the networks to be dynamic as well. Using the machine learning concept and predictive strategy, the networks were able to learn and change their strategy with changing environmental components achieving system stability at a better rate.</p> <p>2) Presenting a game-theoretic framework for making choices over channels to maximize channel utility in the presence of malicious induced-attacks, which included a closed form solution for optimal CRN strategies for both SU and attacker.</p> <p>3) Devising a stochastic model for defining, estimating, and learning channel utilities.</p> <p>4) Further demonstration that, the evolving nature of the attacker, as well as dynamic and stochastic nature of the wireless medium, pose several challenges to the learning mechanism. Suspicious of being trapped, an attacker may intentionally change its strategy of finding highest impacting communication. Also, due to erroneous and stochastic nature of wireless medium, an attacker may err in sensing CRN&rsquo;s highest impacting connection. Such error may result in an attack on different SU communication instead of the communication with desired/targeted characteristics. Such circumstances must be taken into account for effective luring. In this research, we use statistical monitoring threshold to decide whether the changes in recent attack pattern is due to an error in attacker&rsquo;s sensing or whether the attacker has changed its attacking strategy. Our proposed stochastic learning mechanism correctly detects attacker&rsquo;s strategy with a probability of 0.958 within 15 iterations and identifies a change in attacker&rsquo;s strategy dynamically with 95% confidence interval within five iterations. The simulation results show that CR-Honeynet learns attacker&rsquo;s strategy correctly and adapt to attacker&rsquo;s strategy change dynamically which in effect enhances CRN&rsquo;s performance regarding packet delivery ratio.</p> <p>5) Development of a state-of-the-art testbed using off-the-shelf software defined radios.</p> <p>6) Creation of new cybersecurity programs and courses integrating research materials from this project into the curriculum.</p> <p>7) Training next-generation workforce to use the inter-disciplinary framework, e.g., game theoretic framework to formulate the conflicting environment in distributed and uncoordinated environment.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 04/02/2018<br>      Modified by: Shamik&nbsp;Sengupta</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Cognitive radio networks are envisioned to be autonomous, rational and intelligent through their sensing, learning, self-configuration and adaptation capabilities just like human societies. As the conflict among the cognitive radio networks affect efficient and fair spectrum access, similar to the human behavior, the behavior of cognitive radio nodes also gets affected which can be characterized roughly into two classes: (a) the individual behavior and (b) the societal behavior. In light of the above observations, a major challenge is understanding the fundamental vulnerabilities threatening the coexistence of recently emerging CR network societies and based on this understanding, devising mechanisms such that cognitive radio networks can operate efficiently. To address the unique challenges, we advance ideas from evolutionary behavioral models, game theory, and cognitive radio to optimize decisions under uncertainty.  This research work has contributed to studying different aspects of evolutionary dynamics in wireless networking and advance the comprehensive framework of inter-disciplinary systems, e.g., the principles of game theories, microeconomics, social networks, anthropologies to the understanding of evolution of wireless networks, and in general, any communications systems.  The "open access" philosophy of the FCC-proposed DSA paradigm also makes cognitive radio networks susceptible to various unforeseen attacks by smart malicious societies. Malicious attacker societies can be one or multiple malicious radios or compromised radio(s) from inside the secondary networks aiming to disrupt the operation of the secondary networks in the DSA networks. To defend against such smart  disruptions, it is absolutely critical to understand the uniqueness of the attack models/strategies in exploiting the finest granularity of spectrum agility and the shadow-disruptive nature of the malicious societies.  The examination of conflicts present in any network architecture (May it be cognitive, cellular, sensor or ad hoc) can be attributed easily through the game theoretic formalizations and the theory of economics. The wireless networks systems can take advantage of micro and macro economics to understand the behavioral aspects among the rational agents, which can be created easily or refined through techniques from economics principles. The synergy of wireless networking, security, economics and anthropology allow us to provide adaptation at all levels of modern systems and to achieve the necessary vertical integration.  The findings of the project has contributed to understand and analyze: (a) Benefits of inter-operability of wireless cognitive radio networks across spectrum bands and geographical regions; (b) Security vulnerabilities and implications; (c) Network availability/survivability and self-coexistence under disruptions; (d) Network reliability over frequency selective, fast fading channels; (e) Spectrum agility and open access flexibility.  More specifically, the key impacts have been:  1) Presenting a game-theoretic framework where the dynamicity of the environment in this game demands the networks to be dynamic as well. Using the machine learning concept and predictive strategy, the networks were able to learn and change their strategy with changing environmental components achieving system stability at a better rate.  2) Presenting a game-theoretic framework for making choices over channels to maximize channel utility in the presence of malicious induced-attacks, which included a closed form solution for optimal CRN strategies for both SU and attacker.  3) Devising a stochastic model for defining, estimating, and learning channel utilities.  4) Further demonstration that, the evolving nature of the attacker, as well as dynamic and stochastic nature of the wireless medium, pose several challenges to the learning mechanism. Suspicious of being trapped, an attacker may intentionally change its strategy of finding highest impacting communication. Also, due to erroneous and stochastic nature of wireless medium, an attacker may err in sensing CRN?s highest impacting connection. Such error may result in an attack on different SU communication instead of the communication with desired/targeted characteristics. Such circumstances must be taken into account for effective luring. In this research, we use statistical monitoring threshold to decide whether the changes in recent attack pattern is due to an error in attacker?s sensing or whether the attacker has changed its attacking strategy. Our proposed stochastic learning mechanism correctly detects attacker?s strategy with a probability of 0.958 within 15 iterations and identifies a change in attacker?s strategy dynamically with 95% confidence interval within five iterations. The simulation results show that CR-Honeynet learns attacker?s strategy correctly and adapt to attacker?s strategy change dynamically which in effect enhances CRN?s performance regarding packet delivery ratio.  5) Development of a state-of-the-art testbed using off-the-shelf software defined radios.  6) Creation of new cybersecurity programs and courses integrating research materials from this project into the curriculum.  7) Training next-generation workforce to use the inter-disciplinary framework, e.g., game theoretic framework to formulate the conflicting environment in distributed and uncoordinated environment.       Last Modified: 04/02/2018       Submitted by: Shamik Sengupta]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
