<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>STTR Phase I:  Eco-Friendly Mass Production of Highly Conductive Graphene Sheets with Controlled Structures</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>01/01/2014</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2014</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>225000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>225000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07070000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>IIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Industrial Innovation &amp; Partnersh</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Rajesh Mehta</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>rmehta@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922174</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This Small Business Technology Transfer (STTR) Phase I project aims to develop an efficient, rapid, and eco-friendly approach for mass production of highly conductive solution phase graphene with controlled structures. Most of the commercial available solution phase conductive graphene sheets are either highly defective reduced graphene oxide (r-GO) or non-defective pristine graphene sheets. They are either dispersed in special organic solvents or aqueous solutions with the help of surfactants for stabilization. Most of the production processes involve toxic chemicals or release toxic substances as byproducts, causing potential hazard to our environment. The study of novel green microwave oxidation chemistries proposed in this project will lead to rapid (tens of seconds), direct (without requirement for post reduction), and low cost fabrication of highly conductive, clean (without requirement for surfactants and stabilizers), and low oxygen containing graphene sheets with controlled lateral dimensions and molecular structures. The success of the project will leads to a series of new graphene products which are different from both rGO and pristine graphene sheets while combining many of their merits and can be used for the research society to fabricate highly conductive graphene sheets with tailored structures for best fit a broad spectrum of applications.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The broader impact/commercial potential of this project is the great potential to enable cost effective mass production of highly conductive graphene sheets with unique molecular structures and controllable sizes. Given the known wide potential application of graphene in energy generation and storage, catalysts, electronics, coating, sensors, etc, the commercial available of these graphene sheets with well-defined structures will speed up the scientific understanding and technological developments in these broad areas. This project could also greatly benefit our society with the environment friendly and low energy consumption approach for the mass production of these materials.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>12/11/2013</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>12/11/2013</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1346496</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Yongqiang</FirstName>
<LastName>Wang</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>A</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Yongqiang A Wang</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>awang@oceannanotech.com</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>8586898808</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000346918</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>12/11/2013</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Huixin</FirstName>
<LastName>He</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Huixin He</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>huixinhe@newark.rutgers.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>9733531254</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000484380</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>12/11/2013</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Ocean NanoTech, LLC</Name>
<CityName>Springdale</CityName>
<ZipCode>727646050</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>4797515500</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>2143 Worth Lane</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Arkansas</StateName>
<StateCode>AR</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>AR03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>155516987</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>OCEAN NANO TECH LLC</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Rutgers University at Newark]]></Name>
<CityName>Newark</CityName>
<StateCode>NJ</StateCode>
<ZipCode>071021811</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[73 Warren Street]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New Jersey</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>10</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NJ10</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1505</Code>
<Text>STTR Phase I</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>084E</Code>
<Text>NANOMANUFACTURING</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1084</Code>
<Text>NANOTECHNOLOGY INITIATIVE</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1505</Code>
<Text>STTR PHASE I</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8029</Code>
<Text>Manufacturing</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0114</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~225000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><strong><em>Challenges:</em></strong> Graphene, as a unique two-dimensional perfect structure of monolayer carbon atoms packed into a dense honeycomb crystal, has attracted great interest due to its diverse and fascinating properties. In view of its high surface area to mass ratio (2600 m<sup>2</sup>/g), superior charge-carrier mobility (2 &times; 10<sup>5</sup> cm<sup>2</sup>/V s), excellent tensile strength of 130GPa, and thermal conductivity of (4.84~5.30) &times; 10<sup>3</sup> W/m&middot;K, graphene holds great potential for a wide range of applications, such as conductive film, renewable energy production, energy storage, sensor as well as biomedicines. During the past ten years, the research in graphene has proceeded from the initial phase of developing myriad strategies for the synthesis of graphene sheets to the commercial application of graphene in various research fields. Mass production of reduced graphene oxide and graphene nanoplatelets has recently been achieved. However, it is still challenging to controllably produce solution processable highly conductive graphene sheets in large quantity, at low cost, via an eco-friendly and energy saving process. More importantly, most of the commercially available solution processable graphene sheets were fabricated via a long multiple-step process (several hours to 5 days). Finally, majority of the approaches involved and/or generated metal ion containing and other toxic compounds, which pose a potential hazard to our environment if not handled properly.</p> <p><strong><em>Project Outcomes: </em></strong>We have successfully developed<strong><em> </em></strong>an eco-friendly and microwave chemistry to enable rapid production of highly conductive as well as &ldquo;clean&rdquo; solution-phase graphene sheets with controlled lateral size from tens of micrometers to tens of nanometers. We also developed a microwave chemistry to enable one-pot, one-step rapid fabrication of graphene oxide with controlled holey structures. Afterwards, in order to achieve mass production of highly conductive graphene sheets, we developed a continuous flow microwave system to produce the graphene which is a very simple, rapid, and low energy-consuming approach in large scale.&nbsp; In addition, we utilized solvothermal reaction to hybridize highly crystalline graphene with various -metal and metal oxide nanocrystals (NCs) including:&nbsp; metal Pt and Pd, alloys (PtPd and PtCo) as well as transition metal oxide (Fe<sub>3</sub>O<sub>4</sub> and Mn<sub>3</sub>O<sub>4</sub>) NCs.</p> <p><strong><em>Intellectual Merit:</em></strong> The conductivity of exfoliated graphene reaches as high as 791,615 S/m, greatly enabling the very promising applications in commercial printed electronics, conductive coatings and composite fillers. These exfoliated conductive graphene sheets could also be used to produce high-performance graphene hybrid devices, advance the field of graphene-based nanotechnology tremendously. Our novel method not only simplifies the scalable production of conductive graphene via continuous microwave flow system, but also reduces the environmental impact at both the front end and back end of the process. We eliminate the need to add surfactants and stabilizers using our modified &ldquo;Thermal Expansion--Liquid Exfoliation&rdquo; process. In addition, our novel process does not produce any heavy metal waste, toxic product, further neutralizing any environmental impact as well as eliminating the cost of waste/toxic material collection and treatment.</p> <p><strong><em>Broader Impact:</em></strong> These specific highly conductive graphene are especially promising for applications in printed electronics, conductive coatings, lithium ion batteries, methanol oxidation fuel cells, proton exchange membrane, supercapacitor electrode, as well as gas sensors. The research findings have been disseminated broadly through high-impact jour...]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Challenges: Graphene, as a unique two-dimensional perfect structure of monolayer carbon atoms packed into a dense honeycomb crystal, has attracted great interest due to its diverse and fascinating properties. In view of its high surface area to mass ratio (2600 m2/g), superior charge-carrier mobility (2 &times; 105 cm2/V s), excellent tensile strength of 130GPa, and thermal conductivity of (4.84~5.30) &times; 103 W/m&middot;K, graphene holds great potential for a wide range of applications, such as conductive film, renewable energy production, energy storage, sensor as well as biomedicines. During the past ten years, the research in graphene has proceeded from the initial phase of developing myriad strategies for the synthesis of graphene sheets to the commercial application of graphene in various research fields. Mass production of reduced graphene oxide and graphene nanoplatelets has recently been achieved. However, it is still challenging to controllably produce solution processable highly conductive graphene sheets in large quantity, at low cost, via an eco-friendly and energy saving process. More importantly, most of the commercially available solution processable graphene sheets were fabricated via a long multiple-step process (several hours to 5 days). Finally, majority of the approaches involved and/or generated metal ion containing and other toxic compounds, which pose a potential hazard to our environment if not handled properly.  Project Outcomes: We have successfully developed an eco-friendly and microwave chemistry to enable rapid production of highly conductive as well as "clean" solution-phase graphene sheets with controlled lateral size from tens of micrometers to tens of nanometers. We also developed a microwave chemistry to enable one-pot, one-step rapid fabrication of graphene oxide with controlled holey structures. Afterwards, in order to achieve mass production of highly conductive graphene sheets, we developed a continuous flow microwave system to produce the graphene which is a very simple, rapid, and low energy-consuming approach in large scale.  In addition, we utilized solvothermal reaction to hybridize highly crystalline graphene with various -metal and metal oxide nanocrystals (NCs) including:  metal Pt and Pd, alloys (PtPd and PtCo) as well as transition metal oxide (Fe3O4 and Mn3O4) NCs.  Intellectual Merit: The conductivity of exfoliated graphene reaches as high as 791,615 S/m, greatly enabling the very promising applications in commercial printed electronics, conductive coatings and composite fillers. These exfoliated conductive graphene sheets could also be used to produce high-performance graphene hybrid devices, advance the field of graphene-based nanotechnology tremendously. Our novel method not only simplifies the scalable production of conductive graphene via continuous microwave flow system, but also reduces the environmental impact at both the front end and back end of the process. We eliminate the need to add surfactants and stabilizers using our modified "Thermal Expansion--Liquid Exfoliation" process. In addition, our novel process does not produce any heavy metal waste, toxic product, further neutralizing any environmental impact as well as eliminating the cost of waste/toxic material collection and treatment.  Broader Impact: These specific highly conductive graphene are especially promising for applications in printed electronics, conductive coatings, lithium ion batteries, methanol oxidation fuel cells, proton exchange membrane, supercapacitor electrode, as well as gas sensors. The research findings have been disseminated broadly through high-impact journal publications, national/international conference presentations, workshops, seminars, and the PIsÆ websites, ensuring that this technology will be widely examined and built upon by ourselves and other researchers.           Last Modified: 03/31/2015       Submitted by: Yongqiang A Wang]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
