<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Continuing Outreach Activities at ASLO Meetings to Assist Ocean Scientists</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>01/15/2014</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2016</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>48640.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>48640</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>06040100</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>GEO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>OCE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Ocean Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Elizabeth Rom</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>elrom@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927709</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Scientists are increasingly called upon by the public, media, and policymakers to explain their science, yet training on how to do this effectively is hard to come by. This award to the University of Delaware provides funding for a set of workshops that will help scientists become better communicators. The workshops will be held at the American Society for Limnology and Oceanography (ASLO) winter conference, one of the largest conferences for marine scientists, in 2014 and 2015. The proposed workshops will provide training to scientists on a variety of communication skills, including the production of short science videos and communication to the general public. Planned workshop events for the February 2014 meeting include 1) a Video Workshop that provides advice to help scientists create videos that maintain accurate science and are interesting and compelling to a broad audience, 2) two half-day workshops on Science Communication - one for graduate students and one for all meeting participants, 3) a Science Communication workshop for about 24 participants to focus on their specific science communication issues, and 4) a Panel Discussion on public communication as part of the mid-morning plenary talks.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>01/03/2014</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>01/03/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.050</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1347503</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Jonathan</FirstName>
<LastName>Sharp</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>H</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Jonathan H Sharp</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>jsharp@udel.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>3026454259</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000195282</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>01/03/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Delaware</Name>
<CityName>Newark</CityName>
<ZipCode>197160099</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>3028312136</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>210 Hullihen Hall</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Delaware</StateName>
<StateCode>DE</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>00</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>DE00</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>059007500</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF DELAWARE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>059007500</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Delaware]]></Name>
<CityName>Lewes</CityName>
<StateCode>DE</StateCode>
<ZipCode>199581298</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[700 Pilottown Rd]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Delaware</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>00</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>DE00</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1690</Code>
<Text>EDUCATION/HUMAN RESOURCES,OCE</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0114</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~48640</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Close to 98% of knowledgeable environmental scientists conclude that there are serious pressing problems with global climate change and that the major cause is human activities. Yet, about 50% of the American public is either skeptical or dismissive of this situation. What is going on here?</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>WHEN SCIENTISTS SPEAK...NOBODY LISTENS. Environmental scientists are not very successful in conveying to the public the gravity of environmental problems. Because of a critical need for the public and elected officials to be more knowledgeable of and concerned about global environmental problems, I have worked for several years on efforts to better understand this disconnect and to train scientists to improve their communication abilities. The efforts for the 2014, 2015, and 2016 meetings were supported by this grant; earlier meeting workshops were supported by previous NSF grants or meeting funds.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>WE NEED TO MAKE SCIENTISTS &ldquo;LISTENABLE&rdquo;. Every two years, the largest assembly of international ocean scientists occurs as the Ocean Sciences Meeting (OSM), jointly sponsored by the Association for the Sciences of Limnology and Oceanography (ASLO), the American Geophysical Union, and The Oceanography Society. In the intervening odd-numbered years, ASLO holds the winter Aquatic Sciences Meeting (ASM), drawing a smaller but similar crowd. At these meetings, I have brought expertise from Hollywood to address outreach activities. The scientific community understands the environment but needs help from the entertainment community that understands how to get public interest.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>BRINGING HOLLYWOOD TO THE SCIENTISTS. Increasing numbers of scientists are making short videos for their web pages and open houses to explain their science to lay audiences. Recognizing the lack of knowledge on how to make interesting videos, Randy Olson, as a PhD Marine Biologist, gave up a tenured faculty position and became an independent filmmaker in Hollywood. At the 2010 OSM, we organized a video analysis workshop, solicited videos from scientists and then discussed and critiqued them at the meeting. At the 2011, 2012, and 2013, we organized a similar video analysis workshops. At the 2012 and 2013 meetings, we used a panel approach with Dorie Barton (actress and story line consultant for movie screenwriters) and Brian Palermo (actor and instructor at the Groundlings Improv Theater in Los Angeles) along with Olson. &nbsp;We discontinued the video workshops for the next few meetings and are starting them again in 2017.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>MORE THAN JUST VIDEOS. We felt that scientists needed better communication skills in all aspects of their work in outreach to the public, policy makers, the press, and presenting at scientific conferences. With this in mind, we added two additional Hollywood events for the 2013 meeting. The first was an all day workshop titled &ldquo;Scintillation &ndash; a workshop to make your science communication scintillate through &ldquo;critical storytelling&rdquo;. The participants were asked to bring a brief story to the workshop. They initially presented their stories, they then worked on improv exercises and studied storyline development; at the end of the workshop their reworked stories were much improved as 40-60 second short discourses that explained science in simple, compelling, and interesting form. The other workshop was titled &ldquo;Snap it up &ndash; advice from Hollywood for short presentations&rdquo;. It was aimed at the presentations given by scientists to each other at these meetings, to make them more interdisciplinary. We selected several presentations being given on the first day of the meeting and had the Hollywood team attend the talks. At the workshop, the team gave critiques of the presentations and discussed with the presenters and the audience how to make the presentations more interesting to a broad audience of their peers. &nbsp;We also held this Sunday workshop (now retitled, &ldquo;Connection&rdquo;) and the Snap-it Up workshops at the 2014, 2015, and 2016 meetings. For the 2014 meeting, Olson was again our communications expert.&nbsp; At the 2015 and 2016 meeting, Palermo was our communications expert, assisted by me, and Adrienne Sponberg (ASLO Director of Communications and Science).</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>ALSO, SCIENTISTS NEED TO BETTER UNDERSTAND THE DISCONNECT. In addition to the Hollywood efforts, I organized panel discussions at the 2014 and 2015 meetings to make participants aware of the need for more effective communication. In 2014, the panel titled: &ldquo;Why aren&rsquo;t they listening?&rdquo; was moderated by Richard Harris (NPR science correspondent) with panelists Edward Maibach (Center for Climate Change Communication, George Mason University), Jerry Schubel (President of the Aquarium of the Pacific), and Christine O&rsquo;Connell (Workshop coordinator of Alan Alda Center for Communicating Science, SUNY). In 2015, the panel was titled: &ldquo;What can you do, and should not do to inform the public about environmental problems&rdquo;. The moderator was Montserrat Dominquez, Director of the Spanish office of the Huffington Post.&nbsp; The panelists were Daniel Conley (Professor of Biogeochemistry, Lund University, Sweden), Carlos Duarte (Professor of Biological and Environmental Science and Engineering, King Abdullah University of Science and Technology, Saudi Arabia), and me.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 01/25/2017<br>      Modified by: Jonathan&nbsp;H&nbsp;Sharp</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Close to 98% of knowledgeable environmental scientists conclude that there are serious pressing problems with global climate change and that the major cause is human activities. Yet, about 50% of the American public is either skeptical or dismissive of this situation. What is going on here?     WHEN SCIENTISTS SPEAK...NOBODY LISTENS. Environmental scientists are not very successful in conveying to the public the gravity of environmental problems. Because of a critical need for the public and elected officials to be more knowledgeable of and concerned about global environmental problems, I have worked for several years on efforts to better understand this disconnect and to train scientists to improve their communication abilities. The efforts for the 2014, 2015, and 2016 meetings were supported by this grant; earlier meeting workshops were supported by previous NSF grants or meeting funds.     WE NEED TO MAKE SCIENTISTS "LISTENABLE". Every two years, the largest assembly of international ocean scientists occurs as the Ocean Sciences Meeting (OSM), jointly sponsored by the Association for the Sciences of Limnology and Oceanography (ASLO), the American Geophysical Union, and The Oceanography Society. In the intervening odd-numbered years, ASLO holds the winter Aquatic Sciences Meeting (ASM), drawing a smaller but similar crowd. At these meetings, I have brought expertise from Hollywood to address outreach activities. The scientific community understands the environment but needs help from the entertainment community that understands how to get public interest.     BRINGING HOLLYWOOD TO THE SCIENTISTS. Increasing numbers of scientists are making short videos for their web pages and open houses to explain their science to lay audiences. Recognizing the lack of knowledge on how to make interesting videos, Randy Olson, as a PhD Marine Biologist, gave up a tenured faculty position and became an independent filmmaker in Hollywood. At the 2010 OSM, we organized a video analysis workshop, solicited videos from scientists and then discussed and critiqued them at the meeting. At the 2011, 2012, and 2013, we organized a similar video analysis workshops. At the 2012 and 2013 meetings, we used a panel approach with Dorie Barton (actress and story line consultant for movie screenwriters) and Brian Palermo (actor and instructor at the Groundlings Improv Theater in Los Angeles) along with Olson.  We discontinued the video workshops for the next few meetings and are starting them again in 2017.     MORE THAN JUST VIDEOS. We felt that scientists needed better communication skills in all aspects of their work in outreach to the public, policy makers, the press, and presenting at scientific conferences. With this in mind, we added two additional Hollywood events for the 2013 meeting. The first was an all day workshop titled "Scintillation &ndash; a workshop to make your science communication scintillate through "critical storytelling". The participants were asked to bring a brief story to the workshop. They initially presented their stories, they then worked on improv exercises and studied storyline development; at the end of the workshop their reworked stories were much improved as 40-60 second short discourses that explained science in simple, compelling, and interesting form. The other workshop was titled "Snap it up &ndash; advice from Hollywood for short presentations". It was aimed at the presentations given by scientists to each other at these meetings, to make them more interdisciplinary. We selected several presentations being given on the first day of the meeting and had the Hollywood team attend the talks. At the workshop, the team gave critiques of the presentations and discussed with the presenters and the audience how to make the presentations more interesting to a broad audience of their peers.  We also held this Sunday workshop (now retitled, "Connection") and the Snap-it Up workshops at the 2014, 2015, and 2016 meetings. For the 2014 meeting, Olson was again our communications expert.  At the 2015 and 2016 meeting, Palermo was our communications expert, assisted by me, and Adrienne Sponberg (ASLO Director of Communications and Science).     ALSO, SCIENTISTS NEED TO BETTER UNDERSTAND THE DISCONNECT. In addition to the Hollywood efforts, I organized panel discussions at the 2014 and 2015 meetings to make participants aware of the need for more effective communication. In 2014, the panel titled: "Why aren?t they listening?" was moderated by Richard Harris (NPR science correspondent) with panelists Edward Maibach (Center for Climate Change Communication, George Mason University), Jerry Schubel (President of the Aquarium of the Pacific), and Christine O?Connell (Workshop coordinator of Alan Alda Center for Communicating Science, SUNY). In 2015, the panel was titled: "What can you do, and should not do to inform the public about environmental problems". The moderator was Montserrat Dominquez, Director of the Spanish office of the Huffington Post.  The panelists were Daniel Conley (Professor of Biogeochemistry, Lund University, Sweden), Carlos Duarte (Professor of Biological and Environmental Science and Engineering, King Abdullah University of Science and Technology, Saudi Arabia), and me.          Last Modified: 01/25/2017       Submitted by: Jonathan H Sharp]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
