<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>EAGER: A Logic-Based Security Framework for Wired and Mobile Perimeter</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>10/01/2013</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>09/30/2016</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>150000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>150000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>05050000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>CSE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CNS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Computer and Network Systems</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Ralph Wachter</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>rwachter@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032928950</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Mobile (wireless) communication has become an essential information exchange platform for today's enterprise and government organizations. They need to secure mobile devices as they secure wired devices. Today, it is common for these organizations to have multiple external mobile and wireless connections to the outside world to provide high bandwidth and tolerate connection failures. One way to protect the network perimeter is to use border gateways that impose a uniform static policy on network traffic (wired and wireless) entering through its borders and by installing effective security schemes and policies on mobile devices itself. While being simple, such a static policy has many disadvantages and may not provide necessary protection to mobile and wired perimeter. They are (a) unable to react to changes in its external environment, (b) they have physical limitations and differences in trust relationships, and (c) completeness among a non- communicating set of policies is problematic. Therefore, in order to provide perimeter protection policies that react to dynamic changes (quite frequent in mobile perimeter) and respect organizational objectives such as preferential treatment, yet enforce overall security objectives of organizations, requires that individual policies enforced at each border gateway be (a) dynamic and flexible, and (b) be a part of a global policy such that taken together enforce common security objectives in mobile infrastructure. In this proposal we achieve this by a logic-based security framework. Our solution has the potential to improve the security while reducing the management costs.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>09/12/2013</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>09/12/2013</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.070</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1347958</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Vijay</FirstName>
<LastName>Kumar</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Vijay Kumar</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>kumarv@umkc.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>8162352366</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000270068</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/12/2013</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Missouri-Kansas City</Name>
<CityName>Kansas City</CityName>
<ZipCode>641102499</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>8162355839</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>5100 Rockhill Road</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Missouri</StateName>
<StateCode>MO</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MO05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>010989619</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF MISSOURI SYSTEM</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>006326904</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Missouri-Kansas City]]></Name>
<CityName>Kansas City</CityName>
<StateCode>MO</StateCode>
<ZipCode>641102499</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[5100 Rockhill Road]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Missouri</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MO05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>8060</Code>
<Text>Secure &amp;Trustworthy Cyberspace</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7434</Code>
<Text>CNCI</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7916</Code>
<Text>EAGER</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0113</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2013~150000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The security requirements of every organization, small or big, frequently change as a result of its internal reorganization and its business dynamics. In multi-national organization's environment, every branch has its own security policies based on its specific security requirements, type of information, information processing systems, location based compliance requirements, etc. These policies are defined and installed in firewalls to stop undesirable packets. Updating firewall policies is still, more or less, manual where new policies are inserted by security staff. As branches of multinational organizations span across the globe, managing firewall policies at every branch and ensuring their compliance and consistency is quite complex. Misconfiguration of even a single firewall policy at any branch may create security risk to the organization in terms of financial loss and reputation.</p> <p>We developed a framework to enforce firewall policy management of multi-national organizations. As discussed in the proposal, the first outcome of our research work is the introduction of automation in policy management in a distributed firewall setup. Every branch of an organization has a perimeter firewall which is managed by a centralized controller called global policy manager in our scheme. As a part of automation of policy management, we identified the necessity of location-based compliance policies and developed hierarchical structure to represent them based on the geo-location of the organizational branch.</p> <p>The second outcome of our research work is the design of innovative temporal policies. We discovered that inclusion of time-based policies to the standard firewall policies causes additional overhead in terms of storage and processing time. We developed an innovative and efficient method for composing time-based policies which includes compact representation of temporal policies using bit representation and detection of anomalies using set operations. Our method of creating policy sets based on days of the week significantly reduces the storage and processing time of time-based policies.</p> <p>The third outcome of our research work is the identification of high cyber-crime locations. The cyber-attacks often originate from specific locations. To mitigate the risks from these location-based attacks, firewalls are required to block the traffic from high cyber-crime locations. We developed an algorithm to identify and categorize the attack locations as (a) high unsafe, (b) medium unsafe and (c) low unsafe locations based on the frequency of the attacks.</p> <p>The fourth outcome is the logic-based language to specify organizational, location-based, group and local policies. It also includes the predicates to resolve the conflicts with the various policy categories. We discovered that the processing of conflict resolution using predicate language is more efficient.</p> <p>We developed prototype and tools to test the above outcomes. We used synthesized datasets to drive the prototype and analyzed the results to validate the correctness of our framework. We published one research paper in IEEE Cloud Computing and published and presented our works in Mobile Data Management 2015 and in COMPSAC 2016 conferences. We were invited to presented invited talks of our works at 2016 MasterCard Cybercon conference, St. Louis, Missouri and at 2015 Army workshop on cybersecurity, Miami, Florida.</p> <p>Our research work complements our existing graduate course &ldquo;Information Security and Assurance&rdquo; at University of Missouri &ndash; Kansas City. We developed a number of tools as a part of this project. We are using them in this course to demonstrate firewall policy management in distributed network. As a result of this project, we setup a security lab in collaboration with University of Missouri, St. Louis campus for our students to do their semester long security projects and lab assignments.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 11/30/2016<br>      Modified by: Vijay&nbsp;Kumar</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The security requirements of every organization, small or big, frequently change as a result of its internal reorganization and its business dynamics. In multi-national organization's environment, every branch has its own security policies based on its specific security requirements, type of information, information processing systems, location based compliance requirements, etc. These policies are defined and installed in firewalls to stop undesirable packets. Updating firewall policies is still, more or less, manual where new policies are inserted by security staff. As branches of multinational organizations span across the globe, managing firewall policies at every branch and ensuring their compliance and consistency is quite complex. Misconfiguration of even a single firewall policy at any branch may create security risk to the organization in terms of financial loss and reputation.  We developed a framework to enforce firewall policy management of multi-national organizations. As discussed in the proposal, the first outcome of our research work is the introduction of automation in policy management in a distributed firewall setup. Every branch of an organization has a perimeter firewall which is managed by a centralized controller called global policy manager in our scheme. As a part of automation of policy management, we identified the necessity of location-based compliance policies and developed hierarchical structure to represent them based on the geo-location of the organizational branch.  The second outcome of our research work is the design of innovative temporal policies. We discovered that inclusion of time-based policies to the standard firewall policies causes additional overhead in terms of storage and processing time. We developed an innovative and efficient method for composing time-based policies which includes compact representation of temporal policies using bit representation and detection of anomalies using set operations. Our method of creating policy sets based on days of the week significantly reduces the storage and processing time of time-based policies.  The third outcome of our research work is the identification of high cyber-crime locations. The cyber-attacks often originate from specific locations. To mitigate the risks from these location-based attacks, firewalls are required to block the traffic from high cyber-crime locations. We developed an algorithm to identify and categorize the attack locations as (a) high unsafe, (b) medium unsafe and (c) low unsafe locations based on the frequency of the attacks.  The fourth outcome is the logic-based language to specify organizational, location-based, group and local policies. It also includes the predicates to resolve the conflicts with the various policy categories. We discovered that the processing of conflict resolution using predicate language is more efficient.  We developed prototype and tools to test the above outcomes. We used synthesized datasets to drive the prototype and analyzed the results to validate the correctness of our framework. We published one research paper in IEEE Cloud Computing and published and presented our works in Mobile Data Management 2015 and in COMPSAC 2016 conferences. We were invited to presented invited talks of our works at 2016 MasterCard Cybercon conference, St. Louis, Missouri and at 2015 Army workshop on cybersecurity, Miami, Florida.  Our research work complements our existing graduate course "Information Security and Assurance" at University of Missouri &ndash; Kansas City. We developed a number of tools as a part of this project. We are using them in this course to demonstrate firewall policy management in distributed network. As a result of this project, we setup a security lab in collaboration with University of Missouri, St. Louis campus for our students to do their semester long security projects and lab assignments.          Last Modified: 11/30/2016       Submitted by: Vijay Kumar]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
