<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Connections:  STEM Educational Research Communities and Knowledge Transfer</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/15/2014</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>547561.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>564921</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>11090000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>EHR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DRL</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Research On Learning</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Finbarr Sloane</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>fsloane@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032928465</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This project, conducted by Search Technology, Inc., and Georgia Institute of Technology, will seek to better understand how research ideas are communicated in science, technology, engineering and mathematics (STEM) education.  The project will use bibliometric analysis to study patterns in how research publications cite each other, mapping the flow of ideas within STEM education research as well as cognitive science research.  This project will help show what are the key influences on STEM education research, and what makes STEM education research influential.  This project will aim to help the STEM education research community develop and make better use of its research base, and work effectively with researchers from other fields.  The Division of Research on Learning in the Education and Human Resources directorate supports this work as part of its mission to advance STEM education research, including research on STEM learning. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The first stage of the project will involve analyzing data bases covering a broad range of published research, examining patterns of citation.  The second stage will focus on the influential report, How People Learn, published by the National Research Council, and include textual analysis of content.  The third stage will involve outreach to the research community.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/14/2014</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/18/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.076</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1348765</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Jan</FirstName>
<LastName>Youtie</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Jan Youtie</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>jan.youtie@innovate.gatech.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>4048946111</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000342944</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/14/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Alan</FirstName>
<LastName>Porter</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>L</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Alan L Porter</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>aporter@searchtech.com</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>7704411457</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000545566</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/14/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Search Technology Inc</Name>
<CityName>Peachtree Corners</CityName>
<ZipCode>300923328</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>7704411457</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>6025 The Corners Parkway</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[STE 202]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Georgia</StateName>
<StateCode>GA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>GA07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>066923632</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>SEARCH TECHNOLOGY, INC.</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Search Technology Inc]]></Name>
<CityName>Norcross</CityName>
<StateCode>GA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>300923328</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[6025 The Corners Parkway]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Georgia</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>GA07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7625</Code>
<Text>REAL</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7980</Code>
<Text>ECR-EHR Core Research</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9251</Code>
<Text>REU SUPP-Res Exp for Ugrd Supp</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0414</Code>
<Name>NSF Education &amp; Human Resource</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040106</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0415</Code>
<Name>NSF Education &amp; Human Resource</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040106</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0416</Code>
<Name>NSF Education &amp; Human Resource</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040106</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~171995</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2015~234767</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2016~158159</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><span style="font-family: Calibri; font-size: small;">The driving research question for this project is:&nbsp; How much do researchers in each of the sciences of learning -- Education Research, Cognitive Science, and related Border Fields -- draw on the research literatures of the others?&nbsp; In particular, we ask if Education Researchers increasingly connect with Cognitive Science research?&nbsp;</span></p> <p><span style="font-family: Calibri; font-size: small;">To address these issues, we analyzed 32,121 abstract records drawn from the Web of Science. &nbsp;This dataset consists of papers published in 177 journals identified with Education Research, Cognitive Science (including several Psychology sub-fields), or Border Fields (e.g., Educational Psychology) in 1994, 1999, 2004, 2009, and 2014.&nbsp; For analysis of citation connections among papers in these fields, the team captured 1,372,984 references cited by the 32,121 papers, and information on 446,280 papers that, in turn, cite them.</span></p> <p><span style="font-family: Calibri;"><span style="font-size: small;">A separate project component analyzed 1641 papers citing the National Academies Report, <em>How People Learn </em>(HPL).&nbsp; HPL sought to advance the flow of knowledge about Cognitive Science findings into the Education Research community.&nbsp; To understand how Education Research, Cognitive Science, and other fields drew on the report, we linked the citations to specific content in the report. &nbsp;</span></span></p> <p><span style="font-family: Calibri; font-size: small;">So in both cases, we compile three generations of data:&nbsp; scholarly output (papers); and looking back, the literature resources that those papers cite; and looking forward, the papers that cite them.</span></p> <p><span style="text-decoration: underline;"><span style="font-family: Calibri; font-size: small;">Intellectual Merit</span></span></p> <p><span style="font-family: Calibri; font-size: small;">The extent to which papers cite different fields is based on counts of citation frequencies.&nbsp; This project developed a new metric, Knowledge MEDiators (KMEDs), to measure the extent to which a paper Aggregates by drawing substantially from both fields under scrutiny, Bridges by citing one field substantially and being substantially cited by the other field, or Diffuses by being substantially cited by both fields) research knowledge.&nbsp;</span></p> <p><span style="font-family: Calibri;"><span style="font-size: small;">Project findings show that the percentage of Education Research papers that extensively cite (25% or more of their sources) from Cognitive Science literature has increased since the 1990s, but the reverse is not so.&nbsp; Border Fields extensively cite, and are cited by, both Education Research and Cognitive Science. They offer a notable bridge connecting those fields. &nbsp;</span></span></p> <p><span style="font-family: Calibri; font-size: small;">A key challenge has been to classify references into the fields of interest. Some references are relatively straightforward to classify because they are indexed by Web of Science.&nbsp; Other cited literatures, especially unpublished reports, are more difficult. &nbsp;An automated classifier was developed to categorize these non-indexed sources into the three fields of interest. &nbsp;Education Research is especially strongly represented in the literature not indexed by Web of Science, making it important to include that literature to understand research knowledge interchanges.</span></p> <p><span style="font-family: Calibri; font-size: small;">Our examination of <em>How People Learn</em> (HPL), finds it to be highly multidisciplinary, based on its diverse references.&nbsp; In terms of its influence, HPL is cited widely across disciplines, notably in Medical/Health, Engineering, and other Discipline-Based Education Research fields.&nbsp; However, probing more deeply, we find publications more likely to refer to concepts in HPL already prevalent in their disciplinary literature.</span></p> <p><span style="text-decoration: underline;"><span style="font-family: Calibri; font-size: small;">Broader Impacts</span></span></p> <p><span style="font-family: Calibri; font-size: small;">The National Science Foundation (NSF), National Institute of Education, McDonnell Foundation, and others had determined that it would be desirable to strengthen connections between those doing research in Education and in Cognitive Science.&nbsp; This seems a vital step to accrue benefits of what is being learned about learning from multiple perspectives.&nbsp; Our findings lend support that connections among these sciences of learning have gotten stronger since several initiatives about the year 2000 took aim at that objective, e.g., through NSF funding programs and HPL publication.</span></p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 11/07/2018<br>      Modified by: Alan&nbsp;L&nbsp;Porter</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The driving research question for this project is:  How much do researchers in each of the sciences of learning -- Education Research, Cognitive Science, and related Border Fields -- draw on the research literatures of the others?  In particular, we ask if Education Researchers increasingly connect with Cognitive Science research?   To address these issues, we analyzed 32,121 abstract records drawn from the Web of Science.  This dataset consists of papers published in 177 journals identified with Education Research, Cognitive Science (including several Psychology sub-fields), or Border Fields (e.g., Educational Psychology) in 1994, 1999, 2004, 2009, and 2014.  For analysis of citation connections among papers in these fields, the team captured 1,372,984 references cited by the 32,121 papers, and information on 446,280 papers that, in turn, cite them.  A separate project component analyzed 1641 papers citing the National Academies Report, How People Learn (HPL).  HPL sought to advance the flow of knowledge about Cognitive Science findings into the Education Research community.  To understand how Education Research, Cognitive Science, and other fields drew on the report, we linked the citations to specific content in the report.    So in both cases, we compile three generations of data:  scholarly output (papers); and looking back, the literature resources that those papers cite; and looking forward, the papers that cite them.  Intellectual Merit  The extent to which papers cite different fields is based on counts of citation frequencies.  This project developed a new metric, Knowledge MEDiators (KMEDs), to measure the extent to which a paper Aggregates by drawing substantially from both fields under scrutiny, Bridges by citing one field substantially and being substantially cited by the other field, or Diffuses by being substantially cited by both fields) research knowledge.   Project findings show that the percentage of Education Research papers that extensively cite (25% or more of their sources) from Cognitive Science literature has increased since the 1990s, but the reverse is not so.  Border Fields extensively cite, and are cited by, both Education Research and Cognitive Science. They offer a notable bridge connecting those fields.    A key challenge has been to classify references into the fields of interest. Some references are relatively straightforward to classify because they are indexed by Web of Science.  Other cited literatures, especially unpublished reports, are more difficult.  An automated classifier was developed to categorize these non-indexed sources into the three fields of interest.  Education Research is especially strongly represented in the literature not indexed by Web of Science, making it important to include that literature to understand research knowledge interchanges.  Our examination of How People Learn (HPL), finds it to be highly multidisciplinary, based on its diverse references.  In terms of its influence, HPL is cited widely across disciplines, notably in Medical/Health, Engineering, and other Discipline-Based Education Research fields.  However, probing more deeply, we find publications more likely to refer to concepts in HPL already prevalent in their disciplinary literature.  Broader Impacts  The National Science Foundation (NSF), National Institute of Education, McDonnell Foundation, and others had determined that it would be desirable to strengthen connections between those doing research in Education and in Cognitive Science.  This seems a vital step to accrue benefits of what is being learned about learning from multiple perspectives.  Our findings lend support that connections among these sciences of learning have gotten stronger since several initiatives about the year 2000 took aim at that objective, e.g., through NSF funding programs and HPL publication.       Last Modified: 11/07/2018       Submitted by: Alan L Porter]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
