<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Collaborative Research: STEM Education Effects on a Diverse Workforce's Development over the Life Cycle</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>10/01/2013</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>09/30/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>257245.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>257245</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>11060000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>EHR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>HRD</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Human Resource Development</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Mark Leddy</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>mleddy@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924655</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This collaborative study is investigating how the STEM skills and training that individuals from underrepresented groups acquired during high school and postsecondary education have contributed to their STEM workforce success and the types of occupations they now enjoy in midlife.  It is uses the High School &amp; Beyond (HS&amp;B) database, a nationally representative study of high school sophomores from 1980.  HS&amp;B contains a large sample of African Americans and Latinos, women, and people with disabilities, including those who earned postsecondary degrees, to provide information about how our education system has and can prepare diverse students to fully participate in a complex and rapidly changing workforce, even during middle and later adulthood.   &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The project has the following three aims:&lt;br/&gt;1. Identifying the aspects of STEM training in schools, from specific coursework to degree attainment and field of degree, that contribute to workforce success and flexibility during early adulthood and in later midlife work.  &lt;br/&gt;Research Question: Which STEM skills and training have high labor market value in (i) early and (ii) middle to late careers?&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;2. Analyzing whether the relationship between STEM training and workforce success is the same for all workers, and if not, how it differs for women and men, African Americans, Latinos, and Whites, and for persons with and without disabilities.&lt;br/&gt;Research Question: Do the relationships between skills and the labor market generalize to underrepresented groups?&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;3. Producing a database, that will be released through NCES, on HS&amp;B sample members' occupations that can be used by the broader research community to generate new knowledge on workforce development and broadening participation in STEM.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>09/04/2013</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>09/04/2013</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.076</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1348557</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>John</FirstName>
<LastName>Warren</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>R</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>John R Warren</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>warre046@umn.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6126242310</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000231635</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/04/2013</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Minnesota-Twin Cities</Name>
<CityName>Minneapolis</CityName>
<ZipCode>554552070</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6126245599</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>200 OAK ST SE</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Minnesota</StateName>
<StateCode>MN</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MN05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>555917996</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>REGENTS OF THE UNIVERSITY OF MINNESOTA</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>117178941</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Minnesota Population Center]]></Name>
<CityName>Minneapolis</CityName>
<StateCode>MN</StateCode>
<ZipCode>554550428</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[50 Willey Hall, 225 19th Ave. So]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Minnesota</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MN05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7980</Code>
<Text>ECR-EHR Core Research</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1515</Code>
<Text>MINORITY GRADUATE EDUC ACTIVIT</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1545</Code>
<Text>RES IN DISABILITIES ED</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8212</Code>
<Text>Broaden Particip STEM Resrch</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9178</Code>
<Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0413</Code>
<Name>NSF Education &amp; Human Resource</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040106</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2013~257245</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>We have found that aspects of the high school experience?especially the math and science courses that students took-- affect students throughout their life course and into midlife. Our midlife outcomes range from educational achievement (both postsecondary and later life training), physical and mental health, disability status, body weight, labor market (occupations, including STEM occupations, skills demanded in occupations, employment/unemployment), and financial stability. We have modeled these outcomes later in life with a rich set of indicators of educational opportunity and course-taking (particularly mathematics, science, and computer programming course-taking), educational stratification, school effects, as well as non-cognitive skills.&nbsp;&nbsp;</p> <p>Some of the more notable outcomes/findings include:</p> <p>- Individuals? skills in adolescence are protective against work disability at midlife. People who had higher math achievement test scores and a greater sense of personal control when they left high school are less likely to be out of the labor force due to disability over thirty years later. These findings suggest that skills do not simply sort students into higher education and occupations that protect against work disability; they may also enable people to adapt to their circumstances and maintain an attachment to the workforce as they age.</p> <p>- Taking college preparatory math coursework in high school protects women from bad occupations and jobs over thirty years later, even when they do not attain a bachelor?s degree.</p> <p>- African American women have higher prestige and skill than African American men in midlife but not in early career. These results add to the literature by showing the importance of gender in understanding racial stratification, and pointing out possible analytical convergence of occupational prestige and analytical skill.</p> <p>- Students who took a medium to high-level course of study in high school have better self-reported health and physical functioning in midlife, even net of family background, adolescent health, baseline skills, and school characteristics. The association partially operates through pathways into postsecondary education.</p> <p>- Returns to high school mathematics course-taking and test scores on midlife obesity that vary according to students? demographic attributes and operate partially through postsecondary pathways.</p> <p>- All else constant, educational attainment is predictive of accidental (less education, more accidents) and ?other? causes of death; math test scores are predictive (protective against) of death from heart disease; and lower level math coursework is predictive of suicidal death. None are predictive of death from homicide or cancer.&nbsp;</p> <p>- Key findings on disparities in course-taking by race/ethnicity, family background, gender, disability status and immigrant status, and the effects of curricular differentiation on school and non-school outcomes. We additionally note measurement issues within curriculum research and implications for policy, practice and social inequality.</p> <p>- Individuals who only took low levels of math and those who didn?t increase their civic knowledge during high school are less likely to vote in midlife in both presidential and midterm elections, compared to those who took higher-level math and who increased their civics knowledge in high school. These relationships hold while controlling on family background, base year math and civics knowledge, civic engagement during high school, and degree attainment in early adulthood.</p> <p>- Students with teachers who believed they were going to go to college, were working up to their potential, were self-disciplined and liked school are more likely to vote in midlife, even conditioning on students? family background, skills, civic participation in high school, course-taking, and educational attainment.</p> <p>- Post-educational trajectories predict differential midlife health among Blacks as compared to whites.</p> <p>- Many dimensions of education are associated with young adult mortality, and some?high school students? math course taking and non-cognitive skills?affect mortality net of educational attainment.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <div id="_mcePaste" class="mcePaste" style="position: absolute; left: -10000px; top: 0px; width: 1px; height: 1px; overflow: hidden;"></div><br> <p>            Last Modified: 04/20/2019<br>      Modified by: John&nbsp;R&nbsp;Warren</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ We have found that aspects of the high school experience?especially the math and science courses that students took-- affect students throughout their life course and into midlife. Our midlife outcomes range from educational achievement (both postsecondary and later life training), physical and mental health, disability status, body weight, labor market (occupations, including STEM occupations, skills demanded in occupations, employment/unemployment), and financial stability. We have modeled these outcomes later in life with a rich set of indicators of educational opportunity and course-taking (particularly mathematics, science, and computer programming course-taking), educational stratification, school effects, as well as non-cognitive skills.    Some of the more notable outcomes/findings include:  - Individuals? skills in adolescence are protective against work disability at midlife. People who had higher math achievement test scores and a greater sense of personal control when they left high school are less likely to be out of the labor force due to disability over thirty years later. These findings suggest that skills do not simply sort students into higher education and occupations that protect against work disability; they may also enable people to adapt to their circumstances and maintain an attachment to the workforce as they age.  - Taking college preparatory math coursework in high school protects women from bad occupations and jobs over thirty years later, even when they do not attain a bachelor?s degree.  - African American women have higher prestige and skill than African American men in midlife but not in early career. These results add to the literature by showing the importance of gender in understanding racial stratification, and pointing out possible analytical convergence of occupational prestige and analytical skill.  - Students who took a medium to high-level course of study in high school have better self-reported health and physical functioning in midlife, even net of family background, adolescent health, baseline skills, and school characteristics. The association partially operates through pathways into postsecondary education.  - Returns to high school mathematics course-taking and test scores on midlife obesity that vary according to students? demographic attributes and operate partially through postsecondary pathways.  - All else constant, educational attainment is predictive of accidental (less education, more accidents) and ?other? causes of death; math test scores are predictive (protective against) of death from heart disease; and lower level math coursework is predictive of suicidal death. None are predictive of death from homicide or cancer.   - Key findings on disparities in course-taking by race/ethnicity, family background, gender, disability status and immigrant status, and the effects of curricular differentiation on school and non-school outcomes. We additionally note measurement issues within curriculum research and implications for policy, practice and social inequality.  - Individuals who only took low levels of math and those who didn?t increase their civic knowledge during high school are less likely to vote in midlife in both presidential and midterm elections, compared to those who took higher-level math and who increased their civics knowledge in high school. These relationships hold while controlling on family background, base year math and civics knowledge, civic engagement during high school, and degree attainment in early adulthood.  - Students with teachers who believed they were going to go to college, were working up to their potential, were self-disciplined and liked school are more likely to vote in midlife, even conditioning on students? family background, skills, civic participation in high school, course-taking, and educational attainment.  - Post-educational trajectories predict differential midlife health among Blacks as compared to whites.  - Many dimensions of education are associated with young adult mortality, and some?high school students? math course taking and non-cognitive skills?affect mortality net of educational attainment.           Last Modified: 04/20/2019       Submitted by: John R Warren]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
