<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>ARI-MA: Investigation of Structure Property Relationships in Metallic Actinide Alloys to Enable Forensic Analysis</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>10/01/2013</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>09/30/2015</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>221675.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>221675</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07010000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>ECCS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Electrical, Commun &amp; Cyber Sys</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Kenneth Hicks</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This research program will develop atomistic and microstructural models of the structure-property-processing relationships in actinide metals and alloys (U, Pu alloys). The project focuses its attention on metallic actinide alloys that are relevant to nuclear forensics.  Metallic forms are the final forms of the actinide before use in a weapon.  By developing these microstructure and atomistic models, we aim to understand how the microstructure evolves under processing such as casting and rolling for the alloys.  This understanding provides the forensic scientist a capability to trace the provenance of such special nuclear materials should they be interdicted in the alloy form. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project will train graduate students and involve undergraduates in research experiences through Georgia Tech Summer Undergraduate Research Experience and broaden participation of under-represented groups, for example, by recruiting students from minority serving institutions.  It will by establish collaborations with researchers in INL and PNNL where graduate students will interact directly with researchers. Significant faculty involvement, participation by underrepresented minorities, and active learning distinguish the education and outreach component of this project.  The outreach program is especially important in the case of a topic where the general public is not conversant with the science such as actinide chemistry and metallurgy.  This program will educate a new generation of undergraduate and graduate students on actinide chemistry and metallurgy and provide resources to K-12 students to become interested and conversant in the actinide sciences while enhancing national security by providing a means to improve nuclear forensics science.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>09/11/2013</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>09/11/2013</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1348222</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Hamid</FirstName>
<LastName>Garmestani</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Hamid Garmestani</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>hamid.garmestani@mse.gatech.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>4043854495</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000265052</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/11/2013</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Chaitanya</FirstName>
<LastName>Deo</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>S</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Chaitanya S Deo</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>chaitanya.deo@nre.gatech.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>4043850866</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000503896</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/11/2013</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Georgia Tech Research Corporation</Name>
<CityName>Atlanta</CityName>
<ZipCode>303320420</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>4048944819</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>Office of Sponsored Programs</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Georgia</StateName>
<StateCode>GA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>GA05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>097394084</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>GEORGIA TECH RESEARCH CORPORATION</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>097394084</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Georgia Institute of Technology]]></Name>
<CityName>Atlanta</CityName>
<StateCode>GA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>303320002</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[225 North Ave NW]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Georgia</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>GA05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>M576</Code>
<Text/>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7707</Code>
<Text>NSF/DHS ACADEMIC RES INITIAT</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0113</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2013~221675</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><ul> <li>The National Technical Nuclear Forensics community is interested in advancements in separations or analyses of nuclear or radioactive materials that result in improvements in the speed, accuracy, and precision of determining the physical, chemical, radiological, micro-structural and/or morphological qualities of materials [Domestic Nuclear Detection Office-National Science Foundation Academic Research Initiative]. </li> <li>Microstructural analysis of interdicted U alloys may suggest processing paths leading to the establishment of the provenance of interdicted nuclear materials. </li> <li>Derivation of the process path functions of thermo-mechanical processing of materials provides robust computational means to analyze the microstructural evolutions[H.J. Bunge, Texture analysis in materials science. <em>Butterworth Press</em>, 1982].</li> <li>To derive the process path functions, a distribution functions (e.g. orientation distribution function of crystallites) is expanded by finite series; where the evolution of the microstructure can be captured by the change of the series terms due to thermo-mechanical processing[H. Garmestani et al.&nbsp; <em>Acta Mater. </em>55(2007) 647-654]. </li> <li>This work focuses on using the Zr-Nb system as a surrogate for U-Nb alloys where experimental studies are difficult and costly to implement. </li> <li>The first objective of this work is to experimentally capture the microstructural evolutions in cold and hot rolling .</li> <li>The second objective of this work is to computationally capture the microstructural evolutions caused by thermo-mechanical processing by means of descriptor coefficients of series terms, therefore process path path functions can be obtained. </li> <li>Analysis of XRD data showed that the high temperature bcc phase (&beta;-Nb) was retained at room temperature.</li> <li>Analysis of EBSD patterns showed differences between the grain structure, phase structure, and texture of unrolled, hot rolled, and cold rolled samples. </li> <li>The orientation distribution functions were expanded in spectral form in order to obtain microstructure descriptor coefficients.</li> <li>The initial microstructure hull was plotted which demonstrates the differences between the as-cast and hot and cold rolled materials. </li> <li>The EAM and MEAM potentials are able to give insight into experimental properties and phenomena as well as provide some mechanical properties for which there is no experimental data. </li> <li>Twinning depends on directional bonding &ndash; difficult to discern twinning from phase transformation.</li> <li>Homo-interphase shows significant atomic reorganization near interface</li> <li>Heterophase highly unstable at temperature and is very sensitive to simulation methods.</li> </ul> <ul> <li>Process Path Functions in Rolling and Heat Treating of Meta-Stable Cubic Zr-18Nb Alloy, Ali&nbsp; Tabei, Richard&nbsp; Hoffman III, <span style="text-decoration: underline;">Chaitanya&nbsp; Deo</span>, Hamid&nbsp; Garmestani, Materials Research Society Spring Meeting, San Francisco, CA, April 2015 (<em>the poster presented at MRS Spring symposium received an award for  best poster in that session (Wednesday night session April 8, 2015)</em></li> <li>Undergraduate students from underrepresented communities were included in the project as summer students in summer 2013 and 2014 through the SUmmer Undergraduate Research Experience program.&nbsp; PI conducted workshops at elementary schools to describe basic atomic physics</li> </ul><br> <p>            Last Modified: 12/09/2015<br>      Modified by: Chaitanya&nbsp;S&nbsp;Deo</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The National Technical Nuclear Forensics community is interested in advancements in separations or analyses of nuclear or radioactive materials that result in improvements in the speed, accuracy, and precision of determining the physical, chemical, radiological, micro-structural and/or morphological qualities of materials [Domestic Nuclear Detection Office-National Science Foundation Academic Research Initiative].  Microstructural analysis of interdicted U alloys may suggest processing paths leading to the establishment of the provenance of interdicted nuclear materials.  Derivation of the process path functions of thermo-mechanical processing of materials provides robust computational means to analyze the microstructural evolutions[H.J. Bunge, Texture analysis in materials science. Butterworth Press, 1982]. To derive the process path functions, a distribution functions (e.g. orientation distribution function of crystallites) is expanded by finite series; where the evolution of the microstructure can be captured by the change of the series terms due to thermo-mechanical processing[H. Garmestani et al.  Acta Mater. 55(2007) 647-654].  This work focuses on using the Zr-Nb system as a surrogate for U-Nb alloys where experimental studies are difficult and costly to implement.  The first objective of this work is to experimentally capture the microstructural evolutions in cold and hot rolling . The second objective of this work is to computationally capture the microstructural evolutions caused by thermo-mechanical processing by means of descriptor coefficients of series terms, therefore process path path functions can be obtained.  Analysis of XRD data showed that the high temperature bcc phase (&beta;-Nb) was retained at room temperature. Analysis of EBSD patterns showed differences between the grain structure, phase structure, and texture of unrolled, hot rolled, and cold rolled samples.  The orientation distribution functions were expanded in spectral form in order to obtain microstructure descriptor coefficients. The initial microstructure hull was plotted which demonstrates the differences between the as-cast and hot and cold rolled materials.  The EAM and MEAM potentials are able to give insight into experimental properties and phenomena as well as provide some mechanical properties for which there is no experimental data.  Twinning depends on directional bonding &ndash; difficult to discern twinning from phase transformation. Homo-interphase shows significant atomic reorganization near interface Heterophase highly unstable at temperature and is very sensitive to simulation methods.   Process Path Functions in Rolling and Heat Treating of Meta-Stable Cubic Zr-18Nb Alloy, Ali  Tabei, Richard  Hoffman III, Chaitanya  Deo, Hamid  Garmestani, Materials Research Society Spring Meeting, San Francisco, CA, April 2015 (the poster presented at MRS Spring symposium received an award for  best poster in that session (Wednesday night session April 8, 2015) Undergraduate students from underrepresented communities were included in the project as summer students in summer 2013 and 2014 through the SUmmer Undergraduate Research Experience program.  PI conducted workshops at elementary schools to describe basic atomic physics        Last Modified: 12/09/2015       Submitted by: Chaitanya S Deo]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
