<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>CSBR: Natural History: Launching the University of Vermont Natural History Museum Step One: Securing the Collections</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>06/01/2014</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>471072.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>471072</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>08080000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>BIO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DBI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Biological Infrastructure</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Reed Beaman</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>rsbeaman@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927163</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The University of Vermont Natural History Museum (UVM) collections are a valuable resource for researchers throughout the world because of their worldwide geographic scope and long history of collecting specimens. By far the largest in the state, they serve as the State of Vermont's official archive for documentation of its flora and fauna.  The reorganization of the collections will expand its access to a wide array of people, including UVM undergraduate and graduate students, researchers, citizen scientists, and local volunteers. Outreach efforts will attract K-12 groups interested in learning about biodiversity and conservation through hands-on use of the specimens. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This investment into UVM's natural history collections will help to improve specimen storage conditions, enhancing pest control strategies and reduce the chance of damage from fire and flood. The targeted collection houses over 660,000 specimens of plants, arthropods and mammals. While the specimens are being secured, curators and students will systematically reorganize them to reflect contemporary taxonomic classification.  Also, the plant and arthropod digitization program will be expanded to fully represent the collections and make specimen images and related data available to researchers and educators. Additional information about the collection and its scientific and educational missions is publicly available on the museum's website: http://www.uvm.edu/~uvmnhm/.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>05/20/2014</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/20/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.074</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1349205</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>David</FirstName>
<LastName>Barrington</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>S</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>David S Barrington</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>dbarring@zoo.uvm.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>8026560431</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000098895</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/20/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>C</FirstName>
<LastName>Kilpatrick</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>W</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>C W Kilpatrick</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>wkilpatr@uvm.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>8026560453</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000373914</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/20/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Ingi</FirstName>
<LastName>Agnarsson</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Ingi Agnarsson</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>iagnarsson@gmail.com</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>8026560460</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000530419</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/20/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Vermont &amp; State Agricultural College</Name>
<CityName>Burlington</CityName>
<ZipCode>054050160</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>8026563660</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>85 South Prospect Street</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Vermont</StateName>
<StateCode>VT</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>00</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>VT00</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>066811191</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF VERMONT &amp; STATE AGRICULTURAL COLLEGE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>066811191</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Vermont & State Agricultural College]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>VT</StateCode>
<ZipCode>054051737</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Vermont</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>00</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>VT00</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1197</Code>
<Text>BIOLOGICAL RESEARCH COLLECTION</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9178</Code>
<Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9179</Code>
<Text>GRADUATE INVOLVEMENT</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0114</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~471072</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The general goal of this project has&nbsp;been twofold: first to secure the natural history collections at the University of Vermont Natural History Museum with the installation of new cabinets to replace the array of insecure and unsound cabinets in place at the outset, and second to dramatically expand our previous work towards making the collections available as data and images on the worldwide web. We were also committed to involving students, scholars, and citizen scientists in the utilization and enhancement of the University of Vermont Natural History Museum as a way of making as many people as possible aware of the value and utility of these collections.</p> <p>The University of Vermont Natural History Museum includes three collections, a plant collection in the Pringle Herbarium and both vertebrate (most bird and mammal) and invertebrate (mostly insect and spider) collections in the Zadock Thompson Collection. All of these collections were dramatically improved by the funding from this grant.&nbsp; The installation of our collections in state-of-the-art storage cabinets substantially increased the security of the collections. &nbsp;This security was instrumental to the survival of the entire collection in spite of a major fire in Torrey Hall, the building housing them. The water used in extinguishing the fire flooding the entire building, compromising the electrical system, the sheetrock and floor coverings, but so fortunately not the collections. We were able to complete the tasks we set out to do with a one-year extension to the grant. This work was done by a cast of dozens, mostly undergraduate students at the University, who moved the plants and animals from cabinet to cabinet to establish the new order and did the hard work of making images and entering data for digitization of each one of the roughly 600,000 collections in our museum.</p> <p>Our collections, now secure, will be permanently available to scholars and specialists in systematics and conservation as a result.&nbsp; Enthusiasm for the collections and for contributing to the them is already evident in our communication with local specialists as well as regional natural history museums. Our activities with the collections have the potential to provide research and teaching resources to the University, the State, and beyond, most especially in the areas of regional&nbsp; history, the historical role of plants and animals in human culture, and among the broader community of biological and physical scientists in need of sources of material for documentation of genetic variation. The reorganization of the collections in the current classifications, as well as the digitization activities, will make our collections much more accessible to the biodiversity and systematics community throughout the world. The realization of a Natural History Museum, which was the conceptual basis for this granted activity, will yield a permanent new institution that will add substantively to the teaching and research resources available to the University of Vermont and the State of Vermont.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 09/07/2018<br>      Modified by: David&nbsp;S&nbsp;Barrington</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Images (<span id="selectedPhoto0">1</span> of <span class="totalNumber"></span>)           </div> <div class="galControls" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1349205/1349205_10304070_1536353487814_movingday--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1349205/1349205_10304070_1536353487814_movingday--rgov-800width.jpg" title="movingday"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1349205/1349205_10304070_1536353487814_movingday--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="movingday"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Moving day: new cabinets right, old left.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Michael Sundue</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Royalty-free (unrestricted use)</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">David&nbsp;S&nbsp;Barrington</div> <div class="imageTitle">movingday</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1349205/1349205_10304070_1536353681931_frostfungi--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1349205/1349205_10304070_1536353681931_frostfungi--rgov-800width.jpg" title="frostfungi"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1349205/1349205_10304070_1536353681931_frostfungi--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="frostfungi"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Fern and Audrey enter data for the Charles Frost mushroom collection</div> <div class="imageCredit">David Barrington</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Royalty-free (unrestricted use)</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">David&nbsp;S&nbsp;Barrington</div> <div class="imageTitle">frostfungi</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1349205/1349205_10304070_1536353776124_zamirabutterflies--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1349205/1349205_10304070_1536353776124_zamirabutterflies--rgov-800width.jpg" title="zamirabutterflies"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1349205/1349205_10304070_1536353776124_zamirabutterflies--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="zamirabutterflies"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Zamira works with the butterfly collection</div> <div class="imageCredit">David Barrington</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">David&nbsp;S&nbsp;Barrington</div> <div class="imageTitle">zamirabutterflies</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The general goal of this project has been twofold: first to secure the natural history collections at the University of Vermont Natural History Museum with the installation of new cabinets to replace the array of insecure and unsound cabinets in place at the outset, and second to dramatically expand our previous work towards making the collections available as data and images on the worldwide web. We were also committed to involving students, scholars, and citizen scientists in the utilization and enhancement of the University of Vermont Natural History Museum as a way of making as many people as possible aware of the value and utility of these collections.  The University of Vermont Natural History Museum includes three collections, a plant collection in the Pringle Herbarium and both vertebrate (most bird and mammal) and invertebrate (mostly insect and spider) collections in the Zadock Thompson Collection. All of these collections were dramatically improved by the funding from this grant.  The installation of our collections in state-of-the-art storage cabinets substantially increased the security of the collections.  This security was instrumental to the survival of the entire collection in spite of a major fire in Torrey Hall, the building housing them. The water used in extinguishing the fire flooding the entire building, compromising the electrical system, the sheetrock and floor coverings, but so fortunately not the collections. We were able to complete the tasks we set out to do with a one-year extension to the grant. This work was done by a cast of dozens, mostly undergraduate students at the University, who moved the plants and animals from cabinet to cabinet to establish the new order and did the hard work of making images and entering data for digitization of each one of the roughly 600,000 collections in our museum.  Our collections, now secure, will be permanently available to scholars and specialists in systematics and conservation as a result.  Enthusiasm for the collections and for contributing to the them is already evident in our communication with local specialists as well as regional natural history museums. Our activities with the collections have the potential to provide research and teaching resources to the University, the State, and beyond, most especially in the areas of regional  history, the historical role of plants and animals in human culture, and among the broader community of biological and physical scientists in need of sources of material for documentation of genetic variation. The reorganization of the collections in the current classifications, as well as the digitization activities, will make our collections much more accessible to the biodiversity and systematics community throughout the world. The realization of a Natural History Museum, which was the conceptual basis for this granted activity, will yield a permanent new institution that will add substantively to the teaching and research resources available to the University of Vermont and the State of Vermont.       Last Modified: 09/07/2018       Submitted by: David S Barrington]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
