<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>CSBR: Natural History: Uncrowding, rehousing, and digitization of the non-federal fossil vertebrate collection at the Denver Museum of Nature &amp; Science</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>06/01/2014</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>449999.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>449999</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>08080000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>BIO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DBI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Biological Infrastructure</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Reed Beaman</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>rsbeaman@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927163</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This project proposes to secure and digitize a collection of fossils at the Denver Museum of Nature &amp; Science (DMNS), accommodating their use as part of the strong suite research and outreach activities at that institution. The fossil vertebrate collection will continue to enhance DMNS exhibits, visitor programming, and educational outreach activities. This project will utilize the Museum's large volunteer program, which unites the public with museum collections to assist with project-related tasks. The collections and their importance will be highlighted in a series of 'Scientists in Action' satellite broadcasts directly from the Museum, connecting scientists with grades 4-12 students. Additionally, underrepresented high school students interested in science careers will work on collections-based research projects through the Museum's successful 'Teen Science Scholars Program', contributing to their success in STEM fields.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The Denver Museum of Nature &amp; Science (DMNS) is the largest public natural history museum in the Rocky Mountain region. The Museum houses a rapidly expanding fossil vertebrate collection spanning more than 330 million years of evolution in the Rocky Mountain region and beyond. Over the past 20 years, the collection has experienced the greatest period of growth in its history, with acquisitions outpacing the institution's ability to store, curate, and digitize fossils. Coupled with the completion of a new state-of-the-art collections facility, this project provides support for the digitization of over 56,000 significant vertebrate fossils, increasing accessibility and facilitating research and education. Additional information about the Museum's scientific and outreach missions, as they relate to this project, is publicly available at: www.dmns.org/science/collections/.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>05/20/2014</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/20/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.074</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1349326</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Richard</FirstName>
<LastName>Stucky</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>K</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Richard K Stucky</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>richard.stucky@dmns.org</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>3033706434</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000409698</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/20/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Joseph</FirstName>
<LastName>Sertich</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Joseph Sertich</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>jsertich@dmns.org</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>3033706331</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000516204</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/20/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Logan</FirstName>
<LastName>Ivy</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Logan Ivy</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>logan.ivy@dmns.org</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>3033708304</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000648930</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/20/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Denver Museum of Nature and Science</Name>
<CityName>Denver</CityName>
<ZipCode>802055732</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>3033708304</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>2001 Colorado Boulevard</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Colorado</StateName>
<StateCode>CO</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CO01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>021695689</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>COLORADO MUSEUM OF NATURAL HISTORY, THE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Denver Museum of Nature & Science]]></Name>
<CityName>Denver</CityName>
<StateCode>CO</StateCode>
<ZipCode>802055732</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[2001 Colorado Blvd]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Colorado</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CO01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1197</Code>
<Text>BIOLOGICAL RESEARCH COLLECTION</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0114</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~449999</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Over the last 30 years, the Denver Museum of Nature &amp; Science has focused increasing attention on its collections stewardship responsibilities by growing and professionalizing the staff, collections procedures, and modernizing cabinetry and equipment. Despite these efforts, collections were subject to varying risk factors that included inadequate storage conditions, overcrowding, and a lack of climate control, coupled with a lack of space for future growth and research. To address these concerns, the Museum completed construction of the state-of-the-art Avenir Collections Center in 2014, with 63,000 square feet dedicated to collections and research spaces.</p> <p>The fossil vertebrate collections at DMNS span the past 300 million years of life on Earth, with a focus on regionally significant, ecosystem-centric collections from the Rocky Mountains and western Great Plains. These collections consist of more than 1 million unique specimens, with most significant growth occurring over the past 20 years. Of note are several large-scale, publicly visible discoveries including the 2010 discovery of a major Pleistocene assemblage near Snowmass Village, CO. The rate of discoveries and growth far outpaced the capacity for proper curation and storage.</p> <p>Funding from NSF-CSBR allowed DMNS to enhance its commitment to the public, research scientists, and its collections. The objectives of the 4-year project were to: (1) purchase and install replacement cabinets and shelves to rehouse 100% of the non-federal fossil vertebrate collection; (2) support a full-time curatorial assistant to assist with identification, inventory, uncrowding, rehousing, and photography of collections; (3) streamline collections digitization, including specimen imaging, of all reliably identified specimens (around 56,000 records) to the newly instituted, web-accessible database KE EMu and to make records publicly available via a web-accessible interface; and (4) Support the successful DMNS program &ldquo;Scientists in Action&rdquo; directed at educating students about the use and importance of collections and research.</p> <p>The Denver Museum of Nature &amp; Science has been able to significantly improve the storage conditions (e.g., uncrowding, climate control, cabinetry/shelving), curation, and public visibility of its fossil vertebrate collections with support from NSF. The transfer of specimens from suboptimal storage areas to the new, state-of-the-art collections facility was accomplished in 2016. Cabinets and shelves purchased with NSF funds allowed us to rehouse 100% of the non-federal fossil vertebrate collections. During the term of the NSF-funded project, 105 volunteers contributed 11,327 hours of collections work on the collections efforts, and an additional 17 volunteers contributed 2,861 hours of work photographing specimens. In part because of this outpouring of local volunteer support, 38,616 new, unique records were processed for 64,762 individual specimens, far exceeding the target of 56,000 individual specimens.</p> <p>In addition, a fully web-accessible platform (IMu) for our collections database KE Emu was developed with the support of NSF project and was made active late in 2016. This platform has, for the first time, allowed researchers and the general public to access data and images for specimens held in the DMNS collections. All fossil vertebrate records had been migrated to IMu by the end of the project term. To date, images have been captured for 2,088 macrovertebrate specimens and 4,947 microvertebrate specimens. Photography of specimens and data management related to the web-based system has continued past completion of the project and has become standard practice for our collections process, making our behind-the-scenes research collections publicly visible.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>During the term of the project, students across the country learned about the importance of collections and research through the <em>Scientists in Action</em> program supported by this project. These schools ranging across the US, interacted directly with DMNS collections and had their questions answered live via digital feed. A total of 4,686 students were reached over 20, 1-hour sessions NSF-supported SIA broadcasts during the project term. For many of the students, this was their first look behind the scenes at a natural history museum.</p> <p>Throughout the project, we also highlighted the DMNS fossil vertebrate collection through tours, special events, member&rsquo;s nights, and free days. DMNS participated in the annual <em>National Fossil Day</em> celebrations with collections highlights and discussions. Behind-the-Scenes tours of collections for visitors, university classes, schools, and educators have brought several thousand people into direct contact with collections and research activities. In addition, the curatorial assistant funded by the award and one of the graduate student interns have transitioned into permanent, collections management positions in the fossil collections at DMNS underscoring the success of the project and the long-lasting impact it will have on our collections well into the future.</p> <p>In summary, NSF support for this project has helped DMNS accomplish its goals related to the long term care of collections. Further, this award has helped expand the visibility of the DMNS fossil vertebrate collections for the research community, and most significantly, for the broader public, building support and understanding for critical natural history collections.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 09/13/2018<br>      Modified by: Joseph&nbsp;Sertich</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Images (<span id="selectedPhoto0">1</span> of <span class="totalNumber"></span>)           </div> <div class="galControls" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1349326/1349326_10304087_1536815113429_EAS_Grant_2018-5--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1349326/1349326_10304087_1536815113429_EAS_Grant_2018-5--rgov-800width.jpg" title="DMNS small fossil vertebrates"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1349326/1349326_10304087_1536815113429_EAS_Grant_2018-5--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="DMNS small fossil vertebrates"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Reorganized, digitized, and inventoried small vertebrate fossils at the Denver Museum of Nature & Science.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Rick Wicker, DMNS</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Royalty-free (unrestricted use)</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Joseph&nbsp;Sertich</div> <div class="imageTitle">DMNS small fossil vertebrates</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1349326/1349326_10304087_1536815225994_EAS_Grant_2018-2--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1349326/1349326_10304087_1536815225994_EAS_Grant_2018-2--rgov-800width.jpg" title="DMNS large fossil vertebrates"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1349326/1349326_10304087_1536815225994_EAS_Grant_2018-2--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="DMNS large fossil vertebrates"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Rehoused, uncrowded large fossil vertebrates at the Denver Museum of Nature & Science.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Rick Wicker, DMNS</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Royalty-free (unrestricted use)</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Joseph&nbsp;Sertich</div> <div class="imageTitle">DMNS large fossil vertebrates</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Over the last 30 years, the Denver Museum of Nature &amp; Science has focused increasing attention on its collections stewardship responsibilities by growing and professionalizing the staff, collections procedures, and modernizing cabinetry and equipment. Despite these efforts, collections were subject to varying risk factors that included inadequate storage conditions, overcrowding, and a lack of climate control, coupled with a lack of space for future growth and research. To address these concerns, the Museum completed construction of the state-of-the-art Avenir Collections Center in 2014, with 63,000 square feet dedicated to collections and research spaces.  The fossil vertebrate collections at DMNS span the past 300 million years of life on Earth, with a focus on regionally significant, ecosystem-centric collections from the Rocky Mountains and western Great Plains. These collections consist of more than 1 million unique specimens, with most significant growth occurring over the past 20 years. Of note are several large-scale, publicly visible discoveries including the 2010 discovery of a major Pleistocene assemblage near Snowmass Village, CO. The rate of discoveries and growth far outpaced the capacity for proper curation and storage.  Funding from NSF-CSBR allowed DMNS to enhance its commitment to the public, research scientists, and its collections. The objectives of the 4-year project were to: (1) purchase and install replacement cabinets and shelves to rehouse 100% of the non-federal fossil vertebrate collection; (2) support a full-time curatorial assistant to assist with identification, inventory, uncrowding, rehousing, and photography of collections; (3) streamline collections digitization, including specimen imaging, of all reliably identified specimens (around 56,000 records) to the newly instituted, web-accessible database KE EMu and to make records publicly available via a web-accessible interface; and (4) Support the successful DMNS program "Scientists in Action" directed at educating students about the use and importance of collections and research.  The Denver Museum of Nature &amp; Science has been able to significantly improve the storage conditions (e.g., uncrowding, climate control, cabinetry/shelving), curation, and public visibility of its fossil vertebrate collections with support from NSF. The transfer of specimens from suboptimal storage areas to the new, state-of-the-art collections facility was accomplished in 2016. Cabinets and shelves purchased with NSF funds allowed us to rehouse 100% of the non-federal fossil vertebrate collections. During the term of the NSF-funded project, 105 volunteers contributed 11,327 hours of collections work on the collections efforts, and an additional 17 volunteers contributed 2,861 hours of work photographing specimens. In part because of this outpouring of local volunteer support, 38,616 new, unique records were processed for 64,762 individual specimens, far exceeding the target of 56,000 individual specimens.  In addition, a fully web-accessible platform (IMu) for our collections database KE Emu was developed with the support of NSF project and was made active late in 2016. This platform has, for the first time, allowed researchers and the general public to access data and images for specimens held in the DMNS collections. All fossil vertebrate records had been migrated to IMu by the end of the project term. To date, images have been captured for 2,088 macrovertebrate specimens and 4,947 microvertebrate specimens. Photography of specimens and data management related to the web-based system has continued past completion of the project and has become standard practice for our collections process, making our behind-the-scenes research collections publicly visible.     During the term of the project, students across the country learned about the importance of collections and research through the Scientists in Action program supported by this project. These schools ranging across the US, interacted directly with DMNS collections and had their questions answered live via digital feed. A total of 4,686 students were reached over 20, 1-hour sessions NSF-supported SIA broadcasts during the project term. For many of the students, this was their first look behind the scenes at a natural history museum.  Throughout the project, we also highlighted the DMNS fossil vertebrate collection through tours, special events, member?s nights, and free days. DMNS participated in the annual National Fossil Day celebrations with collections highlights and discussions. Behind-the-Scenes tours of collections for visitors, university classes, schools, and educators have brought several thousand people into direct contact with collections and research activities. In addition, the curatorial assistant funded by the award and one of the graduate student interns have transitioned into permanent, collections management positions in the fossil collections at DMNS underscoring the success of the project and the long-lasting impact it will have on our collections well into the future.  In summary, NSF support for this project has helped DMNS accomplish its goals related to the long term care of collections. Further, this award has helped expand the visibility of the DMNS fossil vertebrate collections for the research community, and most significantly, for the broader public, building support and understanding for critical natural history collections.       Last Modified: 09/13/2018       Submitted by: Joseph Sertich]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
