<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Collaborative Research: Millennial variability of hillslope dynamics and alluvial aggradation in semiarid regions: a view from the southern Hemisphere</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>05/01/2014</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2016</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>354431.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>354431</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>06030206</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>GEO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>EAR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Earth Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Richard Yuretich</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>ryuretic@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924744</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This international, multi-institutional, collaborative project will advance our knowledge regarding how alluvial and fluvial geomorphic systems respond to climate change at millennial timescales in arid and semiarid regions. The project specifically aims to analyze the coupled hydrologic and geomorphic response during post-glacial times in the arid Elqui valley in northern Chile.  Cosmogenic nuclides, luminescence dating and soils stratigraphy will be used to characterize, in terms of process and timing, the production, storage and transport of sediment from hillslopes to alluvial and fluvial reaches. Two nearby lacustrine records will be analyzed over the same temporal window with a suite of paleoenvironmental indicators. The robust coupled dataset is expected to contribute to our understanding of the local and regional pedology, geomorphology, tectonics and paleoenvironment of the semiarid western Andes.  Furthermore, understanding how landforms and soils evolve over Holocene timescales will contribute to geologic research of similar regions in other parts of the world.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The project will contribute to the advancement of undergraduate geology programs at University of Nevada Reno and California State University Bakersfield, the latter a Hispanic-Serving Institution.  The project  has a strong international partnership with Centro de Estudios Avanzado en Zonas Aridas (CEAZA) in La Serena, Chile, as well as Dalhousie University in Canada and will provide international research experiences for two U.S. undergraduate students.  The research will aid land use planning and hazards mitigation efforts for the region as well as other parts of the world with similar arid environments.   Outreach activities will be coordinated with the Chilean partner.  This project is jointly supported by the Geomorphology and Land Use Dynamics, Paleoclimatology, and International Science and Engineering programs.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>04/28/2014</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>10/17/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.050</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1349416</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Eric</FirstName>
<LastName>McDonald</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Eric McDonald</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>emcdonald@dri.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>7756737302</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000470544</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>10/17/2016</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Eric</FirstName>
<LastName>McDonald</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Eric McDonald</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>emcdonald@dri.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>7756737302</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000470544</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/28/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate>10/17/2016</EndDate>
<RoleCode>Former Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Jose Luis</FirstName>
<LastName>Antinao Rojas</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Jose Luis Antinao Rojas</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>jantinao@iu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>8128551366</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000557240</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/28/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate>10/17/2016</EndDate>
<RoleCode>Former Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Nevada System of Higher Education, Desert Research Institute</Name>
<CityName>Reno</CityName>
<ZipCode>895121095</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>7756737300</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>2215 Raggio Parkway</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Nevada</StateName>
<StateCode>NV</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NV02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>134599174</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>NEVADA SYSTEM OF HIGHER EDUCATION</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>067808063</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Nevada Desert Research Institute]]></Name>
<CityName>Reno</CityName>
<StateCode>NV</StateCode>
<ZipCode>895121095</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[2215 Raggio Pkwy]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Nevada</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NV02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1577</Code>
<Text>GLOBAL CHANGE</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7298</Code>
<Text>International Research Collab</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7458</Code>
<Text>Geomorphology &amp; Land-use Dynam</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1304</Code>
<Text>EARTH SYSTEM HISTORY</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>5974</Code>
<Text>CHILE</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>EGCH</Code>
<Text>ENVIRONMENT AND GLOBAL CHANGE</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0114</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0115</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~190391</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2015~164040</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>This project evaluated sediment transport and deposition on hillslopes and alluvial fans in the arid southern Central Andes of Chile during the last 11,000 years (the Holocene period), testing how arid landscapes respond to vegetation and climate change.</p> <p>The study was an international collaborative effort that included Chilean research groups. &nbsp;We studied the sediment record in two shallow, high elevation lakes (2,000-3,000 meters above sea level; MASL), and the stratigraphy and soils associated with over a dozen alluvial fans in a high relief region of the Andes, from elevations of ~1,000 &ndash; 4,000 MASL.</p> <p>Intellectual Merit:</p> <p>Our investigation of hypothesized climate-landscape process linkages led us to conclude that along the two main river valleys of the studied region, the main process responsible for deposition of thick sediment packages in tributary stream junctions is the occurrence of intense precipitation in storms originating from high elevation areas of the Andes. The last 5,000 years have been more similar to present-day conditions, when storm events recorded in the sediments are likely derived from westerly frontal (Pacific storms) precipitation. This is consistent with other paleoclimate records south of the study area, along the coast and in the Andes. Between 9,000 and 5,000 years ago (mid-Holocene), intense aridity dominated the region. At the peak aridity in this period, a distinct humid event appears at ~8,200 &ndash; 7,900 years ago (the 8.2-7.9 ka event). This event was detected in both the alluvial fan and lacustrine record. In this case, an easterly component is inferred given that Pacific precipitation events are absent from coastal and low elevation records south of our study area during this period. Indeed, synoptic conditions in our interpretation are similar to those documented for major convective storm events from the east (Argentina) during southern Hemisphere summers the past 30 years.</p> <p>The 8.2-7.9 ka event is strikingly similar in timing to a North Atlantic cooling event that significantly lowered temperatures in the Northern Hemisphere at that time. A potential teleconnection between the North Atlantic and the central Andes is viable through a southward movement of the tropical band of atmospheric convection in the oceans. This in turn decreased the intensity of the global atmospheric westerly flow at this latitude, already weak at the time. Weaker zonal (westerly) atmospheric flow allowed entrance of convective instability and moisture from the eastern Andes. Our study suggests the possibility of a connection of climate effects from the North Atlantic to western South America; more studies in this region are needed to test this new hypothesis.</p> <p>Broader Impacts:</p> <p>Our study gives a consistent explanation of dissimilar sedimentation records occurring during the last 11,000 years in lacustrine and alluvial systems of the southern Central Andes and the coastal lowlands south of there, in Mediterranean Chile. Our research is the first to propose increased convective activity in the arid mid-Holocene, linking it to a global event. We have fully described a detailed Holocene lacustrine record (Laguna El Cepo, ~3,000 MASL) that is a unique benchmark in the region, nonexistent until now, and that will be extremely useful in paleoenvironmental reconstruction of the region. Our project is the first to show the benefits of luminescence dating for the region studied. We also interpreted synoptic conditions for the first time in the context of extreme sediment transport and sedimentation events. This will be of relevance for hazards planning in the region and other arid regions that might be affected by future regional and global climate change.</p> <p>In this study we have collaborated with regional institutes like the Center for Aridlands Research (CEAZA) in Chile, a paleoenvironmental research group of global reach. Our collaboration extended into developing outreach strategies to be applied in geoscience education at K-12 and undergraduate level in the United States, with international and local components.</p> <p>Data collected will also help geological hazards, soils, and landscape evolution studies of the region at longer timescales (thousands of years). We characterized many outcrops of deeply weathered soil profiles (saprolite profiles) representing long-lived landforms, in close vicinity of deposits only a few thousand years old. We also characterized discontinuous ash levels from explosive volcanic eruptions with affinity to volcanic centers in the southern Andes. These ash layers capped the saprolites or were embedded in hillslope deposits. Our results speak about the rich, relatively unexplored geology of unconsolidated deposits in the region, whose study will benefit not only regional analysis, but also global research on climate, soils and landscape evolution in arid mountain regions.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 08/10/2017<br>      Modified by: Eric&nbsp;V&nbsp;Mcdonald</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ This project evaluated sediment transport and deposition on hillslopes and alluvial fans in the arid southern Central Andes of Chile during the last 11,000 years (the Holocene period), testing how arid landscapes respond to vegetation and climate change.  The study was an international collaborative effort that included Chilean research groups.  We studied the sediment record in two shallow, high elevation lakes (2,000-3,000 meters above sea level; MASL), and the stratigraphy and soils associated with over a dozen alluvial fans in a high relief region of the Andes, from elevations of ~1,000 &ndash; 4,000 MASL.  Intellectual Merit:  Our investigation of hypothesized climate-landscape process linkages led us to conclude that along the two main river valleys of the studied region, the main process responsible for deposition of thick sediment packages in tributary stream junctions is the occurrence of intense precipitation in storms originating from high elevation areas of the Andes. The last 5,000 years have been more similar to present-day conditions, when storm events recorded in the sediments are likely derived from westerly frontal (Pacific storms) precipitation. This is consistent with other paleoclimate records south of the study area, along the coast and in the Andes. Between 9,000 and 5,000 years ago (mid-Holocene), intense aridity dominated the region. At the peak aridity in this period, a distinct humid event appears at ~8,200 &ndash; 7,900 years ago (the 8.2-7.9 ka event). This event was detected in both the alluvial fan and lacustrine record. In this case, an easterly component is inferred given that Pacific precipitation events are absent from coastal and low elevation records south of our study area during this period. Indeed, synoptic conditions in our interpretation are similar to those documented for major convective storm events from the east (Argentina) during southern Hemisphere summers the past 30 years.  The 8.2-7.9 ka event is strikingly similar in timing to a North Atlantic cooling event that significantly lowered temperatures in the Northern Hemisphere at that time. A potential teleconnection between the North Atlantic and the central Andes is viable through a southward movement of the tropical band of atmospheric convection in the oceans. This in turn decreased the intensity of the global atmospheric westerly flow at this latitude, already weak at the time. Weaker zonal (westerly) atmospheric flow allowed entrance of convective instability and moisture from the eastern Andes. Our study suggests the possibility of a connection of climate effects from the North Atlantic to western South America; more studies in this region are needed to test this new hypothesis.  Broader Impacts:  Our study gives a consistent explanation of dissimilar sedimentation records occurring during the last 11,000 years in lacustrine and alluvial systems of the southern Central Andes and the coastal lowlands south of there, in Mediterranean Chile. Our research is the first to propose increased convective activity in the arid mid-Holocene, linking it to a global event. We have fully described a detailed Holocene lacustrine record (Laguna El Cepo, ~3,000 MASL) that is a unique benchmark in the region, nonexistent until now, and that will be extremely useful in paleoenvironmental reconstruction of the region. Our project is the first to show the benefits of luminescence dating for the region studied. We also interpreted synoptic conditions for the first time in the context of extreme sediment transport and sedimentation events. This will be of relevance for hazards planning in the region and other arid regions that might be affected by future regional and global climate change.  In this study we have collaborated with regional institutes like the Center for Aridlands Research (CEAZA) in Chile, a paleoenvironmental research group of global reach. Our collaboration extended into developing outreach strategies to be applied in geoscience education at K-12 and undergraduate level in the United States, with international and local components.  Data collected will also help geological hazards, soils, and landscape evolution studies of the region at longer timescales (thousands of years). We characterized many outcrops of deeply weathered soil profiles (saprolite profiles) representing long-lived landforms, in close vicinity of deposits only a few thousand years old. We also characterized discontinuous ash levels from explosive volcanic eruptions with affinity to volcanic centers in the southern Andes. These ash layers capped the saprolites or were embedded in hillslope deposits. Our results speak about the rich, relatively unexplored geology of unconsolidated deposits in the region, whose study will benefit not only regional analysis, but also global research on climate, soils and landscape evolution in arid mountain regions.          Last Modified: 08/10/2017       Submitted by: Eric V Mcdonald]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
