<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>CSBR: Living Stocks - A Genetic Stock Center for Peromyscus</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>06/01/2014</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>449889.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>482119</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>08080000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>BIO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DBI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Biological Infrastructure</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Reed Beaman</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>rsbeaman@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927163</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Rodents in the genus Peromyscus have become ideal models for studying the genetic and other factors responsible for reproductive isolation and speciation, as well as those factors enabling adaptive responses by organisms to changing environmental conditions, including parasites and to other species. An award is made to the Peromyscus Genetic Stock Center to provide a reliable source of live Peromyscus animals (of seven species) and related materials to the national scientific and educational communities. The Stock Center also functions as a clearing house for information regarding this group of animals by sponsoring an internet database, maintaining a reference collection of journal reprints, and hosting a Peromyscus discussion blog. These resources are widely used in the U.S. and elsewhere including numerous NSF-Bio supported researchers. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;To date the Stock Center has supplied about 27,000 animals, providing the basis for about 300 research articles spanning most areas of biology. Recently, the Stock Center has contributed to numerous high impact discoveries that were featured in the popular media. The Center also supports onsite research by visiting scientists, hosting many such visitors each year. A substantial number of graduate and undergraduate students conduct their research within the Center, producing several Honors Theses and Ph.D. dissertations. Additional outreach involves providing animals to zoos and participation of the Center's staff in K-12 educational programs. More information on the Stock Center and its programs may be obtained at: http://stkctr.biol.sc.edu.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>05/20/2014</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/05/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.074</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1349230</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Michael</FirstName>
<LastName>Felder</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Michael Felder</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>mrfelder@mailbox.sc.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>8037775135</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000369034</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/20/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate>09/21/2015</EndDate>
<RoleCode>Former Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Gabor</FirstName>
<LastName>Szalai</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Gabor Szalai</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>szalai@mailbox.sc.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>8037777093</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000648735</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/20/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate>01/11/2016</EndDate>
<RoleCode>Former Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Hippokratis</FirstName>
<LastName>Kiaris</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Hippokratis Kiaris</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>kiarish@cop.sc.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>8037779322</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000714456</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>01/11/2016</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of South Carolina at Columbia</Name>
<CityName>COLUMBIA</CityName>
<ZipCode>292080001</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>8037777093</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>Sponsored Awards Management</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[1600 Hampton Street, Suite 414]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>South Carolina</StateName>
<StateCode>SC</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>06</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>SC06</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>041387846</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF SOUTH CAROLINA</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>041387846</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of South Carolina at Columbia]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>SC</StateCode>
<ZipCode>292080001</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>South Carolina</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>06</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>SC06</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1197</Code>
<Text>BIOLOGICAL RESEARCH COLLECTION</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0114</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0115</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0116</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~149963</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2015~182193</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2016~149963</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Rodents of the genus <em>Peromyscus</em> are among the most abundant and widely distributed North American mammals. Although they resemble mice and rats in appearance they constitute a different genus that diverged quite early in evolution. <em>Peromyscus</em> species occupy diverse habitats and exhibit clear differences in their appearance as well as in their behavior and physiology. Due to a series of characteristics they accumulate, <em>Peromyscus</em> animals emerged a model of choice for the study of major biological processes such as speciation, stress response, altitude adaptation, behavior adaptation in the context of physiology and evolution, host-parasite interactions, microbiome-associated studies and others.</p> <p>The University of South Carolina, in order to provide researchers access to various wild type and mutant stocks of <em>Peromyscus</em>, established more than 30 years ago and since then maintains and distributes upon request various <em>Peromyscus</em> species. A major aim of this proposal was to support the smooth and uninterrupted operation, at the highest standards, of the unique in the world USC-based <em>Peromyscus</em> genetic Stock Center. During this grant more than 150 requests have been fulfilled and more than 4500 animals have been supplied to investigators that operate primarily in the academic setting. Such recipient institutions in the US that have received animals and/or biological material from the PGSC included the Cold Spring Harbor Laboratory, Univ. of Maryland, University of Minnesota, Cornell University, University of California, University of Georgia, Ohio State University, Loyola University (MD), Harvard University, North Carolina College of Veterinary Medicine, Johns Hopkins School of Medicine, Tufts University, Vanderbilt University, Centers for Disease Control, Governors State University, Colgate University, and others. Universities abroad have also received Peromyscus animals or biological material such as the University of Quebec in Montreal (Canada), Max-Planck-Institut fuer Experimentelle Medizin (Germany) and the North-West University, Potchefstroom, South Africa. Other Governmental entities such as the Center for Disease Control (Atlanta, GA) and the Department of the Army have also received animals from the PGSC.</p> <p>This grant also allowed the Center to fulfill additional missions stated in the proposal such as the improvement of the Center&rsquo;s and of its operations&rsquo; visibility with the ultimate goal to make it a focal point for Peromyscus-associated research. To that end the center&rsquo;s web site has been redesigned and a biannual newsletter, the <em>Perotimes</em>, hasbeen published and distributed. In addition, several investigators from outside Institutions visit the PGSC, while others are trained on site and utilize the Center&rsquo;s services to perform experimental tasks facilitating their research.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 06/13/2017<br>      Modified by: Hippokratis&nbsp;Kiaris</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Rodents of the genus Peromyscus are among the most abundant and widely distributed North American mammals. Although they resemble mice and rats in appearance they constitute a different genus that diverged quite early in evolution. Peromyscus species occupy diverse habitats and exhibit clear differences in their appearance as well as in their behavior and physiology. Due to a series of characteristics they accumulate, Peromyscus animals emerged a model of choice for the study of major biological processes such as speciation, stress response, altitude adaptation, behavior adaptation in the context of physiology and evolution, host-parasite interactions, microbiome-associated studies and others.  The University of South Carolina, in order to provide researchers access to various wild type and mutant stocks of Peromyscus, established more than 30 years ago and since then maintains and distributes upon request various Peromyscus species. A major aim of this proposal was to support the smooth and uninterrupted operation, at the highest standards, of the unique in the world USC-based Peromyscus genetic Stock Center. During this grant more than 150 requests have been fulfilled and more than 4500 animals have been supplied to investigators that operate primarily in the academic setting. Such recipient institutions in the US that have received animals and/or biological material from the PGSC included the Cold Spring Harbor Laboratory, Univ. of Maryland, University of Minnesota, Cornell University, University of California, University of Georgia, Ohio State University, Loyola University (MD), Harvard University, North Carolina College of Veterinary Medicine, Johns Hopkins School of Medicine, Tufts University, Vanderbilt University, Centers for Disease Control, Governors State University, Colgate University, and others. Universities abroad have also received Peromyscus animals or biological material such as the University of Quebec in Montreal (Canada), Max-Planck-Institut fuer Experimentelle Medizin (Germany) and the North-West University, Potchefstroom, South Africa. Other Governmental entities such as the Center for Disease Control (Atlanta, GA) and the Department of the Army have also received animals from the PGSC.  This grant also allowed the Center to fulfill additional missions stated in the proposal such as the improvement of the Center?s and of its operations? visibility with the ultimate goal to make it a focal point for Peromyscus-associated research. To that end the center?s web site has been redesigned and a biannual newsletter, the Perotimes, hasbeen published and distributed. In addition, several investigators from outside Institutions visit the PGSC, while others are trained on site and utilize the Center?s services to perform experimental tasks facilitating their research.       Last Modified: 06/13/2017       Submitted by: Hippokratis Kiaris]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
