<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>CAREER: Electrokinetic Flows and Electrochemical Dynamics in Concentrated Electrolytes and Ionic Liquids</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>05/01/2014</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>04/30/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>400075.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>400075</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07020000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CBET</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Chem, Bioeng, Env, &amp; Transp Sys</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>William Olbricht</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>wolbrich@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924842</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>CAREER: Electrokinetic Flows and Electrochemical Dynamics in Concentrated Electrolytes and Ionic Liquids&lt;br/&gt;PI: Khair, Aditya&lt;br/&gt;Institution: Carnegie Mellon University&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Many liquid and particle systems in technology and biology contain ions, and in some of these systems, the concentration of ions is large.  The theory that scientists and engineers use to predict the dynamics of these systems is based on assumptions that the ions can be considered to be point charges and that interactions among the ions are not important.  The equations based on this theory work well for dilute ion concentrations, but they fail to predict interesting phenomena observed when the concentration of ions is large.  Systems containing high concentrations of ions appear in many problems of technological and biological importance, including water desalination, the development of batteries and super-capacitors, and transfer of ions across cell membranes through ion channels.  The goal of this project is to develop an integrated research and teaching program to develop a new model that scientists and engineers can use to describe the essential features of electrically driven transport in concentrated systems. Understanding such phenomena and training students to appreciate them will enhance manufacturing capabilities and may lead to new technological developments such as novel separation protocols for nanoparticles and biomolecules based on the motion of charged objects.  The multi-tiered educational plan for the project includes outreach activities, undergraduate and graduate course design and research, technical software development, and organization of scientific meetings.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project will develop a continuum framework for electrically driven (electrokinetic) fluid flow and particle transport in concentrated electrolytes and ionic liquids, via a combination of modeling, computation, and experiment. Concentrated electrolytes and ionic liquids are attractive materials for energy storage and conversion technologies, but existing theoretical models fail to describe their dynamical response to applied voltages. The central hypothesis of the project is that explicit ion-ion interactions in concentrated systems, due to steric repulsion and electrostatic correlations, result in their dynamics being radically different from dilute solutions. Molecular simulations can quantify ion-ion interactions in equilibrium systems; however, they are often too computationally expensive to capture electrokinetic phenomena. Thus, there is a pressing need for a continuum-level theory that encapsulates the essential features of nonequilibrium transport in concentrated charge-carrying liquids in complex geometries. A model will be developed for anomalous electrokinetic transport in concentrated systems, including electrophoretic mobility reversals. The electrostatic forces between particles in concentrated electrolytes and ionic liquids will be quantified to predict suspension stability and flocculation in these media.  The electrochemical dynamics of ionic liquids will be analyzed.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>04/22/2014</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/07/2018</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1350647</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Aditya</FirstName>
<LastName>Khair</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Aditya Khair</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>akhair@andrew.cmu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>4122689527</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000572369</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/22/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Carnegie-Mellon University</Name>
<CityName>PITTSBURGH</CityName>
<ZipCode>152133815</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>4122688746</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>5000 Forbes Avenue</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[WQED Building]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Pennsylvania</StateName>
<StateCode>PA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>18</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>PA18</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>052184116</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>CARNEGIE MELLON UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>052184116</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Carnegie Mellon University]]></Name>
<CityName>Pittsburgh</CityName>
<StateCode>PA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>152133815</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[5000 Forbes Avenue]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Pennsylvania</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>18</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>PA18</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1415</Code>
<Text>PMP-Particul&amp;MultiphaseProcess</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>055E</Code>
<Text>Particle science and technology</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1045</Code>
<Text>CAREER-Faculty Erly Career Dev</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0114</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0115</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0116</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0117</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0118</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~77932</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2015~77697</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2016~79800</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2017~81207</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2018~83439</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Electrically conducting fluids, or electrolytes, which contain dissolved ionic species, find applications in energy storage and conversion (think batteries and super-capacitors); enhanced oil recovery; and water desalination.&nbsp; The intellectual merit of this project was to quantify electrochemical and fluid flow processes in concentrated electrolytes and ionic liquids.&nbsp; The central hypothesis of our work was that interactions between ions in concentrated systems, arising from steric and electrostatic forces, result in their dynamics being radically different from dilute solutions.&nbsp; For instance, we demonstrated that correlated electrostatic forces between ions drive anomalous electrophoretic &ldquo;mobility reversals&rdquo; of charged colloidal particles in concentrated electrolytes, wherein a positively charged particle can drift to a positive electrode, in apparent violation of Coulomb&rsquo;s law! Such anomalous motion has been observed experimentally, and our theory identified electrostatic correlations as the root cause. Further work investigated a range of unconventional electrically-driven transport and particle motion, including field-dependent electrophoresis and electrolyte dynamics at large voltages; ion steric effects on diffusiophoresis (i.e., colloid motion under salt gradients); and multi-component (Stefan-Maxwell) fluxes in electrochemical systems. <br /><br />In broader technological impact, our work on mobility reversals will enable researchers to design new particulate separations in highly charged solutions. Specifically, the occurrence of a mobility reversal would require adjustment of detector position or switching the polarity of driving electrodes; otherwise, a species would not be detected. Thus, the ability to predict reversals, which our work has enabled, is necessary to enable separations in high-salt media, e.g. bio-fluids and ionic liquids. In terms of broader educational impact, this project has supported the training of three graduate students at CMU. Two undergraduate students have also participated. Students involved in the research took part in outreach activities at CMU; course material relevant to the project was developed; and technical symposia at conferences related to electrically-driven transport were organized.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 08/27/2019<br>      Modified by: Aditya&nbsp;Khair</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Electrically conducting fluids, or electrolytes, which contain dissolved ionic species, find applications in energy storage and conversion (think batteries and super-capacitors); enhanced oil recovery; and water desalination.  The intellectual merit of this project was to quantify electrochemical and fluid flow processes in concentrated electrolytes and ionic liquids.  The central hypothesis of our work was that interactions between ions in concentrated systems, arising from steric and electrostatic forces, result in their dynamics being radically different from dilute solutions.  For instance, we demonstrated that correlated electrostatic forces between ions drive anomalous electrophoretic "mobility reversals" of charged colloidal particles in concentrated electrolytes, wherein a positively charged particle can drift to a positive electrode, in apparent violation of Coulomb?s law! Such anomalous motion has been observed experimentally, and our theory identified electrostatic correlations as the root cause. Further work investigated a range of unconventional electrically-driven transport and particle motion, including field-dependent electrophoresis and electrolyte dynamics at large voltages; ion steric effects on diffusiophoresis (i.e., colloid motion under salt gradients); and multi-component (Stefan-Maxwell) fluxes in electrochemical systems.   In broader technological impact, our work on mobility reversals will enable researchers to design new particulate separations in highly charged solutions. Specifically, the occurrence of a mobility reversal would require adjustment of detector position or switching the polarity of driving electrodes; otherwise, a species would not be detected. Thus, the ability to predict reversals, which our work has enabled, is necessary to enable separations in high-salt media, e.g. bio-fluids and ionic liquids. In terms of broader educational impact, this project has supported the training of three graduate students at CMU. Two undergraduate students have also participated. Students involved in the research took part in outreach activities at CMU; course material relevant to the project was developed; and technical symposia at conferences related to electrically-driven transport were organized.       Last Modified: 08/27/2019       Submitted by: Aditya Khair]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
