<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>EAGER: Fluorescence Studies of  Surface Micro-heterogeneity in Thermoacidophile Lipid Membranes</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>01/01/2014</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>181000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>185000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07020000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CBET</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Chem, Bioeng, Env, &amp; Transp Sys</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Nora Savage</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>nosavage@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927949</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Abstract&lt;br/&gt;#1350841&lt;br/&gt;Chong, Parkson L.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Stable liposomes have many potential uses in drug formulations (and even skin-care products). Liposomes that can withstand autoclaving are especially desirable for medical applications. The PI proposes to investigate highly stable bipolar membranes (liposomes) with fluorescent tags that probe membrane properties at different membrane depths or at different lateral positions. Specifically, he hypothesizes that there should be significant structural and functional heterogeneities along the membrane normal and in the plane of the membrane, which are of critical importance in understanding membrane structure-function relationship for these ultra-stable architectures.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The results obtained from this research should enhance the understanding of lipid-protein interactions and solute permeation in archaeal membranes and will have profound implications in technological applications, such as extraordinarily stable lipid matrix for biosensors, light harvesting devices, and nanoparticles for targeted imaging and therapy.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/26/2013</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/18/2017</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1350841</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Parkson</FirstName>
<LastName>Chong</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>L</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Parkson L Chong</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>pchong02@temple.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2157074182</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000475960</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/26/2013</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Temple University</Name>
<CityName>Philadelphia</CityName>
<ZipCode>191226003</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2157077547</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1801 N. Broad Street</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Pennsylvania</StateName>
<StateCode>PA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>PA02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>057123192</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>TEMPLE UNIVERSITY-OF THE COMMONWEALTH SYSTEM OF HIGHER EDUCATION</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>057123192</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Temple University]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>PA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>191226027</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Pennsylvania</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>PA02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1179</Code>
<Text>Nanoscale Interactions Program</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1414</Code>
<Text>INTERFAC PROCESSES &amp; THERMODYN</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>051E</Code>
<Text>Interfacial trans &amp; thermodynamic</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7916</Code>
<Text>EAGER</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9251</Code>
<Text>REU SUPP-Res Exp for Ugrd Supp</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0113</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0117</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2013~181000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2017~4000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The goal of this research is to study the micro-heterogeneity of dynamics and lateral organization in membranes composed of bipolar tetraether lipids (BTL) derived from the thermoacidophilic archaeon <em>Sulfolobus acidocaldarius</em>. This micro-organism thrives at high temperatures (65-85<sup>o</sup>C) and low pHs (2-3). BTLs are the dominating lipid species in crenarchaeota including thermoacidophiles, and the chemical structures of BTLs are distinctly different from the structures of lipids found in animals and bacteria. Archaeal BTLs have different kinds such as glycerol dialky calditol tetraether (GDNT), glycerol dialky glycerol tetraether (GDGT) and glycerol trialkyl glycerol tetraether (GTGT). Specifically, this research has been focused on the membranes containing the polar lipid fraction E (PLFE, 90% GDNT and 10% GDGT), a major BTL fraction found in <em>S. acidocaldarius</em>. PLFE lipids are macro-cyclic amphipathic and asymmetric compounds; the middle part of the molecules are hydrophobic and the two ends contain different polar moieties, with one end negatively charged at neutral pH and the other end not charged. In this project, various membrane-soluble fluorescent probes and fluorescence spectroscopy techniques have been used to investigate the micro-heterogeneity of PLFE lipid membranes in the water-membrane interfacial regions as well as the hydrophobic core regions at different membrane depths. In addition, dynamic light scattering and zeta potential measurements as well as Monte Carlo computer simulations have been employed.</p> <p><strong>Intellectual Merit:</strong></p> <p>Membrane micro-heterogeneity has emerged as an active research area in recent years. Previous studies in this area have been exclusively on diester lipid model membranes or mammalian/bacteria cell membranes. This project has been one of the first studies on membrane micro-heterogeneity in archaeal tetraether lipid membranes. Membrane micro-heterogeneity, such as the interfacial regions between gel and fluid lipid domains in the plane of the membrane and the order parameter at different membrane depths, has tremendous functional implications. Thus, the results obtained from this research could greatly improve the understanding of the structure-function relationship in archaeal lipid membranes. The major findings resulting from this project include: (1) A gradual increase in mobility, polarity and heterogeneity along the membrane longitudinal depth is a hallmark of fluid phase diester or diether phospholipid membranes. However, using a series of membrane depth-dependent fluorescent probes, and compared with membranes prepared from a typical diether lipid from higher organisms (eukaryotes), we found that such a gradual change in probe dynamics and heterogeneity with membrane depth is absent in PLFE archaeal tetraether lipid membranes; (2) It was found that the motions of solvent molecules (mainly water) around the probe Laurdan, which is located in the membrane surfaces of PLFE liposomes, are much more restricted, compared to those in non-archaeal lipid membranes, probably due to the strong hydrogen bonding network imposed by GDNT; (3) The amount and the orientation of the negatively-charged PLFE lipids in the membrane are important determinants of membrane properties such as zeta potential and extra-vesicular ion distributions in tetraether/diester phospholipid hybrid liposomes.</p> <p><strong>Broader Impacts:</strong></p> <p>Membranes made of archaeal bipolar tetraether lipids (BTLs) are extraordinarily stable against a variety of physical and chemical stressors and hold great promise for technological applications. It is conceivable that the results obtained from this study could facilitate and improve the design of BTL membrane-based biosensors and nanocarriers. Since BTLs are abundant not only in <em>S. acidocaldarius</em>, but also in virtually all crenarchaeota, which exist in a broad range of habitats and contribute significantly to the total biomass on Earth, this research could also have a profound implication in environmental biology and biomaterials availability. This research project has involved archaea growth, lipid isolation, liposome engineering and characterization, as well as fluorescence spectroscopy and the use of other biophysical approaches. Thus, it has been established as a rigorous multidisciplinary research training program. During the entire funding period, this project has been used to train two Ph.D. graduate students, one MS graduate student, and three undergraduate students, including one from historically underrepresented groups.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 04/30/2018<br>      Modified by: Parkson&nbsp;L&nbsp;Chong</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The goal of this research is to study the micro-heterogeneity of dynamics and lateral organization in membranes composed of bipolar tetraether lipids (BTL) derived from the thermoacidophilic archaeon Sulfolobus acidocaldarius. This micro-organism thrives at high temperatures (65-85oC) and low pHs (2-3). BTLs are the dominating lipid species in crenarchaeota including thermoacidophiles, and the chemical structures of BTLs are distinctly different from the structures of lipids found in animals and bacteria. Archaeal BTLs have different kinds such as glycerol dialky calditol tetraether (GDNT), glycerol dialky glycerol tetraether (GDGT) and glycerol trialkyl glycerol tetraether (GTGT). Specifically, this research has been focused on the membranes containing the polar lipid fraction E (PLFE, 90% GDNT and 10% GDGT), a major BTL fraction found in S. acidocaldarius. PLFE lipids are macro-cyclic amphipathic and asymmetric compounds; the middle part of the molecules are hydrophobic and the two ends contain different polar moieties, with one end negatively charged at neutral pH and the other end not charged. In this project, various membrane-soluble fluorescent probes and fluorescence spectroscopy techniques have been used to investigate the micro-heterogeneity of PLFE lipid membranes in the water-membrane interfacial regions as well as the hydrophobic core regions at different membrane depths. In addition, dynamic light scattering and zeta potential measurements as well as Monte Carlo computer simulations have been employed.  Intellectual Merit:  Membrane micro-heterogeneity has emerged as an active research area in recent years. Previous studies in this area have been exclusively on diester lipid model membranes or mammalian/bacteria cell membranes. This project has been one of the first studies on membrane micro-heterogeneity in archaeal tetraether lipid membranes. Membrane micro-heterogeneity, such as the interfacial regions between gel and fluid lipid domains in the plane of the membrane and the order parameter at different membrane depths, has tremendous functional implications. Thus, the results obtained from this research could greatly improve the understanding of the structure-function relationship in archaeal lipid membranes. The major findings resulting from this project include: (1) A gradual increase in mobility, polarity and heterogeneity along the membrane longitudinal depth is a hallmark of fluid phase diester or diether phospholipid membranes. However, using a series of membrane depth-dependent fluorescent probes, and compared with membranes prepared from a typical diether lipid from higher organisms (eukaryotes), we found that such a gradual change in probe dynamics and heterogeneity with membrane depth is absent in PLFE archaeal tetraether lipid membranes; (2) It was found that the motions of solvent molecules (mainly water) around the probe Laurdan, which is located in the membrane surfaces of PLFE liposomes, are much more restricted, compared to those in non-archaeal lipid membranes, probably due to the strong hydrogen bonding network imposed by GDNT; (3) The amount and the orientation of the negatively-charged PLFE lipids in the membrane are important determinants of membrane properties such as zeta potential and extra-vesicular ion distributions in tetraether/diester phospholipid hybrid liposomes.  Broader Impacts:  Membranes made of archaeal bipolar tetraether lipids (BTLs) are extraordinarily stable against a variety of physical and chemical stressors and hold great promise for technological applications. It is conceivable that the results obtained from this study could facilitate and improve the design of BTL membrane-based biosensors and nanocarriers. Since BTLs are abundant not only in S. acidocaldarius, but also in virtually all crenarchaeota, which exist in a broad range of habitats and contribute significantly to the total biomass on Earth, this research could also have a profound implication in environmental biology and biomaterials availability. This research project has involved archaea growth, lipid isolation, liposome engineering and characterization, as well as fluorescence spectroscopy and the use of other biophysical approaches. Thus, it has been established as a rigorous multidisciplinary research training program. During the entire funding period, this project has been used to train two Ph.D. graduate students, one MS graduate student, and three undergraduate students, including one from historically underrepresented groups.             Last Modified: 04/30/2018       Submitted by: Parkson L Chong]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
