<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>CAREER: Microassembly Using Transfer Printing for MEMS Fabrication</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>02/01/2014</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>01/31/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>400000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>400000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CMMI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Civil, Mechanical, &amp; Manufact Inn</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Steve Schmid</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The research objective of this Faculty Early Career Development (CAREER) Program award is to understand the fundamental limits of transfer printing regarding dry adhesion control and extend it to 3D additive micromanufacturing for the flexible production of microsystems. Transfer printing is a method to transfer solid materials from a substrate where they are generated to a different substrate by using controlled dry adhesion of elastomeric stamps. This approach in conjunction with material bonding techniques will enable the assembly of 3D microsystems with heterogeneous materials that cannot be realized by conventional monolithic microfabrication. As a step toward the research objective, shape memory polymer will be studied in terms of controllable dry adhesion to overcome the limit of elastomeric stamp-based transfer printing. Furthermore, the fundamental physical properties of interfaces formed by transfer printing will be characterized and laser assisted localized bonding will be exploited to establish transfer printing-based 3D additive micromanufacturing. The educational objective of this project is to transfer the experience and excitement of adhesion science and microscale engineering to students with diverse backgrounds. This will be accomplished by building teaching modules in adhesion science for K-12 outreach, developing course and curriculum in advanced micromanufacturing for undergraduate/graduate programs, and participating in existing outreach activities for underrepresented students at the University of Illinois.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Knowledge obtained from this research will complement and transform the manufacture of microsystems towards flexible, rapid, and cost-effective production. Microsystems, such as the miniaturization of large scale ordinary 3D machines, are indispensable for advancing modern technologies. Current hindrances to further innovations in microsystems encompass the difficulty of 3D manufacturing and the process complexity originated from the nature of layer-by-layer microfabrication. The outcomes from this award will mitigate these hindrances, thus greatly benefit microscale scientific research and the manufacturing sector in the USA by providing a new transformative methodology for 3D additive micromanufacturing.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>01/10/2014</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>01/10/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1351370</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Seok</FirstName>
<LastName>Kim</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Seok Kim</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>skm@illinois.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2172655656</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000600324</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>01/10/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign</Name>
<CityName>Champaign</CityName>
<ZipCode>618207406</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2173332187</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1901 South First Street</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[Suite A]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Illinois</StateName>
<StateCode>IL</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>13</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>IL13</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>041544081</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF ILLINOIS</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>041544081</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign]]></Name>
<CityName>Champaign</CityName>
<StateCode>IL</StateCode>
<ZipCode>618207473</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[1901 S. First Street, Suite A]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Illinois</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>13</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>IL13</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1468</Code>
<Text>Manufacturing Machines &amp; Equip</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>082E</Code>
<Text>MFG MACHINES &amp; METROLOGY</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>083E</Code>
<Text>MATERIAL TRANSFORMATION PROC</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1045</Code>
<Text>CAREER-Faculty Erly Career Dev</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0114</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~400000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><span>Over monolithic microfabrication, the heterogeneous integration via highly scalable and flexible deterministic microassembly of device-grade materials as well as mechanically soft materials is beginning to shape next-generation manufacturing technologies in diverse fields from electronics to microelectromechanical systems (MEMS). Through this project, the PI has established a microassembly called micro-LEGO which involves transfer printing for material transfer and thermal processing for material joining. Here, transfer printing is originally a method to transfer solid materials from a substrate where they are generated to a different substrate where they are utilized upon the controlled dry adhesion of an elastomer stamp. To establish micro-LEGO, the PI first explored a shape memory polymer and studied the related adhesion mechanics to replace an elastomer as a stamp material and advance transfer printing by eliminating challenges associated with an elastomer stamp. Second, the PI adopted well-established wafer bonding techniques at the microscale to join transfer-printed heterogeneous materials and studied their resultant interfacial joining characteristics. These microscale material transfer and joining strategies have enabled unusual 3D heterogeneous microscale architectures and 3D MEMS devices during the project. Furthermore, the PI exploited the transfer printing-based microassembly to produce elastomer-silicon hybrid functional materials which exhibit dynamically tunable surface functions including surface adhesion, wetting, reflectance, and coloration. These research efforts have also led to new lecture materials for courses that the PI teaches. Students involved in this project have had many educational and training opportunities which should help them be better prepared for emerging interdisciplinary fields.</span></p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 03/07/2019<br>      Modified by: Seok&nbsp;Kim</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Over monolithic microfabrication, the heterogeneous integration via highly scalable and flexible deterministic microassembly of device-grade materials as well as mechanically soft materials is beginning to shape next-generation manufacturing technologies in diverse fields from electronics to microelectromechanical systems (MEMS). Through this project, the PI has established a microassembly called micro-LEGO which involves transfer printing for material transfer and thermal processing for material joining. Here, transfer printing is originally a method to transfer solid materials from a substrate where they are generated to a different substrate where they are utilized upon the controlled dry adhesion of an elastomer stamp. To establish micro-LEGO, the PI first explored a shape memory polymer and studied the related adhesion mechanics to replace an elastomer as a stamp material and advance transfer printing by eliminating challenges associated with an elastomer stamp. Second, the PI adopted well-established wafer bonding techniques at the microscale to join transfer-printed heterogeneous materials and studied their resultant interfacial joining characteristics. These microscale material transfer and joining strategies have enabled unusual 3D heterogeneous microscale architectures and 3D MEMS devices during the project. Furthermore, the PI exploited the transfer printing-based microassembly to produce elastomer-silicon hybrid functional materials which exhibit dynamically tunable surface functions including surface adhesion, wetting, reflectance, and coloration. These research efforts have also led to new lecture materials for courses that the PI teaches. Students involved in this project have had many educational and training opportunities which should help them be better prepared for emerging interdisciplinary fields.       Last Modified: 03/07/2019       Submitted by: Seok Kim]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
