<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>CAREER: Interior 5D Micro-CT to Analyze Atherosclerotic Plaques In Vivo</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2014</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2020</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>400000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>400000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07020000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CBET</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Chem, Bioeng, Env, &amp; Transp Sys</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Leon Esterowitz</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>lesterow@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927942</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>#1351936&lt;br/&gt;P.I.: Guohua Cao&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project addresses contemporary challenges in atherosclerotic plaque imaging of small animals using state-of-the-art hardware components and modern reconstruction techniques, pushes a new frontier of biomedical imaging, and promotes new preclinical applications in mouse models. By synergistically integrating three separately developed components CNT source, Medipix detector, and interior tomography into a novel interior 5D micro-CT system, the resulted whole system is much more than the sum of the components. The system will provide significantly higher spatial and contrast resolution, finer temporal resolution, and lower radiation dose than the state-of-the-art micro-CT. It will transform the method for studying cardiovascular diseases in mice and rats, make a significant impact on atherosclerosis research through facilitating basic mechanistic studies in mice and advancing our knowledge on pathogenesis of atherosclerosis, and has potential in clinical assessment of vulnerable plaques.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>12/11/2013</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>12/11/2013</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1351936</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Guohua</FirstName>
<LastName>Cao</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Guohua Cao</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>ghcao@vt.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5402315686</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000624733</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>12/11/2013</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University</Name>
<CityName>BLACKSBURG</CityName>
<ZipCode>240610001</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5402315281</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>Sponsored Programs 0170</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[300 Turner Street NW, Suite 4200]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Virginia</StateName>
<StateCode>VA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>09</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>VA09</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>003137015</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>VIRGINIA POLYTECHNIC INSTITUTE AND STATE UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>003137015</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Virginia Polytechnic Institute  State University]]></Name>
<CityName>Blacksburg</CityName>
<StateCode>VA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>240603580</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[Office of Sponsored Programs]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Virginia</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>09</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>VA09</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7236</Code>
<Text>BioP-Biophotonics</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>005E</Code>
<Text>Neuro-photonics</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1045</Code>
<Text>CAREER-Faculty Erly Career Dev</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0114</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~400000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Micro-Computed Tomography (Micro-CT) is a powerful imaging tool for biomedical researchers in observing biological process, understanding disease mechanism, and developing therapeutic drugs or devices. It enables 3D tomographic imaging of biological bodies at high resolution.&nbsp; The research goal of this project is to advance the carbon nanotube (CNT) micro-CT technology that was previously developed by the PI's team to an unprecedented new level, with high spatial, temporal and contrast resolution as well as reduced radiation dose and cost. The aims of the integrated education component of the project are to train graduate and undergraduate students and develop new biomedical imaging courses for the recently established biomedical engineering program at Virginia Tech.</p> <p>Intellectual Merit: This project addressed contemporary challenges in micro-CT imaging of small animals. The project resulted in a proof-of-concept small-animal micro-CT imaging system that has the potential for high-resolution, high-speed, energy-sensitive and low-dose tomographic imaging of small animal models. The micro-CT scanner incorporated a CNT field emission X-ray source that was built in-house, a prototype energy-sensitive photon-counting X-ray detector, and more importantly, cutting-edge CT image reconstruction and image processing algorithms that were constantly being improved. The micro-CT scanner was used to perform experimental feasibility study in cardiac imaging of mice.&nbsp; The new micro-CT scanner significantly improved the spatial and contrast resolutions while reduced the radiation dose.</p> <p>This project has accomplished its three main goals: (i) A first-of-its-kind interior micro-CT scanner based on a CNT X-ray source and a photon-counting X-ray detector has been designed and constructed in the PI's laboratory; (ii) Interior tomography reconstruction algorithms for sparse-view CT sampling have been developed; and (iii) The micro-CT scanner performance has been evaluated, optimized with phantom experiments, and its feasibility and utility in region-of-interest (ROI) oriented high-resolution micro-CT imaging of mouse heart has been demonstrated. The micro-CT scanner can target a ROI of 10 mm in diameter, and provide image resolution at about 50 micrometers.&nbsp; The radiation risk from this novel micro-CT scanning mode can be reduced by up to 84%, compared to the typical radiation risk from a conventional micro-CT. &nbsp;The new image reconstruction and image processing algorithms developed for this project leveraged the recent advances in iterative reconstruction, deep learning, as well as physical model-based artifacts/scatter corrections. The micro-CT design and its image formation algorithms could potentially be transformed into a clinical CT counterpart.</p> <p>Broader Impacts: This project has significantly expanded our knowledge in biomedical imaging in general and improved the biomedical CT imaging technology in particular. Over its entire period of performance, this project has resulted in more than 20 peer-reviewed journal papers and over 20 conference papers. Moreover, over 10 graduate and undergraduate students have participated in the project, and two new biomedical engineering courses were developed for the aspiring biomedical engineering program at Virginia Tech. The advanced micro-CT imaging capability resulted from this project has also helped several investigators at Virginia Tech in their respective domains including biology, geoscience, as well as veterinary and clinical medicine.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 10/23/2020<br>      Modified by: Guohua&nbsp;Cao</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Micro-Computed Tomography (Micro-CT) is a powerful imaging tool for biomedical researchers in observing biological process, understanding disease mechanism, and developing therapeutic drugs or devices. It enables 3D tomographic imaging of biological bodies at high resolution.  The research goal of this project is to advance the carbon nanotube (CNT) micro-CT technology that was previously developed by the PI's team to an unprecedented new level, with high spatial, temporal and contrast resolution as well as reduced radiation dose and cost. The aims of the integrated education component of the project are to train graduate and undergraduate students and develop new biomedical imaging courses for the recently established biomedical engineering program at Virginia Tech.  Intellectual Merit: This project addressed contemporary challenges in micro-CT imaging of small animals. The project resulted in a proof-of-concept small-animal micro-CT imaging system that has the potential for high-resolution, high-speed, energy-sensitive and low-dose tomographic imaging of small animal models. The micro-CT scanner incorporated a CNT field emission X-ray source that was built in-house, a prototype energy-sensitive photon-counting X-ray detector, and more importantly, cutting-edge CT image reconstruction and image processing algorithms that were constantly being improved. The micro-CT scanner was used to perform experimental feasibility study in cardiac imaging of mice.  The new micro-CT scanner significantly improved the spatial and contrast resolutions while reduced the radiation dose.  This project has accomplished its three main goals: (i) A first-of-its-kind interior micro-CT scanner based on a CNT X-ray source and a photon-counting X-ray detector has been designed and constructed in the PI's laboratory; (ii) Interior tomography reconstruction algorithms for sparse-view CT sampling have been developed; and (iii) The micro-CT scanner performance has been evaluated, optimized with phantom experiments, and its feasibility and utility in region-of-interest (ROI) oriented high-resolution micro-CT imaging of mouse heart has been demonstrated. The micro-CT scanner can target a ROI of 10 mm in diameter, and provide image resolution at about 50 micrometers.  The radiation risk from this novel micro-CT scanning mode can be reduced by up to 84%, compared to the typical radiation risk from a conventional micro-CT.  The new image reconstruction and image processing algorithms developed for this project leveraged the recent advances in iterative reconstruction, deep learning, as well as physical model-based artifacts/scatter corrections. The micro-CT design and its image formation algorithms could potentially be transformed into a clinical CT counterpart.  Broader Impacts: This project has significantly expanded our knowledge in biomedical imaging in general and improved the biomedical CT imaging technology in particular. Over its entire period of performance, this project has resulted in more than 20 peer-reviewed journal papers and over 20 conference papers. Moreover, over 10 graduate and undergraduate students have participated in the project, and two new biomedical engineering courses were developed for the aspiring biomedical engineering program at Virginia Tech. The advanced micro-CT imaging capability resulted from this project has also helped several investigators at Virginia Tech in their respective domains including biology, geoscience, as well as veterinary and clinical medicine.          Last Modified: 10/23/2020       Submitted by: Guohua Cao]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
