<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>A Combined Experimental-Computational Method to Evaluate Abdominal Aortic Aneurysm Wall Stress</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2012</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>09/30/2015</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>284835.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>308835</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CMMI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Civil, Mechanical, &amp; Manufact Inn</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>David Fyhrie</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>dfyhrie@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032920000</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>PROJECT ABSTRACT&lt;br/&gt;Intellectual Merit:&lt;br/&gt;Abdominal aortic aneurysms (AAAs) represent permanent, localized swellings of the aorta that occur where the diseased vessel is weakened.  AAA rupture accounts for 14,000 deaths in the US annually.  A growing body of literature has developed in recent years concerned with methods for quantitatively evaluating the distribution and magnitude of stress in patient-specific models of the aneurysm wall, since mechanical stress is thought to be the cause of rupture.  However, the role of blood flow in creating wall stress has not been addressed to date.  Accordingly, the research objective of this award is to develop a combined experimental-computational physiologic wall stress analysis (PWSA) procedure that evaluates wall stress distributions and maxima in models accurately replicating the shape, non-uniform thickness and mechanical properties of individual patient AAAs.  To accomplish this aim, AAA wall tissue samples will be collected from patients undergoing surgical repair.  The mechanical properties of those samples will be measured, and an elastic material replicating the diseased wall stiffness will be used to fabricate a model replicating the shape of the patient lesion.  Wall pressure in this model will be measured under flow conditions emulating the patient aorta.  The measured wall pressure data will then be used as loading in a corresponding computational evaluation of stress levels within the wall.&lt;br/&gt;Broader Impact:&lt;br/&gt;Establishment of a protocol for accurate assessment of AAA wall stress using patient-specific information has the potential to significantly impact clinical AAA management.  The proposed studies will provide the first quantitative measurements of pressure distributions using aneurysm phantoms with both realistic geometries and patient-derived mechanical properties, as well as the first quantitative evaluation of wall stress based entirely on patient properties.  Furthermore, the project will permit us to continue to engage undergraduate as well as graduate students in our ongoing research efforts, expanding the research training, educational experience and opportunities available to the students involved.  Moreover, we will take full advantage of infrastructure in place at Tufts University for recruiting and retaining women and underrepresented minorities in research.  These include undergraduate outreach programs in Computer Science, Biomedical Engineering and robotics.  In addition, the Tufts University School of Medicine has conducted a highly successful NIH-funded minority outreach program for over ten years, permitting underrepresented undergraduates to spend summers at Tufts involved in biomedical science research.  Research-driven training activities generated through this project will engage students in cross-disciplinary computational thinking, thus providing critical training for future scientists and engineers.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/08/2013</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/08/2013</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1352955</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Robert</FirstName>
<LastName>Peattie</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>A</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Robert A Peattie</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>robert.peattie@tufts.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6176365992</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000113966</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/08/2013</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Tufts Medical Center, Inc</Name>
<CityName>Boston</CityName>
<ZipCode>021111552</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6176362892</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>800 Washington Street</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
<StateCode>MA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MA07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>079532263</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>TUFTS MEDICAL CENTER, INC.</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>061552123</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Tufts Medical Center]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>MA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>021111552</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MA07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7479</Code>
<Text>BMMB-Biomech &amp; Mechanobiology</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>024E</Code>
<Text>MATERIALS DESIGN</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>027E</Code>
<Text>NANOMECHANICS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>028E</Code>
<Text>BIOMECHANICS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>036E</Code>
<Text>CIVIL INFRASTRUCTURE</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1057</Code>
<Text>CIS BASE RESEARCH</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>116E</Code>
<Text>RESEARCH EXP FOR UNDERGRADS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9178</Code>
<Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9231</Code>
<Text>SUPPL FOR UNDERGRAD RES ASSIST</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9251</Code>
<Text>REU SUPP-Res Exp for Ugrd Supp</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0110</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0111</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0112</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2010~284835</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2011~12000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2012~12000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; The long-term goal of this research is to develop a computational protocol capable of accurately evaluating risk of rupture for abdominal aortic aneurysms (AAAs).&nbsp; In particular, the goal of this specific project was to develop and evaluate a physiologic wall stress analysis procedure; that is, a computational technique to evaluate the distribution and maximum levels of mechanical wall stress in aortic aneurysm walls with physiologic realism.&nbsp; This is very important, since mechanical stress is the physical cause of aneurysm rupture.&nbsp; The analysis procedure was to make use of models accurately replicating the exact shape of individual patient aneurysms, with loading derived from corresponding experimental measurements in phantoms fabricated with wall stiffness matching patient-derived material properties, under flow conditions found in the aorta.&nbsp; Outcomes of the project were as follows.</p> <p><span style="text-decoration: underline;">Intellectual merit:</span>&nbsp; All procedures were carried out with the full approval of the Tufts Institutional Review Board.&nbsp; First, AAA wall tissue samples were obtained from a series of patients undergoing surgical repair at Tufts Medical Center (TMC, Figure 1).&nbsp; These tissue samples were brought to the laboratory and their properties were measured.&nbsp; Examination under a microscopic showed them to have highly disorganized cell and fiber structures that would not normally be seen in healthy aortas (Figure 2).&nbsp; In mechanical testing, the tissue samples showed the J-shaped increase of stiffness with increasing stretch that is typical of all aortas, but also exhibited pronounced differences in stiffness with direction of stretch, much larger than those typical of healthy aortas (Figure 3). &nbsp;A set of synthetic materials reproducing the patient mechanical properties were then developed.&nbsp; These consisted of a base casting elastomer on which a layer of stiff mesh was deposited.&nbsp; The most successful of these composite materials used Dow Corning Sylgard 170 (Dow Corning, Inc.) or Dragon Skin 20 (Smooth-on, Inc.) as the base material, reinforced with 100% pure silk thread.&nbsp; Varying the spacing of the thread allowed the behavior of the patient tissue to be emulated accurately.</p> <p>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; Separately, a series of wall pressure measurements were carried out in models replicating the shape of individual patient AAAs under flow conditions matching the <em>in vivo</em> aorta.&nbsp; The distribution of wall stress in these models was then calculated using the pressure measurements as loading.&nbsp; Results of these calculations showed that wall stress in the models could reach levels exceeding the strength of the wall to resist (Figure 4).&nbsp; As a result, these patients would be considered to be at high risk of rupture.</p> <p>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; In a related aim, a mathematical model of AAA growth was created based on turnover of collagen fibers in the AAA wall.&nbsp; The model showed that growth rate could be predicted for patients by optimally adjusting the rates of old collagen loss and new collagen deposition.&nbsp; Finally, in a spin-off project, CT image series of past patients undergoing AAA surgical repair at TMC were examined to look for features correlating with unsuccessful repair.&nbsp; It was found that patients with bulges of high tortuosity were at significantly greater risk for repair failures than were patients with low tortuosity bulges.</p> <p><span style="text-decoration: underline;">Broad impact:</span>&nbsp; In due course, the results of this project are expected to improve the ability to determine and forecast risk of rupture for specific patient AAAs.&nbsp; The project has shown that proper accounting for aorta blood flow can improve the accuracy of wall stre...]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[         The long-term goal of this research is to develop a computational protocol capable of accurately evaluating risk of rupture for abdominal aortic aneurysms (AAAs).  In particular, the goal of this specific project was to develop and evaluate a physiologic wall stress analysis procedure; that is, a computational technique to evaluate the distribution and maximum levels of mechanical wall stress in aortic aneurysm walls with physiologic realism.  This is very important, since mechanical stress is the physical cause of aneurysm rupture.  The analysis procedure was to make use of models accurately replicating the exact shape of individual patient aneurysms, with loading derived from corresponding experimental measurements in phantoms fabricated with wall stiffness matching patient-derived material properties, under flow conditions found in the aorta.  Outcomes of the project were as follows.  Intellectual merit:  All procedures were carried out with the full approval of the Tufts Institutional Review Board.  First, AAA wall tissue samples were obtained from a series of patients undergoing surgical repair at Tufts Medical Center (TMC, Figure 1).  These tissue samples were brought to the laboratory and their properties were measured.  Examination under a microscopic showed them to have highly disorganized cell and fiber structures that would not normally be seen in healthy aortas (Figure 2).  In mechanical testing, the tissue samples showed the J-shaped increase of stiffness with increasing stretch that is typical of all aortas, but also exhibited pronounced differences in stiffness with direction of stretch, much larger than those typical of healthy aortas (Figure 3).  A set of synthetic materials reproducing the patient mechanical properties were then developed.  These consisted of a base casting elastomer on which a layer of stiff mesh was deposited.  The most successful of these composite materials used Dow Corning Sylgard 170 (Dow Corning, Inc.) or Dragon Skin 20 (Smooth-on, Inc.) as the base material, reinforced with 100% pure silk thread.  Varying the spacing of the thread allowed the behavior of the patient tissue to be emulated accurately.          Separately, a series of wall pressure measurements were carried out in models replicating the shape of individual patient AAAs under flow conditions matching the in vivo aorta.  The distribution of wall stress in these models was then calculated using the pressure measurements as loading.  Results of these calculations showed that wall stress in the models could reach levels exceeding the strength of the wall to resist (Figure 4).  As a result, these patients would be considered to be at high risk of rupture.          In a related aim, a mathematical model of AAA growth was created based on turnover of collagen fibers in the AAA wall.  The model showed that growth rate could be predicted for patients by optimally adjusting the rates of old collagen loss and new collagen deposition.  Finally, in a spin-off project, CT image series of past patients undergoing AAA surgical repair at TMC were examined to look for features correlating with unsuccessful repair.  It was found that patients with bulges of high tortuosity were at significantly greater risk for repair failures than were patients with low tortuosity bulges.  Broad impact:  In due course, the results of this project are expected to improve the ability to determine and forecast risk of rupture for specific patient AAAs.  The project has shown that proper accounting for aorta blood flow can improve the accuracy of wall stress analysis.  Further, in addition to the scientific activities, the project also included a major outreach aspect intended to bring the project to wider attention beyond the immediate scientific community and to use the project to stimulate interest in scientific and medical careers among high school students.  In this outreach program, a set of high school students and teachers carry out internship...]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
