<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>EAGER: Student Outcomes in a Computer Science MOOC (SOCSMOOC)</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/15/2013</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>299995.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>299995</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>11040200</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>EHR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DUE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Undergraduate Education</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Victor Piotrowski</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>vpiotrow@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032925141</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This EAGER project seeks to study a Massive Open Online Course (MOOC) offered by HarvardX, an experiment created in response to a need by Harvard faculty for a central resource to help them push the boundaries of learning through re-imagined teaching and to take advantage of new possibilities for educational research in the online era. The topic of the study is "Introduction to Computer Science", a course with the largest initial enrollment of all of Harvard's MOOCs (150,349), as well as the second largest enrollment of all of Harvard's traditionally taught courses (714). Two versions of this course, CS50x and CS50, share many features (lectures, problem sets, exams, and projects), but differ in grading, student feedback, and classroom interactivity. Unlike the traditional course which has a 99.6% completion rate, CS50x awards completion certificates to only 6.3% of those who enroll. This presents an opportunity to study high attrition rates in MOOCS, a problem that plagues online courses nationwide. Little is known about why students do not finish MOOCs. Are there disparities in completion rates by gender, minorities underrepresented in STEM, age of students, language fluency? The project gathers empirical evidence in the CS50x MOOC to create a profile of the enrolled students and to determine which factors in their background, in their prior experience with computing, and in their learning behaviors during the course, predict successful completion of the course. Statistical survival analysis will be used to model the risk of dropping out. The broader impact of the project is that, by characterizing factors that positively and negatively influence students' success in MOOCs, it will allow for more informed, and hence more potentially effective, pedagogical and institutional policies aimed at increasing student success and broadening participation.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/15/2013</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/21/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.076</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1352696</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Philip</FirstName>
<LastName>Sadler</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>M</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Philip M Sadler</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>psadler@cfa.harvard.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6179055540</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000110731</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/15/2013</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Gerhard</FirstName>
<LastName>Sonnert</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Gerhard Sonnert</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>gsonnert@cfa.harvard.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6174958248</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000498138</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/15/2013</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Harvard University</Name>
<CityName>Cambridge</CityName>
<ZipCode>021385369</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6174955501</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1033 MASSACHUSETTS AVE</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[5th Floor]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
<StateCode>MA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MA05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>082359691</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>PRESIDENT AND FELLOWS OF HARVARD COLLEGE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>001963263</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Harvard University]]></Name>
<CityName>Cambridge</CityName>
<StateCode>MA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>021383846</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[60 Garden Street]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MA05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1536</Code>
<Text>S-STEM-Schlr Sci Tech Eng&amp;Math</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7513</Code>
<Text>TUES-Type 1 Project</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7916</Code>
<Text>EAGER</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9178</Code>
<Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>SMET</Code>
<Text>SCIENCE, MATH, ENG &amp; TECH EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0413</Code>
<Name>NSF Education &amp; Human Resource</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040106</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>13XX</Code>
<Name>H-1B FUND, EHR, NSF</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>045176</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2013~299995</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Massive Open Online Courses (MOOCs), which are college courses offered online to the general public and which are typically available for free and do not offer college credits, have recently sprung up and have greatly multiplied amidst great fanfare. They have been taunted as a potentially transformative phenomenon in college-level education and specifically in science education.</p> <p>The goal of this study was to examine the experience of students with a MOOC and the factors that positively and negatively influenced their persistence in it. The data came from the Harvard University MOOC CS50x, <em>Introduction to Computer Science, </em>which was produced by HarvardX, a member of the EdX MOOC consortium of prestigious institutions of higher education.</p> <p>The key findings include:</p> <p>1. Very few participants completed the MOOC (in the 1% range, depending on the definitions of participation and completion).</p> <p>2. Participants took a variety of paths through the MOOC (not only the linear path designated by the MOOC sequence).</p> <p>3. Of the tested predictors of student dropout in survival models, we found:</p> <p>3.a. Predictors that made no difference:</p> <p>Students&rsquo; education levels.</p> <p>Students&rsquo; self-reported English fluency.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>3.b. Predictors that made a difference throughout the MOOC:</p> <p>Students from outside the U.S had higher dropout rates throughout.</p> <p>Students who played more computer games had higher dropout rates throughout.</p> <p>Students with lower motivation had higher dropout rates throughout.</p> <p>Students currently in school had higher dropout rates throughout.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>3.c. Predictors that made a difference at the beginning of the MOOC, but then attenuated:</p> <p>Females had higher dropout rates than males initially, but not in the later parts of the MOOC.</p> <p>Students with a low computer readiness score (pretest) had higher dropout rates than those with high scores initially, but not in the later parts of the MOOC.</p> <p>Students with a no prior computer science experience had higher dropout rates than those with such experience initially, but not in the later parts of the MOOC.</p> <p>Younger students had higher dropout rates than older students initially, but not in the later parts of the MOOC.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 10/30/2017<br>      Modified by: Philip&nbsp;M&nbsp;Sadler</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Images (<span id="selectedPhoto0">1</span> of <span class="totalNumber"></span>)           </div> <div class="galControls" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1352696/1352696_10267986_1509389687734_SurvivalAnalysis--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1352696/1352696_10267986_1509389687734_SurvivalAnalysis--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Survial Analysis"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1352696/1352696_10267986_1509389687734_SurvivalAnalysis--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Survial Analysis"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Figure 2. Separately plotting the early challengers by those who passed and those who failed in their challenges to the final exam</div> <div class="imageCredit">Chen Chen</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Public Domain</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Philip&nbsp;M&nbsp;Sadler</div> <div class="imageTitle">Survial Analysis</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1352696/1352696_10267986_1509388701398_Figure1--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1352696/1352696_10267986_1509388701398_Figure1--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Sankey diagram"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1352696/1352696_10267986_1509388701398_Figure1--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Sankey diagram"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Figure 1. Sankey diagram for all paths that have been taken by all enrollees. The nodes represent psets (P1 ? P8), the pretest (Pre), the final exam (FINAL), and dropping out of the MOOC (DROP). The link between nodes represent the transitional pathways, and the widths of the links are proportional</div> <div class="imageCredit">Chen Chen</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Public Domain</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Philip&nbsp;M&nbsp;Sadler</div> <div class="imageTitle">Sankey diagram</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Massive Open Online Courses (MOOCs), which are college courses offered online to the general public and which are typically available for free and do not offer college credits, have recently sprung up and have greatly multiplied amidst great fanfare. They have been taunted as a potentially transformative phenomenon in college-level education and specifically in science education.  The goal of this study was to examine the experience of students with a MOOC and the factors that positively and negatively influenced their persistence in it. The data came from the Harvard University MOOC CS50x, Introduction to Computer Science, which was produced by HarvardX, a member of the EdX MOOC consortium of prestigious institutions of higher education.  The key findings include:  1. Very few participants completed the MOOC (in the 1% range, depending on the definitions of participation and completion).  2. Participants took a variety of paths through the MOOC (not only the linear path designated by the MOOC sequence).  3. Of the tested predictors of student dropout in survival models, we found:  3.a. Predictors that made no difference:  Students? education levels.  Students? self-reported English fluency.     3.b. Predictors that made a difference throughout the MOOC:  Students from outside the U.S had higher dropout rates throughout.  Students who played more computer games had higher dropout rates throughout.  Students with lower motivation had higher dropout rates throughout.  Students currently in school had higher dropout rates throughout.     3.c. Predictors that made a difference at the beginning of the MOOC, but then attenuated:  Females had higher dropout rates than males initially, but not in the later parts of the MOOC.  Students with a low computer readiness score (pretest) had higher dropout rates than those with high scores initially, but not in the later parts of the MOOC.  Students with a no prior computer science experience had higher dropout rates than those with such experience initially, but not in the later parts of the MOOC.  Younger students had higher dropout rates than older students initially, but not in the later parts of the MOOC.       Last Modified: 10/30/2017       Submitted by: Philip M Sadler]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
