<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>pH, Oxygen and Nitrate Chemical Sensors for Southern Ocean Floats</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>10/01/2013</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>09/30/2015</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>135375.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>135375</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>06090300</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>GEO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>OPP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Office of Polar Programs (OPP)</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Peter Milne</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>pmilne@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924714</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The proposal will build and validate a set of 6 pH and nitrate sensors for profiling floats that will be deployed in the Southern Ocean. These sensors will be integrated with floats supplied by the University of Washington Float lab. In addition to the pH and oxygen sensors, the floats will also carry fluorescence optode oxygen sensors together with biooptical sensors for chlorophyll fluorescence and backscatter. Each float will operate for approximately 330 profiles from 1700 m depth to the surface. This should equate to a 5 year endurance at profiling intervals near 7 days. The profiling floats will be deployed along the decadal CLIVAR P16S cruise, scheduled to leave New Zealand in March 2014. The P16S line will go north from the ice edge along 150 degrees W. Three of the floats with chemical sensors will be deployed at latitudes where there should be seasonal ice cover and three will be deployed to the north of the ice covered ocean.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The pH data collected by the floats should provide one of the first records of the annual cycle of pH in a region that is expected to become undersaturated with aragonite as atmospheric CO2 continues to increase. This will allow a unique assessment of the ability of current generation climate models to predict ocean pH trajectories.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/09/2013</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/09/2013</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.078</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1353177</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Kenneth</FirstName>
<LastName>Johnson</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>S</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Kenneth S Johnson</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>johnson@mbari.org</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>8317751985</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000427227</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/09/2013</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Monterey Bay Aquarium Research Institute</Name>
<CityName>MOSS LANDING</CityName>
<ZipCode>950399644</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>8317751803</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>7700 SANDHOLDT RD</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>20</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CA20</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>178341772</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>MONTEREY BAY AQUARIUM RESEARCH INSTITUTE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[MBARI]]></Name>
<CityName>Moss Landing</CityName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>950399644</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[7700 Sandholdt Road]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>20</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CA20</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>5113</Code>
<Text>ANT Ocean &amp; Atmos Sciences</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7916</Code>
<Text>EAGER</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>02XX</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2013~135375</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The ecosystem function of the Southern Ocean is seldom observed on a regular basis because of the great difficulty and expense in operating ships in such remote regions.&nbsp; Yet this is one of the regions of the ocean that may be most impacted by a changing environment. In our work, we deployed an array of robots and sensors into the Pacific sector of the Southern Ocean from the ice edge up to 40&deg;N along 150&deg;W to provide a first order assessment of ecosystem functioning.&nbsp; These sensors monitor the cycling of essential chemical elements that are driven by biological and physical processes.</p> <p>The basic metabolism of the open ocean can be monitored with chemical and biological sensors mounted on profiling floats of the type used in the Argo array.&nbsp; Profiling floats cycle from depths near 2 km to the surface, making physical, chemical and biological measurements.&nbsp; The data is transmitted by satellite and immediately made available for analysis on the internet. These floats and sensors can operate for years and, in the open waters of the Southern Ocean, this enables the first &nbsp;year around view of biologically driven cycles of ocean chemistry.&nbsp; These cycles provide a basic assessment of the rates of oxygen production by photosynthesis, carbon production during respiration and the uptake of essential plant nutrients.&nbsp;</p> <p>We deployed an array of 12 profiling floats equipped with pH, oxygen, nitrate and biooptical sensors from March through April, 2014.&nbsp; Floats were deployed from the US GO-SHIP P16S cruise (Photo by Isa Rosso).&nbsp; One float failed on deployment.&nbsp; The other 11 have transmitted data continuously since then.&nbsp; This includes floats that have operated under sea ice in winter, which provided the first view of chemical cycles at the ice edge.&nbsp; An example of the data being collected by these floats is shown in Fig. 1.&nbsp; The panels in this plot show the time series in the upper 500 m of the water column for temperature and mixing depth (MLD), Particulate Organic Carbon (a tracer of plankton biomass), percent saturation of the water with oxygen, nitrate concentration, pH, Dissolved Inorganic Carbon (DIC), surface water pCO2 (partial pressure of carbon dioxide gas) and a map of the float trajectory as it drifter over the past 20 months.</p> <p>Now that full annual cycles of data are available from each float, the results will be analyzed to determine rates of biological cycling, ocean uptake of carbon dioxide, and a variety of other processes.&nbsp; &nbsp;Much of this work is being done by graduate students and postdoctoral scholars in the SOCCOM program and it is an essential component of their training.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 12/22/2015<br>      Modified by: Kenneth&nbsp;S&nbsp;Johnson</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Images (<span id="selectedPhoto0">1</span> of <span class="totalNumber"></span>)           </div> <div class="galControls" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2015/1353177/1353177_10265568_1450821070491_Photo--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2015/1353177/1353177_10265568_1450821070491_Photo--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Profiling float launch"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2015/1353177/1353177_10265568_1450821070491_Photo--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Profiling float launch"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">A profiling float launch of the GO-SHIP P16S cruise.  Photo by Isa Rosso.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Isa Rosso</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Pub...]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The ecosystem function of the Southern Ocean is seldom observed on a regular basis because of the great difficulty and expense in operating ships in such remote regions.  Yet this is one of the regions of the ocean that may be most impacted by a changing environment. In our work, we deployed an array of robots and sensors into the Pacific sector of the Southern Ocean from the ice edge up to 40&deg;N along 150&deg;W to provide a first order assessment of ecosystem functioning.  These sensors monitor the cycling of essential chemical elements that are driven by biological and physical processes.  The basic metabolism of the open ocean can be monitored with chemical and biological sensors mounted on profiling floats of the type used in the Argo array.  Profiling floats cycle from depths near 2 km to the surface, making physical, chemical and biological measurements.  The data is transmitted by satellite and immediately made available for analysis on the internet. These floats and sensors can operate for years and, in the open waters of the Southern Ocean, this enables the first  year around view of biologically driven cycles of ocean chemistry.  These cycles provide a basic assessment of the rates of oxygen production by photosynthesis, carbon production during respiration and the uptake of essential plant nutrients.   We deployed an array of 12 profiling floats equipped with pH, oxygen, nitrate and biooptical sensors from March through April, 2014.  Floats were deployed from the US GO-SHIP P16S cruise (Photo by Isa Rosso).  One float failed on deployment.  The other 11 have transmitted data continuously since then.  This includes floats that have operated under sea ice in winter, which provided the first view of chemical cycles at the ice edge.  An example of the data being collected by these floats is shown in Fig. 1.  The panels in this plot show the time series in the upper 500 m of the water column for temperature and mixing depth (MLD), Particulate Organic Carbon (a tracer of plankton biomass), percent saturation of the water with oxygen, nitrate concentration, pH, Dissolved Inorganic Carbon (DIC), surface water pCO2 (partial pressure of carbon dioxide gas) and a map of the float trajectory as it drifter over the past 20 months.  Now that full annual cycles of data are available from each float, the results will be analyzed to determine rates of biological cycling, ocean uptake of carbon dioxide, and a variety of other processes.   Much of this work is being done by graduate students and postdoctoral scholars in the SOCCOM program and it is an essential component of their training.          Last Modified: 12/22/2015       Submitted by: Kenneth S Johnson]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
