<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>IDBR: TYPE B: High temperature MEMS flow controller for MEMS enabled chopper-modulated gas chromatography - electroantennography (MEMS- GC-EAG) and other GC applications</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2014</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>443257.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>443257</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>08080000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>BIO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DBI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Biological Infrastructure</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Robert Fleischmann</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>rfleisch@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927191</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>An award is made to the Pennsylvania State University to develop a microfabricated high-temperature flow control device for gas chromatography (GC) applications that will benefit agriculture and forestry to better target invasive species and pests.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Non Technical Abstract:&lt;br/&gt;The device will enable a technique named chopper-modulated electroantennograph (EAG), which uses GC to separate volatile odorants, and insect antennae as detectors to identify specific compounds that are of importance to, and able to be sensed by the insect. As a result of millions of years of evolution, insect antennae are capable of detecting certain chemicals more sensitively and specifically than artificial chemical sensors. The chopper-modulated GC-EAG method will use the proposed flow control device to regulate gas flow in GC and improve the signal-to-noise ratio of the EAG, with a resulting several orders of magnitude improvement in detection sensitivity for behaviorally important volatile chemicals.  The use of the proposed device in other GC applications can potentially contribute to the general chemical sensing community and benefit the society with more sensitive analysis for environmental monitoring, food safety, disease diagnostics and etc. The education plan includes student training and curriculum development. The instrument will also be integrated into various outreach activities including the annual PSU "Great Insect Fair", at which attendance routinely surpasses 8,000 people annually.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Technical Abstract:&lt;br/&gt;The overall goal of the research is to develop a high temperature microelectromechanical system (MEMS) flow controller (HT-MEMS flow controller) whose purpose is to operate inside a conventional gas chromatography (GC) oven to enable chopper-modulated electroantennograph (EAG) &amp;#8722; MEMS- GC-EAG as well as other GC applications. This project aims to develop and lead to commercialization of the HT-MEMS flow controller to (1) implement chopper stabilization for GC-EAG, which holds the promise of improving the sensitivity of the current GC-EAG system by orders of magnitude; (2) explore applications of the instrument in broader chemical sensing areas, including other GC detectors beyond EAG and two dimensional GC (2D-GC). Apart from resulting publications and presentations at workshops and meetings, the technology will be disseminated through a partnership with GC equipment manufacturers and distributors.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/04/2014</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/04/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.074</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1353870</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Thomas</FirstName>
<LastName>Baker</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>C</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Thomas C Baker</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>tcb10@psu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>8148651895</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000282333</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/04/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Siyang</FirstName>
<LastName>Zheng</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Siyang Zheng</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>sxz10@psu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>8148658090</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000572778</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/04/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Pennsylvania State Univ University Park</Name>
<CityName>University Park</CityName>
<ZipCode>168021503</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>8148651372</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>201 Old Main</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Pennsylvania</StateName>
<StateCode>PA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>PA05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>003403953</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>PENNSYLVANIA STATE UNIVERSITY, THE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>003403953</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Pennsylvania State Univ University Park]]></Name>
<CityName>University Park</CityName>
<StateCode>PA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>168021503</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[201 Old Main]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Pennsylvania</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>PA05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1108</Code>
<Text>INSTRUMENTAT &amp; INSTRUMENT DEVP</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8007</Code>
<Text>BioMaPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9179</Code>
<Text>GRADUATE INVOLVEMENT</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0114</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~443257</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Coupled gas chromatography electroantennography (GC-EAG) is a conventional technique used to study the volatile organic chemicals used by insects for mating and finding host plants. These special and low concentration chemicals have been shown to benefit agriculture and forestry against endemic and invasive pest species, with pheromones having achieved wide commercial success, especially in organic agriculture. Some novel sex pheromone chemical blends are now used by growers all over the world for mating disruption and population monitoring.&nbsp; In conventional GC-EAG, signals from these unusual chemicals, often emitted by female moths at only trillionths of a gram per minute, are sometimes buried in noise signals on a gas chromatograph recording and cannot easily been detected. We developed a method to reject the noise in GC-EAG analyses, thereby boosting the detection sensitivity of important bio-active compounds by orders of magnitude. To enable this method, we designed and manufactured a microdevice that can operate under high temperatures up to 400 degrees Celsius, that may occur in analytical instruments such as gas chromatographs. The microdevice interrupts the gas flow with a specified frequency, and the gas carrying trace amounts of bioactive compounds flowing over detectors such as an insect antenna then evokes greater signal strength from the detectors than if the flow were continuous. Advanced signal processing then removes the background noise from the EAG detector that is usually caused by spurious compounds, to further help the real signal from bio-active target compounds to stand out. We successfully demonstrated the new technology, used it in entomology research, and made it available to the research community.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 11/29/2017<br>      Modified by: Siyang&nbsp;Zheng</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Coupled gas chromatography electroantennography (GC-EAG) is a conventional technique used to study the volatile organic chemicals used by insects for mating and finding host plants. These special and low concentration chemicals have been shown to benefit agriculture and forestry against endemic and invasive pest species, with pheromones having achieved wide commercial success, especially in organic agriculture. Some novel sex pheromone chemical blends are now used by growers all over the world for mating disruption and population monitoring.  In conventional GC-EAG, signals from these unusual chemicals, often emitted by female moths at only trillionths of a gram per minute, are sometimes buried in noise signals on a gas chromatograph recording and cannot easily been detected. We developed a method to reject the noise in GC-EAG analyses, thereby boosting the detection sensitivity of important bio-active compounds by orders of magnitude. To enable this method, we designed and manufactured a microdevice that can operate under high temperatures up to 400 degrees Celsius, that may occur in analytical instruments such as gas chromatographs. The microdevice interrupts the gas flow with a specified frequency, and the gas carrying trace amounts of bioactive compounds flowing over detectors such as an insect antenna then evokes greater signal strength from the detectors than if the flow were continuous. Advanced signal processing then removes the background noise from the EAG detector that is usually caused by spurious compounds, to further help the real signal from bio-active target compounds to stand out. We successfully demonstrated the new technology, used it in entomology research, and made it available to the research community.       Last Modified: 11/29/2017       Submitted by: Siyang Zheng]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
