<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Autophagy and ER stress in plants</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>02/15/2014</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>01/31/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>437816.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>437816</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>08090300</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>BIO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>IOS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Integrative Organismal Systems</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Gerald Schoenknecht</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>gschoenk@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032925076</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Diane C Bassham&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Proposal number IOS- 1353867, Autophagy and ER stress in plants.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Tolerance of changing environmental conditions is critical for plant growth and survival as they are unable to seek refuge from the environment. A key unresolved issue is how plants adapt their cellular functions to respond to stress conditions such as heat and drought. Two pathways required for stress tolerance are autophagy, in which damaged cell components are broken down and recycled, and the unfolded protein response, in which misfolded proteins activate the expression of genes that mitigate stress damage. In this project, the relationship between these two pathways will be examined. Additional proteins that are required for the regulation of both of these pathways will be identified and their functions analyzed by a combination of biochemical, cell biology and genetic approaches. The mechanism by which cells select substrates for recycling by autophagy will also be determined. This will provide insight into how plants sense adverse environmental conditions, how stress response pathways are then activated and how different responses work together to produce stress tolerance. The results of this project could provide information leading to the production of stress tolerant varieties of agriculturally important plants. The project will provide research training in plant genetics, cell and molecular biology for graduate and undergraduate students. In addition, the results of the research will be incorporated into a module of the Meta!Blast educational video game to help undergraduate and high school students learn cell biology. Seed stocks and plasmids generated in the course of the research will be donated to the Arabidopsis Biological Resource Center for distribution to the scientific community.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>02/11/2014</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>02/03/2015</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.074</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1353867</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Stephen</FirstName>
<LastName>Howell</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>H</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Stephen H Howell</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>SHH@iastate.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5152945737</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000387578</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>02/11/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Diane</FirstName>
<LastName>Bassham</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>C</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Diane C Bassham</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>bassham@iastate.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5152947461</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000318488</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>02/11/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Iowa State University</Name>
<CityName>AMES</CityName>
<ZipCode>500112207</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5152945225</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1138 Pearson</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Iowa</StateName>
<StateCode>IA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>IA04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>005309844</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>IOWA STATE UNIVERSITY OF SCIENCE AND TECHNOLOGY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>005309844</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Iowa State University]]></Name>
<CityName>Ames</CityName>
<StateCode>IA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>500112207</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[1043 Carver Co-Lab]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Iowa</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>IA04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7658</Code>
<Text>Physiolgcl Mechnsms&amp;Biomechnsm</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9178</Code>
<Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9179</Code>
<Text>GRADUATE INVOLVEMENT</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0114</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0115</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~213765</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2015~224051</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Due to the growing concern about the adaptation of plants to climate change, we have examined the response of plants to adverse environmental conditions.&nbsp; Such conditions, such as heat, salt stress and drought, upset proteostasis, the normal process by which plants maintain quality control over the proteins they make.&nbsp; Adverse environmental conditions disrupt the delicate process of protein folding leading to an accumulation of misfolded proteins in the plant cell&rsquo;s endoplasmic reticulum (ER), a subcellular structure involved in protein synthesis.&nbsp; The accumulation of misfolded proteins in the ER results in a condition called ER stress, which evokes the Unfolded Protein Response (UPR).&nbsp; The UPR, in turn, activates a process called autophagy, literally meaning &ldquo;self-eating&rdquo;, by which plant cells degrade or turn over damaged proteins or subcellular organelles. &nbsp;Thus, autophagy is a cell survival process by which cells mitigate the damage caused by adverse environmental conditions and protect themselves from further stress.</p> <p>One of the aims of our project was to determine whether unfolded proteins are a direct trigger for activation of autophagy in the model plant, Arabidopsis. After exposing plants in the laboratory to agents that cause ER stress, plants were treated with chemical chaperones that aid in protein folding and lessen the load of unfolded proteins. We found that the chemical chaperones blocked the activation of autophagy, implicating unfolded proteins as the trigger for autophagy. This was confirmed by overexpression of normal plant protein chaperones, which gave the same result. To bolster these findings, an artificial, constitutively misfolded protein was overexpressed in Arabidopsis, and it was seen to activate autophagy in absence of exogenous stress, again indicating that unfolded proteins directly induce autophagy.</p> <p>An additional aim was to understand the signaling pathways that lead from the accumulation of unfolded proteins to the activation of autophagy. We previously identified a protein called IRE1, known to function in the UPR, as being also required for autophagy during ER stress. IRE1 is a dual function protein kinase and ribonuclease that splices the mRNA encoding the transcription factor bZIP60, which then activates transcription of molecular chaperones and other UPR proteins. It also degrades mRNAs associated with the ER to prevent synthesis of their encoded proteins and thus decrease unfolded protein production in a process known as the RIDD pathway. To assess which of its known functions are required for autophagy during ER stress, we first tested a <em>bzip60</em> mutant for its effect on autophagy. The mutation in bZIP60 had no effect on autophagy, indicating that the splicing activity of IRE1 was not important for autophagy activation. A series of IRE1 mutants that disrupt different aspects of its function were then tested. Blocking the protein kinase activity of IRE1 had no effect on autophagy, but interfering with the ribonuclease activity prevented autophagy activation. Overall, these results indicate that the RIDD pathway is important for autophagy during ER stress.</p> <p>We followed up on this finding by investigating which mRNAs need to be degraded by RIDD in order to induce autophagy. RNAseq analysis of wild-type and <em>ire1</em> mutant plants during ER stress allowed the identification of RIDD target mRNAs, and the top candidates were overexpressed to determined their effect on autophagy. Three mRNAs were identified whose overproduction blocked autophagy activation, and mutational analysis indicated that their translation into protein was required for this activity. The mechanism of function of these proteins in ER stress and autophagy is now under investigation.</p> <p>Overall, our research helps us to understand how plants can tolerate and adapt to environmental stresses such as heat and drought, and elucidates the mechanisms and signaling pathways by which these responses occur.</p> <p>We have also further developed the Meta!Blast computer game (www.metablast.org), designed to help high school and undergraduate students learn cell biology. A module on transcription and a mini-game on genetics have been created and incorporated into the game. Aspects of the game are now being included in introductory biology labs at Iowa State University.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 03/21/2017<br>      Modified by: Diane&nbsp;C&nbsp;Bassham</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Due to the growing concern about the adaptation of plants to climate change, we have examined the response of plants to adverse environmental conditions.  Such conditions, such as heat, salt stress and drought, upset proteostasis, the normal process by which plants maintain quality control over the proteins they make.  Adverse environmental conditions disrupt the delicate process of protein folding leading to an accumulation of misfolded proteins in the plant cell?s endoplasmic reticulum (ER), a subcellular structure involved in protein synthesis.  The accumulation of misfolded proteins in the ER results in a condition called ER stress, which evokes the Unfolded Protein Response (UPR).  The UPR, in turn, activates a process called autophagy, literally meaning "self-eating", by which plant cells degrade or turn over damaged proteins or subcellular organelles.  Thus, autophagy is a cell survival process by which cells mitigate the damage caused by adverse environmental conditions and protect themselves from further stress.  One of the aims of our project was to determine whether unfolded proteins are a direct trigger for activation of autophagy in the model plant, Arabidopsis. After exposing plants in the laboratory to agents that cause ER stress, plants were treated with chemical chaperones that aid in protein folding and lessen the load of unfolded proteins. We found that the chemical chaperones blocked the activation of autophagy, implicating unfolded proteins as the trigger for autophagy. This was confirmed by overexpression of normal plant protein chaperones, which gave the same result. To bolster these findings, an artificial, constitutively misfolded protein was overexpressed in Arabidopsis, and it was seen to activate autophagy in absence of exogenous stress, again indicating that unfolded proteins directly induce autophagy.  An additional aim was to understand the signaling pathways that lead from the accumulation of unfolded proteins to the activation of autophagy. We previously identified a protein called IRE1, known to function in the UPR, as being also required for autophagy during ER stress. IRE1 is a dual function protein kinase and ribonuclease that splices the mRNA encoding the transcription factor bZIP60, which then activates transcription of molecular chaperones and other UPR proteins. It also degrades mRNAs associated with the ER to prevent synthesis of their encoded proteins and thus decrease unfolded protein production in a process known as the RIDD pathway. To assess which of its known functions are required for autophagy during ER stress, we first tested a bzip60 mutant for its effect on autophagy. The mutation in bZIP60 had no effect on autophagy, indicating that the splicing activity of IRE1 was not important for autophagy activation. A series of IRE1 mutants that disrupt different aspects of its function were then tested. Blocking the protein kinase activity of IRE1 had no effect on autophagy, but interfering with the ribonuclease activity prevented autophagy activation. Overall, these results indicate that the RIDD pathway is important for autophagy during ER stress.  We followed up on this finding by investigating which mRNAs need to be degraded by RIDD in order to induce autophagy. RNAseq analysis of wild-type and ire1 mutant plants during ER stress allowed the identification of RIDD target mRNAs, and the top candidates were overexpressed to determined their effect on autophagy. Three mRNAs were identified whose overproduction blocked autophagy activation, and mutational analysis indicated that their translation into protein was required for this activity. The mechanism of function of these proteins in ER stress and autophagy is now under investigation.  Overall, our research helps us to understand how plants can tolerate and adapt to environmental stresses such as heat and drought, and elucidates the mechanisms and signaling pathways by which these responses occur.  We have also further developed the Meta!Blast computer game (www.metablast.org), designed to help high school and undergraduate students learn cell biology. A module on transcription and a mini-game on genetics have been created and incorporated into the game. Aspects of the game are now being included in introductory biology labs at Iowa State University.          Last Modified: 03/21/2017       Submitted by: Diane C Bassham]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
