<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>SBIR Phase II:  Microelectromechanical Sensor for Touch Surfaces</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>04/15/2014</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>03/31/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>500000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>589924</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07070000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>IIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Industrial Innovation &amp; Partnersh</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Muralidharan Nair</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>mnair@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927059</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This Small Business Innovation Research Phase II project seeks to commercialize a force sensitive solution for touch applications that will overcome the technical shortcomings of currently available technologies. The design utilizes the sensitivity, size, and cost advantages of microelectromechanical systems (MEMS) in a novel configuration to prevent overloading of the sensor for large applied forces. The solution will enable truly force sensitive touch that is low cost and highly sensitive. It will be operable with any object, including fingernails, gloves, and styluses, while not being susceptible to environmental factors that hinder current capacitive technologies, such as dirt and moisture.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The broader impact/commercial potential of this project lies in the opportunity to disrupt the status quo in touch-based human interface technology. Two decades ago, touch technology was primarily found within ATMs and point-of-sale systems. More recently, the technology migrated to other electronic industry verticals, including one of the largest and certainly the fastest growing ? smartphones and tablet PCs. Consumer demand is driving an explosion of applications in every vertical. There is increasing demand for low cost, low power, more feature rich touch solutions. In addition, new user experience benefits such as force sensitivity are constantly being pursued, yet there is no viable solution yet on the market. Such a technology would be poised to capture significant market share from existing technologies.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>04/02/2014</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>12/05/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1353450</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Ryan</FirstName>
<LastName>Diestelhorst</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>M</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Ryan M Diestelhorst</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>ryan@nextinput.com</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>4042933434</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000621718</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/02/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>NextInput, Inc.</Name>
<CityName>Atlanta</CityName>
<ZipCode>303081066</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>4042933434</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>75 5th Street NW</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[Suite 206]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Georgia</StateName>
<StateCode>GA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>GA05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>078476985</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>NEXTINPUT, INC.</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>078476985</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[NextInput, Inc.]]></Name>
<CityName>Atlanta</CityName>
<StateCode>GA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>303081066</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[75 5th Street NW]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Georgia</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>GA05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>5373</Code>
<Text>SBIR Phase II</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>169E</Code>
<Text>SBIR Tech Enhan Partner (TECP)</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>4080</Code>
<Text>ADVANCED COMP RESEARCH PROGRAM</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>5373</Code>
<Text>SMALL BUSINESS PHASE II</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8032</Code>
<Text>Software Services and Applications</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9139</Code>
<Text>INFORMATION INFRASTRUCTURE &amp; TECH APPL</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>HPCC</Code>
<Text>HIGH PERFORMANCE COMPUTING &amp; COMM</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0114</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0115</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~491604</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2015~98320</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>NextInput is a high-tech Silicon Valley startup originating from the Advanced Technology Development Center at Georgia Tech. The company was formed to commercialize a next generation touch technology called &ldquo;ForceTouch&reg;&rdquo;, which consists of a hardware sensor layer (a MEMS force sensor referred to as the &ldquo;ForceTouch Sensor&rdquo;), a firmware layer, and an operating system driver and software API layer. It was conceived to address many of the key pains described by users of touch-enabled devices, while simultaneously adding a third dimension of user input: &ldquo;force&rdquo;.</p> <p>The major goals of this Phase II SBIR project entitled "MEMS Force Sensor for Touch Surfaces" were focused on the development of a microelectromechanical (MEMS) force sensor that is well-suited for human interface applications. While MEMS sensors are inherently sensitive and linear (both advantages in touch applications), they are also inherently fragile. The primary development goal was to design and commercialize a sensor that could survive the rigors of human interface applications while not sacrificing the advantages it possesses as a precision MEMS device. Finally, compatibility with existing high-volume semiconductor manufacturing processes was determined to be a necessary requirement to allow the product, and company, to scale.</p> <p>The growth in the touch technology market is being driven by two primary trends: the growth in demand for touch-enabled devices like smartphones and tablets, and the expansion of the touch technology market into new application areas including automotive, industrial, and home appliance/automation. As the breadth and depth of the touch technology market grows, NextInput is well positioned to offer an attractive alternative to a broad range of mechanical button applications and high-performance force augmentation to existing capacitive and resistive touch solutions.</p> <p>This SBIR project resulted in the release of NextInput&rsquo;s first product - the FT-4100, which is specifically designed to address these markets. It outshines its competition due to its high sensitivity, linearity, and physical robustness, and it has been selected for multiple design wins in mobile and automotive markets. NextInput has gained significant traction and is well-positioned to expand both its market reach and product roadmap thanks in part to the support of the NSF.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 06/02/2017<br>      Modified by: Ryan&nbsp;M&nbsp;Diestelhorst</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ NextInput is a high-tech Silicon Valley startup originating from the Advanced Technology Development Center at Georgia Tech. The company was formed to commercialize a next generation touch technology called "ForceTouch&reg;", which consists of a hardware sensor layer (a MEMS force sensor referred to as the "ForceTouch Sensor"), a firmware layer, and an operating system driver and software API layer. It was conceived to address many of the key pains described by users of touch-enabled devices, while simultaneously adding a third dimension of user input: "force".  The major goals of this Phase II SBIR project entitled "MEMS Force Sensor for Touch Surfaces" were focused on the development of a microelectromechanical (MEMS) force sensor that is well-suited for human interface applications. While MEMS sensors are inherently sensitive and linear (both advantages in touch applications), they are also inherently fragile. The primary development goal was to design and commercialize a sensor that could survive the rigors of human interface applications while not sacrificing the advantages it possesses as a precision MEMS device. Finally, compatibility with existing high-volume semiconductor manufacturing processes was determined to be a necessary requirement to allow the product, and company, to scale.  The growth in the touch technology market is being driven by two primary trends: the growth in demand for touch-enabled devices like smartphones and tablets, and the expansion of the touch technology market into new application areas including automotive, industrial, and home appliance/automation. As the breadth and depth of the touch technology market grows, NextInput is well positioned to offer an attractive alternative to a broad range of mechanical button applications and high-performance force augmentation to existing capacitive and resistive touch solutions.  This SBIR project resulted in the release of NextInput?s first product - the FT-4100, which is specifically designed to address these markets. It outshines its competition due to its high sensitivity, linearity, and physical robustness, and it has been selected for multiple design wins in mobile and automotive markets. NextInput has gained significant traction and is well-positioned to expand both its market reach and product roadmap thanks in part to the support of the NSF.       Last Modified: 06/02/2017       Submitted by: Ryan M Diestelhorst]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
