<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Legal Mobilization, Rights Claims, and Federal Indian Policy Reform</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>05/01/2014</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>249952.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>249952</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>04050000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>SBE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>SES</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Divn Of Social and Economic Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Reggie Sheehan</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>rsheehan@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032925389</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>It is often assumed that minority groups seeking to claim rights are more successful in federal courts than when working through the legislative process. Yet, American Indians, which remain the most impoverished group in the United States, lose in the Supreme Court over 75% of the time.  As a result, many lawyers and advocates have encouraged Indian nations to pursue legislative rather than judicial solutions to problems plaguing Indian country, even though little is actually known about how American Indians and Indian nations fare in the political process. &lt;br/&gt; &lt;br/&gt;This study begins to fill this gap in our knowledge by examining how, when, and with what success the 565 Indian nations in the United States use the political process to change the law.  It focuses on Indian nations? support or opposition for relevant bills introduced and enacted between 1975 and 2011, and determines whether such support or opposition led to the enactment of federal policies beneficial to Indians.  Case studies, selected from trends in the quantitative study and developed using archival data and new ethnographic research, supplement the initial quantitative analysis of legislative hearings to better assess the variety of legislative strategies used by Indian nations and the success of those strategies.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The study?s findings will provide legal scholars, practicing lawyers, law reformers, and legislative advocates with a more nuanced and comprehensive understanding of how underrepresented communities might use various institutions and strategies to influence the enactment of laws and policies favorable to them.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>02/18/2014</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/31/2018</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.075</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1353255</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Kirsten</FirstName>
<LastName>Carlson</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>S</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Kirsten S Carlson</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>kirsten.carlson@wayne.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>3135771201</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000230463</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>02/18/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Wayne State University</Name>
<CityName>Detroit</CityName>
<ZipCode>482023622</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>3135772424</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>5057 Woodward</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[6th Floor]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Michigan</StateName>
<StateCode>MI</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>13</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MI13</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>001962224</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>WAYNE STATE UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>001962224</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Wayne State University]]></Name>
<CityName>Detroit</CityName>
<StateCode>MI</StateCode>
<ZipCode>482023986</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[471 W. Palmer]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Michigan</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>13</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MI13</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1372</Code>
<Text>LSS-Law And Social Sciences</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>0000</Code>
<Text>UNASSIGNED</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>OTHR</Code>
<Text>OTHER RESEARCH OR EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0114</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~249952</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>This project charted new territory in an understudied area by developing a more comprehensive understanding of how, when, and with what success Indian nations use the political process to change the law.</p> <p>The project developed new, systematic databases on American Indian advocacy.&nbsp;&nbsp;It created the first database to systematically collect information on reported lobbying and reported expenditures by Indian nations and organizations from 1978 to 2012.&nbsp;Analysis of this data revealed a 600 percent increase in reported lobbying by Indian nations and organizations from 1978 to 2012.&nbsp;&nbsp;This dramatic increase in reported lobbying challenged traditional narratives that groups lacking political power litigate because they cannot attain their goals politically.&nbsp;&nbsp;In contrast, this research presented a more accurate and complete narrative about how, when, and why American Indians used legislative strategies.</p> <p>The project developed another database, which is the first to systematically link American Indian advocacy to legislative outcomes.&nbsp;It measures Indian influence on legislative outcomes by tracking testimony on specific bills in legislative hearings held on those bills.&nbsp;&nbsp;It includes all 262 legislative hearings held on each Indian-related bill in five Congresses (97th, 100th, 103rd, 106th, and 109th).&nbsp;&nbsp;Each hearing was coded to determine tribal support and opposition for each bill.&nbsp;&nbsp;The coding made it possible to determinate how frequently Indian nations and organizations advocated for and against bills in general, and on specific subject matters.&nbsp;It also allowed for analysis of how frequently Indian nations and organizations were successful in advocating for and against legislation.&nbsp;</p> <p>To complement the quantitative data, case studies were conducted on two Congresses (97th and 106th).&nbsp;&nbsp;The case studies contextualize and develop a deeper understanding of the different patterns of American Indian influence and how they change over time.&nbsp;The case studies use archival research and interviews to explore how, when, and to what extent Indian tribes influence federal policymaking. &nbsp;</p> <p>The project has broadened discussions about legal change and the role of legislative advocacy as a strategy for facilitating legal and social change. My research has integrated two distinct literatures?sociolegal and interest group studies?to produce nuanced and complicated understandings of group advocacy. &nbsp;It has provided scholars with new methodologies for studying legislative advocacy in a more systematic way.&nbsp;&nbsp;The project has also stimulated conversations among scholars of race, ethnicity, and politics about the role of marginalized groups in legislative politics and how different groups may approach the political process differently.</p> <p>In addition to the contributions made to academia, this research offers insights to tribal leaders, lobbyists, and policymakers crafting federal Indian law. The new and detailed information on advocacy will help Indian nations and their advocates formulate effective law reform strategies. The databases, which allow for tracing the development of Indian-related policies over time, will be useful to legislators, judges, and bureaucrats as well.&nbsp;&nbsp;For example, legal advocates relied on data generated by the study to inform lawmakers in amicus briefs to the U.S. Supreme Court in&nbsp;<em>Nebraska v. Parker</em>and&nbsp;<em>Patchak v. Zinke</em>.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 08/14/2019<br>      Modified by: Kirsten&nbsp;S&nbsp;Carlson</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ This project charted new territory in an understudied area by developing a more comprehensive understanding of how, when, and with what success Indian nations use the political process to change the law.  The project developed new, systematic databases on American Indian advocacy.  It created the first database to systematically collect information on reported lobbying and reported expenditures by Indian nations and organizations from 1978 to 2012. Analysis of this data revealed a 600 percent increase in reported lobbying by Indian nations and organizations from 1978 to 2012.  This dramatic increase in reported lobbying challenged traditional narratives that groups lacking political power litigate because they cannot attain their goals politically.  In contrast, this research presented a more accurate and complete narrative about how, when, and why American Indians used legislative strategies.  The project developed another database, which is the first to systematically link American Indian advocacy to legislative outcomes. It measures Indian influence on legislative outcomes by tracking testimony on specific bills in legislative hearings held on those bills.  It includes all 262 legislative hearings held on each Indian-related bill in five Congresses (97th, 100th, 103rd, 106th, and 109th).  Each hearing was coded to determine tribal support and opposition for each bill.  The coding made it possible to determinate how frequently Indian nations and organizations advocated for and against bills in general, and on specific subject matters. It also allowed for analysis of how frequently Indian nations and organizations were successful in advocating for and against legislation.   To complement the quantitative data, case studies were conducted on two Congresses (97th and 106th).  The case studies contextualize and develop a deeper understanding of the different patterns of American Indian influence and how they change over time. The case studies use archival research and interviews to explore how, when, and to what extent Indian tribes influence federal policymaking.    The project has broadened discussions about legal change and the role of legislative advocacy as a strategy for facilitating legal and social change. My research has integrated two distinct literatures?sociolegal and interest group studies?to produce nuanced and complicated understandings of group advocacy.  It has provided scholars with new methodologies for studying legislative advocacy in a more systematic way.  The project has also stimulated conversations among scholars of race, ethnicity, and politics about the role of marginalized groups in legislative politics and how different groups may approach the political process differently.  In addition to the contributions made to academia, this research offers insights to tribal leaders, lobbyists, and policymakers crafting federal Indian law. The new and detailed information on advocacy will help Indian nations and their advocates formulate effective law reform strategies. The databases, which allow for tracing the development of Indian-related policies over time, will be useful to legislators, judges, and bureaucrats as well.  For example, legal advocates relied on data generated by the study to inform lawmakers in amicus briefs to the U.S. Supreme Court in Nebraska v. Parkerand Patchak v. Zinke.          Last Modified: 08/14/2019       Submitted by: Kirsten S Carlson]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
