<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Graduate Student Training through Research on Plasma-Based Accelerators</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2014</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2015</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>26030.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>26030</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03010000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>PHY</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Physics</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Vyacheslav (Slava) Lukin</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>vlukin@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927382</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The NSF Collaborative grant "Graduate Student Training through Research on Plasma-Based Accelerators", has supported the work of 14 graduate students since September 1, 2009 at seven different institutions.  Eight of these students have already graduated and another six are expected to graduate by September 2014. This project supports one of these six students, whose scientific goal is to visualize --- in a single shot --- evolving plasma structures that propagate at the speed of light in the wake of intense ultrashort laser pulses or electron bunches.  The single-shot Frequency Domain Holography (FDH) visualization and control techniques developed and refined through this research can impact a wide cross section of plasma and accelerator science through the impact on Laser Plasma Accelerators (LPA). In LPA science, FDT will contribute fundamentally to scaling LPAs to multi-GeV energy. Compact FDT systems could ultimately become standard in-line metrology for future laser- and proton-driven plasma accelerators that produce electrons up to the energy frontier. These methods will also promote more reliable plasma-based accelerators, which are useful as compact, coherent x-ray sources for biological, chemical, and medical research, injectors for conventional accelerators, and medical accelerators. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The student  will apply and adapt the Frequency Domain Holography (FDH) cutting-edge visualization method developed in the PI's laboratory to new frontier plasma science problems: (1) He will implement FDT visualization of evolving laser-driven plasma bubbles in two regimes: (a) atmospheric density plasma driven by an ultrashort terawatt laser pulse; (b) 0.01 atmosphere plasma driven by the Texas Petawatt Laser, with the aim of understanding, optimizing and scaling a laser-plasma accelerator (LPA) that recently accelerated electrons to a world-record-breaking energy of 2 GeV. Particle-in-cell and photon-in-cell simulations will guide the experiments. (2) He will develop methods suitable for visualizing wakes in meter-long tenuous plasma. These methods will be designed with the intention of implementing them ultimately at advanced accelerator facilities such as SLAC's Facility for Accelerator Science and Experimental Tests (FACET).</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/26/2014</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/26/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1354531</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Michael</FirstName>
<LastName>Downer</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>C</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Michael C Downer</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>downer@physics.utexas.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5124716054</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000174282</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/26/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Texas at Austin</Name>
<CityName>Austin</CityName>
<ZipCode>787595316</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5124716424</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>3925 W Braker Lane, Ste 3.340</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Texas</StateName>
<StateCode>TX</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>10</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>TX10</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>170230239</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF TEXAS AT AUSTIN</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>042000273</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Texas at Austin]]></Name>
<CityName>Austin</CityName>
<StateCode>TX</StateCode>
<ZipCode>787595316</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[3925 W Braker Lane, Ste 3.340]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Texas</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>10</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>TX10</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1242</Code>
<Text>PLASMA PHYSICS</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1062</Code>
<Text>BASIC PLASMA SCIENCE &amp; ENGINEERING</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0114</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~26030</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Particle accelerators are used to probe nature&rsquo;s deepest sub-atomic secrets, to irradiate cancerous tumors, and to produce bright x-rays that reveal the structure of molecules essential to life. However, they have become the largest and most expensive of scientific instruments. The overall purpose of this project was to develop a particle accelerator thousands of times smaller. &nbsp;It works by surfing particles on electron density waves created by short intense laser pulses propagating through plasma, or ionized gas. Figure 1 shows an analogy to explain the basic principles.&nbsp; The boat is like the laser pulse -- it provides the energy source.&nbsp; The wake behind the boat is like the electron density wave behind the laser pulse &ndash; it stores the boat&rsquo;s energy and provides the accelerating structure.&nbsp; The surfer is like the charged particle &ndash; it accelerates by surfing from the top of the wave to the bottom before exiting the medium. The laser-plasma accelerator is about ten thousand times smaller than the boat and water wave. But since particles accelerate much faster within such tiny waves than in conventional accelerators, accelerators can be much smaller and less expensive.&nbsp; They occupy a tabletop rather than acres of real estate.&nbsp;</p> <p>To make such tiny accelerators work well, researchers must learn to SEE them. This is hard because the waves move at the speed of light and are ten times smaller than a small strand of hair.&nbsp; <strong>One major outcome of this project </strong>was &ldquo;pictures&rdquo; of laser-generated plasma waves, and development of new methods to record them.&nbsp; Figure 2 (left panel) shows an example of one of our &ldquo;snapshots&rdquo; of an electron density wave riding in the wake of an intense laser pulse.&nbsp; This is quite different from ordinary photography.&nbsp; In ordinary photography, a &ldquo;flash&rdquo; propagates from a bulb to the object, which modifies the flash by reflection, refraction and absorption before it propagates to the recording medium.&nbsp;&nbsp; This works fine if the object is stationary, or moving at much less than the speed of light, as ordinary objects always do.&nbsp; But our object (the electron density wave) moves at the speed of light.&nbsp; To record its shape, the &ldquo;flash&rdquo; co-propagated with the light-speed object like a pack of fleas around a sprinting animal.&nbsp; The object imprinted its shape onto the flash as it propagated through the plasma.&nbsp; We then used holographic techniques to recover the imprinted shape.&nbsp; The value of such snapshots is that they can be compared directly with computer simulations of the wave, as shown in Figure 2 (right panel).&nbsp; Such comparisons help us to understand the detailed physics of how laser pulses generate electron density waves, and how to optimize their shape for best acceleration.&nbsp;</p> <p>Through such work, we learned that the accelerator works best when the wave evolves, or changes shape, during its transit through the plasma.&nbsp; Such evolution, unfortunately, blurs snapshot images like the one in Figure 2, as when a subject moves while a camera shutter is open.&nbsp; Returning to the analogy of the pack of fleas around a sprinting animal, such an animal changes shape as its legs and lungs extend and contract.&nbsp; <strong>A second major outcome of this project</strong>, designed to address this problem, was &ldquo;movies&rdquo; of evolving laser-generated electron density waves.&nbsp; To record a movie, instead of one &ldquo;flash&rdquo;, we fired several simultaneously across the evolving object&rsquo;s path at different angles, like a cross fire of bullets.&nbsp; The object imprinted a &ldquo;streaked&rdquo; record of its evolution onto each flash.&nbsp; We then recovered a multi-frame &ldquo;movie&rdquo; of the object&rsquo;s evolving structure using the methods of com...]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Particle accelerators are used to probe natureÆs deepest sub-atomic secrets, to irradiate cancerous tumors, and to produce bright x-rays that reveal the structure of molecules essential to life. However, they have become the largest and most expensive of scientific instruments. The overall purpose of this project was to develop a particle accelerator thousands of times smaller.  It works by surfing particles on electron density waves created by short intense laser pulses propagating through plasma, or ionized gas. Figure 1 shows an analogy to explain the basic principles.  The boat is like the laser pulse -- it provides the energy source.  The wake behind the boat is like the electron density wave behind the laser pulse &ndash; it stores the boatÆs energy and provides the accelerating structure.  The surfer is like the charged particle &ndash; it accelerates by surfing from the top of the wave to the bottom before exiting the medium. The laser-plasma accelerator is about ten thousand times smaller than the boat and water wave. But since particles accelerate much faster within such tiny waves than in conventional accelerators, accelerators can be much smaller and less expensive.  They occupy a tabletop rather than acres of real estate.   To make such tiny accelerators work well, researchers must learn to SEE them. This is hard because the waves move at the speed of light and are ten times smaller than a small strand of hair.  One major outcome of this project was "pictures" of laser-generated plasma waves, and development of new methods to record them.  Figure 2 (left panel) shows an example of one of our "snapshots" of an electron density wave riding in the wake of an intense laser pulse.  This is quite different from ordinary photography.  In ordinary photography, a "flash" propagates from a bulb to the object, which modifies the flash by reflection, refraction and absorption before it propagates to the recording medium.   This works fine if the object is stationary, or moving at much less than the speed of light, as ordinary objects always do.  But our object (the electron density wave) moves at the speed of light.  To record its shape, the "flash" co-propagated with the light-speed object like a pack of fleas around a sprinting animal.  The object imprinted its shape onto the flash as it propagated through the plasma.  We then used holographic techniques to recover the imprinted shape.  The value of such snapshots is that they can be compared directly with computer simulations of the wave, as shown in Figure 2 (right panel).  Such comparisons help us to understand the detailed physics of how laser pulses generate electron density waves, and how to optimize their shape for best acceleration.   Through such work, we learned that the accelerator works best when the wave evolves, or changes shape, during its transit through the plasma.  Such evolution, unfortunately, blurs snapshot images like the one in Figure 2, as when a subject moves while a camera shutter is open.  Returning to the analogy of the pack of fleas around a sprinting animal, such an animal changes shape as its legs and lungs extend and contract.  A second major outcome of this project, designed to address this problem, was "movies" of evolving laser-generated electron density waves.  To record a movie, instead of one "flash", we fired several simultaneously across the evolving objectÆs path at different angles, like a cross fire of bullets.  The object imprinted a "streaked" record of its evolution onto each flash.  We then recovered a multi-frame "movie" of the objectÆs evolving structure using the methods of computer-aided tomography (CAT), the same "CAT-scan" method used to obtain 3D images of internal bodily organs.  Such movies greatly improved our ability to diagnose and optimize laser-plasma accelerators.   We actually used these pictures and movies to optimize laser-plasma accelerator performance.  A third major outcome of this project was demonstratio...]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
