<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>I-Corps:  Social Gaze for Software Agents and Robots</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>02/01/2014</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2014</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>50000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>50000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07070000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>IIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Industrial Innovation &amp; Partnersh</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Rathindra DasGupta</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This proposal further develops a software package that autonomously generates head and eye movements, in a virtual assistant or social robot synchronized with real-time speech for "human-like" conversation. Existing solutions use preprogrammed head and eye movements for conversation, as current technology cannot synchronize head and eye gaze for real-time speech. The proposed technology can be used in interactive open-ended conversations and can adapt to gender and culture of the conversation partner.  This project presents three contributions to human-computer and human-robot interaction. First, autonomous generation of head and eye gaze in a virtual assistant or social robot synchronized with real-time speech for open-ended interactive conversations. Second, the front end of the social agent responsible for gesture generation is completely independent of the back end knowledge base; hence deployments of virtual assistant or social robot solutions are easier, cheaper, and faster. Third, the technology enables generation of social gaze sensitive to gender and culture. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The broader impact of the project include the validated benefits of the technology for end users, such as increased social acceptance, increased positive feelings, increased engagement, improved understandability, and superior likeability. Stemming from encouraging initial discussions with end users the proposed technology may be transformative in a large number of markets like video games, online marketing, web customer service, telepresence, telemedicine, entertainment, eldercare, and healthcare.&lt;br/&gt;A successful deployment of the technology may result in substantial cost savings to organizations that deploy virtual assistant or social robot solutions, and increased revenues for the vendors of these solutions due to accelerated consumer adoption.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>01/22/2014</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>04/10/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1355874</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Robin</FirstName>
<LastName>Murphy</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>R</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Robin R Murphy</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>robin.r.murphy@tamu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>9798621696</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000511836</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>01/22/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Texas A&amp;M Engineering Experiment Station</Name>
<CityName>College Station</CityName>
<ZipCode>778454645</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>9798626777</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>400 Harvey Mitchell Pkwy S</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[Suite 300]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Texas</StateName>
<StateCode>TX</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>17</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>TX17</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>847205572</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>TEXAS A&amp;M ENGINEERING EXPERIMENT STATION</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>042915991</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Texas Engineering Experiment Station]]></Name>
<CityName>College Station</CityName>
<StateCode>TX</StateCode>
<ZipCode>778433112</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[TAMU 3112]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Texas</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>17</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>TX17</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>8023</Code>
<Text>I-Corps</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0114</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~50000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Team &ldquo;Socially Adept Avatars&rdquo; participated in the NSF Innovation Corps (I-Corps) program with the following team members: Entrepreneurial Lead Vasant Srinivasan, Principal Investigator Dr. Robin Murphy, and Business Mentor Dr. Adam Steele.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>This grant focused on investigating the commercial viability for a software package that autonomously generates head and eye movements, in a virtual assistant or social robot synchronized with real-time speech for &ldquo;human-like&rdquo; conversation. Existing solutions use preprogrammed?head and eye movements for conversation, as current technology cannot synchronize head and?eye gaze for real-time speech.</p> <p>The limitations of current approaches are that they use pre-recorded?speech for the social agent, require significant human effort to identify the utterances?for which head and eye gaze should be activated, are semantically dependent, and restrict interactive dialog.&nbsp; At the start of the program, it was expected that the proposed technology would be beneficial to five customer segments &ndash; Animators (Games and Films), Customer Support Directors at Enterprise Companies, Social Robot Vendors, Virtual Agent Vendors, and Consumers (Users)&ndash; because it is autonomous, can be used in interactive open-ended conversations, and can adapt to gender and culture of the conversation partner. At this stage each of the nine business model canvas boxes (for example, value propositions, customer segments, etc.) were just hypotheses. The team met with 100 potential customers within a period of seven weeks as a part of the customer development effort to determine a repeatable and scalable business model. The intense and immersive learning experience associated with this grant has resulted in a much clearer understanding about the path and capabilities needed to bring such a technology from the university laboratory to the potential adopters in commercial marketplace. After the first three weeks into the program, the team identified that the market sector which best suited this technology was web customer support. Specifically, during a meeting with a virtual agent vendor company, it was learned that enterprise companies want to reduce customer support costs and volume of calls. Therefore, it was decided that the technology would be repositioned as &ldquo;Intelligent Virtual Customer Service Agents&rdquo; and the business model would be designed around the &ldquo;Customer Support Directors at Enterprise Companies&rdquo; customer segment. Further meetings yielded the customer archetype including such characteristics that they: 1) Want to address mismatch of culture between customer support agents and users, 2) Want 24 hour support, 3) Want to efficiently address repeat questions, 4) Want to minimize stress related to large number of calls waiting, 5) Want to have good experience with consumer and solve their problem, and 6) Want better integrated tools to log reports and manage consumer experience. The addressable market was then discovered to be about $275 million. It was learned that a single costumer service call costs typically about $6, where as a single web customer service interaction could be as little as $0.0025 per interaction. As a result of discovering this need in the market, it was determined that our technology requires additional competencies such as dialog processing and extensive back office management. In order to acquire these competencies, key partnerships with Business Processing Outsourcing (BPO) companies were evaluated. The benefits and risks of partnerships with existing companies were evaluated. During conversations with Directors at BPO companies it emerged that the risks for such a partnership were twofold - 1) Significantly reduced profits and 2) Duplication. The I-Corps program has provided great value for the team to identify value propositions of the technology....]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Team "Socially Adept Avatars" participated in the NSF Innovation Corps (I-Corps) program with the following team members: Entrepreneurial Lead Vasant Srinivasan, Principal Investigator Dr. Robin Murphy, and Business Mentor Dr. Adam Steele.     This grant focused on investigating the commercial viability for a software package that autonomously generates head and eye movements, in a virtual assistant or social robot synchronized with real-time speech for "human-like" conversation. Existing solutions use preprogrammed?head and eye movements for conversation, as current technology cannot synchronize head and?eye gaze for real-time speech.  The limitations of current approaches are that they use pre-recorded?speech for the social agent, require significant human effort to identify the utterances?for which head and eye gaze should be activated, are semantically dependent, and restrict interactive dialog.  At the start of the program, it was expected that the proposed technology would be beneficial to five customer segments &ndash; Animators (Games and Films), Customer Support Directors at Enterprise Companies, Social Robot Vendors, Virtual Agent Vendors, and Consumers (Users)&ndash; because it is autonomous, can be used in interactive open-ended conversations, and can adapt to gender and culture of the conversation partner. At this stage each of the nine business model canvas boxes (for example, value propositions, customer segments, etc.) were just hypotheses. The team met with 100 potential customers within a period of seven weeks as a part of the customer development effort to determine a repeatable and scalable business model. The intense and immersive learning experience associated with this grant has resulted in a much clearer understanding about the path and capabilities needed to bring such a technology from the university laboratory to the potential adopters in commercial marketplace. After the first three weeks into the program, the team identified that the market sector which best suited this technology was web customer support. Specifically, during a meeting with a virtual agent vendor company, it was learned that enterprise companies want to reduce customer support costs and volume of calls. Therefore, it was decided that the technology would be repositioned as "Intelligent Virtual Customer Service Agents" and the business model would be designed around the "Customer Support Directors at Enterprise Companies" customer segment. Further meetings yielded the customer archetype including such characteristics that they: 1) Want to address mismatch of culture between customer support agents and users, 2) Want 24 hour support, 3) Want to efficiently address repeat questions, 4) Want to minimize stress related to large number of calls waiting, 5) Want to have good experience with consumer and solve their problem, and 6) Want better integrated tools to log reports and manage consumer experience. The addressable market was then discovered to be about $275 million. It was learned that a single costumer service call costs typically about $6, where as a single web customer service interaction could be as little as $0.0025 per interaction. As a result of discovering this need in the market, it was determined that our technology requires additional competencies such as dialog processing and extensive back office management. In order to acquire these competencies, key partnerships with Business Processing Outsourcing (BPO) companies were evaluated. The benefits and risks of partnerships with existing companies were evaluated. During conversations with Directors at BPO companies it emerged that the risks for such a partnership were twofold - 1) Significantly reduced profits and 2) Duplication. The I-Corps program has provided great value for the team to identify value propositions of the technology. However, the final decision was a "No Go" because the technology at its current state and capability is not adequate to exploit the value...]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
