<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Using Primate Comparative Biology to Understand Human Uniqueness</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>04/01/2014</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>03/31/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>234495.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>234495</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>04040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>SBE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>BCS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Behavioral and Cognitive Sci</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Rebecca Ferrell</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>rferrell@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927850</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>A fundamental question in biology concerns the ways that species differ from one another.  Perhaps nowhere is this more prominent than in the field of biological anthropology, where researchers investigate how and why humans differ from other primates, often under the assumption that human traits resulted from a unique constellation of forces that made our lineage particularly successful.  Humans are clearly unique in many ways relative to other primates, including use of language, impressive problem-solving abilities, and cumulative cultural evolution.  It is less clear how other biological traits - such as life history and physiology - have catalyzed these major changes.  Have our unique cognitive abilities arisen from only a few underlying biological changes, or many changes?  Which traits are involved, and how do they relate to one another?  &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The central goal of this research to rigorously identify biological traits that are exceptional in humans, and thus important to other traits involved in our extraordinary success.  This goal will be achieved through in-depth, advanced analyses of a wide range of important variables involving brain size, lifespan and related traits, and key physiological variables, such as immune system characteristics and body temperature.  The research team will also investigate parasites and pathogens, which have been hypothesized to be super-abundant in humans, yet are known to depress cognitive performance.  Two new statistical approaches will be developed.  One set of methods predicts trait values in humans based on a statistical model estimated in non-human primates, and then evaluates whether the observed value in Homo sapiens departs from the predicted value.  A second set of methods investigates evolutionary rates on different parts of an evolutionary tree.  Under the hypothesis that a biological trait is exceptional in humans relative to non-human primates, elevated rates of evolutionary change in that trait are expected along the lineage leading to humans. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;In terms of intellectual merit, the research will open new avenues to better integrate studies of non-human primates into our understanding of human evolution.  In the process, the research will address the question, what are the fundamental biological traits that have lead to human uniqueness and success?  The new methods complement existing approaches to studying the fossil record, and they provide ways to investigate traits that do not fossilize, including behavioral and ecological traits.  &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The research also will support important broader impacts, especially involving hands-on training in statistics and databases for the next generation of young scientists, and opportunities for these developing scientists to expand their knowledge of biology and anthropology.  The research team also will produce new databases of primate and human characteristics that enable other scientists and students to investigate additional research questions important in the fields of biological anthropology.  Finally, the investigator will organize a conference symposium in the final year of funding to share the results of this effort and stimulate future extensions of it</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>02/05/2014</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>02/05/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.075</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1355902</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Charles</FirstName>
<LastName>Nunn</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>L</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Charles L Nunn</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>clnunn@duke.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>9196607281</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000226329</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>02/05/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Duke University</Name>
<CityName>Durham</CityName>
<ZipCode>277054010</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>9196843030</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>2200 W. Main St, Suite 710</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[Erwin Square]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>North Carolina</StateName>
<StateCode>NC</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NC01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>044387793</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>DUKE UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>044387793</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Duke University]]></Name>
<CityName>Durham</CityName>
<StateCode>NC</StateCode>
<ZipCode>277089976</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[Biological Sciences Building]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>North Carolina</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NC04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1392</Code>
<Text>Biological Anthropology</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1392</Code>
<Text>Biological Anthropology</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9178</Code>
<Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9179</Code>
<Text>GRADUATE INVOLVEMENT</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0114</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~234495</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>A fundamental question in biology concerns the ways that species differ from one another.&nbsp; Perhaps nowhere is this more prominent than in the field of biological anthropology, where many researchers investigate how and why humans differ from other primates, often under the assumption that human traits result from a unique constellation of forces that made our lineage particularly successful.&nbsp; To rigorously identify the ways that humans differ from other primates requires data on the traits of interest, potential correlates of these traits, a phylogeny representing how the species in the analysis relate to one another, and an underlying evolutionary model of phenotypic trait change.&nbsp; The research under this award made these methods available and applied them to rigorously investigate whether and how humans differ from other primates.</p> <p>This research tested specific hypotheses for differences between humans and other primates through evolutionary analyses of a wide range of key variables involving brain size, a longer lifespan and related life history characteristics, sleep duration, and fundamental physiological variables, such as white blood cell counts and body temperature.&nbsp; To achieve this goal, new statistical-evolutionary methods were developed to investigate whether human phenotypes differ from predictions based on comparative variation in primates.&nbsp; The investigator also explicitly modeled trait covariation in primates under different evolutionary frameworks. &nbsp;For some traits, these approaches were used to make inferences of when exceptional phenotypic changes occurred in human evolution.&nbsp;&nbsp;</p> <p>In addition to the methodological advances, the team made several important findings related to human evolution.&nbsp; (1) The research revealed that humans sleep substantially less than predicted, and that this was achieved through reductions in non-rapid eye movement (NREM) sleep.&nbsp; (2) Analyses quantified how much larger human brains are than expected based on variation in other primates, and also estimated the timing of brain size expansion in humans by applying these methods to endocranial volume on a hominin evolutionary tree (see figure).&nbsp; (3) Analyses also demonstrated substantial deviations from predictions in some, but not all, life history traits in humans:&nbsp; interbirth interval was shorter than predicted, longevity was longer than predicted, but age at first reproduction was not different from predicted based on phylogeny and cross-primate variation.&nbsp; (4) We discovered that human physiology has shifted dramatically over the human lineage, with humans exhibiting more cases of exceptional phenotypic change than other species in the analysis.&nbsp;</p> <p>The research supported several important broader impacts, especially involving hands-on training in statistics and databases for the next generation of young scientists, and opportunities for these developing scientists to expand their knowledge of biology and anthropology. &nbsp;Two of these trainees are now in top Ph.D. programs.&nbsp; The research team also produced new methods to enable other scientists and students to investigate additional research questions important in the fields of biological anthropology.&nbsp; The research has been presented at multiple scientific conferences &ndash; including by early-career scientists involved in the research &ndash; and at invited seminars by the Principal Investigator.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 05/01/2018<br>      Modified by: Charles&nbsp;L&nbsp;Nunn</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Image         </div> <div class="galControls onePhoto" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation onePhoto" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1355902/1355902_10290875_1525169566589_figure2A--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1355902/1355902_10290875_1525169566589_figure2A--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Evolutionary Modeling of Hominin Brain Size"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1355902/1355902_10290875_1525169566589_figure2A--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Evolutionary Modeling of Hominin Brain Size"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Location of inferred shifts in selective regimes from modeling endocranial volume in hominin lineages.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Ian Miller, Princeton University</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Charles&nbsp;L&nbsp;Nunn</div> <div class="imageTitle">Evolutionary Modeling of Hominin Brain Size</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ A fundamental question in biology concerns the ways that species differ from one another.  Perhaps nowhere is this more prominent than in the field of biological anthropology, where many researchers investigate how and why humans differ from other primates, often under the assumption that human traits result from a unique constellation of forces that made our lineage particularly successful.  To rigorously identify the ways that humans differ from other primates requires data on the traits of interest, potential correlates of these traits, a phylogeny representing how the species in the analysis relate to one another, and an underlying evolutionary model of phenotypic trait change.  The research under this award made these methods available and applied them to rigorously investigate whether and how humans differ from other primates.  This research tested specific hypotheses for differences between humans and other primates through evolutionary analyses of a wide range of key variables involving brain size, a longer lifespan and related life history characteristics, sleep duration, and fundamental physiological variables, such as white blood cell counts and body temperature.  To achieve this goal, new statistical-evolutionary methods were developed to investigate whether human phenotypes differ from predictions based on comparative variation in primates.  The investigator also explicitly modeled trait covariation in primates under different evolutionary frameworks.  For some traits, these approaches were used to make inferences of when exceptional phenotypic changes occurred in human evolution.    In addition to the methodological advances, the team made several important findings related to human evolution.  (1) The research revealed that humans sleep substantially less than predicted, and that this was achieved through reductions in non-rapid eye movement (NREM) sleep.  (2) Analyses quantified how much larger human brains are than expected based on variation in other primates, and also estimated the timing of brain size expansion in humans by applying these methods to endocranial volume on a hominin evolutionary tree (see figure).  (3) Analyses also demonstrated substantial deviations from predictions in some, but not all, life history traits in humans:  interbirth interval was shorter than predicted, longevity was longer than predicted, but age at first reproduction was not different from predicted based on phylogeny and cross-primate variation.  (4) We discovered that human physiology has shifted dramatically over the human lineage, with humans exhibiting more cases of exceptional phenotypic change than other species in the analysis.   The research supported several important broader impacts, especially involving hands-on training in statistics and databases for the next generation of young scientists, and opportunities for these developing scientists to expand their knowledge of biology and anthropology.  Two of these trainees are now in top Ph.D. programs.  The research team also produced new methods to enable other scientists and students to investigate additional research questions important in the fields of biological anthropology.  The research has been presented at multiple scientific conferences &ndash; including by early-career scientists involved in the research &ndash; and at invited seminars by the Principal Investigator.          Last Modified: 05/01/2018       Submitted by: Charles L Nunn]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
