<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>I-Corps:  Protein Transduction Domain Mimics to Revolutionize Immunology</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>12/01/2013</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2015</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>50000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>50000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07070000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>IIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Industrial Innovation &amp; Partnersh</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Rathindra DasGupta</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The proposed technology is based on the discovery of a class of polymeric protein transduction domain mimics (PTDMs) with the unique ability to intra-cellularly deliver a large variety of biomolecules (small molecules, nucleic acids, proteins and even whole, intact antibodies). Both in vitro and in vivo (with mouse models) experiments have been successfully performed demonstrating the efficacy of this technology. These molecules are synthesized via Ring-Opening Metathesis Polymerization (ROMP), which allows high fidelity over the chemical composition and structure. These PTDMs do not require covalent attached of the cargo, making this innovation applicable to various biomolecules and extremely easy to use. This innovation gives potential access to many intracellular compartments and functions thus offering new research and therapeutic opportunities.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Accessibility to the human body and its highly regulated functions has always been one of the biggest challenges for biomedical sciences. The human genome and proteome projects have greatly contributed to elucidate many biological and molecular functions of the human body and to advance treatment of diseases by discovering new cellular targets. Unfortunately, this important knowledge cannot yet been fully applied because of the lack of permeability and the high selectivity of the cell membrane which makes these targets inaccessible. The delivery described in this proposal has the potential to enable many new research and application opportunities, especially, but not exclusively, in the immunology field where it will finally become possible to manipulate the so far impenetrable T-cells. T-cells play a critical role in cell-mediated immune response, for example against infections, cancer and HIV. The ability to control their activation, in a more efficient and safer way than the traditional electroporation and virus infection, will have a big societal and commercial impact.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>11/27/2013</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>11/27/2013</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1355761</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Gregory</FirstName>
<LastName>Tew</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>N</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Gregory N Tew</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>tew@mail.pse.umass.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>4135771612</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000251585</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>11/27/2013</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Massachusetts Amherst</Name>
<CityName>Hadley</CityName>
<ZipCode>010359450</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>4135450698</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>Research Administration Building</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[100 Venture Way, Suite 201]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
<StateCode>MA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MA02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>153926712</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF MASSACHUSETTS</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Massachusetts Amherst]]></Name>
<CityName>Amherst</CityName>
<StateCode>MA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>010039263</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[120 Governors Drive]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MA02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>8023</Code>
<Text>I-Corps</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0114</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~50000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The delivery of macromolecules inside of cells is a fundamental technique which enables basic scientific questions to be answered and ultimately new commercial opportunities to be developed.&nbsp; At the same time, the routine delivery of biologics, particularly proteins and antibodies, is non-trivial.&nbsp; We developed a novel, robust technology that enables delivery of siRNA, proteins, and antibodies into previously difficult-to-enter cell types.&nbsp; During the I-Corps program, we focused on getting this technology into the market place to gain customer validation.&nbsp; Our approach to customer development was two-fold:&nbsp; (a) widely disseminate our information and (b)&nbsp; work closely with a selected number of customers to extend the list of applications for this innovation.</p> <p class="NIH12space">The technology is based on the discovery of a new potent class of polymeric molecules with the unique ability to intracellularly deliver a large variety of biomolecules (small molecules, nucleic acids, proteins and even whole, intact antibodies). Both in vitro and in vivo (with mouse models) experiments successfully demonstrated the efficacy of this technology compared to the top commercially available delivery agents. These molecules are synthesized via ring-opening metathesis polymerization.&nbsp; The molecules are termed protein transduction domain mimics (PTDMs). This innovation gives potential access to many intracellular compartments and functions thus offering new research and therapeutic opportunities.</p> <p>Accessibility to the human body and its highly regulated functions has always been one of the biggest challenges for modern sciences. The human genome and proteome projects have greatly contributed to elucidate many biological and molecular functions of the human body and to advance treatment of diseases by discovering new cellular targets. Unfortunately, this important knowledge cannot yet been fully applied because of the lack of permeability and the high selectivity of the cell membrane which makes these targets inaccessible. The delivery breakthrough developed here enables many new research and application opportunities, especially, but not exclusively, in the immunology field where it will finally become possible to manipulate the so far impenetrable T-cells. T-cells play a critical role in cell-mediated immune response, for example against infections, cancer and HIV. The ability to control their activation, in a more efficient and safer way than the traditional electroporation and virus infection, will have a big societal and commercial impact.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 07/24/2015<br>      Modified by: Gregory&nbsp;N&nbsp;Tew</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Image         </div> <div class="galControls onePhoto" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation onePhoto" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2015/1355761/1355761_10285966_1437746063600_Overviewimage--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2015/1355761/1355761_10285966_1437746063600_Overviewimage--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Overview of Project"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2015/1355761/1355761_10285966_1437746063600_Overviewimage--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Overview of Project"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Our novel polymers allow the intracellular delivery of biologics.</div> <div class="imageCredit">greg tew</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Gregory&nbsp;N&nbsp;Tew</div> <div class="imageTitle">Overview of Project</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The delivery of macromolecules inside of cells is a fundamental technique which enables basic scientific questions to be answered and ultimately new commercial opportunities to be developed.  At the same time, the routine delivery of biologics, particularly proteins and antibodies, is non-trivial.  We developed a novel, robust technology that enables delivery of siRNA, proteins, and antibodies into previously difficult-to-enter cell types.  During the I-Corps program, we focused on getting this technology into the market place to gain customer validation.  Our approach to customer development was two-fold:  (a) widely disseminate our information and (b)  work closely with a selected number of customers to extend the list of applications for this innovation. The technology is based on the discovery of a new potent class of polymeric molecules with the unique ability to intracellularly deliver a large variety of biomolecules (small molecules, nucleic acids, proteins and even whole, intact antibodies). Both in vitro and in vivo (with mouse models) experiments successfully demonstrated the efficacy of this technology compared to the top commercially available delivery agents. These molecules are synthesized via ring-opening metathesis polymerization.  The molecules are termed protein transduction domain mimics (PTDMs). This innovation gives potential access to many intracellular compartments and functions thus offering new research and therapeutic opportunities.  Accessibility to the human body and its highly regulated functions has always been one of the biggest challenges for modern sciences. The human genome and proteome projects have greatly contributed to elucidate many biological and molecular functions of the human body and to advance treatment of diseases by discovering new cellular targets. Unfortunately, this important knowledge cannot yet been fully applied because of the lack of permeability and the high selectivity of the cell membrane which makes these targets inaccessible. The delivery breakthrough developed here enables many new research and application opportunities, especially, but not exclusively, in the immunology field where it will finally become possible to manipulate the so far impenetrable T-cells. T-cells play a critical role in cell-mediated immune response, for example against infections, cancer and HIV. The ability to control their activation, in a more efficient and safer way than the traditional electroporation and virus infection, will have a big societal and commercial impact.       Last Modified: 07/24/2015       Submitted by: Gregory N Tew]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
