<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Research Initiation Awards: Spatial-temporal Information Fusion and Real-time Sensor Data Assimilation Using Sequential Monte Carlo Methods</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/15/2013</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>03/31/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>160448.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>160448</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>11060000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>EHR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>HRD</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Human Resource Development</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Claudia Rankins</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The Research Initiation Award project entitled - Spatial-temporal Information Fusion and Real-time Sensor Data Assimilation Using Sequential Monte Carlo Methods - has the overarching goal to develop tractable approaches for spatial-temporal information fusion and real time sensor data assimilation using state of the art probabilistic techniques based on sequential Monte Carlo (SMC) methods. New algorithms and methods will be developed to enhance the effectiveness and efficiency of information fusion and data assimilation for large-scale spatial temporal systems. A special focus is to effectively use real-time information and sensor data from geographically distributed data sources for more accurate state inference using SMC methods. Specific objectives of this project include: developing innovative algorithms to exploit the spatial-temporal state of a system for more effective sampling/resampling and convergence of SMC methods; developing advanced data integration methods to support assimilating real-time information and sensor data from distributed data sources;  and developing new computing methods and infrastructure based on parallel environment to enhance performance of large-scale information fusion and data assimilation.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The project promises to have an impact on both theoretical and practical aspects of spatial-temporal information fusion and real time sensor data assimilation. The newly developed methods will increase the capability of seamlessly integrating real time data streams to support better analysis and prediction and real time decision making. The project involves undergraduate students by training them to conduct research in a stepwise manner, broadening their network, and preparing them for graduate studies or the workforce. The project will enhance the teaching of computer science classes on campus of Voorhees College by remotely accessing the cluster system at Georgia State University on which students can run parallel and distributed programs.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>09/01/2013</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>09/01/2013</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.076</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1356977</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Feng</FirstName>
<LastName>Gu</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Feng Gu</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>Feng.Gu@csi.cuny.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>7189822847</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000587895</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/01/2013</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>CUNY College of Staten Island</Name>
<CityName>Staten Island</CityName>
<ZipCode>103146609</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>7189822254</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>2800 Victory Boulevard</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[1A-211]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>11</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NY11</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>620128079</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>RESEARCH FOUNDATION OF THE CITY UNIVERSITY OF NEW YORK</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>073268849</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[CUNY College of Staten Island]]></Name>
<CityName>Staten Island</CityName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<ZipCode>103146609</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[2800 Victory Blvd]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>11</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NY11</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1594</Code>
<Text>Hist Black Colleges and Univ</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9178</Code>
<Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0413</Code>
<Name>NSF Education &amp; Human Resource</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040106</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2013~160448</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; Assimilating real time sensor data into large-scale spatial temporal dynamic systems for improved state inference is a challenging task since these systems exhibit dynamic behaviors in both space and time. Sequential Monte Carlo methods (also called particle filters) are used for data assimilation of large-scale spatial temporal dynamic systems due to their very little assumptions for the systems' properties. The challenges are associated with the high computational cost due to a large number of used particles&nbsp;in the particle filters algorithm,&nbsp;the complexity of the models of the dynamic systems, and the availability and heterogeneity of real time sensor data. These require the innovative sampling/resampling algorithms, effective data integration, and high performance computing methods. In this project, we aimed to resolve&nbsp;these challenges and produced the following research and educational outcomes.</p> <p>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; 1. We designed a hybrid particle routing policy&nbsp;for parallel/distributed particle filters of large-scale spatial temporal dynamic systems by systematically analyzing different particle routing policies including the centralized resampling algorithms and the decentralized resampling algorithms. The hybrid particle routing policy is based on the decentralized resampling and occasionally uses the centralized resampling. Thus we decrease the computational cost by mainly using the decentralized resampling and&nbsp;guarantee the accuracy by occasionally using the centralized resampling. The designed algorithm was applied to the application of wildfire spread and achieved improved&nbsp;performance without loss of accuracy. &nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; 2. The hybrid particle routing policy can improve the performance of parallel/distributed particle filters by using both of the centralized&nbsp;resampling and the decentralized resampling. In many scenarios, the occasional usage of the centralized resampling is even not needed. We designed adaptive particle routing policy by&nbsp;replacing those unnecessary&nbsp;centralized resampling steps with the decentralized resampling&nbsp;based on the measured convergence of particles to further improve the performance.</p> <p>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; 3. We designed a Localized Recursive Spatial-temporal State Quantification (LRSSQ) methods to support runtime quantification in sequential Monte Carlo methods. By adapting the LRSSQ method, we use different sampling or resampling algorithms to achieve improved state inference or improve the performance. Two different algorithms were developed for the LRSSQ methods, the algorithm to adaptively perturb the state space and the adaptive particle filtering algorithm. They either improve the state inference or enhance the performance of particle filters in large-scale spatial temporal dynamic systems.</p> <p>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; 4. We developed an on-demand data assimilation algorithm of large-scale spatial temporal dynamic systems based on sequential Monte Carlo methods. This on-demand algorithm checks the measured convergence of particles at runtime and decides if additional data are needed from the sensor data module. If multiple types of data are available, the combined effect will be used according to their measures of convergence.</p> <p>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; 5. We applied particle filters algorithms in transportation systems to reconstruct events, such as the traffic congestion caused by a slow car in the transportation network.</p> <p>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; 6. We provided exposures of research in modeling and simulation and high performance computing to faculty and students at both Voorhees College and CUNY College of Staten Island, and Ph.D. students at CUNY Graduate Center by disseminating the project via invited research talks, trainings, and dedicated websites.</p> <p>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; 7. About seven undergraduate students and four Ph.D. students conducted research in this project,&nbsp;and more other students motivated by the project were involved in the research in modeling and simulation and high performance computing.</p> <p>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; 8. We restarted the teaching of modeling and simulation for graduate students at CUNY College of Staten Island, taught modeling and simulation course for Ph.D. students at CUNY Graduate Center and other New York City institutions. Three different levels of high performance computing courses were offered to undergraduate students and master students at CUNY College of Staten Island, and one parallel computing course was offered to Ph.D. students at CUNY Graduate Center.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 06/25/2017<br>      Modified by: Feng&nbsp;Gu</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[       Assimilating real time sensor data into large-scale spatial temporal dynamic systems for improved state inference is a challenging task since these systems exhibit dynamic behaviors in both space and time. Sequential Monte Carlo methods (also called particle filters) are used for data assimilation of large-scale spatial temporal dynamic systems due to their very little assumptions for the systems' properties. The challenges are associated with the high computational cost due to a large number of used particles in the particle filters algorithm, the complexity of the models of the dynamic systems, and the availability and heterogeneity of real time sensor data. These require the innovative sampling/resampling algorithms, effective data integration, and high performance computing methods. In this project, we aimed to resolve these challenges and produced the following research and educational outcomes.        1. We designed a hybrid particle routing policy for parallel/distributed particle filters of large-scale spatial temporal dynamic systems by systematically analyzing different particle routing policies including the centralized resampling algorithms and the decentralized resampling algorithms. The hybrid particle routing policy is based on the decentralized resampling and occasionally uses the centralized resampling. Thus we decrease the computational cost by mainly using the decentralized resampling and guarantee the accuracy by occasionally using the centralized resampling. The designed algorithm was applied to the application of wildfire spread and achieved improved performance without loss of accuracy.          2. The hybrid particle routing policy can improve the performance of parallel/distributed particle filters by using both of the centralized resampling and the decentralized resampling. In many scenarios, the occasional usage of the centralized resampling is even not needed. We designed adaptive particle routing policy by replacing those unnecessary centralized resampling steps with the decentralized resampling based on the measured convergence of particles to further improve the performance.        3. We designed a Localized Recursive Spatial-temporal State Quantification (LRSSQ) methods to support runtime quantification in sequential Monte Carlo methods. By adapting the LRSSQ method, we use different sampling or resampling algorithms to achieve improved state inference or improve the performance. Two different algorithms were developed for the LRSSQ methods, the algorithm to adaptively perturb the state space and the adaptive particle filtering algorithm. They either improve the state inference or enhance the performance of particle filters in large-scale spatial temporal dynamic systems.        4. We developed an on-demand data assimilation algorithm of large-scale spatial temporal dynamic systems based on sequential Monte Carlo methods. This on-demand algorithm checks the measured convergence of particles at runtime and decides if additional data are needed from the sensor data module. If multiple types of data are available, the combined effect will be used according to their measures of convergence.        5. We applied particle filters algorithms in transportation systems to reconstruct events, such as the traffic congestion caused by a slow car in the transportation network.        6. We provided exposures of research in modeling and simulation and high performance computing to faculty and students at both Voorhees College and CUNY College of Staten Island, and Ph.D. students at CUNY Graduate Center by disseminating the project via invited research talks, trainings, and dedicated websites.        7. About seven undergraduate students and four Ph.D. students conducted research in this project, and more other students motivated by the project were involved in the research in modeling and simulation and high performance computing.        8. We restarted the teaching of modeling and simulation for graduate students at CUNY College of Staten Island, taught modeling and simulation course for Ph.D. students at CUNY Graduate Center and other New York City institutions. Three different levels of high performance computing courses were offered to undergraduate students and master students at CUNY College of Staten Island, and one parallel computing course was offered to Ph.D. students at CUNY Graduate Center.       Last Modified: 06/25/2017       Submitted by: Feng Gu]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
