<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Collaborative Research: ABI Innovation: Algorithms and tools for modeling macromolecular assemblies</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2014</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>234668.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>234668</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>08080000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>BIO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DBI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Biological Infrastructure</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Jennifer Weller</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This research seeks to develop novel methods and software tools for mining structures of large molecular assemblies from imaging data. Macromolecular assemblies, such as ribosomes and viruses, are responsible for driving nearly all cellular events. How these assemblies function, in turn, is closely related with their 3D&lt;br/&gt;structures, which are analogous to interlocking puzzles consisting of tens to hundreds of proteins, each having its own unique shape. The ability to model the structure of individual proteins as well as their architecture in an assembly is therefore critically important for understanding how the cell, and more broadly the biological system, function. While state-of-art imaging methods have been developed to capture macromolecular assemblies as 3D density volumes, such as X-ray crystallography and electron cryo-microscopy, creating structural models from such imagery remains a time-consuming and highly manual process in part due to the limited resolution of the data. The goal of the project is to streamline the image-to-structure pipeline by designing novel computational algorithms and developing a comprehensive modeling platform. The algorithms seek to leverage the advance in computer graphics and vision while combining image data, sequence data, and expert knowledge to improve the efficiency and accuracy of common modeling tasks. The modeling platform will integrate the investigator's methods with third-party modeling packages to provide an easy-to-use one-stop-shop for creating and validating structures of macromolecular assemblies all the way from raw images and individual protein sequences. The platform will be built upon the existing Gorgon software (http://gorgon.wustl.edu) and distributed together with the popular EMAN2 software for image analysis of density maps. The outcome of the project will have a direct impact on reducing the time and effort that biologists spend on translating experimental results to knowledge, discoveries, and treatments.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;More specifically, the project will focus on algorithmic development on three modeling tasks that currently either rely on manual labor or are computationally expensive. These problems include detecting secondary structure elements (e.g., alpha-helices and beta-sheets) at various non-atomic resolutions, tracing protein backbones in the density volume, and flexibly fitting probe structures into the volume. The algorithms will build upon successful techniques from computer graphics and vision, including mesh deformation using differential coordinates and spectral feature matching. To transform Gorgon into a modeling "hub", the software architecture and interface of Gorgon will be redesigned in this project to improve inter-operability, scalability, and usability. Plug-ins will also be developed for third-party tools that provide complementary modeling capability such as comparative modeling and protein folding.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/08/2014</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/08/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.074</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1356388</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Tao</FirstName>
<LastName>Ju</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Tao Ju</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>taoju@cse.wustl.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>3149356648</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000492331</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/08/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Washington University</Name>
<CityName>Saint Louis</CityName>
<ZipCode>631304862</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>3147474134</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>CAMPUS BOX 1054</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[1 Brookings Drive]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Missouri</StateName>
<StateCode>MO</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MO01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>068552207</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>WASHINGTON UNIVERSITY, THE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>068552207</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Washington University]]></Name>
<CityName>St. Louis</CityName>
<StateCode>MO</StateCode>
<ZipCode>631304899</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[One Brookings Drive]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Missouri</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MO01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1165</Code>
<Text>ADVANCES IN BIO INFORMATICS</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9179</Code>
<Text>GRADUATE INVOLVEMENT</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0114</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~234668</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><span id="docs-internal-guid-fd4a4142-7fff-bf73-7314-c53763f66bcb"> </span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>Advances in biological imaging methods (e.g., X-ray crystallography and electron cryo-microscopy, or cryo-EM) have allowed macromolecular assemblies, such as viruses and ribosomes, to be captured in intricate details. However, challenged by the limited resolution afforded by these imaging techniques, computational methods for creating biologically meaningful structural models from images are still underdeveloped. Furthermore, creating a structural model currently requires mix-and-matching of a variety of interactive and automated tools, while a coherent modeling environment is lacking.</span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>In this collaborative project between researchers at Washington University in St. Louis and Baylor College of Medicine, we have developed novel algorithms and software package to improve the automation, efficiency and coherence of the data-to-knowledge process from 3D images to macromolecular assembly structures. On one hand, we have designed and tested novel algorithms for feature detection from density maps, matching secondary structures, and flexible fitting of templates. These algorithms have significantly outperformed previous methods in terms of accuracy, efficiency, and scalability. On the other hand, we have re-engineered the Gorgon software, a platform for protein modeling from density maps. While the original tool has already been widely used in the structural biology community due to its unique features for de novo modeling, the re-designed software has significantly improved modularity, scalability, and interoperability with 3rd party tools, making it a flexible modeling platform for density maps.</span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>The outcome of our has significant impact both within structure biology and in other disciplines. Within structural biology, the proposed research fills a critical need as the macromolecular assemblies captured by X-ray crystallography or cryo-EM imaging continues to grow. Beyond structural biology, our research for more efficient and accurate model-building of macromolecular assemblies contributes to both basic biological science and biotechnology.</span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>The research has produced six peer-reviewed publications in top venues in both biology (e.g., Nature and J. Structure Biology) and computer science (e.g., &nbsp;ACM Transactions on Graphics). The redesigned Gorgon software is publicly distributed on GitHub to serve the biology community. The PIs have presented numerous talks in conferences and invited venues. The project has provided training for a number of graduate students, undergraduate students, and a scientific programmer across the two institutions.</span></p> <div></div> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 09/17/2018<br>      Modified by: Tao&nbsp;Ju</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Images (<span id="selectedPhoto0">1</span> of <span class="totalNumber"></span>)           </div> <div class="galControls" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1356388/1356388_10316866_1537217914666_gr4--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1356388/1356388_10316866_1537217914666_gr4--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Flexible fitting of atomic structures"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1356388/1356388_10316866_1537217914666_gr4--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Flexible fitting of atomic structures"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">This picture from [Dou et al. 2017] compares the results of our flexible fitting method (purple) with rigid-body fitting on six density maps.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Tao Ju</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Tao&nbsp;Ju</div> <div class="imageTitle">Flexible fitting of atomic structures</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1356388/1356388_10316866_1537217728080_Untitled-1--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1356388/1356388_10316866_1537217728080_Untitled-1--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Helix matching"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1356388/1356388_10316866_1537217728080_Untitled-1--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Helix matching"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Picture from [Dou et al. 2015] paper on matching two sets of helical segments, one from an existing template structure (a,c) and one from a target density map (b,d).</div> <div class="imageCredit">Tao Ju</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Tao&nbsp;Ju</div> <div class="imageTitle">Helix matching</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[   Advances in biological imaging methods (e.g., X-ray crystallography and electron cryo-microscopy, or cryo-EM) have allowed macromolecular assemblies, such as viruses and ribosomes, to be captured in intricate details. However, challenged by the limited resolution afforded by these imaging techniques, computational methods for creating biologically meaningful structural models from images are still underdeveloped. Furthermore, creating a structural model currently requires mix-and-matching of a variety of interactive and automated tools, while a coherent modeling environment is lacking. In this collaborative project between researchers at Washington University in St. Louis and Baylor College of Medicine, we have developed novel algorithms and software package to improve the automation, efficiency and coherence of the data-to-knowledge process from 3D images to macromolecular assembly structures. On one hand, we have designed and tested novel algorithms for feature detection from density maps, matching secondary structures, and flexible fitting of templates. These algorithms have significantly outperformed previous methods in terms of accuracy, efficiency, and scalability. On the other hand, we have re-engineered the Gorgon software, a platform for protein modeling from density maps. While the original tool has already been widely used in the structural biology community due to its unique features for de novo modeling, the re-designed software has significantly improved modularity, scalability, and interoperability with 3rd party tools, making it a flexible modeling platform for density maps. The outcome of our has significant impact both within structure biology and in other disciplines. Within structural biology, the proposed research fills a critical need as the macromolecular assemblies captured by X-ray crystallography or cryo-EM imaging continues to grow. Beyond structural biology, our research for more efficient and accurate model-building of macromolecular assemblies contributes to both basic biological science and biotechnology. The research has produced six peer-reviewed publications in top venues in both biology (e.g., Nature and J. Structure Biology) and computer science (e.g.,  ACM Transactions on Graphics). The redesigned Gorgon software is publicly distributed on GitHub to serve the biology community. The PIs have presented numerous talks in conferences and invited venues. The project has provided training for a number of graduate students, undergraduate students, and a scientific programmer across the two institutions.           Last Modified: 09/17/2018       Submitted by: Tao Ju]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
