<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Scholarships for Tech Valley Scholars in Computational, Mathematical, and Physical Sciences</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>04/15/2014</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>03/31/2020</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>618689.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>618689</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>11040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>EHR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DUE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Undergraduate Education</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Michael Ferrara</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>mferrara@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922635</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The Computer Science and Physics &amp; Astronomy Departments at Siena College, through their Scholarships for Tech Valley Scholars in Computational, Mathematical and Physical Sciences (CMPS), are providing scholarships for a total of forty talented undergraduates with financial need who are majoring in Computer Science, Mathematics, or Physics. By increasing the number and quality of STEM majors through focused recruitment, retention, and career placement practices, the Tech Valley Scholars (TVS) program is helping to meet regional workforce development needs in New York's greater Hudson Valley.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Key project elements include cohort support activities centered on a TVS one-credit seminar each semester, continuous mentoring and guidance of students throughout the program, and creation of an innovative learning environment using the latest developments in STEM education research.  As TVS participants, undergraduate students gain experience working on teams and developing skills and perspectives that are necessary for innovations in the application of STEM technologies.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>04/06/2014</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/23/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.076</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1356379</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Lucas</FirstName>
<LastName>Tucker</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>J</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Lucas J Tucker</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>ltucker@siena.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5187832300</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000150650</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/06/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Jodi</FirstName>
<LastName>O'Donnell</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>L</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Jodi L O'Donnell</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>jodonnell@siena.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5187832509</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000207741</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/23/2016</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Michele</FirstName>
<LastName>McColgan</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>W</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Michele W McColgan</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>mmccolgan@siena.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5187832300</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000502428</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/06/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Jon</FirstName>
<LastName>Bannon</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>P</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Jon P Bannon</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>jbannon@siena.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5187832300</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000516638</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/06/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Sharon</FirstName>
<LastName>Small</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Sharon Small</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>ssmall@siena.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5187832300</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000605870</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/06/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Larry</FirstName>
<LastName>Medsker</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Larry Medsker</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>lrm@gwu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>8024884708</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000648547</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/06/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate>06/23/2016</EndDate>
<RoleCode>Former Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Siena College</Name>
<CityName>LOUDONVILLE</CityName>
<ZipCode>122111462</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5187822322</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>515 LOUDON ROAD</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>20</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NY20</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>080481351</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>SIENA COLLEGE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>080481351</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Siena College]]></Name>
<CityName>Loudonville</CityName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<ZipCode>122111462</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[515 Loudon Road]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>20</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NY20</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1536</Code>
<Text>S-STEM-Schlr Sci Tech Eng&amp;Math</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9178</Code>
<Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>SMET</Code>
<Text>SCIENCE, MATH, ENG &amp; TECH EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>13XX</Code>
<Name>H-1B FUND, EHR, NSF</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>045176</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~618689</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The NSF S-STEM Award to Siena College, Scholarships for Tech Valley Scholars (TVS) in Computational, Mathematical, and Physical Sciences, resulted in very high STEM retention with excellent educational outcomes for students in groups that typically experience poor retention due to high unmet financial need and other retention risk factors. Our study published in 2016 on our first TVS cohort identified a number of risk factors for non-persistence in STEM at Siena College and concluded that participation in the TVS program greatly enhanced both retention and GPAs for students in the program relative to matched and unmatched control groups. Preliminary analysis of the cohort supported by this award shows similar outcomes, with no statistically significant declines in STEM persistence or GPA based on the risk factors we previously identified. For example, ten of the 34 students participating in the community-engaged research cohort had unmet need after scholarships and grants exceeding $10,000 yet retained in STEM at a rate of 100% with an average GPA of 3.57.&nbsp;</p> <p>Our cohort experience focused on teambuilding, career exploration, soft skills for interviewing and career success, and group work on in-depth multi-semester projects with our community partner, Radix Ecological Sustainability Center. Each semester, student gave team presentations on their Radix projects and STEM careers. Individual students also spoke to the cohort about experiences from study abroad, internships, and REUs. Individual and panel presentations from Siena faculty, STEM professionals from the local community, and TVS alumni afforded participants opportunities to engage with various aspects of life after college.</p> <p>In addition to providing need-based grants, cohort members were eligible for stipends to do original research during both the summer and the academic year and to travel to national conferences to present their research results. While at conferences, participants explored career and graduate school opportunities. The PI has also communicated our successes and methods to regional and national audiences.</p> <p>In summary, there appear to be significant gains in academic performance and STEM retention for participants in the TVS. While financial assistance provided by the program greatly diminishes the risk factor associated with high unmet need, even in cases where high unmet need after scholarship awards wasn&rsquo;t mitigated, participants greatly outperformed peers of similar unmet need. This outcome suggests that our cohort experience alone may have a positive impact on outcomes for some populations at risk of non-retention in STEM. We continue our efforts to elucidate the role of the financial support versus that of the cohort experience by comparing student outcomes and persistence data between this program and other cohort experiences at Siena.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 07/30/2020<br>      Modified by: Jodi&nbsp;L&nbsp;O'donnell</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The NSF S-STEM Award to Siena College, Scholarships for Tech Valley Scholars (TVS) in Computational, Mathematical, and Physical Sciences, resulted in very high STEM retention with excellent educational outcomes for students in groups that typically experience poor retention due to high unmet financial need and other retention risk factors. Our study published in 2016 on our first TVS cohort identified a number of risk factors for non-persistence in STEM at Siena College and concluded that participation in the TVS program greatly enhanced both retention and GPAs for students in the program relative to matched and unmatched control groups. Preliminary analysis of the cohort supported by this award shows similar outcomes, with no statistically significant declines in STEM persistence or GPA based on the risk factors we previously identified. For example, ten of the 34 students participating in the community-engaged research cohort had unmet need after scholarships and grants exceeding $10,000 yet retained in STEM at a rate of 100% with an average GPA of 3.57.   Our cohort experience focused on teambuilding, career exploration, soft skills for interviewing and career success, and group work on in-depth multi-semester projects with our community partner, Radix Ecological Sustainability Center. Each semester, student gave team presentations on their Radix projects and STEM careers. Individual students also spoke to the cohort about experiences from study abroad, internships, and REUs. Individual and panel presentations from Siena faculty, STEM professionals from the local community, and TVS alumni afforded participants opportunities to engage with various aspects of life after college.  In addition to providing need-based grants, cohort members were eligible for stipends to do original research during both the summer and the academic year and to travel to national conferences to present their research results. While at conferences, participants explored career and graduate school opportunities. The PI has also communicated our successes and methods to regional and national audiences.  In summary, there appear to be significant gains in academic performance and STEM retention for participants in the TVS. While financial assistance provided by the program greatly diminishes the risk factor associated with high unmet need, even in cases where high unmet need after scholarship awards wasn’t mitigated, participants greatly outperformed peers of similar unmet need. This outcome suggests that our cohort experience alone may have a positive impact on outcomes for some populations at risk of non-retention in STEM. We continue our efforts to elucidate the role of the financial support versus that of the cohort experience by comparing student outcomes and persistence data between this program and other cohort experiences at Siena.       Last Modified: 07/30/2020       Submitted by: Jodi L O'donnell]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
