<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Alcohol Intoxication and Young Adults</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2014</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2016</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>219996.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>219996</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>04050000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>SBE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>SES</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Divn Of Social and Economic Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Patricia White</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This project will examine the meaning, practices, and contexts of alcohol intoxication among young adults. Alcohol intoxication is associated with a wide range of health problems and adverse consequences, is a major risk factor for mortality and morbidity, and can lead to a host of social problems. The existing research indicates that gender patterns in alcohol consumption may be converging, yet it is unclear if the meaning, practices, and contexts of intoxication for men and women are also converging. The vast majority of research on alcohol use and intoxication has been conducted within epidemiological, psychological, treatment, or bio-health traditions, however in this sociological study our aim is to examine issues of the meaning of intoxication for young adult men and women. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The primary data collection tool will be in-depth interviews with 50 young adults, between the ages of 18 to 25, who drink to intoxication. The interview will include a survey with open-ended questions to gather extensive information about their beliefs about intoxication; the social practices, settings, and perceived consequences of intoxication; and the role and meanings of alcohol intoxication within their lives. Broader Impacts of the project include making an important contribution to sociological inquiry, and especially the connections between social context and cultural consumption. In addition, the results will produce important information about the meaning, practices, and contexts of alcohol intoxication in a diverse sample of young adult men and women.  The knowledge generated can make an important contribution to public health and policy by expanding and transforming knowledge about alcohol intoxication from the perspective of young adults.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/30/2014</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/30/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.075</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1356094</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Geoffrey</FirstName>
<LastName>Hunt</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>P</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Geoffrey P Hunt</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>huntgisa@ix.netcom.com</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>4157772352</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000625398</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/30/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Molly</FirstName>
<LastName>Moloney</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Molly Moloney</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>molly.moloney@gmail.com</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>4157772352</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000625965</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/30/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Scientific Analysis Corporation</Name>
<CityName>San Francisco</CityName>
<ZipCode>941071227</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>4157772352</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>390 4th Street</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[2nd Floor]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>12</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CA12</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>044875854</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>SCIENTIFIC ANALYSIS CORPORATION</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>044875854</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Scientific Analysis Corporation]]></Name>
<CityName>San Francisco</CityName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>941071227</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[390 4th Street]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>12</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CA12</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1331</Code>
<Text>Sociology</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0114</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~219996</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><span style="text-decoration: underline;">Overview:</span>The aim of the project was to develop a theory of intoxication that examined &nbsp;the relationship between gender and the meaning, practices, and contexts of alcohol intoxication among young adults.</p> <p><span style="text-decoration: underline;">Intellectual Merit: </span>Alcohol intoxication and heavy drinking among young adults has been highlighted as a noteworthy social phenomenon by alcohol researchers, who have documented young adulthood as a peak period of heavy drinking and have noted a trend toward gender convergence in many drinking practices. The outcome of the project has been to advance sociological knowledge by developing a theory of intoxication to inform contemporary discussions.</p> <p><span style="text-decoration: underline;">Broader Impact: </span>Alcohol intoxication is associated with a wide range of health problems and adverse consequences and is a major risk factor for mortality and morbidity,which can lead to a whole host of social problems. Recently, researchers have noted a culture of &rdquo;extreme drinking&rdquo;&nbsp; among young people, both young women and men which has normalized drinking to intoxication.The project has produced important information about the meaning and practicesof alcohol intoxication in a sample of young adult men and women.Although this project was driven by sociologically theoretical questions, the results can make an important contribution to public health and policy by expanding our knowledge about alcohol intoxication. These findings can be utilized in designing more effective gender-specific messages or preventive interventions designed to decrease the harms associated with heavy alcohol consumption.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>Results from this project will also be important in informing the recent debate on drinking and sexual consent. Sexual assault (i.e., nonconsensual sexual activity) is a substantial problem in the United States. Public concern about sexual assault has grown in recent years, particularly on college campuses. Although concerns about sexual assault and sexual consent among young adults have proliferated, the available research on sexual consent is still relatively sparse. What is clear from the available literature is that pathways to sexual consent appear quite different for young women and men. The research illustrates how women&rsquo;s preferences for negotiating consent (i.e. explicit verbal communication) do not appear to operate in practice, suggesting that men&rsquo;s preferences for how to negotiate consent continue to dominate sexual encounters in spite of increasingly common &ldquo;Yes Means Yes&rdquo; sexual health promotion campaigns.</p> <p>Given the endemic nature of alcohol consumption within sexual encounters, a key element in any discussion of sexual consent is the connection between drinking and sexual encounters, a relationship that has been well developed in research studies. Research suggests that women and men are both more likely to engage in casual sex when alcohol is involved, and the more alcohol consumed the greater the probability that casual sexual encounters will occur. Young adults consume alcohol with the expected belief that alcohol will increase their sexual drive and decrease their inhibitions and men encourage women to consume alcohol because they believe that women will become more promiscuous and more sexually available. Therefore, it is clear that alcohol does not just enable or facilitate sexual encounters, but also influences the dynamics of the interaction, by signaling to many young adults an expectation of a sexual encounter when they become intoxicated. Furthermore, researchers have pointed to the influence of the &ldquo;rules of the game,&rdquo; where men are expected to be the initiators of sexual activity, and women play a more passive role as gatekeepers. This may account then for the extent to which young women report that, although they had sex while intoxicated, they had not wanted it. This finding was also discovered in our results, where young women distinguished cases of sexual assault from cases of unwanted sexual experiences. The key question for future research is whether or not the operation of these &ldquo;rules of the game&rdquo; within sexual encounters is further supported when alcohol and alcohol intoxication is involved. Does the presence of alcohol intoxication operate to excuse violent or aggressive acts. In other words, to what extent does intoxication excuse male aggression within sexual encounters.To date, intoxication has been argued to further excuse male sexual aggression and perpetuate victim-blaming narratives of young women.In light of the structural factors shaping sexual encounters, questions can be raised about the ability of affirmative models of consent to change the frequency of unwanted sex and sexual assaults, especially when intoxication is present, without a stronger acknowledgement of the centrality of intoxication in youth cultures.Consequently, we suggest that future research explore how alcohol intoxication operates within sexual encounters to further enable the existing unequal &ldquo;rules of the game&rdquo; for young women and men in sexual encounters.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 09/08/2016<br>      Modified by: Geoffrey&nbsp;P&nbsp;Hunt</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Overview:The aim of the project was to develop a theory of intoxication that examined  the relationship between gender and the meaning, practices, and contexts of alcohol intoxication among young adults.  Intellectual Merit: Alcohol intoxication and heavy drinking among young adults has been highlighted as a noteworthy social phenomenon by alcohol researchers, who have documented young adulthood as a peak period of heavy drinking and have noted a trend toward gender convergence in many drinking practices. The outcome of the project has been to advance sociological knowledge by developing a theory of intoxication to inform contemporary discussions.  Broader Impact: Alcohol intoxication is associated with a wide range of health problems and adverse consequences and is a major risk factor for mortality and morbidity,which can lead to a whole host of social problems. Recently, researchers have noted a culture of "extreme drinking"  among young people, both young women and men which has normalized drinking to intoxication.The project has produced important information about the meaning and practicesof alcohol intoxication in a sample of young adult men and women.Although this project was driven by sociologically theoretical questions, the results can make an important contribution to public health and policy by expanding our knowledge about alcohol intoxication. These findings can be utilized in designing more effective gender-specific messages or preventive interventions designed to decrease the harms associated with heavy alcohol consumption.     Results from this project will also be important in informing the recent debate on drinking and sexual consent. Sexual assault (i.e., nonconsensual sexual activity) is a substantial problem in the United States. Public concern about sexual assault has grown in recent years, particularly on college campuses. Although concerns about sexual assault and sexual consent among young adults have proliferated, the available research on sexual consent is still relatively sparse. What is clear from the available literature is that pathways to sexual consent appear quite different for young women and men. The research illustrates how women?s preferences for negotiating consent (i.e. explicit verbal communication) do not appear to operate in practice, suggesting that men?s preferences for how to negotiate consent continue to dominate sexual encounters in spite of increasingly common "Yes Means Yes" sexual health promotion campaigns.  Given the endemic nature of alcohol consumption within sexual encounters, a key element in any discussion of sexual consent is the connection between drinking and sexual encounters, a relationship that has been well developed in research studies. Research suggests that women and men are both more likely to engage in casual sex when alcohol is involved, and the more alcohol consumed the greater the probability that casual sexual encounters will occur. Young adults consume alcohol with the expected belief that alcohol will increase their sexual drive and decrease their inhibitions and men encourage women to consume alcohol because they believe that women will become more promiscuous and more sexually available. Therefore, it is clear that alcohol does not just enable or facilitate sexual encounters, but also influences the dynamics of the interaction, by signaling to many young adults an expectation of a sexual encounter when they become intoxicated. Furthermore, researchers have pointed to the influence of the "rules of the game," where men are expected to be the initiators of sexual activity, and women play a more passive role as gatekeepers. This may account then for the extent to which young women report that, although they had sex while intoxicated, they had not wanted it. This finding was also discovered in our results, where young women distinguished cases of sexual assault from cases of unwanted sexual experiences. The key question for future research is whether or not the operation of these "rules of the game" within sexual encounters is further supported when alcohol and alcohol intoxication is involved. Does the presence of alcohol intoxication operate to excuse violent or aggressive acts. In other words, to what extent does intoxication excuse male aggression within sexual encounters.To date, intoxication has been argued to further excuse male sexual aggression and perpetuate victim-blaming narratives of young women.In light of the structural factors shaping sexual encounters, questions can be raised about the ability of affirmative models of consent to change the frequency of unwanted sex and sexual assaults, especially when intoxication is present, without a stronger acknowledgement of the centrality of intoxication in youth cultures.Consequently, we suggest that future research explore how alcohol intoxication operates within sexual encounters to further enable the existing unequal "rules of the game" for young women and men in sexual encounters.          Last Modified: 09/08/2016       Submitted by: Geoffrey P Hunt]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
