<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Collaborative Research: Elucidating Conduit, Eruption, and Pyroclast Transport Dynamics of Large Silicic Submarine Eruptions</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>12/01/2014</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>11/30/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>278746.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>278746</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>06040200</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>GEO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>OCE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Ocean Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Deborah K. Smith</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>dksmith@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927978</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>There are tens of thousands of volcanoes on the ocean floor. It is not known how many of these are erupting at any given time because most are overlain by many hundreds to thousands of feet of water that prevent the escape of eruption products into the atmosphere or onto the sea surface where they can be spotted by ships, airplanes, or satellites. Similarly, it is not known how many of these undersea volcanoes erupt explosively, generating large quantities of ash and pumice that is then distributed by currents or cause volcanic slope instabilities that can result in tsunamis. Because seafloor eruptions, in particular those that are explosive in nature, are hidden from view, our knowledge of how they operate, their eruption products and their distribution, and their geohazard potential is almost unknown. Luckily in July 2012, a 200 square kilometer raft of pumice was spotted floating on the ocean in the western Pacific just above Havre Volcano which is under 1600 meters of water, indicating a major explosive eruption. Taking advantage of this event, this project mounts a major scientific investigation of the eruption. The research involves a comprehensive physical and chemical study of the volcano, the eruption, and the associated eruption products and their distribution near and far from their point of origin.  Through an oceanographic cruise using state-of-the-art robotic vehicles, the investigators will collect samples and sediment cores and create seafloor photo mosaics of the area.  The research also involves high resolution seafloor mapping and stratigraphic analysis of the related deposits in the vicinity of the volcano and in areas extending away from it.  Investigators will compile and analyze all available photographic images, pre- and post-eruptive seafloor maps, as well as analyze sediment cores and ash textures. The project also includes analysis and interpretation of stratigraphic, geochemical, and other associated datasets. A specific focus of the research is determining the role that volatiles such as H2O, SO2, and sulfur played in the eruption. Goals of the research are to determine: (1) what combination of magma ascent rates and conduit processes caused the formation of a subaerial eruption plume from water depths of more than 1600 m; (2) if the data can shed light on the outstanding controversy regarding the lack of fine ash in deposits now found on land but that were derived from subaqueous eruptions; and (3) whether density currents that result from eruption column collapse are the primary transport mechanism for mass sediment flux away from the volcano or if other processes dominate.  &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Broader impacts of the research include significant undergraduate training in research and state of the art field and laboratory scientific techniques, as well as cross training and video presentations that will link together all of the researchers and students at the institutions involved.  Additional impacts include international collaboration with New Zealand scientists and the creation of a new, international body to study submarine volcanoes and the impacts of their explosive eruption. Also included are presentations to local community groups and K-12 schools, impacts for geohazards and disaster planning, support of an institution in an EPSCoR state, and support of an early career investigator whose gender is under-represented in the sciences and engineering.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>11/18/2014</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/27/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.050</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1357216</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Samuel</FirstName>
<LastName>Soule</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>A</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Samuel A Soule</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>ssoule@whoi.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5082893213</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000431954</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>11/18/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Woods Hole Oceanographic Institution</Name>
<CityName>Woods Hole</CityName>
<ZipCode>025431535</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5082892623</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>266 Wood Hole Road</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[Fenno House, MS#39]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
<StateCode>MA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>09</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MA09</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>001766682</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>WOODS HOLE OCEANOGRAPHIC INSTITUTION</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>001766682</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Woods Hole Oceanographic Institution]]></Name>
<CityName>Woods Hole</CityName>
<StateCode>MA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>025431041</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[183 Oyster Pond Rd]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>09</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MA09</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1620</Code>
<Text>Marine Geology and Geophysics</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>0000</Code>
<Text>UNASSIGNED</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1620</Code>
<Text>MARINE GEOLOGY AND GEOPHYSICS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>OTHR</Code>
<Text>OTHER RESEARCH OR EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0115</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0116</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2015~196022</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2016~82724</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><span> </span>This project investigated the 2012 eruption of Havre Volcano in the Kermadec Arc. The eruption produced a volume of material that rivaled the 1980 eruption of Mt. St. Helens, making this the largest, deep-water silicic eruption to be well documented. The eruption was discovered serendipitously by an airline passenger noting a large &rsquo;something&rsquo; floating on the sea surface that turned out to be a raft of pumice from an eruption located 700-1000m below the surface. We conducted a field study using the National Deep Submergence Facility ROV Jason and AUV Sentry. We mapped the entire summit of the volcano at 1m resolution by AUV and conducted 13 ROV dives collecting over 200 seafloor samples.<span> </span></p> <p>The key findings of the study include the range of products produced during the eruption including lava flows and domes, fine ash, and pumice fragments, some of which were as large as a minivan. Careful documentation of the seafloor deposits revealed that most of the erupted material was carried away from the volcano in the pumice raft. The products deposited on the seafloor allowed us to reconstruct the dynamics of the eruption and investigate the processes of dispersal and deposition. Giant pumice are hypothesized to remain buoyant and travel farther from the eruptive vent the larger they are. Experiments and numerical models we conducted quantified those relationships. Direct observations of pumice deposits, however did not fit well with those models. Through detailed analysis of pumice textures via X-ray computed tomography, we discovered that giant pumice may contain large (5-10cm diameter) vesicle pipes that enhance cooling and saturation. This observation provides a framework to harmonize theoretical models (that assume homogeneous porosity) and observation. In contrast to pumice, studies of fine ash showed that dispersal is inversely related to size and is consistent with models from subaerial volcanoes that predict fining and thinning with distance. Together, these studies of dispersal lay a foundation for developing tools to reconstruct eruption dynamics simply from examination of deposits (as is done on land). This is critical at submarine volcanoes where observations of active eruptions are extremely rare.&nbsp;<span> </span></p> <p>Documenting the size and dynamics of submarine eruptions is important not only for volcanic studies, but for studies of the water column and sea surface. Retrospective analysis of ARGO float data and satellite imagery showed that the 2012 Havre eruption produced clear signals in salinity and temperature. In oligotrophic waters, this type of &lsquo;fertilization&rsquo; with nutrients by reactions with suspended volcanic particles and upwelling of deep water, can influence biological productivity.&nbsp;<span> </span></p> <p>At the seabed, dramatic changes in benthic habitat were produced during this eruption including the generation of new &lsquo;hard&rsquo; seafloor and blanketing by ash to produce new &lsquo;soft&rsquo; seafloor. Documentation of these new habitats and how they are colonized is of interest to the agencies and orginizations responsible for permitting and monitoring future seafloor mining operations that are expected to produce similar seabed disruption.<span> </span></p> <p>This study contributed to the training of one postdoctoral scholar, four PhD students, 2 masters students, and more than 10 graduate students, and more than 20 presentations at national and international meetings. In addition, the data and results were used in undergraduate and graduate courses at multiple institutions and were presented through the popular press (e.g., NPR Science Friday). Data and results are archived in over a dozen peer reviewed publications and in national archives (e.g., MGDS).</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 11/09/2020<br>      Modified by: Samuel&nbsp;A&nbsp;Soule</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[  This project investigated the 2012 eruption of Havre Volcano in the Kermadec Arc. The eruption produced a volume of material that rivaled the 1980 eruption of Mt. St. Helens, making this the largest, deep-water silicic eruption to be well documented. The eruption was discovered serendipitously by an airline passenger noting a large ’something’ floating on the sea surface that turned out to be a raft of pumice from an eruption located 700-1000m below the surface. We conducted a field study using the National Deep Submergence Facility ROV Jason and AUV Sentry. We mapped the entire summit of the volcano at 1m resolution by AUV and conducted 13 ROV dives collecting over 200 seafloor samples.   The key findings of the study include the range of products produced during the eruption including lava flows and domes, fine ash, and pumice fragments, some of which were as large as a minivan. Careful documentation of the seafloor deposits revealed that most of the erupted material was carried away from the volcano in the pumice raft. The products deposited on the seafloor allowed us to reconstruct the dynamics of the eruption and investigate the processes of dispersal and deposition. Giant pumice are hypothesized to remain buoyant and travel farther from the eruptive vent the larger they are. Experiments and numerical models we conducted quantified those relationships. Direct observations of pumice deposits, however did not fit well with those models. Through detailed analysis of pumice textures via X-ray computed tomography, we discovered that giant pumice may contain large (5-10cm diameter) vesicle pipes that enhance cooling and saturation. This observation provides a framework to harmonize theoretical models (that assume homogeneous porosity) and observation. In contrast to pumice, studies of fine ash showed that dispersal is inversely related to size and is consistent with models from subaerial volcanoes that predict fining and thinning with distance. Together, these studies of dispersal lay a foundation for developing tools to reconstruct eruption dynamics simply from examination of deposits (as is done on land). This is critical at submarine volcanoes where observations of active eruptions are extremely rare.    Documenting the size and dynamics of submarine eruptions is important not only for volcanic studies, but for studies of the water column and sea surface. Retrospective analysis of ARGO float data and satellite imagery showed that the 2012 Havre eruption produced clear signals in salinity and temperature. In oligotrophic waters, this type of ‘fertilization’ with nutrients by reactions with suspended volcanic particles and upwelling of deep water, can influence biological productivity.    At the seabed, dramatic changes in benthic habitat were produced during this eruption including the generation of new ‘hard’ seafloor and blanketing by ash to produce new ‘soft’ seafloor. Documentation of these new habitats and how they are colonized is of interest to the agencies and orginizations responsible for permitting and monitoring future seafloor mining operations that are expected to produce similar seabed disruption.   This study contributed to the training of one postdoctoral scholar, four PhD students, 2 masters students, and more than 10 graduate students, and more than 20 presentations at national and international meetings. In addition, the data and results were used in undergraduate and graduate courses at multiple institutions and were presented through the popular press (e.g., NPR Science Friday). Data and results are archived in over a dozen peer reviewed publications and in national archives (e.g., MGDS).       Last Modified: 11/09/2020       Submitted by: Samuel A Soule]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
