<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>IRES: US-Swedish Student Research Experience in Colloidal Science and Interfacial Engineering at the Royal Institute of Technology (KTH), Stockholm</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2014</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>01/31/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>250000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>250000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>01090000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>O/D</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Office Of The Director</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>OISE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Office Of Internatl Science &amp;Engineering</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Mangala Sharma</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>msharma@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924773</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The experience U.S. student participants obtain in the U.S.-Swedish summer research program at the Royal Institute of Technology (KTH), in Stockholm, focuses on colloidal science and interfacial engineering. Led by the prinicpal investigator, Ilona Kretzschmar of CUNY City College (CUNYCC), with Swedish counterparts,this interdisciplinary program encompasses research from traditional science and engineering disciplines and brings together qualified students from diverse backgrounds for a ten week program for early career research experience. Projects will range from biological colloids to new materials for energy storage and conversion, as well as fundamental science projects that address the assembly and interactions in the colloidal domain.  Overall, the IRES program at KTH intentionally relies on an  interdisciplinary team approach to train both graduate and undergraduate participants to be able to adapt to new disciplines, learn from each other, and to gain more global perspective and access to cutting edge colloidal science and interfacial engineering.&lt;br/&gt;  &lt;br/&gt;The U.S.-Swedish research experiences for participants run for an annual ten week period and entail mentoring by the PI and counterparts centered in three major divisions of KTH, in Surface Science and Corrosion, Biotechnology, and Chemical Technology. To examine colloidal science in the broadest sense, planned activities range from work on compression of molecular and colloidal layers at interfaces and the measurement of colloidal interaction via the synthesis of biomolecules and sequencing of genes, to the fabrication of colloidal batteries and fuel cells. Prior to the actual research experience, IRES scholars receive research training at CUNYCC laboratories, meet with previous scholars, and network with Swedish exchange students in residence at CUNYCC. During the initial research experience abroad, students remain in touch with the PI via a combination of weekly and monthly reporting and video conferencing.  The PI spends the final weeks of the program at KTH with the IRES participants to interact with mentors, ensure individual progress, and prepare for a cumulating conference in collaboration with the NYC-Louis Stokes for Minority Participation (NYC-LSAMP) Program through which many IRES students are recruited.  KTH is ideally suited for a diverse IRES program as it educates a significant share of Sweden's engineering students and is a well-known Swedish public institution with an outstanding research portfolio and a student body similar to that of CUNYCC. The overall success of this cooperative and diverse IRES program is built on technically strong intellectual partnering and a mutually benefical working program structure that has proven successful in promoting synergy among lead researchers and excellent early-career team experiences for U.S. and Swedish student participants.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/31/2014</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/31/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.079</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1358179</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Ilona</FirstName>
<LastName>Kretzschmar</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Ilona Kretzschmar</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>kretzschmar@ccny.cuny.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2126506769</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000108038</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/31/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>CUNY City College</Name>
<CityName>New York</CityName>
<ZipCode>100319101</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2126505418</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>Convent Ave at 138th St</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>13</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NY13</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>603503991</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>RESEARCH FOUNDATION OF THE CITY UNIVERSITY OF NEW YORK</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>073268849</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[CUNY City College]]></Name>
<CityName>New York City</CityName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<ZipCode>100319198</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[160 Convent Avenue]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>13</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NY13</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7727</Code>
<Text>IRES Track I: IRES Sites (IS)</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>5937</Code>
<Text>SWEDEN</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>5979</Code>
<Text>Europe and Eurasia</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0114</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~250000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The goal of this grant was to continue the exposure of undergraduate and MS students at the City College of New York (CCNY) and other colleges of the City University of New York (CUNY) to an international research environment and build a growing US-Swedish materials network of junior and senior researchers with broad participation from underrepresented groups (female and minority students). Three objectives were defined: Objective 1: Identify, select, and prepare promising young researchers at the City University of New York, in the NYC-Louis Stokes Alliance for Minority Participation program, and in the Bridge-to-the-doctorate program at CCNY to perform cutting-edge materials science and engineering research at the Royal Institute of Technology. Objective 2: Mentor and support students throughout a 10-week research experience at the Royal Institute of Technology involving cutting-edge materials research. Objective 3: Develop students? soft and research skills such that they are successful in obtaining and maintaining a position in a PhD program in the United States.</p> <p><span style="text-decoration: underline;">Research Outcomes:</span></p> <p>28 ten-week summer international research projects were supported. 4<strong> </strong>publications, 3 conference presentations, and 43 poster presentations have resulted from the students? research so far. The PI has given two invited presentations. Projects covered research in the general area of colloids and interfaces with specific focus on biology/health issues, environmental engineering, engineering of energy storage and conversion devices, corrosion, and automation. A few highlights of the research are provided here. For example, students worked on plasma separation filters for point of care devices, brominated flame-retardant reduction in plastic waste from electronics, manufacturing of ZnO films for solar cells using magnetron sputtering, and the preparation of smart surfaces by absorption of pH responsive polymers to surfaces.</p> <p><span style="text-decoration: underline;">Educational Outcomes &amp; Human Resource Development</span></p> <p>A successful international research exchange program has been run between the City University of New York (CUNY) and the Royal Institute of Technology (KTH).</p> <p>Twenty-eight students from both CCNY and other CUNY schools have been supported by this grant. The program increased the awareness of the students with respect to differences and similarities between European and US cultures, gave them access to an international research experience, and helped to prepare them in becoming global citizens. Fourteen of these students were female and sixteen were from underrepresented minority groups (African American: 1 male and 3 female and Hispanic: 5 male and 7 female). Eight students belonged to neither of these two groups.</p> <p>Of the 28 students, twelve are currently en route to their PhDs at New York University (1), NJIT (1), Cornell University (1), Penn State University (1), Cambridge University (1), University of California ? Santa Barbara (2), University of Tennessee (1), RPI (1), University of Notre Dame (1), KTH (1), and CUNY Graduate Center (1). Six obtained their MS degrees at CCNY (2), Stony Brook (1), University of San Francisco (1), JHU (1), and Cornell University (1). Four have started an industrial position.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 05/12/2019<br>      Modified by: Ilona&nbsp;Kretzschmar</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The goal of this grant was to continue the exposure of undergraduate and MS students at the City College of New York (CCNY) and other colleges of the City University of New York (CUNY) to an international research environment and build a growing US-Swedish materials network of junior and senior researchers with broad participation from underrepresented groups (female and minority students). Three objectives were defined: Objective 1: Identify, select, and prepare promising young researchers at the City University of New York, in the NYC-Louis Stokes Alliance for Minority Participation program, and in the Bridge-to-the-doctorate program at CCNY to perform cutting-edge materials science and engineering research at the Royal Institute of Technology. Objective 2: Mentor and support students throughout a 10-week research experience at the Royal Institute of Technology involving cutting-edge materials research. Objective 3: Develop students? soft and research skills such that they are successful in obtaining and maintaining a position in a PhD program in the United States.  Research Outcomes:  28 ten-week summer international research projects were supported. 4 publications, 3 conference presentations, and 43 poster presentations have resulted from the students? research so far. The PI has given two invited presentations. Projects covered research in the general area of colloids and interfaces with specific focus on biology/health issues, environmental engineering, engineering of energy storage and conversion devices, corrosion, and automation. A few highlights of the research are provided here. For example, students worked on plasma separation filters for point of care devices, brominated flame-retardant reduction in plastic waste from electronics, manufacturing of ZnO films for solar cells using magnetron sputtering, and the preparation of smart surfaces by absorption of pH responsive polymers to surfaces.  Educational Outcomes &amp; Human Resource Development  A successful international research exchange program has been run between the City University of New York (CUNY) and the Royal Institute of Technology (KTH).  Twenty-eight students from both CCNY and other CUNY schools have been supported by this grant. The program increased the awareness of the students with respect to differences and similarities between European and US cultures, gave them access to an international research experience, and helped to prepare them in becoming global citizens. Fourteen of these students were female and sixteen were from underrepresented minority groups (African American: 1 male and 3 female and Hispanic: 5 male and 7 female). Eight students belonged to neither of these two groups.  Of the 28 students, twelve are currently en route to their PhDs at New York University (1), NJIT (1), Cornell University (1), Penn State University (1), Cambridge University (1), University of California ? Santa Barbara (2), University of Tennessee (1), RPI (1), University of Notre Dame (1), KTH (1), and CUNY Graduate Center (1). Six obtained their MS degrees at CCNY (2), Stony Brook (1), University of San Francisco (1), JHU (1), and Cornell University (1). Four have started an industrial position.       Last Modified: 05/12/2019       Submitted by: Ilona Kretzschmar]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
