<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>REU Site: UCSB Mathematics Summer Research Program for Undergraduates</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2014</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>352000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>352000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DMS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Nandini Kannan</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>nakannan@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032928104</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The Research Experience for Undergraduates (REU) program at the University of California - Santa Barbara is an eight-week-long program designed to introduce its participants to mathematical research. It seeks to admit twelve students each summer from 2015-2017 to work with two faculty members on original research problems in mathematics.  Previous iterations of this REU have prided themselves on their track record of recruiting women, minorities, and students from colleges that lack research opportunities for their students.  The program aims to continue this trend of recruiting underrepresented and underserved groups in mathematics, and views this as one of the fundamental goals of this REU.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The goal of this REU is to introduce its undergraduate participants to the practice and culture of mathematical research.  The topics researched will vary from year to year; likely candidate areas include the fields of design theory, matrix theory, linear algebra, and graph theory. On an academic level, students in the REU will be exposed to a large amount of background material in mathematics.  They will learn about their fields of interest through minicourses taught by faculty and immersion in their research problem.  As well, students will be guided in the practical-level concerns of how to give talks, create posters, and write research papers through weekly meetings, presentations, and written reports.  Students will be guided by faculty in how to present their results in appropriate research conferences and in submitting papers containing their work to refereed journals. Moreover, panels throughout the summer will advise students on how to pursue graduate studies, write a resume and personal statement, network in conferences, and continue to engage with the wider mathematical community once they return to their home institution among others.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/08/2014</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>02/18/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1358884</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Maria Isabel</FirstName>
<LastName>Bueno Cachadina</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Maria Isabel Bueno Cachadina</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>mbueno@math.ucsb.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>8058935245</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000244312</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/08/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Padraic</FirstName>
<LastName>Bartlett</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>J</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Padraic J Bartlett</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>padraic@math.ucsb.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>8058934188</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000651984</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/08/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate>02/18/2016</EndDate>
<RoleCode>Former Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Karel</FirstName>
<LastName>Casteels</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Karel Casteels</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>casteels@math.ucsb.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>8056178654</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000716255</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>02/18/2016</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of California-Santa Barbara</Name>
<CityName>Santa Barbara</CityName>
<ZipCode>931062050</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>8058934188</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>Office of Research</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[Rm 3227 Cheadle Hall]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>24</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CA24</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>094878394</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF CALIFORNIA, SANTA BARBARA</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>071549000</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of California-Santa Barbara]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>931060001</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>24</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CA24</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7335</Code>
<Text>WORKFORCE IN THE MATHEMAT SCI</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9250</Code>
<Text>REU SITE-Res Exp for Ugrd Site</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0114</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~352000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>For nearly a century, the United States has been the world leader in science and technology, which has directly resulted in the largest and most diverse economy in the world. In order to continue this dominance, it is clear that a scientifically literate workforce is increasingly essential. However the development of new science often requires new mathematics. Conversely, new mathematics can point to new directions in science and technology. Therefore, it is vital for our society that new generations of skilled mathematicians are supported and trained.</p> <p>A typical mathematician begins by completing a bachelor's degree as an undergraduate before obtaining a doctorate in graduate school. The essential difference between these degrees is that the former only teaches students about mathematics that is already known, while the latter is focused on the development of new mathematics. The transition from studying the known to the unknown can be difficult, especially for people without experience or guidance. Moreover, there are many soft skills necessary for success in graduate school that are not often obtained as an undergraduate such as public speaking, professional writing and collaborative work.&nbsp;</p> <p>Our Research Experience for Undergraduates (REU) program at the University of California, Santa Barbara (UCSB) was designed to give talented undergraduate students the experience and skills that will help them succeed in graduate school and beyond.&nbsp;</p> <p>"Research" in mathematics means attempting to to prove a given statement true or false by exacting logical precision. Mathematics has grown exponentially over the past century so that most research-level problems are far out of reach of almost every undergraduate. The first step therefore, was for our faculty mentors to choose problems that were important yet could be understood and tackled using knowledge obtained from a standard undergraduate curriculum.&nbsp;</p> <p>The problems selected came from various subfields of algebra and combinatorics. Applications of this work include the study of squealing tires and to the understanding of wave interactions. This is in addition to the many applications within mathematics.&nbsp;</p> <p>Once the mentor's projects were chosen, applications were invited from undergraduate students from across the country. Each summer, 12-13 students accepted our invitation to attend our eight week program at UCSB, evenly distributed between male and female students.</p> <p>The students researched their chosen problems for the better part of each weekday from 9am to 5pm. Interspersed throughout the week were training sessions for computer programs essential for mathematics, colloquia by local professors, professional career development seminars offered by UCSB, and, at the end of each week, seminars given by our own students about their results from the past week.&nbsp;</p> <p>Near the end of the summer, the students created large posters about their summer work which was presented to and discussed with other undergraduate researchers at the university. We also had the students apply for the Young Mathematicians Conference in Ohio which occurred in August. We had good success with these applications, with roughly half of our students being accepted to give presentations there.</p> <p>At the end of the summer we administered a survey of our students to gauge their opinion of our program and to suggest any changes. The responses were very strong. Most felt that their confidence increased a great deal, that they really found out what mathematics research is like and reinforced their decisions to go to graduate school or pursue a career in industry.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 11/30/2017<br>      Modified by: Karel&nbsp;Casteels</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Images (<span id="selectedPhoto0">1</span> of <span class="totalNumber"></span>)           </div> <div class="galControls" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1358884/1358884_10317007_1512018279261_asdf1--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1358884/1358884_10317007_1512018279261_asdf1--rgov-800width.jpg" title="2017 Group Photo"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1358884/1358884_10317007_1512018279261_asdf1--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="2017 Group Photo"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">The 2017 REU students near the end of summer, practicing their poster presentation.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Karel Casteels</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Karel&nbsp;Casteels</div> <div class="imageTitle">2017 Group Photo</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1358884/1358884_10317007_1512018447914_REUPhotos(Compressed)--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1358884/1358884_10317007_1512018447914_REUPhotos(Compressed)--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Giving a talk"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1358884/1358884_10317007_1512018447914_REUPhotos(Compressed)--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Giving a talk"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">A 2016 student speaks about his work.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Karel Casteels</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Karel&nbsp;Casteels</div> <div class="imageTitle">Giving a talk</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1358884/1358884_10317007_1512018534649_REUPhotos(Compressed)2--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1358884/1358884_10317007_1512018534649_REUPhotos(Compressed)2--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Discussing their poster"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1358884/1358884_10317007_1512018534649_REUPhotos(Compressed)2--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Discussing their poster"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Three 2016 REU students discuss their work</div> <div class="imageCredit">Karel Casteels</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Karel&nbsp;Casteels</div> <div class="imageTitle">Discussing their poster</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1358884/1358884_10317007_1512018659650_REUPhotos(Compressed)3--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1358884/1358884_10317007_1512018659650_REUPhotos(Compressed)3--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Students Completes a Proof"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1358884/1358884_10317007_1512018659650_REUPhotos(Compressed)3--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Students Completes a Proof"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">A 2016 REU student finally completes her complex proof.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Karel Casteels</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Karel&nbsp;Casteels</div> <div class="imageTitle">Students Completes a Proof</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ For nearly a century, the United States has been the world leader in science and technology, which has directly resulted in the largest and most diverse economy in the world. In order to continue this dominance, it is clear that a scientifically literate workforce is increasingly essential. However the development of new science often requires new mathematics. Conversely, new mathematics can point to new directions in science and technology. Therefore, it is vital for our society that new generations of skilled mathematicians are supported and trained.  A typical mathematician begins by completing a bachelor's degree as an undergraduate before obtaining a doctorate in graduate school. The essential difference between these degrees is that the former only teaches students about mathematics that is already known, while the latter is focused on the development of new mathematics. The transition from studying the known to the unknown can be difficult, especially for people without experience or guidance. Moreover, there are many soft skills necessary for success in graduate school that are not often obtained as an undergraduate such as public speaking, professional writing and collaborative work.   Our Research Experience for Undergraduates (REU) program at the University of California, Santa Barbara (UCSB) was designed to give talented undergraduate students the experience and skills that will help them succeed in graduate school and beyond.   "Research" in mathematics means attempting to to prove a given statement true or false by exacting logical precision. Mathematics has grown exponentially over the past century so that most research-level problems are far out of reach of almost every undergraduate. The first step therefore, was for our faculty mentors to choose problems that were important yet could be understood and tackled using knowledge obtained from a standard undergraduate curriculum.   The problems selected came from various subfields of algebra and combinatorics. Applications of this work include the study of squealing tires and to the understanding of wave interactions. This is in addition to the many applications within mathematics.   Once the mentor's projects were chosen, applications were invited from undergraduate students from across the country. Each summer, 12-13 students accepted our invitation to attend our eight week program at UCSB, evenly distributed between male and female students.  The students researched their chosen problems for the better part of each weekday from 9am to 5pm. Interspersed throughout the week were training sessions for computer programs essential for mathematics, colloquia by local professors, professional career development seminars offered by UCSB, and, at the end of each week, seminars given by our own students about their results from the past week.   Near the end of the summer, the students created large posters about their summer work which was presented to and discussed with other undergraduate researchers at the university. We also had the students apply for the Young Mathematicians Conference in Ohio which occurred in August. We had good success with these applications, with roughly half of our students being accepted to give presentations there.  At the end of the summer we administered a survey of our students to gauge their opinion of our program and to suggest any changes. The responses were very strong. Most felt that their confidence increased a great deal, that they really found out what mathematics research is like and reinforced their decisions to go to graduate school or pursue a career in industry.                   Last Modified: 11/30/2017       Submitted by: Karel Casteels]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
