<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>REU Site: Research Experiences in Astronomy for Undergraduate Students at the Maria Mitchell Observatory</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>06/01/2014</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>318760.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>318760</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03020000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>AST</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Astronomical Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Matthew Benacquista</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>mbenacqu@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032928535</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This award is for renewed funding of the Maria Mitchell Observatory (MMO) Research Experiences for Undergraduates (REU) Site in Nantucket, Massachusetts. The REU program will be offered annually to six qualified applicants, who will perform state-of-the-art data analysis using a wide variety of space- and ground-based astronomical observations. The student projects on offer include mapping star formation across galaxies, uncovering the universe of hidden quasars, and understanding the structure and evolution of galaxy clusters.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The MMO REU program will have a significant impact on the skills and career development of student participants by enhancing their capability to do research, to present their results at scientific meetings and in public settings, to write scientific papers, and to write observing proposals to use national and international telescope facilities.  Hundreds of undergraduate students have participated in the REU program to date, the great majority of them women, and many have gone on to successful careers as astronomers at leading universities, observatories and other organizations around the world. Indeed, roughly one of every 20 American women with a PhD in astronomy today acquired formative research experience at the MMO. This award will therefore contribute to developing a talented STEM workforce in the United States.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>05/30/2014</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/27/2017</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1358980</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Regina</FirstName>
<LastName>Jorgenson</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Regina Jorgenson</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>rjorgenson@mariamitchell.org</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5082229273</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000504453</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>03/10/2016</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Michael</FirstName>
<LastName>West</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Michael West</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>mwest@lowell.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>9282333247</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000650911</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/30/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate>03/10/2016</EndDate>
<RoleCode>Former Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Nantucket Maria Mitchell Association</Name>
<CityName>Nantucket</CityName>
<ZipCode>025542609</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5082289198</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>4 Vestal Street</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
<StateCode>MA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>09</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MA09</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>135334324</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>NANTUCKET MARIA MITCHELL ASSOCIATION, THE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>135334324</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Maria Mitchell Observatory]]></Name>
<CityName>Nantucket</CityName>
<StateCode>MA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>025542609</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[4 Vestal Street]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>09</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MA09</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1219</Code>
<Text>SPECIAL PROGRAMS IN ASTRONOMY</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1207</Code>
<Text>OBSERVATIONAL ASTRONOMY</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9178</Code>
<Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9250</Code>
<Text>REU SITE-Res Exp for Ugrd Site</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>SMET</Code>
<Text>SCIENCE, MATH, ENG &amp; TECH EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0114</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0115</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0116</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0117</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~79690</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2015~79690</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2016~79690</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2017~79690</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>For more than 60 years, the Maria Mitchell Observatory (MMO) has offered unique summer research opportunities in astronomy and astrophysics for undergraduate students on the island of Nantucket.&nbsp; Today, MMO is a recognized leader in training the next generation of astronomers.&nbsp; The success of this pioneering program was recognized in 2009 with the prestigious Presidential Award for Excellence in Science, Mathematics and Engineering Mentoring from President Obama.&nbsp; Hundreds of undergraduate students have participated to date, the great majority of them women, and many have gone on to successful careers as astronomers at leading universities, observatories and other organizations around the world. Indeed, roughly one of every 20 American women with a PhD in astronomy today acquired formative research experience at the MMO. &nbsp;</p> <p>This award supported the summer research experiences of 24 undergraduate students from around the country and helped the MMO continue its mission of providing professionally guided summer research opportunities in astronomy for undergraduate students, especially for women and other underrepresented groups as well as students from colleges and universities with limited research opportunities. Fully 67% (16/24) of the students supported on this award are women, while 42% (10/24) are members of traditionally under-represented racial and ethnic groups.&nbsp; 50% (12/24) of the students hail from small, liberal arts, and undergraduate-only universities, where access to astrophysics research is limited or non-existent.&nbsp; An an additional 17% (4/24) are from larger, state universities without advanced astrophysics degree programs or significant research opportunities. &nbsp;</p> <p>Keenly aware of the importance of cultivating diverse mentors, 50% (8/16) of the affiliated astronomers active during this award are women.&nbsp; Of those, three women are alumnae of the MMO REU program, providing not only first-hand testaments to the long-term career successes of MMO REU alumnae, but also, real-world mentoring and networking for current MMO REU students.&nbsp; Finally, it should be noted that the current Director of the MMO is a woman and also an alumna of the MMO REU program.&nbsp;</p> <p><strong>Intellectual Merit: </strong></p> <p>Research at MMO emphasizes state-of-the-art data reduction techniques and thoughtful physical interpretation. Data for projects come from leading ground- and space-based observatories as well as next generation surveys and cosmological simulations. Students also obtain data with the MMO's 24- and 17- inch research telescopes equipped with modern CCD cameras. Each MMO REU student works on an individualized research project under the guidance of experienced astronomers, as well as a collaborative team project. All projects focus on original research aimed at producing a new and publishable result, with the student taking a genuine leadership role.&nbsp; Throughout the summer students participate in weekly group meetings to discuss their research progress, weekly professional development activities, and lectures from visiting astronomers.&nbsp;</p> <p>MMO REU students disseminate results of their research at the annual winter meeting of the American Astronomical Society (AAS) where 100% (24/24) of the students presented either a poster or talk.&nbsp; During this award period, two MMO REU students won the prestigious Chambliss Award for best student poster, while one student was accorded an Honorable Mention.&nbsp; Students presented at multiple other scientific conferences and at their home institutions, as well as publishing papers in peer-reviewed scientific journals. During this award period, MMO REU students have published two first-author peer-reviewed papers, three contributing author papers, and four senior theses.&nbsp; Several additional papers are currently in preparation for submission to peer-reviewed journals.&nbsp;&nbsp;</p> <p>Students also develop their communication skills by participating actively in public outreach, especially our twice-weekly public stargazing nights at the observatory, a very successful outreach program that attracts more than 3,500 visitors each summer. Finally, each student gives a short public presentation of their research results to an audience of approximately 75 members of the public on Nantucket at the conclusion of the summer.</p> <p><strong>Broader Impacts: </strong></p> <p>Few organizations have had a greater demonstrable impact on increasing participation by women in astronomy than the Maria Mitchell Observatory. Extensive follow-up shows that their REU experience at the MMO crucially influences the career choices of many students. Most of them continue on to graduate school in astronomy or physics, and more than half eventually obtain a PhD. &nbsp;Of the current award period, 75% (18/24) of the students are now enrolled in graduate programs, while three are working in STEM fields and intend to go to the graduate school, a following two have not yet completed undergraduate studies and one is working as STEM teacher.&nbsp; The long-term mentoring and advising of each MMO REU student is continued well after their summer research experience is over and each student becomes part of the MMO &lsquo;family,&rsquo; supported by the Director and an online community of alumni and affiliated astronomers.&nbsp; MMO REU alumni reunion events, such as the annual alumni breakfast at the AAS meeting, nurture students&rsquo; professional growth and provide further networking opportunities.&nbsp; &nbsp;&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 09/26/2018<br>      Modified by: Regina&nbsp;Jorgenson</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Images (<span id="selectedPhoto0">1</span> of <span class="totalNumber"></span>)           </div> <div class="galControls" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1358980/1358980_10306132_1537926078593_2017_loines_drone_telvin--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1358980/1358980_10306132_1537926078593_2017_loines_drone_telvin--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Summer 2017 REU students at MMO's Loines Observatory"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1358980/1358980_10306132_1537926078593_2017_loines_drone_telvin--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Summer 2017 REU students at MMO's Loines Observatory"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Drone's eye view of the MMO's Loines Observatory containing the 24-inch research telescope.  Seen here with the summer 2017 REU students and Director Jorgenson</div> <div class="imageCredit">Telvin Benjamin</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Public Domain</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Regina&nbsp;Jorgenson</div> <div class="imageTitle">Summer 2017 REU students at MMO's Loines Observatory</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1358980/1358980_10306132_1537926257699_ScreenShot2018-09-25at9.43.32PM--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1358980/1358980_10306132_1537926257699_ScreenShot2018-09-25at9.43.32PM--rgov-800width.jpg" title="REU students in front of MMO's historic Vestal Street Observatory"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1358980/1358980_10306132_1537926257699_ScreenShot2018-09-25at9.43.32PM--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="REU students in front of MMO's historic Vestal Street Observatory"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">REU students in front of MMO's historic Vestal Street Observatory, along with Director Jorgenson.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Jorgenson</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Public Domain</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Regina&nbsp;Jorgenson</div> <div class="imageTitle">REU students in front of MMO's historic Vestal Street Observatory</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1358980/1358980_10306132_1537926450899_ScreenShot2018-09-25at9.46.57PM--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1358980/1358980_10306132_1537926450899_ScreenShot2018-09-25at9.46.57PM--rgov-800width.jpg" title="2017 MMO REU student Telvin Benjamin presenting at the AAS meeting"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1358980/1358980_10306132_1537926450899_ScreenShot2018-09-25at9.46.57PM--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="2017 MMO REU student Telvin Benjamin presenting at the AAS meeting"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">2017 MMO REU student Telvin Benjamin presenting his research poster at the American Astronomical Society meeting in Washington D.C.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Jorgenson</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Public Domain</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Regina&nbsp;Jorgenson</div> <div class="imageTitle">2017 MMO REU student Telvin Benjamin presenting at the AAS meeting</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1358980/1358980_10306132_1537926591350_2017_Niko_public_talk--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1358980/1358980_10306132_1537926591350_2017_Niko_public_talk--rgov-800width.jpg" title="MMO REU student Niko Thomashow giving a talk"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1358980/1358980_10306132_1537926591350_2017_Niko_public_talk--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="MMO REU student Niko Thomashow giving a talk"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">MMO REU student Niko Thomashow giving a public presentation on her summer research results at the Maria Mitchell Association's Summer Science Speaker Series, August 2017.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Jorgenson</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Public Domain</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Regina&nbsp;Jorgenson</div> <div class="imageTitle">MMO REU student Niko Thomashow giving a talk</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ For more than 60 years, the Maria Mitchell Observatory (MMO) has offered unique summer research opportunities in astronomy and astrophysics for undergraduate students on the island of Nantucket.  Today, MMO is a recognized leader in training the next generation of astronomers.  The success of this pioneering program was recognized in 2009 with the prestigious Presidential Award for Excellence in Science, Mathematics and Engineering Mentoring from President Obama.  Hundreds of undergraduate students have participated to date, the great majority of them women, and many have gone on to successful careers as astronomers at leading universities, observatories and other organizations around the world. Indeed, roughly one of every 20 American women with a PhD in astronomy today acquired formative research experience at the MMO.    This award supported the summer research experiences of 24 undergraduate students from around the country and helped the MMO continue its mission of providing professionally guided summer research opportunities in astronomy for undergraduate students, especially for women and other underrepresented groups as well as students from colleges and universities with limited research opportunities. Fully 67% (16/24) of the students supported on this award are women, while 42% (10/24) are members of traditionally under-represented racial and ethnic groups.  50% (12/24) of the students hail from small, liberal arts, and undergraduate-only universities, where access to astrophysics research is limited or non-existent.  An an additional 17% (4/24) are from larger, state universities without advanced astrophysics degree programs or significant research opportunities.    Keenly aware of the importance of cultivating diverse mentors, 50% (8/16) of the affiliated astronomers active during this award are women.  Of those, three women are alumnae of the MMO REU program, providing not only first-hand testaments to the long-term career successes of MMO REU alumnae, but also, real-world mentoring and networking for current MMO REU students.  Finally, it should be noted that the current Director of the MMO is a woman and also an alumna of the MMO REU program.   Intellectual Merit:   Research at MMO emphasizes state-of-the-art data reduction techniques and thoughtful physical interpretation. Data for projects come from leading ground- and space-based observatories as well as next generation surveys and cosmological simulations. Students also obtain data with the MMO's 24- and 17- inch research telescopes equipped with modern CCD cameras. Each MMO REU student works on an individualized research project under the guidance of experienced astronomers, as well as a collaborative team project. All projects focus on original research aimed at producing a new and publishable result, with the student taking a genuine leadership role.  Throughout the summer students participate in weekly group meetings to discuss their research progress, weekly professional development activities, and lectures from visiting astronomers.   MMO REU students disseminate results of their research at the annual winter meeting of the American Astronomical Society (AAS) where 100% (24/24) of the students presented either a poster or talk.  During this award period, two MMO REU students won the prestigious Chambliss Award for best student poster, while one student was accorded an Honorable Mention.  Students presented at multiple other scientific conferences and at their home institutions, as well as publishing papers in peer-reviewed scientific journals. During this award period, MMO REU students have published two first-author peer-reviewed papers, three contributing author papers, and four senior theses.  Several additional papers are currently in preparation for submission to peer-reviewed journals.    Students also develop their communication skills by participating actively in public outreach, especially our twice-weekly public stargazing nights at the observatory, a very successful outreach program that attracts more than 3,500 visitors each summer. Finally, each student gives a short public presentation of their research results to an audience of approximately 75 members of the public on Nantucket at the conclusion of the summer.  Broader Impacts:   Few organizations have had a greater demonstrable impact on increasing participation by women in astronomy than the Maria Mitchell Observatory. Extensive follow-up shows that their REU experience at the MMO crucially influences the career choices of many students. Most of them continue on to graduate school in astronomy or physics, and more than half eventually obtain a PhD.  Of the current award period, 75% (18/24) of the students are now enrolled in graduate programs, while three are working in STEM fields and intend to go to the graduate school, a following two have not yet completed undergraduate studies and one is working as STEM teacher.  The long-term mentoring and advising of each MMO REU student is continued well after their summer research experience is over and each student becomes part of the MMO ?family,? supported by the Director and an online community of alumni and affiliated astronomers.  MMO REU alumni reunion events, such as the annual alumni breakfast at the AAS meeting, nurture students? professional growth and provide further networking opportunities.           Last Modified: 09/26/2018       Submitted by: Regina Jorgenson]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
