<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>IRES: Undergraduate Research at CERN - Explorations in Accelerator-Based Science</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2014</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>214176.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>214176</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>01090000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>O/D</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Office Of The Director</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>OISE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Office Of Internatl Science &amp;Engineering</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Roxanne Nikolaus</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>rnikolau@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927578</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Through this three-year International Research Experiences for Students (IRES) program for U.S. students, George Mason University (GMU) will conduct a nine-week, combined research internship-training program for eighteen undergraduates in cooperation with counterparts at CERN, the European Organization for Nuclear Research. Located in Geneva, Switzerland, CERN is a world-class international research center that supports all aspects of accelerator-based science: theory, research and development, information technology, experiments, and data analysis. Users of the facilities, including students, work in these areas along with research counterparts and staff at CERN. With access to technically complex particle accelerators and detectors, experiments and research activities carried out there are among the most advanced in accelerator-based science.  Each year, scientists from almost 600 institutes and universities (and 85 nations) visit the laboratory to collaborate.  U.S. scientists, including the Principal Investigator, are engaged in experiments based at one or another of the accelerators at the CERN complex, including the Large Hadron Collider (LHC).  In this exceptional setting, CERN conducts an annual Summer Student Research Programme for up to 300 undergraduates from Europe and other countries.  With direction from the P.I., six U.S. students supported by this IRES grant will work with CERN-affiliated mentors and participate in the summer program, where they will learn alongside fellow students and professionals from every corner of the globe.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;To ensure opportunities for broader participation in the IRES at CERN, George Mason University will recruit by inviting advanced students to apply who are in science, technology, engineering and mathematics (STEM) fields and attending member institutions of the diverse Consortium of Universities of the Washington Metropolitan Area, an historically Black or women's college or university in the greater District of Columbia region, or a Northern Virginia community college.  Selected student participants will spend their first of nine weeks at GMU in a preparatory workshop, followed by eight weeks at CERN for a well-planned program that includes skill development, research experience under the co-supervision of the P.I. and an on-site expert, academic and career advising, and multiple professional networking opportunities.  Participating students must make one or more presentations at CERN and author a technical report on their project for posting on the IRES program web site and evaluation by mentors.  IRES participation will contribute not only to on-going accelerator-based science, but also-very importantly-to workforce preparation of junior U.S. scientists and engineers with a full range of scientific experience, including areas that involve hardware, software, data analysis, computer engineering, and design and simulation.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/01/2014</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/01/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.079</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1358071</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Philip</FirstName>
<LastName>Rubin</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>D</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Philip D Rubin</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>prubin@gmu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>7039933815</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000176707</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/01/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>George Mason University</Name>
<CityName>FAIRFAX</CityName>
<ZipCode>220304422</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>7039932295</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>4400 UNIVERSITY DR</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Virginia</StateName>
<StateCode>VA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>11</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>VA11</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>077817450</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>GEORGE MASON UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>077817450</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[George Mason University]]></Name>
<CityName>FAIRFAX</CityName>
<StateCode>VA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>220304422</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[4400 UNIVERSITY DR]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Virginia</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>11</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>VA11</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7727</Code>
<Text>IRES Track I: IRES Sites (IS)</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>5950</Code>
<Text>SWITZERLAND</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>5979</Code>
<Text>Europe and Eurasia</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0114</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~214176</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>This award supported 18 undergraduate students (6 per Summer) in a nine-week research-internship and educational training program in cooperation with CERN, the European Organization for Nuclear Research.&nbsp; Among the students, nearly 30% were women and 11% were Hispanic.<br /><br />In the program, the students developed skills, learned new knowledge, received academic and career advising, undertook research projects, and networked in an international environment among 300 or more other students from around the world in CERN's Summer Student Programme.&nbsp; They were mentored by resident scientists and engineers.<br /><br />The program's first week consisted of an orientation at George Mason University (GMU) during which students finalized paperwork, were informed about living and work expectations at CERN and surrounding areas and their research projects (in particular, the scientific context in which it will take place), and helped to develop skills required for their projects.<br /><br />Projects spanned nearly all of CERN's science and technology, covering theory, simulation, information technology, data analysis, and hardware.&nbsp; They included, for example, an alternative formulation of General Relativity, simulating the effect of beam loss energy deposition in LHC magnets, developing a machine-learning algorithm to classify Higgs boson production and decay, and determining how to distribute signal readout in a detector based on rates.<br /><br />At CERN, the students attended academic training lectures, participated in skill-building workshops, and took guided tours of laboratory spaces and experimental areas, in addition to working on their individual research projects.&nbsp; On top of these, the students were guided through the processes of professional presentations and technical writing.&nbsp; And last but not least, they experienced international living and discovered first-hand what the life of a scientist amounts to.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 12/17/2018<br>      Modified by: Philip&nbsp;D&nbsp;Rubin</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ This award supported 18 undergraduate students (6 per Summer) in a nine-week research-internship and educational training program in cooperation with CERN, the European Organization for Nuclear Research.  Among the students, nearly 30% were women and 11% were Hispanic.  In the program, the students developed skills, learned new knowledge, received academic and career advising, undertook research projects, and networked in an international environment among 300 or more other students from around the world in CERN's Summer Student Programme.  They were mentored by resident scientists and engineers.  The program's first week consisted of an orientation at George Mason University (GMU) during which students finalized paperwork, were informed about living and work expectations at CERN and surrounding areas and their research projects (in particular, the scientific context in which it will take place), and helped to develop skills required for their projects.  Projects spanned nearly all of CERN's science and technology, covering theory, simulation, information technology, data analysis, and hardware.  They included, for example, an alternative formulation of General Relativity, simulating the effect of beam loss energy deposition in LHC magnets, developing a machine-learning algorithm to classify Higgs boson production and decay, and determining how to distribute signal readout in a detector based on rates.  At CERN, the students attended academic training lectures, participated in skill-building workshops, and took guided tours of laboratory spaces and experimental areas, in addition to working on their individual research projects.  On top of these, the students were guided through the processes of professional presentations and technical writing.  And last but not least, they experienced international living and discovered first-hand what the life of a scientist amounts to.       Last Modified: 12/17/2018       Submitted by: Philip D Rubin]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
