<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>IRES: US-India Collaborative Research in Mechanical, Biomedical, and Materials Science Engineering for Undergraduates</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2014</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>147307.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>147307</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>01090000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>O/D</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Office Of The Director</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>OISE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Office Of Internatl Science &amp;Engineering</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Mangala Sharma</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>msharma@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924773</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>IRES: The U.S.-India Collaborative Research in Mechanical, Biomedical, and Materials Science Engineering for Undergraduates is a joint research project between Ohio State and Colorado State Universities, and the Malaviya National Institute of Technology in India. U.S. students will conduct research on a prosthetic device that was pioneered several decades ago at the Dr. P.K. Sethi Rehabilitation and Jaipur Limb Training Centre. It continues to be used throughout India due to the low-cost, cultural appropriateness, and magnitude of the amputee population. At present, the number of amputees in the world is significant, particularly in the developing countries. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This IRES project will provide internships for five talented US-undergraduate engineering students each year over three years to conduct research and development activities that will provide a thorough understanding of this prosthetic device. At present, little is known about the properties of the individual components that comprise the device. The goal of this research is to improve the product for wider distribution within India and for eventual mass production so that it's potential for relieving the suffering of amputees in the developing world and beyond may be realized. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Broader Description &lt;br/&gt;This project will make significant advances in prosthetic devices for the developing world. Although much is known in the U.S. regarding prosthetic devices, understanding the various design and production constraints for developing countries is less well-known. The project evaluation will lead to a better understanding of the impact of humanitarian projects on the development of engineering students. The research has the potential to transform the way that prosthetic devices are made in non-western regions in the world. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The benefit to society accrued through this project is significant. Researchers will target women and underrepresented students for participation, encouraging them to pursue advanced degrees in engineering. This will serve to broaden participation in STEM fields. The results will be broadly disseminated through a variety of journals and conference venues. The impact on the world's poor who are amputees is potentially significant.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/13/2014</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>04/10/2018</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.079</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1358157</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Sheryl</FirstName>
<LastName>Sorby</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>A</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Sheryl A Sorby</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>sorbysa@ucmail.uc.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>9062317133</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000331918</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/13/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate>04/10/2018</EndDate>
<RoleCode>Former Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Lisa</FirstName>
<LastName>Abrams</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>M</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Lisa M Abrams</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>abrams.34@osu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6146881735</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000515329</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/13/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Ohio State University</Name>
<CityName>Columbus</CityName>
<ZipCode>432101016</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6146888735</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>Office of Sponsored Programs</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[1960 Kenny Road]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Ohio</StateName>
<StateCode>OH</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>OH03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>832127323</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>OHIO STATE UNIVERSITY, THE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>001964634</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Ohio State University]]></Name>
<CityName>Columbus</CityName>
<StateCode>OH</StateCode>
<ZipCode>432101016</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[2070 Neil Avenue]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Ohio</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>OH03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>5342</Code>
<Text>Disability &amp; Rehab Engineering</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7727</Code>
<Text>IRES Track I: IRES Sites (IS)</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>010E</Code>
<Text>DISABILITY RES &amp; HOMECARE TECH</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>5919</Code>
<Text>INDIA (COOPERATIVE SCIENCE)</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>5976</Code>
<Text>AFRICA, NEAR EAST, &amp; SO ASIA</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>SMET</Code>
<Text>SCIENCE, MATH, ENG &amp; TECH EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0114</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~147307</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The incidence of missing limbs, particularly feet/legs, is much higher in the developing world, when compared to the U.S. In the United States around 1/22,000 people are amputees whereas in Cambodia it is 1/256 people, in Somalia it is 1/1000, and in India it is 1/56. Prosthetic devices in the western world have made significant advances in the past fifty years, however, they are not affordable to the world&rsquo;s poor. Recognizing the need for a low-cost, simple prosthetic device, Dr. P.K. Sethi of the Rehabilitation &amp; Jaipur Limb Training Centre in Jaipur, India developed a low-cost simple prosthetic device known as the Jaipur Foot in the 1970s. The low cost made it accessible to everyone, however there were issues with the design and/or materials that prevented a long life-span for the prosthetic device. The India Research Project was a 3-year initiative to conduct the type of rigorous engineering research that would form the foundation for future attempts at mass production of this innovative product that is clearly needed across the globe. For each of the summers from 2015-1017, undergraduate students were carefully selected from Ohio State University and Colorado State University to serve on research teams in Jaipur. They were provided information to prepare them before departure, took an on-line &ldquo;pre-survey&rdquo; just before departing, were led to work independently on improving the Jaipur Foot once they arrived in India (although had regular email contact and weekly conference calls with their advisors in the US), and took an on-line &ldquo;post-survey&rdquo; shortly after returning to the US. Approximately a year after their return to the United States, all but one student participated in an hour-long phone interview to review their insights with the added perspective of a bit of time after their India experience.&nbsp;</p> <p>The goals of the project were:</p> <p>1. Provide undergraduate engineering students with the ability to conduct meaningful research in an international setting.</p> <p>2.&nbsp; Expand the global awareness of the students who participate in the research experiences.</p> <p>3. Provide meaningful research data and other information to the staff at Jaipur Foot so that they can explore options for mass production of the prosthetic device.</p> <p><br />Feedback gathered by the external evaluator from students across all three years (during phone interviews with students conducted a minimum of one year after they completed their India research experience) indicate that the international experience had a deep and meaningful impact on their professional and personal life.</p> <p>Remarks that were representative of what 60-90% of the students said include:</p> <p>"&hellip;I [learned] to navigate a new country even without knowing the language. It also impacted my academics, I got over the challenge of language barriers to still communicate and it is a skill that can serve me anywhere.&rdquo;</p> <p>&nbsp;&ldquo;I didn&rsquo;t really have a global perspective before. I&rsquo;m from a small farm community in the US but never saw cows in the street. Life and work is so different there, there are 36 languages spoken there!&rdquo;</p> <p>&nbsp;&ldquo;One of the best things I&rsquo;ve ever done in my life. Opened a lot of doors for me.&rdquo;</p> <p>&ldquo;I learned to work with others, overcame cultural barriers and challenges, I gained trust to use the machine as I needed permission at first and by end, I was given access of my own. Acclimatizing to the culture was overwhelming for the first 2 weeks, but I became much more comfortable by the end. I did not feel out of place anymore and I was comfortable doing things in that environment.&rdquo;</p> <p>A full 100% of the students interviewed in all three years looked back on this experience as one they would highly recommend to others. As noted in the surveys and during the phone interviews, while the language barrier was mentioned frequently as a challenge, it seems that the challenge was not insurmountable and actually was the impetus for growth in many instances. Similarly, other areas they found challenging or frustrating were often also cited as areas of greatest success (pride and confidence in overcoming barriers). Many students remarked that they expected to gain valuable research experience, which they did, but they did not expect to gain so many other professional/personal skills such as being able to work effectively with a team and across cultures and being able to travel and communicate with others despite language barriers.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 02/27/2020<br>      Modified by: Lisa&nbsp;M&nbsp;Abrams</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The incidence of missing limbs, particularly feet/legs, is much higher in the developing world, when compared to the U.S. In the United States around 1/22,000 people are amputees whereas in Cambodia it is 1/256 people, in Somalia it is 1/1000, and in India it is 1/56. Prosthetic devices in the western world have made significant advances in the past fifty years, however, they are not affordable to the world’s poor. Recognizing the need for a low-cost, simple prosthetic device, Dr. P.K. Sethi of the Rehabilitation &amp; Jaipur Limb Training Centre in Jaipur, India developed a low-cost simple prosthetic device known as the Jaipur Foot in the 1970s. The low cost made it accessible to everyone, however there were issues with the design and/or materials that prevented a long life-span for the prosthetic device. The India Research Project was a 3-year initiative to conduct the type of rigorous engineering research that would form the foundation for future attempts at mass production of this innovative product that is clearly needed across the globe. For each of the summers from 2015-1017, undergraduate students were carefully selected from Ohio State University and Colorado State University to serve on research teams in Jaipur. They were provided information to prepare them before departure, took an on-line "pre-survey" just before departing, were led to work independently on improving the Jaipur Foot once they arrived in India (although had regular email contact and weekly conference calls with their advisors in the US), and took an on-line "post-survey" shortly after returning to the US. Approximately a year after their return to the United States, all but one student participated in an hour-long phone interview to review their insights with the added perspective of a bit of time after their India experience.   The goals of the project were:  1. Provide undergraduate engineering students with the ability to conduct meaningful research in an international setting.  2.  Expand the global awareness of the students who participate in the research experiences.  3. Provide meaningful research data and other information to the staff at Jaipur Foot so that they can explore options for mass production of the prosthetic device.   Feedback gathered by the external evaluator from students across all three years (during phone interviews with students conducted a minimum of one year after they completed their India research experience) indicate that the international experience had a deep and meaningful impact on their professional and personal life.  Remarks that were representative of what 60-90% of the students said include:  "&hellip;I [learned] to navigate a new country even without knowing the language. It also impacted my academics, I got over the challenge of language barriers to still communicate and it is a skill that can serve me anywhere."   "I didn’t really have a global perspective before. I’m from a small farm community in the US but never saw cows in the street. Life and work is so different there, there are 36 languages spoken there!"   "One of the best things I’ve ever done in my life. Opened a lot of doors for me."  "I learned to work with others, overcame cultural barriers and challenges, I gained trust to use the machine as I needed permission at first and by end, I was given access of my own. Acclimatizing to the culture was overwhelming for the first 2 weeks, but I became much more comfortable by the end. I did not feel out of place anymore and I was comfortable doing things in that environment."  A full 100% of the students interviewed in all three years looked back on this experience as one they would highly recommend to others. As noted in the surveys and during the phone interviews, while the language barrier was mentioned frequently as a challenge, it seems that the challenge was not insurmountable and actually was the impetus for growth in many instances. Similarly, other areas they found challenging or frustrating were often also cited as areas of greatest success (pride and confidence in overcoming barriers). Many students remarked that they expected to gain valuable research experience, which they did, but they did not expect to gain so many other professional/personal skills such as being able to work effectively with a team and across cultures and being able to travel and communicate with others despite language barriers.          Last Modified: 02/27/2020       Submitted by: Lisa M Abrams]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
