<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>REU Site:  Physical Properties of Materials</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>03/01/2014</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>02/28/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>295319.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>295319</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03070000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DMR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Materials Research</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Lynnette Madsen</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>lmadsen@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924936</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>TECHNICAL DESCRIPTION&lt;br/&gt;The Mississippi State University REU Site "Physical Properties of Materials" will expose students to the interdisciplinary nature of materials-related research and the intersection between the life sciences and engineering.  The goal is to involve undergraduates in interdisciplinary materials research so that they are empowered to pursue advanced degrees and careers in science and engineering.  Existing MSU research infrastructure and instrumentation will be utilized by participants with guidance from a group of materials science and engineering research mentors.  The research experience will be complemented by trips to local industry to show how materials science/engineering can be applied to aerospace, manufacturing, and biomedical industries.  The REU program boasts available research instrumentation and expertise, strong and sustained faculty and administrative commitment, and an independent assessment plan.  Each student participant will be involved in an independent research project under the guidance and mentorship of a faculty member and involvement with a research team.  Student projects address a diverse range of contemporary challenges in materials science research (e.g. biomaterials, nanoparticles, composites, and polymers) and will be part of larger, ongoing research projects within the faculty research groups so that participants can also gain an appreciation for the bigger science picture.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;NON-TECHNICAL DESCRIPTION&lt;br/&gt;REU participants, faculty, and graduate student mentors will gain a greater awareness of, and appreciation for, the contributions of diverse disciplines to materials research.  This project introduces participants to inquiry-based/interdisciplinary research, informs students about careers, and empowers students with the support and tools needed to pursue materials-related graduate degrees or careers.  The intention is to prepare students to become future leaders and innovators in science and engineering.  The educational objective is to prepare undergraduate students to pursue a career in engineering and science.  The program has established 4 learning outcomes that students are expected to attain by the end of the 10-week program in order to achieve the educational objectives.  These outcomes are:  (a) Participants will demonstrate an ability to conduct experiments, as well as to analyze and interpret data.  (b) Participants will have an understanding of professional and ethical responsibility.  (c) Participants will effectively communicate scientific information in written, graphical and oral format.  (d) Participants will demonstrate an ability to conduct self-directed learning.  The learning outcomes will be directly assessed and the data will be systematically evaluated and used to continuously improve the research experience in successive years.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>12/30/2013</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>03/16/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1359437</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Giselle</FirstName>
<LastName>Thibaudeau</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Giselle Thibaudeau</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>giselle@i2at.msstate.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6623253019</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000094315</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>12/30/2013</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>James</FirstName>
<LastName>Warnock</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>N</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>James N Warnock</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>james.warnock@uga.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6787784956</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000494166</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>12/30/2013</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Mississippi State University</Name>
<CityName>MISSISSIPPI STATE</CityName>
<ZipCode>397629662</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6623257404</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>PO Box 6156</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Mississippi</StateName>
<StateCode>MS</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MS03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>075461814</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>MISSISSIPPI STATE UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>075461814</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Mississippi State University]]></Name>
<CityName>Mississippi State</CityName>
<StateCode>MS</StateCode>
<ZipCode>397629999</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[130 Creelman]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Mississippi</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MS03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7222</Code>
<Text>XC-Crosscutting Activities Pro</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1711</Code>
<Text>MATERIALS EDUCATION AND RESEARCH</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9250</Code>
<Text>REU SITE-Res Exp for Ugrd Site</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0114</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0115</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0116</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~139255</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2015~139255</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2016~16809</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The <em>REU Site: Physical Properties of Materials</em> program exposes students to the interdisciplinary nature of materials-related research and the intersection between life sciences and engineering. The overall goal of this project is to involve undergraduates in interdisciplinary materials research so that they are empowered to pursue advanced degrees and careers in science and engineering. Existing MSU research infrastructure and instrumentation are utilized by participants with guidance from a dynamic group of materials science and engineering research mentors. The research experience is complimented by field trips to local industry and a bi-monthly seminar. Through these activities, students observe how materials science and engineering can be applied to the aerospace, manufacturing and biomedical industries. The seminars enable students to develop research skills that extend beyond the laboratory.</p> <p>During the three years of the program, we have hosted 36 students (28 students funded by NSF, 5 students funded by Army Research Laboratory in 2016, 3 students funded by Bagley College of Engineering in 2016) with a 50-50 distribution of male and female students. Demographic data are shown in Figure 1. Of the 36 students, 14 students came from predominantly undergraduate institutions (PUI) and three were MSU students. To date, student participants have been co-authors on two peer-reviewed journal papers [1, 2] and two international conference papers [3, 4]. All students have presented their work at the Undergraduate Summer Research Symposium, hosted by the Shackouls Honors College at MSU. In 2015, REU students won first place in the Biological Sciences and Engineering category and first place in the Physical Sciences and Engineering category. In 2016, REU students won first, second and third place in the Physical Sciences and Engineering category.</p> <p>The assessment data collected for the program demonstrate that the learning objectives are being met. When asked how much the REU program had helped them develop their experimental skills, &gt;80% of students responded that the program had helped them develop their experimental skills for all performance indicators except the ability to use appropriate statistical methods. Only 70% of students responded that the program had helped them some or a lot to develop their ability to use appropriate statistical methods. The data showed that 18% of students did not think the program helped them develop an ability to use lab equipment and 24% didn&rsquo;t think the program helped them in their ability to identify the appropriate lab equipment for an experiment (see table 1a). However, these students worked on computational projects and therefore did not have an opportunity to develop these skills. More than 95% of students that responded to the exit survey said the program had increased their understanding of ethical and professional responsibility, as shown in table 1b, while more than 88% of respondents indicated that the program had helped increase their ability to conduct self-directed learning, as seen in table 1c. The data did indicate that the program needs to do more to help students develop their communication skills, particularly in the areas of writing a technical report, making oral presentations and preparing a scientific poster. Overall, students were extremely happy with the program and <strong>100% said they would recommend the REU to other students </strong>and 88% ranked the overall research experience as either very good or excellent. When asked about graduate school, 76% stated they would consider attending MSU. Of those that said they would not consider attending MSU, 2 students said it was because MSU didn&rsquo;t offer research programs that were of interest to them, one student said they did not plan to attend graduate school and one student stated financial reasons.&nbsp;</p> <p><span style="text-decoration: underline;"><strong>References:</strong></span></p> <ol> <li>Pinheiro, A., A. Cooley, J. Liao, R. Prabhu, and S. Elder, <em>Comparison of natural crosslinking agents for the stabilization of xenogenic articular cartilage.</em> Journal of Orthopaedic Research, 2016. <strong>34</strong>(6): p. 1037-1046.</li> <li>Figueroa, L., B. Brazile, S. Lin, B. Nelson, and J. Liao, <em>Characterization of the Unique Viscoelastic Properties of the Mitral Valve Anterior Leaflet.</em> The FASEB Journal, 2016. <strong>30</strong>(1 Supplement): p. 558.1.</li> <li>Figueroa;, L., B. Brazile;, S. Lin;, B. Nelson;, and J. Liao, <em>Characterization of the Unique Viscoelastic Properties of the Mitral Valve Anterior Leaflet</em>, in <em>2015 Annual Biomedical Research Conference for Minority Students </em>2015: Seattle, WA.</li> <li>Pinheiro, A., A. Gottipatu, and S. Elder, <em>Use of Natural Crosslinkers to Stabilize Decellularized Cartilage</em>, in <em>Biomedical Engineering Society Annual Meeting</em>. 2014: San Antonio, TX.</li> </ol><br> <p>            Last Modified: 04/05/2017<br>      Modified by: James&nbsp;N&nbsp;Warnock</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Images (<span id="selectedPhoto0">1</span> of <span class="totalNumber"></span>)           </div> <div class="galControls" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1359437/1359437_10287832_1491399098558_ScreenShot2017-04-05at8.29.53AM--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1359437/1359437_10287832_1491399098558_ScreenShot2017-04-05at8.29.53AM--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Figure 1"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1359437/1359437_10287832_1491399098558_ScreenShot2017-04-05at8.29.53AM--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Figure 1"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Student demographics for the REU Site: Physical Properties of Materials</div> <div class="imageCredit">J. Warnock</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">James&nbsp;N&nbsp;Warnock</div> <div class="imageTitle">Figure 1</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1359437/1359437_10287832_1491399495688_ScreenShot2017-04-05at8.36.34AM--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1359437/1359437_10287832_1491399495688_ScreenShot2017-04-05at8.36.34AM--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Table 1."><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1359437/1359437_10287832_1491399495688_ScreenShot2017-04-05at8.36.34AM--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Table 1."></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Achievement of learning outcomes from the REU Site: Physical Properties of Materials.</div> <div class="imageCredit">J. Warnock</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">James&nbsp;N&nbsp;Warnock</div> <div class="imageTitle">Table 1.</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The REU Site: Physical Properties of Materials program exposes students to the interdisciplinary nature of materials-related research and the intersection between life sciences and engineering. The overall goal of this project is to involve undergraduates in interdisciplinary materials research so that they are empowered to pursue advanced degrees and careers in science and engineering. Existing MSU research infrastructure and instrumentation are utilized by participants with guidance from a dynamic group of materials science and engineering research mentors. The research experience is complimented by field trips to local industry and a bi-monthly seminar. Through these activities, students observe how materials science and engineering can be applied to the aerospace, manufacturing and biomedical industries. The seminars enable students to develop research skills that extend beyond the laboratory.  During the three years of the program, we have hosted 36 students (28 students funded by NSF, 5 students funded by Army Research Laboratory in 2016, 3 students funded by Bagley College of Engineering in 2016) with a 50-50 distribution of male and female students. Demographic data are shown in Figure 1. Of the 36 students, 14 students came from predominantly undergraduate institutions (PUI) and three were MSU students. To date, student participants have been co-authors on two peer-reviewed journal papers [1, 2] and two international conference papers [3, 4]. All students have presented their work at the Undergraduate Summer Research Symposium, hosted by the Shackouls Honors College at MSU. In 2015, REU students won first place in the Biological Sciences and Engineering category and first place in the Physical Sciences and Engineering category. In 2016, REU students won first, second and third place in the Physical Sciences and Engineering category.  The assessment data collected for the program demonstrate that the learning objectives are being met. When asked how much the REU program had helped them develop their experimental skills, &gt;80% of students responded that the program had helped them develop their experimental skills for all performance indicators except the ability to use appropriate statistical methods. Only 70% of students responded that the program had helped them some or a lot to develop their ability to use appropriate statistical methods. The data showed that 18% of students did not think the program helped them develop an ability to use lab equipment and 24% didn?t think the program helped them in their ability to identify the appropriate lab equipment for an experiment (see table 1a). However, these students worked on computational projects and therefore did not have an opportunity to develop these skills. More than 95% of students that responded to the exit survey said the program had increased their understanding of ethical and professional responsibility, as shown in table 1b, while more than 88% of respondents indicated that the program had helped increase their ability to conduct self-directed learning, as seen in table 1c. The data did indicate that the program needs to do more to help students develop their communication skills, particularly in the areas of writing a technical report, making oral presentations and preparing a scientific poster. Overall, students were extremely happy with the program and 100% said they would recommend the REU to other students and 88% ranked the overall research experience as either very good or excellent. When asked about graduate school, 76% stated they would consider attending MSU. Of those that said they would not consider attending MSU, 2 students said it was because MSU didn?t offer research programs that were of interest to them, one student said they did not plan to attend graduate school and one student stated financial reasons.   References:  Pinheiro, A., A. Cooley, J. Liao, R. Prabhu, and S. Elder, Comparison of natural crosslinking agents for the stabilization of xenogenic articular cartilage. Journal of Orthopaedic Research, 2016. 34(6): p. 1037-1046. Figueroa, L., B. Brazile, S. Lin, B. Nelson, and J. Liao, Characterization of the Unique Viscoelastic Properties of the Mitral Valve Anterior Leaflet. The FASEB Journal, 2016. 30(1 Supplement): p. 558.1. Figueroa;, L., B. Brazile;, S. Lin;, B. Nelson;, and J. Liao, Characterization of the Unique Viscoelastic Properties of the Mitral Valve Anterior Leaflet, in 2015 Annual Biomedical Research Conference for Minority Students 2015: Seattle, WA. Pinheiro, A., A. Gottipatu, and S. Elder, Use of Natural Crosslinkers to Stabilize Decellularized Cartilage, in Biomedical Engineering Society Annual Meeting. 2014: San Antonio, TX.        Last Modified: 04/05/2017       Submitted by: James N Warnock]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
