<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Enhancement of Participation at the Spatial Accuracy 2014 Conference, July 2014, East Lansing, Michigan</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2014</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2015</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>31652.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>31652</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>04040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>SBE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>BCS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Behavioral and Cognitive Sci</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Thomas Baerwald</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This award will provide support to facilitate the involvement of scholars from a broad range of research communities and nations to participate in the Spatial Accuracy 2014 conference, which will be held in July 2014 in East Lansing, Michigan.  Spatial Accuracy 2014 will be the 11th in a series of international symposia that have focused on topics of uncertainty in environmental data and model.  Theoretical, methodological, software, and instructional advancements shared at Spatial Accuracy 2014 will allow current and future practitioners to draw valid inference about large and complex systems through a number of different lines of inquiry, including assimilating disparate sources and types of data; accommodating spatial and temporal dependence to satisfy statistical model assumptions and improve predictive inference; partitioning and propagating sources of uncertainty through fine spatial scale predictions over large domains and; scaling to effectively exploit information in massive datasets.  The exchange of knowledge at the conference will advance scientific practice and interdisciplinary collaboration extending from geography and the spatial sciences to many other fields in the natural and social sciences, engineering, and the humanities.  The conference will provide excellent education and networking opportunities for students, post-doctoral scholars, and early-career researchers, and international collaboration will be enhanced because of special emphasis being placed on the involvement of scholars from developing nations.  Although the majority of conference participants will be from academic organizations, methodological advances that deal more effectively with uncertainty and error ultimately will lead to improved models used in a diverse range of settings by public, private, and other groups.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award will expand participation in the Spatial Accuracy 2014 conference by providing partial support for travel to and lodging at the conference for up to fifty scholars, including graduate students, early-career researchers, and scholars from developing nations.  Special efforts will be made to highlight a number of exciting cutting-edge findings from this set of national and international participants, and special activities will ensure their full engagement in the conference.  Because papers in the conference proceedings, all of which will be peer-reviewed to ensure high quality, will be freely disseminated via the Internet, the all participants and other scientists will be able to benefit from the enhanced scientific and technological understanding that will result.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/03/2014</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/03/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.075</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1359891</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Joseph</FirstName>
<LastName>Messina</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>P</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Joseph P Messina</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>jpm@msu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5173531715</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000279475</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/03/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Ashton</FirstName>
<LastName>Shortridge</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>M</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Ashton M Shortridge</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>ashton@msu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5174323561</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000329068</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/03/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Alexandra</FirstName>
<LastName>Kravchenko</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>N</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Alexandra N Kravchenko</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>kravche1@msu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5173551855</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000414106</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/03/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Andrew</FirstName>
<LastName>Finley</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>O</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Andrew O Finley</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>finleya@msu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5174327219</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000224556</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/03/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Michigan State University</Name>
<CityName>East Lansing</CityName>
<ZipCode>488242600</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5173555040</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>Office of Sponsored Programs</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[426 Administration Bldg, Rm2]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Michigan</StateName>
<StateCode>MI</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>08</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MI08</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>193247145</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>MICHIGAN STATE UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>053343976</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Michigan State University - Department of Geography]]></Name>
<CityName>East Lansing</CityName>
<StateCode>MI</StateCode>
<ZipCode>488241046</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[673 Auditorium Road]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Michigan</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>08</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MI08</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1352</Code>
<Text>Geography and Spatial Sciences</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1352</Code>
<Text>GEOGRAPHY AND SPATIAL SCIENCES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0114</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~31652</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><!-- p { margin-bottom: 0.08in; } --> <p style="margin-bottom: 0in;"><em><strong>Overview</strong></em></p> <!-- p { margin-bottom: 0.08in; } --> <p>This report summarizes the distribution and impact of National Science Foundation support for Spatial Accuracy 2014, an academic conference held on the campus of Michigan State University from July 8-11, 2014. The organizers thank the National Science Foundation for its generous support.</p> <p style="margin-bottom: 0in;">Spatial Accuracy was the 11<sup>th</sup> conference in a series held biennially: the International Symposia on Spatial Accuracy Assessment in Natural Resources and Environmental Sciences. These symposia have generally been hosted by academic units at universities around the world (on five continents), and have attracted a diverse set of scholars from Geography, Statistics, and the Environmental Sciences, as well as from government and other non-academic organizations.</p> <p style="margin-bottom: 0in;">&nbsp;</p> <p style="margin-bottom: 0in;">The proposal requested $31,652 to cover travel and accommodation costs for graduate students and global south scholars. These funds would be sufficient to partly offset travel costs for up to 50 people, and to provide free accommodation in a university residence hall for up to 30 people.</p> <p style="margin-bottom: 0in;">&nbsp;</p> <p style="margin-bottom: 0in;"><em><strong>Travel Support</strong></em></p> <p style="margin-bottom: 0in;">Fourteen people requested and were eligible for travel support. Four were in Group 1(Global South scholars), five were in Group 2 (international graduate students), and five were in Group 3 (US and Canadian graduate students). One of the Group 2 applicants subsequently withdrew her paper from the conference and did not participate, so the final number covered was 13. Three of the Group 1 participants were from Brazil, and one was from Mexico; two of the four were female. The four participating Group 2 members hailed from China, France, Germany, and the United Kingdom; two were female. The five Group 3 members were graduate students from Texas (three), California, and New York State. All five were males. All Group 1 and Group 2 members received a wire transfer of $1,000 USD to partially offset their travel expenses. All Group 3 members received a wire transfer of $500 USD to partially offset their travel expenses. These values are in accordance with the plan in the original proposal.</p> <p style="margin-bottom: 0in;">&nbsp;</p> <p style="margin-bottom: 0in;">In total, $10,500 was distributed for travel support. Wire transfer costs, also covered by NSF funding, cost $25 apiece for a total of $325.</p> <p style="margin-bottom: 0in;">&nbsp;</p> <p style="margin-bottom: 0in;"><em><strong>Accomodation Support</strong></em></p> <p style="margin-bottom: 0in;">Accommodation was in a modern, air conditioned residence hall a short walk from the on-campus conference center where Accuracy 2014 was held. Nine participants requested and were eligible. All were graduate students; six were from domestic universities, and the others were from European universities. Eight of the nine were male. Housing was entirely free for these participants, thanks to the funding supplied by the NSF.</p> <p style="margin-bottom: 0in;">&nbsp;</p> <p style="margin-bottom: 0in;">The rate for MSU Residence Halls was $40 per night for each room. Most attendees stayed for four nights; two stayed for 5 nights. The total cost covered by the NSF grant was $1,520.</p> <p style="margin-bottom: 0in;">&nbsp;</p> <p style="margin-bottom: 0in;"><em><strong>Discussion</strong></em></p> <p style="margin-bottom: 0in;">Fifteen participants in Accuracy 2014 were supported by by this project. For many, the funding they received to offset travel and accommodation costs was critical in enabling them to attend and contribute to the conference. As a consequence of their participation, bot...]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Overview   This report summarizes the distribution and impact of National Science Foundation support for Spatial Accuracy 2014, an academic conference held on the campus of Michigan State University from July 8-11, 2014. The organizers thank the National Science Foundation for its generous support. Spatial Accuracy was the 11th conference in a series held biennially: the International Symposia on Spatial Accuracy Assessment in Natural Resources and Environmental Sciences. These symposia have generally been hosted by academic units at universities around the world (on five continents), and have attracted a diverse set of scholars from Geography, Statistics, and the Environmental Sciences, as well as from government and other non-academic organizations.   The proposal requested $31,652 to cover travel and accommodation costs for graduate students and global south scholars. These funds would be sufficient to partly offset travel costs for up to 50 people, and to provide free accommodation in a university residence hall for up to 30 people.   Travel Support Fourteen people requested and were eligible for travel support. Four were in Group 1(Global South scholars), five were in Group 2 (international graduate students), and five were in Group 3 (US and Canadian graduate students). One of the Group 2 applicants subsequently withdrew her paper from the conference and did not participate, so the final number covered was 13. Three of the Group 1 participants were from Brazil, and one was from Mexico; two of the four were female. The four participating Group 2 members hailed from China, France, Germany, and the United Kingdom; two were female. The five Group 3 members were graduate students from Texas (three), California, and New York State. All five were males. All Group 1 and Group 2 members received a wire transfer of $1,000 USD to partially offset their travel expenses. All Group 3 members received a wire transfer of $500 USD to partially offset their travel expenses. These values are in accordance with the plan in the original proposal.   In total, $10,500 was distributed for travel support. Wire transfer costs, also covered by NSF funding, cost $25 apiece for a total of $325.   Accomodation Support Accommodation was in a modern, air conditioned residence hall a short walk from the on-campus conference center where Accuracy 2014 was held. Nine participants requested and were eligible. All were graduate students; six were from domestic universities, and the others were from European universities. Eight of the nine were male. Housing was entirely free for these participants, thanks to the funding supplied by the NSF.   The rate for MSU Residence Halls was $40 per night for each room. Most attendees stayed for four nights; two stayed for 5 nights. The total cost covered by the NSF grant was $1,520.   Discussion Fifteen participants in Accuracy 2014 were supported by by this project. For many, the funding they received to offset travel and accommodation costs was critical in enabling them to attend and contribute to the conference. As a consequence of their participation, both intellectual merit and broader impact elements of the proposal were met. Through their participation in the conference, these scholars were able to both contribute ideas to the wider Spatial Accuracy community, and take ideas back to their home institutions and professional networks. As a consequence, the scholarship presented at Spatial Accuracy enjoyed greater distribution than it otherwise could have. Further, several Latin American scholars who had participated in the 2012 conference in Brazil were able to attend the 2014 symposium, so that continuity of the Spatial Accuracy community could be better maintained. Supported participants were deeply appreciative to the National Science Foundation, as are the conference organizers.       Last Modified: 08/31/2015       Submitted by: Ashton M Shortridge]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
