<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>REU Site: Accelerator and Nuclear Physics</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>03/15/2014</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>02/28/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>228900.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>228900</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03010000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>PHY</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Physics</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Kathleen McCloud</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>kmccloud@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032928236</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This Research Experiences for Undergraduates (REU) site at Old Dominion University provides opportunities to eight undergraduate students each summer for ten weeks of research with continued opportunities for two students during the academic year on topics in accelerator and nuclear physics. The REU students will conduct the research at the Thomas Jefferson National Accelerator Facility. In addition to participating in research with an experienced mentor, the students will engage in weekly activities to ensure not only that their research stays on track but that they have an engaging collegial and scholarly experience. By the end of the program, every student will have written a research report and presented the results of their work in a talk, as well as prepared a poster. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This REU site will have a number of broader impacts with its focus on providing research opportunities to undergraduates to help prepare them for future science, technology, engineering, and mathematics careers. Additionally, the site focuses on providing research opportunities to students from institutions with small or no research programs in physics. The site has a strong plan to recruit students from groups underrepresented in physics.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>03/25/2014</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>02/08/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1359026</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Stephen</FirstName>
<LastName>Bueltmann</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>L</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Stephen L Bueltmann</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>sbueltma@odu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>7576836401</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000242176</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>03/25/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Hari</FirstName>
<LastName>Areti</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Hari Areti</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>areti@jlab.org</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>7572697187</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000303770</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>03/25/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Old Dominion University Research Foundation</Name>
<CityName>Norfolk</CityName>
<ZipCode>235082561</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>7576834293</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>4111 Monarch Way</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[Suite 204]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Virginia</StateName>
<StateCode>VA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>VA03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>077945947</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>OLD DOMINION UNIVERSITY RESEARCH FOUNDATION</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Old Dominion University]]></Name>
<CityName>Norfolk</CityName>
<StateCode>VA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>235290001</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[5115 Hampton Blvd]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Virginia</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>VA02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>9134</Code>
<Text>Integrative Activities in Phys</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9250</Code>
<Text>REU SITE-Res Exp for Ugrd Site</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>SMET</Code>
<Text>SCIENCE, MATH, ENG &amp; TECH EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0114</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0115</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0116</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~73900</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2015~76300</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2016~78700</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The Research Experience for Undergraduates (REU) program at Old Dominion University (ODU) is conducted in association with the Thomas Jefferson National Accelerator Facility (Jefferson Lab). The program's goal is to excite and encourage students into pursuing scientific careers in nuclear and accelerator physics.</p> <p>ODU has had a large presence at Jefferson Lab in experimental and theoretical nuclear physics since the laboratory's inception. During the last decade, this association expanded into the field of accelerator physics.&nbsp; While nuclear physics is a well-known field to undergraduates, accelerator physics remains somewhat unknown, even though accelerators have increasingly become important research tools in biology, medicine, and material sciences, to name just a few.&nbsp; The increasing numbers of accelerators for research and for applications such as medical diagnostics and treatment resulted in a demand for accelerator scientists nationally and world-wide. Additionally, accelerator physics is inherently inter-disciplinary and offers a variety of scientific and engineering career choices to students. In addition to being a unique nuclear physics research facility, Jefferson Lab is a world leader in both Superconducting Radio Frequency (SRF) accelerator technology and high current polarized electron sources. SRF technology is becoming the choice for many contemplated light sources and also the envisioned International Linear Collider. Our REU program makes students not only aware of these exciting possibilities but prepares them to take advantage of them.</p> <p>Our REU students participate in ongoing leading edge projects in both nuclear and accelerator physics. They receive safety training relevant to their projects, attend a seminar series (including a seminar on ethics in research), presented by leading scientists, tailored specifically for their level, and have access to excellent facilities. While the students have primary mentors, they work as part of a team (scientists, engineers, technicians, post-docs and graduate students) and are thus mentored by the team. Each student is required to write a paper at the end of their term, prepare and present a poster at the poster session, and orally present their research.&nbsp; The students receive training in all aspects of scientific communication. Planned recreational and social activities provide a break from the busy research work. We encourage our students to participate in undergraduate gatherings. The REU students interact with approximately 15 to 20 other undergraduates from within and outside the US.</p> <p>We receive about 175 applicants each year (increased to well over 200 in 2016). Over the past three years (2014-2017), 26 students participated in the ODU/Jefferson Lab REU program which included five female students and five under-represented minority students. Over half of our students are from institutions with limited or no research facilities.&nbsp;</p> <p>Of the students&nbsp; that participated in the program in 2014 and 2015 whom we were able to contact, eight of the students are pursuing doctoral degrees in physics, three students are continuing undergraduate studies, two are employed and one student changed field.</p> <p>One of our 2014 students won the "Best Poster Award" at the WoPhys15 (undergraduate women in physical sciences conference).</p> <p>In summary, the ODU/Jefferson Lab REU program attempts to provide excellent research training to undergraduate students with the goal of increasing their chances of pursuing scientific careers, especially in nuclear and accelerator physics.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 05/29/2018<br>      Modified by: Stephen&nbsp;L&nbsp;Bueltmann</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Images (<span id="selectedPhoto0">1</span> of <span class="totalNumber"></span>)           </div> <div class="galControls" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1359026/1359026_10296003_1488921950960_Khensu-RaLoveElpresentationSurfaceresistivityofSuperconductingCavities--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1359026/1359026_10296003_1488921950960_Khensu-RaLoveElpresentationSurfaceresistivityofSuperconductingCavities--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Khensu-Ra Love El, Morehouse College 2015"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1359026/1359026_10296003_1488921950960_Khensu-RaLoveElpresentationSurfaceresistivityofSuperconductingCavities--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Khensu-Ra Love El, Morehouse College 2015"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Oral Presentation on Surface Resistivity of Superconducting Cavities</div> <div class="imageCredit">Jefferson Lab Education Department</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Public Domain</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Hari&nbsp;Areti</div> <div class="imageTitle">Khensu-Ra Love El, Morehouse College 2015</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1359026/1359026_10296003_1488922090613_StudentsatODU'scenterforAcceleratorScience--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1359026/1359026_10296003_1488922090613_StudentsatODU'scenterforAcceleratorScience--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Students at ODU's Center for Accelerator Science"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1359026/1359026_10296003_1488922090613_StudentsatODU'scenterforAcceleratorScience--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Students at ODU's Center for Accelerator Science"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Prof. Jean Delayen Explaining SRF structures</div> <div class="imageCredit">H. Areti</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Public Domain</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Hari&nbsp;Areti</div> <div class="imageTitle">Students at ODU's Center for Accelerator Science</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1359026/1359026_10296003_1488922325715_Characteriszing750MHzSeparatorCavity--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1359026/1359026_10296003_1488922325715_Characteriszing750MHzSeparatorCavity--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Andrew Jacobs, Benedictine College"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1359026/1359026_10296003_1488922325715_Characteriszing750MHzSeparatorCavity--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Andrew Jacobs, Benedictine College"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Characterizing 750 MHz Superconducting Cavity</div> <div class="imageCredit">Jefferson Lab's Education Department</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Hari&nbsp;Areti</div> <div class="imageTitle">Andrew Jacobs, Benedictine College</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The Research Experience for Undergraduates (REU) program at Old Dominion University (ODU) is conducted in association with the Thomas Jefferson National Accelerator Facility (Jefferson Lab). The program's goal is to excite and encourage students into pursuing scientific careers in nuclear and accelerator physics.  ODU has had a large presence at Jefferson Lab in experimental and theoretical nuclear physics since the laboratory's inception. During the last decade, this association expanded into the field of accelerator physics.  While nuclear physics is a well-known field to undergraduates, accelerator physics remains somewhat unknown, even though accelerators have increasingly become important research tools in biology, medicine, and material sciences, to name just a few.  The increasing numbers of accelerators for research and for applications such as medical diagnostics and treatment resulted in a demand for accelerator scientists nationally and world-wide. Additionally, accelerator physics is inherently inter-disciplinary and offers a variety of scientific and engineering career choices to students. In addition to being a unique nuclear physics research facility, Jefferson Lab is a world leader in both Superconducting Radio Frequency (SRF) accelerator technology and high current polarized electron sources. SRF technology is becoming the choice for many contemplated light sources and also the envisioned International Linear Collider. Our REU program makes students not only aware of these exciting possibilities but prepares them to take advantage of them.  Our REU students participate in ongoing leading edge projects in both nuclear and accelerator physics. They receive safety training relevant to their projects, attend a seminar series (including a seminar on ethics in research), presented by leading scientists, tailored specifically for their level, and have access to excellent facilities. While the students have primary mentors, they work as part of a team (scientists, engineers, technicians, post-docs and graduate students) and are thus mentored by the team. Each student is required to write a paper at the end of their term, prepare and present a poster at the poster session, and orally present their research.  The students receive training in all aspects of scientific communication. Planned recreational and social activities provide a break from the busy research work. We encourage our students to participate in undergraduate gatherings. The REU students interact with approximately 15 to 20 other undergraduates from within and outside the US.  We receive about 175 applicants each year (increased to well over 200 in 2016). Over the past three years (2014-2017), 26 students participated in the ODU/Jefferson Lab REU program which included five female students and five under-represented minority students. Over half of our students are from institutions with limited or no research facilities.   Of the students  that participated in the program in 2014 and 2015 whom we were able to contact, eight of the students are pursuing doctoral degrees in physics, three students are continuing undergraduate studies, two are employed and one student changed field.  One of our 2014 students won the "Best Poster Award" at the WoPhys15 (undergraduate women in physical sciences conference).  In summary, the ODU/Jefferson Lab REU program attempts to provide excellent research training to undergraduate students with the goal of increasing their chances of pursuing scientific careers, especially in nuclear and accelerator physics.          Last Modified: 05/29/2018       Submitted by: Stephen L Bueltmann]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
