<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Integrated Optics for Undergraduate Native Americans (IOU-NA)</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>04/01/2014</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>03/31/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>290889.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>290889</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07050000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>EEC</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Engineering Education and Centers</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Mary Poats</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>TECHNICAL SUMMARY:&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;With the committed support from the Division of Engineering Education and Centers, CIAN's IOU-NA REU program will provide research training for 8 Native American STEM undergraduate students, for 10 weeks during the summers of 2014-2016. CIAN's research addresses photonic materials and devices for optical communication that will be the cornerstone of future Internet technologies. Many leading companies that develop hardware for Internet equipment such as Intel, Cisco, Oracle, Alcatel-Lucent, and Fujitsu are CIAN industrial affiliates with a keen interest to recruit students with these specialized skills. Over a fifteen year horizon, keeping the U.S. as a leader in information technology will require developing dense, integrated optoelectronic systems that extend the capabilities of the current fiber network core while retaining the same cost as today's electronic access network. In addition, entirely new applications for photonics with internet data centers and within the infrastructure of cloud computing are already emerging. IOU-NA students will join experienced CIAN research teams working on improved fiber optics, waveguide materials, short-pulsed lasers, nanofabrication, silicon photonics, and nonlinear photonics, as well as teams in the COS, specifically in the area of Hydrology and Environmental Sciences. This interdisciplinary approach will provide REU participants with a more rounded research experience. The research projects selected for this program have the potential to advance the fields of optical sciences and environmental sciences across the United States. The IOU-NA program prepares students for the challenges of modern engineering by providing a series of trainings and workshops that deliver information and strategies for success in STEM careers and education, practice in communicating the application and motivation of their research projects, and encouraging ambition to publish and share research at conferences, encouraging them to share these developed skill sets within their tribal and urban communities.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;NON-TECHNICAL SUMMARY:&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;In 2012, NSF reported that of the nearly 3500 engineering doctorate degrees awarded to U.S. citizens in the United States, fewer than .17 went to Native Americans. It has become increasingly evident that there is an enormous need to support Native Americans pursuing STEM fields, and is aligned with national endeavors to increase and improve STEM education for underrepresented minorities. With only 42% of Native Americans pursuing any form of higher education and only 13% of that number attaining a bachelor's degree or higher, the need for programs to support Native Americans in undergraduate STEM fields is immediate.  CIAN's REU, IOU-NA program is an essential step ensuring these students with unique obstacles gain the confidence and tools needed to graduate with STEM bachelor's degrees and pursue graduate degrees. CIAN's current REU program is a proven, multi-disciplinary, multi-institutional program that provides research experiences to undergraduate students, who, without this program, would have minimal alternatives for undergraduate experiences. Adding a Native American focus to CIAN's REU by mentoring 8 students who are either Native American by citizenship or undergraduate students attending an American Indian serving college or university is in line with the priorities of this nation. CIAN's IOU-NA program will increase opportunities for underrepresented minorities to successfully graduate with higher education STEM majors and pursue STEM careers and graduate studies. In addition to participation in cutting-edge research, IOU-NA students will participate in workshops and a STEM Native American speakers series This IOU-NA is one of several education programs that CIAN has developed in an effort to streamline the STEM pipeline for Native American youth.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>03/18/2014</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>03/18/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1359163</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Robert</FirstName>
<LastName>Norwood</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>A</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Robert A Norwood</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>rnorwood@optics.arizona.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5206260936</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000221967</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>03/18/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Allison</FirstName>
<LastName>Huff</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>J</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Allison J Huff</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>allison7@arizona.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5206262719</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000593239</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>03/18/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Arizona</Name>
<CityName>Tucson</CityName>
<ZipCode>857194824</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5206266000</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>888 N Euclid Ave</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Arizona</StateName>
<StateCode>AZ</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>AZ03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>806345617</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF ARIZONA</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>072459266</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Arizona]]></Name>
<CityName>Tucson</CityName>
<StateCode>AZ</StateCode>
<ZipCode>857210001</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[1630 E. University Blvd.]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Arizona</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>AZ03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1360</Code>
<Text>EWFD-Eng Workforce Development</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>116E</Code>
<Text>RESEARCH EXP FOR UNDERGRADS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9178</Code>
<Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9250</Code>
<Text>REU SITE-Res Exp for Ugrd Site</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0114</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~290889</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><strong>Summary</strong></p> <p>The Center for Integrated Access Networks (CIAN), an engineering research center (ERC) funded by the National Science Foundation (NSF), received a three-year Research Experience for Undergraduates (REU) site award from NSF and a year extension (2014-2017), entitled Integrated Optics for Undergraduate Native Americans (IOUNA). Thirty-five participants from around the nation participated in the 10-week IOUNA program. IOUNA participants included freshmen through seniors from 17 colleges/universities across the United States that represented 11 different tribes. The primary goals of this REU program are to expand participation and interest in optics and STEM among Native American undergraduate students; to encourage undergraduate students to pursue graduate school studies and professional careers in science and engineering; to boost demographic representation of Native Americans in graduate studies; and to develop the teaching, mentoring, and project management skills of CIAN graduate and postdoctoral mentors.</p> <p>IOU-NA students conducted 10-weeks of summer research in STEM laboratories, including CIAN labs, at the University of Arizona (UA).&nbsp; As was done previously with CIAN&rsquo;s IOU REU, the IOUNA program was administered in concert with other undergraduate summer programs that participated in UA&rsquo;s Undergraduate Research Opportunities Consortium (UROC). Such partnerships provided the REU students with a larger cohort experience, exposure to a variety of disciplines, social/professional networking, and academic enrichment workshops made possible by cost-sharing. This collaboration also allowed the REU students to optimize their undergraduate research experiences.</p> <p>The IOUNA students conclude their program with a research poster and oral presentation for university faculty, students, staff, and families. This opportunity to network and present their work prepares them for conferences and future professional development activities. This program also funds IOUNA students to attend the annual American Indian Science and Engineering Society (AISES) conference. Attending this conference and networking within a strong Native American STEM community is an invaluable experience that provides resources to drive Native American undergraduates toward graduate school and careers in STEM.</p> <p><strong>IOUNA program Ratings and Outcomes</strong></p> <p>Survey responses from IOUNA participants from 2014 &ndash; 2017 indicate a great impact on participant confidence, research skills, STEM interest, graduate school interest and preparation, and life-long learner attributes that increase Native American participation in STEM. In the most recent alumni survey, 100% of the respondents indicated that their research experience in the program affected their educational plans and career plans.</p> <p>However, proof of IOUNA success is in the outcomes. Apart from professional development and improved research skills, IOU-NA students experienced many other positive outcomes as a result of their REU participation. Several students have graduated and are preparing for graduate school. At least 16 students have completed their undergraduate degrees, and currently, nine students are currently attending graduate school studying STEM subjects. Students from the 2014-2017 IOUNA REU have reported presenting their own research at the following conferences: AISES 2014, Blinded by the Light 2014, NCUR 2014, AGMUS 2015, AISES 2015, Arizona Space Grant Statewide Symposium 2015, Cornell University LSAMP &amp; McNair Symposium 2015, HENAAC 2015, MRS 2015, NGWA 2015, SACNAS 2015, AISES 2016, IONS 2016, American Geophysical Union 2016, Pacific Northwest LSAMP conference 2016, AISES 2017, NSF Engineering Education and Centers Grantees 2017. Students have also reported attendance at the following conferences: American Geophysical Union 2014, SACNAS 2014, California for Minority Participation Statewide 2015, National Academy of Engineering 2015, SHPE Regional Conference 2015, SACNAS 2016, and the Summit for Sustainable Agriculture 2017. Several students are continuing to collaborate with their mentors in publishing their research; so far, IOUNA students have reported five peer-reviewed publications, four pending publications, and one awarded patent. They have also gained further professional development opportunities with internships, including internships at Woods Hole Oceanographic Institution, Sandia National Labs, US Department of Agriculture, NASA, Boeing, and Neya Automation Systems. Several students have also reported continuing and expanding their research at universities across the US. The extensive accomplishments described, however, are merely a selection of the continuous achievements of IOUNA alumni.</p> <p>One former IOUNA participant emailed the PI the following: "I just graduated and&nbsp;<span>I wanted to thank you for giving me a chance to become part of your team and program. Like I said before, I honestly did not know what research was until your program. I am happy you are taking time out of your normal work day to focus on Native American students. It really makes me happy to see you and&nbsp;</span><span id="0.8402055400834918" class="currentHitHighlight">Amee</span><span>&nbsp;help Natives with their education. I would not be where I am today if it wasn&rsquo;t for both you and Amee.</span><span>&nbsp;I got to see the behind the scenes of your operation; it was amazing and very inspiring."</span></p> <p>IOUNA participants consistently report incredible personal achievements. This program and the numerous impacts reported would not have been possible without the funding and support provided by NSF&rsquo;s REU programs.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 06/29/2018<br>      Modified by: Allison&nbsp;Huff Macpherson</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Images (<span id="selectedPhoto0">1</span> of <span class="totalNumber"></span>)           </div> <div class="galControls" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1359163/1359163_10295166_1530318988420_IOU-NA-Solianna--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1359163/1359163_10295166_1530318988420_IOU-NA-Solianna--rgov-800width.jpg" title="IOU-NA Lab Photo"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1359163/1359163_10295166_1530318988420_IOU-NA-Solianna--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="IOU-NA Lab Photo"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">IOU-NA student in lab</div> <div class="imageCredit">University of Arizona</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyright owner is an institution with an existing agreement allowing use by NSF</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Allison&nbsp;Huff Macpherson</div> <div class="imageTitle">IOU-NA Lab Photo</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1359163/1359163_10295166_1530318813593_IOU-NA_2017--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1359163/1359163_10295166_1530318813593_IOU-NA_2017--rgov-800width.jpg" title="IOU-NA Group Photo"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1359163/1359163_10295166_1530318813593_IOU-NA_2017--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="IOU-NA Group Photo"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Group of participants for the 2016 IOU-NA REU program</div> <div class="imageCredit">University of Arizona</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyright owner is an institution with an existing agreement allowing use by NSF</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Allison&nbsp;Huff Macpherson</div> <div class="imageTitle">IOU-NA Group Photo</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1359163/1359163_10295166_1530319108617_Antonia_Lab--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1359163/1359163_10295166_1530319108617_Antonia_Lab--rgov-800width.jpg" title="IOU-NA Lab"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1359163/1359163_10295166_1530319108617_Antonia_Lab--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="IOU-NA Lab"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">IOU-NA student in Lab</div> <div class="imageCredit">University of Arizona</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyright owner is an institution with an existing agreement allowing use by NSF</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Allison&nbsp;Huff Macpherson</div> <div class="imageTitle">IOU-NA Lab</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1359163/1359163_10295166_1530319192853_IOU_NA_AnthonyPresentation--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1359163/1359163_10295166_1530319192853_IOU_NA_AnthonyPresentation--rgov-800width.jpg" title="IOU-NA Presenter"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1359163/1359163_10295166_1530319192853_IOU_NA_AnthonyPresentation--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="IOU-NA Presenter"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">IOU-NA Final presentation</div> <div class="imageCredit">University of Arizona</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyright owner is an institution with an existing agreement allowing use by NSF</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Allison&nbsp;Huff Macpherson</div> <div class="imageTitle">IOU-NA Presenter</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1359163/1359163_10295166_1530319283128_IOU-NAPosterSession--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1359163/1359163_10295166_1530319283128_IOU-NAPosterSession--rgov-800width.jpg" title="IOU-NA Poster Session"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1359163/1359163_10295166_1530319283128_IOU-NAPosterSession--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="IOU-NA Poster Session"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">IOU-NA Student Poster Session</div> <div class="imageCredit">University of Arizona</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyright owner is an institution with an existing agreement allowing use by NSF</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Allison&nbsp;Huff Macpherson</div> <div class="imageTitle">IOU-NA Poster Session</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1359163/1359163_10295166_1530319388677_CraigDraper_Lab5--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1359163/1359163_10295166_1530319388677_CraigDraper_Lab5--rgov-800width.jpg" title="IOU-NA Student in Lab"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1359163/1359163_10295166_1530319388677_CraigDraper_Lab5--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="IOU-NA Student in Lab"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">IOU-NA student in their research lab</div> <div class="imageCredit">University of Arizona</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyright owner is an institution with an existing agreement allowing use by NSF</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Allison&nbsp;Huff Macpherson</div> <div class="imageTitle">IOU-NA Student in Lab</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Summary  The Center for Integrated Access Networks (CIAN), an engineering research center (ERC) funded by the National Science Foundation (NSF), received a three-year Research Experience for Undergraduates (REU) site award from NSF and a year extension (2014-2017), entitled Integrated Optics for Undergraduate Native Americans (IOUNA). Thirty-five participants from around the nation participated in the 10-week IOUNA program. IOUNA participants included freshmen through seniors from 17 colleges/universities across the United States that represented 11 different tribes. The primary goals of this REU program are to expand participation and interest in optics and STEM among Native American undergraduate students; to encourage undergraduate students to pursue graduate school studies and professional careers in science and engineering; to boost demographic representation of Native Americans in graduate studies; and to develop the teaching, mentoring, and project management skills of CIAN graduate and postdoctoral mentors.  IOU-NA students conducted 10-weeks of summer research in STEM laboratories, including CIAN labs, at the University of Arizona (UA).  As was done previously with CIAN?s IOU REU, the IOUNA program was administered in concert with other undergraduate summer programs that participated in UA?s Undergraduate Research Opportunities Consortium (UROC). Such partnerships provided the REU students with a larger cohort experience, exposure to a variety of disciplines, social/professional networking, and academic enrichment workshops made possible by cost-sharing. This collaboration also allowed the REU students to optimize their undergraduate research experiences.  The IOUNA students conclude their program with a research poster and oral presentation for university faculty, students, staff, and families. This opportunity to network and present their work prepares them for conferences and future professional development activities. This program also funds IOUNA students to attend the annual American Indian Science and Engineering Society (AISES) conference. Attending this conference and networking within a strong Native American STEM community is an invaluable experience that provides resources to drive Native American undergraduates toward graduate school and careers in STEM.  IOUNA program Ratings and Outcomes  Survey responses from IOUNA participants from 2014 &ndash; 2017 indicate a great impact on participant confidence, research skills, STEM interest, graduate school interest and preparation, and life-long learner attributes that increase Native American participation in STEM. In the most recent alumni survey, 100% of the respondents indicated that their research experience in the program affected their educational plans and career plans.  However, proof of IOUNA success is in the outcomes. Apart from professional development and improved research skills, IOU-NA students experienced many other positive outcomes as a result of their REU participation. Several students have graduated and are preparing for graduate school. At least 16 students have completed their undergraduate degrees, and currently, nine students are currently attending graduate school studying STEM subjects. Students from the 2014-2017 IOUNA REU have reported presenting their own research at the following conferences: AISES 2014, Blinded by the Light 2014, NCUR 2014, AGMUS 2015, AISES 2015, Arizona Space Grant Statewide Symposium 2015, Cornell University LSAMP &amp; McNair Symposium 2015, HENAAC 2015, MRS 2015, NGWA 2015, SACNAS 2015, AISES 2016, IONS 2016, American Geophysical Union 2016, Pacific Northwest LSAMP conference 2016, AISES 2017, NSF Engineering Education and Centers Grantees 2017. Students have also reported attendance at the following conferences: American Geophysical Union 2014, SACNAS 2014, California for Minority Participation Statewide 2015, National Academy of Engineering 2015, SHPE Regional Conference 2015, SACNAS 2016, and the Summit for Sustainable Agriculture 2017. Several students are continuing to collaborate with their mentors in publishing their research; so far, IOUNA students have reported five peer-reviewed publications, four pending publications, and one awarded patent. They have also gained further professional development opportunities with internships, including internships at Woods Hole Oceanographic Institution, Sandia National Labs, US Department of Agriculture, NASA, Boeing, and Neya Automation Systems. Several students have also reported continuing and expanding their research at universities across the US. The extensive accomplishments described, however, are merely a selection of the continuous achievements of IOUNA alumni.  One former IOUNA participant emailed the PI the following: "I just graduated and I wanted to thank you for giving me a chance to become part of your team and program. Like I said before, I honestly did not know what research was until your program. I am happy you are taking time out of your normal work day to focus on Native American students. It really makes me happy to see you and Amee help Natives with their education. I would not be where I am today if it wasn?t for both you and Amee. I got to see the behind the scenes of your operation; it was amazing and very inspiring."  IOUNA participants consistently report incredible personal achievements. This program and the numerous impacts reported would not have been possible without the funding and support provided by NSF?s REU programs.          Last Modified: 06/29/2018       Submitted by: Allison Huff Macpherson]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
