<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>US-China Planning Visit: Understanding earth's Solar Wind-Magnetosphere-Ionosphere system from the Antarctic</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>03/15/2014</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>02/28/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>19007.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>19007</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>01090000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>O/D</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Office Of The Director</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>OISE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Office Of Internatl Science &amp;Engineering</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Anne Emig</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>aemig@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927241</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>NSF funding will support planning visits to promote and develop a new collaboration with Dr. Yonghua Liu and his research group at the Polar Research Institute of China, in Shanghai.  The collaboration centers on the combination of data obtained from autonomous space weather stations operated in remote polar Antarctic locations by the Chinese group and the Virginia Tech Center for Space Science and Engineering Research.   The stations are at synergistic locations in the Antarctic to enable investigations of: 1) the coupling of energy from the solar wind to the magnetosphere and ionosphere through the associated development of electrical current systems in space and in the ionosphere; 2) the production of density irregularities in the high latitude ionosphere that can disrupt communication and navigation systems and 3) the energization of charged particles in space that can damage satellite electronics.  The Solar Wind-Magnetosphere-Ionosphere is a complex natural system that can impact a variety of human technology. To forecast and mitigate that impact is a major goal of the U. S. National Space Weather Program. Achieving this goal is hampered, however, by the lack of sufficient data coverage to validate global models, particularly in the southern hemisphere. The recent availability of data from autonomous space weather stations deployed along a latitude chain in the Antarctic by Virginia Tech enables new investigations of the Sun-Earth system. China, one of the leading countries actively involved in the Antarctic programs, is operating stations in the East Antarctic that complement the Virginia Tech stations by adding a longitudinal chain. Considering the extreme conditions of weather and logistics in the Antarctic, international collaboration enables more efficient and more wide-ranging investigations using data from the combined stations.   The Virginia Tech and Chinese stations together monitor the region where the geomagnetic field lines that interact with the solar wind intersect the dayside high latitude ionosphere, thus enabling investigation of the processes that couple energy from the solar wind to the magnetosphere and ionosphere.  The collaborative work will greatly expand scientific investigations that could not be accomplished by either data set alone.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>03/05/2014</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>04/08/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.079</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1359691</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Calvin Robert</FirstName>
<LastName>Clauer</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Calvin Robert Clauer</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>rclauer@vt.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5402316646</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000276141</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>03/05/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University</Name>
<CityName>BLACKSBURG</CityName>
<ZipCode>240610001</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5402315281</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>Sponsored Programs 0170</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[300 Turner Street NW, Suite 4200]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Virginia</StateName>
<StateCode>VA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>09</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>VA09</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>003137015</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>VIRGINIA POLYTECHNIC INSTITUTE AND STATE UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>003137015</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[National Institute of Aerospace]]></Name>
<CityName>Hampton</CityName>
<StateCode>VA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>236666266</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[100 Exploration Way]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Virginia</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>VA03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7299</Code>
<Text>Catalyzing New Intl Collab</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>5978</Code>
<Text>EAST ASIA AND PACIFIC PROGRAM</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9200</Code>
<Text>US CHINA COOP IN BASIC SCIENCE</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0114</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~19007</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The project &ldquo;Catalyzing New International Collaborations in Antarctic Space Weather Research&rdquo; was developed to promote and develop a new collaboration with Dr. Yonghua Liu and his research group at the Polar Research Institute of China, in Shanghai, China.&nbsp; The collaboration centers on the combination of data obtained from autonomous measurement stations at synergistic locations in the Antarctic obtained by our respective groups.&nbsp; These data in combination greatly expand the scientific investigations that can be accomplished by either data set alone.&nbsp; The investigations are relevant to understanding the complex interactions of the solar wind with the Earth&rsquo;s magnetosphere and ionosphere that lead, in turn, to various space weather phenomena.&nbsp; These include: the development of electrical current systems in space and in the ionosphere that carry over a million amperes of current; the energization of charged particles that can damage satellite electronics in space; and the production of density irregularities in the high latitude ionosphere that can disrupt communication and navigation systems.&nbsp; The Antarctic stations monitor the region where the geomagnetic field lines that first encounter the solar wind intersect the dayside high latitude ionosphere, thus enabling investigation of the processes that couple energy from the solar wind to the magnetosphere and ionosphere.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>This project supported the initiation of communication between the Magnetosphere Ionosphere Science Team (MIST) at Virginia Tech and Dr. Liu at the Polar Atmosphere and Space Physics Division of the Polar Research Institute of China (PRIC).&nbsp; This was followed by a visit to PRIC in May 2014 by Dr. Clauer, Dr. Hyomin Kim, and Dr. Zhonghua Xu.&nbsp; The visit enabled us to discuss our scientific research programs and data collection efforts in Antarctica and also in the northern hemisphere.&nbsp;&nbsp; Several areas of common interest were identified for collaboration and a document outlining our planned scientific cooperation was developed and signed.&nbsp;&nbsp; This document is attached at the end of this report.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>Due to scheduling difficulties and also a visa problem, Dr. Liu&rsquo;s visit to Virginia Tech was delayed until December 2016.&nbsp; During the time between our visit in May 2014 to Dr. Liu&rsquo;s visit in December 2016, the MIST group completed the deployment of an Antarctic magnetometer chain along the 40&deg; magnetic meridian in the Antarctic.&nbsp;&nbsp; This chain is magnetically conjugate to a magnetometer chain established in the northern hemisphere along the west coast of Greenland.&nbsp;&nbsp; Thus enabling, for the first time, simultaneous measurements in both hemispheres related to the interactions of the solar wind with the Earth&rsquo;s magnetosphere in the region of the high latitude day-side polar cusp.&nbsp;&nbsp; This is the region in the ionosphere that is directly coupled to the solar wind and measurements using these chains help to elucidate the coupling processes.&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>Dr. Liu and the PRIC have established a latitudinal chain of autonomous magnetometers by utilizing the overland traverse from Zhongshan station on the Antarctic coast to Kunlun station located at Dome A.&nbsp; When combined with our stations along the 40&deg; magnetic meridian, we have a two dimensional conjugate area experiment using also stations in the northern hemisphere.&nbsp; This is particularly important because there are many reasons to expect asymmetries in both longitude and latitude resulting from solar wind interactions with the dayside magnetosphere.&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>It is unfortunate, however, that the three stations deployed along the chain from Zhongshan Station to Kulun station have been unreliable.&nbsp; Therefore, during the visit in December 2016, we developed plans to replace these stations with ones following the design of the Virginia Tech systems.&nbsp;&nbsp; Some of these stations have been operating successfully for over 6 years and they also provide both fluxgate and induction coil magnetometer data.&nbsp; A proposal is in preparation now, resulting from the visits and discussions supported by this project.&nbsp;&nbsp; The proposed effort that has resulted from the support of this project is being expressed in a proposal to NSF directed toward an investigation of the coupling phenomena between the solar wind and the Earth&rsquo;s magnetosphere, particularly on the dayside of the Earth and observed simultaneously at high latitudes in both northern and southern hemispheres.&nbsp; This will be a collaboration between Virginia Tech, the University of New Hampshire, New Jersey Institute of Technology, the University of Michigan, the Polar Research Institute of China and the Danish Space Research Institute at the Danish Technical University.&nbsp; The proposal to NSF seeks funding for the US partners in this scientific collaboration that consists of two parts.&nbsp; The first part is to construct and test instrumentation that will be shipped to the PRIC to be deployed in the Antarctic along the chain from Zhongshan Station to Kunlun station by the Chinese Antarctic Expedition.&nbsp; The second part of the project will be devoted to the collection and analysis of data from the conjugate area array, along with other publically available data to address some specific space weather science questions.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 04/06/2017<br>      Modified by: Calvin Robert&nbsp;Clauer</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Images (<span id="selectedPhoto0">1</span> of <span class="totalNumber"></span>)           </div> <div class="galControls" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1359691/1359691_10293556_1491503088208_aalpip_map--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1359691/1359691_10293556_1491503088208_aalpip_map--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Station locations for Conjugate Area Array"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1359691/1359691_10293556_1491503088208_aalpip_map--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Station locations for Conjugate Area Array"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">This map show the 40-degree magnetic meridian stations (red and blue) the conjugate Greenland stations (green) and the PRIC stations (black).</div> <div class="imageCredit">C. Robert Clauer</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Public Domain</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Calvin Robert&nbsp;Clauer</div> <div class="imageTitle">Station locations for Conjugate Area Array</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1359691/1359691_10293556_1491503189773_CollaborationDocument--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1359691/1359691_10293556_1491503189773_CollaborationDocument--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Collaboration Document"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1359691/1359691_10293556_1491503189773_CollaborationDocument--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Collaboration Document"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Collaboration Document signed in May 2014</div> <div class="imageCredit">C. Robert Clauer</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Public Domain</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Calvin Robert&nbsp;Clauer</div> <div class="imageTitle">Collaboration Document</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The project "Catalyzing New International Collaborations in Antarctic Space Weather Research" was developed to promote and develop a new collaboration with Dr. Yonghua Liu and his research group at the Polar Research Institute of China, in Shanghai, China.  The collaboration centers on the combination of data obtained from autonomous measurement stations at synergistic locations in the Antarctic obtained by our respective groups.  These data in combination greatly expand the scientific investigations that can be accomplished by either data set alone.  The investigations are relevant to understanding the complex interactions of the solar wind with the Earth?s magnetosphere and ionosphere that lead, in turn, to various space weather phenomena.  These include: the development of electrical current systems in space and in the ionosphere that carry over a million amperes of current; the energization of charged particles that can damage satellite electronics in space; and the production of density irregularities in the high latitude ionosphere that can disrupt communication and navigation systems.  The Antarctic stations monitor the region where the geomagnetic field lines that first encounter the solar wind intersect the dayside high latitude ionosphere, thus enabling investigation of the processes that couple energy from the solar wind to the magnetosphere and ionosphere.     This project supported the initiation of communication between the Magnetosphere Ionosphere Science Team (MIST) at Virginia Tech and Dr. Liu at the Polar Atmosphere and Space Physics Division of the Polar Research Institute of China (PRIC).  This was followed by a visit to PRIC in May 2014 by Dr. Clauer, Dr. Hyomin Kim, and Dr. Zhonghua Xu.  The visit enabled us to discuss our scientific research programs and data collection efforts in Antarctica and also in the northern hemisphere.   Several areas of common interest were identified for collaboration and a document outlining our planned scientific cooperation was developed and signed.   This document is attached at the end of this report.     Due to scheduling difficulties and also a visa problem, Dr. Liu?s visit to Virginia Tech was delayed until December 2016.  During the time between our visit in May 2014 to Dr. Liu?s visit in December 2016, the MIST group completed the deployment of an Antarctic magnetometer chain along the 40&deg; magnetic meridian in the Antarctic.   This chain is magnetically conjugate to a magnetometer chain established in the northern hemisphere along the west coast of Greenland.   Thus enabling, for the first time, simultaneous measurements in both hemispheres related to the interactions of the solar wind with the Earth?s magnetosphere in the region of the high latitude day-side polar cusp.   This is the region in the ionosphere that is directly coupled to the solar wind and measurements using these chains help to elucidate the coupling processes.      Dr. Liu and the PRIC have established a latitudinal chain of autonomous magnetometers by utilizing the overland traverse from Zhongshan station on the Antarctic coast to Kunlun station located at Dome A.  When combined with our stations along the 40&deg; magnetic meridian, we have a two dimensional conjugate area experiment using also stations in the northern hemisphere.  This is particularly important because there are many reasons to expect asymmetries in both longitude and latitude resulting from solar wind interactions with the dayside magnetosphere.      It is unfortunate, however, that the three stations deployed along the chain from Zhongshan Station to Kulun station have been unreliable.  Therefore, during the visit in December 2016, we developed plans to replace these stations with ones following the design of the Virginia Tech systems.   Some of these stations have been operating successfully for over 6 years and they also provide both fluxgate and induction coil magnetometer data.  A proposal is in preparation now, resulting from the visits and discussions supported by this project.   The proposed effort that has resulted from the support of this project is being expressed in a proposal to NSF directed toward an investigation of the coupling phenomena between the solar wind and the Earth?s magnetosphere, particularly on the dayside of the Earth and observed simultaneously at high latitudes in both northern and southern hemispheres.  This will be a collaboration between Virginia Tech, the University of New Hampshire, New Jersey Institute of Technology, the University of Michigan, the Polar Research Institute of China and the Danish Space Research Institute at the Danish Technical University.  The proposal to NSF seeks funding for the US partners in this scientific collaboration that consists of two parts.  The first part is to construct and test instrumentation that will be shipped to the PRIC to be deployed in the Antarctic along the chain from Zhongshan Station to Kunlun station by the Chinese Antarctic Expedition.  The second part of the project will be devoted to the collection and analysis of data from the conjugate area array, along with other publically available data to address some specific space weather science questions.                   Last Modified: 04/06/2017       Submitted by: Calvin Robert Clauer]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
