<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Collaborative Research: Plug and Play Photosynthesis for RuBisCO Independent Fuels</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>06/01/2014</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>415620.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>415620</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>08070000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>BIO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>MCB</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Molecular and Cellular Bioscience</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Steve Clouse</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>sclouse@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032928440</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Global human energy consumption is expected to increase by over 30% in the next 15 years. Although there is more than enough energy in sunlight to meet this challenge, efficient means to concentrate this diffuse solar energy and store it have not yet been developed. Photosynthesis is the biological process by which green plants and some microorganisms capture and store solar energy; they use it to convert carbon dioxide to metabolic fuels. However, photosynthesis is inherently an inefficient process; it is limited not by the availability of light from the sun but by the rate of the first step in the chemical reactions by which carbon dioxide is converted into products that are rich in energy. There is therefore unused capacity for the capture and use of solar energy by natural photosynthesis. This program engages teams of researchers from the US and the United Kingdom with the goal to re-invent photosynthesis with enhanced efficiency thereby improving the capacity of photosynthetic organisms to make renewable fuels and enhance food security. In the course of the scientific research, this project will provide research training opportunities for more than 14 people (including both women and underrepresented minorities) at the post-doctoral, graduate and undergraduate levels. The international and interdisciplinary nature of the project will build bridges between the US and UK scientific communities in a range of important scientific areas including synthetic biology, photosynthetic physiology, catalysis, and metabolic regulation. The researchers will engage and inform both the public and other investigators through activities that include peer-reviewed publications, public science lectures, blogs, websites, and popular science articles. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;To dramatically enhance the efficiency of photosynthesis, this project will develop a range of mechanisms to electrically connect light-activated electron flow from the photosynthetic reaction center  (PSI) to downstream fuel-production pathways. This will include increasing flux through natural pathways, creating electrical connections between distinct microbial cell types by construction of artificial biological nanowires, and employing a soluble, chemical, redox shuttle to transfer reducing equivalents from a light harvesting cell to different fuel-producing cells. These scientific goals will be accomplished  through four parallel specific aims. 1. Characterization of the components of (and mechanism for controlling flux through) the natural extracellular electron transfer pathway of the cyanobacterium Synechocystis. 2. Construction of artificial systems to  abstract reducing equivalents from PSI; these will compete with natural electron acceptors only under highly reducing conditions. 3. Development of artificial means to move reducing equivalents out of the cytoplasm of Synechocystis. 4. Construction within microbes of artificial fuel-production modules that require only reducing equivalents and carbon dioxide as inputs. The project is highly interdisciplinary and will employ a range of techniques including those from microbiology, molecular biology, synthetic biology, biochemistry, electrochemistry, and protein and metabolic engineering.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award is supported jointly by the Cellular Dynamics and Function Cluster in the Division of Molecular and Cellular Biosciences and by the Biotechnology, Biochemical and Biomass Engineering Program in the Division of Chemical, Bioengineering, Environmental and Transport Systems.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>05/30/2014</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/30/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.074</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1359575</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Ichiro</FirstName>
<LastName>Matsumura</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Ichiro Matsumura</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>imatsum@emory.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>4047275625</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000327396</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/30/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Emory University</Name>
<CityName>Atlanta</CityName>
<ZipCode>303224250</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>4047272503</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1599 Clifton Rd NE, 4th Floor</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[1599-001-1BA]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Georgia</StateName>
<StateCode>GA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>GA05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>066469933</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>EMORY UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>066469933</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Emory University School of Medicine]]></Name>
<CityName>Atlanta</CityName>
<StateCode>GA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>303224218</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[1510 Clifton Road NE, room 4119]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Georgia</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>GA05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1114</Code>
<Text>Cellular Dynamics and Function</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>8015</Code>
<Text>BIO Innovation Activities</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1114</Code>
<Text>CELLULAR SYSTEMS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1228</Code>
<Text>MINORITY INVOLVEMENT -- BIO</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1757</Code>
<Text>Quantitative sys bio and biotech</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7465</Code>
<Text>NANOSCALE BIO CORE</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8007</Code>
<Text>BioMaPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8015</Code>
<Text>Research Ntwrks in Mathematical Sciences</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9178</Code>
<Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9179</Code>
<Text>GRADUATE INVOLVEMENT</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9183</Code>
<Text>GENERAL FOUNDATIONS OF BIOTECHNOLOGY</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0114</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~415620</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Synthetic biologists re-design living things to learn how biological systems work, and to create useful living "devices." The notion of engineer living systems may be worrying to some, but in actuality most of the recombinant bacterial strains reported cannot survive long outside of carefully controlled conditions in the laboratory. The original purpose of this project was to create a genetically modified bacteria that convert sunlight into energetic elections, which were then going to be transmitted to a second bacterium that would use the energy to create a liquid fuel. An international team of researchers from seven universities in the U.S. and U.K. was assembled, but it lacked the right tools and in-depth understanding natural biological electron transmission to complete the work.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>Some on the team learned more about natural systems while others developed better tools. Most synthetic biologists rely on "plasmids," which are circular mini-chromosomes that are easy to modify and replicate within bacteria. One problem with nearly all existing plasmids is that they don't survive long in a host bacteria unless an antibiotic is added to the growth medium. Another problem is that nearly all are detrimental to the health of the host cell. Since bacteria multiply quickly, it doesn't take long for mutations that improve the health of the cell at the expense of the recombinant plasmid to accumulate. These shortcomings limit the ability of synthetic biologists to scale up populations for genetically modified bacteria, or to use them to solve problems outside the laboratory.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>A new approach to plasmid design, called ribosome pegging, was developed. The ribosome is a highly abundant molecular machine that manufactures protein within the cell. The gene encoding one component was knocked out of the E. coli chromosome. A copy of the same gene was encoded on a plasmid, so that the bacterial strain was absolutely dependent upon the plasmid regardless of the presence or absence of antibiotic in the medium. When a foreign gene, a fluorescent red protein, was encoded on the same plasmid, the bacteria continued to fluoresce after 100 generations of growth. The ribosome pegging strategy could serve as an important step toward the dreams of synthetic biologists.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>The potential for undesirable outcomes was discussed at length by undergraduate students at Emory University, who presented the work at the International Genetically Engineered Machine Competition in October, 2018. The technology could someday add value to medicine, agriculture or industry. It could, however, cause harm to the environment or even people if it were applied thoughtlessly or maliciously. One shortcoming of science as it is practiced in the U.S. is that scientists, who are often relatively privileged, are making most of the decisions about which problems are most worth solving, A more inclusive decision-making process would lead to better outcomes.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 06/04/2019<br>      Modified by: Ichiro&nbsp;Matsumura</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Image         </div> <div class="galControls onePhoto" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation onePhoto" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1359575/1359575_10306180_1559682440628_ribosomepegging--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1359575/1359575_10306180_1559682440628_ribosomepegging--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Ribosome pegged plasmid"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1359575/1359575_10306180_1559682440628_ribosomepegging--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Ribosome pegged plasmid"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Bacterial colonies on left and right are nearly identical and transformed with the same plasmid. Those on the left are wild-type and those on the right are missing an essential gene encoded on the plasmid.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Ichiro Matsumura</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Royalty-free (unrestricted use)</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Ichiro&nbsp;Matsumura</div> <div class="imageTitle">Ribosome pegged plasmid</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Synthetic biologists re-design living things to learn how biological systems work, and to create useful living "devices." The notion of engineer living systems may be worrying to some, but in actuality most of the recombinant bacterial strains reported cannot survive long outside of carefully controlled conditions in the laboratory. The original purpose of this project was to create a genetically modified bacteria that convert sunlight into energetic elections, which were then going to be transmitted to a second bacterium that would use the energy to create a liquid fuel. An international team of researchers from seven universities in the U.S. and U.K. was assembled, but it lacked the right tools and in-depth understanding natural biological electron transmission to complete the work.     Some on the team learned more about natural systems while others developed better tools. Most synthetic biologists rely on "plasmids," which are circular mini-chromosomes that are easy to modify and replicate within bacteria. One problem with nearly all existing plasmids is that they don't survive long in a host bacteria unless an antibiotic is added to the growth medium. Another problem is that nearly all are detrimental to the health of the host cell. Since bacteria multiply quickly, it doesn't take long for mutations that improve the health of the cell at the expense of the recombinant plasmid to accumulate. These shortcomings limit the ability of synthetic biologists to scale up populations for genetically modified bacteria, or to use them to solve problems outside the laboratory.     A new approach to plasmid design, called ribosome pegging, was developed. The ribosome is a highly abundant molecular machine that manufactures protein within the cell. The gene encoding one component was knocked out of the E. coli chromosome. A copy of the same gene was encoded on a plasmid, so that the bacterial strain was absolutely dependent upon the plasmid regardless of the presence or absence of antibiotic in the medium. When a foreign gene, a fluorescent red protein, was encoded on the same plasmid, the bacteria continued to fluoresce after 100 generations of growth. The ribosome pegging strategy could serve as an important step toward the dreams of synthetic biologists.     The potential for undesirable outcomes was discussed at length by undergraduate students at Emory University, who presented the work at the International Genetically Engineered Machine Competition in October, 2018. The technology could someday add value to medicine, agriculture or industry. It could, however, cause harm to the environment or even people if it were applied thoughtlessly or maliciously. One shortcoming of science as it is practiced in the U.S. is that scientists, who are often relatively privileged, are making most of the decisions about which problems are most worth solving, A more inclusive decision-making process would lead to better outcomes.             Last Modified: 06/04/2019       Submitted by: Ichiro Matsumura]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
