<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Collaborative Research: RAPID: Short-and Long-term Sediment Dynamics Following Wildfire in Chaparral Environments</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/15/2013</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>02/28/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>16764.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>22866</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>06030206</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>GEO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>EAR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Earth Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Justin Lawrence</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>jlawrenc@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922425</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This RAPID project focuses on production and delivery of dry ravel, a characteristic and immediate post-fire response on steep slopes in the western USA. Dry ravel arises from a dry-season transport process whereby gravel sediment moving down hillslopes by gravity becomes trapped by vegetation. This material provides a significant sediment source into river channels after wildfire in chaparral environments. The investigators will quantify the volume of dry ravel sediment deposited along channel margins as a result of the Springs Fire that burned Big Sycamore Canyon in southern California during May 2013. Terrestrial laser scanning before and after the rainy season (which typically begins around October 1) will capture initial changes in landscape topography. These data will be augmented by field surveys. Data collected during the first post-fire year are important for developing models of the dynamics of dry ravel. The investigators have geomorphic data spanning over 25 years for Big Sycamore Canyon and two comparable basins nearby with different fire histories--a tributary to north fork Matilija Creek that burned completely during the July 1985 Wheeler Fire-- and a tributary to Malibu Creek that has remained unburned. Comparing dry ravel processes at these three sites will enable a direct comparison of both short- and long-term sediment dynamics following wildfire in chaparral environments. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Developing a predictive understanding of both short- and long-term effects of wildfire is critical, especially in an era of changing climate that has increased frequencies and magnitudes of wildfires. Yet, accurately predicting post-fire effects remains elusive, and physically-based models of post-fire runoff and erosion are still being developed. The proposed project will integrate research and education by involving undergraduate students from California State University, Channel Islands (CSUCI). These students will pursue their capstone undergraduate coursework while assisting the PIs with field data collection and analysis. Two of these students are participants of the Hispanic-Serving Institutes ACCESO (Achieving a Cooperative College Education Through STEM Opportunities) Research Assistant Program on the CSUCI campus. These students will receive valuable research experiences including training in use of cutting-edge technologies.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>09/10/2013</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>03/09/2015</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.050</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1359734</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Joan</FirstName>
<LastName>Florsheim</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Joan Florsheim</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>florsheim@eri.ucsb.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>4153899461</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000640311</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/10/2013</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of California-Santa Barbara</Name>
<CityName>Santa Barbara</CityName>
<ZipCode>931062050</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>8058934188</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>Office of Research</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[Rm 3227 Cheadle Hall]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>24</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CA24</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>094878394</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF CALIFORNIA, SANTA BARBARA</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>071549000</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of California-Santa Barbara]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>931062050</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>24</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CA24</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1579</Code>
<Text>Hydrologic Sciences</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7458</Code>
<Text>Geomorphology &amp; Land-use Dynam</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7914</Code>
<Text>RAPID</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0113</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0115</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2013~16764</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2015~6102</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Wildfire transforms the physical and biological elements of watersheds causing impacts to people and the environment they live in.&nbsp; Because fire has become more frequent in the western United States, and because more people live in fire-prone areas, improved scientific predictions about the effects of wildfire are needed to guide emergency management efforts.&nbsp; One significant effect of wildfire in steep mountainous areas is the loss of vegetation and the resulting increase in erosion from hillslopes and the associated impacts to stream channels.&nbsp; Our research filled a critical gap in knowledge regarding the<strong> </strong>magnitude and importance of &ldquo;dry-ravel,&rdquo; an erosion process whereby gravel-sized sediment moving down hillslopes by gravity is trapped by vegetation. &nbsp;After wildfire burns the vegetation that had previously stabilized this sediment on the hillslopes, dry ravel delivers a significant sediment source to the margins of stream channels in steep, semi-arid Mediterranean environments.&nbsp; Dry ravel is pervasive on steep hillslopes in southern California&rsquo;s chaparral environments during and immediately after wildfires&mdash;but before winter rains occur. &nbsp;Storm flows that occur after measurable rain falls during the post-fire wet season generate stream flows that mobilize this gravel sediment supply poised at the base of hillslopes and transport it downstream.&nbsp; This NSF RAPID project enabled measurements to document short-term post-fire effects of dry ravel during the winter following the 2013 Springs Fire in Big Sycamore Canyon, in the steep southern California Transverse Ranges.&nbsp; We conducted two field campaigns after the fire (before and after the small 28Feb &ndash; Mar 2014 storm) including longitudinal profile and cross section surveys, measurement of sediment grain size distributions, and Terrestrial LiDAR scanning in Big Sycamore Creek.&nbsp; The comparison of the before and after storm datasets quantified a dramatic channel transformation.&nbsp; Even the small 28Feb &ndash; Mar 2014 storm flow initiated transport of the post-fire sediment pulse derived from dry ravel.&nbsp; Sediment dynamics in the channel led to burying of the step-like channel morphology and aquatic habitat, including the filling of pools, before streamflow receded in Big Sycamore Creek. The resulting significant geomorphic change and ecological disturbance persisted for several more years because stream flows during the following winters through California&rsquo;s continued drought were not sufficient to transport the large volume of fire-related sediment supplied from the hillslopes and tributaries downstream and out of Big Sycamore Creek. &nbsp;Simultaneous field data collection in two nearby chaparral streams that burned decades ago showed no significant geomorphic changes during the same 28Feb &ndash; Mar 2014 storm that transformed Big Sycamore Creek.&nbsp; This result highlights the important short-term stream channel response to dry ravel processes initiated by wildfire, in contrast to longer-term sediment dynamics in systems where vegetation and geomorphic hillslope recovery have already taken place over decades. &nbsp;Understanding both the short-term and longer-term perspectives is critical in linking cause and effect mechanisms and in developing models that predict how wildfire impacts Earth surface processes in the context of landscape evolution. &nbsp;In addition, results showed that drought lengthens the short-term post-wildfire geomorphic recovery period in stream channels, with significant impacts to aquatic ecology. &nbsp;The project offered training of undergraduate students in field and analytical methods, strengthened collaboration between academic institutions and governmental agencies, and provided knowledge that will advance post-wildfire hazard management.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 04/18/2017<br>      Modified by: Joan&nbsp;Florsheim</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Wildfire transforms the physical and biological elements of watersheds causing impacts to people and the environment they live in.  Because fire has become more frequent in the western United States, and because more people live in fire-prone areas, improved scientific predictions about the effects of wildfire are needed to guide emergency management efforts.  One significant effect of wildfire in steep mountainous areas is the loss of vegetation and the resulting increase in erosion from hillslopes and the associated impacts to stream channels.  Our research filled a critical gap in knowledge regarding the magnitude and importance of "dry-ravel," an erosion process whereby gravel-sized sediment moving down hillslopes by gravity is trapped by vegetation.  After wildfire burns the vegetation that had previously stabilized this sediment on the hillslopes, dry ravel delivers a significant sediment source to the margins of stream channels in steep, semi-arid Mediterranean environments.  Dry ravel is pervasive on steep hillslopes in southern California?s chaparral environments during and immediately after wildfires&mdash;but before winter rains occur.  Storm flows that occur after measurable rain falls during the post-fire wet season generate stream flows that mobilize this gravel sediment supply poised at the base of hillslopes and transport it downstream.  This NSF RAPID project enabled measurements to document short-term post-fire effects of dry ravel during the winter following the 2013 Springs Fire in Big Sycamore Canyon, in the steep southern California Transverse Ranges.  We conducted two field campaigns after the fire (before and after the small 28Feb &ndash; Mar 2014 storm) including longitudinal profile and cross section surveys, measurement of sediment grain size distributions, and Terrestrial LiDAR scanning in Big Sycamore Creek.  The comparison of the before and after storm datasets quantified a dramatic channel transformation.  Even the small 28Feb &ndash; Mar 2014 storm flow initiated transport of the post-fire sediment pulse derived from dry ravel.  Sediment dynamics in the channel led to burying of the step-like channel morphology and aquatic habitat, including the filling of pools, before streamflow receded in Big Sycamore Creek. The resulting significant geomorphic change and ecological disturbance persisted for several more years because stream flows during the following winters through California?s continued drought were not sufficient to transport the large volume of fire-related sediment supplied from the hillslopes and tributaries downstream and out of Big Sycamore Creek.  Simultaneous field data collection in two nearby chaparral streams that burned decades ago showed no significant geomorphic changes during the same 28Feb &ndash; Mar 2014 storm that transformed Big Sycamore Creek.  This result highlights the important short-term stream channel response to dry ravel processes initiated by wildfire, in contrast to longer-term sediment dynamics in systems where vegetation and geomorphic hillslope recovery have already taken place over decades.  Understanding both the short-term and longer-term perspectives is critical in linking cause and effect mechanisms and in developing models that predict how wildfire impacts Earth surface processes in the context of landscape evolution.  In addition, results showed that drought lengthens the short-term post-wildfire geomorphic recovery period in stream channels, with significant impacts to aquatic ecology.  The project offered training of undergraduate students in field and analytical methods, strengthened collaboration between academic institutions and governmental agencies, and provided knowledge that will advance post-wildfire hazard management.          Last Modified: 04/18/2017       Submitted by: Joan Florsheim]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
