<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Africa's Endangered Languages: Documentary and Theoretical Approaches</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>01/01/2014</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2015</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>24601.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>30601</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>04040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>SBE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>BCS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Behavioral and Cognitive Sci</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Colleen M. Fitzgerald</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The state of language endangerment in sub-Saharan Africa is distinct from much of the rest of the world, typified by threatened languages distributed across several geographically distinct regions of the continent and internal pressures rather than external factors driving endangerment. As such, African language endangerment has great potential to provide fresh perspectives on and valuable new insights into the questions of how and why languages erode.  Furthermore, Africa's endangered languages pose several unique challenges to documentation efforts. Insufficient infrastructure, scarcity of resources, incomplete and/or inaccurate information, and a general absence of public awareness (locally and internationally), for example, provide serious hurdles for the documentation and maintenance of threatened languages in most regions. However, because the threat level of language endangerment in Africa has been characterized as low, research on and funding opportunities for endangered African languages are often perceived as less urgent. Consequently, a disproportionate amount of funding and research is devoted to the study of endangered African languages than any other linguistically threatened region in the world.  &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This grant supports a special conference workshop entitled "Africa's Endangered Languages: Documentary and Theoretical Approaches," to be held at the University of Kansas in conjunction with the 45th Annual Conference on African Linguistics.  The workshop seeks to stimulate and enhance the visibility of endangered African language research in the hopes of reversing this trend and bringing the unique insights and perspectives afforded by African language endangerment to bear on the fields of language documentation and endangered language research. The workshop will emphasize the synergistic relationship between documentation and linguistic theory in endangered African language research. Thus, it will serve a crucial role in catalyzing a deeper and more collaborative relationship between documentary and theoretical linguists for the purpose of growing, maintaining, and sustaining research efforts to document and preserve Africa's endangered languages.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>12/16/2013</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>04/11/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.075</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1360823</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Harold</FirstName>
<LastName>Torrence</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Harold Torrence</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>torrence@ku.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>7858642882</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000572980</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>12/16/2013</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Jason</FirstName>
<LastName>Kandybowicz</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Jason Kandybowicz</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>jkandybowicz@gc.cuny.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2128178503</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000573643</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>12/16/2013</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Kansas Center for Research Inc</Name>
<CityName>Lawrence</CityName>
<ZipCode>660457552</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>7858643441</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>2385 IRVING HILL RD</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Kansas</StateName>
<StateCode>KS</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>KS02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>076248616</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF KANSAS CENTER FOR RESEARCH, INC.</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>007180078</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Kansas Center for Research Inc]]></Name>
<CityName>Lawrence</CityName>
<StateCode>KS</StateCode>
<ZipCode>660457568</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[2385 IRVING HILL RD]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Kansas</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>KS02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1311</Code>
<Text>Linguistics</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7719</Code>
<Text>DEL</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1311</Code>
<Text>LINGUISTICS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7556</Code>
<Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7719</Code>
<Text>DEL</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>SMET</Code>
<Text>SCIENCE, MATH, ENG &amp; TECH EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0114</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~30601</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>This grant funded a three-day workshop at the University of Kansas entitled &ldquo;Africa&rsquo;s Endangered Languages: Documentary and Theoretical Approaches&rdquo;, which was held in conjunction with the 45<sup>th</sup> Annual Conference on African Linguistics (ACAL 45).&nbsp;&nbsp; The three-day workshop, with 38 presentations by 56 scholars, was funded by a grant from the National Science Foundation (BCS DEL 1360823).&nbsp; The organizing team consisted of Drs. Jason Kandybowicz and Harold Torrence, along with University of Kansas Linguistics graduate students Travis Major, Ibrahima Ba, and Mfon Udoinyang.&nbsp; Dr. Carlos Nash from the University of Kansas department of Anthropology provided critical technical support.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>The major objective of the endangered languages workshop was to facilitate synergistic partnerships between documentary and theoretical/formal linguists working on endangered African languages.&nbsp; The workshop was based on the idea of showing how documentation and description of endangered languages can contribute to linguistic theory and how theoretical analysis can enrich documentation and description of endangered languages by pushing field linguists to obtain the kinds of data that might not typically be sought/found in descriptive or documentary work. By bringing together both documentarians and theoreticians, the workshop presentations also highlighted the ways in which language endangerment&nbsp; in Africa, with its very high multilingualism and long-term language contact, is different from language endangerment in other parts of the world.&nbsp; Unlike most other regions, the greatest threat to minority African languages comes from other local/subnational African languages, not colonial languages like English or French.&nbsp; In addition, mass migration and cyclic immigration have put internal pressure on minority languages across Africa.&nbsp; Thus, Africa presents a unique situation of language endangerment.&nbsp; Because of this, examination of the situation in Africa provides fresh insight in the causes and consequences of human language endangerment.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>The talks given in the workshop covered a wide range of topics including phonetics (sounds), phonology (sound systems), morphology (word structure), syntax (sentence structure), semantics (meaning), sociolinguistics, and historical linguistics. The workshop featured talks from six plenary speakers, all field linguists, drawn from a variety of specializations.&nbsp; In his plenary, Dr. Kofi Agyekum (University of Ghana-Legon) focused on the interaction of sociolinguistic theory, language policy, and documentary linguistics (&ldquo;Decolonising Linguistic Imperialism in Africa through Documentation and Preservation&rdquo;).&nbsp; Dr. Chris Collins (New York University) presented &ldquo;The Linker in the Khoisan Languages&rdquo;, which summarized aspects of his long-running research on the linker systems of the highly endangered southern Khoisan languages.&nbsp; Dr. Michael Marlo (University of Missouri) spoke on his fieldwork on &ldquo;The Exceptional Properties of the 1<sup>st</sup> SG and Reflexive Object Markers in Bantu&rdquo;.&nbsp; Dr. Carlos Nash (University of Kansas) discussed his ongoing community-driven documentation project in &ldquo;Working with the Abagusii of Kenya:&nbsp; Applying an &lsquo;Empowering&rsquo; Research Model to Linguistic Fieldwork&rdquo;.&nbsp; Dr. Bonny Sands (Northern Arizona University) addressed the synergistic focus of the conference in &ldquo;The Challenge(s) of Documenting Africa&rsquo;s Least Known Languages&rdquo;.&nbsp; Dr. Malte Zimmermann (Universit&auml;t Potsdam) discussed semantic fieldwork on endangered African languages in &ldquo;Universal and Existential Quantifiers in Chadic and Beyond&rdquo;. &nbsp;The grant (together with its Supplement - BCS DEL 1439970) also provided travel funds for one dom...]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ This grant funded a three-day workshop at the University of Kansas entitled "AfricaÆs Endangered Languages: Documentary and Theoretical Approaches", which was held in conjunction with the 45th Annual Conference on African Linguistics (ACAL 45).   The three-day workshop, with 38 presentations by 56 scholars, was funded by a grant from the National Science Foundation (BCS DEL 1360823).  The organizing team consisted of Drs. Jason Kandybowicz and Harold Torrence, along with University of Kansas Linguistics graduate students Travis Major, Ibrahima Ba, and Mfon Udoinyang.  Dr. Carlos Nash from the University of Kansas department of Anthropology provided critical technical support.     The major objective of the endangered languages workshop was to facilitate synergistic partnerships between documentary and theoretical/formal linguists working on endangered African languages.  The workshop was based on the idea of showing how documentation and description of endangered languages can contribute to linguistic theory and how theoretical analysis can enrich documentation and description of endangered languages by pushing field linguists to obtain the kinds of data that might not typically be sought/found in descriptive or documentary work. By bringing together both documentarians and theoreticians, the workshop presentations also highlighted the ways in which language endangerment  in Africa, with its very high multilingualism and long-term language contact, is different from language endangerment in other parts of the world.  Unlike most other regions, the greatest threat to minority African languages comes from other local/subnational African languages, not colonial languages like English or French.  In addition, mass migration and cyclic immigration have put internal pressure on minority languages across Africa.  Thus, Africa presents a unique situation of language endangerment.  Because of this, examination of the situation in Africa provides fresh insight in the causes and consequences of human language endangerment.     The talks given in the workshop covered a wide range of topics including phonetics (sounds), phonology (sound systems), morphology (word structure), syntax (sentence structure), semantics (meaning), sociolinguistics, and historical linguistics. The workshop featured talks from six plenary speakers, all field linguists, drawn from a variety of specializations.  In his plenary, Dr. Kofi Agyekum (University of Ghana-Legon) focused on the interaction of sociolinguistic theory, language policy, and documentary linguistics ("Decolonising Linguistic Imperialism in Africa through Documentation and Preservation").  Dr. Chris Collins (New York University) presented "The Linker in the Khoisan Languages", which summarized aspects of his long-running research on the linker systems of the highly endangered southern Khoisan languages.  Dr. Michael Marlo (University of Missouri) spoke on his fieldwork on "The Exceptional Properties of the 1st SG and Reflexive Object Markers in Bantu".  Dr. Carlos Nash (University of Kansas) discussed his ongoing community-driven documentation project in "Working with the Abagusii of Kenya:  Applying an æEmpoweringÆ Research Model to Linguistic Fieldwork".  Dr. Bonny Sands (Northern Arizona University) addressed the synergistic focus of the conference in "The Challenge(s) of Documenting AfricaÆs Least Known Languages".  Dr. Malte Zimmermann (Universit&auml;t Potsdam) discussed semantic fieldwork on endangered African languages in "Universal and Existential Quantifiers in Chadic and Beyond".  The grant (together with its Supplement - BCS DEL 1439970) also provided travel funds for one domestic and 15 international graduate Linguistics students to attend the workshop and present their work.     A particularly important aspect of the workshop was that it included a session that was designed to increase awareness of language endangerment in Africa for undergraduate students, who typically do not recei...]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
