<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Collaborative Research: AGNES: Algebraic Geometry NorthEastern Series, April 25-27, 2014</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>04/01/2014</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>03/31/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>33548.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>33548</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DMS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>James Matthew Douglass</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>mdouglas@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922467</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This project will support six semiannual AGNES weekend workshops in Algebraic Geometry, the first of which is to be held at Stony Brook University, April 25 - 27, 2014. Algebraic geometry is a dynamic subject with vital connections to physics, applied mathematics, and fields such as number theory, differential geometry and representation theory. The Northeastern United States are a particular nexus, with a density of researchers and an output rivaling any region in the world. AGNES weekend workshops bring together a spectrum of algebraic geometers from the region and beyond, as well as representatives from allied fields invigorating algebraic geometry. There is diversity both in speakers and participants, from senior experts to burgeoning young researchers. There is a special emphasis on students: AGNES hosts "students-only" introductory pre-talks, as well as professional development sessions. Through lectures, panels, problem sessions, poster sessions, and informal discussion periods, AGNES informs the community of developments, AGNES fosters new research collaborations, and AGNES trains junior algebraic geometers.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Algebraic geometers study the geometry of shapes defined by the polynomial equations of Algebra. In fact, the geometric shapes occurring in nature -- in science, in engineering, etc. -- are frequently "algebraic", explaining the vital importance of algebraic geometry in physics and applied mathematics. This grant promotes research, dissemination and training in algebraic geometry through a series of conferences held throughout the Northeastern United States. There is an emphasis on supporting graduate students, highlighting the broad array of work in the area and its many connections to allied areas, and fostering communication in our broad research community.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;AGNES website is available at http://www.agneshome.org/</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>04/03/2014</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/04/2015</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1360598</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Dawei</FirstName>
<LastName>Chen</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Dawei Chen</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>dawei.chen@bc.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6175523755</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000511957</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/03/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Maksym</FirstName>
<LastName>Fedorchuk</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Maksym Fedorchuk</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>maksym.fedorchuk@bc.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6175523757</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000574412</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/03/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Boston College</Name>
<CityName>Chestnut Hill</CityName>
<ZipCode>024673800</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6175528000</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>140 Commonwealth Avenue</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
<StateCode>MA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MA04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>045896339</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>TRUSTEES OF BOSTON COLLEGE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>045896339</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Boston College]]></Name>
<CityName>Chestnut Hill</CityName>
<StateCode>MA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>024673800</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[140 Commonwealth Avenue]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MA04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1264</Code>
<Text>ALGEBRA,NUMBER THEORY,AND COM</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7556</Code>
<Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0114</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0115</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~200</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2015~33348</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>This grant supported a Spring 2015 meeting of AGNES (Algebraic Geometry North-Eastern Series) held at Boston College in March 20-22, 2015. AGNES is a series of semiannual conferences that alternate between a number of the Northeastern universities with a specific goal of familiarizing and involving graduate students with cutting edge research in algebraic geometry. The majority of AGNES participants are graduate students and the conference is designed to maximize their benefit. This is done through introductory <span><span>pre</span></span>-talks, open problem sessions, poster sessions, and, on more inf<span><span>ormal</span></span> level, by giving students access to established senior researchers. In the past <span><span>se</span></span><span><span>veral</span></span> years, AGNES has created a vibrant algebraic geometry community that has cultivated a great number of young researchers.</p> <p>The Spring 2015 meeting featured 8 research talks covering a wide range of topics in algebraic geometry and neighboring areas.&nbsp; Titles, abstracts, and links to the videos of the talks can be found at the conference website: <span><span>http</span></span>://<span><span>www</span></span>.<span><span>agneshome</span></span>.<span><span>org</span></span>/<span><span>boston</span></span>-college-2015</p> <p>A novel feature of this AGNES meeting was a mini-school for graduate<br />students that was held on Friday preceding the main conference. With over 60 students attending 4 lectures by prominent Boston-based algebraic geometers, the mini-school has been the largest AGNES-related event aimed exclusively at graduate students.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 07/11/2017<br>      Modified by: Maksym&nbsp;Fedorchuk</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ This grant supported a Spring 2015 meeting of AGNES (Algebraic Geometry North-Eastern Series) held at Boston College in March 20-22, 2015. AGNES is a series of semiannual conferences that alternate between a number of the Northeastern universities with a specific goal of familiarizing and involving graduate students with cutting edge research in algebraic geometry. The majority of AGNES participants are graduate students and the conference is designed to maximize their benefit. This is done through introductory pre-talks, open problem sessions, poster sessions, and, on more informal level, by giving students access to established senior researchers. In the past several years, AGNES has created a vibrant algebraic geometry community that has cultivated a great number of young researchers.  The Spring 2015 meeting featured 8 research talks covering a wide range of topics in algebraic geometry and neighboring areas.  Titles, abstracts, and links to the videos of the talks can be found at the conference website: http://www.agneshome.org/boston-college-2015  A novel feature of this AGNES meeting was a mini-school for graduate students that was held on Friday preceding the main conference. With over 60 students attending 4 lectures by prominent Boston-based algebraic geometers, the mini-school has been the largest AGNES-related event aimed exclusively at graduate students.       Last Modified: 07/11/2017       Submitted by: Maksym Fedorchuk]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
