<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Laser Excitation of the 229-Th Nuclear Isomer</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2013</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>440000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>440000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03010000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>PHY</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Physics</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>John D. Gillaspy</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>jgillasp@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927173</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>While typical nuclear excitation energies are in the keV to MeV range, there are several exceptional cases where the excitation energies are much lower. The subject of this project is the thorium-229 isotope, which, uniquely, has an excited state in the UV optical spectrum. Several experimental searches for optical emission in this range undertaken in the past ten years were unsuccessful or inconclusive. In addition to searching in the wrong energy region, the searches were challenged by the narrow linewidth of the nuclear transition. In this work, an alternative electron-bridge transition will be employed for the initial laser excitation of the nuclear isomer level in thorium-229. The nuclear transition is likely to be exceptionally sensitive to the variation of fundamental constants, due to the interplay of the strong and electroweak interactions inside this nucleus. After the isomer level is found, the sensitivity of the nuclear transition to time variation of the fine structure constant will be determined.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This research will have broad impact across several areas of physics and technology. Laser excitation and coherent manipulation of nuclear states would establish a new bridge between atomic and nuclear physics, with the promise of new levels of accuracy for frequency metrology. The project will involve extensive graduate and undergraduate student training and participation.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>09/16/2013</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/02/2015</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1360546</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Alex</FirstName>
<LastName>Kuzmich</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>M</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Alex M Kuzmich</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>akuzmich@umich.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>4045094099</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000488754</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/16/2013</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Regents of the University of Michigan - Ann Arbor</Name>
<CityName>Ann Arbor</CityName>
<ZipCode>481091274</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>7347636438</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>3003 South State St. Room 1062</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Michigan</StateName>
<StateCode>MI</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>12</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MI12</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>073133571</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>REGENTS OF THE UNIVERSITY OF MICHIGAN</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>073133571</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Michigan Ann Arbor]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>MI</StateCode>
<ZipCode>481091271</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Michigan</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>12</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MI12</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1234</Code>
<Text>NUCLEAR PRECISION MEASUREMENTS</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1289</Code>
<Text>PRECISION MEASUREMENTS</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7244</Code>
<Text>COMPUTATIONAL PHYSICS</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7282</Code>
<Text>Midscale Physics Projects</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7553</Code>
<Text>PHYSICS AT THE INFO FRONTIER</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1289</Code>
<Text>PRECISION MEASUREMENTS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0113</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0114</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0115</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2013~288459</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~131541</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2015~20000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Atomic nuclei usually possess excitation energies in the keV to MeV range. However, there are a few known nuclides where the energies of lowest excited levels lie in the sub-100 eV range. In the remarkable case of the 229Th nucleus, the energy splitting of the ground state doublet is only several eV, which may be within the reach of coherent table-top (UV) lasers. The excited state decays via photon emission, with a predicted lifetime of <em>&sim;</em>5 hr. Next to 229Th, the lowest known energy of a nuclear excited state is 76.8 eV for 235U. This makes 229Th unique in having a nuclear excitation energy commensurate with electronic and optical energy scales.</p> <p>This NSF-sponsored research program has investigated possibilities for laser excitation of the isomer transition using trapped and laser cooled 229Th3+.&nbsp;Specifically, excitation of the ions into the isomer (229mTh3+) manifold by a multi-photon laser excitation process has been explored. The mechanism relies on the so-called electron bridge between the nuclear ground and the nuclear isomer electron level manifolds. The bridge arises due to hyperfine-like electron-nucleus interaction.</p> <p>Main results include a) developed protocols for fast and reliable production, trapping, and cooling of Thorium ions, b) proposeda four-photon scheme of the nuclear isomer excitation using optical parametric oscillators, and c) the magnetic dipole and the electric quadrupole moments of the 229Th nucleus have been determined.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 12/16/2018<br>      Modified by: Alex&nbsp;M&nbsp;Kuzmich</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Atomic nuclei usually possess excitation energies in the keV to MeV range. However, there are a few known nuclides where the energies of lowest excited levels lie in the sub-100 eV range. In the remarkable case of the 229Th nucleus, the energy splitting of the ground state doublet is only several eV, which may be within the reach of coherent table-top (UV) lasers. The excited state decays via photon emission, with a predicted lifetime of &sim;5 hr. Next to 229Th, the lowest known energy of a nuclear excited state is 76.8 eV for 235U. This makes 229Th unique in having a nuclear excitation energy commensurate with electronic and optical energy scales.  This NSF-sponsored research program has investigated possibilities for laser excitation of the isomer transition using trapped and laser cooled 229Th3+. Specifically, excitation of the ions into the isomer (229mTh3+) manifold by a multi-photon laser excitation process has been explored. The mechanism relies on the so-called electron bridge between the nuclear ground and the nuclear isomer electron level manifolds. The bridge arises due to hyperfine-like electron-nucleus interaction.  Main results include a) developed protocols for fast and reliable production, trapping, and cooling of Thorium ions, b) proposeda four-photon scheme of the nuclear isomer excitation using optical parametric oscillators, and c) the magnetic dipole and the electric quadrupole moments of the 229Th nucleus have been determined.             Last Modified: 12/16/2018       Submitted by: Alex M Kuzmich]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
