<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Mechanisms of Photochemical Reactions -- Emphasis on Biochemically Significant Molecules</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2014</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2020</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>300000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>300000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03090000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CHE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Chemistry</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Tingyu Li</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>tli@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924949</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>In this project funded by the Chemical Structure, Dynamics and Mechanisms-B Program of the Chemistry Division, Professor Jack Saltiel of The Florida State University is determining the response of molecules of biological interest to excitation by light absorption. The research focuses on (i) processes involved in the photobiological and industrial formation of vitamin Ds, (ii) the photochemical properties of resveratrol, a molecule found in the skin of grapes that has many medicinal qualities and is thought to be responsible for the "French Paradox", the beneficial effect of wine drinking, and (iii) the chemical behavior of certain arylacetylenes that are attractive candidates for use in light induced cancer cell death. The research is performed by students at all levels and Professor Jack Saltiel has a proven record of attracting many of them to highly successful scientific careers.&lt;br/&gt; &lt;br/&gt;Findings from this project provide the experimental foundations which test theoretical predictions of the behavior of electronically excited states. The theory of electronically excited states is a scientific frontier whose progress relies on valid experimental conclusions such as those provided by this project.  Sophisticated computer-based quantitative chemometrics analyses of spectral matrices are being developed which are widely applicable in chemical research. Detection of resveratrol photo products in nature has medicinal implications. Research on the arylpyridylacetylenes is in collaboration with Professor Igor Alabugin whose research group has synthesized them and shown them to be highly effective as DNA double strand photocleavers.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/23/2014</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/14/2019</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1361962</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Jack</FirstName>
<LastName>Saltiel</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Jack Saltiel</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>saltiel@chem.fsu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>8506445405</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000373053</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/23/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Florida State University</Name>
<CityName>TALLAHASSEE</CityName>
<ZipCode>323064166</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>8506445260</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>874 Traditions Way, 3rd Floor</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Florida</StateName>
<StateCode>FL</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>FL02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>790877419</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>FLORIDA STATE UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>159621697</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Florida State University]]></Name>
<CityName>Tallahassee</CityName>
<StateCode>FL</StateCode>
<ZipCode>323064390</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[95 Chieftan Way]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Florida</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>FL02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>9102</Code>
<Text>Chem Struct,Dynmcs&amp;Mechansms B</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0114</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~300000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Outcomes of our work are in two major areas: (1) expanding scientific knowledge and (2) teaching co-workers the skills needed in achieving (1).</p> <p>We seek a detailed understanding of the chemical changes that molecules undergo when light absorption energizes them (photochemistry). Major biological consequences of light absorption are vision and vitamin D formation in the skin. In vision the energy of light changes the geometry of a specific molecule in a protein environment - rhodopsin - through rotation about a double bond that is normally rigid and in vitamin D formation provitamin D, a steroid molecule related to cholesterol, utilizes light energy to break open a carbon ring. I will concentrate on outcomes accomplished with the support of this NSF grant that have led to a better understanding of the photochemistry of vision and of molecules related to vitamin D. We have corrected misconceptions, tested theoretical predictions and provided sound experimental benchmarks for the use of theoreticians in improving their theories.&nbsp; &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;</p> <p>Light induced bond rotation: (1) We verified the recent theoretical prediction that the partially rotated high energy intermediate undergoes charge separation such that one of the carbon atoms of the rotating bond becomes positive and the other becomes negative. (2) Of great scientific interest is achieving an understanding of how a bond rotation that superficially involves a large free volume demanding geometric change can occur when the space available to a molecule is restricted by a highly viscous medium, or by a protein environment. Our research showed that molecules minimize the required free space by undergoing simultaneous rotation about two double bonds in a way reminiscent of the motion of bicycle pedals. We observed such bicycle pedal motion in organic glasses at 77 K, and at room temperature in molecular crystals and even in fluid solution. Work supported by this grant, provided experimental verification of the bicycle pedal explanation that Ariel Warshel advanced in 1976.</p> <p>Photochemistry in the vitamin D field: (1) Through ring opening of a six membered carbon ring in provitamin D, a steroid relative of cholesterol, light energy produces previtamin D, the immediate precursor to vitamin D. Conversion of the previtamin to the vitamin is very efficient in the skin. However, in organic solvents used in the industrially important synthesis of vitamin D, much more efficient is the light induced rotation that converts the previtamin to tachysterol. The way this happens in volume confining environments is a topic of current scientific controversy. Our experimental evidence shows that in organic glasses a recent popular explanation involving rotation about two adjacent bonds is not valid. (2) In addition to studying the photochemistry of previtamin D directly, we studied the simplest molecule that possesses the light absorbing portion of previtamin D. We showed that earlier results indicating that molecule to be photochemically inactive are in error. The molecule is highly responsive to light excitation in an unexpected way. Our observations should stimulate theoretical advances because previous theoretical studies had failed to predict its behavior. (3) In seeking a green synthesis of vitamin D, we showed that irradiation of provitamin D in the solid state can lead to reaction with molecular oxygen. This was at first puzzling because it occurred with light that was not absorbed by the provitamin. Light absorption by a molecule with an extra double bond ? a Trienol, present in provitamin D as a minor impurity led to formation of the active form of oxygen. This discovery may have serious implications for the shelf life of drugs. (3) Another property of this Trienol is that it emits light ? it fluoresces ? when it absorbs light energy. Because its structure is very similar to that of cholesterol, it travels in the body with cholesterol. When added to cholesterol, its ability to emit light reveals the presence of cholesterol. Therefore, it has been used to reveal the location of cholesterol as it moves through the body ? cholesterol trafficking. Such studies have ignored the possible formation of toxic photoproducts. We identified the two main photoproducts. One involves a rearrangement of the Trienol bonds and the other involves addition of molecular oxygen to form a cytotoxic peroxide. The possible toxicity of the rearrangement product remains to be explored. &nbsp;</p> <p>This research was described in 13 publications and in 5 invited and 14 contributed presentations at scientific conferences. Three postdoctoral fellows, two graduate students, nineteen undergraduate students, and two high school students carried out this research. Undergraduate students co-authored 8 of the 13 publications and the two high school students co-authored 1. Many of the participants have gone on to graduate schools and to medical schools. A measure of the high regard of the scientific community for our research is my having been awarded the 2018 Josef Michl ACS Award in Photochemistry.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 08/04/2020<br>      Modified by: Jack&nbsp;Saltiel</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Outcomes of our work are in two major areas: (1) expanding scientific knowledge and (2) teaching co-workers the skills needed in achieving (1).  We seek a detailed understanding of the chemical changes that molecules undergo when light absorption energizes them (photochemistry). Major biological consequences of light absorption are vision and vitamin D formation in the skin. In vision the energy of light changes the geometry of a specific molecule in a protein environment - rhodopsin - through rotation about a double bond that is normally rigid and in vitamin D formation provitamin D, a steroid molecule related to cholesterol, utilizes light energy to break open a carbon ring. I will concentrate on outcomes accomplished with the support of this NSF grant that have led to a better understanding of the photochemistry of vision and of molecules related to vitamin D. We have corrected misconceptions, tested theoretical predictions and provided sound experimental benchmarks for the use of theoreticians in improving their theories.        Light induced bond rotation: (1) We verified the recent theoretical prediction that the partially rotated high energy intermediate undergoes charge separation such that one of the carbon atoms of the rotating bond becomes positive and the other becomes negative. (2) Of great scientific interest is achieving an understanding of how a bond rotation that superficially involves a large free volume demanding geometric change can occur when the space available to a molecule is restricted by a highly viscous medium, or by a protein environment. Our research showed that molecules minimize the required free space by undergoing simultaneous rotation about two double bonds in a way reminiscent of the motion of bicycle pedals. We observed such bicycle pedal motion in organic glasses at 77 K, and at room temperature in molecular crystals and even in fluid solution. Work supported by this grant, provided experimental verification of the bicycle pedal explanation that Ariel Warshel advanced in 1976.  Photochemistry in the vitamin D field: (1) Through ring opening of a six membered carbon ring in provitamin D, a steroid relative of cholesterol, light energy produces previtamin D, the immediate precursor to vitamin D. Conversion of the previtamin to the vitamin is very efficient in the skin. However, in organic solvents used in the industrially important synthesis of vitamin D, much more efficient is the light induced rotation that converts the previtamin to tachysterol. The way this happens in volume confining environments is a topic of current scientific controversy. Our experimental evidence shows that in organic glasses a recent popular explanation involving rotation about two adjacent bonds is not valid. (2) In addition to studying the photochemistry of previtamin D directly, we studied the simplest molecule that possesses the light absorbing portion of previtamin D. We showed that earlier results indicating that molecule to be photochemically inactive are in error. The molecule is highly responsive to light excitation in an unexpected way. Our observations should stimulate theoretical advances because previous theoretical studies had failed to predict its behavior. (3) In seeking a green synthesis of vitamin D, we showed that irradiation of provitamin D in the solid state can lead to reaction with molecular oxygen. This was at first puzzling because it occurred with light that was not absorbed by the provitamin. Light absorption by a molecule with an extra double bond ? a Trienol, present in provitamin D as a minor impurity led to formation of the active form of oxygen. This discovery may have serious implications for the shelf life of drugs. (3) Another property of this Trienol is that it emits light ? it fluoresces ? when it absorbs light energy. Because its structure is very similar to that of cholesterol, it travels in the body with cholesterol. When added to cholesterol, its ability to emit light reveals the presence of cholesterol. Therefore, it has been used to reveal the location of cholesterol as it moves through the body ? cholesterol trafficking. Such studies have ignored the possible formation of toxic photoproducts. We identified the two main photoproducts. One involves a rearrangement of the Trienol bonds and the other involves addition of molecular oxygen to form a cytotoxic peroxide. The possible toxicity of the rearrangement product remains to be explored.    This research was described in 13 publications and in 5 invited and 14 contributed presentations at scientific conferences. Three postdoctoral fellows, two graduate students, nineteen undergraduate students, and two high school students carried out this research. Undergraduate students co-authored 8 of the 13 publications and the two high school students co-authored 1. Many of the participants have gone on to graduate schools and to medical schools. A measure of the high regard of the scientific community for our research is my having been awarded the 2018 Josef Michl ACS Award in Photochemistry.       Last Modified: 08/04/2020       Submitted by: Jack Saltiel]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
