<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Mechanisms of Complex Carbocation Rearrangements</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/15/2014</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2016</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>280000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>280000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03090000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CHE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Chemistry</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Tingyu Li</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>tli@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924949</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>In this project funded by the Chemical Structure, Dynamic &amp; Mechanism B Program of the Division of Chemistry, Professor Dean J. Tantillo of the Department of Chemistry at the University of California-Davis will use modern computer modeling techniques, coupled with laboratory experiments, to uncover fundamental principles of chemical reactivity that govern mechanisms of formation of complex molecules. This research will uncover principles of reactivity and test their generality. The mechanistic models resulting from this work will be of utility to those working in the synthetic organic, biological, physical organic and chemical education fields. In addition to the fundamental importance of the chemistry uncovered through this research, the projects pursued will be used to train students (graduate and undergraduate, several from underrepresented groups) in multidisciplinary approaches to mechanistic chemistry and expose them to careers that employ such techniques. In addition, new methods for making applied computational chemistry accessible to blind and visually impaired students will be developed as part of an effort to encourage this group to pursue careers in STEM fields.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This research will advance knowledge in mechanistic chemistry through the construction of new mechanistic models for rearrangements of complex carbocations. Specific mechanistic models for particular terpene-forming carbocation rearrangements will be developed, and general principles of reactivity for carbocations with complex molecular architectures will be derived from extensive studies spanning different classes of carbocations. The goals of this research are to (a) use modern quantum chemical methods to assess the energetic viability of various carbocation cyclization and rearrangement mechanisms leading to terpene natural products, characterize the electronic structures of the intermediates and transition state structures involved in these processes, and assess the dynamical tendencies associated with the potential energy surfaces for these rearrangements, (b) assess the ability of these intermediates and transition state structures to engage in noncovalent/intermolecular interactions with functional groups present in enzyme active sites and assess the consequences of these interactions, and (c) uncover fundamental, general principles of carbocation reactivity in complex systems.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/07/2014</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/14/2015</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1361807</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Dean</FirstName>
<LastName>Tantillo</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>J</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Dean J Tantillo</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>djtantillo@ucdavis.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5307545635</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000089995</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/07/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of California-Davis</Name>
<CityName>Davis</CityName>
<ZipCode>956186134</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5307547700</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>OR/Sponsored Programs</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[1850 Research Park Dr., Ste 300]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CA03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>047120084</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF CALIFORNIA, DAVIS</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>071549000</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Regents  of the University of California]]></Name>
<CityName>Davis</CityName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>956165270</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[One Shields Ave]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CA03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>9102</Code>
<Text>Chem Struct,Dynmcs&amp;Mechansms B</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0114</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0115</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~137227</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2015~142773</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Terpenes are natural occurring molecules that have found use in many applications ranging from medicine to fuels to flavors and fragrances. This research has led to clarification of the mechanisms by which these complex molecules are formed in nature and has revealed key prinicples that govern the chemical reactions by which they are formed. In particular, it was found that the roles of enzymes in promoting formation of terpenes may have been overestimated; i.e., the inherent reactivity of precursors to terpenes governs many aspects of product formation. The reactivity priniciples uncovered are applicable to other types of chemical reactions, biological or not.&nbsp;</p> <p>In carrying out such research, various methods were developed for making scientific research accessible to blind and visually impaired individuals. These methods include computer-based tools co-developed with a blind graduate student studying terpene forming reactions. In addition, 3-dimensional printing techniques that allow for structures of molecules to be explored and manipulated tactilely were developed and used extensively in carrying out this research project. Overall, a diverse group of students (in terms of gender ethnicity, disability status) were trained in computational chemistry research through this project. These students not only helped design their research projects, but also presented their results to large audiences, including the general public &ndash; skills relevant to their future success in STEM careers.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 08/03/2016<br>      Modified by: Dean&nbsp;J&nbsp;Tantillo</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Terpenes are natural occurring molecules that have found use in many applications ranging from medicine to fuels to flavors and fragrances. This research has led to clarification of the mechanisms by which these complex molecules are formed in nature and has revealed key prinicples that govern the chemical reactions by which they are formed. In particular, it was found that the roles of enzymes in promoting formation of terpenes may have been overestimated; i.e., the inherent reactivity of precursors to terpenes governs many aspects of product formation. The reactivity priniciples uncovered are applicable to other types of chemical reactions, biological or not.   In carrying out such research, various methods were developed for making scientific research accessible to blind and visually impaired individuals. These methods include computer-based tools co-developed with a blind graduate student studying terpene forming reactions. In addition, 3-dimensional printing techniques that allow for structures of molecules to be explored and manipulated tactilely were developed and used extensively in carrying out this research project. Overall, a diverse group of students (in terms of gender ethnicity, disability status) were trained in computational chemistry research through this project. These students not only helped design their research projects, but also presented their results to large audiences, including the general public &ndash; skills relevant to their future success in STEM careers.          Last Modified: 08/03/2016       Submitted by: Dean J Tantillo]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
