<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Planning Grant:  I/UCRC for Expansion of CICI to Add a Site at UTA on Sustainable Utilization of Composites in Infrastructure Systems</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>04/01/2014</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2015</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>14546.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>14546</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07070000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>IIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Industrial Innovation &amp; Partnersh</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Raffaella Montelli</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The research at UTA site of CICI will focus upon soil-structure interaction with an emphasis on minimizing scour issues using composites and fiber reinforcements to enhance the tensile strengths of the soils to mitigate shrinkage cracking. The site will investigate geocomposites in reinforced wall systems in expansive soil environment. Both mechanical and long term durability issues related to composite materials will also be explored. Special emphasis will be given to life-cycle cost analysis and sustainability studies for better understanding of the benefits of using novel composites, as applied to civil infrastructure projects.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The site at UTA will make effort to involve underrepresented students of various ethnicity and backgrounds. They will develop trained workforce in areas related to geosynthetics and geocomposites, thereby enhancing the global competitiveness of US industry. Research will be disseminated to the academia, research community and industry through publications and presentations. The site will develop strategies for evaluating sustainability and reduction of carbon emissions in air due to the usage of specific composite materials. Short courses on the applications of composites and sustainable practices will be offered to educate and train practicing engineers, construction engineers and agencies. K-12 students will be involved in the program through summer camps.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>03/23/2014</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>03/23/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1361871</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Anand</FirstName>
<LastName>Puppala</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>J</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Anand J Puppala</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>anandp@tamu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>9794586346</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000357815</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>03/23/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Shih-Ho</FirstName>
<LastName>Chao</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Shih-Ho Chao</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>shchao@uta.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>8172722105</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000497651</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>03/23/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Texas at Arlington</Name>
<CityName>Arlington</CityName>
<ZipCode>760190145</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>8172722105</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>701 S Nedderman Dr, Box 19145</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Texas</StateName>
<StateCode>TX</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>06</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>TX06</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>064234610</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF TEXAS AT ARLINGTON</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>042000273</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Texas at Arlington]]></Name>
<CityName>Arlington</CityName>
<StateCode>TX</StateCode>
<ZipCode>760190302</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[416 Yates Street]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Texas</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>06</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>TX06</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>5761</Code>
<Text>IUCRC-Indust-Univ Coop Res Ctr</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>125E</Code>
<Text>CENTERS: CIVIL INFRASTRUCTURE SYS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>5761</Code>
<Text>INDUSTRY/UNIV COOP RES CENTERS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0114</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~14546</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The Sustainable and Resilient Civil Infrastructure (SARCI) Center at the University of Texas at Arlington (UTA) has received a planning grant funding from NSF to demonstrate the benefits of academia, government, and industry partnerships as a new site of the Center for Integration of Composites into Infrastructure (CICI), a center established as a part of the NSF Industry - University Cooperative Research Center (I/UCRC) program. CICI is currently comprised of West Virginia University (lead institution), the University of Miami, and North Carolina State University. Its current mission is to accelerate the adoption of composites into infrastructure applications through a collaborative research partnership. The main focus of CICI is to utilize advanced fiber reinforced polymer (FRP) composites in infrastructure, employing innovative manufacturing techniques to arrive at structurally efficient components and subsystems, and embedding modern sensors during manufacturing, thus leading to intelligent communications between a structural system response and its users for cost-effective field evaluation.</p> <p>The UTA new site termed as CICI-UTA and its research team have been aiming to focus on creating an innovative and synergistic relationship between current CICI partners and UTA researchers that will enhance the current on-going activities of CICI into Geoinfrastructure while bringing our both sustainability aspects of using the polymeric composites in the infrastructure applications. Bringing the sustainability component to the forefront of CICI and extending CICI&rsquo;s work on natural fibers (kenaf, flax, jute and others), Geosynthetics, Biopolymers, and others to the civil and military infrastructure by developing innovative polymeric materials, novel fiber coating techniques, curing and sizing techniques, including nano materials, will be major focuses the proposed CICI-UTA. Other synergistic components of the proposed site will include extending UTA&rsquo;s research expertise in sustainability assessments including comprehensive life cycle cost benefits to the on-going and future research studies at other sites. This would further enhance the applications of composites in infrastructure systems.</p> <p><strong>Planning Grant Meeting Details </strong></p> <p>UTA&rsquo;s planning grant meeting was successfully held on July 31 and August 1, 2014. The meeting attracted seventeen companies and agencies. A total of forty-four persons attended the meeting, including the NSF Program Director, Dr. Sashank Priya; NSF Program Evaluator, Dr. Denis Gray; and CICI Host Site Director, Dr. Hota G. Rao, made presentations on NSF IUCRC program and CICI&rsquo;s vision and goals. UTA President, Dr. Vistasp Karbhari; Vice President &ndash; Research, Dr. Carolyn Cason; and Dean of the College of Engineering, Dr. Khosrow Behbehani, represented UTA and have made presentations that described UTA administration&rsquo;s support of the new&nbsp; site. UTA researchers, led by Drs. Puppala (PI), Chao (Co-PI), Hoyos and Yu (Senior Personnel) presented potential research projects that will be undertaken at CICI-UTA.&nbsp;</p> <p><strong>Project Outcomes</strong></p> <p>The following lists major outcomes from the UTA&rsquo;s successful planning grant meeting and follow up activities:</p> <ul> <li>A total of twelve research statements and presentations were made to the attendees of the planning grant meeting, who participated in ranking of the research presentations including comments on the research topics. These ranking evaluations were made through the on-line assessment tool, LIFE. The PIs provided responses to the comments made and as a result of the members&rsquo; comments, a total of eight research statements were developed. Overall, the planning meeting was successful as it developed future research program for the proposed CICI-UTA. These eight statements were ranked again by the membe...]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The Sustainable and Resilient Civil Infrastructure (SARCI) Center at the University of Texas at Arlington (UTA) has received a planning grant funding from NSF to demonstrate the benefits of academia, government, and industry partnerships as a new site of the Center for Integration of Composites into Infrastructure (CICI), a center established as a part of the NSF Industry - University Cooperative Research Center (I/UCRC) program. CICI is currently comprised of West Virginia University (lead institution), the University of Miami, and North Carolina State University. Its current mission is to accelerate the adoption of composites into infrastructure applications through a collaborative research partnership. The main focus of CICI is to utilize advanced fiber reinforced polymer (FRP) composites in infrastructure, employing innovative manufacturing techniques to arrive at structurally efficient components and subsystems, and embedding modern sensors during manufacturing, thus leading to intelligent communications between a structural system response and its users for cost-effective field evaluation.  The UTA new site termed as CICI-UTA and its research team have been aiming to focus on creating an innovative and synergistic relationship between current CICI partners and UTA researchers that will enhance the current on-going activities of CICI into Geoinfrastructure while bringing our both sustainability aspects of using the polymeric composites in the infrastructure applications. Bringing the sustainability component to the forefront of CICI and extending CICIÆs work on natural fibers (kenaf, flax, jute and others), Geosynthetics, Biopolymers, and others to the civil and military infrastructure by developing innovative polymeric materials, novel fiber coating techniques, curing and sizing techniques, including nano materials, will be major focuses the proposed CICI-UTA. Other synergistic components of the proposed site will include extending UTAÆs research expertise in sustainability assessments including comprehensive life cycle cost benefits to the on-going and future research studies at other sites. This would further enhance the applications of composites in infrastructure systems.  Planning Grant Meeting Details   UTAÆs planning grant meeting was successfully held on July 31 and August 1, 2014. The meeting attracted seventeen companies and agencies. A total of forty-four persons attended the meeting, including the NSF Program Director, Dr. Sashank Priya; NSF Program Evaluator, Dr. Denis Gray; and CICI Host Site Director, Dr. Hota G. Rao, made presentations on NSF IUCRC program and CICIÆs vision and goals. UTA President, Dr. Vistasp Karbhari; Vice President &ndash; Research, Dr. Carolyn Cason; and Dean of the College of Engineering, Dr. Khosrow Behbehani, represented UTA and have made presentations that described UTA administrationÆs support of the new  site. UTA researchers, led by Drs. Puppala (PI), Chao (Co-PI), Hoyos and Yu (Senior Personnel) presented potential research projects that will be undertaken at CICI-UTA.   Project Outcomes  The following lists major outcomes from the UTAÆs successful planning grant meeting and follow up activities:  A total of twelve research statements and presentations were made to the attendees of the planning grant meeting, who participated in ranking of the research presentations including comments on the research topics. These ranking evaluations were made through the on-line assessment tool, LIFE. The PIs provided responses to the comments made and as a result of the membersÆ comments, a total of eight research statements were developed. Overall, the planning meeting was successful as it developed future research program for the proposed CICI-UTA. These eight statements were ranked again by the members and in particular those who provided letters of commitments. Based on the ranking scores, the top five statements were selected and were presented in the NSF formal site proposal as requi...]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
