<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Collaborative Research: Three-Dimensional Assessment of Stresses and Fracture Behavior in Sand</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2014</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>70569.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>70569</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CMMI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Civil, Mechanical, &amp; Manufact Inn</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Richard Fragaszy</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This award concerns fundamental aspects of stress distribution and fracture behavior in sands.  Granular materials such as sand, gravel, aggregates, agricultural grains, and pharmaceutical products are comprised of discrete particles in contact with each other.  At the micro-scale, each particle is in contact with neighboring particles where individual particle properties and contact mechanics govern particle interaction.  At the macro-scale, multiple-particle assemblies interact through networks of force chains at contact points.  As the applied stresses increase, some particles may fracture, which causes a change in the distribution of force chains within the mass of the granular material.  Characterization of force chains has been the subject of extensive research primarily using photoelastic materials and the discrete element method (DEM).  Experimental characterization, however, of the development and evolution of force chains in three dimensions (3D) is not available.  Measuring properties of force chains and contact forces between particles experimentally - while they may be fracturing - is an important step toward enhancing knowledge of particle-scale behavior in granular materials.  The award supports fundamental research to provide critical experimental measurements at a range of length-scales, from the particle-scale to the size of a typical soil mechanics laboratory specimen.  The research will have major impact on the development of more accurate computational models that can be applied to better understand a variety of engineering problems involving flow and deformation of granular materials, insertion of piles in sandy soils, in-situ measurement of shear strength in sands using penetrometer devices, tires rolling or skidding through granular soils on the Earth or other planets, high velocity impact of sands, explosive loading of soils, grain silo design, and more efficient manufacturing, handling, and processing of pharmaceutical, agricultural, and food products that are granular in nature.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The objective of the research is to use 3D x-ray diffraction (3DXRD) and synchrotron micro-computed tomography (SMT) to answer fundamental questions about fracture behavior, contact stresses and strains, and onset and evolution of force chains in silica sand. The research will (i) investigate the influence of crystallographic orientation on fracture behavior of silica sand; (ii) measure the distribution of strain and stress within compressed sand particles and investigate their influence on particle fracture in 3D; (iii) quantify the contact stresses between sand particles and assess their influence on fracture behavior of silica sand and on the evolution of force chains; (iv) investigate the factors that affect the onset and collapse of force chains in sand in 3D; and (v) model fracture behavior and force transmission behavior of silica sand in 3D using crystal elasticity and the finite element method (FEM). SMT and 3DXRD are powerful non-destructive 3D techniques that offer complementary experimental measurements and have the potential to yield breakthroughs in the measurement of stress and strain in granular materials at multiple length-scales.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/06/2014</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/06/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1361267</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Richard</FirstName>
<LastName>Regueiro</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>A</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Richard A Regueiro</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>richard.regueiro@colorado.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>3034928026</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000219216</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/06/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Colorado at Boulder</Name>
<CityName>Boulder</CityName>
<ZipCode>803031058</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>3034926221</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>3100 Marine Street, Room 481</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[572 UCB]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Colorado</StateName>
<StateCode>CO</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CO02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>007431505</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>REGENTS OF THE UNIVERSITY OF COLORADO, THE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>007431505</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Colorado Boulder]]></Name>
<CityName>Boulder</CityName>
<StateCode>CO</StateCode>
<ZipCode>803090572</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[3100 Marine St Rm 481 572 UCB]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Colorado</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CO02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1634</Code>
<Text>GEOMECHANICS &amp; GEOMATERIALS</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>036E</Code>
<Text>CIVIL INFRASTRUCTURE</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>172E</Code>
<Text>Geomechanics</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9102</Code>
<Text>WOMEN, MINORITY, DISABLED, NEC</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0114</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~70569</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>This is Collaborative Research on a sub-awarded project at the University of Colorado Boulder.&nbsp; The lead awarded project at the University of Tennessee, Knoxville, led by Dr. Khalid Alshibli, will describe the project outcomes when the lead awarded project is completed in 2019.&nbsp; This part of the project involved a crystal elasticity formulation, with proper orientation of crystal lattice planes for trigonal/hexagonal systems (alpha-quartz is trigonal) with respect to global coordinate axes, being implemented in a Matlab FE code, and then checked against a built-in anisotropic elasticity model in Abaqus, and also a UMAT and VUMAT implemented in Abaqus.&nbsp; This will allow comparison up to the point of fracture in the experimental data for multi-grain simulations being conducted at the University of Tennesse, Knoxville, and then subsequently a smeared fracture model within the VUMAT will capture the post-fracture response of the grains.&nbsp; It has been observed thus far that orientation of the sand grains with respect to the granular triaxial compression specimen, and in turn the crystallographic planes of each grain, will influence the macroscopic fracture behavior of the specimen, assuming the grains are single crystalline.&nbsp; The force chain rearrangement and subsequent grain fracture will likewise be influenced by initial grain orientation and crystal lattice orientation.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 08/27/2018<br>      Modified by: Richard&nbsp;A&nbsp;Regueiro</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ This is Collaborative Research on a sub-awarded project at the University of Colorado Boulder.  The lead awarded project at the University of Tennessee, Knoxville, led by Dr. Khalid Alshibli, will describe the project outcomes when the lead awarded project is completed in 2019.  This part of the project involved a crystal elasticity formulation, with proper orientation of crystal lattice planes for trigonal/hexagonal systems (alpha-quartz is trigonal) with respect to global coordinate axes, being implemented in a Matlab FE code, and then checked against a built-in anisotropic elasticity model in Abaqus, and also a UMAT and VUMAT implemented in Abaqus.  This will allow comparison up to the point of fracture in the experimental data for multi-grain simulations being conducted at the University of Tennesse, Knoxville, and then subsequently a smeared fracture model within the VUMAT will capture the post-fracture response of the grains.  It has been observed thus far that orientation of the sand grains with respect to the granular triaxial compression specimen, and in turn the crystallographic planes of each grain, will influence the macroscopic fracture behavior of the specimen, assuming the grains are single crystalline.  The force chain rearrangement and subsequent grain fracture will likewise be influenced by initial grain orientation and crystal lattice orientation.       Last Modified: 08/27/2018       Submitted by: Richard A Regueiro]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
