<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>I/UCRC: NSF Net-centric and Cloud Software and Systems</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>04/15/2014</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>03/31/2021</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>120000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>238748</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>05050000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>CSE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CNS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Computer and Network Systems</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Behrooz Shirazi</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>bshirazi@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032928343</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The NSF Net-centric and Cloud Software and Systems Industry/University Cooperative Research Center (NCSS I/UCRC) is a multi-university cooperative established in 2009 with a collaborative research partnership between the University of North Texas (UNT) and the University of Texas at Dallas (UTD), with Southern Methodist University (SMU) as an affiliated academic site. The original academic sites (UNT and UTD, with SMU as an affiliated member) will complete Phase I in February 2014 and are seeking to continue operations as Phase II I/UCRC sites. The research focus of the NCSS I/UCRC is on cost-effective methods of enabling the rapid design and deployment of highly efficient and dependable net centric and cloud hardware/software systems that must operate in various environments subject to potentially stringent response time, power, heat, security and resource constraints. By combining the diverse capabilities and expertise of the participating academic institutions and the real-world experiences of engineers from well-known innovative high tech companies, the center will enhance the research capabilities of all the participants. The NCSS I/UCRC will develop innovative and practical technologies for modeling, analysis, design, implementation, verification and validation, deployment, and evolution of a variety of net-centric and cloud systems. This systems-oriented research is aimed at enabling the coordinated hardware/software development of highly dependable integrated net-centric and cloud systems.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The NCSS I/UCRC research will enable industry to develop and leverage emerging net-centric and cloud computing platforms and infrastructures. The industrial sectors that benefit from the center include defense, energy, transportation, health care, commerce, homeland security, and emergency preparedness/emergency response industries. The Center has actively worked with the Metroplex Technology Business Council (MTBC) Innovation Group in Dallas/Fort Worth metropolitan area and led to the creation of a new MTBC Special Interest Group (SIG) in the area of cloud computing. The NCSS I/UCRC will continue to provide education and training of students to meet our nation?s future workforce needs in these rapidly emerging and evolving technology areas. Many of the software tools, and infrastructure (e.g., sensors labs) developed at UNT site were made available to students in various courses such as sensor networks (with 30 students per year), computer architecture (with 40 students per year). The UTD site developed courses on cloud computing systems, Internet of Things, programming and optimization of applications on heterogeneous multicore systems, power management for multi-core systems, and other NCSS related topics. Over 60 students have enrolled in these courses over the past 3 years. A significant growth in enrollments in these courses is anticipated. The Center activities also have and will continue to provide real-world research experience for several graduate and undergraduate students as well as international education and research collaboration in this area with some faculty and students from universities in China, France, Germany, Italy, Taiwan, and Turkey.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>04/10/2014</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/15/2018</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.070</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1361795</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Dung</FirstName>
<LastName>Huynh</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>T</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Dung T Huynh</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>huynh@utdallas.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>9728832169</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000430489</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/10/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Neeraj</FirstName>
<LastName>Mittal</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Neeraj Mittal</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>neerajm@utdallas.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>9728832347</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000491862</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/10/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>I-Ling</FirstName>
<LastName>Yen</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>I-Ling Yen</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>ilyen@utdallas.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>9728836446</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000422138</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/10/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Gopal</FirstName>
<LastName>Gupta</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Gopal Gupta</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>gupta@utdallas.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>4698781991</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000249848</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/10/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Farokh</FirstName>
<LastName>Bastani</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>B</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Farokh B Bastani</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>bastani@utdallas.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>9728832299</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000449693</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/10/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Texas at Dallas</Name>
<CityName>Richardson</CityName>
<ZipCode>750803021</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>9728832313</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>800 W. Campbell Rd., AD15</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Texas</StateName>
<StateCode>TX</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>32</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>TX32</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>800188161</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF TEXAS AT DALLAS</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>042000273</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Texas at Dallas]]></Name>
<CityName>Richardson</CityName>
<StateCode>TX</StateCode>
<ZipCode>750803021</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[800 West Campbell Rd., EC 31]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Texas</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>32</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>TX32</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>5761</Code>
<Text>IUCRC-Indust-Univ Coop Res Ctr</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>N561</Code>
<Text/>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>170E</Code>
<Text>Interagency Agreements</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>5761</Code>
<Text>INDUSTRY/UNIV COOP RES CENTERS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8039</Code>
<Text>Information, Communication &amp; Computing</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0114</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0115</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0116</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0118</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~118748</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2015~40000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2016~40000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2018~40000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>This project supported the continuation of the NSF Net-centric and Cloud Software and Systems (NCSS) Industry/University Cooperative Research Center (I/UCRC). The center includes the University of North Texas (lead), the University of Texas at Dallas, and Arizona State University.&nbsp; It also includes Southern Methodist University as an affiliated site.</p> <p>The intellectual merit of this project is the development of cost-effective methods of enabling rapid design and deployment of highly efficient net-centric and cloud hardware/software systems that must operate in various environments subject to potentially stringent response time, power, security, and other resource constraints. Many of these goals were achieved as can be evidenced from a combined effort of all academic sites over a seven-year period leading to over 300 publications, a dozen patents either filed or granted, more than 150 graduate and undergraduate students and more than 25 faculty that participated in the various research activities undertaken by the center. The majority of the center?s research funding, averaging more than one million dollars per year, was funded by memberships from more than 20 industrial organizations.</p> <p>Some key outcomes included software tools for capturing and analyzing cybersecurity threats, secure information sharing in IoT and cloud environments, improving performance of heterogeneous memory systems, and machine learning techniques for signal processing. The research results have been very impressive for all the industrial members.&nbsp; Based on one research project, a PhD student started a new company immediately after graduating with the PhD degree.&nbsp; The new company was very successful from the beginning and has been a member of the center since 2017 and supported some new research projects.&nbsp; The center has also continued to actively work with the Dallas-Fort Worth Metroplex Technology Business Council&nbsp; (MTBC) in the MTBC Special Interest Group (SIG) in the area of cloud computing and another SIG in the area of Internet of Things (IoT) technologies.&nbsp; The research results have also been used to create new courses related to emerging research areas, including a course on Internet of Things, a course on Cloud Computing Systems, a course on Language-Based Security, and a course on Advanced Programming Languages.&nbsp; All these courses are essential to the development of state-of-the-art systems in secure IoT and Cloud Computing applications.&nbsp; Also, the projects have been used to introduce several high school students to current research projects in the area of drone technologies and smart vehicle systems.</p> <p>Broader Impacts: In addition to the impact on the educational and research training of the students that participated in the research activities, the project also involved researchers from industrial member organizations. Since the majority of the research was based on the industrial needs, many of the outcomes have impacted the direction and products produced by member organizations.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 05/27/2021<br>      Modified by: Farokh&nbsp;B&nbsp;Bastani</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ This project supported the continuation of the NSF Net-centric and Cloud Software and Systems (NCSS) Industry/University Cooperative Research Center (I/UCRC). The center includes the University of North Texas (lead), the University of Texas at Dallas, and Arizona State University.  It also includes Southern Methodist University as an affiliated site.  The intellectual merit of this project is the development of cost-effective methods of enabling rapid design and deployment of highly efficient net-centric and cloud hardware/software systems that must operate in various environments subject to potentially stringent response time, power, security, and other resource constraints. Many of these goals were achieved as can be evidenced from a combined effort of all academic sites over a seven-year period leading to over 300 publications, a dozen patents either filed or granted, more than 150 graduate and undergraduate students and more than 25 faculty that participated in the various research activities undertaken by the center. The majority of the center?s research funding, averaging more than one million dollars per year, was funded by memberships from more than 20 industrial organizations.  Some key outcomes included software tools for capturing and analyzing cybersecurity threats, secure information sharing in IoT and cloud environments, improving performance of heterogeneous memory systems, and machine learning techniques for signal processing. The research results have been very impressive for all the industrial members.  Based on one research project, a PhD student started a new company immediately after graduating with the PhD degree.  The new company was very successful from the beginning and has been a member of the center since 2017 and supported some new research projects.  The center has also continued to actively work with the Dallas-Fort Worth Metroplex Technology Business Council  (MTBC) in the MTBC Special Interest Group (SIG) in the area of cloud computing and another SIG in the area of Internet of Things (IoT) technologies.  The research results have also been used to create new courses related to emerging research areas, including a course on Internet of Things, a course on Cloud Computing Systems, a course on Language-Based Security, and a course on Advanced Programming Languages.  All these courses are essential to the development of state-of-the-art systems in secure IoT and Cloud Computing applications.  Also, the projects have been used to introduce several high school students to current research projects in the area of drone technologies and smart vehicle systems.  Broader Impacts: In addition to the impact on the educational and research training of the students that participated in the research activities, the project also involved researchers from industrial member organizations. Since the majority of the research was based on the industrial needs, many of the outcomes have impacted the direction and products produced by member organizations.       Last Modified: 05/27/2021       Submitted by: Farokh B Bastani]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
