<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>New Algorithms and their Use in the Study of Nonadiabatic Processes Influenced by Conical Intersections</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2014</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>425000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>425000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03090000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CHE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Chemistry</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Evelyn Goldfield</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>egoldfie@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032920000</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>David Yarkony of Johns Hopkins University is supported by an award from the Chemical Theory, Models and Computational Methods program in the Chemistry Division to develop theoretical and computational approaches to study chemical reactions that are initiated when a molecule is excited by absorbing energy from light.  Scientists can describe a chemical reaction as a marble rolling on a surface:  reactants point A; products point B; moving downhill is easy (extract chemical energy); moving uphill is hard (need to add energy).  For many light-initiated  processes such as  photosynthesis, vision, and solar energy conversion, this notion must be generalized.  In this case, as the result of absorbing light, the marble starts on a higher surface. Scientists want to know how the marble gets back to the lower surface and where it ends up on that surface, that is, what molecules are made and how much energy they have.    If the light is provided by a laser, the task at hand may be laser control of a chemical reaction.  If the light comes from the sun, energy conversion, photosynthesis or cell damage may be the issue.  The passage from the upper surface to the lower surface not unlike spiraling down a drain - it involves funneling by a double cone-like structure (two cones joined at their vertices) called a "conical intersection". The mathematical description of the resulting multi-surface process requires detailed knowledge of the surfaces and the connecting cones.  The more accurate the description of the surfaces and cones the more likely the computer simulation will correspond to reality.  The principal goal of this project is the representation of the surfaces and connecting cones using the most accurate tools available and enabling computers to reliably simulate energetic processes.&lt;br/&gt; &lt;br/&gt;A principal issue in nonadiabatic dynamics is the quality of the electronic structure data (energies and interstate couplings) used. When direct or on-the-fly dynamics techniques are employed, the quality of electronic structure data is subordinated to the need to obtain that data quickly.  The alternative is to use fitted coupled potential energy surfaces. This method can use electronic structure descriptions more accurately than those used in direct dynamics and can smooth the irregularities that may occur in the electronic energies due to the orbital changes inherent in nonadiabatic processes.  The challenge is to determine the fit.  By combining least squares fitting with exact data representation and incorporating derivative coupling data directly into the fitting process, an algorithm has been developed that provides a quantifiably quasi-diabatic fitted representation of electronic structure data including a reliable description of seams of conical intersections. That approach is suitable for 4-5 atom systems. The goal of this research is to extend this algorithm to treat significantly larger molecules, such as the photodissociation of phenol. The proposed fit surfaces algorithm will make high quality electronic structure data available for the study of nonadiabatic dynamics in nucleobases and a multitude of comparably sized systems.   Determining how far this methodology can be extended, that is how large a system can be treated, is one of the principal goals of this research.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/23/2014</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/04/2015</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1361121</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>David</FirstName>
<LastName>Yarkony</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>R</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>David R Yarkony</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>yarkony@jhu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>4105164663</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000167227</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/23/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Johns Hopkins University</Name>
<CityName>Baltimore</CityName>
<ZipCode>212182686</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>4439971898</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1101 E 33rd St</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[Suite B001]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Maryland</StateName>
<StateCode>MD</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MD07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>001910777</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>JOHNS HOPKINS UNIVERSITY, THE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>001910777</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Johns Hopkins University]]></Name>
<CityName>Baltimore</CityName>
<StateCode>MD</StateCode>
<ZipCode>212182608</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[3400 North Charles Street]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Maryland</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MD07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>6881</Code>
<Text>Chem Thry, Mdls &amp; Cmptnl Mthds</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7433</Code>
<Text>CyberInfra Frmwrk 21st (CIF21)</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9216</Code>
<Text>ADVANCED SOFTWARE TECH &amp; ALGOR</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9263</Code>
<Text>COMPUTATIONAL SCIENCE &amp; ENGING</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0114</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0115</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~155000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2015~270000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The scientific description of the &nbsp;natural world has &nbsp;provided enormous benefits for mankind. &nbsp;The real world, however is far too complex to describe exactly, so solvable models/approximations must be built. &nbsp;One of the most fundamental models used by scientists to understand molecular interactions and molecular processes is the adiabatic states model. &nbsp;While this model is broadly applicable, scientist who wish to model processes including vision, photosynthesis, interstellar and upper atmospheric chemistry and solar energy conversion, must &nbsp;confront the fact that these most basic processes cannot be described by this most basic model. The cause of this failure is&nbsp;an arcane topological feature of the &nbsp;adiabatic states, a conical intersection (see figure), which 30 years &nbsp;ago would have &nbsp;been considered generally irrelevant. &nbsp;</p> <p>Our &nbsp;research in this current grant considered intrinsic limitations of the adiabatic states model both those well understood and those largely unexpected.</p> <p>WELL UNDERSTOOD</p> <p>For energetic states the role of &nbsp;conical intersections is now well understood if difficult to describe computationally. The adiabatic states model breaks down and is replaced by an alternative model, the diabatic state model. Although the diabatic states model has been used for close to 90 years, as part &nbsp;of this grant we found limitations in the methods used to &nbsp;construct existing diabatic models, Significantly we were able to show how those limitations can be removed. &nbsp;</p> <p>UNEXPECTED</p> <p>In the case of the ground ( lowest energy) &nbsp;state one normally expects, and correctly so, that the &nbsp;adiabatic states model is valid since the conical intersections which could invalidate the adibatic &nbsp;states model are energetically inaccessible( too high). However, energetic inaccessibilty is not sufficient(see figure), &nbsp;Problems may still exist. When forwarned of the problem, with sufficient care the adiabatic state model can be salvaged provided proper account is taken of the energetically inaccessible conical intersection and its attendant issues. &nbsp;In this grant we describe how this &nbsp;can be accomplished .</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 01/17/2018<br>      Modified by: David&nbsp;R&nbsp;Yarkony</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Image         </div> <div class="galControls onePhoto" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation onePhoto" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1361121/1361121_10312640_1516226671065_nsfci--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1361121/1361121_10312640_1516226671065_nsfci--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Conical Intersection"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1361121/1361121_10312640_1516226671065_nsfci--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Conical Intersection"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Conical Intersection impacts dissociation of H from phenol (C6H5OH) by modifying wave function along two paths ( black arrows)</div> <div class="imageCredit">Phys. Chem. Chem. Phys. 18, 26335(2016) with permission from the PCCP Owner Societies.</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Royalty-free (restricted use - cannot be shared)</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">David&nbsp;R&nbsp;Yarkony</div> <div class="imageTitle">Conical Intersection</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The scientific description of the  natural world has  provided enormous benefits for mankind.  The real world, however is far too complex to describe exactly, so solvable models/approximations must be built.  One of the most fundamental models used by scientists to understand molecular interactions and molecular processes is the adiabatic states model.  While this model is broadly applicable, scientist who wish to model processes including vision, photosynthesis, interstellar and upper atmospheric chemistry and solar energy conversion, must  confront the fact that these most basic processes cannot be described by this most basic model. The cause of this failure is an arcane topological feature of the  adiabatic states, a conical intersection (see figure), which 30 years  ago would have  been considered generally irrelevant.    Our  research in this current grant considered intrinsic limitations of the adiabatic states model both those well understood and those largely unexpected.  WELL UNDERSTOOD  For energetic states the role of  conical intersections is now well understood if difficult to describe computationally. The adiabatic states model breaks down and is replaced by an alternative model, the diabatic state model. Although the diabatic states model has been used for close to 90 years, as part  of this grant we found limitations in the methods used to  construct existing diabatic models, Significantly we were able to show how those limitations can be removed.    UNEXPECTED  In the case of the ground ( lowest energy)  state one normally expects, and correctly so, that the  adiabatic states model is valid since the conical intersections which could invalidate the adibatic  states model are energetically inaccessible( too high). However, energetic inaccessibilty is not sufficient(see figure),  Problems may still exist. When forwarned of the problem, with sufficient care the adiabatic state model can be salvaged provided proper account is taken of the energetically inaccessible conical intersection and its attendant issues.  In this grant we describe how this  can be accomplished .       Last Modified: 01/17/2018       Submitted by: David R Yarkony]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
