<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>SusChEM: Surface Reactions in Lithium-Oxygen Batteries</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2014</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>448661.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>448661</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03090000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CHE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Chemistry</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Colby Foss</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>cfoss@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032925327</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>In this award, co-funded by the Chemical Structure, Dynamics and Mechanisms A (CSDM-A) Program of the Division of Chemistry and the Energy for Sustainability Program of the Division of Chemical, Bioengineering, Environmental and Transport Systems of the Engineering Directorate, Professor Eric Stuve of the University of Washington and his graduate student researchers are working to develop a better understanding of the chemical reactions that take place at the electrode surfaces in lithium-oxygen batteries, a technologically-promising, new kind of battery.  They are investigating the elementary chemical processes that are taking place in model systems using surface science techniques.  In doing these experiments, Prof. Stuve and his group are striving to provide researchers with chemical insights that will allow for improved battery performance.  Graduate students working on this project will receive training in chemistry and engineering, and Prof. Stuve will continue his efforts at educating the wider public about energy-related research.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Prof. Stuve and his research group are conducting a series of experiments on model electrode materials, mimicking the electrode materials in lithium-oxygen batteries.  Among the areas being studied are:  (1) the study of the growth and morphology of LiOx on the electrode surface; (2) the investigation of the chemical stability of the solvent, including reactions that consume Li and the passivation of the electrode surface; and (3) the exploration of the reaction mechanism and reversibility of oxygen uptake/production.  The systems will be studied using a number of sensitive surface science techniques, including Field Emission Microscopy (FEM), Field Ionization Microscopy (FIM), Pulsed Filed Desorption Mass Spectrometry (PFDMS) and Ramped Field Desorption (RFD).  Students working on this project will receive training that will prepare them for research positions in academia, national Laboratories or industry.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/28/2014</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/28/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1361709</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Eric</FirstName>
<LastName>Stuve</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>M</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Eric M Stuve</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>stuve@uw.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2065430156</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000293036</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/28/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Washington</Name>
<CityName>Seattle</CityName>
<ZipCode>981950001</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2065434043</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>4333 Brooklyn Ave NE</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Washington</StateName>
<StateCode>WA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>WA07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>605799469</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF WASHINGTON</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>042803536</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Washington]]></Name>
<CityName>Seattle</CityName>
<StateCode>WA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>981951750</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Washington</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>WA07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7644</Code>
<Text>EchemS-Electrochemical Systems</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>9101</Code>
<Text>Chem Struct,Dynmcs&amp;Mechansms A</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8248</Code>
<Text>SusChEM</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8396</Code>
<Text>Clean Energy Technology</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8650</Code>
<Text>Sustainable Chemistry</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0114</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~448661</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The lithium-oxygen (Li-O<sub>2</sub>) battery has the potential to revolutionize energy storage in batteries by offering the promise of energy storage capacities up to five times that of lithium-ion batteries. &nbsp;The Li-O<sub>2</sub> battery, illustrated in Fig. 1, consists of an anode of solid lithium (left), a non-aqueous electrolyte that contains lithium ions Li<sup>+</sup> (center), and a carbon cathode (right). &nbsp; The cathode compartment is open to gaseous O<sub>2</sub> or air. &nbsp;During discharge, lithium ions (green) and oxygen molecules (blue) react at the cathode to form a lithium peroxide (Li<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub>) deposit. &nbsp;During charge, the process reverses: the Li<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> deposit dissociates back into Li<sup>+</sup> and O<sub>2</sub>.</p> <p>The Li-O<sub>2</sub> battery faces several challenges before it can become commercially feasible. &nbsp;The battery can only undergo a small number of discharge/charge cycles; it requires high voltage to charge it, which is inefficient; and it degrades due to reaction with the electrolyte. &nbsp;The specific research goals of this project were to understand: (1) the growth and morphology of lithium-oxygen deposits, (2) degradation reactions in the solvent, and (3) kinetics and mechanism of the reaction between Li<sup>+</sup> and O<sub>2</sub> during discharge and decomposition of Li<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> during charge.</p> <p><strong>Methods of Study</strong></p> <p>Experimental research was conducted with the methods of field ionization microscopy (FIM). &nbsp;This is a novel approach that exposes the buried electrode/electrolyte interface of a battery for study by ultrahigh vacuum surface science methods. &nbsp;The experimental system consists of a Pt field emitter tip (with or without carbon) of small radius (&asymp; 35 nm) onto which Li, O<sub>2</sub>, and a solvent can be adsorbed. &nbsp;A high electric field, up to 30 V/nm, can be achieved by applying a 1-3 kV bias on the tip. &nbsp;Fields of this magnitude can initiate surface chemistry by breaking bonds. &nbsp;More importantly, the electric field is analogous to electrode potential within a battery.</p> <p><strong>Outcomes</strong></p> <p>The manner in which field ionization experiments can be used to simulate electrochemical reactions was described in conference presentations and publication. &nbsp;The field ionization system is a complex system and thus is difficult to operate. &nbsp;We were unable to achieve full operation of the system, so experimental results are limited.</p> <p>The issue of fundamental studies of Li-O<sub>2</sub> chemistry remains a timely and important topic in battery chemistry. &nbsp;We have reviewed the scientific and technological literature of alkali metal-O<sub>2</sub> batteries (Li-O<sub>2</sub>, Na-O<sub>2</sub>, K-O<sub>2</sub>) to identify a set of fundamental studies needed to advance our understanding of this battery chemistry. &nbsp;</p> <p>At present there is no set of standard measurements for characterizing Li-O<sub>2</sub> batteries. &nbsp;We have identified a number of "key states" of the battery discharge/charge curve that can be used to relate battery performance with molecular level details of the cathode surface chemistry. &nbsp;Figure 2 shows the key states along with some information that they provide. &nbsp;Figure 2(a) shows a typical discharge/charge curve for a Li-O<sub>2</sub> battery. &nbsp;Beginning with the fully charged battery (key state D<sub>0</sub>), there is a rapid decrease in potential that occurs when the first monolayer of deposits builds up. &nbsp;The first layer is completed at key state D<sub>0+</sub>. &nbsp;(The subscript 0 represents zero discharge, and the plus sign signifies 1 monolayer of discharge, a small amount compared to full discharge.) &nbsp;Further discharge produces a steady build up of deposits and progressively decreasing potential. &nbsp;At cell death, key state D<sub>1</sub> (the 1 indicates full discharge), the potential falls rapidly to zero. &nbsp;</p> <p>The charge process begins at key state C<sub>0</sub>, which is equal to D<sub>1</sub>. &nbsp;The potential increases rapidly because of the inefficiency of charging. &nbsp;The first layer of deposits is removed at key state C<sub>0+</sub>. &nbsp;Further charge produces a steady increase in potential and several features that can be associated with morpohology and nature of the deposit layer. &nbsp;At any point in the charge and discharge region, it is possible to identify "linked key states", labeled D and C. &nbsp;Linked key states help identify fundamental studies to determine the reasons for high charge potentials. &nbsp;As the battery becomes fully charged, the carbon surface is again exposed at key state C<sub>1-.</sub>&nbsp;(The minus sign indicates that only the first layer remains until full charge.). Removal of the last layer of deposits occurs between C<sub>1-</sub> and C<sub>1</sub>.</p> <p>The manner in which the key states can be used is illustrated in Fig. 2. &nbsp;Figure 2(b) depicts the build up of the first layer of Li<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> deposits between key states D<sub>0</sub> and D<sub>0+</sub>. &nbsp;Careful analysis of the discharge curve between these two key states, along with fundamental studies, can determine the kinetics and mechanism of the first layer build up. &nbsp;Figure 2(c) shows removal of Li<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2&nbsp;</sub>to form Li<sup>+</sup> ions and O<sub>2</sub> molecules in solution. &nbsp;This process can occur in a variety of ways, which are themselves subjects of study. &nbsp;</p> <p>Publication of the scientific review and a full description of the key states concept are in process.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 10/31/2018<br>      Modified by: Eric&nbsp;M&nbsp;Stuve</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Images (<span id="selectedPhoto0">1</span> of <span class="totalNumber"></span>)           </div> <div class="galControls" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1361709/1361709_10324573_1541038393196_lio2_key_states_2--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1361709/1361709_10324573_1541038393196_lio2_key_states_2--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Li-O2 key states"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1361709/1361709_10324573_1541038393196_lio2_key_states_2--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Li-O2 key states"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Figure 2: (a) Discharge/charge curve of a Li-oxygen battery; (b) illustration of formation of first layer deposits on discharge; and (c) illustration of deposit removal on charge.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Eric Stuve</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Eric&nbsp;M&nbsp;Stuve</div> <div class="imageTitle">Li-O2 key states</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1361709/1361709_10324573_1541040060543_li-air_cell3--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1361709/1361709_10324573_1541040060543_li-air_cell3--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Li-O2 battery"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1361709/1361709_10324573_1541040060543_li-air_cell3--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Li-O2 battery"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Figure 1: Illustration of lithium-oxygen battery.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Eric Stuve</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Eric&nbsp;M&nbsp;Stuve</div> <div class="imageTitle">Li-O2 battery</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The lithium-oxygen (Li-O2) battery has the potential to revolutionize energy storage in batteries by offering the promise of energy storage capacities up to five times that of lithium-ion batteries.  The Li-O2 battery, illustrated in Fig. 1, consists of an anode of solid lithium (left), a non-aqueous electrolyte that contains lithium ions Li+ (center), and a carbon cathode (right).   The cathode compartment is open to gaseous O2 or air.  During discharge, lithium ions (green) and oxygen molecules (blue) react at the cathode to form a lithium peroxide (Li2O2) deposit.  During charge, the process reverses: the Li2O2 deposit dissociates back into Li+ and O2.  The Li-O2 battery faces several challenges before it can become commercially feasible.  The battery can only undergo a small number of discharge/charge cycles; it requires high voltage to charge it, which is inefficient; and it degrades due to reaction with the electrolyte.  The specific research goals of this project were to understand: (1) the growth and morphology of lithium-oxygen deposits, (2) degradation reactions in the solvent, and (3) kinetics and mechanism of the reaction between Li+ and O2 during discharge and decomposition of Li2O2 during charge.  Methods of Study  Experimental research was conducted with the methods of field ionization microscopy (FIM).  This is a novel approach that exposes the buried electrode/electrolyte interface of a battery for study by ultrahigh vacuum surface science methods.  The experimental system consists of a Pt field emitter tip (with or without carbon) of small radius (&asymp; 35 nm) onto which Li, O2, and a solvent can be adsorbed.  A high electric field, up to 30 V/nm, can be achieved by applying a 1-3 kV bias on the tip.  Fields of this magnitude can initiate surface chemistry by breaking bonds.  More importantly, the electric field is analogous to electrode potential within a battery.  Outcomes  The manner in which field ionization experiments can be used to simulate electrochemical reactions was described in conference presentations and publication.  The field ionization system is a complex system and thus is difficult to operate.  We were unable to achieve full operation of the system, so experimental results are limited.  The issue of fundamental studies of Li-O2 chemistry remains a timely and important topic in battery chemistry.  We have reviewed the scientific and technological literature of alkali metal-O2 batteries (Li-O2, Na-O2, K-O2) to identify a set of fundamental studies needed to advance our understanding of this battery chemistry.    At present there is no set of standard measurements for characterizing Li-O2 batteries.  We have identified a number of "key states" of the battery discharge/charge curve that can be used to relate battery performance with molecular level details of the cathode surface chemistry.  Figure 2 shows the key states along with some information that they provide.  Figure 2(a) shows a typical discharge/charge curve for a Li-O2 battery.  Beginning with the fully charged battery (key state D0), there is a rapid decrease in potential that occurs when the first monolayer of deposits builds up.  The first layer is completed at key state D0+.  (The subscript 0 represents zero discharge, and the plus sign signifies 1 monolayer of discharge, a small amount compared to full discharge.)  Further discharge produces a steady build up of deposits and progressively decreasing potential.  At cell death, key state D1 (the 1 indicates full discharge), the potential falls rapidly to zero.    The charge process begins at key state C0, which is equal to D1.  The potential increases rapidly because of the inefficiency of charging.  The first layer of deposits is removed at key state C0+.  Further charge produces a steady increase in potential and several features that can be associated with morpohology and nature of the deposit layer.  At any point in the charge and discharge region, it is possible to identify "linked key states", labeled D and C.  Linked key states help identify fundamental studies to determine the reasons for high charge potentials.  As the battery becomes fully charged, the carbon surface is again exposed at key state C1-. (The minus sign indicates that only the first layer remains until full charge.). Removal of the last layer of deposits occurs between C1- and C1.  The manner in which the key states can be used is illustrated in Fig. 2.  Figure 2(b) depicts the build up of the first layer of Li2O2 deposits between key states D0 and D0+.  Careful analysis of the discharge curve between these two key states, along with fundamental studies, can determine the kinetics and mechanism of the first layer build up.  Figure 2(c) shows removal of Li2O2 to form Li+ ions and O2 molecules in solution.  This process can occur in a variety of ways, which are themselves subjects of study.    Publication of the scientific review and a full description of the key states concept are in process.       Last Modified: 10/31/2018       Submitted by: Eric M Stuve]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
