<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>CyberWatch West</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/25/2013</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>09/30/2016</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>2095549.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>2095549</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>11040100</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>EHR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DUE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Undergraduate Education</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>R. Corby Hovis</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>chovis@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924625</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Mt. San Antonio College (Mt. SAC) and five educational partners [California State Polytechnic University, Pomona, California State Universities at Dominguez Hills and San Bernardino, and Whatcom Community College (WA)] are establishing an ATE regional center for cybersecurity, CyberWatch West, serving California, Washington, and Oregon. There are, at present, three other ATE regional centers for cybersecurity education: CyberWatch at Prince George CC in Washington, DC, metropolitan area; CSSIA based at Moraine Valley CC, near Chicago; and CSEC based at the University of Tulsa, in Oklahoma.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The overarching goal of CyberWatch West is to strengthen the cybersecurity workforce in California and the Pacific Northwest. To accomplish this goal, CyberWatch West is concentrating on the following four major areas: (1) student activities, including meaningful internships and a cyber-defense league with weekly virtual exercises; (2) assistance in curriculum development based on recognized standards and creation of cybersecurity pathways from community colleges to four-year institutions; (3) a faculty development and mentor program to help infuse cybersecurity concepts into coursework; (4) outreach and partnership with regional community colleges, universities, high schools, and industry to determine and assist with regional needs in cybersecurity education.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Each of the core partners has large minority student enrollments and the project is targeting these underrepresented groups in cybersecurity. In addition, the consortium includes 16 other postsecondary institutions throughout the western United States and its outreach program is reaching a large number of high schools. The dissemination efforts include a web portal, presentations at national conferences, and an active participation in the National Initiative for Cybersecurity Education (NICE).</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>09/27/2013</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/17/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.076</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1361636</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Dan</FirstName>
<LastName>Manson</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Dan Manson</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>dmanson@cpp.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>9098693244</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000446705</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/12/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Jaishri</FirstName>
<LastName>Mehta</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Jaishri Mehta</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>jmehta@mtsac.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>9095945611</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000483459</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/27/2013</StartDate>
<EndDate>09/30/2013</EndDate>
<RoleCode>Former Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Nancy</FirstName>
<LastName>Jones</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Nancy Jones</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>njones@coastline.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>7142416209</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000036365</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/12/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Tony</FirstName>
<LastName>Coulson</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Tony Coulson</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>tcoulson@csusb.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>9095375768</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000517961</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/12/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Corrinne</FirstName>
<LastName>Sande</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Corrinne Sande</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>csande@whatcom.ctc.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>3603833552</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000547688</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/17/2016</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Whatcom Community College</Name>
<CityName>Bellingham</CityName>
<ZipCode>982269050</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>3603833235</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>237 W. Kellogg Road</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Washington</StateName>
<StateCode>WA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>WA01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>039739222</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>WHATCOM COMMUNITY COLLEGE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Whatcom Community College]]></Name>
<CityName>Bellingham</CityName>
<StateCode>WA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>982268033</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[237 West Kellogg Rd]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Washington</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>WA02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7412</Code>
<Text>Advanced Tech Education Prog</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1032</Code>
<Text>ADVANCED TECHNOLOGY EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9178</Code>
<Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0412</Code>
<Name>NSF Education &amp; Human Resource</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040106</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0414</Code>
<Name>NSF Education &amp; Human Resource</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040106</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2012~589750</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~1505799</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The CyberWatch West (CWW) Advanced Technology Education Center, funded by the National Science Foundation (NSF), was established in October of 2011. The Center covers a 14-state region and is led by four core educational partners: Whatcom Community College (WA); California State Polytechnic University, Pomona; California State University, San Bernardino; and Coastline Community College (CA). Whatcom Community College serves as the lead institution for the Center.</p> <p>CWW&rsquo;s mission is to strengthen the cybersecurity workforce in the Western United States by providing solutions to address the limited resources at community colleges through innovative curriculum development; building an online community for faculty professional growth and mentoring; creating a developmental pathway of competitions that facilitate growth of students&rsquo; cybersecurity skills; and facilitating processes at the state and national level conducive to development of cybersecurity educational programs.</p> <p>CWW accomplishments include:</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <ul> <li>Expansion into 14 states in the western region with over 100 member institutions from high schools, community colleges, and universities.</li> <li>The establishment of the first 2+2 transfer pathway for California cybersecurity students.</li> <li>The establishment of the first baccalaureate in cybersecurity in California at CaliforniaState University San Bernardino.</li> <li>Significant growth in participation by middle and high school students in cybersecurity competition events.</li> <li>Development of a new Critical Infrastructure cybersecurity curriculum for community colleges.</li> <li>Enhanced engagement with industry through industry events held throughout the region.</li> <li>Rapid expansion of the CyberPatriot program throughout the region.</li> <li>Increase in the number of CAE2Ys in the region from five to nine (180% increase).</li> <li>Convergence developing for cybersecurity education and overall awareness in the Western region &ndash; participation from all sectors, including K-12, industry, and Government.</li> </ul> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>CyberWatch West funding was renewed in 2015 and the center is starting its fifth year. This center has had a tremendous impact in the Western United States. Cybersecurity education programs are now established at colleges in every state in the 14 state region and beyond. This center is contributing to the overall economic and homeland security of the nation, and is impacting the lives of thousands of students who complete these college and university programs and are hired into well paying high-demand jobs.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 09/23/2016<br>      Modified by: Corrinne&nbsp;Sande</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Image         </div> <div class="galControls onePhoto" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation onePhoto" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2016/1361636/1361636_10140335_1474645567233_CWWLogo-color-hi-res--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2016/1361636/1361636_10140335_1474645567233_CWWLogo-color-hi-res--rgov-800width.jpg" title="CWW logo"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2016/1361636/1361636_10140335_1474645567233_CWWLogo-color-hi-res--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="CWW logo"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">CyberWatch West logo</div> <div class="imageCredit">James Zyon</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Corrinne&nbsp;Sande</div> <div class="imageTitle">CWW logo</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The CyberWatch West (CWW) Advanced Technology Education Center, funded by the National Science Foundation (NSF), was established in October of 2011. The Center covers a 14-state region and is led by four core educational partners: Whatcom Community College (WA); California State Polytechnic University, Pomona; California State University, San Bernardino; and Coastline Community College (CA). Whatcom Community College serves as the lead institution for the Center.  CWW?s mission is to strengthen the cybersecurity workforce in the Western United States by providing solutions to address the limited resources at community colleges through innovative curriculum development; building an online community for faculty professional growth and mentoring; creating a developmental pathway of competitions that facilitate growth of students? cybersecurity skills; and facilitating processes at the state and national level conducive to development of cybersecurity educational programs.  CWW accomplishments include:     Expansion into 14 states in the western region with over 100 member institutions from high schools, community colleges, and universities. The establishment of the first 2+2 transfer pathway for California cybersecurity students. The establishment of the first baccalaureate in cybersecurity in California at CaliforniaState University San Bernardino. Significant growth in participation by middle and high school students in cybersecurity competition events. Development of a new Critical Infrastructure cybersecurity curriculum for community colleges. Enhanced engagement with industry through industry events held throughout the region. Rapid expansion of the CyberPatriot program throughout the region. Increase in the number of CAE2Ys in the region from five to nine (180% increase). Convergence developing for cybersecurity education and overall awareness in the Western region &ndash; participation from all sectors, including K-12, industry, and Government.      CyberWatch West funding was renewed in 2015 and the center is starting its fifth year. This center has had a tremendous impact in the Western United States. Cybersecurity education programs are now established at colleges in every state in the 14 state region and beyond. This center is contributing to the overall economic and homeland security of the nation, and is impacting the lives of thousands of students who complete these college and university programs and are hired into well paying high-demand jobs.          Last Modified: 09/23/2016       Submitted by: Corrinne Sande]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
