<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Nanoscale Transition Metal Pnictides: Materials by Design</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>06/01/2014</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>420000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>420000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03070000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DMR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Materials Research</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Birgit Schwenzer</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>bschwenz@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924771</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>NON-TECHNICAL SUMMARY&lt;br/&gt;With support from the National Science Foundation, Division of Materials Research, the development of new materials and knowledge for the design of cooling devices will be achieved. Air conditioning and refrigeration is a part of daily life, with air conditioning consuming 5%, and commercial refrigeration up to 20%, of energy output. The conventional process of refrigeration (gas compression and expansion) has limited efficiency, and the refrigerants are often ozone-depleting and/or Greenhouse gases, raising concerns whenever inevitable leaks arise. A more energy efficient (by up to 50%) and environmentally friendly process is magnetic refrigeration, where application of a magnetic field to a magnetocaloric (MC) material results in heat emission, and removal of that field results in heat absorption, effectively acting as a heat pump. Traditional MC materials are based on the rare-earth metal gadolinium, which suffers from poor efficiency near room temperature and is prohibitively expensive. In this NSF-DMR supported project a rational approach will be exploited for the development of MC materials based on nanoparticles comprising earth-abundant elements.  The effect of nanoparticle composition and size, as well as interactions between particles on magnetic properties will studied en route to developing inexpensive and efficient devices for magnetic refrigeration.  Over the course of the project, graduate and undergraduate students will develop critical thinking and technical skills, as well as hands-on experience with cutting-edge techniques, for developing the next generation of advanced technologies.  The project will also introduce Detroit-area middle and high school girls, many of whom are underrepresented minorities, to materials science through the GO-GIRL (Gaining Options-Girls Investigate Real Life) Material Girls outreach project.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;TECHNICAL SUMMARY&lt;br/&gt;With support from the National Science Foundation, Division of Materials Research, the principal investigator will produce functional transition metal pnictide (pnicogen = Group 15 element) nanoparticles and assemblies, focusing on materials for magnetic refrigeration (MR). Transition metal pnictides comprise a large but relatively underexplored class of materials, despite having properties that span the energy landscape. These materials are being investigated in thermoelectric devices (waste heat conversion), batteries (energy storage), catalysis (fuel processing), and magnetic refrigeration (climate control). Many of the envisioned advances in these technologies presume the ability to control the physical dimensions of the materials on the nanoscale, a significant challenge. Moreover, confinement to nanoscale dimensions impacts properties in sometimes unexpected ways (intraparticle effects), as does integration/assembly (interparticle effects). These issues have hampered the development of transition metal pnictide nanoparticles to address key technological problems.   MR is based on the absorption and release of energy during a magnetic transition (the magnetocaloric effect), and is 50% more efficient than traditional gas compression/expansion systems and more environmentally friendly, as it does not exploit ozone-depleting or greenhouse gases. Heretofore inaccessible but promising nanoscale phases for MR will be produced by exploiting ion-exchange routes and direct syntheses, targeting Fe-doped Mn pnictides (Aim 1). On a parallel track, anion (P, Sb) doped MnAs nanoparticles will be synthesized and detailed structure-property-size correlations established (Aim 2). This information will be used to narrow the parameter space for production of new materials in Aim 1 so as to target the most promising phases and sizes. The final parallel investigation (Aim 3) will focus on integration and assessment of interparticle interactions in known phases, subsequently moving to new phases as materials from Aims 1 and 2 become available.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>05/13/2014</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/13/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1361470</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Stephanie</FirstName>
<LastName>Brock</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>L</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Stephanie L Brock</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>sbrock@chem.wayne.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON/>
<NSF_ID>000427611</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/13/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Wayne State University</Name>
<CityName>Detroit</CityName>
<ZipCode>482023622</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>3135772424</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>5057 Woodward</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[6th Floor]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Michigan</StateName>
<StateCode>MI</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>13</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MI13</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>001962224</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>WAYNE STATE UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>001962224</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Wayne State University]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>MI</StateCode>
<ZipCode>482023929</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Michigan</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>13</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MI13</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1762</Code>
<Text>SOLID STATE &amp; MATERIALS CHEMIS</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7237</Code>
<Text>NANO NON-SOLIC SCI &amp; ENG AWD</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7969</Code>
<Text>FY 2010 Funding for PTR</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0114</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~420000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>With support from the National Science Foundation, Division of Materials Research (NSF-DMR), new materials and fundamental insights into their size-dependent physical properties relevant to energy-efficient refrigeration technologies has been achieved. Despite continuous improvements in compressor efficiencies, refrigeration methods based on gas-compression, including air-conditioning and commercial refrigeration, consume up to 17% of the global electrical energy supply. Magnetic refrigeration (MR), in which magnetic ordering and relaxation in a solid phase acts as a heat pump has the potential to dramatically increase the efficiency of the process (theoretically by up to 50%), while eliminating the use of refrigerant gases that contribute to the Greenhouse effect. Most of the conventional MR materials are based on gadolinium (Gd) compounds, but Gd is an expensive metal with a low natural abundance, making it non-ideal for large-scale commercial deployment.&nbsp; Accordingly, recent efforts in MR have focused on exploiting earth-abundant, inexpensive elemental components.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>In this NSF-DMR project, the Materials by Design (MbD) paradigm was exploited to develop new materials for MR. In MbD, an active feedback loop that links materials synthesis, physical properties and integration is employed to ensure that materials with ideal properties can be synthetically accessed and integrated without loss of functionality.&nbsp; In this project, transition metal pnictide (pnicogen = Group 15 element) nanomaterials were studied because bulk phase analogs are known to exhibit a strong magnetocaloric effect (MCE) in which magnetic changes are accompanied by significant absorption or release of heat.&nbsp; However, bulk phases also have limitations including (1) a limited temperature range of operation, dictated by the stoichiometry of the chemical constituents; (2) reduced cycling efficiency due to losses associated with poor reversibility (hysteresis). By reducing the size of the particle to the nanoscale and simultaneously adding additional elemental components (doping), these deficits are being addressed.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>Over the course of the NSF-DMR project, syntheses for manganese arsenide (MnAs) nanoparticles incorporating low (&lt;4%) substitution of phosphorus (P) for As have been developed (MnAs:P). MnAs:P nanoparticles exhibit P concentration-dependent transition temperatures (corresponding to the operational temperature for MR), enabling responsiveness to a broad range of temperatures near room temperature. Likewise, smaller particles appear to respond with minimal losses, desirable behavior that is distinct from their bulk counterparts. The incorporation of antimony (Sb) for As was also studied, starting from a systematic evaluation of MnSb nanoparticle syntheses that led to the targeted materials, but with significant loss of magnetism due to surface oxidation. Treatment protocols to enhance the magnetic characteristics of MnSb were successfully conducted. Finally, on the integration end, transition metal phosphide nanoparticles were assembled into 3-D porous architectures (aerogels) to evaluate the consequences of particle interactions on magnetic properties, work that is still in progress.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>In addition to impacting development of materials for MR, the NSF-DMR project is also influencing unrelated fields, by developing syntheses to transition metal pnictide nanoparticles, since these are also of interest as earth-abundant catalytic materials for hydrogen production from water and removal of sulfur species in petroleum refining. With respect to development of human resources, this research has resulted in the training of seven doctoral students and two undergraduates in state-of-the art techniques for materials synthesis and characterization. Of these, six are female and two are members of underrepresented groups in the sciences (one Samoan and one Hispanic); six Ph.D.s have been produced as well as 1. B.S. degree. Finally, educational modules focusing on engaging 8-12<sup>th</sup> grade students in Science, Technology, Engineering and Math were developed for the Gaining Options: Girls Investigate Real Life (GO-GIRL) program. Some 500+ adolescent girls from the Metro Detroit area, comprising a large cohort (&gt;80%) of African Americans, came to campus and participated in hands-on activities over the course of the grant.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 03/21/2019<br>      Modified by: Stephanie&nbsp;L&nbsp;Brock</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ With support from the National Science Foundation, Division of Materials Research (NSF-DMR), new materials and fundamental insights into their size-dependent physical properties relevant to energy-efficient refrigeration technologies has been achieved. Despite continuous improvements in compressor efficiencies, refrigeration methods based on gas-compression, including air-conditioning and commercial refrigeration, consume up to 17% of the global electrical energy supply. Magnetic refrigeration (MR), in which magnetic ordering and relaxation in a solid phase acts as a heat pump has the potential to dramatically increase the efficiency of the process (theoretically by up to 50%), while eliminating the use of refrigerant gases that contribute to the Greenhouse effect. Most of the conventional MR materials are based on gadolinium (Gd) compounds, but Gd is an expensive metal with a low natural abundance, making it non-ideal for large-scale commercial deployment.  Accordingly, recent efforts in MR have focused on exploiting earth-abundant, inexpensive elemental components.     In this NSF-DMR project, the Materials by Design (MbD) paradigm was exploited to develop new materials for MR. In MbD, an active feedback loop that links materials synthesis, physical properties and integration is employed to ensure that materials with ideal properties can be synthetically accessed and integrated without loss of functionality.  In this project, transition metal pnictide (pnicogen = Group 15 element) nanomaterials were studied because bulk phase analogs are known to exhibit a strong magnetocaloric effect (MCE) in which magnetic changes are accompanied by significant absorption or release of heat.  However, bulk phases also have limitations including (1) a limited temperature range of operation, dictated by the stoichiometry of the chemical constituents; (2) reduced cycling efficiency due to losses associated with poor reversibility (hysteresis). By reducing the size of the particle to the nanoscale and simultaneously adding additional elemental components (doping), these deficits are being addressed.     Over the course of the NSF-DMR project, syntheses for manganese arsenide (MnAs) nanoparticles incorporating low (&lt;4%) substitution of phosphorus (P) for As have been developed (MnAs:P). MnAs:P nanoparticles exhibit P concentration-dependent transition temperatures (corresponding to the operational temperature for MR), enabling responsiveness to a broad range of temperatures near room temperature. Likewise, smaller particles appear to respond with minimal losses, desirable behavior that is distinct from their bulk counterparts. The incorporation of antimony (Sb) for As was also studied, starting from a systematic evaluation of MnSb nanoparticle syntheses that led to the targeted materials, but with significant loss of magnetism due to surface oxidation. Treatment protocols to enhance the magnetic characteristics of MnSb were successfully conducted. Finally, on the integration end, transition metal phosphide nanoparticles were assembled into 3-D porous architectures (aerogels) to evaluate the consequences of particle interactions on magnetic properties, work that is still in progress.     In addition to impacting development of materials for MR, the NSF-DMR project is also influencing unrelated fields, by developing syntheses to transition metal pnictide nanoparticles, since these are also of interest as earth-abundant catalytic materials for hydrogen production from water and removal of sulfur species in petroleum refining. With respect to development of human resources, this research has resulted in the training of seven doctoral students and two undergraduates in state-of-the art techniques for materials synthesis and characterization. Of these, six are female and two are members of underrepresented groups in the sciences (one Samoan and one Hispanic); six Ph.D.s have been produced as well as 1. B.S. degree. Finally, educational modules focusing on engaging 8-12th grade students in Science, Technology, Engineering and Math were developed for the Gaining Options: Girls Investigate Real Life (GO-GIRL) program. Some 500+ adolescent girls from the Metro Detroit area, comprising a large cohort (&gt;80%) of African Americans, came to campus and participated in hands-on activities over the course of the grant.       Last Modified: 03/21/2019       Submitted by: Stephanie L Brock]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
