<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Accurate molecular crystal modeling for nuclear magnetic resonance crystallography</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2014</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>443001.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>443001</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03090000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CHE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Chemistry</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Evelyn Goldfield</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>egoldfie@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032920000</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Gregory Beran at the University of California, Riverside is supported by an award from the Chemical Theory, Models and Computational Methods (CTMC) Program in the Chemistry Division and the Computational and Data-Enabled Science and Engineering Program  (CDS&amp;E)  to develop  state-of-the-art computational strategies for predicting the most stable molecular crystal structures and for coupling these predictions with experiments to determine crystal packing,  The efficacy of pharmaceuticals, novel organic electronic materials, and many other crystalline solids depends critically on the manner in which the molecules pack together to form crystals.  In the longer term, these studies of pharmaceutical crystal packing will help the formulation of medicinal drugs with improved shelf-life, solubility, and other important properties.  Software resulting from this project will be made widely available to the community.  The principal investigator also engages in outreach activities to bring awareness of scientific computing to the a broad range of students and to the general public.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;To achieve these goals, new electronic structure algorithms that provide more accurate descriptions of intermolecular interactions at lower computational cost are being developed that will enable reliable crystal structure modeling.  Improved techniques for predicting nuclear magnetic resonance chemical shifts are being developed to allow mapping between experimentally measured spectra and three-dimensional structural models.  High-quality chemical shift predictions are needed to discriminate among different crystal packing forms.  These techniques are being integrated into a workflow that combines crystal structure prediction, nuclear magnetic resonance spectrum simulations, and experimental measurements to identify the structures for several unknown crystal forms of two important pharmaceuticals.  The new methods are incorporated into software which will be released to under open-source licensing terms.  The code will be integrated into the Q-CHEM package, a commercial code with a very large user base.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/12/2014</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/12/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1362465</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Gregory</FirstName>
<LastName>Beran</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>J</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Gregory J Beran</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>gregory.beran@ucr.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>9518275535</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000508339</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/12/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of California-Riverside</Name>
<CityName>RIVERSIDE</CityName>
<ZipCode>925210217</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>9518275535</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>Research &amp; Economic Development</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[245 University Office Building]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>44</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CA44</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>627797426</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>REGENTS OF THE UNIVERSITY OF CALIFORNIA AT RIVERSIDE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>071549000</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of California-Riverside]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>925210001</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>41</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CA41</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>6881</Code>
<Text>Chem Thry, Mdls &amp; Cmptnl Mthds</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>8084</Code>
<Text>CDS&amp;E</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7433</Code>
<Text>CyberInfra Frmwrk 21st (CIF21)</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8084</Code>
<Text>CDS&amp;E</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9216</Code>
<Text>ADVANCED SOFTWARE TECH &amp; ALGOR</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9263</Code>
<Text>COMPUTATIONAL SCIENCE &amp; ENGING</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0114</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~443001</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><!--   @page { margin: 0.79in }   p { margin-bottom: 0.1in; line-height: 120% } --> <p>How molecules pack together to form a crystalline solid has a tremendous impact on the properties of the solid.  For example, the majority of pharmaceuticals are delivered in crystalline form, and surveys indicate that 1 in 2 drugs exhibits multiple crystal packing forms, or polymorphs. Crystal packing can affect how readily a drug tablet dissolves in the body, and an insoluble crystal polymorph will  prevent the drug molecules from having their intended effect in the  patient.  Indeed, drug recalls of ritonavir (HIV), rotigotine (Parkinson's disease) and carbamazepine (seizures) have been linked to  unexpected occurrences of insoluble crystal polymorphs.  To understand  polymorphism in existing drugs and to ward off potential problems in  new drugs, there is a considerable need to understand which polymorphs might form and to predict the properties of those polymorphs.  Crystal  polymorphism also affects many other practical branches of chemistry,  ranging from foods to organic semiconductor materials.</p> <p>This project successfully addressed all three goals of the original proposal. For Objective 1, we improved our understanding of how groups of molecules interact and how the interactions differ when you have more than only two molecules, and we developed a new electronic structure method capable of describing such interactions effectively.  These advances are important not only for molecular crystals, but also for liquids or other  condensed-phase molecular systems.</p> <p>For Objective 2, we developed a new computationally efficient tool for modeling nuclear magnetic resonance (NMR) chemical shifts in molecular crystals.  NMR is widely used by the pharmaceutical industry and others to characterize crystal structures, and NMR chemical shift prediction is used to connect the experimentally observed spectrum to a three-dimensional crystal structure.  Our new modeling approach can predict chemical shifts with up to 30-40% higher accuracy than previously used techniques, and this higher accuracy translates to increased discrimination between correct and incorrect structural assignments.  We also developed improved techniques for modeling how crystal structures change with temperature and pressure, to model NMR and other properties under conditions that more closely mimic the real world.  All of these tools facilitate the study of and differentiation between crystal polymorphs.</p> <p>For Objective 3, we helped solve the crystal structure of 9-tert-butyl anthracene ester nanorods, which exhibit very interesting photomechanical properties.  The combination of experiment and the new methods developed here proved key to solving the structures, and that in turn has revealed the mechanism through which these nanorods expand.  The insights gained could help design new molecular materials with active, rather than static, mechanical properties.  We also demonstrated that the existing understanding of high-pressure carbon dioxide was flawed, with our modeling revealing that two claimed phases of carbon dioxide are actually the same.  A proper understanding of the high-pressure carbon dioxide phase diagram is important for geo- and astrochemistry.</p> <p>This funding resulted in 22 peer-reviewed publications and one book chapter, and the research has been presented in approximately 30 talks/seminars.  The project supported the training of six graduate students, two undergraduates, and one postdoctoral researcher.  The graduate students and postdoctoral researcher have subsequently obtained positions in academia and industry.  The undergraduates have either started graduate school or are in the process of applying to graduate school in Chemistry or related areas.  The principal investigator has also been active in outreach activities, including elementary school science demonstrations and career days, lectures on graduate school and academic careers to college students (many from disadvantaged backgrounds), and a public lecture on the importance of crystal polymorphism in daily life.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 10/29/2018<br>      Modified by: Gregory&nbsp;J&nbsp;Beran</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[  How molecules pack together to form a crystalline solid has a tremendous impact on the properties of the solid.  For example, the majority of pharmaceuticals are delivered in crystalline form, and surveys indicate that 1 in 2 drugs exhibits multiple crystal packing forms, or polymorphs. Crystal packing can affect how readily a drug tablet dissolves in the body, and an insoluble crystal polymorph will  prevent the drug molecules from having their intended effect in the  patient.  Indeed, drug recalls of ritonavir (HIV), rotigotine (Parkinson's disease) and carbamazepine (seizures) have been linked to  unexpected occurrences of insoluble crystal polymorphs.  To understand  polymorphism in existing drugs and to ward off potential problems in  new drugs, there is a considerable need to understand which polymorphs might form and to predict the properties of those polymorphs.  Crystal  polymorphism also affects many other practical branches of chemistry,  ranging from foods to organic semiconductor materials.  This project successfully addressed all three goals of the original proposal. For Objective 1, we improved our understanding of how groups of molecules interact and how the interactions differ when you have more than only two molecules, and we developed a new electronic structure method capable of describing such interactions effectively.  These advances are important not only for molecular crystals, but also for liquids or other  condensed-phase molecular systems.  For Objective 2, we developed a new computationally efficient tool for modeling nuclear magnetic resonance (NMR) chemical shifts in molecular crystals.  NMR is widely used by the pharmaceutical industry and others to characterize crystal structures, and NMR chemical shift prediction is used to connect the experimentally observed spectrum to a three-dimensional crystal structure.  Our new modeling approach can predict chemical shifts with up to 30-40% higher accuracy than previously used techniques, and this higher accuracy translates to increased discrimination between correct and incorrect structural assignments.  We also developed improved techniques for modeling how crystal structures change with temperature and pressure, to model NMR and other properties under conditions that more closely mimic the real world.  All of these tools facilitate the study of and differentiation between crystal polymorphs.  For Objective 3, we helped solve the crystal structure of 9-tert-butyl anthracene ester nanorods, which exhibit very interesting photomechanical properties.  The combination of experiment and the new methods developed here proved key to solving the structures, and that in turn has revealed the mechanism through which these nanorods expand.  The insights gained could help design new molecular materials with active, rather than static, mechanical properties.  We also demonstrated that the existing understanding of high-pressure carbon dioxide was flawed, with our modeling revealing that two claimed phases of carbon dioxide are actually the same.  A proper understanding of the high-pressure carbon dioxide phase diagram is important for geo- and astrochemistry.  This funding resulted in 22 peer-reviewed publications and one book chapter, and the research has been presented in approximately 30 talks/seminars.  The project supported the training of six graduate students, two undergraduates, and one postdoctoral researcher.  The graduate students and postdoctoral researcher have subsequently obtained positions in academia and industry.  The undergraduates have either started graduate school or are in the process of applying to graduate school in Chemistry or related areas.  The principal investigator has also been active in outreach activities, including elementary school science demonstrations and career days, lectures on graduate school and academic careers to college students (many from disadvantaged backgrounds), and a public lecture on the importance of crystal polymorphism in daily life.                Last Modified: 10/29/2018       Submitted by: Gregory J Beran]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
