<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Limit Theorems in Dynamical Systems</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/15/2014</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>239990.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>239990</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DMS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Edward Taylor</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>It is well known that many deterministic systems exhibit random behavior. The simplest example of one such system is provided by a ball moving between two infinitely heavy periodically moving walls. This example was studied by Fermi and Ulam in the middle of the last century.  More complicated examples include the motion of charged particles in plasma and the motion of the asteroids in the asteroid belt. The aim of this proposal is to understand the origin of stochasticity (randomness of motion) of such systems using recent advances in chaotic dynamics, with the goals of making precise predictions about their behavior.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The PI will continue his work on limit theorems for dynamical systems combing the methods of probability theory and dynamical systems. The main directions of research will be the following: (1) Evolution of adiabatic invariants, and (2) Local Limit Theorems. This proposal will concentrate on the methods of obtaining precise asymptotics which allows control of the limit distributions on long temporal scales and short spatial scales. The broader impact of the proposed activity will be in applying dynamical systems tools to other fields including probability theory, number theory, and statistical physics. The PI will continue his synergistic activities including organizing conferences, giving lectures and minicourses on recent advances in dynamics, writing survey papers and mentoring graduate students.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/03/2014</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>04/29/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1362064</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Dmitry</FirstName>
<LastName>Dolgopyat</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Dmitry Dolgopyat</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>dmitry@math.umd.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>3014055118</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000196443</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/03/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Maryland, College Park</Name>
<CityName>College Park</CityName>
<ZipCode>207425141</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>3014056269</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>3112 LEE BLDG 7809 Regents Drive</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Maryland</StateName>
<StateCode>MD</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MD05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>790934285</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF MARYLAND, COLLEGE PARK</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>003256088</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Maryland, College Park]]></Name>
<CityName>College Park</CityName>
<StateCode>MD</StateCode>
<ZipCode>207425141</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[3112 LEE BLDG 7809 Regents Drive]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Maryland</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MD05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1281</Code>
<Text>ANALYSIS PROGRAM</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0114</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0116</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~148420</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2016~91570</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The project was devoted to better understanding of stochasticity of detrministic systems. The particular attention was paid to sharp constructive estimates for systems whose evolution laws may change with time, including local limit theorems descibing the fine scale structure of complicated deterministic systems. The results of this project have a wide range of applicability both in science where they could be used to describe the motion of sabatomic particles as well as asymptotics of branching processes which describe the evolution of colonies of biological organisms and in different branches of mathematics including number theory and geometry.</p> <p>The highlights of the current projects are sharp local limit theorems for non autonomous systems and new type of limit theorems for low complecity systems where time is sampled at random.&nbsp;</p> <p>The project also contributed to training of young scientists. Two graduate students involved in this project have obtained their PhD during the lifeteme of the project and two more started their research. The PI has delivered two week long minicourses on the topics related to current project which were attended by a number of graduate students and postdoctoral fellows working in Dynamics and related fields and published a book containing lectures from a special semester devoted to Fuctuations and Large Deviations in deterministic systems he has organized at Bernoulli Center.&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 09/06/2017<br>      Modified by: Dmitry&nbsp;Dolgopyat</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The project was devoted to better understanding of stochasticity of detrministic systems. The particular attention was paid to sharp constructive estimates for systems whose evolution laws may change with time, including local limit theorems descibing the fine scale structure of complicated deterministic systems. The results of this project have a wide range of applicability both in science where they could be used to describe the motion of sabatomic particles as well as asymptotics of branching processes which describe the evolution of colonies of biological organisms and in different branches of mathematics including number theory and geometry.  The highlights of the current projects are sharp local limit theorems for non autonomous systems and new type of limit theorems for low complecity systems where time is sampled at random.   The project also contributed to training of young scientists. Two graduate students involved in this project have obtained their PhD during the lifeteme of the project and two more started their research. The PI has delivered two week long minicourses on the topics related to current project which were attended by a number of graduate students and postdoctoral fellows working in Dynamics and related fields and published a book containing lectures from a special semester devoted to Fuctuations and Large Deviations in deterministic systems he has organized at Bernoulli Center.                    Last Modified: 09/06/2017       Submitted by: Dmitry Dolgopyat]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
