<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Orthogonal Polynomials and Random Matrices</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/15/2014</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>240000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>240000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DMS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Justin Holmer</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>It was the physicist Eugene Wigner who in the 1950's first used eigenvalues of random matrices to model the interactions of neutrons for heavy nuclei. Random matrices have since become a major research area with connections to mathematical physics, probability theory, number theory, numerical analysis, and orthogonal polynomials. Indeed, there is a well known anecdote about an interaction in the early 1970's between the physicist Freeman Dyson, and number theorist Hugh Montgomery, at Princeton, where their discussions led to the realization that there is a link between random matrices and the Riemann Zeta function of number theory. The PI's focus is on "universal" behavior of these random matrices: certain features seem to be independent of almost any underlying assumption, and consequently hold very generally. This has been known for a long time, and has been explored by both mathematical physicists and pure mathematicians. The techniques that have been developed to study this "universality" have been useful in many other areas of mathematics. This proposal will develop appropriate tools from orthogonal polynomials and classical analysis, and use these to establish "universal" features in as great a generality as possible. There will be also be an educational component to the project, involving  collaboration with other researchers, organization of conferences, editorial duties, and supervision of undergraduate and/or graduate students.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The specific goals of the project include investigating the ramifications and generalizations of a variational property recently established by the PI. It is hoped that this will enable one to establish universality limits for Hermitian ensembles under minimal conditions on measures with compact support, and also for varying measures. Monotonicity in the measure, and techniques of orthogonal polynomials are key tools in this approach. Somewhat more ambitious is the goal of extending the variational principle to beta-ensembles. This will include  asymptotics of generalized Christoffel functions involving alternating polynomials in several variables. Discrete analogues will also be studied. Another major goal is developing the theory of Dirichlet orthogonal polynomials, and investigating their application to the Lindelof hypothesis for the Riemann Zeta function. Additional goals include investigating biorthogonal polynomials, and related numerical quadratures; orthogonal polynomials on curves in the plane, and Pade approximations.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/15/2014</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>04/04/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1362208</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Doron</FirstName>
<LastName>Lubinsky</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Doron Lubinsky</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>lubinsky@math.gatech.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>4043852133</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000482471</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/15/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Georgia Tech Research Corporation</Name>
<CityName>Atlanta</CityName>
<ZipCode>303320420</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>4048944819</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>Office of Sponsored Programs</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Georgia</StateName>
<StateCode>GA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>GA05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>097394084</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>GEORGIA TECH RESEARCH CORPORATION</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>097394084</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Georgia Institute of Technology]]></Name>
<CityName>Atlanta</CityName>
<StateCode>GA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>303320002</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[225 North Avenue]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Georgia</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>GA05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1281</Code>
<Text>ANALYSIS PROGRAM</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0114</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0115</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0116</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~79439</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2015~82722</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2016~77839</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>It was the physicist Eugene Wigner who in the 1950's first used eigenvalues of random matrices to model the interactions of neutrons for heavy nuclei. Random matrices have since become a major research area with connections to mathematical physics, probability theory, number theory, numerical analysis, and orthogonal polynomials. The PI&rsquo;s focus is on &ldquo;universal&rdquo; behavior of these random matrices: certain features seem to be independent of almost any underlying assumption, and consequently hold very generally. This has been known for a long time, and has been explored by both mathematical physicists and pure mathematicians. The techniques that have been developed to study this &ldquo;universality&rdquo; have been useful in many other areas of mathematics. This proposal&rsquo;s goal was to develop appropriate tools from orthogonal polynomials and classical analysis, and use these to establish &ldquo;universal&rdquo; features in as great a generality as possible.</p> <p>The specific goals of the project included establishing universality limits in as general a context as possible. &nbsp;This was achieved for varying measures in various settings. In addition, the fluctuation of spacings of eigenvalues was shown to exhibit a Gaussian behavior fairly generally. Perhaps the most significant achievement of the project was the discovery that universality limits can be used to establish pointwise asymptotics of orthogonal polynomials. The ramifications of this are still being explored.</p> <p>Another major focus of the project is Pad&eacute; approximation. These rational functions are a special case of the Hermite- Pad&eacute; approximation, which was introduced by the French mathematician Charles Hermite in the 19<sup>th</sup> century, in order to prove that the number e is transcendental. Hermite&rsquo;s student Henri Pad&eacute;, studied the special case that now bears his name. They have many applications, including approximation of special functions, location of singularities in statistical physics, and numerical solution of partial differential equations. One of the inherent problems of Pad&eacute; approximation is the appearance of &ldquo;spurious poles&rdquo;, namely singularities that have little to do with the underlying function.</p> <p>One of the significant results of this project was to show how spurious poles are closely related to the appearance of extra interpolation points. In particular, it was shown that when there are no spurious poles, there are necessarily no extra interpolation points. The deeper converse is that when there are no extra interpolation points, at least a subsequence of approximants have no spurious poles. This has an impact on the convergence theory of sequences of Pad&eacute; approximants.</p> <p>The results were disseminated in about twenty papers, a research monograph, and in several plenary conference talks at conferences. There was also an educational component to the project, involving collaboration with other researchers, organization of conferences, editorial duties, and supervision of undergraduate research projects. The PI also co-organized two major conferences, and a workshop.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 05/01/2018<br>      Modified by: Doron&nbsp;Lubinsky</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ It was the physicist Eugene Wigner who in the 1950's first used eigenvalues of random matrices to model the interactions of neutrons for heavy nuclei. Random matrices have since become a major research area with connections to mathematical physics, probability theory, number theory, numerical analysis, and orthogonal polynomials. The PI?s focus is on "universal" behavior of these random matrices: certain features seem to be independent of almost any underlying assumption, and consequently hold very generally. This has been known for a long time, and has been explored by both mathematical physicists and pure mathematicians. The techniques that have been developed to study this "universality" have been useful in many other areas of mathematics. This proposal?s goal was to develop appropriate tools from orthogonal polynomials and classical analysis, and use these to establish "universal" features in as great a generality as possible.  The specific goals of the project included establishing universality limits in as general a context as possible.  This was achieved for varying measures in various settings. In addition, the fluctuation of spacings of eigenvalues was shown to exhibit a Gaussian behavior fairly generally. Perhaps the most significant achievement of the project was the discovery that universality limits can be used to establish pointwise asymptotics of orthogonal polynomials. The ramifications of this are still being explored.  Another major focus of the project is Pad&eacute; approximation. These rational functions are a special case of the Hermite- Pad&eacute; approximation, which was introduced by the French mathematician Charles Hermite in the 19th century, in order to prove that the number e is transcendental. Hermite?s student Henri Pad&eacute;, studied the special case that now bears his name. They have many applications, including approximation of special functions, location of singularities in statistical physics, and numerical solution of partial differential equations. One of the inherent problems of Pad&eacute; approximation is the appearance of "spurious poles", namely singularities that have little to do with the underlying function.  One of the significant results of this project was to show how spurious poles are closely related to the appearance of extra interpolation points. In particular, it was shown that when there are no spurious poles, there are necessarily no extra interpolation points. The deeper converse is that when there are no extra interpolation points, at least a subsequence of approximants have no spurious poles. This has an impact on the convergence theory of sequences of Pad&eacute; approximants.  The results were disseminated in about twenty papers, a research monograph, and in several plenary conference talks at conferences. There was also an educational component to the project, involving collaboration with other researchers, organization of conferences, editorial duties, and supervision of undergraduate research projects. The PI also co-organized two major conferences, and a workshop.       Last Modified: 05/01/2018       Submitted by: Doron Lubinsky]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
