<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Fiber Optic Method for Bridge Health Assessment Based on Long-Gauge Sensors</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2014</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>200000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>200000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CMMI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Civil, Mechanical, &amp; Manufact Inn</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Yick Hsuan</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>For civil infrastructure there is a need for structural health monitoring to provide an optimized maintenance, lifetime extension, and improved safety. Structural health monitoring can provide accurate and in-time information concerning condition and residual life of civil infrastructure. It consists of instrumentation of the structure with sensors and transformation of the collected data into meaningful and actionable information for the owner or manager of the structure, so decision makers can undertake informed and economical maintenance and repair actions. This project focuses on the typical bridge beam systems that represent 60 percent of all US bridges.  &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The objective of this project is to pursue research in creating and validating a universal health assessment system for typical beam bridges based on static and dynamic measured strains using long-gauge fiber optic sensors. This research will provide means to avoid disruptive closures and catastrophic failures, while also ensuring on-going reliable health assessment. The success of the project stands to have profound societal impact by addressing public safety and minimizing economic disruption. The neutral axis and the deformed shape are universal beam parameters that reflect bridge health and performance condition. Real-time determination of these parameters has potential to enable a robust bridge health monitoring assessment method. Fundamental questions associated with determination of these parameters addressed in this project are related to:  1) variability of these parameters and uncertainty in their determination under damaged and undamaged conditions, and 2) transformation of the collected data into meaningful and actionable information to the bridge owner or manager. The objective of the project is to create a reliable method for performance and health assessment of beams in bridges based on determination of the position of the neutral axis and on deformed shape. State-of-the-art long-gauge fiber optic strain sensors have inherent advantage to acquire data relevant to the global structural scale. Algorithms will be created based on general probabilistic approaches, Bayesian structural identification, and performance prediction models taking in to account variability and uncertainties in collected data. Experimental validation will be performed both through laboratory tests and controlled tests on two bridges in-use. The method will be applicable to existing and new beam bridges and will not be material dependent.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>03/30/2014</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>03/30/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1362723</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Branko</FirstName>
<LastName>Glisic</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Branko Glisic</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>bglisic@princeton.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6092588278</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000528562</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>03/30/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Princeton University</Name>
<CityName>Princeton</CityName>
<ZipCode>085442020</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6092583090</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>Off. of Research &amp; Proj. Admin.</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[P.O. Box 36]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New Jersey</StateName>
<StateCode>NJ</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>12</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NJ12</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>002484665</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>TRUSTEES OF PRINCETON UNIVERSITY, THE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>002484665</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Princeton University]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>NJ</StateCode>
<ZipCode>085442020</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New Jersey</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>12</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NJ12</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1637</Code>
<Text>Structural and Architectural E</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>039E</Code>
<Text>STRUCTURAL SYSTEMS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>040E</Code>
<Text>Haz mitigation of structural sys</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>043E</Code>
<Text>EARTHQUAKE ENGINEERING</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0114</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~200000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The most common bridge systems in the U.S. are composed of beams; in fact 60% of the U.S. bridges are beam systems such as multi-, T-, box-, and channel- beams. These typical bridges compose 70% of all deficient bridges in the U.S. Insights into true structural behavior, capacity, and vulnerability of this bridge type are a necessity for efficient, effective, and economical preservation and maintenance actions. Structural Health Monitoring (SHM) holds great potential, but is rarely utilized on typical bridges due to limited reliability of current monitoring technologies. The objective of this project was to research, create, and validate a universal yet reliable methods for health assessment of typical beam bridges based on static and dynamic strain monitoring using long-gauge fiber optic sensors.</p> <p>This research was facilitated by the inherent advantage of state-of-the-art long-gauge fiber optic strain sensors to acquire data relevant at the global structural scale. Four methods were created that address the monitoring and evaluation of the following four parameters: (1) the position of the neutral axis, (2) the deformed shape, (3) dynamic curvature ratios, and (4) prestress force (and prestress loss) distribution in long term. Each method includes (i) design of optimal sensor network, to best capture monitoring parameter, (ii) data analysis algorithms, to extract the desired parameter from strain measurements, (iii) rigorous evaluation measures of accuracy (limits of error or uncertainty), to enable setting thresholds for evaluation of structural health condition and performance, and (iv) validation in laboratory settings and on real structures, to assess practicality and applicability. The methods are universally applicable to a wide range of existing and new beam bridges, are not material dependent (except for method for determination of prestressed force), and do not require interference with traffic to be applied (e.g., no need to interrupt the traffic, to perform additional tests, etc.). To facilitate the application of the methods, flowcharts (guidelines) for their implementation are provided in published papers.</p> <p>The created methods have potential to provide means to avoid disruptive closures, costly repairs, and catastrophic structural failures of bridges, while also ensuring their on-going reliability through an efficient monitoring and health assessment. This stands to have profound societal impact by addressing public safety, minimizing economic disruption, and mitigating environmental damage. A widespread use of the methods based on long-gauge fiber optic sensors may create new job positions and set prevalence of the U.S. products and know-how in the world. Extensive implementation of SHM on typical infrastructure will provide invaluable experience through informed decision making and by reinforcing the U.S. competence in the field of SHM. To conduct the research itself, women in engineering and research were engaged through undergraduate and graduate student projects. The project outcomes are incorporated in Civil Engineering undergraduate and graduate courses at Princeton University, and graduate students were involved in undergraduate teaching activities. Special attention was paid to ensure that students experienced the interdisciplinary nature of the research, which combined structural engineering, metrology, and statistical analysis. Outreach to K-12 and broader public was realized through event &ldquo;Materials Science Day&rdquo; held in Princeton public library. Dissemination to academic and industrial communities, as well as infrastructure authorities, is ongoing through published papers, posters, seminars, websites, and live demonstrations on the Streicker Bridge.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 11/07/2017<br>      Modified by: Branko&nbsp;Glisic</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The most common bridge systems in the U.S. are composed of beams; in fact 60% of the U.S. bridges are beam systems such as multi-, T-, box-, and channel- beams. These typical bridges compose 70% of all deficient bridges in the U.S. Insights into true structural behavior, capacity, and vulnerability of this bridge type are a necessity for efficient, effective, and economical preservation and maintenance actions. Structural Health Monitoring (SHM) holds great potential, but is rarely utilized on typical bridges due to limited reliability of current monitoring technologies. The objective of this project was to research, create, and validate a universal yet reliable methods for health assessment of typical beam bridges based on static and dynamic strain monitoring using long-gauge fiber optic sensors.  This research was facilitated by the inherent advantage of state-of-the-art long-gauge fiber optic strain sensors to acquire data relevant at the global structural scale. Four methods were created that address the monitoring and evaluation of the following four parameters: (1) the position of the neutral axis, (2) the deformed shape, (3) dynamic curvature ratios, and (4) prestress force (and prestress loss) distribution in long term. Each method includes (i) design of optimal sensor network, to best capture monitoring parameter, (ii) data analysis algorithms, to extract the desired parameter from strain measurements, (iii) rigorous evaluation measures of accuracy (limits of error or uncertainty), to enable setting thresholds for evaluation of structural health condition and performance, and (iv) validation in laboratory settings and on real structures, to assess practicality and applicability. The methods are universally applicable to a wide range of existing and new beam bridges, are not material dependent (except for method for determination of prestressed force), and do not require interference with traffic to be applied (e.g., no need to interrupt the traffic, to perform additional tests, etc.). To facilitate the application of the methods, flowcharts (guidelines) for their implementation are provided in published papers.  The created methods have potential to provide means to avoid disruptive closures, costly repairs, and catastrophic structural failures of bridges, while also ensuring their on-going reliability through an efficient monitoring and health assessment. This stands to have profound societal impact by addressing public safety, minimizing economic disruption, and mitigating environmental damage. A widespread use of the methods based on long-gauge fiber optic sensors may create new job positions and set prevalence of the U.S. products and know-how in the world. Extensive implementation of SHM on typical infrastructure will provide invaluable experience through informed decision making and by reinforcing the U.S. competence in the field of SHM. To conduct the research itself, women in engineering and research were engaged through undergraduate and graduate student projects. The project outcomes are incorporated in Civil Engineering undergraduate and graduate courses at Princeton University, and graduate students were involved in undergraduate teaching activities. Special attention was paid to ensure that students experienced the interdisciplinary nature of the research, which combined structural engineering, metrology, and statistical analysis. Outreach to K-12 and broader public was realized through event "Materials Science Day" held in Princeton public library. Dissemination to academic and industrial communities, as well as infrastructure authorities, is ongoing through published papers, posters, seminars, websites, and live demonstrations on the Streicker Bridge.       Last Modified: 11/07/2017       Submitted by: Branko Glisic]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
