<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Planning Grant:  I/UCRC for Sustainable Use of Greenhouse Gases</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>04/01/2014</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>03/31/2015</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>11500.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>11500</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07070000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>IIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Industrial Innovation &amp; Partnersh</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Raffaella Montelli</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The planned I/UCRC for the Sustainable Use of Greenhouse Gases intends to undertake research aimed at advancing current theory and technology, and to become a scientific focal point within the renewables and sustainability fields. Work will include (a) novel scalable plant and algae based systems and synthetic biomimicry approaches to capture and convert CO2 and CH4 into methanol, sugars, fatty acids, and oils, (b) scalable fermentation and biohybrid catalytic approaches to up-convert these into high demand, high value industrial chemicals and fuels, (c) application of these approaches to capture and convert greenhouse gases from distributed systems (e.g., the atmosphere) and concentrated systems (e.g., flu streams from coal and gas powered generators). &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Through the planned center?fs addressing of industrial needs through efficient capture and up-conversion of greenhouse gases to valuable chemicals and fuels, the major threats and potential impacts of climate change may be in part ameliorated on both a sustainable and profitable basis. The planned center will develop and promote a collaborative, focused scientific community on the sustainable use of greenhouse gases, including short courses, cross?]departmental and cross?]university graduate course offerings, and internships with member organizations. The Center will recruit and train underrepresented groups (minorities, women, and students with disabilities) through various existing programs on campus as well as new programs. &lt;br/&gt;</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>03/23/2014</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>03/23/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1362049</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>David</FirstName>
<LastName>Bayless</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>J</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>David J Bayless</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>bayless@ohio.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>7403314536</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000398206</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>03/23/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Ben</FirstName>
<LastName>Stuart</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>J</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Ben J Stuart</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>bstuart@odu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>7576834271</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000198048</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>03/23/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Jason</FirstName>
<LastName>Trembly</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Jason Trembly</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>trembly@ohio.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>7403314921</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000607541</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>03/23/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Ohio University</Name>
<CityName>ATHENS</CityName>
<ZipCode>457012979</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>7405932857</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>108 CUTLER HL</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Ohio</StateName>
<StateCode>OH</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>15</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>OH15</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>041077983</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>OHIO UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>041077983</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Ohio University]]></Name>
<CityName>Athens</CityName>
<StateCode>OH</StateCode>
<ZipCode>457012979</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[122 Stocker Center]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Ohio</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>15</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>OH15</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>5761</Code>
<Text>IUCRC-Indust-Univ Coop Res Ctr</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>5761</Code>
<Text>INDUSTRY/UNIV COOP RES CENTERS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8042</Code>
<Text>Health and Safety</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0114</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~11500</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>There is growing global concern over the negative impact of greenhouse gases (primarily carbon dioxide and methane) in the atmosphere. At the same time, there is a demand for massive quantities of renewable and economical feedstocks to supply the global marketplace with carbon-based products (e.g. food, fuels, nutraceuticals, pharmaceuticals, plastics and advanced materials, etc.). It is the primary goal of the proposed Center for the Sustainable Use of Greenhouse Gases (CSUG2) to provide industry partners with sustainable and economically viable technological solutions for the capture of carbon emissions from a variety of industrial and natural sources, as well offering industry technologies to transform these sources into high value products through physical, chemical and biological means.</p> <p>Led by The Ohio State University, academic partners The University of Akron, the University of Toledo and Ohio University have united to form a state-wide collaboration of over 70 scholars to tackle the research needs of industry members. At the First Ohio Conference on the Sustainable Use of Greenhouse Gases in August 2014, over 100 interested faculty, staff, and student researchers from a wide array of colleges and departments networked and shared ideas and sought potential collaborations for novel and innovative approaches to greenhouse gas utilization.</p> <p>The CSUG2 team worked to identify and contact over 150 companies with a potential interest in the activities of the proposed Center with the desired result of attracting the industry representatives to an Industry Planning Meeting (IPM). After conducting two such IPMs in November 2014 and June 2015, the consortium is currently working to convince industry partners to pledge membership in the Center and they plan to submit a full proposal to NSF in the Fall of 2015.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 06/30/2015<br>      Modified by: Ben&nbsp;J&nbsp;Stuart</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ There is growing global concern over the negative impact of greenhouse gases (primarily carbon dioxide and methane) in the atmosphere. At the same time, there is a demand for massive quantities of renewable and economical feedstocks to supply the global marketplace with carbon-based products (e.g. food, fuels, nutraceuticals, pharmaceuticals, plastics and advanced materials, etc.). It is the primary goal of the proposed Center for the Sustainable Use of Greenhouse Gases (CSUG2) to provide industry partners with sustainable and economically viable technological solutions for the capture of carbon emissions from a variety of industrial and natural sources, as well offering industry technologies to transform these sources into high value products through physical, chemical and biological means.  Led by The Ohio State University, academic partners The University of Akron, the University of Toledo and Ohio University have united to form a state-wide collaboration of over 70 scholars to tackle the research needs of industry members. At the First Ohio Conference on the Sustainable Use of Greenhouse Gases in August 2014, over 100 interested faculty, staff, and student researchers from a wide array of colleges and departments networked and shared ideas and sought potential collaborations for novel and innovative approaches to greenhouse gas utilization.  The CSUG2 team worked to identify and contact over 150 companies with a potential interest in the activities of the proposed Center with the desired result of attracting the industry representatives to an Industry Planning Meeting (IPM). After conducting two such IPMs in November 2014 and June 2015, the consortium is currently working to convince industry partners to pledge membership in the Center and they plan to submit a full proposal to NSF in the Fall of 2015.       Last Modified: 06/30/2015       Submitted by: Ben J Stuart]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
