<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Collaborative Research:  Laboratory-to-Field Scaling and Geophysical Monitoring for Soil Bio-Improvement</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2014</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>205000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>205000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CMMI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Civil, Mechanical, &amp; Manufact Inn</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Richard Fragaszy</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The growth of large urban populations worldwide and the associated need to build on sites with problematic soils has increased the need for low-noise/low-energy ground improvement techniques to hinder soil settlements, increase soil strength, and prevent subsurface soil instabilities such as liquefaction. Microbial-induced carbonate precipitation (MICP) has emerged as a promising technique to improve soil sites because microorganisms capable of causing calcium carbonate precipitation are ubiquitous in earth systems, and naturally-occurring biogeochemical reactions can be augmented and engineered. However, MICP faces inherent soil type limitations and spatial variability issues, requires adequate quality control/adaptation, must satisfy required "permanency," and may pose unwanted environmental consequences. There is limited experience with upscaling successful laboratory results to field conditions, and there are high early costs inherently related to new technology.  The goal of this research is to combine emerging geophysical technologies with established soil strengthening techniques to first investigate the feasibility of MICP in the laboratory and then upscale the results in a field study case. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;MICP has emerged as a promising bio-mediated soil improvement technique. Carbonate precipitation can be engineered by biostimulation, whereby selected nutrients are injected into the soil and indigenous soil microorganisms are used to catalyze carbonate precipitation throughout the sediment porous network as a direct consequence of byproducts formed during cell growth or active metabolism. The effect of cementation on soil behavior depends on the amount and type of cementing agent, grain size distribution of the soil, density, and degree of confinement at the time of cementation, i.e., the stress-cementation history.  Carbonate precipitation reduces porosity, stiffens and strengthens the soil mass, alters the response of the internal fabric to stress changes, and increases the dilative tendency upon shear. Quality control is a critical component of any soil improvement effort. The process can be quantitatively examined in real time to assess the evolution and spatial extent of the bio-treatment and to adapt/optimize it to increase its efficiency. This research will explore complementary, real-time monitoring concepts.  The non-invasive, geophysical tools selected for this study will be developed and optimized in the laboratory, and then will be scaled up to field conditions.  This research will include the following activities: (1) explore environmentally-safe, optimal deployment strategies, (2) identify conditions to minimize spatial variability and develop control techniques, (3) test complementary process-monitoring techniques (elastic shear wave velocity and electrical-spectral induced polarization using both local and tomographic test conditions and penetration CPTu in the field), and (4) scale up laboratory studies to the field.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/19/2014</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>01/29/2019</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1362777</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Frederick</FirstName>
<LastName>Colwell</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>S</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Frederick S Colwell</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>rcolwell@coas.oregonstate.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5417375220</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000434129</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/19/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Oregon State University</Name>
<CityName>Corvallis</CityName>
<ZipCode>973318507</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5417374933</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>OREGON STATE UNIVERSITY</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Oregon</StateName>
<StateCode>OR</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>OR04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>053599908</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>OREGON STATE UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>053599908</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Oregon State University]]></Name>
<CityName>Corvallis</CityName>
<StateCode>OR</StateCode>
<ZipCode>973315503</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[104 CEOAS Admin]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Oregon</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>OR04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1634</Code>
<Text>GEOMECHANICS &amp; GEOMATERIALS</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1636</Code>
<Text>Geotechnical Engineering and M</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>025E</Code>
<Text>INFRASTRUCTURE MATERIALS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>036E</Code>
<Text>CIVIL INFRASTRUCTURE</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>037E</Code>
<Text>GEOTECHNICAL ENGINEERING</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>043E</Code>
<Text>EARTHQUAKE ENGINEERING</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1057</Code>
<Text>CIS BASE RESEARCH</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0114</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0115</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0116</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~1460</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2015~100367</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2016~103173</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Microbially induced calcite precipitation (MICP) is an alternative to existing soil stabilization techniques that use concrete for construction of foundations and to prevent erosion. It works by encouraging microorganisms that are naturally present in the subsurface to form a mineral cement that binds together loose soil or sand particles. During MICP it is important to study the changes in microbial communities in the soils or sediments because the types of microbes indicate whether the engineered plan is on track to completion and how it is progressing.&nbsp;&nbsp;Our research assessed how native microbial aquifer communities developed in response to a field study of MICP that involved adding dilute molasses as a carbon source and urea as a source of nitrogen and alkalinity to a shallow aquifer in western Colorado.&nbsp;&nbsp;This is an accepted practice and such additions to groundwater have been used in the past to induce MICP in aquifers. During the two-week MICP study we collected a series of groundwater and sediment samples from the field site and then measured microbial community composition (by sequencing 16S rRNA genes), microbial ureolytic potential (by screening for&nbsp;<em>ureC</em>gene copy numbers) and aquifer geochemistry. These measurements showed evidence of sequential microbial processes stimulated in the aquifer over the treatment period and reflected that MICP was successful and the conditions under which it developed. We found evidence of microbial taxa in the groundwater that are known to be capable of diverse biological processes including the formation of calcite cement. We detected an increase in the number of&nbsp;<em>ureC</em>genes in the microbial communities at the end of the injection period, suggesting an increase in the abundance of microbes with this gene which is required to induce MICP.&nbsp;Our biogeochemical findings matched several parallel measurements of the aquifer system indicating successful MICP: 1) evidence of formation of calcite (the desired cement); 2) changes in the electrical properties of the sediments that were consistent with calcite formation; and 3) a decrease in the ability of fluid to move through the aquifer. We identify geochemical and biological markers that highlight a progressive microbial community response when MICP is induced. These markers can be used by&nbsp;practitioners of MICP to assess progress and determine whether the manipulation is complete or requiring further amendment and assay. Along with other measurements that should be made during MICP the methods that we explored can be included as the technology moves to a phase where it is more commonly used.</p> <p>In a broader sense, the refinement of ways to evaluate successful MICP will lead to validation of the method and will move the technology towards a position where it can be used in lieu of more energy intensive strategies for solidifying loose soils and foundation materials.&nbsp;&nbsp;MICP represents one of many biostimulation approaches that serve as alternatives that can be judiciously used where conventional cementation processes are difficult or costly to implement. Our research also supported a graduate student in&nbsp;Microbiology at&nbsp;Oregon State University who completed her degree in 2018 and is now employed at Los Alamos National Laboratory. Furthermore, as a part of this research, each year our team offered public, free-choice learning opportunities through a DNA-extraction demonstration at the annual da Vinci Days celebration of science, arts, and engineering in Corvallis, OR and at public elementary schools in Corvallis.&nbsp;&nbsp;These outreach events allowed us to contact and inform approximately 1000 people in the general public (ages: 5-93) over several years. Lead PI Colwell has also given several public lectures (e.g., to the Academy of Life Long Learning in Corvallis; a Science Pub in Bend, OR) on the research topics covered by this MICP research. These experiences further extended the reach of the research findings beyond the scientific community.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 01/12/2020<br>      Modified by: Frederick&nbsp;S&nbsp;Colwell</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Microbially induced calcite precipitation (MICP) is an alternative to existing soil stabilization techniques that use concrete for construction of foundations and to prevent erosion. It works by encouraging microorganisms that are naturally present in the subsurface to form a mineral cement that binds together loose soil or sand particles. During MICP it is important to study the changes in microbial communities in the soils or sediments because the types of microbes indicate whether the engineered plan is on track to completion and how it is progressing.  Our research assessed how native microbial aquifer communities developed in response to a field study of MICP that involved adding dilute molasses as a carbon source and urea as a source of nitrogen and alkalinity to a shallow aquifer in western Colorado.  This is an accepted practice and such additions to groundwater have been used in the past to induce MICP in aquifers. During the two-week MICP study we collected a series of groundwater and sediment samples from the field site and then measured microbial community composition (by sequencing 16S rRNA genes), microbial ureolytic potential (by screening for ureCgene copy numbers) and aquifer geochemistry. These measurements showed evidence of sequential microbial processes stimulated in the aquifer over the treatment period and reflected that MICP was successful and the conditions under which it developed. We found evidence of microbial taxa in the groundwater that are known to be capable of diverse biological processes including the formation of calcite cement. We detected an increase in the number of ureCgenes in the microbial communities at the end of the injection period, suggesting an increase in the abundance of microbes with this gene which is required to induce MICP. Our biogeochemical findings matched several parallel measurements of the aquifer system indicating successful MICP: 1) evidence of formation of calcite (the desired cement); 2) changes in the electrical properties of the sediments that were consistent with calcite formation; and 3) a decrease in the ability of fluid to move through the aquifer. We identify geochemical and biological markers that highlight a progressive microbial community response when MICP is induced. These markers can be used by practitioners of MICP to assess progress and determine whether the manipulation is complete or requiring further amendment and assay. Along with other measurements that should be made during MICP the methods that we explored can be included as the technology moves to a phase where it is more commonly used.  In a broader sense, the refinement of ways to evaluate successful MICP will lead to validation of the method and will move the technology towards a position where it can be used in lieu of more energy intensive strategies for solidifying loose soils and foundation materials.  MICP represents one of many biostimulation approaches that serve as alternatives that can be judiciously used where conventional cementation processes are difficult or costly to implement. Our research also supported a graduate student in Microbiology at Oregon State University who completed her degree in 2018 and is now employed at Los Alamos National Laboratory. Furthermore, as a part of this research, each year our team offered public, free-choice learning opportunities through a DNA-extraction demonstration at the annual da Vinci Days celebration of science, arts, and engineering in Corvallis, OR and at public elementary schools in Corvallis.  These outreach events allowed us to contact and inform approximately 1000 people in the general public (ages: 5-93) over several years. Lead PI Colwell has also given several public lectures (e.g., to the Academy of Life Long Learning in Corvallis; a Science Pub in Bend, OR) on the research topics covered by this MICP research. These experiences further extended the reach of the research findings beyond the scientific community.       Last Modified: 01/12/2020       Submitted by: Frederick S Colwell]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
