<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Harmonic analysis and spaces of analytic functions in several variables</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2014</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>138000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>138000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DMS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Justin Holmer</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Operator theory, harmonic analysis, and analytic function theory of one variable form a collection of interwoven fields that were created to solve some of the most important problems in pure and applied mathematics.  For example, Norbert Wiener initiated the study of time series for the purpose of tackling engineering "prediction" problems in World War II.  Time series is a term for a sequence of "random" data, such as stock market prices or the positions of a jet being tracked.  Harmonic analysis, which can loosely be described as a set of techniques for breaking up a "signal," such as a sound, into fundamental "tones," provided a natural set of tools for solving time series prediction problems.  Operator theory and analytic function theory in one variable have had similar success in related engineering "control" problems involving feedback, for example, designing a thermostat or an automatic pilot.   These problems all involve "one-dimensional" data in a certain sense, and operator theory, harmonic analysis, and analytic function theory bring an impressive toolbox of related techniques to bear on them.  Multivariate versions of these theories exist to address multidimensional problems (e.g., image or video processing), but the connections between the different theories are weaker and less well understood.  It is the goal of this project to expand some known and particularly strong interactions of these fundamental subjects to build a more robust toolbox for addressing fundamentally multidimensional problems.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The specific topics this project will develop further are (1) characterizations of when a positive trigonometric polynomial can be factored as a single square, (2) weak factorization of Hardy spaces on the polydisk, and (3) operator theoretic models for bounded analytic functions.  Success in topic (1) will deepen our understanding of multivariate moment problems, multivariable polynomials, sums of squares decompositions and determinantal representations, and multivariate operator theory related to von Neumann's inequality. Success in topic (2) will bridge a gap between harmonic analysis and function theory in several variables and could lead to applications in Dirichlet series.  This project will use recent innovations in item (3) to study spaces of entire functions in several variables and their connections with Fourier analysis, which could have profound implications in old and difficult completeness problems in Fourier analysis.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/31/2014</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/31/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1363239</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Greg</FirstName>
<LastName>Knese</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Greg Knese</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>geknese@wustl.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>3149358614</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000396582</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/31/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Washington University</Name>
<CityName>Saint Louis</CityName>
<ZipCode>631304862</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>3147474134</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>CAMPUS BOX 1054</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[1 Brookings Drive]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Missouri</StateName>
<StateCode>MO</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MO01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>068552207</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>WASHINGTON UNIVERSITY, THE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>068552207</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Washington University]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>MO</StateCode>
<ZipCode>631304899</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Missouri</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MO01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1281</Code>
<Text>ANALYSIS PROGRAM</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9251</Code>
<Text>REU SUPP-Res Exp for Ugrd Supp</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0114</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~138000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Harmonic analysis is a field concerned with breaking up a sound, signal, or some other type of data efficiently into more basic pieces.&nbsp; The most famous example is that of Fourier analysis which gives a method for breaking up a sound into tones.&nbsp; On the other hand, complex analysis is a field concerned with studying analytic functions which in many ways can be thought of as a generalization of polynomials, functions built out of a complex variable through multiplication and addition.&nbsp; Harmonic analysis and complex analysis have deep ties that go back over a hundred years. A famous example of this is Nobert Wiener's work on gunfire control which led to prediction theory of time series in the 1940's.&nbsp;</p> <p>This project was concerned with deepening these ties in the realm of harmonic analysis of several variables (which would correspond to multi-dimensional data) and complex analysis of several variables (which is a generalization of the study of multi-variable polynomials).&nbsp; The PI solved a fundamental problems about rational functions in two variables, problems related to prediction theory in two variables, and two variable approximation theory problems.&nbsp; The PI also solved an open problem in operator theory, the 3x3 von Neumann inequality, which is about the relationship between multivariable polynomials and commuting matrices.&nbsp; The PI established new connections between complex/harmonic analysis and the field of hyperbolic or stable polynomials. &nbsp;</p> <p>A significant broader impact of this project was the PI's organization of the International Workshop on Operator Theory and Applications (IWOTA) held in July 2016 at Washington University in St. Louis.&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 09/07/2018<br>      Modified by: Greg&nbsp;Knese</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Harmonic analysis is a field concerned with breaking up a sound, signal, or some other type of data efficiently into more basic pieces.  The most famous example is that of Fourier analysis which gives a method for breaking up a sound into tones.  On the other hand, complex analysis is a field concerned with studying analytic functions which in many ways can be thought of as a generalization of polynomials, functions built out of a complex variable through multiplication and addition.  Harmonic analysis and complex analysis have deep ties that go back over a hundred years. A famous example of this is Nobert Wiener's work on gunfire control which led to prediction theory of time series in the 1940's.   This project was concerned with deepening these ties in the realm of harmonic analysis of several variables (which would correspond to multi-dimensional data) and complex analysis of several variables (which is a generalization of the study of multi-variable polynomials).  The PI solved a fundamental problems about rational functions in two variables, problems related to prediction theory in two variables, and two variable approximation theory problems.  The PI also solved an open problem in operator theory, the 3x3 von Neumann inequality, which is about the relationship between multivariable polynomials and commuting matrices.  The PI established new connections between complex/harmonic analysis and the field of hyperbolic or stable polynomials.    A significant broader impact of this project was the PI's organization of the International Workshop on Operator Theory and Applications (IWOTA) held in July 2016 at Washington University in St. Louis.        Last Modified: 09/07/2018       Submitted by: Greg Knese]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
