<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Workshop Travel to Study Analysis and Geometry in Metric Spaces</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>05/01/2015</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>10/31/2016</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>47840.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>47840</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DMS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Edward Taylor</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This award will provide support for sixteen U.S. mathematicians to participate in the Research Term on Analysis and Geometry in Metric Spaces from  April through June, 2015 at the Instituto de Ciencias Matemáticas (ICMAT) in Madrid, Spain.  Metric spaces are useful models anytime one wants to consider sets of objects with a natural notion of "distance" -- for example, images, DNA sequences, and data in general can be modeled with metric spaces.  Developing calculus in metric spaces is useful in part because it allows one to formulate and solve optimization problems in these settings. This research term will, in particular, integrate metric space theory with a wide variety of applications including image processing, reconstruction theory, control theory, and robotics.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;More specifically, program brings together three areas of metric space research: first-order analysis (including theories of Sobolev spaces, solutions to the p-Laplace equation, and functions of bounded variation on metric measure spaces), geometric measure theory and variational problems (particularly in the sub-Riemannian setting), and versions of weak curvature (for example, the the setting of Alexandrov spaces).  It is expected to facilitate crossflow of ideas and techniques between these areas and establish international collaborations between researchers. The schedule includes four, week-long minicourses for non-specialists and young researchers during the month of May taught by leading experts in metric space analysis and geometry, followed by a workshop in June that brings together topics from the minicourses.  Priority for travel support from this award will be given to graduate students, early-career mathematicians, and mathematicians from under-represented groups.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Research Term web site: http://www.icmat.es/RT/AGMS2015/</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>01/08/2015</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>01/08/2015</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1500982</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Marie</FirstName>
<LastName>Snipes</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Marie Snipes</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>snipesm@kenyon.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>7404275929</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000620951</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>01/08/2015</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Kenyon College</Name>
<CityName>Gambier</CityName>
<ZipCode>430229623</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>7404275114</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>22 Ransom Hall</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Ohio</StateName>
<StateCode>OH</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>OH07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>063580369</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>KENYON COLLEGE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>063580369</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Kenyon College]]></Name>
<CityName>Gambier</CityName>
<StateCode>OH</StateCode>
<ZipCode>430229623</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[22 Ransom Hall]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Ohio</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>OH07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1281</Code>
<Text>ANALYSIS PROGRAM</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7556</Code>
<Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0115</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2015~47840</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>This award provided support for fifteen U.S. mathematicians to participate in the Research Term on Analysis and Geometry in Metric Spaces from &nbsp;April through June, 2015 at the Instituto de Ciencias Matem&aacute;ticas (ICMAT) in Madrid, Spain. &nbsp;Metric spaces are useful models anytime one wants to consider sets of objects with a natural notion of &ldquo;distance&rdquo; -- for example, images, DNA sequences, and data in general can be modeled with metric spaces. &nbsp;</p> <p>The research term included four, week-long minicourses for non-specialists and young researchers during the month of May taught by leading experts in metric space analysis and geometry, followed by a workshop in June that brought together topics from the minicourses.</p> <p>Participants had the opportunity to present their research to peers, and to network and collaborate with other members of the international research community. &nbsp;Nine of the funded participants were graduate students, four were post-docs (receiving their Ph.D. within the past 5 years), and three were from primarily undergraduate institutions. &nbsp;Several participants reported that publications would likely result from their experience.</p> <p>Further funding was provided for ten mathematicians to travel to give talks or attend conferences in fields related to analysis and geometry in metric spaces; of these, three were undergraduate students, three were graduate students, and one was an early career mathematician.&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 01/29/2017<br>      Modified by: Marie&nbsp;Snipes</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ This award provided support for fifteen U.S. mathematicians to participate in the Research Term on Analysis and Geometry in Metric Spaces from  April through June, 2015 at the Instituto de Ciencias Matem&aacute;ticas (ICMAT) in Madrid, Spain.  Metric spaces are useful models anytime one wants to consider sets of objects with a natural notion of "distance" -- for example, images, DNA sequences, and data in general can be modeled with metric spaces.    The research term included four, week-long minicourses for non-specialists and young researchers during the month of May taught by leading experts in metric space analysis and geometry, followed by a workshop in June that brought together topics from the minicourses.  Participants had the opportunity to present their research to peers, and to network and collaborate with other members of the international research community.  Nine of the funded participants were graduate students, four were post-docs (receiving their Ph.D. within the past 5 years), and three were from primarily undergraduate institutions.  Several participants reported that publications would likely result from their experience.  Further funding was provided for ten mathematicians to travel to give talks or attend conferences in fields related to analysis and geometry in metric spaces; of these, three were undergraduate students, three were graduate students, and one was an early career mathematician.        Last Modified: 01/29/2017       Submitted by: Marie Snipes]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
