<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Collaborative Research: Experimental and Theoretical Study of the Plasma Physics of Antihydrogen Generation and Trapping</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2015</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>228000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>228000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03010000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>PHY</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Physics</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Vyacheslav (Slava) Lukin</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>vlukin@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927382</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The long-term goals of this research address the very basis of our understanding of the world around us. Potentially, it has deep implications on the nature of particle interactions, on the question of matter-antimatter symmetry, and on cosmology. At the same time, this research is uniquely visible because the study of antimatter is accessible and fascinating to the public. Antihydrogen experiments are sufficiently simple that they can be comprehended in their entirety by graduate students. Consequently, they offer students a broad education. Experimental students learn beam and plasma physics, experimental planning and design, instrumentation, electronics, cryogenics, magnetics and software development. Along with theory development, theory students can make critical contributions to the design, operation, and analysis of the experiments. The relative accessibility of the material makes it easy to integrate undergraduate students into both the experimental and theoretical program. The research includes significant participation by members of underrepresented groups.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The research is primarily focused on the immediate plasma and atomic physics issues surrounding improving the trapping of antihydrogen, and on the design of a third generation trap optimized for gravitational research. The physics issues will be studied with experiments at Berkeley and at CERN, with classical trajectory Monte Carlo, molecular dynamics, Vlasov codes and 3D Particle-In-Cell codes, and with analytic theory. Some of the questions that will be addressed include: achieving improved (lower) lepton and antiproton temperatures; studying how leptons interact with the background radiation field; studying how leptons interact with resonant cavities; improved plasma diagnostics; and improved mixing of positrons and antiprotons, so that more of the resultant antihydrogen can be held in a very shallow neutral trap. While the motivation for seeking answers to these questions comes from antihydrogen research, many of these questions raise novel and deep issues in plasma and atomic physics.  This research is co-sponsored by the NSF's Physics Division and the Office of International Science and Engineering.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/19/2015</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/19/2015</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1500427</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Carlos</FirstName>
<LastName>Ordonez</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>A</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Carlos A Ordonez</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>cao@unt.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>9405654860</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000367265</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/19/2015</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of North Texas</Name>
<CityName>Denton</CityName>
<ZipCode>762035017</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>9405653940</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1155 Union Circle #305250</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Texas</StateName>
<StateCode>TX</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>26</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>TX26</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>614168995</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF NORTH TEXAS</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>064117963</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of North Texas]]></Name>
<CityName>Denton</CityName>
<StateCode>TX</StateCode>
<ZipCode>762035017</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[Department of Physics]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Texas</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>26</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>TX26</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1242</Code>
<Text>PLASMA PHYSICS</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7298</Code>
<Text>International Research Collab</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1062</Code>
<Text>BASIC PLASMA SCIENCE &amp; ENGINEERING</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>5950</Code>
<Text>SWITZERLAND</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7298</Code>
<Text>COLLABORATIVE RESEARCH</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8084</Code>
<Text>CDS&amp;E</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0115</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2015~228000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>For the project, "Collaborative Research: Experimental and Theoretical Study of the Plasma Physics of Antihydrogen Generation and Trapping," UNT research focussed primarily on finding a way to simultaneously confine plasmas of antiprotons and positrons, such that antihydrogen is formed with sufficiently low kinetic energy to be suitable for envisioned scientific studies. &nbsp;The Penning trap, an electromagnetic plasma confinement approach that employs static electric and magnetic fields, had been used successfully in a nested configuration to produce cold antihydrogen. &nbsp;However, theoretical research at UNT early in the project found significant issues with using nested Penning traps for the ultimately envisioned antihydrogen studies. &nbsp;Much of the progress in the project at UNT was associated with a search for an alternative plasma confinement approach.</p> <p><br />The UNT portion of the project has yielded a theoretical basis for an alternative electromagnetic plasma confinement approach. &nbsp;The alternative electromagnetic plasma confinement approach relies on an artificially structured boundary for confining a single-species non-neutral plasma. &nbsp;The artificially structured boundary produces a spatially periodic static electromagnetic field along the plasma periphery, such that the spatial period of the applied field is much smaller than the dimensions of the confined plasma. The non-neutral plasma is found to self-consistently produce an electrostatic potential energy well for oppositely signed charged particles. Such a well was also found to occur in a Penning trap with an axially varying magnetic field. &nbsp;The results support the prospect of developing plasma space-charge based confinement, with a plasma of one species of charged particles confined by an electric field produced by a plasma of a second species of charged particles.&nbsp;</p> <p><br />The UNT portion of the project has also yielded a theoretical basis for an alternative magnetic plasma confinement approach. &nbsp;The alternative magnetic plasma confinement approach relies on an artificial phenomenon called magnetic plasma expulsion, which may serve to keep plasma away from nonmagnetic material objects that are inserted into the plasma. &nbsp;Magnetic plasma expulsion would be used to keep plasma away from support structures that hold a plasma-immersed magnetic solenoid in place as part of the alternative magnetic plasma confinement approach. &nbsp;</p> <p><br />UNT research also focussed on developing an understanding of transport processes in magnetized plasmas that may have implications for antihydrogen production. &nbsp;Specifically, phenomena called magnetobound positronium, magnetobound protonium, and quasibound antihydrogen were studied. &nbsp;An electron-positron pair collision can result in a correlated drift of the two particles perpendicular to a magnetic field. While the two particles remain in their correlated drift, they are referred to as being in a magnetobound state. &nbsp;That is, a magnetobound state is defined as a matter-antimatter two-particle quasi-bound system that has positive total energy, where the energy of the system is defined to be zero when the two particles are at rest with infinite separation. &nbsp;</p> <p><br />In addition, the UNT portion of the project included a search for an alternative way to carry out an experiment that would indicate the direction of the acceleration of antimatter due to Earth's gravity. &nbsp;One possibility is based on using material structures that surround an antihydrogen source and form apertures. &nbsp;Annihilations that occur on certain surfaces of the structure would indicate the direction of the gravitational acceleration of antihydrogen.</p> <p><br />The accomplishments at UNT that resulted from the NSF award are associated with the development of new knowledge reported in scientific publications. &nbsp;The new knowledge represents an improved understanding of various phenomena and scientific innovations, which include the following:</p> <p><br />Artificially Structured Boundary for Producing a Spatially Periodic Field<br />Space-Charge Based Plasma Confinement<br />Magnetic Plasma Expulsion<br />Magnetobound Positronium and Protonium<br />Quasibound Antihydrogen<br />Aperture-Based Antihydrogen Gravity Experiment</p> <p><br />Other accomplishments at UNT that resulted from the NSF award are associated with research training provided to UNT students. &nbsp;All of the people who worked on the project at UNT were students, except for the UNT PI and one other UNT faculty member. &nbsp;The project has provided training opportunities for students who enrolled in courses such as Senior Thesis, Master's Thesis, and Doctoral Dissertation. Such courses can apply towards a degree. The project has provided financial support for students who served as research assistants. The project has also provided opportunities for research to members of underrepresented groups. &nbsp;The work carried out by students as part of the research training they received was supervised by the PI to assure professional quality, and the team reported the research results in peer-reviewed journals and at technical conferences.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 09/13/2019<br>      Modified by: Carlos&nbsp;A&nbsp;Ordonez</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ For the project, "Collaborative Research: Experimental and Theoretical Study of the Plasma Physics of Antihydrogen Generation and Trapping," UNT research focussed primarily on finding a way to simultaneously confine plasmas of antiprotons and positrons, such that antihydrogen is formed with sufficiently low kinetic energy to be suitable for envisioned scientific studies.  The Penning trap, an electromagnetic plasma confinement approach that employs static electric and magnetic fields, had been used successfully in a nested configuration to produce cold antihydrogen.  However, theoretical research at UNT early in the project found significant issues with using nested Penning traps for the ultimately envisioned antihydrogen studies.  Much of the progress in the project at UNT was associated with a search for an alternative plasma confinement approach.   The UNT portion of the project has yielded a theoretical basis for an alternative electromagnetic plasma confinement approach.  The alternative electromagnetic plasma confinement approach relies on an artificially structured boundary for confining a single-species non-neutral plasma.  The artificially structured boundary produces a spatially periodic static electromagnetic field along the plasma periphery, such that the spatial period of the applied field is much smaller than the dimensions of the confined plasma. The non-neutral plasma is found to self-consistently produce an electrostatic potential energy well for oppositely signed charged particles. Such a well was also found to occur in a Penning trap with an axially varying magnetic field.  The results support the prospect of developing plasma space-charge based confinement, with a plasma of one species of charged particles confined by an electric field produced by a plasma of a second species of charged particles.    The UNT portion of the project has also yielded a theoretical basis for an alternative magnetic plasma confinement approach.  The alternative magnetic plasma confinement approach relies on an artificial phenomenon called magnetic plasma expulsion, which may serve to keep plasma away from nonmagnetic material objects that are inserted into the plasma.  Magnetic plasma expulsion would be used to keep plasma away from support structures that hold a plasma-immersed magnetic solenoid in place as part of the alternative magnetic plasma confinement approach.     UNT research also focussed on developing an understanding of transport processes in magnetized plasmas that may have implications for antihydrogen production.  Specifically, phenomena called magnetobound positronium, magnetobound protonium, and quasibound antihydrogen were studied.  An electron-positron pair collision can result in a correlated drift of the two particles perpendicular to a magnetic field. While the two particles remain in their correlated drift, they are referred to as being in a magnetobound state.  That is, a magnetobound state is defined as a matter-antimatter two-particle quasi-bound system that has positive total energy, where the energy of the system is defined to be zero when the two particles are at rest with infinite separation.     In addition, the UNT portion of the project included a search for an alternative way to carry out an experiment that would indicate the direction of the acceleration of antimatter due to Earth's gravity.  One possibility is based on using material structures that surround an antihydrogen source and form apertures.  Annihilations that occur on certain surfaces of the structure would indicate the direction of the gravitational acceleration of antihydrogen.   The accomplishments at UNT that resulted from the NSF award are associated with the development of new knowledge reported in scientific publications.  The new knowledge represents an improved understanding of various phenomena and scientific innovations, which include the following:   Artificially Structured Boundary for Producing a Spatially Periodic Field Space-Charge Based Plasma Confinement Magnetic Plasma Expulsion Magnetobound Positronium and Protonium Quasibound Antihydrogen Aperture-Based Antihydrogen Gravity Experiment   Other accomplishments at UNT that resulted from the NSF award are associated with research training provided to UNT students.  All of the people who worked on the project at UNT were students, except for the UNT PI and one other UNT faculty member.  The project has provided training opportunities for students who enrolled in courses such as Senior Thesis, Master's Thesis, and Doctoral Dissertation. Such courses can apply towards a degree. The project has provided financial support for students who served as research assistants. The project has also provided opportunities for research to members of underrepresented groups.  The work carried out by students as part of the research training they received was supervised by the PI to assure professional quality, and the team reported the research results in peer-reviewed journals and at technical conferences.       Last Modified: 09/13/2019       Submitted by: Carlos A Ordonez]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
