<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Free Gibbs States: Von Neumann Algebras, Random Matrices, and Subfactors</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2015</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>420000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>420000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DMS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Marian Bocea</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>mbocea@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922595</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This project intends to develop mathematical tools that are in common use in classical analysis (e.g., notions of regularity, ideas from the theory of partial differential equations) in the noncommutative context that arises in so-called free probability theory.  The underlying mathematics is extremely rich and has many connections with quantum physics.  Progress in development of these tools is expected to have a significant impact on von Neumann algebra theory and random matrix theory, as well as on subfactor theory.  &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The principal aim fo the project is to understand the structure of a class of noncommutative states called "free Gibbs states."  These objects appear in Voiculescu's free probability theory as analogs of classical-probability Gibbs distributions.  Besides free probability, their properties turn out to be important in von Neumann algebra theory, random matrix theory, and subfactor theory.  The main new tool useful for understanding these states is that of free transport.  Developed by A. Guoinnet and the principal investigator, this tool has already been proved to be useful for answering questions such as isomorphism of certain von Neumann algebras and computations of standard invariants of certain subfactors.  More development and understanding is needed.  The project will study and develop noncommutative techniques in partial differential equations that would enable one to construct transport maps, as well as to study critical phenomena.  Along the way, the principal investigator will investigate questions of regularity of noncommutative maps.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>03/24/2015</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/09/2017</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1500035</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Dimitri</FirstName>
<LastName>Shlyakhtenko</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>Y</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Dimitri Y Shlyakhtenko</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>shlyakht@ipam.ucla.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>3109833297</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000426634</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>03/24/2015</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of California-Los Angeles</Name>
<CityName>LOS ANGELES</CityName>
<ZipCode>900951406</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>3107940102</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>10889 Wilshire Boulevard</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[Suite 700]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>33</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CA33</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>092530369</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF CALIFORNIA, LOS ANGELES</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>071549000</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of California-Los Angeles]]></Name>
<CityName>Los Angeles</CityName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>900951555</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[520 Portola Plaza, 7308 MSB]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>33</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CA33</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1281</Code>
<Text>ANALYSIS PROGRAM</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0115</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0116</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0117</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2015~140001</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2016~139999</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2017~140000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Work under this proposal has advanced our undersatnding of free probability theory. &nbsp;This theory describes behavior of certain classes of large matrices, and has applications to a number of mathematical fields, including operator algebras, probability theory, and random matrix theory. &nbsp;Beyond interesting mathematics, these fields have direct connections to important applications, ranging from machine learning to numerical methods.</p> <p>The focus of the award was the development of the emerging theory of "transportation" in free probability theory. &nbsp;Classically, tranportation theory studies ways to efficiently transport mass -- one of the first publications in that area is by G. Monge in 1781 concerns the question of efficiently transporting a pile of dirt to fill a hole in the ground. &nbsp;In free probability theory, ideas from classical transport theory can be used to construct "matricial" functions that transform one free probabilty setting to another. &nbsp;These non-commutative changes of variables can be used to deduce unexpected isomorphisms in oprator algebra theory. &nbsp;At the same time, they give efficient approximations to changes of variables in random matrix models, and can be used to deduce such results as universality for certain types of random matrices.</p> <p>To produce these non-commutative changes of variables, one needs to solve equations that deal with non-commutative (matricial) functions. &nbsp;This leads to a new direction: adaptation of classical Partial Differential Equation (PDE) results in the context of free probability. &nbsp;Work supported by this proposal can be viewed as laying the groundwork for this approach.</p> <p>The award has resulted in 5 publications by the PI. &nbsp;Three of PI's students have been supported as research assistants by this award; two of them have by now received their PhD degrees (in 2017 and 2019).</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 07/01/2019<br>      Modified by: Dimitri&nbsp;Y&nbsp;Shlyakhtenko</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Work under this proposal has advanced our undersatnding of free probability theory.  This theory describes behavior of certain classes of large matrices, and has applications to a number of mathematical fields, including operator algebras, probability theory, and random matrix theory.  Beyond interesting mathematics, these fields have direct connections to important applications, ranging from machine learning to numerical methods.  The focus of the award was the development of the emerging theory of "transportation" in free probability theory.  Classically, tranportation theory studies ways to efficiently transport mass -- one of the first publications in that area is by G. Monge in 1781 concerns the question of efficiently transporting a pile of dirt to fill a hole in the ground.  In free probability theory, ideas from classical transport theory can be used to construct "matricial" functions that transform one free probabilty setting to another.  These non-commutative changes of variables can be used to deduce unexpected isomorphisms in oprator algebra theory.  At the same time, they give efficient approximations to changes of variables in random matrix models, and can be used to deduce such results as universality for certain types of random matrices.  To produce these non-commutative changes of variables, one needs to solve equations that deal with non-commutative (matricial) functions.  This leads to a new direction: adaptation of classical Partial Differential Equation (PDE) results in the context of free probability.  Work supported by this proposal can be viewed as laying the groundwork for this approach.  The award has resulted in 5 publications by the PI.  Three of PI's students have been supported as research assistants by this award; two of them have by now received their PhD degrees (in 2017 and 2019).          Last Modified: 07/01/2019       Submitted by: Dimitri Y Shlyakhtenko]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
