<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Karuk (kyh) Archives and Accessibility Project</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>06/15/2015</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>11/30/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>100000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>102555</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>04040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>SBE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>BCS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Behavioral and Cognitive Sci</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Joan Maling</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>jmaling@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032928046</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Karuk is a language of the Karuk Tribe, a federally-recognized tribe situated on the middle course of the Klamath River in northwestern California.  Karuk is well known for its complex accentual system such as the rules in English (PHOTOgraph versus photoGRAPHic), its unique patterns of word and sentence formation.  Thus more data on this language will help with understanding more about its grammar.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;PI Susan Gehr of Humboldt University, along with a Karuk Language Program Coordinator and 20 community participants, will create an archival repository of Karuk materials, making them searchable and accessible in perpetuity.  The materials to be archived include data from the Karuk Tribe's Language Program and materials donated by community members.  These unique data will then enrich current knowledge of this highly endangered language.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;While there are just five elderly known fluent speakers of the Karuk language, there is an active community of Karuk people documenting the fluent speakers of Karuk and publishing Karuk texts, audio and video. Gehr will hold four workshops where she will share state-of-the-art techniques in archiving and preservation methodologies to community members with the view to supporting sustainable archiving practices in the community.  The project will not only create infrastructure in the Karuk community, it also provided an example of how to do this with community. This project will also use best practices from the archival profession to produce a freely available collection guide for the Karuk language materials created and collected by the Karuk Tribe's Language Program.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/05/2015</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/29/2018</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.075</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1500605</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Susan</FirstName>
<LastName>Gehr</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Susan Gehr</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>susangehr@sonic.net</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5304931600</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000063858</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/05/2015</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Karuk Tribe</Name>
<CityName>Happy Camp</CityName>
<ZipCode>960391016</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5304931600</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>64236 Second Avenue</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CA01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>145307930</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>KARUK TRIBE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>145307930</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Karuk Tribe]]></Name>
<CityName>Happy Camp</CityName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>960391016</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[64236 Second Avenue]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CA01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7719</Code>
<Text>DEL</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1311</Code>
<Text>LINGUISTICS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7719</Code>
<Text>DEL</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9178</Code>
<Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9251</Code>
<Text>REU SUPP-Res Exp for Ugrd Supp</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0115</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0117</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2015~100000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2017~2555</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>As the speech communities of Indigenous languages of California increasingly rely on archival materials as part of language research, documentation and revitalization, the major goals of the Karuk Archives and Accessibility Project were twofold:</p> <ul> </ul> <ul> <li>To encourage and educate Karuk community      members who are involved in documenting and revitalizing the Karuk      language to care for their work products with preservation and future      access in mind, and</li> <li>to prepare the materials of the Karuk Tribe, a      federally-recognized tribe of northwestern California, for archival      processing.</li> </ul> <ul> </ul> <p>The project facilitated preservation and care of Karuk language materials by the Karuk Tribe and members of the Karuk language community.&nbsp;</p> <p>Through the project, a series of four workshops were held to teach Karuk language community scholars on the care and preservation of their personal language materials. Language communities studied with professional archivists and gained the capacity to become researchers and donors to archives, and consider establishing archives.</p> <p>Through language community understanding of the life cycle of language research information materials, archival repositories may increasingly receive materials from language communities from the perspectives of language communities themselves. These materials will contain language and analyses that will reflect &nbsp;community members' perspectives. As an outcome of this project, more conversations with archives will happen at an earlier stage in the research, and materials will be processed better and more accessibly.</p> <p>For the final workshop, a preservation archivist was brought in. After the training portion of the workshop, the archivist reviewed samples of scholars' personal language collections to make recommendations about care for those items.&nbsp; At least one Karuk language community scholar has already built on the work of this project and donated portions of their personal language collections to Humboldt State University. Project activities and outcomes have also been shared at CoLang (the Institute for Collaborative Language Research), the 2019 Live Your Language Alliance Conference, and the 2020 Linguistic Society of America Annual Meeting.</p> <p>A finding guide of language collections created and collected by the Karuk Tribe's language program was written and provided to the Tribe in preparation for future use and access to those materials.&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 08/07/2020<br>      Modified by: Susan&nbsp;Gehr</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ As the speech communities of Indigenous languages of California increasingly rely on archival materials as part of language research, documentation and revitalization, the major goals of the Karuk Archives and Accessibility Project were twofold:    To encourage and educate Karuk community      members who are involved in documenting and revitalizing the Karuk      language to care for their work products with preservation and future      access in mind, and to prepare the materials of the Karuk Tribe, a      federally-recognized tribe of northwestern California, for archival      processing.     The project facilitated preservation and care of Karuk language materials by the Karuk Tribe and members of the Karuk language community.   Through the project, a series of four workshops were held to teach Karuk language community scholars on the care and preservation of their personal language materials. Language communities studied with professional archivists and gained the capacity to become researchers and donors to archives, and consider establishing archives.  Through language community understanding of the life cycle of language research information materials, archival repositories may increasingly receive materials from language communities from the perspectives of language communities themselves. These materials will contain language and analyses that will reflect  community members' perspectives. As an outcome of this project, more conversations with archives will happen at an earlier stage in the research, and materials will be processed better and more accessibly.  For the final workshop, a preservation archivist was brought in. After the training portion of the workshop, the archivist reviewed samples of scholars' personal language collections to make recommendations about care for those items.  At least one Karuk language community scholar has already built on the work of this project and donated portions of their personal language collections to Humboldt State University. Project activities and outcomes have also been shared at CoLang (the Institute for Collaborative Language Research), the 2019 Live Your Language Alliance Conference, and the 2020 Linguistic Society of America Annual Meeting.  A finding guide of language collections created and collected by the Karuk Tribe's language program was written and provided to the Tribe in preparation for future use and access to those materials.        Last Modified: 08/07/2020       Submitted by: Susan Gehr]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
