<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Multi-disciplinary Conference Investigating Tlingit Indigenous Place Names, Language and History</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2015</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2016</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>50000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>50000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>04040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>SBE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>BCS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Behavioral and Cognitive Sci</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Colleen M. Fitzgerald</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Insights into language are enriched through cross-disciplinary investigation.  The Indigenous Place Names, Language, and History conference will bring together experts in biology, traditional ecological knowledge, archaeology, linguistics, museum studies, cultural anthropology, education, ethnohistory, art, music, and indigenous law to share information from many perspectives on Tlingit (tli) language and culture.  In addition to social scientists and humanities experts, the conference will include equal participation and presentations from Tlingit speakers and other tradition bearers who hold keys to contextualize linguistic and cultural findings.  Under the direction of Alice Taff of Tlingit Readers, Incorporated, this Clan conference will generate knowledge on place names from coastal Southeastern Alaska from Yakutat south to Ketchikan.  &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Conference proceedings and presentations will be archived at the SeaAlaska Heritage Institute, Alaska State Library, and clanconference.org websites.  The session will be available for viewing at  clanconference.org.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/24/2015</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/24/2015</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.075</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1500824</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Alice</FirstName>
<LastName>Taff</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Alice Taff</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>alicetaff@gmail.com</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>9079572208</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000196655</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/24/2015</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Tlingit Readers, Inc.</Name>
<CityName>Juneau</CityName>
<ZipCode>998010000</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>9077962923</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>503 W 10th St</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Alaska</StateName>
<StateCode>AK</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>00</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>AK00</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>831172023</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>TLINGIT READERS, INC.</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Tlingit Readers, Inc.]]></Name>
<CityName>Juneau</CityName>
<StateCode>AK</StateCode>
<ZipCode>998011245</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[1000 Egan Hwy]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Alaska</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>00</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>AK00</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7719</Code>
<Text>DEL</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1311</Code>
<Text>LINGUISTICS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>5221</Code>
<Text>ARCTIC SOCIAL SCIENCES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7556</Code>
<Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7719</Code>
<Text>DEL</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0115</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2015~50000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>&nbsp;</p> <p>The major goals of our multi-disciplinary conference &ldquo;Sharing Our Knowledge: a conference of Tlingit Tribes and Clans&rdquo; have been to gather all populations and areas of Tlingit expertise to share knowledge on their subjects in respectful communication. This has meant bringing together Native and non-Native cultural experts, scholars, scientists, clan leaders, writers, visual artists, and building upon past conferences in order to learn and foster future collaborations.</p> <p>This project&rsquo;s overall goal is to promote sharing of Tlingit language knowledge to future Tlingit generations and the broader community and, as result, promote continuity of the language and the Tlingit culture it represents. This goal was furthered though the objective of gathering a wide variety of Tlingit speakers and other knowledge holders for the four-day event.</p> <p>The Sharing Our Knowledge organizing committee, composed of 8 Tlingit and 5 non-Native people met every month for 2 years, by audioconference, to plan all aspects of the conference. Agreement on all matters was reached by consensus and all tasks were accepted voluntarily.</p> <p>The ninth Sharing Our Knowledge conference of Tlingit clans and tribes was held Oct. 29 &ndash; Nov. 1, 2015, in Juneau, Alaska. Over 350 people attended. The program consisted of 67 sessions and events.</p> <p>Meeting our objective to<strong> </strong>attract a wide range of presenters and participants Native and non-Native, academic and community experts, elders and cultural specialists, teachers and students, artists, tribal representatives, we find that, of the registered attendees, 46% self-identified as Native. There were more than 60 presentations as well as other events. 60% of the 73 presenters were Native. The conference theme, <em>Haa Saax&rsquo;&uacute;, Haa Latseen&iacute; </em>(Our Names, Our Strength), drew 5 presentations on place names and 5 on Tlingit personal names, 3 on historical photo collections, 3 on Tlingit weaving, 11 on visual arts and museums, 5 on Tlingit language, 11 on history, 3 on Indigenous wellness/ethics/spirituality, 6 on environmental concerns, 1 on cultural mathematics, 2 on Tlingit protocol. Approximately 100 non-registered attendees came to participate in fee-free activities such as the weavers&rsquo; demonstration. Native and non-Native experts met, shared information, and made personal connections for future work.</p> <p>The conference began with an evening event, &ldquo;Warming of the Hands&rdquo;, (see image 1) a traditional Tlingit ceremony to welcome visitors after a long journey. The local clans of the &Aacute;ak&rsquo;w Khw&aacute;an (people of the Auke area), and T&rsquo;aakh&uacute; Khw&aacute;an (people of the Taku area) welcomed visitors to their ancestral territory (aka City and Borough of Juneau.)</p> <p>The Tlingit Spelling Bee (see image 2) is a conference favorite.</p> <p>Award winning glass artist, Preston Singletary, presented &ldquo;Modern Heritage art or Neo-indigenous art&rdquo; (see image 3).</p> <p>To model Tlingit ways if interacting, Harold Jacobs organized a session, &ldquo;I&rsquo;m going to visit him&rdquo; (see image 4).</p> <p>Other events included an evening of &ldquo;Readings of Indigenous Literature&rdquo; at the Alaska Governor&rsquo;s mansion, hosted by Alaska&rsquo;s First Lady, Donna Walker, and attended by Alaska Governor Bill Walker, Lieutenant Governor Byron Mallott and Mrs. Toni Mallott. The Mallotts are Tlingit. At this event, First Lady Walker was given a Deisheet&aacute;n clan name and adopted into that clan by Mrs. Selina Everson (see image 5).</p> <p>For 3 days, the conference lobby was filled with weavers, some demonstrating Chilkat and Raven&rsquo;s Tail weaving using mountain goat wool, others creating traditional hats and containers from spruce roots and cedar inner bark.</p> <p>Collaborating with the Juneau Public Library under their Story Corps project, for 3 days a room was devoted to audio recording on the topic, &ldquo;Every Voice Matters: Recording Alaska Native Educational Stories.&rdquo;</p> <p>For Tlingit language documentation, discoverable, accessible video recording of each session provides the opportunity for linguists to study aspects of language use, for instance, comparing the amount of Tlingit language use at the first SOK to language usage at 2015 conference will test the hypothesis that there was a downturn in usage from 1993 until around the year 2003 but by 2015 Tlingit language usage is greater than that 23 years prior. The 2015 sessions were documented in high quality video and are the prime data result of the conference. These videos are accessible at</p> <p><a href="https://www.youtube.com/playlist?list=PL5JmUC9niijhUlC6VqD_KlphgP8AeBB7v">https://www.youtube.com/playlist?list=PL5JmUC9niijhUlC6VqD_KlphgP8AeBB7v</a> , archived at the Alaska Historical Collection of the Alaska State Library located in Juneau, Alaska.</p> <p>It is too early to report published results from the 2015 conference. However, we would like to draw attention the the 2015 publication by Sergei Kan, based on earlier conference experiences:<strong>&nbsp;</strong><em>Sharing Our Knowledge</em>: <em>the Tlingit and Their Coastal Neighbors.</em> Lincoln: University of Nebraska Press. 2015.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 11/04/2016<br>      Modified by: Alice&nbsp;E&nbsp;Taff</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Images (<span id="selectedPhoto0">1</span> of <span class="totalNumber"></span>)           </div> <div class="galControls" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2016/1500824/1500824_10380238_1475815780808_VideoRecordings--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2016/1500824/1500824_10380238_1475815780808_VideoRecordings--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Video recordings of Sharing Our Knowledge all posted on YouTube"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2016/1500824/1500824_10380238_1475815780808_VideoRecordings--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Video recordings of Sharing Our Knowledge all posted on YouTube"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">The example video here is of the opening session, Warming of the Hands, a ceremony in which the clans of the land on which an event takes place, make the incoming guests welcome.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Sharing Our Knowledge</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Creative Commons</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Alice&nbsp;E&nbsp;Taff</div> <div class="imageTitle">Video recordings of Sharing Our Knowledge all posted on YouTube</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2016/1500824/1500824_10380238_1475816074803_TlingitSpllingBee--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2016/1500824/1500824_10380238_1475816074803_TlingitSpllingBee--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Tlingit Spelling Bee"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2016/1500824/1500824_10380238_1475816074803_TlingitSpllingBee--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Tlingit Spelling Bee"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Spellers of all ages compete in the bee, this year won by a Canadian Tlingit. This contest encourages reading and writing in Tlingit to enhance current and future documentation and use of Tlingit.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Shari</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Creative Commons</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Alice&nbsp;E&nbsp;Taff</div> <div class="imageTitle">Tlingit Spelling Bee</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2016/1500824/1500824_10380238_1475816342857_ModernHeritageArt--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2016/1500824/1500824_10380238_1475816342857_ModernHeritageArt--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Preston Singletary: Modern Heritage Art"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2016/1500824/1500824_10380238_1475816342857_ModernHeritageArt--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Preston Singletary: Modern Heritage Art"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">World renowned artist, Tlingit Preston Singletary, works primarily in glass. Here, he describes how he uses traditional forms in this modern medium.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Sharing Our Knowledge</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Creative Commons</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Alice&nbsp;E&nbsp;Taff</div> <div class="imageTitle">Preston Singletary: Modern Heritage Art</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2016/1500824/1500824_10380238_1475816587813_I'mGoingToVisitHim--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2016/1500824/1500824_10380238_1475816587813_I'mGoingToVisitHim--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Du &eacute;en yoo xwalee.&aacute;t 'I'm going to visit him'"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2016/1500824/1500824_10380238_1475816587813_I'mGoingToVisitHim--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Du &eacute;en yoo xwalee.&aacute;t 'I'm going to visit him'"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Participants in this session talk about the practice of respectful visiting among Tlingit people.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Sharing Our Knowledge</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Creative Commons</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Alice&nbsp;E&nbsp;Taff</div> <div class="imageTitle">Du éen yoo xwalee.át 'I'm going to visit him'</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2016/1500824/1500824_10380238_1475817170111_Governor'sMansion--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2016/1500824/1500824_10380238_1475817170111_Governor'sMansion--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Indigenous Literature Reading at the Governor's Mansion"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2016/1500824/1500824_10380238_1475817170111_Governor'sMansion--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Indigenous Literature Reading at the Governor's Mansion"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Alaska's First Lady, Donna Walker, hosted an Indigenous literature reading at the Governor's Mansion. From left to right:  Governor Bill Walker, Sharing Our Knowledge director, Gerry Hope, Donna Walker, Paul Marks, Ishmael Hope, Lance Twitchell, Toni Mallott and Lt. Governor Byron Mallott.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Sharing Our Knowledge</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Creative Commons</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Alice&nbsp;E&nbsp;Taff</div> <div class="imageTitle">Indigenous Literature Reading at the Governor's Mansion</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[    The major goals of our multi-disciplinary conference "Sharing Our Knowledge: a conference of Tlingit Tribes and Clans" have been to gather all populations and areas of Tlingit expertise to share knowledge on their subjects in respectful communication. This has meant bringing together Native and non-Native cultural experts, scholars, scientists, clan leaders, writers, visual artists, and building upon past conferences in order to learn and foster future collaborations.  This project?s overall goal is to promote sharing of Tlingit language knowledge to future Tlingit generations and the broader community and, as result, promote continuity of the language and the Tlingit culture it represents. This goal was furthered though the objective of gathering a wide variety of Tlingit speakers and other knowledge holders for the four-day event.  The Sharing Our Knowledge organizing committee, composed of 8 Tlingit and 5 non-Native people met every month for 2 years, by audioconference, to plan all aspects of the conference. Agreement on all matters was reached by consensus and all tasks were accepted voluntarily.  The ninth Sharing Our Knowledge conference of Tlingit clans and tribes was held Oct. 29 &ndash; Nov. 1, 2015, in Juneau, Alaska. Over 350 people attended. The program consisted of 67 sessions and events.  Meeting our objective to attract a wide range of presenters and participants Native and non-Native, academic and community experts, elders and cultural specialists, teachers and students, artists, tribal representatives, we find that, of the registered attendees, 46% self-identified as Native. There were more than 60 presentations as well as other events. 60% of the 73 presenters were Native. The conference theme, Haa Saax?&uacute;, Haa Latseen&iacute; (Our Names, Our Strength), drew 5 presentations on place names and 5 on Tlingit personal names, 3 on historical photo collections, 3 on Tlingit weaving, 11 on visual arts and museums, 5 on Tlingit language, 11 on history, 3 on Indigenous wellness/ethics/spirituality, 6 on environmental concerns, 1 on cultural mathematics, 2 on Tlingit protocol. Approximately 100 non-registered attendees came to participate in fee-free activities such as the weavers? demonstration. Native and non-Native experts met, shared information, and made personal connections for future work.  The conference began with an evening event, "Warming of the Hands", (see image 1) a traditional Tlingit ceremony to welcome visitors after a long journey. The local clans of the &Aacute;ak?w Khw&aacute;an (people of the Auke area), and T?aakh&uacute; Khw&aacute;an (people of the Taku area) welcomed visitors to their ancestral territory (aka City and Borough of Juneau.)  The Tlingit Spelling Bee (see image 2) is a conference favorite.  Award winning glass artist, Preston Singletary, presented "Modern Heritage art or Neo-indigenous art" (see image 3).  To model Tlingit ways if interacting, Harold Jacobs organized a session, "I?m going to visit him" (see image 4).  Other events included an evening of "Readings of Indigenous Literature" at the Alaska Governor?s mansion, hosted by Alaska?s First Lady, Donna Walker, and attended by Alaska Governor Bill Walker, Lieutenant Governor Byron Mallott and Mrs. Toni Mallott. The Mallotts are Tlingit. At this event, First Lady Walker was given a Deisheet&aacute;n clan name and adopted into that clan by Mrs. Selina Everson (see image 5).  For 3 days, the conference lobby was filled with weavers, some demonstrating Chilkat and Raven?s Tail weaving using mountain goat wool, others creating traditional hats and containers from spruce roots and cedar inner bark.  Collaborating with the Juneau Public Library under their Story Corps project, for 3 days a room was devoted to audio recording on the topic, "Every Voice Matters: Recording Alaska Native Educational Stories."  For Tlingit language documentation, discoverable, accessible video recording of each session provides the opportunity for linguists to study aspects of language use, for instance, comparing the amount of Tlingit language use at the first SOK to language usage at 2015 conference will test the hypothesis that there was a downturn in usage from 1993 until around the year 2003 but by 2015 Tlingit language usage is greater than that 23 years prior. The 2015 sessions were documented in high quality video and are the prime data result of the conference. These videos are accessible at  https://www.youtube.com/playlist?list=PL5JmUC9niijhUlC6VqD_KlphgP8AeBB7v , archived at the Alaska Historical Collection of the Alaska State Library located in Juneau, Alaska.  It is too early to report published results from the 2015 conference. However, we would like to draw attention the the 2015 publication by Sergei Kan, based on earlier conference experiences: Sharing Our Knowledge: the Tlingit and Their Coastal Neighbors. Lincoln: University of Nebraska Press. 2015.             Last Modified: 11/04/2016       Submitted by: Alice E Taff]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
