<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>DISSERTATION RESEARCH: The molecular basis of convergent innovations: co-option or independent origin of regulatory modules?</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>06/01/2015</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>19337.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>19337</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>08010207</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>BIO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DEB</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Environmental Biology</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>George Gilchrist</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Although the diversity of traits observed in nature can seem infinite, it still represents only a subset of possible traits. Furthermore, some traits have evolved repeatedly in distantly related species. Does repeated origin of certain traits reflect shared genetic constraints? The structure of gene networks that control development could favor the evolution of some traits while making the origin of other traits less likely. In order to determine the role of gene networks in shaping biological diversity, this study will identify and compare the molecular mechanisms that led to the independent origin of similar traits in two distantly related species. This research provides important insights into the translation of genotype to phenotype. The PIs propose novel mentoring in molecular techniques to high school and undergraduate students from underrepresented groups. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The proposed study investigates distantly related groups of fruit fly species, which have independently gained similar male-specific morphological structures.  Previous work has shown that the gene doublesex (dsx) is important in the formation of these traits in both groups, and that specific changes in the DNA sequence of dsx correlate with the origin of one of these structures. This research will test whether evolutionary changes in the same or different DNA sequences are associated with the origin of the convergent structure in the other group. Answering this question will help determine the role of the genetic network encompassing dsx in the independent origin of similar traits in these two groups of species.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>03/31/2015</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>03/31/2015</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.074</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1501148</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Artyom</FirstName>
<LastName>Kopp</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Artyom Kopp</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>akopp@ucdavis.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5307528657</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000398427</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>03/31/2015</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Gavin</FirstName>
<LastName>Rice</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>R</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Gavin R Rice</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>grrice@ucdavis.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5307547700</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000653998</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>03/31/2015</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of California-Davis</Name>
<CityName>Davis</CityName>
<ZipCode>956186134</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5307547700</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>OR/Sponsored Programs</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[1850 Research Park Dr., Ste 300]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CA03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>047120084</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF CALIFORNIA, DAVIS</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>071549000</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of California-Davis]]></Name>
<CityName>Davis</CityName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>956165270</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[One Shields Avenue]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CA03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7378</Code>
<Text>EVOLUTIONARY GENETICS</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9169</Code>
<Text>BIODIVERSITY AND ECOSYSTEM DYNAMICS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9179</Code>
<Text>GRADUATE INVOLVEMENT</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>EGCH</Code>
<Text>ENVIRONMENT AND GLOBAL CHANGE</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>SMET</Code>
<Text>SCIENCE, MATH, ENG &amp; TECH EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0115</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2015~19337</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Some of most striking examples of morphological variation are those that differ between males and females of the same species (sexually dimorphic traits). Sexually dimorphic traits show accelerated morphological diversification and are rapidly gained and lost. What causes some traits to differ between males and females, while others are virtually identical? How do these changes occur on a genetic level? Are there any fundamental mechanisms that affect which traits become different between the sexes?</p> <p>In order to study general mechanisms of evolution, we must establish an effective model system. For the rapid gain and loss of sex specific traits, the foreleg of fruit flies is an ideal system. The male forelegs are often used during courtship with females and many dramatic orientations of the legs have been documented. The genomic and transgenic tools available in the model <em>Drosophila melanogaster</em> allow us to quickly and effectively determine the effected genes and genetic pathways. By establishing whether the same genes are responsible for the evolution of independent traits, we can better determine whether there are essential mechanisms to establish a new sex-specific trait.</p> <p>We compare the evolution of two independent male specific modifications of the forelegs: the sex comb of <em>Drosophila melanogaster</em> and foreleg brush of <em>Drosophila immigrans</em>. In the sex comb, previous studies have found that the gene: <em>doublesex</em> played a major part in the origin and diversification of the sex comb. Although there have been many studies on the sex comb, ours is one of the first to address the evolution foreleg brush. We investigated if the gene <em>doublesex</em> plays a similar role in the evolution of foreleg brush and therefore may represent a more general mechanism. To accomplish this, we had the following aims: 1) To establish a clear definition of the foreleg brush morphology; 2) To establish which species contain the foreleg brush; 3) To determine the expression of <em>doublesex</em> in the species closely related to <em>Drosophila immigrans</em>; 4) To determine the whether the changes in foreleg brush morphology are linked to changes in <em>doublesex</em> expression.</p> <p>We used a technique known as Scanning Electronic Microscopy to take high-resolution images of the <em>Drosophila immigrans </em>foreleg brush bristles. This allowed us to better resolve the distribution of bristles but also the shape of the individual bristles. This level of resolution was not possible with light microscopy. We found that the foreleg brush of <em>Drosophila immigrans</em> is composed of many corkscrew-like bristles with hooked ends, almost resembling velcro. This is the first description of this bristle type and may represent a new evolutionary innovation. To determine the distribution of the foreleg brush among closely related species to <em>Drosophila immigrans</em> we analyzed the adult morphology using light microscopy. We were able to determine the presence or absence of the brush in closely related 11 species. To determine the phylogeny of these species we sequenced 9 genes from each species and created a robust phylogeny. This allowed us to determine whether the presence or absence of the foreleg brush was due to a secondarily loss of the trait, or whether the ancestors of the species likely never had the trait. We found that many closely related species also contained the foreleg brush but that the amount of the foreleg covered by these modified hairs greatly varied. We then used antibody staining to determine how much of the developing foreleg expressed the protein <em>doublesex</em>. The changes in the distribution of the foreleg brush bristles highly correlated with the amount of the foreleg that expressed <em>doublesex</em>. When we examined species that ancestrally lacked the foreleg brush, they also lacked <em>doublesex</em> expression. This leads us to conclude that <em>doublesex</em> expression is correlated with both the origin and diversification of the sexually dimorphic foreleg brush. Our results closely mirror those of a previous study which also found that <em>doublesex</em> was correlated with the origin and diversification the sex comb.</p> <p>The recurrent use of <em>doublesex</em> in both of these traits suggests that it may be a general mechanism. This raises the question of whether <em>doublesex</em> is involved in the evolution of the numerous other sexually dimorphic structures in fruit flies.&nbsp;</p> <p>This project has also allowed us to reach out to the local community. Science programs in education are one of the most critical ways in which we can educate and excite the general public about science. This project allowed us to work with our local High School to mentor a student. This gave the student the chance to use cutting edge equipment and techniques that would not be available even at the best high school science laboratories. When subjects such as genetically modified organisms and gene therapy become a bigger part of legislation and everyday life, the education of our youth in science during these pivotal points in their education becomes even more important.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 06/22/2017<br>      Modified by: Gavin&nbsp;R&nbsp;Rice</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Some of most striking examples of morphological variation are those that differ between males and females of the same species (sexually dimorphic traits). Sexually dimorphic traits show accelerated morphological diversification and are rapidly gained and lost. What causes some traits to differ between males and females, while others are virtually identical? How do these changes occur on a genetic level? Are there any fundamental mechanisms that affect which traits become different between the sexes?  In order to study general mechanisms of evolution, we must establish an effective model system. For the rapid gain and loss of sex specific traits, the foreleg of fruit flies is an ideal system. The male forelegs are often used during courtship with females and many dramatic orientations of the legs have been documented. The genomic and transgenic tools available in the model Drosophila melanogaster allow us to quickly and effectively determine the effected genes and genetic pathways. By establishing whether the same genes are responsible for the evolution of independent traits, we can better determine whether there are essential mechanisms to establish a new sex-specific trait.  We compare the evolution of two independent male specific modifications of the forelegs: the sex comb of Drosophila melanogaster and foreleg brush of Drosophila immigrans. In the sex comb, previous studies have found that the gene: doublesex played a major part in the origin and diversification of the sex comb. Although there have been many studies on the sex comb, ours is one of the first to address the evolution foreleg brush. We investigated if the gene doublesex plays a similar role in the evolution of foreleg brush and therefore may represent a more general mechanism. To accomplish this, we had the following aims: 1) To establish a clear definition of the foreleg brush morphology; 2) To establish which species contain the foreleg brush; 3) To determine the expression of doublesex in the species closely related to Drosophila immigrans; 4) To determine the whether the changes in foreleg brush morphology are linked to changes in doublesex expression.  We used a technique known as Scanning Electronic Microscopy to take high-resolution images of the Drosophila immigrans foreleg brush bristles. This allowed us to better resolve the distribution of bristles but also the shape of the individual bristles. This level of resolution was not possible with light microscopy. We found that the foreleg brush of Drosophila immigrans is composed of many corkscrew-like bristles with hooked ends, almost resembling velcro. This is the first description of this bristle type and may represent a new evolutionary innovation. To determine the distribution of the foreleg brush among closely related species to Drosophila immigrans we analyzed the adult morphology using light microscopy. We were able to determine the presence or absence of the brush in closely related 11 species. To determine the phylogeny of these species we sequenced 9 genes from each species and created a robust phylogeny. This allowed us to determine whether the presence or absence of the foreleg brush was due to a secondarily loss of the trait, or whether the ancestors of the species likely never had the trait. We found that many closely related species also contained the foreleg brush but that the amount of the foreleg covered by these modified hairs greatly varied. We then used antibody staining to determine how much of the developing foreleg expressed the protein doublesex. The changes in the distribution of the foreleg brush bristles highly correlated with the amount of the foreleg that expressed doublesex. When we examined species that ancestrally lacked the foreleg brush, they also lacked doublesex expression. This leads us to conclude that doublesex expression is correlated with both the origin and diversification of the sexually dimorphic foreleg brush. Our results closely mirror those of a previous study which also found that doublesex was correlated with the origin and diversification the sex comb.  The recurrent use of doublesex in both of these traits suggests that it may be a general mechanism. This raises the question of whether doublesex is involved in the evolution of the numerous other sexually dimorphic structures in fruit flies.   This project has also allowed us to reach out to the local community. Science programs in education are one of the most critical ways in which we can educate and excite the general public about science. This project allowed us to work with our local High School to mentor a student. This gave the student the chance to use cutting edge equipment and techniques that would not be available even at the best high school science laboratories. When subjects such as genetically modified organisms and gene therapy become a bigger part of legislation and everyday life, the education of our youth in science during these pivotal points in their education becomes even more important.          Last Modified: 06/22/2017       Submitted by: Gavin R Rice]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
