<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Leading Innovation through Green High-Tech Engineering, Sustainability &amp; Security (LIGHTES^2)</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>06/01/2015</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>699486.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>699486</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>11040100</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>EHR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DUE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Undergraduate Education</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>R. Corby Hovis</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>chovis@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924625</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>As attention to the potential for cyber-attacks across industries and municipalities has grown, the need for individuals trained in cybersecurity to protect the nation's information systems, networks, and infrastructure has never been greater. This is evident in cybersecurity jobs growing at twice the rate of all other IT jobs combined. At the same time the potential vulnerabilities in the nation's information infrastructure carry implications for the sustainability of the nation's energy infrastructure. In response, this ATE project will i) engage in the design and creation a new seamless pathway from high school through college in cybersecurity and ii) enhance its existing sustainability programs. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Specific goals of this project are to: 1) increase the capacity to grow and train an advanced technological workforce in cybersecurity; 2) create a seamless pathway for inquiry-based learning for STEM students, with attention to increased participation of underrepresented students, from high school through college; 3) engage and expand the number of minority and non-traditional students in cybersecurity and sustainability programs at the College;  and 4) foster regional collaboration among industry, higher education, secondary schools. The cybersecurity degree will include stacked certifications, permitting both traditional students and professionals returning to college to enter and exit the program flexibly and to obtain certifications while "stacking" those certifications towards the degree, or to complete the program traditionally and exit after two years with a degree and the certifications. Thus, the program will benefit both new students and existing professionals looking to upgrade their skills and obtain additional academic and workplace credentials.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>03/27/2015</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>03/27/2015</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.076</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1501781</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Nina</FirstName>
<LastName>Leonhardt</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>A</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Nina A Leonhardt</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>leonhan@sunysuffolk.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6314514607</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000169511</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>03/27/2015</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Peter</FirstName>
<LastName>Maritato</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>J</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Peter J Maritato</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>maritap@sunysuffolk.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6314514277</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000163749</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>03/27/2015</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Suffolk Community College</Name>
<CityName>Selden</CityName>
<ZipCode>117842899</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6314514760</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>533 College Road</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NY01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>068017615</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>SUFFOLK COUNTY COMMUNITY COLLEGE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>041002973</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Suffolk Community College]]></Name>
<CityName>Selden</CityName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<ZipCode>117842899</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[533 College Road]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NY01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7412</Code>
<Text>Advanced Tech Education Prog</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1032</Code>
<Text>ADVANCED TECHNOLOGY EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9178</Code>
<Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>SMET</Code>
<Text>SCIENCE, MATH, ENG &amp; TECH EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0415</Code>
<Name>NSF Education &amp; Human Resource</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040106</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2015~699486</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Suffolk County Community College&rsquo;s NSF ATE LIGHTES<sup>2</sup> project set out to establish a two-year degree in Cybersecurity. We successfully accomplished the design and implementation of this degree where, upon completion, students can either enter industry in a career related to Cybersecurity or transfer to a four-year college or university to continue their studies in Cybersecurity. The program is successful with approximately 75 students enrolled the first year and &nbsp;increasing to approximately 120 students in the second year. In addition to implementing the curriculum, we introduced various avenues for students to learn and demonstrate their expertise. The new program provides a cybersecurity learning/mentoring lab for students to practice skills and receive tutoring. The state-of-the art cybersecurity lab provides authentic cybersecurity exercises using dedicated equipment for each student to experience. We also established a cybersecurity club where&nbsp; students compete in both local and national cybersecurity hackathons.</p> <p>To assist in establishing a pipeline of interested students to enter into the career track of Cybersecurity at the college level, we trained 17 secondary education teachers in cybersecurity and alternative energy efficiency practices. Through this effort, the teachers prepared curriculum and received equipment to implement labs in their classrooms.</p> <p>This project established a strong connection with local and national companies and other educational institutions, such as Brookhaven National Laboratory, the Cyberwatch Center at Prince George&rsquo;s Community College, Cisco and Amazon. We held a Cybersecurity conference for industry, specifically small businesses, to assist them in how to navigate the various issues surrounding cybersecurity that affect their operations. The conference was so well received that we are in the process of developing a regular series of local follow-on conferences.&nbsp; In addition, we established and maintain a monthly online advisory group meeting. This continues to keep industry and education aligned by informing cybersecurity curriculum development helping industry understand their immediate cybersecurity issues. This group was instrumental in planning and implementing the original conference and remains fully engaged as we plan the series.</p> <p>As the Cybersecurity program continues to expand, we have hired two full-time faculty and a lab assistant. In addition, there are plans in place to build a net-zero energy Renewable Energy and STEM building that will allow for the replication of the current Cybersecurity program to our Michael J. Grant campus location. This will essentially double the size of the current program as well as provide access to many more students and industry as well.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 07/29/2019<br>      Modified by: Peter&nbsp;J&nbsp;Maritato</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Suffolk County Community College?s NSF ATE LIGHTES2 project set out to establish a two-year degree in Cybersecurity. We successfully accomplished the design and implementation of this degree where, upon completion, students can either enter industry in a career related to Cybersecurity or transfer to a four-year college or university to continue their studies in Cybersecurity. The program is successful with approximately 75 students enrolled the first year and  increasing to approximately 120 students in the second year. In addition to implementing the curriculum, we introduced various avenues for students to learn and demonstrate their expertise. The new program provides a cybersecurity learning/mentoring lab for students to practice skills and receive tutoring. The state-of-the art cybersecurity lab provides authentic cybersecurity exercises using dedicated equipment for each student to experience. We also established a cybersecurity club where  students compete in both local and national cybersecurity hackathons.  To assist in establishing a pipeline of interested students to enter into the career track of Cybersecurity at the college level, we trained 17 secondary education teachers in cybersecurity and alternative energy efficiency practices. Through this effort, the teachers prepared curriculum and received equipment to implement labs in their classrooms.  This project established a strong connection with local and national companies and other educational institutions, such as Brookhaven National Laboratory, the Cyberwatch Center at Prince George?s Community College, Cisco and Amazon. We held a Cybersecurity conference for industry, specifically small businesses, to assist them in how to navigate the various issues surrounding cybersecurity that affect their operations. The conference was so well received that we are in the process of developing a regular series of local follow-on conferences.  In addition, we established and maintain a monthly online advisory group meeting. This continues to keep industry and education aligned by informing cybersecurity curriculum development helping industry understand their immediate cybersecurity issues. This group was instrumental in planning and implementing the original conference and remains fully engaged as we plan the series.  As the Cybersecurity program continues to expand, we have hired two full-time faculty and a lab assistant. In addition, there are plans in place to build a net-zero energy Renewable Energy and STEM building that will allow for the replication of the current Cybersecurity program to our Michael J. Grant campus location. This will essentially double the size of the current program as well as provide access to many more students and industry as well.          Last Modified: 07/29/2019       Submitted by: Peter J Maritato]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
