<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Using Californias Drought To Analyze Fractured Groundwater Inputs To High Elevation Meadows</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>12/15/2014</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>11/30/2015</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>25434.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>25434</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>06030109</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>GEO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>EAR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Earth Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Thomas Torgersen</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Using California's Drought to Analyze Groundwater Inputs from Fractured Bedrock to Alpine Meadows&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Quantifying the contribution from groundwater is critical for understanding alpine water supply during both drought and future climate change. Past hydrologic studies in high-elevation mountain meadows have focused on water derived from snowmelt, streams, and adjacent hillslopes to support alpine vegetation. Given California's multi-year drought, one can better identify previously unrecognized groundwater contributions to high-elevation meadows from underlying bedrock. This project will sample and better define the deep groundwater component of the Sierra system through chemical and isotopic means. The project will develop connections to scientists at national labs; and two graduate students will gain field experience, learn new field methods, and participate in laboratory analysis. The Sierra Nevada National Parks and Forests represent an important outdoor classroom for education of the general public in the natural sciences. All project results will be given to the National Park Service for incorporation into their outdoor education programs.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This investigation will take advantage of the current drought when contributions from flowpaths in deep fractured bedrock will yield a high-fidelity geochemical signal that will enable quantification of the location and volume of groundwater entering meadows from bedrock sources. This project will demonstrate a computational methodology for geochemical deconvolution of deep bedrock groundwater and shallow groundwater geochemical signals that can be transferred to other high-elevation meadows where groundwater input has generally been unrecognized. This project will investigate a suite of naturally occurring geochemical tracers in Yosemite groundwater wells to identify the locations of groundwater discharge from fractured bedrock contributing to meadows in the Sierra Nevada Mountains of California. New methods of groundwater sampling for noble gas and isotopic tracers will be developed. Samples of groundwater and stream water will be analyzed for multiple chemical constituents through collaboration with the scientists at Lawrence Livermore National Lab.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>12/15/2014</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>12/15/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.050</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1501520</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Christopher</FirstName>
<LastName>Lowry</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>S</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Christopher S Lowry</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>cslowry@buffalo.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>7166454266</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000596063</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>12/15/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>SUNY at Buffalo</Name>
<CityName>Buffalo</CityName>
<ZipCode>142282567</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>7166452634</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>520 Lee Entrance</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[Suite 211]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>26</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NY26</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>038633251</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>RESEARCH FOUNDATION FOR THE STATE UNIVERSITY OF NEW YORK, THE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>020657151</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University at Buffalo]]></Name>
<CityName>Buffalo</CityName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<ZipCode>142600001</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[411 Cooke Hall]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>26</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NY26</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1579</Code>
<Text>Hydrologic Sciences</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7914</Code>
<Text>RAPID</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0115</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2015~25434</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>California experienced one of the driest winters on record in 2014, which resulted in the designation of a drought emergency. Reduced snow pack in the Sierra Nevada Mountains caused significant concerns for agricultural and drinking water supplies. While seasonal snowmelt represents the largest component of water in Sierra Nevada streams, groundwater flowing through fractured bedrock and discharging to streams also contributes to stream flow. This groundwater flow through fractured rock is assumed to be a smaller component of the total flow leaving the Sierra Nevada Mountains. However, the contribution from fractured bedrock is independent of seasonal drought because the long flow paths integrate snowmelt over many seasons. These fractured flow paths leave a unique and identifiable geochemical signature in the water that can be used to quantify groundwater discharge to streams and meadows. Under normal snow pack conditions much of the geochemical signal from fractured bedrock flowpaths is masked due to the larger contribution of water entering the system from annual snowmelt. The 2014 drought resulted in a rare opportunity to analyze the contribution from deep fractured bedrock sources as a result of the weak snowmelt signal. The research presented here took advantage of the multi-year drought to detect a high fidelity signal from deep fractured bedrock sources. <em>The objective of this research was to use the high fidelity geochemical signal from deep bedrock sources to detect and quantify the contribution of fractured flow inputs into high elevation meadows.</em></p> <p>At our study site, Tuolumne Meadows in Yosemite National Park, we used a combination of stream flow and water chemistry measurements to quantify the contribution of fractured bedrock flow. Tuolumne Meadows is one of 17,000 high elevation meadows within the Sierra Nevada Mountains. The Tuolumne River, which is a major supply of drinking water for the San Francisco Bay area, flows through the middle of Tuolumne Meadows. Using a stream flow meter, we were able to quantify the volume of water flowing within the Tuolumne River at seven locations (Figure 1). For any two neighboring stream flow measurements, if the upstream measurement resulted in a larger volume of water as compared to the downstream measurement, we can assume that stream water is infiltrating into the meadow aquifer. If the downstream measurement resulted in a larger volume of water as compared to the upstream measurement, then we can assume that groundwater is entering the stream, causing flow in the stream to increase. Results from stream flow measurements show both patterns, where water is exiting the stream to groundwater and where groundwater is entering the stream (Figure 2, blue line). By combining these data with water chemistry measurements we can quantify how much water enters the stream from distinctive sources, called end-members. Water flowing out of Tuolumne Meadows has three distinct end-members (Figure 3): stream flow entering the meadow from upstream, groundwater (snowmelt) stored in the sediments along the meadow reach, and fractured bedrock groundwater. Using these end-members, we can determine the volume of water in the stream at the outflow point that originated from groundwater (Figure 2, green line) vs. simply stream water coming from upstream of the meadow (Figure 2, red line).</p> <p>Final results using a combination of measurements of stream flow and water chemistry have allowed us to quantify the contribution of water exiting the meadow from (1) local meadow groundwater, (2) deep fractured bedrock flow paths and (3) surface water simply flowing through the meadow. Results show that 45% of the surface water exiting the meadow comes from the locally derived meadow groundwater (Figure 4, green line). This supports the idea that Sierra Nevada Meadows serve as storage reservoirs for groundwater. A range of 2-3% o...]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ California experienced one of the driest winters on record in 2014, which resulted in the designation of a drought emergency. Reduced snow pack in the Sierra Nevada Mountains caused significant concerns for agricultural and drinking water supplies. While seasonal snowmelt represents the largest component of water in Sierra Nevada streams, groundwater flowing through fractured bedrock and discharging to streams also contributes to stream flow. This groundwater flow through fractured rock is assumed to be a smaller component of the total flow leaving the Sierra Nevada Mountains. However, the contribution from fractured bedrock is independent of seasonal drought because the long flow paths integrate snowmelt over many seasons. These fractured flow paths leave a unique and identifiable geochemical signature in the water that can be used to quantify groundwater discharge to streams and meadows. Under normal snow pack conditions much of the geochemical signal from fractured bedrock flowpaths is masked due to the larger contribution of water entering the system from annual snowmelt. The 2014 drought resulted in a rare opportunity to analyze the contribution from deep fractured bedrock sources as a result of the weak snowmelt signal. The research presented here took advantage of the multi-year drought to detect a high fidelity signal from deep fractured bedrock sources. The objective of this research was to use the high fidelity geochemical signal from deep bedrock sources to detect and quantify the contribution of fractured flow inputs into high elevation meadows.  At our study site, Tuolumne Meadows in Yosemite National Park, we used a combination of stream flow and water chemistry measurements to quantify the contribution of fractured bedrock flow. Tuolumne Meadows is one of 17,000 high elevation meadows within the Sierra Nevada Mountains. The Tuolumne River, which is a major supply of drinking water for the San Francisco Bay area, flows through the middle of Tuolumne Meadows. Using a stream flow meter, we were able to quantify the volume of water flowing within the Tuolumne River at seven locations (Figure 1). For any two neighboring stream flow measurements, if the upstream measurement resulted in a larger volume of water as compared to the downstream measurement, we can assume that stream water is infiltrating into the meadow aquifer. If the downstream measurement resulted in a larger volume of water as compared to the upstream measurement, then we can assume that groundwater is entering the stream, causing flow in the stream to increase. Results from stream flow measurements show both patterns, where water is exiting the stream to groundwater and where groundwater is entering the stream (Figure 2, blue line). By combining these data with water chemistry measurements we can quantify how much water enters the stream from distinctive sources, called end-members. Water flowing out of Tuolumne Meadows has three distinct end-members (Figure 3): stream flow entering the meadow from upstream, groundwater (snowmelt) stored in the sediments along the meadow reach, and fractured bedrock groundwater. Using these end-members, we can determine the volume of water in the stream at the outflow point that originated from groundwater (Figure 2, green line) vs. simply stream water coming from upstream of the meadow (Figure 2, red line).  Final results using a combination of measurements of stream flow and water chemistry have allowed us to quantify the contribution of water exiting the meadow from (1) local meadow groundwater, (2) deep fractured bedrock flow paths and (3) surface water simply flowing through the meadow. Results show that 45% of the surface water exiting the meadow comes from the locally derived meadow groundwater (Figure 4, green line). This supports the idea that Sierra Nevada Meadows serve as storage reservoirs for groundwater. A range of 2-3% of the surface water exiting the meadows comes from deep fractured bedrock sources (...]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
