<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Selective Electrocatalytic Oxidation of Biorenewable Polyols over Bimetal Catalysts</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/20/2014</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2015</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>149974.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>149974</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07020000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CBET</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Chem, Bioeng, Env, &amp; Transp Sys</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Robert McCabe</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>rmccabe@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924826</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Biorenewable polyols such as glycerol, xylitol, and sorbitol are expected to become abundant as a result of lignocellulosic biomass conversion and biofuel production, and thus have great potential to serve as the primary building-blocks for future production of valuable fine chemicals. One of the critical challenges in current heterogeneous catalytic conversions of these polyols is the unsatisfactory catalyst selectivity, which is mainly due to largely unknown side reactions. In addition to the problems resulting from poor selectivity, the rich chemical energy stored in these energetic organic compounds is not directly utilized. Thus, there is a clear need to develop innovative strategies for selective production of high-value chemicals and direct generation of energy from these polyols.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Professor Wenzhen Li at Michigan Technological University, Houghton, MI proposes to investigate aqueous-phase selective electrocatalytic oxidation of polyols for the controlled production of higher-valued chemicals and the simultaneous generation of electricity using anion exchange membrane fuel cells  based on bimetallic catalysts. The research hypotheses are that controlled electric potential applied on bimetallic catalysts with tuned electronic and geographic structures (controlled size, shape and structure) at the anion exchange membrane /water/metal interface will offer efficient cogeneration of chemicals and electricity from biorenewable polyols at the anode. Initial target for electricity is enough power density for portable electronics. Li sees the study as one defining the relationships between electric potential, catalyst structure and catalytic functions of selectivity and activity so as to better capitalize on the systems.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Success of this research will advance understanding of selective catalytic oxidation, and open a new avenue for controlled conversion of biorenewable polyols to high-value chemicals through electrocatalysis processes. It will also contribute to the development of efficient electrochemical energy devices that can directly use biorenewable fuels. This project will provide graduate and undergraduate students with a unique intellectual environment to learn catalysis, electrochemistry, energy, and nanomaterials. The generated results will be incorporated into the undergraduate ?Fuel Cell Fundamental? course, and used in Michigan Tech?s existing outreach programs, especially the summer youth program, in which the majority of students are from under-represented groups.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>10/16/2014</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>10/16/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1501124</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Wenzhen</FirstName>
<LastName>Li</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Wenzhen Li</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>wzli@iastate.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5152944582</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000513491</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>10/16/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Iowa State University</Name>
<CityName>AMES</CityName>
<ZipCode>500112207</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5152945225</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1138 Pearson</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Iowa</StateName>
<StateCode>IA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>IA04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>005309844</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>IOWA STATE UNIVERSITY OF SCIENCE AND TECHNOLOGY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>005309844</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Iowa State University]]></Name>
<CityName>Ames</CityName>
<StateCode>IA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>500112207</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[1138 Pearson]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Iowa</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>IA04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1401</Code>
<Text>Catalysis</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>046E</Code>
<Text>Electrochem, Photochem &amp; Fuel Cls</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0112</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2012~149974</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><strong>Selective Electrocatalytic Oxidation of Biorenewable Polyols over Bimetal Catalysts </strong>(<span style="text-decoration: underline;">CBET-1159448</span>. 09/1/2012-07/19/2014, <span style="text-decoration: underline;">CBET-1501224:</span> 07/20/2014-08/31/2015; $259,998)</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p class="Default">&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; This NSF project investigated aqueous-phase selective electrocatalytic oxidation of polyols for controlled production of higher-valued chemicals and simultaneous generation of electricity, and acquired deep understanding of the relationships of electric potential and the catalytic functions (selectivity and activity) on nanostructured bimetal catalysts in high pH media for efficient utilization of biomass-derived compounds. Through this three years NSF grant support, the main research activities/findings include: 1) Two wet-chemistry synthesis methods (nanocapsule and water-phase reduction) were developed to preparation of carbon or carbon nanotube (CNT) supported Pt, Pd, Au, PdAu alloy, PdCo surface dealloy nanoparticle catalysts with small size and narrow uniform size distribution. 2) Potential-controlled glycerol electro-oxidation to chemicals tartronate or mesoxalate on Au nanoparticle catalysts was found in both anion-exchange membrane electro-catalytic flow cell and fuel cell reactors.3) A direct crude glycerol anion-exchange membrane fuel cell with PtCo dealloy /CNT anode catalyst was developed to achieve a high peak power density of 268 mW cm<sup>-2</sup> at 80 &deg;C and ambient pressure. 4) Selective oxidation of multi-functional biorenewable molecule 5-hydroxymethylfurfural (5-HMF, containing one aldehyde and one hydroxyl group) was studied over Pd-Au bimetallic catalysts, and new insights into the synergistic effect of Pd-Au alloying for selective oxidation was gained through electrochemical methods. 5) Selective electro-oxidation of 1,2-propanediol was investigated by combining DFT simulation and examining reaction products of partial oxidation intermediates, and new understanding was generated to explain why deeper oxidized products (such as pyruvate) can be generated through electrocatalytic oxidation (but not through heterogeneous chemical catalytic oxidation). 6) A one-dimensional mathematical model was developed to simulate direct glycerol anion exchange membrane fuel cells with Au-anode catalysts. 7) Ag was found to be more active towards aldehyde oxidation than Pd, while Pd is more active towards hydroxyl group oxidation, therefore, the synergistic effect of PdAg was found to be able to better oxidize polyol or HMF.&nbsp;8) 3D graphene and multi-wall carbon nanotubes were found to be able to work as metal-free carbon catalysts for carbohydrazide oxidation in high pH medium and metal-free fuel cells with carbon only catalysts were demonstrated. The generated knowledge can be widely applied to various areas, such as catalysis, fuel cells, electrolysis, biorefinery, green chemical processes and chemical sensing. Nine papers were published in peer-reviewed journals (including Green Chemistry, Applied Catalysis B Environmental, ACS Catalysis, Carbon, ChemSusChem, and International Journal of Hydrogen Energy), and one book chapter was published by Wiley, and another three manuscripts are under preparation. One patent is under preparation. Totally 17 presentations (in ECS, ACS and AIChE meetings) and nine invited talks in universities and institutes have acknowledged this NSF grant.</p> <p>The research activities have been closely integrated into a variety of education and outreach activities and have greatly stimulated the passion of the participating students in catalysis, materials and clean energy research. Partially supported by this grant, five graduate and four undergraduate students have actively participated in this project, and received strict catalysis and engineering research tr...]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Selective Electrocatalytic Oxidation of Biorenewable Polyols over Bimetal Catalysts (CBET-1159448. 09/1/2012-07/19/2014, CBET-1501224: 07/20/2014-08/31/2015; $259,998)             This NSF project investigated aqueous-phase selective electrocatalytic oxidation of polyols for controlled production of higher-valued chemicals and simultaneous generation of electricity, and acquired deep understanding of the relationships of electric potential and the catalytic functions (selectivity and activity) on nanostructured bimetal catalysts in high pH media for efficient utilization of biomass-derived compounds. Through this three years NSF grant support, the main research activities/findings include: 1) Two wet-chemistry synthesis methods (nanocapsule and water-phase reduction) were developed to preparation of carbon or carbon nanotube (CNT) supported Pt, Pd, Au, PdAu alloy, PdCo surface dealloy nanoparticle catalysts with small size and narrow uniform size distribution. 2) Potential-controlled glycerol electro-oxidation to chemicals tartronate or mesoxalate on Au nanoparticle catalysts was found in both anion-exchange membrane electro-catalytic flow cell and fuel cell reactors.3) A direct crude glycerol anion-exchange membrane fuel cell with PtCo dealloy /CNT anode catalyst was developed to achieve a high peak power density of 268 mW cm-2 at 80 &deg;C and ambient pressure. 4) Selective oxidation of multi-functional biorenewable molecule 5-hydroxymethylfurfural (5-HMF, containing one aldehyde and one hydroxyl group) was studied over Pd-Au bimetallic catalysts, and new insights into the synergistic effect of Pd-Au alloying for selective oxidation was gained through electrochemical methods. 5) Selective electro-oxidation of 1,2-propanediol was investigated by combining DFT simulation and examining reaction products of partial oxidation intermediates, and new understanding was generated to explain why deeper oxidized products (such as pyruvate) can be generated through electrocatalytic oxidation (but not through heterogeneous chemical catalytic oxidation). 6) A one-dimensional mathematical model was developed to simulate direct glycerol anion exchange membrane fuel cells with Au-anode catalysts. 7) Ag was found to be more active towards aldehyde oxidation than Pd, while Pd is more active towards hydroxyl group oxidation, therefore, the synergistic effect of PdAg was found to be able to better oxidize polyol or HMF. 8) 3D graphene and multi-wall carbon nanotubes were found to be able to work as metal-free carbon catalysts for carbohydrazide oxidation in high pH medium and metal-free fuel cells with carbon only catalysts were demonstrated. The generated knowledge can be widely applied to various areas, such as catalysis, fuel cells, electrolysis, biorefinery, green chemical processes and chemical sensing. Nine papers were published in peer-reviewed journals (including Green Chemistry, Applied Catalysis B Environmental, ACS Catalysis, Carbon, ChemSusChem, and International Journal of Hydrogen Energy), and one book chapter was published by Wiley, and another three manuscripts are under preparation. One patent is under preparation. Totally 17 presentations (in ECS, ACS and AIChE meetings) and nine invited talks in universities and institutes have acknowledged this NSF grant.  The research activities have been closely integrated into a variety of education and outreach activities and have greatly stimulated the passion of the participating students in catalysis, materials and clean energy research. Partially supported by this grant, five graduate and four undergraduate students have actively participated in this project, and received strict catalysis and engineering research training. One student received his PhD degree and one planned to defend his PhD dissertation in 2015 December. The PI has participated in Michigan TechÆs existing Summer Youth Programs and trained with over 20 diverse high school students to learn catalyst preparation, elect...]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
