<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Dissertation Research: Evolutionary transitions: pollination biology and domestication of Artocarpus (Moraceae)</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2015</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>17882.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>17882</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>08010206</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>BIO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DEB</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Environmental Biology</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Simon Malcomber</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>smalcomb@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032928227</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The rapid diversification and rise to dominance of angiosperms is one of the enduring mysteries of evolutionary biology. While coevolution with animal pollinators is a major driver of angiosperm diversity, the degree of advantage conferred by animal pollination over wind pollination has been controversial, and the rarity of appropriate study systems has hampered progress in understanding the consequences of this transition. This research uses the tropical tree genus Artocarpus (Moraceae)- one of the rare systems exhibiting transitions from wind to animal pollination - to investigate evolutionary implications of that shift. Artocarpus pollination ranges from wind to a unique mutualism mediated by parasitic fungi that provide a brood site and nutrition for fly pollinators. This project provides the opportunity to understand morphological characters associated with pollination shifts, challenge assumptions about reversions from wind to animal pollination, and expose characters that may have been involved in the early radiation of flowering plants as they co-evolved with their animal pollinators. Artocarpus contains several underutilized crops including breadfruit, jackfruit, and terap. This research will support efforts to develop and improve important Artocarpus crops by increasing understanding of their reproductive biology.&lt;br/&gt; &lt;br/&gt;The project combines experimental pollinator-exclusion studies with morphological analysis to elucidate pollination mechanisms in Artocarpus and reveal morphological traits correlated with transitions between wind and insect pollination. These transitions will be combined with phylogenomic analyses for the group, to analyze changes in morphology in an evolutionary context, and to resolve the number and direction of wind-insect pollination transitions in Artocarpus. The research uses microsatellite DNA fingerprinting to uncover the domestication history of the insect-pollinated species Artocarpus odoratissimus, one of several underutilized tropical tree crops in this genus. Through collaborations in Malaysia, this project will promote scientific research on a group of underutilized crops in developing tropical regions and provide training in pollination biology to local scientists. The research will also provide research opportunities for undergraduates. The researchers will engage the public through displays at the Chicago Botanic Garden to promote awareness of pollination biology and tropical biodiversity.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>03/24/2015</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>03/24/2015</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.074</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1501373</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Nyree</FirstName>
<LastName>Zerega</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>J</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Nyree J Zerega</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>nzerega@chicagobotanic.org</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>8478356916</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000273879</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>03/24/2015</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Elliot</FirstName>
<LastName>Gardner</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Elliot Gardner</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>egardner@u.northwestern.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>9179025064</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000734426</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>03/24/2015</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Chicago Horticultural Society</Name>
<CityName>Glencoe</CityName>
<ZipCode>600221168</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>8478355440</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1000 Lake Cook Road</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Illinois</StateName>
<StateCode>IL</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>10</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>IL10</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>068477231</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>CHICAGO HORTICULTURAL SOCIETY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Chicago Botanic Garden]]></Name>
<CityName>Glencoe</CityName>
<StateCode>IL</StateCode>
<ZipCode>600221168</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[1000 Lake Cook Road]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Illinois</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>10</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>IL10</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1171</Code>
<Text>PHYLOGENETIC SYSTEMATICS</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9169</Code>
<Text>BIODIVERSITY AND ECOSYSTEM DYNAMICS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9179</Code>
<Text>GRADUATE INVOLVEMENT</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>EGCH</Code>
<Text>ENVIRONMENT AND GLOBAL CHANGE</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>SMET</Code>
<Text>SCIENCE, MATH, ENG &amp; TECH EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0115</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2015~17882</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The breadfruit genus (<em>Artocarpus</em>)<em> </em>is a member of the mulberry (Moraceae) family. <em>Artocarpus </em>contains over 70 species, thought to include both wind and insect pollinated species. About a dozen species are also important underutilized crops, including breadfruit (<em>A. altilis</em>), jackfruit (<em>A, heterophyllus</em>), cempedak (<em>A. integer</em>), and several others. This genus provides an opportunity to study a rare evolutionary transition from wind to insect pollination, while also contributing to increased understanding of underutilized crops to promote food security. Transitions from insect to wind pollination, and associated loss of animal attractants such as showy petals or nectar, are fairly common among flowering plants. However, the reverse transition from wind to insect pollination is rarely documented, but it is found in <em>Artocarpus. </em>This project combined genetic studies with field experiments, floral scent analysis, and observations to investigate the evolutionary history of <em>Artocarpus </em>and transitions between wind and insect pollination. Additionally, genetic analyses were used to investigate the origin and diversity of tarap (<em>A. odoratissimus</em>), an underutilized but locally important fruit tree in Borneo.<em>&nbsp;</em></p> <p>This award supported fieldwork in Sabah and Sarawak, Malaysia, as well as in Hawai&rsquo;i and Florida. The project resulted in more than 300 plant specimen collections, including over 150 herbarium specimens that will be permanently archived in natural history collections in Malaysia and the USA. The co-PI also collected several hundred insects in Malaysia and Florida, also to be archived in natural history collections, including at least three previously undescribed species that are likely important pollinators of two&nbsp;<em>Artocarpus&nbsp;</em>fruit crops &ndash; jackfruit and cempedak.</p> <p>The first publication from this project, currently in review, provides a detailed look at jackfruit pollination and the behavior of a likely pollinator, a new species of gall midge described in the paper. The gall midge is attracted to male and female flower heads by floral scent, but only receives a reward, in the form of a brood site, in the male flower head. The second publication, in preparation, provides a high-resolution tree (phylogeny) of evolutionary relationships in <em>Artocarpus</em>, based on DNA from both newly-collected specimens and museum specimens up to 107 years old; that paper will provide the basis for analyses of transitions in pollination and also reveals previously-unknown wild relatives of cultivated species such as breadfruit. &nbsp;Other publications arising from this project will provide one of the first in-depth examinations of transitions from wind to animal pollination in the tropics, combining morphology, empirical studies, observations, and floral scent chemistry. Results challenge assumptions concerning both the possibility of the evolution of animal pollination in wind-pollinated lineages, but also the wind/insect pollination dichotomy itself, with results raising the possibility that some&nbsp;<em>Artocarpus&nbsp;</em>species may take advantage of both mechanisms. The research on the origins and diversity of tarap (<em>A. odoratissimus</em>) have provided a rare densely-sampled look at the genetics of a tropical underutilized crop. A publication in preparation will also highlight the importance of traditional indigenous knowledge in biodiversity studies.</p> <p>This award provided the co-PI, a PhD candidate, with important opportunities to present his work at international conferences and develop collaborations with other scientists in the USA and abroad, one of which led directly to a postdoctoral fellowship. In addition, the project provided hands-on research opportunities for two undergraduate and three high-school students. The PIs used project results and scientific images for outreach to the general public through the Chicago Botanic Garden, Northwestern University, and local schools, to promote awareness of tropical biodiversity, underutilized crops, and how biodiversity science can promote both conservation and food security.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 10/31/2017<br>      Modified by: Elliot&nbsp;Gardner</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Image         </div> <div class="galControls onePhoto" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation onePhoto" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1501373/1501373_10355629_1509390008711_Figure1-Artocarpusdiversity--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1501373/1501373_10355629_1509390008711_Figure1-Artocarpusdiversity--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Diversity of Artocarpus"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1501373/1501373_10355629_1509390008711_Figure1-Artocarpusdiversity--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Diversity of Artocarpus"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Diversity of Artocarpus (Moraceae). (A-C), A. limpato; (D-I), subgenus Pseudojaca; (J-N) subgenus Cauliflori, including jackfruit (K-N); (O-U), subgenus Artocarpus, including breadfruit (O, T) and tarap (Q, R).</div> <div class="imageCredit">E. Gardner, N. Zerega</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Elliot&nbsp;Gardner</div> <div class="imageTitle">Diversity of Artocarpus</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The breadfruit genus (Artocarpus) is a member of the mulberry (Moraceae) family. Artocarpus contains over 70 species, thought to include both wind and insect pollinated species. About a dozen species are also important underutilized crops, including breadfruit (A. altilis), jackfruit (A, heterophyllus), cempedak (A. integer), and several others. This genus provides an opportunity to study a rare evolutionary transition from wind to insect pollination, while also contributing to increased understanding of underutilized crops to promote food security. Transitions from insect to wind pollination, and associated loss of animal attractants such as showy petals or nectar, are fairly common among flowering plants. However, the reverse transition from wind to insect pollination is rarely documented, but it is found in Artocarpus. This project combined genetic studies with field experiments, floral scent analysis, and observations to investigate the evolutionary history of Artocarpus and transitions between wind and insect pollination. Additionally, genetic analyses were used to investigate the origin and diversity of tarap (A. odoratissimus), an underutilized but locally important fruit tree in Borneo.   This award supported fieldwork in Sabah and Sarawak, Malaysia, as well as in Hawai?i and Florida. The project resulted in more than 300 plant specimen collections, including over 150 herbarium specimens that will be permanently archived in natural history collections in Malaysia and the USA. The co-PI also collected several hundred insects in Malaysia and Florida, also to be archived in natural history collections, including at least three previously undescribed species that are likely important pollinators of two Artocarpus fruit crops &ndash; jackfruit and cempedak.  The first publication from this project, currently in review, provides a detailed look at jackfruit pollination and the behavior of a likely pollinator, a new species of gall midge described in the paper. The gall midge is attracted to male and female flower heads by floral scent, but only receives a reward, in the form of a brood site, in the male flower head. The second publication, in preparation, provides a high-resolution tree (phylogeny) of evolutionary relationships in Artocarpus, based on DNA from both newly-collected specimens and museum specimens up to 107 years old; that paper will provide the basis for analyses of transitions in pollination and also reveals previously-unknown wild relatives of cultivated species such as breadfruit.  Other publications arising from this project will provide one of the first in-depth examinations of transitions from wind to animal pollination in the tropics, combining morphology, empirical studies, observations, and floral scent chemistry. Results challenge assumptions concerning both the possibility of the evolution of animal pollination in wind-pollinated lineages, but also the wind/insect pollination dichotomy itself, with results raising the possibility that some Artocarpus species may take advantage of both mechanisms. The research on the origins and diversity of tarap (A. odoratissimus) have provided a rare densely-sampled look at the genetics of a tropical underutilized crop. A publication in preparation will also highlight the importance of traditional indigenous knowledge in biodiversity studies.  This award provided the co-PI, a PhD candidate, with important opportunities to present his work at international conferences and develop collaborations with other scientists in the USA and abroad, one of which led directly to a postdoctoral fellowship. In addition, the project provided hands-on research opportunities for two undergraduate and three high-school students. The PIs used project results and scientific images for outreach to the general public through the Chicago Botanic Garden, Northwestern University, and local schools, to promote awareness of tropical biodiversity, underutilized crops, and how biodiversity science can promote both conservation and food security.          Last Modified: 10/31/2017       Submitted by: Elliot Gardner]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
