<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>DISSERTATION RESEARCH: Evolutionary Consequences of Direct and Indirect Contributions to Additive Genetic Variation in Wild Baboons.</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2015</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>20515.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>20515</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>08010207</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>BIO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DEB</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Environmental Biology</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Leslie J. Rissler</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>lrissler@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924628</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>A major goal of evolutionary biology is to understand how genes and environments combine to create the variation we see among animals in nature. Variation in social behavior, in particular, is important to understand, because we know that an animal's social behavior has a major impact on how effectively it copes with its environment. However, social living blurs the distinction between genes and environments because the social environment is (at least partly) determined by the genes of its members. Accordingly, the genes that influence an animal's social behavior include its own genes (direct genetic effects, DGEs) and potentially also the genes of its parents, siblings and social partners (indirect genetic effects, IGEs). Theory has shown that IGEs can profoundly affect how social behavior evolves.  However, remarkably few studies have investigated how IGEs contribute to variation in social behavior or whether IGEs affect life history traits and social behavior in natural animal populations, outside of the laboratory.  This proposal investigates the role of direct and indirect genetic effects in the evolution of life history and social behavior in a natural population of highly social non-human primates and will thus provide data that can test the theoretical result described above. This will be one of only a handful of studies of both direct and indirect genetic effects on phenotypic variation in the wild, and has the potential to greatly enhance understanding of the evolution of life history and social behavior. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The PIs will use mixed effects linear models (in particular, the 'animal model') in a quantitative genetics approach to measure the direct and indirect genetic variation contributing to life history and social behaviors in the well-studied wild baboons of Amboseli National Park, Kenya.  We will also measure the covariance between direct and indirect genetic effects to understand the consequences of this genetic architecture on the phenotypic evolution of these traits.  These findings will be communicated to the scientific community and general public through conference presentations and educational outreach.  Additionally, this work will provide important training for students and researchers from underrepresented minorities and foster global collaborations between USA, Kenyan and UK institutions.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>04/01/2015</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>11/27/2017</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.074</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1501971</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Susan</FirstName>
<LastName>Alberts</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>C</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Susan C Alberts</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>alberts@duke.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>9196607272</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000433448</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/01/2015</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Emily</FirstName>
<LastName>McLean</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Emily McLean</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>emily.m.mclean@gmail.com</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>9196843030</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000678902</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/01/2015</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Duke University</Name>
<CityName>Durham</CityName>
<ZipCode>277054010</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>9196843030</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>2200 W. Main St, Suite 710</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[Erwin Square]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>North Carolina</StateName>
<StateCode>NC</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NC01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>044387793</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>DUKE UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>044387793</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Duke University]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>NC</StateCode>
<ZipCode>277054010</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>North Carolina</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NC04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7378</Code>
<Text>EVOLUTIONARY GENETICS</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9169</Code>
<Text>BIODIVERSITY AND ECOSYSTEM DYNAMICS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9179</Code>
<Text>GRADUATE INVOLVEMENT</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>EGCH</Code>
<Text>ENVIRONMENT AND GLOBAL CHANGE</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>SMET</Code>
<Text>SCIENCE, MATH, ENG &amp; TECH EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0115</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2015~20515</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Understanding the genetic and environmental forces that contribute to phenotypic variation is a major goal of evolutionary biology. However, social living blurs the distinction between genes and environments because the social environmentis (at least in part) determined by the genes of its members. Therefore, the genes that influence an individual&rsquo;s phenotype are not limited to his own genes (direct genetic effects) but potentially include the genes of individuals in his social context (indirect genetic effects). Indirect genetic effects are thought to be of particular importance in the evolution of social behavior.</p> <p>Social living is a common phenotype in many animal taxa and is especially well-developed in non-human primates and humans. Social living is believed to be an adaptive response to ecological pressures and indeed, positive correlations between social behaviors and fitness components have been demonstrated in multiple species. However, despite a long-history of theoretical studies investigating the evolution of social behavior, whether social behaviors demonstrate the additive genetic variation necessary for evolution to occur remains poorly understood. No doubt this is due in part to the difficulty of determining the genetic basis of social behavior; social phenotypes are complex and by definition involve interactions between multiple individuals. Genetic variation for social behaviors, therefore, likely results from both direct and indirect genetic effects.</p> <p>With this award, we investigated the direct and indirect sources of additive genetic variancein both agonistic and affiliative social behaviors, in a population of wild baboons. In this population (as well as in other populations and species), affiliative social behaviors have been clearly linked to survival, an important fitness component. Therefore, we began with an investigation of the sources of variance in female fitness in our population. <span style="color: #2d2d2d;">We found that heterogeneity in the phenotypic quality of female&nbsp;&mdash;&nbsp;which we assess by a combined metric that considered their age at maturity, how rapidly they were able to reproduce, how long they lived, and how well their offspring survived&nbsp;&mdash;&nbsp; &nbsp;was a primary driver of the relationship between&nbsp;</span><span>life history traits. Specifically, while all females experienced tradeoffs between life history traits, these tradeoffs were apparent only when considering variation&nbsp;</span><span>among females in their individual quality.</span> Next, we used a quantitative genetic approach to examine the direct and indirect sources of genetic variation in affiliative social behavior (grooming). We found that both grooming given and grooming received were heritable, and documented a positive genetic correlation between these traits. Finaly, we examined the sources of genetic variation in agonistic behavior. This investigation was complicated by the non-genetic transmission of dominance ranks from mothers to daughters. We implemented a novel method to partition social and genetic sources of similarity between relatives and found important roles for both genetic and social variance in therelationship between agonism given and agonism received.</p> <p>The work described here is among the first to integrate primate behavioral ecology and quantitative genetics. We hope this integration serves to advance both fields, as behavioral ecology is investigation of how behavior evolves in response to ecological and environmental pressures and quantitative genetics provides the information needed to build realistic evolutionary models which consider the genetic (co)variation in traits.</p> <p>This work may prove to have profound implications for our understanding of the evolution of cooperation. Theoretical work has shown that the covariance between IGEs and DGEs could play a vital role in the evolution of altruism.&nbsp;&nbsp;Despite the potentially large effects of IGEs on the evolution of altruism or cooperation, to date, we are unaware of any previous studies that have examined the IGE-DGE covariance for cooperative behaviors in wild populations. Non-human primates, as close relatives of humans, are an especially exciting group in which to study the genetic basis of affiliative social behaviors because such studies may lead to insight about the evolution of the extreme cooperation and altruism seen in humans.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 04/02/2019<br>      Modified by: Emily&nbsp;Mclean</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Understanding the genetic and environmental forces that contribute to phenotypic variation is a major goal of evolutionary biology. However, social living blurs the distinction between genes and environments because the social environmentis (at least in part) determined by the genes of its members. Therefore, the genes that influence an individual?s phenotype are not limited to his own genes (direct genetic effects) but potentially include the genes of individuals in his social context (indirect genetic effects). Indirect genetic effects are thought to be of particular importance in the evolution of social behavior.  Social living is a common phenotype in many animal taxa and is especially well-developed in non-human primates and humans. Social living is believed to be an adaptive response to ecological pressures and indeed, positive correlations between social behaviors and fitness components have been demonstrated in multiple species. However, despite a long-history of theoretical studies investigating the evolution of social behavior, whether social behaviors demonstrate the additive genetic variation necessary for evolution to occur remains poorly understood. No doubt this is due in part to the difficulty of determining the genetic basis of social behavior; social phenotypes are complex and by definition involve interactions between multiple individuals. Genetic variation for social behaviors, therefore, likely results from both direct and indirect genetic effects.  With this award, we investigated the direct and indirect sources of additive genetic variancein both agonistic and affiliative social behaviors, in a population of wild baboons. In this population (as well as in other populations and species), affiliative social behaviors have been clearly linked to survival, an important fitness component. Therefore, we began with an investigation of the sources of variance in female fitness in our population. We found that heterogeneity in the phenotypic quality of female &mdash; which we assess by a combined metric that considered their age at maturity, how rapidly they were able to reproduce, how long they lived, and how well their offspring survived &mdash;   was a primary driver of the relationship between life history traits. Specifically, while all females experienced tradeoffs between life history traits, these tradeoffs were apparent only when considering variation among females in their individual quality. Next, we used a quantitative genetic approach to examine the direct and indirect sources of genetic variation in affiliative social behavior (grooming). We found that both grooming given and grooming received were heritable, and documented a positive genetic correlation between these traits. Finaly, we examined the sources of genetic variation in agonistic behavior. This investigation was complicated by the non-genetic transmission of dominance ranks from mothers to daughters. We implemented a novel method to partition social and genetic sources of similarity between relatives and found important roles for both genetic and social variance in therelationship between agonism given and agonism received.  The work described here is among the first to integrate primate behavioral ecology and quantitative genetics. We hope this integration serves to advance both fields, as behavioral ecology is investigation of how behavior evolves in response to ecological and environmental pressures and quantitative genetics provides the information needed to build realistic evolutionary models which consider the genetic (co)variation in traits.  This work may prove to have profound implications for our understanding of the evolution of cooperation. Theoretical work has shown that the covariance between IGEs and DGEs could play a vital role in the evolution of altruism.  Despite the potentially large effects of IGEs on the evolution of altruism or cooperation, to date, we are unaware of any previous studies that have examined the IGE-DGE covariance for cooperative behaviors in wild populations. Non-human primates, as close relatives of humans, are an especially exciting group in which to study the genetic basis of affiliative social behaviors because such studies may lead to insight about the evolution of the extreme cooperation and altruism seen in humans.       Last Modified: 04/02/2019       Submitted by: Emily Mclean]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
