<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Promoting Technology Apprenticeship Consortia</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2015</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>197910.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>197910</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>11040100</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>EHR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DUE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Undergraduate Education</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Elizabeth Teles</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>In recent years manufacturing and industry in the United States have changed remarkably. Low-skill, labor intensive jobs have moved overseas while processes have become highly technical and automated. Workers who lost jobs in manufacturing find they do not have the technical skills needed to qualify for new jobs in modern industry. High school graduates also will need additional technical education to compete for good jobs in the current economy. Apprenticeship, which was for centuries the primary method of technical training, is re-emerging in the United States as a means to meet the needs of modern industry. This project at Gaston College in North Carolina will build on a successful apprenticeship program created in partnership with a local industry and will provide a model for the creation and support of apprenticeship consortia in which industries partner with each other, the community college, the public school system, and local economic development agencies to provide highly skilled advanced technology workers. The knowledge obtained from the project will allow other colleges to adapt the model to the needs of their own local industries and will promote the creation of similar consortia. Through this program, students will work and receive specific on-the-job training while concurrently taking technical college courses related to their job. The company will pay the wages of the students and also pay for their tuition and books. Upon completion, students will receive an academic certificate from the college, will be certified as a Journeyworker in a U.S. Department of Labor recognized job title, and will have secure employment with the company. The company will have an employee whose education and training is tailored to their specific needs. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The goal of this project is to promote the creation of local consortia of industries with similar needs. The primary advantage will be a pool of students that will allow the college to offer and schedule classes as well as purchase laboratory equipment that will meet the needs of employers. Each consortium will belong to the industry members; but the college will provides advice, support, and coordination for the academic portion of the program. This project will allow the college to create services and activities that will promote the formation and growth of apprenticeship consortia for Chemical Operators and Industrial Mechanics, the two college programs already in place. A Success Coach will provide assistance to apprentices in the academic portion of their program. A consultant will assist the companies with development and maintenance of apprenticeship programs and will facilitate communications between the companies and the college. Marketing materials will be created to promote advanced manufacturing and apprenticeships. Partners will include the industries in the consortia, Lincoln County and Gaston County Public Schools, the North Carolina Department of Commerce, which administers apprenticeship programs in the state, and Economic Development entities in both counties. A comprehensive evaluation will determine the components needed for these apprenticeship programs to succeed.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>05/27/2015</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>01/27/2017</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.076</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1501267</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>George</FirstName>
<LastName>Hendricks</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>H</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME>III</PI_SUFX_NAME>
<PI_FULL_NAME>George H Hendricks</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>hendricks.george@gaston.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>7049226305</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000678509</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/27/2015</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Diane</FirstName>
<LastName>Metcalfe</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>B</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Diane B Metcalfe</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>metcalfe.diane@gaston.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>7049226591</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000678521</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/27/2015</StartDate>
<EndDate>01/27/2017</EndDate>
<RoleCode>Former Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Dennis</FirstName>
<LastName>McElhoe</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>L</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Dennis L McElhoe</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>McElhoe.Dennis@gaston.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>7049226266</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000741285</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>01/27/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Gaston College</Name>
<CityName>Dallas</CityName>
<ZipCode>280349565</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>7049226511</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>201 Highway 321 South</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>North Carolina</StateName>
<StateCode>NC</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>10</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NC10</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>030497689</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>GASTON COLLEGE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>003459047</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Gaston College]]></Name>
<CityName>Dallas</CityName>
<StateCode>NC</StateCode>
<ZipCode>280341499</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[201 Hwy 321 South]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>North Carolina</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NC05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1536</Code>
<Text>S-STEM-Schlr Sci Tech Eng&amp;Math</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7412</Code>
<Text>Advanced Tech Education Prog</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1032</Code>
<Text>ADVANCED TECHNOLOGY EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9178</Code>
<Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>SMET</Code>
<Text>SCIENCE, MATH, ENG &amp; TECH EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0415</Code>
<Name>NSF Education &amp; Human Resource</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040106</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>13XX</Code>
<Name>H-1B FUND, EHR, NSF</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>045176</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2015~197910</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The Promoting Apprenticeship Consortia for Technology project allowed Gaston College to expand an apprenticeship program with one company into Apprenticeship 321, a consortium of 12 companies with six advanced manufacturing apprenticeship jobs registered to the college. During the project 33 students have received academic course credits and on-the-job training; seven have completed their programs, received academic certificates, been certified as Journeyworkers in U.S. Department of Labor job titles, and are continuing to work with their company.</p> <p>Students have benefitted by earning employer-funded academic credits while working in their industry and by making progress toward nationally recognized Journeyworker certification in their job titles. These credits put them well along the path to earn Associate of Applied Science degrees. Beyond this, they have received valuable hands-on training in their specific jobs and have the opportunity to continue promising careers as highly skilled advanced manufacturing technicians.</p> <p>Industry has benefitted by having an opportunity to custom train apprentices to fill in-demand high-skill positions in their companies. Recognizing the challenge of an aging workforce and the scarcity of qualified mid-skill candidates, they have found apprenticeship an excellent way to ensure that they maintain the technically capable workforce they need to continue to be successful. Because the apprenticeship jobs are registered to the college, they are able to do this without the administrative overhead of creating their own registered program. This centralization avoids a great deal of duplication of effort among the companies and allows even smaller companies to enjoy the benefits of an apprenticeship program. Employment at member companies ranges from about 100 employees to about 1000 employees.</p> <p>Gaston College has benefitted from the project through increased enrollment in technical courses and an opportunity to contribute directly to our institutional goal of providing a highly skilled workforce for our service area. It has also benefitted from increased internal and external collaboration. Internally, the project has created close ties between the Engineering and Industrial Technologies academic division that provide technical education and Economic and Workforce Development division that works closely with local industry. Despite limited interaction in the past, the project was successful due to a strong collaborative team effort between the divisions. The project has also brought the college together with multiple local industries, economic development entities, and public school Career and Technical Education representatives.</p> <p>Apprenticeship 321 continues to grow; we believe it will continue to provide benefits for all involved for years to come.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 11/20/2017<br>      Modified by: George&nbsp;H&nbsp;Hendricks</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Images (<span id="selectedPhoto0">1</span> of <span class="totalNumber"></span>)           </div> <div class="galControls" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1501267/1501267_10365576_1511206844085_PACT1--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1501267/1501267_10365576_1511206844085_PACT1--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Apprentice at Work"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1501267/1501267_10365576_1511206844085_PACT1--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Apprentice at Work"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Apprentice at work.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Gaston College</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">George&nbsp;H&nbsp;Hendricks</div> <div class="imageTitle">Apprentice at Work</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1501267/1501267_10365576_1511206915803_PACT2--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1501267/1501267_10365576_1511206915803_PACT2--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Apprentice with Mentor"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1501267/1501267_10365576_1511206915803_PACT2--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Apprentice with Mentor"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Apprentice with mentor</div> <div class="imageCredit">Gaston College</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">George&nbsp;H&nbsp;Hendricks</div> <div class="imageTitle">Apprentice with Mentor</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1501267/1501267_10365576_1511207011566_PACT4--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1501267/1501267_10365576_1511207011566_PACT4--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Journeyworker Presention Ceremony"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1501267/1501267_10365576_1511207011566_PACT4--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Journeyworker Presention Ceremony"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Apprentices and sponsors at a ceremony awarding them journeyworker status</div> <div class="imageCredit">Gaston College</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">George&nbsp;H&nbsp;Hendricks</div> <div class="imageTitle">Journeyworker Presention Ceremony</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The Promoting Apprenticeship Consortia for Technology project allowed Gaston College to expand an apprenticeship program with one company into Apprenticeship 321, a consortium of 12 companies with six advanced manufacturing apprenticeship jobs registered to the college. During the project 33 students have received academic course credits and on-the-job training; seven have completed their programs, received academic certificates, been certified as Journeyworkers in U.S. Department of Labor job titles, and are continuing to work with their company.  Students have benefitted by earning employer-funded academic credits while working in their industry and by making progress toward nationally recognized Journeyworker certification in their job titles. These credits put them well along the path to earn Associate of Applied Science degrees. Beyond this, they have received valuable hands-on training in their specific jobs and have the opportunity to continue promising careers as highly skilled advanced manufacturing technicians.  Industry has benefitted by having an opportunity to custom train apprentices to fill in-demand high-skill positions in their companies. Recognizing the challenge of an aging workforce and the scarcity of qualified mid-skill candidates, they have found apprenticeship an excellent way to ensure that they maintain the technically capable workforce they need to continue to be successful. Because the apprenticeship jobs are registered to the college, they are able to do this without the administrative overhead of creating their own registered program. This centralization avoids a great deal of duplication of effort among the companies and allows even smaller companies to enjoy the benefits of an apprenticeship program. Employment at member companies ranges from about 100 employees to about 1000 employees.  Gaston College has benefitted from the project through increased enrollment in technical courses and an opportunity to contribute directly to our institutional goal of providing a highly skilled workforce for our service area. It has also benefitted from increased internal and external collaboration. Internally, the project has created close ties between the Engineering and Industrial Technologies academic division that provide technical education and Economic and Workforce Development division that works closely with local industry. Despite limited interaction in the past, the project was successful due to a strong collaborative team effort between the divisions. The project has also brought the college together with multiple local industries, economic development entities, and public school Career and Technical Education representatives.  Apprenticeship 321 continues to grow; we believe it will continue to provide benefits for all involved for years to come.          Last Modified: 11/20/2017       Submitted by: George H Hendricks]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
