<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>DISSERTATION RESEARCH:  Partitioning rhizosphere effects on microbial community structure and carbon cycling across a peatland water table gradient.</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2015</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>21091.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>21091</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>08010209</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>BIO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DEB</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Environmental Biology</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Matthew Kane</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>mkane@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927186</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Peatlands, such as bogs, are unique ecosystems that occupy only a small fraction of the Earth's land surface but contain vast quantities of carbon. Peatlands  store so much carbon because they are saturated with water, and this creates an anaerobic environment that slows decomposition of complex organic (carbon-containing) substances. Over the next 100 years, heightened drought frequency and severity is projected to reduce water table heights in high latitude peatlands, causing them to emit more carbon gases to the atmosphere. The goal of this project is to identify the effect of water table reduction and associated changes in plant community structure on the microorganisms living in a northern peatland.  The release of carbon gasses is controlled by these microorganisms through their  decomposition of organic material. The work will provide novel insight into the impact of physical and plant-mediated environmental changes on microbial community structure and activity, and will deepeour understanding of ecosystem responses to climate change. In addition to support the graduate student's doctoral dissertation research, this project will also provide opportunities for Boston University undergraduates to learn laboratory techniques and methods of data analysis, and the research scientists leading this project will develop educational modules related to peatland carbon storage that will be presented at area elementary schools and community festivals.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Microbial (bacteria and funga) groups have distinct physiology and developmental histories that will impact their responses to water table decline and contribute to changes in ecosystem carbon and nitrogen cycling. Changes in vascular plant abundance and root biomass associated with water table decline may further impact the microbial environment through increased plant-carbon allocation to mycorrhizal fungal communities. In particular, this research seeks to determine if the physical effect of water table reduction on microbial community composition, enzyme production, and carbon mineralization is amplified by increased vascular plant abundance and carbon allocation to mycorrhizal fungal communities. The research will leverage an ongoing rhizosphere partitioning experiment across a natural water table gradient in Caribou Bog, Maine. Microbial community composition in three rhizosphere communities isolated within root and fungal ingrowth and exclusion cores installed across the water table gradient will be compared to separate the influence of&lt;br/&gt;physical changes in water table from the biological influence of plants and mycorrhizal fungi. The proposed analyses will complement ongoing microbial functional analyses and identify relationships between microbial activity and composition in response to declines in the water table and in the presence or absence of plant and mycorrrhizal inputs.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/06/2015</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/06/2015</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.074</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1501937</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Adrien</FirstName>
<LastName>Finzi</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>C</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Adrien C Finzi</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>afinzi@bu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6173532453</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000201160</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/06/2015</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Allison</FirstName>
<LastName>Gill</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Allison Gill</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>agill@bu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>4013199155</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000681355</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/06/2015</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Trustees of Boston University</Name>
<CityName>BOSTON</CityName>
<ZipCode>022151300</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6173534365</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>881 COMMONWEALTH AVE</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
<StateCode>MA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MA07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>049435266</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>TRUSTEES OF BOSTON UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>049435266</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Trustees of Boston University]]></Name>
<CityName>Boston</CityName>
<StateCode>MA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>022151300</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MA07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1181</Code>
<Text>ECOSYSTEM STUDIES</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9169</Code>
<Text>BIODIVERSITY AND ECOSYSTEM DYNAMICS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9179</Code>
<Text>GRADUATE INVOLVEMENT</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>EGCH</Code>
<Text>ENVIRONMENT AND GLOBAL CHANGE</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>SMET</Code>
<Text>SCIENCE, MATH, ENG &amp; TECH EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0115</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2015~21091</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>High latitude peatlands are currently a major sink for anthropogenic carbon dioxide emissions. Peatland soils are saturated with water, which creates an anoxic environment that slows decomposition and fosters the accumulation of organic material. Over the next 100 years, warming temperatures and increased evapotranspiration are projected to reduce water table heights in high latitude peatlands and increase oxygen availability within peat soil profiles. These physical changes are likely to increase vascular plant abundance and root biomass within the peat and influence the composition and activity of microbial communities that live in close association with vascular plant roots. Previous research in upland forests has shown that roots and root-associated microbes are important sources of slow-cycling soil carbon. Root-associated soil also supports microbial communities and nutrient cycling activity that are distinct from &ldquo;bulk&rdquo; soil zones uninfluenced by the presence of vascular plant roots. As such, the goal of this research was to identify how increases in peatland water table depth and associated changes in vascular plant community composition and root biomass influence peat microbial community composition and activity, as well as peat carbon and nutrient cycling.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>We conducted this work across a natural water table gradient in a black spruce-dominated ombrotrophic bog in central Maine, USA. We found that peat root biomass increased with water table depth, and used a manual rhizosphere partitioning experiment to evaluate the influence of roots on peat microbial biomass, composition, and peat carbon and nutrient cycling. We also performed a fifteen-month root and fungal exclusion experiment to partition the plant and microbial mechanisms influencing carbon and nutrient cycle dynamics in the rhizosphere. We found that microbial activity was stimulated in the presence of roots across the water table and plant community gradient, but that nitrogen-degrading enzyme activity increased relative to carbon- and phosphorus-degrading enzyme activity as the water table dropped and vascular plant abundance increased. Root exclusion reduced rates of microbial respiration and hydrolytic enzyme activity, while mycorrhizal exclusion did not lead to consistent patterns in microbial activity across sites. The results suggest that increased root biomass and rhizosphere size associated with peatland water table reduction may induce greater microbial activity and carbon mineralization and that these losses are unlikely to be slowed by increased microbial competition for nitrogen resources associated with water table decline. This project provided a unique opportunity to integrate questions of community ecology into a biogeochemical context and provided insight into the partitioning of physical and biotic effects of water table reduction on microbial community structure and activity. The results provide a mechanistic framework for understanding how peat microbial community activity will respond to future environmental change. The project also provided opportunities for Boston University undergraduates to be trained in laboratory techniques and data analysis methods, and the results have been disseminated within the scientific community and to the broader public.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 12/21/2018<br>      Modified by: Adrien&nbsp;C&nbsp;Finzi</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ High latitude peatlands are currently a major sink for anthropogenic carbon dioxide emissions. Peatland soils are saturated with water, which creates an anoxic environment that slows decomposition and fosters the accumulation of organic material. Over the next 100 years, warming temperatures and increased evapotranspiration are projected to reduce water table heights in high latitude peatlands and increase oxygen availability within peat soil profiles. These physical changes are likely to increase vascular plant abundance and root biomass within the peat and influence the composition and activity of microbial communities that live in close association with vascular plant roots. Previous research in upland forests has shown that roots and root-associated microbes are important sources of slow-cycling soil carbon. Root-associated soil also supports microbial communities and nutrient cycling activity that are distinct from "bulk" soil zones uninfluenced by the presence of vascular plant roots. As such, the goal of this research was to identify how increases in peatland water table depth and associated changes in vascular plant community composition and root biomass influence peat microbial community composition and activity, as well as peat carbon and nutrient cycling.     We conducted this work across a natural water table gradient in a black spruce-dominated ombrotrophic bog in central Maine, USA. We found that peat root biomass increased with water table depth, and used a manual rhizosphere partitioning experiment to evaluate the influence of roots on peat microbial biomass, composition, and peat carbon and nutrient cycling. We also performed a fifteen-month root and fungal exclusion experiment to partition the plant and microbial mechanisms influencing carbon and nutrient cycle dynamics in the rhizosphere. We found that microbial activity was stimulated in the presence of roots across the water table and plant community gradient, but that nitrogen-degrading enzyme activity increased relative to carbon- and phosphorus-degrading enzyme activity as the water table dropped and vascular plant abundance increased. Root exclusion reduced rates of microbial respiration and hydrolytic enzyme activity, while mycorrhizal exclusion did not lead to consistent patterns in microbial activity across sites. The results suggest that increased root biomass and rhizosphere size associated with peatland water table reduction may induce greater microbial activity and carbon mineralization and that these losses are unlikely to be slowed by increased microbial competition for nitrogen resources associated with water table decline. This project provided a unique opportunity to integrate questions of community ecology into a biogeochemical context and provided insight into the partitioning of physical and biotic effects of water table reduction on microbial community structure and activity. The results provide a mechanistic framework for understanding how peat microbial community activity will respond to future environmental change. The project also provided opportunities for Boston University undergraduates to be trained in laboratory techniques and data analysis methods, and the results have been disseminated within the scientific community and to the broader public.          Last Modified: 12/21/2018       Submitted by: Adrien C Finzi]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
