<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>DISSERTATION RESEARCH: Comparative phylogeography of three co-distributed Neotropical mangrove species</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>06/01/2015</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>19455.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>19455</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>08010206</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>BIO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DEB</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Environmental Biology</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Simon Malcomber</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>smalcomb@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032928227</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Mangroves provide valuable ecosystem services and habitats for many economically important animals, such as fish, birds, and marine invertebrates.  Red (Rhizophora mangle), black (Avicennia germinans), and white (Laguncularia racemosa) mangroves are coastal trees found in estuarine habitats throughout the Neotropics. This project will use genetic tools, evolutionary analyses and niche modeling to analyze current distributions, and then use these data to model past and future geographical distributions for the three species.  The project will also investigate the correlation between dispersal ability and observed patterns of genetic diversity, and infer how seed dispersal potential can affect the genetic structure of populations on broad geographic scales.  One graduate student will be trained in diverse molecular methods, niche modeling and phylogenetic analyses, and undergraduates will be introduced to a diversity of field and laboratory techniques.  A series of talks and presentations will broadly disseminate results of the study in Florida, Aruba, Cayman Islands, and Jamaica where the three mangrove species will be collected. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The comparative phylogeography of coastal and marine animals in the southeastern U. S. has been well studied, with many taxa exhibiting a phylogeographic discontinuity at the southern tip of Florida.  In contrast, only two studies have examined the phylogeography of coastal or marine plant species in this region.  In the Caribbean, studies of historical biogeography have similarly been heavily biased towards vertebrates.  Further study of coastal plants is needed in Florida and the Caribbean to facilitate phylogeographic synthesis for the region.  The researchers will investigate the phylogeographic histories of three mangrove species (Rhizophora mangle, Avicennia germinans, and Laguncularia racemosa) in Florida.  They will test the hypothesis that phylogeographic structure is less pronounced in these highly dispersed organisms than in other coastal organisms, and that propagule size, longevity and proximity to water will be negatively correlated with phylogeographic structure.  To help place these patterns in a broader context, the researchers will also investigate the phylogeography of R. mangle in the Caribbean.  This project will use multiple molecular markers, including complete plastid genomes, RAD-Seq data, and microsatellites, each with different modes of inheritance and mutation rates, to thoroughly investigate the phylogeography of these three species.  Data obtained will facilitate a synthesis of animal and plant phylogeographic and biogeographic studies in Florida and the Caribbean, and also help identify future conservation priorities in the different areas.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>03/24/2015</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>03/24/2015</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.074</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1501600</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Douglas</FirstName>
<LastName>Soltis</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>E</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Douglas E Soltis</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>dsoltis@botany.ufl.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>3523921721</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000241255</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>03/24/2015</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Richard</FirstName>
<LastName>Hodel</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>G</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Richard G Hodel</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>hodel@ufl.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>3523921962</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000653824</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>03/24/2015</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Florida</Name>
<CityName>GAINESVILLE</CityName>
<ZipCode>326112002</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>3523923516</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1 UNIVERSITY OF FLORIDA</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Florida</StateName>
<StateCode>FL</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>FL03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>969663814</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF FLORIDA</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>159621697</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Florida]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>FL</StateCode>
<ZipCode>326112002</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Florida</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>FL03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1171</Code>
<Text>PHYLOGENETIC SYSTEMATICS</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9169</Code>
<Text>BIODIVERSITY AND ECOSYSTEM DYNAMICS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9179</Code>
<Text>GRADUATE INVOLVEMENT</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>EGCH</Code>
<Text>ENVIRONMENT AND GLOBAL CHANGE</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>SMET</Code>
<Text>SCIENCE, MATH, ENG &amp; TECH EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0115</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2015~19455</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Red (<em>Rhizophora mangle</em>), black (<em>Avicennia germinans</em>), and white (<em>Laguncularia racemosa</em>) mangroves are coastal trees found in estuarine habitats throughout the Neotropics. &nbsp;Mangroves provide valuable ecosystem services; their roots accumulate and stabilize sediments, which filter water and mitigate the effects of storm damage on coastal habitats.&nbsp; Mangroves also provide habitat for many economically important animals, such as fish, birds, and marine invertebrates. &nbsp;As climate change threatens to alter sea levels at an unprecedented rate, it is important to conserve species that can mitigate the effects of sea level rise and storm surges to protect valuable coastal habitats and real estate. &nbsp;This project used genetic tools (e.g., DNA sequences) and computational methods to infer the past geographic history of these species. &nbsp;Computer-based ecological niche modeling was also used to infer where these plants will be able to survive in the future, as well as the geographic areas that may be most vulnerable to extirpation. &nbsp;</p> <p>These three mangrove species have seeds that are dispersed via ocean currents; each species has different dispersal capabilities based on how long their seeds can survive in salt water.&nbsp; The research investigated the correlation between dispersal ability and observed patterns of genetic diversity in red and white mangroves in the Caribbean. &nbsp;This portion of the project inferred how seed dispersal potential affected the genetic structure of populations on broad geographic scales.&nbsp; Finally, the data were used to identify biogeographic regions within the Caribbean; this information was valuable for determining potential barriers to dispersal that should be considered when prioritizing species and populations for conservation.&nbsp;</p> <p>Ecological niche modeling uses georeferenced species occurrence data and bioclimatic variables, such as mean annual temperature or mean annual precipitation, to quantify where suitable habitat currently exists for species of interest. &nbsp;Using information about current suitable habitat for a species and models of projected climate change, researchers used niche modeling to infer where suitable habitat will exist for species in the future as the climate changes.&nbsp; The researchers modeled suitable habitat for mangrove species and salt marsh species in the present, and in the year 2070 using projections of climate change.&nbsp; They discovered that most mangrove species are predicted to actually experience an increase in suitable habitat as the climate changes, but at the expense of many salt marsh species, which will see a decline in suitable habitat by 2070.&nbsp; If mangrove species invade salt marshes, as predicted by ecological niche modeling, there could be many unanticipated detrimental effects on the salt marsh ecosystems in the near future due to novel species interactions (e.g., marine invertebrates or juvenile fish that typically live in a salt marsh habitat would suddenly be forced to live in an unfamiliar mangrove habitat).</p> <p>In the Caribbean, studies of historical biogeography have been heavily biased towards vertebrates; few studies examined the phylogeography of coastal or marine plant species in this region. &nbsp;Further study of coastal plants was needed in the Caribbean to facilitate phylogeographic synthesis for the region. &nbsp;Therefore, the researchers investigated the phylogeographic histories of two mangrove species (<em>Rhizophora mangle</em> and <em>Laguncularia racemosa</em>) in the Caribbean.&nbsp; They hypothesized that phylogeographic structure will be less pronounced in these highly dispersed organisms than in other coastal organisms, and that propagule size, longevity and proximity to water will be negatively correlated with phylogeographic structure. &nbsp;This project used multiple molecular markers, including complete chloroplast genomes and RAD-Seq loci, each with different modes of inheritance and mutation rates, to thoroughly investigate the phylogeography of these species.</p> <p>Broad phylogeographic patterns were revealed in each species; the researchers detected genetic discontinuities in the Caribbean.&nbsp; In red mangroves, there is a western group (Florida, Bahamas, Cuba, Central America, Cayman Islands, and western South America) and an eastern group (Lesser Antilles, western Africa, western South America).&nbsp; In white mangroves, there is also a western (Central America) and eastern group (Lesser Antilles), but the discontinuity is further to the west than it is in red mangroves.&nbsp; For each species, the researchers found low phylogeographic structuring compared to other Caribbean taxa.&nbsp; Furthermore, the study revealed lower genetic structuring in red mangroves than white mangroves, as expected.&nbsp; However, analyses comparing the relative contributions of seeds and pollen in influencing geographic patterns of genetic variation yielded unexpected results in red and white mangroves.&nbsp; The smaller, shorter-lived seeds of white mangroves are more important than pollen for moving genetic information, but in red mangroves, the opposite is true: pollen is more important for moving genetic information than the large, long-lived seeds that occur close to the water.&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 08/30/2017<br>      Modified by: Richard&nbsp;G&nbsp;Hodel</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Red (Rhizophora mangle), black (Avicennia germinans), and white (Laguncularia racemosa) mangroves are coastal trees found in estuarine habitats throughout the Neotropics.  Mangroves provide valuable ecosystem services; their roots accumulate and stabilize sediments, which filter water and mitigate the effects of storm damage on coastal habitats.  Mangroves also provide habitat for many economically important animals, such as fish, birds, and marine invertebrates.  As climate change threatens to alter sea levels at an unprecedented rate, it is important to conserve species that can mitigate the effects of sea level rise and storm surges to protect valuable coastal habitats and real estate.  This project used genetic tools (e.g., DNA sequences) and computational methods to infer the past geographic history of these species.  Computer-based ecological niche modeling was also used to infer where these plants will be able to survive in the future, as well as the geographic areas that may be most vulnerable to extirpation.    These three mangrove species have seeds that are dispersed via ocean currents; each species has different dispersal capabilities based on how long their seeds can survive in salt water.  The research investigated the correlation between dispersal ability and observed patterns of genetic diversity in red and white mangroves in the Caribbean.  This portion of the project inferred how seed dispersal potential affected the genetic structure of populations on broad geographic scales.  Finally, the data were used to identify biogeographic regions within the Caribbean; this information was valuable for determining potential barriers to dispersal that should be considered when prioritizing species and populations for conservation.   Ecological niche modeling uses georeferenced species occurrence data and bioclimatic variables, such as mean annual temperature or mean annual precipitation, to quantify where suitable habitat currently exists for species of interest.  Using information about current suitable habitat for a species and models of projected climate change, researchers used niche modeling to infer where suitable habitat will exist for species in the future as the climate changes.  The researchers modeled suitable habitat for mangrove species and salt marsh species in the present, and in the year 2070 using projections of climate change.  They discovered that most mangrove species are predicted to actually experience an increase in suitable habitat as the climate changes, but at the expense of many salt marsh species, which will see a decline in suitable habitat by 2070.  If mangrove species invade salt marshes, as predicted by ecological niche modeling, there could be many unanticipated detrimental effects on the salt marsh ecosystems in the near future due to novel species interactions (e.g., marine invertebrates or juvenile fish that typically live in a salt marsh habitat would suddenly be forced to live in an unfamiliar mangrove habitat).  In the Caribbean, studies of historical biogeography have been heavily biased towards vertebrates; few studies examined the phylogeography of coastal or marine plant species in this region.  Further study of coastal plants was needed in the Caribbean to facilitate phylogeographic synthesis for the region.  Therefore, the researchers investigated the phylogeographic histories of two mangrove species (Rhizophora mangle and Laguncularia racemosa) in the Caribbean.  They hypothesized that phylogeographic structure will be less pronounced in these highly dispersed organisms than in other coastal organisms, and that propagule size, longevity and proximity to water will be negatively correlated with phylogeographic structure.  This project used multiple molecular markers, including complete chloroplast genomes and RAD-Seq loci, each with different modes of inheritance and mutation rates, to thoroughly investigate the phylogeography of these species.  Broad phylogeographic patterns were revealed in each species; the researchers detected genetic discontinuities in the Caribbean.  In red mangroves, there is a western group (Florida, Bahamas, Cuba, Central America, Cayman Islands, and western South America) and an eastern group (Lesser Antilles, western Africa, western South America).  In white mangroves, there is also a western (Central America) and eastern group (Lesser Antilles), but the discontinuity is further to the west than it is in red mangroves.  For each species, the researchers found low phylogeographic structuring compared to other Caribbean taxa.  Furthermore, the study revealed lower genetic structuring in red mangroves than white mangroves, as expected.  However, analyses comparing the relative contributions of seeds and pollen in influencing geographic patterns of genetic variation yielded unexpected results in red and white mangroves.  The smaller, shorter-lived seeds of white mangroves are more important than pollen for moving genetic information, but in red mangroves, the opposite is true: pollen is more important for moving genetic information than the large, long-lived seeds that occur close to the water.              Last Modified: 08/30/2017       Submitted by: Richard G Hodel]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
