<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Collaborative Research: Scalable scaffolding of novice programmers' learning and automated analysis of their online activities</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2015</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>95407.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>95407</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>11040200</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>EHR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DUE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Undergraduate Education</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Stephanie August</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The need for a programming-savvy workforce, the challenges encountered nation-wide in teaching programming skills, and the advent of massively open online courses (MOOCs) all stress the importance of revolutionizing existing technologies meant to support learning via unsupervised practice. The reliance on hand-designed learning experiences in Intelligent Tutoring Systems has created a bottleneck in the enhancement of such technologies. The significance and importance of this project will be the creation of a system that automatically provides programming practice problems via a tutoring system.  Parsons puzzles, which are the focus of this work, have already demonstrated improvement in programming skills.  This project will continue research on the effectiveness of Parsons puzzles and determine whether an evolutionary algorithm approach to creating Parsons puzzles is effective in producing the same or better learning outcomes.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;To this end, this project will achieve two complementary goals. First, Interactive Evolutionary Algorithms will be used to autonomously design Parsons puzzles. These relatively new practice problems have already shown great promise in supporting the development of programming skills. By integrating Vygotsky's Zone of Proximal Development theory in the design of our fitness function, the pedagogical soundness of the evolved Parsons puzzles will be further enhanced. Second, recent breakthroughs in Co-evolutionary Algorithms will be leveraged to data-mine the underlying learners-problems interaction space. This will permit autonomous extraction of insights about the most informational interactions. Such information has the potential to provide new perspectives on the significance of both evolved and hand-designed Parsons puzzles, along with the order in which to guide students through these puzzles to ensure proper scaffolding. Quantitative and objective measures of differences in mean difficulty and number of attempts to solution will be used in comparing hand-designed Parsons puzzles and evolutionary algorithm created Pasons puzzles.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/15/2015</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/15/2015</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.076</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1502564</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Amruth</FirstName>
<LastName>Kumar</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>N</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Amruth N Kumar</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>amruth@ramapo.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2016847712</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000161515</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/15/2015</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Ramapo College of New Jersey</Name>
<CityName>Mahwah</CityName>
<ZipCode>074301623</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2016847500</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>505 Ramapo Valley Road</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New Jersey</StateName>
<StateCode>NJ</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NJ05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>076688399</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>RAMAPO COLLEGE OF NEW JERSEY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>076688399</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Ramapo College of New Jersey]]></Name>
<CityName>Mahwah</CityName>
<StateCode>NJ</StateCode>
<ZipCode>074301623</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[505 Ramapo Valley Road]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New Jersey</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NJ05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1536</Code>
<Text>S-STEM-Schlr Sci Tech Eng&amp;Math</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1998</Code>
<Text>IUSE</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8209</Code>
<Text>Improv Undergrad STEM Ed(IUSE)</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9178</Code>
<Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>SMET</Code>
<Text>SCIENCE, MATH, ENG &amp; TECH EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0415</Code>
<Name>NSF Education &amp; Human Resource</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040106</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>13XX</Code>
<Name>H-1B FUND, EHR, NSF</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>045176</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2015~95407</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Parsons puzzles are gaining popularity among educators of introductory computing. This project was one of the first to implement and evaluate Parsons puzzles in an adaptive software tutor that provides feedback to the learner. It is also the first to provide Parsons puzzles in C++, Java and C#, three of the more popular languages used today. The tutors, called epplets (epplets.org) come with 120 built-in parameterized problems that address 15 concepts on sequence, selection and repetition. The adaptive tutors with their built-in problems represent several hours of programming practice that students can engage in anytime, anywhere.&nbsp;</p> <p>Programming education is at the core of nation-wide initiatives to build a "cyber-savvy" workforce. Researchers have been trying various approaches to programming education, Parsons puzzles being one of them because students prefer solving them to writing code, and performance on Parsons puzzles correlates with performance on code-writing exercises. So, the broader impact of this project is in addressing the need to improve programming education of future information technology workforce by developing Parsons puzzle tutors for C++, Java and C#, three of the languages most widely used in the industry today.</p> <p>Finally, the interfacing of epplets with a remote Parsons puzzle generator that uses evolutionary algorithms demonstrated both a loosely coupled architecture for software tutors and the feasibility of using automated problem generators in intelligent tutors. This is one of the first projects to do so. It promises to reduce the typical 200+ hours of effort needed to develop each intelligent tutoring module, thereby improving the affordability of automated personalized learning, one of the ten grand challenges of computing.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 09/17/2018<br>      Modified by: Amruth&nbsp;N&nbsp;Kumar</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Parsons puzzles are gaining popularity among educators of introductory computing. This project was one of the first to implement and evaluate Parsons puzzles in an adaptive software tutor that provides feedback to the learner. It is also the first to provide Parsons puzzles in C++, Java and C#, three of the more popular languages used today. The tutors, called epplets (epplets.org) come with 120 built-in parameterized problems that address 15 concepts on sequence, selection and repetition. The adaptive tutors with their built-in problems represent several hours of programming practice that students can engage in anytime, anywhere.   Programming education is at the core of nation-wide initiatives to build a "cyber-savvy" workforce. Researchers have been trying various approaches to programming education, Parsons puzzles being one of them because students prefer solving them to writing code, and performance on Parsons puzzles correlates with performance on code-writing exercises. So, the broader impact of this project is in addressing the need to improve programming education of future information technology workforce by developing Parsons puzzle tutors for C++, Java and C#, three of the languages most widely used in the industry today.  Finally, the interfacing of epplets with a remote Parsons puzzle generator that uses evolutionary algorithms demonstrated both a loosely coupled architecture for software tutors and the feasibility of using automated problem generators in intelligent tutors. This is one of the first projects to do so. It promises to reduce the typical 200+ hours of effort needed to develop each intelligent tutoring module, thereby improving the affordability of automated personalized learning, one of the ten grand challenges of computing.          Last Modified: 09/17/2018       Submitted by: Amruth N Kumar]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
