<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>PostDoctoral Research Fellowship</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2015</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>150000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>150000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Fellowship Award</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DMS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Victor Roytburd</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>vroytbur@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032928584</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This award is made as part of the FY 2015 Mathematical Sciences Postdoctoral Research Fellowships Program. Each of the fellowships supports a research and training project at a host institution in the mathematical sciences, including applications to other disciplines, under the mentorship of a sponsoring scientist. The title of the project for this fellowship to Tarik B. Aougab is "Effectivizing Teichmuller Theory, Hyperbolic Geometry and the Mapping Class Group via Combinatorial Complexes." The host institution for the fellowship is Brown University, and the sponsoring scientist is Dr. Jeffrey Brock.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>03/11/2015</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>03/11/2015</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1502623</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Tarik</FirstName>
<LastName>Aougab</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>B</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Tarik B Aougab</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress/>
<PI_PHON>2407535600</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000677787</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>03/11/2015</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Aougab                  Tarik          B</Name>
<CityName>New Haven</CityName>
<ZipCode>065114547</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber/>
<StreetAddress/>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Connecticut</StateName>
<StateCode>CT</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CT03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM/>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME/>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Yale University]]></Name>
<CityName>New Haven</CityName>
<StateCode>CT</StateCode>
<ZipCode>065116810</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Connecticut</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CT03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7335</Code>
<Text>WORKFORCE IN THE MATHEMAT SCI</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9219</Code>
<Text>POSTDOCTORAL FELLOWSHIPS IN MATH SCIENCE</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0115</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2015~150000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Project Outcomes Report for DMS - 1502623<br /><br />There are many beautiful connections between two and three-dimensional geometry, topology, and group theory. In low dimensions, hyperbolic geometry (and by extension hyperbolic surfaces and 3-manifolds) arguably exhibits the richest and most interesting structure. One of Thurston&rsquo;s many celebrated insights is that the geometry and topology of a hyperbolic 3-manifold-- an intrinsically three dimensional object-- can often be reduced to analyzing the dynamics of maps on surfaces (two-dimensional). Indeed, the <em>mapping class group</em> carries instructions for how hyperbolic 3-manifolds are built, and since Thurston, a number of breakthroughs have occurred which allow for the study of these connection via <em>combinatorial</em> tools.&nbsp; <br /><br />One major goal of this project was to sharpen our ability to analyze the structure of a hyperbolic 3-manifold from the combinatorics of the <em>curve graph,</em> a network encoding the ways in which curves intersect on a surface. Roughly speaking, the idea is to understand a complicated three-dimensional geometry from an inherently one-dimensional object, consisting only of nodes connected by edges. Large-scale geometric features of the curve complex have been understood for some time, but finer and more local geometric properties remain completely mysterious. One significant outcome of this project was establishing quantitative knowledge of the local structure of curve complexes and their variants. This led to improved bounds for a family notoriously difficult combinatorial questions in surface topology. <br /><br />Another goal for the project was to understand how the geometry of a hyperbolic surface constrains the combinatorics of curves on the surface, and their orbits under the action of the mapping class group. For instance, a major outcome of the project was obtaining sharp bounds for the number of mapping class group orbits of closed curves on a surface, self-intersecting at most a fixed number of times. Another related outcome was quantifying the relationship between the geometry of a hyperbolic surface minimizing the length of a particular closed curve, and the group theoretic properties of the infinite cyclic subgroup of the surface group represented by that curve (namely the minimum degree of a cover for which the curve lifts to an embedding). <br /><br />This project has also applied the ideas behind these connections to more algebraic settings, such as the outer automorphism group of the free group. The action of the mapping class group on the Teichmuller space led to the notion of a convex cocompact subgroup, which is a subgroup that exhibits properties reminiscent of hyperbolic geometry. An important outcome of this project was to extend and generalize convex cocompactness for subgroups of the outer automorphism group of the free group, via its action on the Culler-Vogtmann Outer space and on the free factor complex, a natural analog of the curve complex. <br /><br />Finally, this project has given the PI an incredible opportunity to grow as a mathematician, teacher, and collaborator. The results of this project include 9 research publications, lectures at over thirty conferences and seminars, and many valuable discussions and collaborations with other researchers, from senior mathematicians to graduate students. The PI has also had the opportunity to mentor numerous undergraduates at summer research programs, and to introduce a new generation of geometers to this fascinating collection of questions.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 07/13/2018<br>      Modified by: Tarik&nbsp;B&nbsp;Aougab</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Project Outcomes Report for DMS - 1502623  There are many beautiful connections between two and three-dimensional geometry, topology, and group theory. In low dimensions, hyperbolic geometry (and by extension hyperbolic surfaces and 3-manifolds) arguably exhibits the richest and most interesting structure. One of Thurston?s many celebrated insights is that the geometry and topology of a hyperbolic 3-manifold-- an intrinsically three dimensional object-- can often be reduced to analyzing the dynamics of maps on surfaces (two-dimensional). Indeed, the mapping class group carries instructions for how hyperbolic 3-manifolds are built, and since Thurston, a number of breakthroughs have occurred which allow for the study of these connection via combinatorial tools.    One major goal of this project was to sharpen our ability to analyze the structure of a hyperbolic 3-manifold from the combinatorics of the curve graph, a network encoding the ways in which curves intersect on a surface. Roughly speaking, the idea is to understand a complicated three-dimensional geometry from an inherently one-dimensional object, consisting only of nodes connected by edges. Large-scale geometric features of the curve complex have been understood for some time, but finer and more local geometric properties remain completely mysterious. One significant outcome of this project was establishing quantitative knowledge of the local structure of curve complexes and their variants. This led to improved bounds for a family notoriously difficult combinatorial questions in surface topology.   Another goal for the project was to understand how the geometry of a hyperbolic surface constrains the combinatorics of curves on the surface, and their orbits under the action of the mapping class group. For instance, a major outcome of the project was obtaining sharp bounds for the number of mapping class group orbits of closed curves on a surface, self-intersecting at most a fixed number of times. Another related outcome was quantifying the relationship between the geometry of a hyperbolic surface minimizing the length of a particular closed curve, and the group theoretic properties of the infinite cyclic subgroup of the surface group represented by that curve (namely the minimum degree of a cover for which the curve lifts to an embedding).   This project has also applied the ideas behind these connections to more algebraic settings, such as the outer automorphism group of the free group. The action of the mapping class group on the Teichmuller space led to the notion of a convex cocompact subgroup, which is a subgroup that exhibits properties reminiscent of hyperbolic geometry. An important outcome of this project was to extend and generalize convex cocompactness for subgroups of the outer automorphism group of the free group, via its action on the Culler-Vogtmann Outer space and on the free factor complex, a natural analog of the curve complex.   Finally, this project has given the PI an incredible opportunity to grow as a mathematician, teacher, and collaborator. The results of this project include 9 research publications, lectures at over thirty conferences and seminars, and many valuable discussions and collaborations with other researchers, from senior mathematicians to graduate students. The PI has also had the opportunity to mentor numerous undergraduates at summer research programs, and to introduce a new generation of geometers to this fascinating collection of questions.       Last Modified: 07/13/2018       Submitted by: Tarik B Aougab]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
