<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>PostDoctoral Research Fellowship</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2015</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>150000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>150000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Fellowship Award</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DMS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Victor Roytburd</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>vroytbur@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032928584</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This award is made as part of the FY 2015 Mathematical Sciences Postdoctoral Research Fellowships Program. Each of the fellowships supports a research and training project at a host institution in the mathematical sciences, including applications to other disciplines, under the mentorship of a sponsoring scientist. The title of the project for this fellowship to Andrew T. Wilson is "Algebraic Combinatorics." The host institution for the fellowship is the University of Pennsylvania, and the sponsoring scientist is Dr. James Haglund.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>03/18/2015</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>03/18/2015</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1502512</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Andrew</FirstName>
<LastName>Wilson</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>T</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Andrew T Wilson</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress/>
<PI_PHON>8159978220</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000677198</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>03/18/2015</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Wilson                  Andrew         T</Name>
<CityName>La Jolla</CityName>
<ZipCode>920930112</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber/>
<StreetAddress/>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>49</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CA49</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM/>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME/>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Department of Mathematics, University of Pennsylvania]]></Name>
<CityName>Philadelphia</CityName>
<StateCode>PA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>191046395</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Pennsylvania</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>PA03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7335</Code>
<Text>WORKFORCE IN THE MATHEMAT SCI</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9219</Code>
<Text>POSTDOCTORAL FELLOWSHIPS IN MATH SCIENCE</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0115</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2015~150000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The Delta Conjecture, formulated by the PI with coauthors Jim Haglund and Jeff Remmel, suggests a connection between algebraic objects (eigenoperators of Macdonald polynomials) and combinatorial ones (decorated parking functions). The goal of this project was to further understand this connection and to seek more connections to other areas of mathematics. The Shuffle Conjecture, a precursor to our conjecture, led to many such connections and serves as a useful template for the potential benefits of such a project.</p> <p><br />This project led to 6 publications and 2 papers which are still under review at journals. These publications appeared in several prominent combinatorics journals as well as the Transactions of the AMS. This work connected several new areas to the Delta Conjecture, such as algebraic topology (via the homology of torus links), geometry (via configurations of lines through the origin), graph theory (via chromatic functions), and, perhaps most enticingly, physics (via supersymmetry, which represents the interactions between bosons and fermions).&nbsp;</p> <p><br />This project's broader impacts include the co-organization of Mid-Atlantic Algebra, Geometry, and Combinatorics (MAAGC) Workshop in 2016, 2017, and 2018, which brings together mathematical researchers in the Mid-Atlantic region and showcases their work to the larger community. This project also allowed the PI to work with Dun Qiu, a young researcher and graduate student at UC San Diego and to disseminate his work by giving 17 talks over the life of the grant.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 07/09/2019<br>      Modified by: Andrew&nbsp;T&nbsp;Wilson</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The Delta Conjecture, formulated by the PI with coauthors Jim Haglund and Jeff Remmel, suggests a connection between algebraic objects (eigenoperators of Macdonald polynomials) and combinatorial ones (decorated parking functions). The goal of this project was to further understand this connection and to seek more connections to other areas of mathematics. The Shuffle Conjecture, a precursor to our conjecture, led to many such connections and serves as a useful template for the potential benefits of such a project.   This project led to 6 publications and 2 papers which are still under review at journals. These publications appeared in several prominent combinatorics journals as well as the Transactions of the AMS. This work connected several new areas to the Delta Conjecture, such as algebraic topology (via the homology of torus links), geometry (via configurations of lines through the origin), graph theory (via chromatic functions), and, perhaps most enticingly, physics (via supersymmetry, which represents the interactions between bosons and fermions).    This project's broader impacts include the co-organization of Mid-Atlantic Algebra, Geometry, and Combinatorics (MAAGC) Workshop in 2016, 2017, and 2018, which brings together mathematical researchers in the Mid-Atlantic region and showcases their work to the larger community. This project also allowed the PI to work with Dun Qiu, a young researcher and graduate student at UC San Diego and to disseminate his work by giving 17 talks over the life of the grant.       Last Modified: 07/09/2019       Submitted by: Andrew T Wilson]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
