<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Investing in the future of paleoclimate research: U.S. graduate student fellowships for the 2015-2017 Urbino Summer Schools in Paleoclimatology</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>06/01/2015</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>161634.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>188634</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>06040200</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>GEO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>OCE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Ocean Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Candace Major</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>cmajor@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927597</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This award funds the participation of U.S. graduate students in the Urbino Summer School in Paleoclimatology (USSP). Held at the University of Urbino, in Italy, the USSP leverages the expertise of internationally-recognized experts from Europe and the US to provide a two-and-a-half-week intensive, immersive learning experience in paleoclimate research topics and methods for an cohort of ~60 students from around the world. These students present their own research and participate in lecture- and lab-style classes while broadening their research networks in an international setting. Each session of the USSP brings in a new group of students and provides fresh opportunities for international collaboration. The experience of previous students suggests that participation in the USSP lays a foundation for success, including international collaborations both with their peers and with more senior researchers. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Roughly ten scholarships are awarded each year to outstanding applicants who are selected on a competitive basis.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>05/22/2015</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/19/2018</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.050</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1503001</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Stephen</FirstName>
<LastName>Schellenberg</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>A</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Stephen A Schellenberg</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>saschellenberg@mail.sdsu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6197873217</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000262853</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/22/2015</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>San Diego State University Foundation</Name>
<CityName>San Diego</CityName>
<ZipCode>921822190</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6195945731</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>5250 Campanile Drive</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>53</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CA53</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>073371346</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>SAN DIEGO STATE UNIVERSITY FOUNDATION</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[San Diego State University]]></Name>
<CityName>San Diego</CityName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>921151020</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[5500 Campanile Drive]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>53</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CA53</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1530</Code>
<Text>Paleoclimate</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1577</Code>
<Text>GLOBAL CHANGE</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1620</Code>
<Text>Marine Geology and Geophysics</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>5112</Code>
<Text>ANT Earth Sciences</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>5280</Code>
<Text>ANS-Arctic Natural Sciences</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1079</Code>
<Text>ARCTIC RESEARCH</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1304</Code>
<Text>EARTH SYSTEM HISTORY</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>4444</Code>
<Text>INTERDISCIPLINARY PROPOSALS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7754</Code>
<Text>CLIMATE VARIABILITY &amp; CHANGE</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8070</Code>
<Text>P2C2 Proposals</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>EGCH</Code>
<Text>ENVIRONMENT AND GLOBAL CHANGE</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0115</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0118</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>02XX</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2015~161634</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2018~27000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Improving our understanding of global climate dynamics is increasingly critical as we continue to perturb our complex Earth system on geologically rapid time&shy;scales. One approach is the modeling of climate dynamics; another is the reconstruction of climate history from natural archives. The field of paleoclimatology strives to integrate these approaches, and views current model-reconstruction disagreements as opportunities for focused investigations designed to improve our understanding of the global climate system. This synergistic approach strengthens our collective scientific framework for evaluating the potential tempo and mode of ongoing climate changes increasingly driven by human activities.</p> <p>To promote this synergistic approach in the next generation of paleoclimatologists, an evolving group of international teacher&shy;-scholars developed the Urbino Summer School in Paleoclimatology (USSP), which has been hosted annually since 2004 by the Universita&#768; degli Studi di Urbino in Urbino, Italy. Each year, the USSP provides ~70 early&shy;-career graduate students&nbsp;with an intensive three&shy;-week program in reconstructing the history and dynamics of Cretaceous to modern climate through an integrated series of lectures, investigations, case&shy;-studies, and field and laboratory analyses. Complementing these formal components, the course actively promotes scientific interactions among faculty and students through periodic &ldquo;open forum&rdquo; discussion and integration sessions, a series of evening presentations, and daily group meals, coffee breaks, and socials.</p> <p>This unique convergence of world-class paleoclimate professionals and early&shy;-career graduate students provides an excellent opportunity to promote communication and collaboration on an international scale; yet, US students were historically underrepresented relative to both non-&shy;US students and US instructors due to the international travel and course costs. The provided NSF support addressed this student access challenge by funding competitive scholarships for over 40 early-career US graduate students from 2015 to 2018. Many of these scholarship awardees are now active educators and researchers across the US and the world, and are actively contributing our understanding of our impacts upon the global climate system from local to global scales.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 07/05/2020<br>      Modified by: Stephen&nbsp;A&nbsp;Schellenberg</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Improving our understanding of global climate dynamics is increasingly critical as we continue to perturb our complex Earth system on geologically rapid time&shy;scales. One approach is the modeling of climate dynamics; another is the reconstruction of climate history from natural archives. The field of paleoclimatology strives to integrate these approaches, and views current model-reconstruction disagreements as opportunities for focused investigations designed to improve our understanding of the global climate system. This synergistic approach strengthens our collective scientific framework for evaluating the potential tempo and mode of ongoing climate changes increasingly driven by human activities.  To promote this synergistic approach in the next generation of paleoclimatologists, an evolving group of international teacher&shy;-scholars developed the Urbino Summer School in Paleoclimatology (USSP), which has been hosted annually since 2004 by the Universita&#768; degli Studi di Urbino in Urbino, Italy. Each year, the USSP provides ~70 early&shy;-career graduate students with an intensive three&shy;-week program in reconstructing the history and dynamics of Cretaceous to modern climate through an integrated series of lectures, investigations, case&shy;-studies, and field and laboratory analyses. Complementing these formal components, the course actively promotes scientific interactions among faculty and students through periodic "open forum" discussion and integration sessions, a series of evening presentations, and daily group meals, coffee breaks, and socials.  This unique convergence of world-class paleoclimate professionals and early&shy;-career graduate students provides an excellent opportunity to promote communication and collaboration on an international scale; yet, US students were historically underrepresented relative to both non-&shy;US students and US instructors due to the international travel and course costs. The provided NSF support addressed this student access challenge by funding competitive scholarships for over 40 early-career US graduate students from 2015 to 2018. Many of these scholarship awardees are now active educators and researchers across the US and the world, and are actively contributing our understanding of our impacts upon the global climate system from local to global scales.          Last Modified: 07/05/2020       Submitted by: Stephen A Schellenberg]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
