<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Collaborative Research: Data-Driven Applications Inspiring Upper-Division Mathematics</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2015</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>47366.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>47366</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>11040200</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>EHR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DUE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Undergraduate Education</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Talitha Washington</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Today's digital environment is  filled with a continuously increasing amount of data stored as images and signals, and there is a critical need in America for students to be prepared to enter the workforce with the ability to research and solve current real-life problems - many of which are data-driven. Investigators from St. Mary's College of Maryland (Lead Institution), Hendrix College, Kenyon College, and Washington State University will collaborate to (1) introduce current cutting-edge research and practical data problems from science, industry, and government to students in undergraduate upper-division mathematics courses and (2) lead these students to develop the problem-solving, collaborative, and research skills that are so crucial in today's work environment.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The focus of this project will be to create a body of applied data-driven instructional modules to motivate student research as well as to generate a deeper student understanding and appreciation of the mathematical theory needed to solve these problems. Modules will center on image and data analysis problems, including image denoising and deblurring, data clustering, data registration, radiographic reconstruction, climate simulation, diffusion, and wave propagation. The goals of the project are to: (i) design, develop, implement, assess, and adjust (as necessary) transportable modules to connect the computational and theoretical sides of of upper division Real Analysis and Linear Algebra; (ii) establish a professional network for classroom testing and assessment of project modules and instructional strategies; and (iii) provide and utilize varied venues for research collaboration. The project team will conduct research to assess how this hands-on data driven approach affects appreciation of the mathematical concepts involved, provides new avenues for student directed study, helps prepare students for a workforce in need of research and data skills, improves student engagement and learning, and inspires students to pursue postgraduate study in theoretical and applied mathematics. Research methods will include the incorporation of beta testing modules and then collecting and analyzing quantitative and qualitative data. The project includes measures of students? knowledge such as course assessments and instruments to measure motivation and self-efficacy related to mathematics. With faculty from four institutions across the country, the project will also study the adaptability to a variety of institutions of the materials and instuctional approach.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>04/01/2015</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>04/01/2015</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.076</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1503929</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Marie</FirstName>
<LastName>Snipes</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Marie Snipes</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>snipesm@kenyon.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>7404275929</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000620951</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/01/2015</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Kenyon College</Name>
<CityName>Gambier</CityName>
<ZipCode>430229623</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>7404275114</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>22 Ransom Hall</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Ohio</StateName>
<StateCode>OH</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>OH07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>063580369</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>KENYON COLLEGE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>063580369</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Kenyon College]]></Name>
<CityName>Gambier</CityName>
<StateCode>OH</StateCode>
<ZipCode>430229623</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[201 N. College Ave.]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Ohio</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>OH07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1536</Code>
<Text>S-STEM-Schlr Sci Tech Eng&amp;Math</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1998</Code>
<Text>IUSE</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8209</Code>
<Text>Improv Undergrad STEM Ed(IUSE)</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9178</Code>
<Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0415</Code>
<Name>NSF Education &amp; Human Resource</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040106</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>13XX</Code>
<Name>H-1B FUND, EHR, NSF</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>045176</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2015~47366</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><span class="im"><span class="m_7069025418574577674m_-1184410633414955711gmail-">Today's digital environment is filled with a huge amount of data stored as images and signals.&nbsp; This presents interesting challenges to any researcher who needs to examine or manipulate this information.&nbsp; Some important examples include removing unwanted noise or blur from astronomical or archival images, interpreting medical x-ray pictures or CT scans, deciding if two pictures show the same or different people, and even comparing the accuracy of climate simulations with historical data.&nbsp; Such problems are of great practical importance in all areas of science, industry and government.&nbsp; The focus of this project will be to introduce these and similar current research problems to upper-division mathematics students and use them to motivate a deeper understanding of mathematical theory.&nbsp; This approach would represent a transformation from typical classroom methods in which mathematical theory is often presented as a collection of theorems and proofs, often without a clear appreciation of practical applications.&nbsp; In particular, the activities developed by this project will give students a research-like experience in the classroom, and will demonstrate to them the real, tangible applications of the mathematical theory they are learning.&nbsp; This active, collaborative, and creative learning environment will empower students to become leaders in science, technology, engineering and mathematics.&nbsp; The project will lead students to develop the problem-solving and collaborative skills that are so important in today's workforce.<br />&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;<br /></span>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; In this project we worked to provide undergraduate mathematics students with a deep appreciation for Analysis tools and their uses in real-life problems. We concentrated our efforts on advanced mathematical subject areas including Analysis, Linear Algebra and Differential Equations because of their significant overlap with a variety of interesting and practical data problems.&nbsp; Inspired by current data problems, we created and tested 5 adaptable and transportable application-based modules. The applications used were: (1) Diffusion Welding in Linear Algebra, (2) Image Warping in Linear Algebra, (3) Brain Scan Reconstruction in Linear Algebra, (4) Tsunami Modeling in Differential Equations, and (5) Image Denoising in Real Analysis.<br />&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;<br /></span><span>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; Each module went through an iterative process of writing, testing, and improving. Development, implementation, and assessment of these modules also fostered a community among faculty, researchers, and students at the intersection of mathematics education and applied analysis. Each</span><span style="color: #000000;">&nbsp;of our modules begins b</span><span>y introducing a cutting edge research problem in data, image, or video analysis. Solution paths inspire the development of mathematical concepts typically taught in either a definition-theorem-proof-examp</span><span>le or an application-integrating course. Because the level and frequency of courses vary from institution to institution, we created these modules so that they are adaptable for both introductory and advanced levels. Our modules can be used as supplements to the standard curriculum or as one or more full-length, problem-driven courses.&nbsp; In classes using these modules, we found students more engaged in the module materials. According to faculty&nbsp; observations students showed interest in the data applications and had a desire to see the outcomes of the data problem.&nbsp; Results from student surveys showed an increase in confidence toward solving data problems as well.&nbsp;</span></p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 09/25/2017<br>      Modified by: Marie&nbsp;Snipes</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Today's digital environment is filled with a huge amount of data stored as images and signals.  This presents interesting challenges to any researcher who needs to examine or manipulate this information.  Some important examples include removing unwanted noise or blur from astronomical or archival images, interpreting medical x-ray pictures or CT scans, deciding if two pictures show the same or different people, and even comparing the accuracy of climate simulations with historical data.  Such problems are of great practical importance in all areas of science, industry and government.  The focus of this project will be to introduce these and similar current research problems to upper-division mathematics students and use them to motivate a deeper understanding of mathematical theory.  This approach would represent a transformation from typical classroom methods in which mathematical theory is often presented as a collection of theorems and proofs, often without a clear appreciation of practical applications.  In particular, the activities developed by this project will give students a research-like experience in the classroom, and will demonstrate to them the real, tangible applications of the mathematical theory they are learning.  This active, collaborative, and creative learning environment will empower students to become leaders in science, technology, engineering and mathematics.  The project will lead students to develop the problem-solving and collaborative skills that are so important in today's workforce.          In this project we worked to provide undergraduate mathematics students with a deep appreciation for Analysis tools and their uses in real-life problems. We concentrated our efforts on advanced mathematical subject areas including Analysis, Linear Algebra and Differential Equations because of their significant overlap with a variety of interesting and practical data problems.  Inspired by current data problems, we created and tested 5 adaptable and transportable application-based modules. The applications used were: (1) Diffusion Welding in Linear Algebra, (2) Image Warping in Linear Algebra, (3) Brain Scan Reconstruction in Linear Algebra, (4) Tsunami Modeling in Differential Equations, and (5) Image Denoising in Real Analysis.          Each module went through an iterative process of writing, testing, and improving. Development, implementation, and assessment of these modules also fostered a community among faculty, researchers, and students at the intersection of mathematics education and applied analysis. Each of our modules begins by introducing a cutting edge research problem in data, image, or video analysis. Solution paths inspire the development of mathematical concepts typically taught in either a definition-theorem-proof-example or an application-integrating course. Because the level and frequency of courses vary from institution to institution, we created these modules so that they are adaptable for both introductory and advanced levels. Our modules can be used as supplements to the standard curriculum or as one or more full-length, problem-driven courses.  In classes using these modules, we found students more engaged in the module materials. According to faculty  observations students showed interest in the data applications and had a desire to see the outcomes of the data problem.  Results from student surveys showed an increase in confidence toward solving data problems as well.        Last Modified: 09/25/2017       Submitted by: Marie Snipes]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
