<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>C3PO: Customizable Computer Coaches for Physics Online</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2015</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>248918.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>254743</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>11040200</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>EHR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DUE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Undergraduate Education</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>R. Corby Hovis</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>chovis@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924625</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>In this project the investigators address the need to provide introductory physics students with effective problem-solving instruction by developing a web-based coaching system. This system goes beyond currently available educational tools in its potential to help students become better problem solvers as well as to be adapted by instructors teaching a wide range of students. This could be very significant for students for whom standard instruction is insufficient. Because of the reproducible fine-grained problem-solving instruction delivered by the coaches, the proposed work can contribute to the knowledge base on how to design effective problem-solving instruction, whether or not this instruction is computer-based. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The key features of the system, called Customizable Computer Coaches for Physics Online (C3PO), are that they (1) provide students with coaching on the generalizable non-linear decision-making processes that are critical to expert-like problem-solving while the students practice solving problems, and (2) provide instructors with the ability to customize the problems, guidance, and feedback given to students. The investigators will collaborate with five physics instructors from diverse post-secondary institutions to develop C3PO coaches and revise the underlying software. The instructors will work with the project team, building coaches and integrating the system into their own classes, while gathering data to assess the feasibility, usability, usefulness, and potential educational impact of the coaches. This data will then be used to develop and prepare the C3PO system for large-scale dissemination in a continuous cycle of improvement. Since a logical expert-like framework for approaching novel problems in a systematic way, is important to all STEM fields, this project contributes to the development of a well-prepared STEM workforce of the future. It has the potential to spawn similar efforts in other STEM fields and across multiple disciplines.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/26/2015</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>01/17/2017</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.076</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1504649</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Kenneth</FirstName>
<LastName>Heller</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>J</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Kenneth J Heller</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>helle001@umn.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6126247314</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000264266</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/26/2015</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Leonardo</FirstName>
<LastName>Hsu</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Leonardo Hsu</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>lhsu@umn.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6126253472</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000368703</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/26/2015</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Minnesota-Twin Cities</Name>
<CityName>Minneapolis</CityName>
<ZipCode>554552070</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6126245599</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>200 OAK ST SE</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Minnesota</StateName>
<StateCode>MN</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MN05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>555917996</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>REGENTS OF THE UNIVERSITY OF MINNESOTA</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>117178941</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Minnesota-Twin Cities]]></Name>
<CityName>Minneapolis</CityName>
<StateCode>MN</StateCode>
<ZipCode>554550149</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[116 Church St. SE]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Minnesota</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MN05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1998</Code>
<Text>IUSE</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8209</Code>
<Text>Improv Undergrad STEM Ed(IUSE)</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8244</Code>
<Text>EHR CL Opportunities (NSF 14-302)</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9178</Code>
<Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0415</Code>
<Name>NSF Education &amp; Human Resource</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040106</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0417</Code>
<Name>NSF Education &amp; Human Resource</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040106</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2015~248918</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2017~5825</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The goal of this project was to develop a computer software system for building, developing, and administering computer coaching programs designed to help introductory physics students improve their problem-solving skills, as well as to test the system for usability in a variety of educational contexts. The work was carried out by a collaboration of physics faculty from research universities, state colleges, and two-year colleges.</p> <p>The project team created computer coaches spanning the range of topics in first year introductory physics, including mechanics and electricity and magnetism, and a website that enabled physics faculty without much programming experience to build and modify the coaches, as well as to administer the coaches in physics classes and track students&rsquo; progress in using the coaches.</p> <p>This work contributes to the knowledge base on the coaching of problem solving and its implementation using computers.&nbsp;</p> <p>In addition, this work contributes to the knowledge base of the different types of coaching used by different instructors and how they desire that coaching to be delivered to their students. Interactions with one instructor who built his own coaches from scratch, and a second instructor who heavily modified the coaches created by the project team, were especially illuminating in that regard.</p> <p>We have also learned about some of the different ways that instructors might adopt an educational tool such as a computer coach in their classes, as well as some of the criteria by which students in introductory physics judge the usefulness of educational tools.</p> <p>Finally, many disciplines emphasize problem solving of the type emphasized by these coaches. It is clear that to maximize their potential for wide adoption, such software coaches must be able to be modified easily by instructors with little software experience. This project is the development of a testbed for such software that can be easily modified by instructors at many different types of institutions in many subject matter fields. At the same time the project has shown some of the characteristics of a student graphical user interface that are necessary to make such software coaches comfortable and compelling to a wide variety of students in classes that use significantly different pedagogies.&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 03/19/2018<br>      Modified by: Leonardo&nbsp;Hsu</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The goal of this project was to develop a computer software system for building, developing, and administering computer coaching programs designed to help introductory physics students improve their problem-solving skills, as well as to test the system for usability in a variety of educational contexts. The work was carried out by a collaboration of physics faculty from research universities, state colleges, and two-year colleges.  The project team created computer coaches spanning the range of topics in first year introductory physics, including mechanics and electricity and magnetism, and a website that enabled physics faculty without much programming experience to build and modify the coaches, as well as to administer the coaches in physics classes and track students? progress in using the coaches.  This work contributes to the knowledge base on the coaching of problem solving and its implementation using computers.   In addition, this work contributes to the knowledge base of the different types of coaching used by different instructors and how they desire that coaching to be delivered to their students. Interactions with one instructor who built his own coaches from scratch, and a second instructor who heavily modified the coaches created by the project team, were especially illuminating in that regard.  We have also learned about some of the different ways that instructors might adopt an educational tool such as a computer coach in their classes, as well as some of the criteria by which students in introductory physics judge the usefulness of educational tools.  Finally, many disciplines emphasize problem solving of the type emphasized by these coaches. It is clear that to maximize their potential for wide adoption, such software coaches must be able to be modified easily by instructors with little software experience. This project is the development of a testbed for such software that can be easily modified by instructors at many different types of institutions in many subject matter fields. At the same time the project has shown some of the characteristics of a student graphical user interface that are necessary to make such software coaches comfortable and compelling to a wide variety of students in classes that use significantly different pedagogies.           Last Modified: 03/19/2018       Submitted by: Leonardo Hsu]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
