<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Development of Multidimensional Resonance Raman Spectroscopies for Studies of Photochemical Dynamics</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2015</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>500000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>500000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03090000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CHE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Chemistry</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Lin He</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>lhe@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924956</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>In this project funded by the Chemical Measurement and Imaging Program, Professor Andrew Moran of the University of North Carolina is developing laser-based experimental methods for studies of photodissociation and electron transfer dynamics in heme proteins. The heme proteins targeted in this research project are of interest, because they mediate electron and oxygen transport in living systems. For example, hemoglobin is responsible for transporting oxygen in blood, whereas cytochrome plays a central role in the electron transport chain in mitochondria. This project focuses on the femtosecond time scale in which elementary nuclear motions of these systems take place. Pulsed laser techniques are uniquely equipped to resolve such fast dynamics. In addition to advancing the understanding of these particular proteins, the experimental methods developed in this project can be adapted by other researchers for applications to a much wider range of systems and processes. The graduate and undergraduate students who conduct this research develop a wide range of technical skills (e.g., optics, instrument development, machining, computer programming).&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project involves the development of two-dimensional resonance Raman (2DRR) spectroscopies in which five noncollinear laser beams induce light emission from a chemical system. Reaction mechanisms are exposed by separating resonances of the reactants and products in separate spectroscopic dimensions, which is not possible in traditional resonance Raman spectroscopies. The background-free nature of these techniques facilitates fast data acquisition rates and enhances sensitivity to weak signals. Two-dimensional Raman spectroscopies are challenged by undesired nonlinearities known as cascades in off-resonant systems (i.e., systems that do not absorb the incoming laser beams). It is generally understood that "forbidden" steps in the desired nonlinear optical processes are the origin of the problems encountered under off-resonant conditions. In contrast, the experiments developed in this proposal are carried out under resonant conditions, where such unfortunate selection rules do not apply. A variety of control experiments are used to rule out contributions from cascades.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/20/2015</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/16/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1504350</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Andrew</FirstName>
<LastName>Moran</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>M</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Andrew M Moran</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>ammoran@email.unc.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>9199663411</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000503338</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/20/2015</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill</Name>
<CityName>CHAPEL HILL</CityName>
<ZipCode>275991350</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>9199663411</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>104 AIRPORT DR STE 2200</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>North Carolina</StateName>
<StateCode>NC</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NC04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>608195277</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF NORTH CAROLINA AT CHAPEL HILL</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>142363428</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>NC</StateCode>
<ZipCode>275993290</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>North Carolina</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NC04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>6880</Code>
<Text>Chemical Measurement &amp; Imaging</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0115</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0116</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2015~364250</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2016~135750</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Knowledge of the structural changes that accompany chemical reactions has motivated the development of a wide variety of experimental methods. Foremost among the techniques applied to sub-picosecond reactions are time-resolved Raman spectroscopies. Despite their utility, time-resolved Raman spectroscopies have remained fairly specialized method because of substantial technical challenges that stem from a large background of residual laser light and lower-order nonlinearities. These challenges were addressed in this research project with an experimental approach, termed two-dimensional resonance Raman (2DRR) spectroscopy, in which signal generation is induced by 3-5 laser beams.</p> <p>The 2DRR method leverages a molecule&rsquo;s electronic structure to selectively probe chromophores embedded in complex environments (e.g., a cofactor in a protein). In addition, correlations between the two dimensions of the 2DRR spectrum reveal information that is not available in traditional Raman techniques. For example, distributions of reactant and product geometries can be correlated in systems that undergo chemical reactions on the femtosecond time scale. Such correlations are physically interesting because they are usually assumed to be absent in thermally activated chemical reactions. Structural heterogeneity in an ensemble may also be reflected in the 2D spectroscopic line shapes of both reactive and non-reactive systems. These capabilities of the 2DRR technique were used to investigate the photo-dissociation mechanisms of triiodide and myoglobin. For example, it was shown that the bond length of a I<sub>3</sub><sup>-</sup> reactant is correlated to the particular vibrational energy levels populated in the I<sub>2</sub> photoproduct.</p> <p>The feasibility of 2DRR experiments is one of the most important findings to emerge from this work. Earlier off-resonant 2D Raman experiments were challenged by artifacts known as cascades, wherein undesired signals are radiated in the same direction as the desired 2DRR response. Isolating the desired signal components had proven to be extremely difficult under off-resonant conditions. We have shown that Franck-Condon activity (i.e., resonant interactions) obviates the problematic selection rules that make off-resonant experiments sensitive to artifacts. Unfortunately, the susceptibilty to cascades and sensitivity to vibrational anharmonicity are two sides of the same coin. Our model calculations suggest that the 2DRR technique is insensitive to anharmonic molecular motions. These calculations also indicate that the solutes and solvents may combine to produce cascades which outcompete the 2DRR response under common experimental conditions. Thus, control experiments should always be conducted to rule out such artifacts.</p> <p>Graduate and undergraduate students involved in this project gained experience in computer programming, machining, electronics, optics, and lasers. In addition, our research group developed and supervised laboratory exercises (e.g., experiments that illustrate principles of optics and solar cells) for middle and high-school students during the summer in collaboration with the School of Education at UNC. These exercises and demonstrations were also conducted in collaboration with Morehead Planetarium on the UNC campus over the past three years.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 09/06/2019<br>      Modified by: Andrew&nbsp;M&nbsp;Moran</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Knowledge of the structural changes that accompany chemical reactions has motivated the development of a wide variety of experimental methods. Foremost among the techniques applied to sub-picosecond reactions are time-resolved Raman spectroscopies. Despite their utility, time-resolved Raman spectroscopies have remained fairly specialized method because of substantial technical challenges that stem from a large background of residual laser light and lower-order nonlinearities. These challenges were addressed in this research project with an experimental approach, termed two-dimensional resonance Raman (2DRR) spectroscopy, in which signal generation is induced by 3-5 laser beams.  The 2DRR method leverages a molecule?s electronic structure to selectively probe chromophores embedded in complex environments (e.g., a cofactor in a protein). In addition, correlations between the two dimensions of the 2DRR spectrum reveal information that is not available in traditional Raman techniques. For example, distributions of reactant and product geometries can be correlated in systems that undergo chemical reactions on the femtosecond time scale. Such correlations are physically interesting because they are usually assumed to be absent in thermally activated chemical reactions. Structural heterogeneity in an ensemble may also be reflected in the 2D spectroscopic line shapes of both reactive and non-reactive systems. These capabilities of the 2DRR technique were used to investigate the photo-dissociation mechanisms of triiodide and myoglobin. For example, it was shown that the bond length of a I3- reactant is correlated to the particular vibrational energy levels populated in the I2 photoproduct.  The feasibility of 2DRR experiments is one of the most important findings to emerge from this work. Earlier off-resonant 2D Raman experiments were challenged by artifacts known as cascades, wherein undesired signals are radiated in the same direction as the desired 2DRR response. Isolating the desired signal components had proven to be extremely difficult under off-resonant conditions. We have shown that Franck-Condon activity (i.e., resonant interactions) obviates the problematic selection rules that make off-resonant experiments sensitive to artifacts. Unfortunately, the susceptibilty to cascades and sensitivity to vibrational anharmonicity are two sides of the same coin. Our model calculations suggest that the 2DRR technique is insensitive to anharmonic molecular motions. These calculations also indicate that the solutes and solvents may combine to produce cascades which outcompete the 2DRR response under common experimental conditions. Thus, control experiments should always be conducted to rule out such artifacts.  Graduate and undergraduate students involved in this project gained experience in computer programming, machining, electronics, optics, and lasers. In addition, our research group developed and supervised laboratory exercises (e.g., experiments that illustrate principles of optics and solar cells) for middle and high-school students during the summer in collaboration with the School of Education at UNC. These exercises and demonstrations were also conducted in collaboration with Morehead Planetarium on the UNC campus over the past three years.       Last Modified: 09/06/2019       Submitted by: Andrew M Moran]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
