<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Promoting the Development of Metacognition and Combating Robust Misconceptions In a Gateway STEM Course Using an Intelligent, Web-based Homework System</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>06/15/2015</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>249724.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>249724</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>11040200</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>EHR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DUE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Undergraduate Education</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Heather Watson</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>To meet the current and projected needs of industry for Science, Technology, Engineering and Math (STEM) professionals, significant efforts to recruit students into STEM fields continue across the nation.  Once recruited into a STEM field, retention is of paramount importance.  Examinations of the retention issue have identified key gateway courses as areas in which many students are lost from STEM fields.  Failure and withdrawal rates in such courses often exceed 30% and issues related to inadequate metacognitive skill and self-regulated learning among struggling students appear to be key contributors to attrition.  This project is exploring cost-effective and transferable means to foster metacognitive skill development among STEM majors in a key gateway engineering course so students become self-regulated learners and progress successfully not only through the gateway course, but through the entire curriculum.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Toward this end, an "intelligent" web-based platform is being developed and deployed in an electric circuit analysis course at two institutions.  The system is being designed to identify knowledge deficits of a student and to deliver an individualized experience for each user according to their current level of mastery.  The web-based approach ensures the interventions will be scalable and transferable and their grounding in established theories from cognitive science suggests they will be effective and broadly applicable.  Unique within the system are features which foster self-reflection on the part of the user with the promise of enhancing metacognitive skill and the correction of common misconceptions. Rigorous assessment and evaluation measures are in place to quantify the project's effectiveness.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/18/2015</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/18/2015</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.076</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1504880</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Rockford</FirstName>
<LastName>Ross</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>J</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Rockford J Ross</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>ross@cs.montana.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>4069944804</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000430140</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/18/2015</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>James</FirstName>
<LastName>Becker</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>P</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>James P Becker</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>jbecker@ece.montana.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>4069945988</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000300483</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/18/2015</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Katharine</FirstName>
<LastName>Polasek</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>H</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Katharine H Polasek</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>polasek@hope.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6163957079</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000572601</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/18/2015</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Montana State University</Name>
<CityName>BOZEMAN</CityName>
<ZipCode>597172470</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>4069942381</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>328 MONTANA HALL</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Montana</StateName>
<StateCode>MT</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>00</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MT00</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>625447982</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>MONTANA STATE UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>079602596</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Montana State University]]></Name>
<CityName>Bozeman</CityName>
<StateCode>MT</StateCode>
<ZipCode>597172470</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[610 Cobleigh Hall]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Montana</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>00</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MT00</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1998</Code>
<Text>IUSE</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8209</Code>
<Text>Improv Undergrad STEM Ed(IUSE)</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8244</Code>
<Text>EHR CL Opportunities (NSF 14-302)</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9178</Code>
<Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0415</Code>
<Name>NSF Education &amp; Human Resource</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040106</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2015~249724</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>This project involved the development, deployment, and evaluation of various web-based materials to improve the performance of students in a sophmore-level course in circuit analysis.&nbsp; Introductory circuit analysis is the typical gateway course to the disciplines of electrical and computer engineering and is well-known as being a common stumbling block for students.&nbsp; Many students enter such a course with common misconceptions regarding the behavior of electric circuits; this project aims at helping students develop proper mental models regarding fundamental concepts relevant to the course.&nbsp;</p> <p>The materials developed in this project include web-based reading exercises, web-based computation problems, and so-called <em>virtual instruments.</em>&nbsp; Regardless of the type of educational material developed, students demonstrated a clear preference for those that were highly interactive and provided immediate feedback regarding their performance on the task at hand.&nbsp; For example, the virtual breadboard introduces students to the common "breadboard" used as a physical platform to wire basic circuits.&nbsp; With the virtual breadboard, students "assemble" their circuits on a web-based platform and are given feedback as to whether their circuit is properly wired and what they can do to correct errors recognized by the software.&nbsp; The highly interactive application has been very popular with students and student performance with physical breadboards in the laboratory has been found to improve with usage of the virtual breadboard.&nbsp; Similar findings have been noted with the virtual oscilloscope that introduces students to one of the most common pieces of test equipment used in the development and testing of electronic circuits.&nbsp; The percentage of students failing to pass the course has dropped by approximately 30% with the inclusion of the various web-based materials.</p> <p>An important aspect of this project was to investigate various means of promptly identifying students likely to struggle in the course.&nbsp; For the predication tool to be useful it had to be both accurate and to provide results within the first weeks of the class.&nbsp; While mulitiple tools were found to be accurate, some were only accurate when administered too late in the course to provide enough time to allow at-risk students to obtain the necessary help to succeed.&nbsp; Initial studies suggest one tool, a conceptual-based writing quiz administered on the fifth day of class, is both accurate and provides results early enough to make a difference to at-risk students.</p> <p>The writing-based exercise was graded using a holistic approach in which not only the correctness but also the richness of response were considered.&nbsp; In other words, even if a student's response was flawed with an evident misconception regarding a basic circuit concept, as long as the response displayed evidence of the student's ability to meaningfully reason, it would not be placed in the lowest scoring category.&nbsp; 93% of students scoring at the lowest level on the writing exercise were found to score below the passing level on the course's first exam given approximately five weeks later, whereas 94% of those scoring above the lowest level on the writing exam scored above the passing level on exam 1.&nbsp; Clearly, initial evidence suggests the use of the writing exercise is a powerful tool for identifying students in need of additional assistance.</p> <p>It is acknowledged that evaluating writing samples of students and providing tailored feedback on these writing samples is time consuming.&nbsp; Due to the time intensive nature of grading and the value students place on immediate feedback, an initial attempt was made to use existing Natural Language Processing (NLP) techniques coded in software to classify responses as belonging to students in the at-risk class or to those outside of the at-risk class.&nbsp; NLP technologies are widely used in internet search engines and in voice activated assistants such as Alexa and Siri.&nbsp; An un-optimized NLP algorithm was shown to achieve a balanced accuracy of 86% in the binary classification task of separating at-risk students from the non at-risk class.&nbsp; This promising result suggests that further research effort be guided towards leveraging state-of-the-art NLP algorithms to not only classify student writings but also to provide individualized feedback to students regarding their understanding of fundamental concepts as determined through their writing.</p> <p>The use of the general techniques employed in this project can extend to many STEM courses.&nbsp; Certainly the use of writing in typical problem-based courses should be further explored as should the use of NLP to make such writing exercises scalable to high-enrollment courses.&nbsp; Finally, a series of outreach activities intended to help fourth-grade students begin to form proper conceptual models for basic concepts in electrical circuits was developed and delivered.&nbsp; The activities are meant to complement existing materials often delivered to fourth-grade students during their common module on electricity and magnetism.&nbsp; The activities were found to be both effective and engaging, with approximately two hundred students taking part.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 06/27/2019<br>      Modified by: James&nbsp;P&nbsp;Becker</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Images (<span id="selectedPhoto0">1</span> of <span class="totalNumber"></span>)           </div> <div class="galControls" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1504880/1504880_10370684_1561388319504_Virtual_Breadboard_Image_1--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1504880/1504880_10370684_1561388319504_Virtual_Breadboard_Image_1--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Virtual Breadboard -- Voltage Measurement"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1504880/1504880_10370684_1561388319504_Virtual_Breadboard_Image_1--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Virtual Breadboard -- Voltage Measurement"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">An image from the virtual breadboard illustrating a measurement of the voltage across a pair of resistors.</div> <div class="imageCredit">James Becker</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">James&nbsp;P&nbsp;Becker</div> <div class="imageTitle">Virtual Breadboard -- Voltage Measurement</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1504880/1504880_10370684_1561389076559_Virtual_Breadboard_Image_2--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1504880/1504880_10370684_1561389076559_Virtual_Breadboard_Image_2--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Virtual Breadboard -- Current Measurement Error"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1504880/1504880_10370684_1561389076559_Virtual_Breadboard_Image_2--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Virtual Breadboard -- Current Measurement Error"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">An image from the virtual breadboard in which the user has incorrectly wired the virtual ammeter.  The system identifies an issue to be addressed.  Clicking on the issue button reveals a message to lead the user to the correct understanding of a current measurement.</div> <div class="imageCredit">James Becker</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">James&nbsp;P&nbsp;Becker</div> <div class="imageTitle">Virtual Breadboard -- Current Measurement Error</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1504880/1504880_10370684_1561389388812_Virtual_Breadboard_Image_3--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1504880/1504880_10370684_1561389388812_Virtual_Breadboard_Image_3--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Virtual Breadboard -- Current Measurement Error Message"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1504880/1504880_10370684_1561389388812_Virtual_Breadboard_Image_3--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Virtual Breadboard -- Current Measurement Error Message"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">An image from the virtual breadboard displaying a message to help the user identify and understand his/her error.</div> <div class="imageCredit">James Becker</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Creative Commons</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">James&nbsp;P&nbsp;Becker</div> <div class="imageTitle">Virtual Breadboard -- Current Measurement Error Message</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1504880/1504880_10370684_1561392639670_Reading_Exercise_A--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1504880/1504880_10370684_1561392639670_Reading_Exercise_A--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Reading Exercise -- An Introductory Question"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1504880/1504880_10370684_1561392639670_Reading_Exercise_A--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Reading Exercise -- An Introductory Question"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">An image from one of several reading applications.  Such applications contain short readings with embedded animations and questions to probe student understanding.  Instant feedback is given to help lead reader to proper understanding of fundamental concepts.</div> <div class="imageCredit">James Becker</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Creative Commons</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">James&nbsp;P&nbsp;Becker</div> <div class="imageTitle">Reading Exercise -- An Introductory Question</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1504880/1504880_10370684_1561393123042_Reading_Exercise_B--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1504880/1504880_10370684_1561393123042_Reading_Exercise_B--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Reading Exercise --Feedback for Incorrect Response"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1504880/1504880_10370684_1561393123042_Reading_Exercise_B--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Reading Exercise --Feedback for Incorrect Response"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">An image from one of several interactive reading exercises.  Feedback is given to the user based on his/her response.  The user may click on the figure to obtain additional assistance.</div> <div class="imageCredit">James Becker</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">James&nbsp;P&nbsp;Becker</div> <div class="imageTitle">Reading Exercise --Feedback for Incorrect Response</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1504880/1504880_10370684_1561393511859_Reading_Exercise_C--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1504880/1504880_10370684_1561393511859_Reading_Exercise_C--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Reading Exercise --Feedback for a Correct Response"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1504880/1504880_10370684_1561393511859_Reading_Exercise_C--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Reading Exercise --Feedback for a Correct Response"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">An image from one of several interactive reading exercises.  In this case, the user has responded correctly to an embedded question which unlocks the opportunity to go more deeply into the subject.</div> <div class="imageCredit">James Becker</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">James&nbsp;P&nbsp;Becker</div> <div class="imageTitle">Reading Exercise --Feedback for a Correct Response</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ This project involved the development, deployment, and evaluation of various web-based materials to improve the performance of students in a sophmore-level course in circuit analysis.  Introductory circuit analysis is the typical gateway course to the disciplines of electrical and computer engineering and is well-known as being a common stumbling block for students.  Many students enter such a course with common misconceptions regarding the behavior of electric circuits; this project aims at helping students develop proper mental models regarding fundamental concepts relevant to the course.   The materials developed in this project include web-based reading exercises, web-based computation problems, and so-called virtual instruments.  Regardless of the type of educational material developed, students demonstrated a clear preference for those that were highly interactive and provided immediate feedback regarding their performance on the task at hand.  For example, the virtual breadboard introduces students to the common "breadboard" used as a physical platform to wire basic circuits.  With the virtual breadboard, students "assemble" their circuits on a web-based platform and are given feedback as to whether their circuit is properly wired and what they can do to correct errors recognized by the software.  The highly interactive application has been very popular with students and student performance with physical breadboards in the laboratory has been found to improve with usage of the virtual breadboard.  Similar findings have been noted with the virtual oscilloscope that introduces students to one of the most common pieces of test equipment used in the development and testing of electronic circuits.  The percentage of students failing to pass the course has dropped by approximately 30% with the inclusion of the various web-based materials.  An important aspect of this project was to investigate various means of promptly identifying students likely to struggle in the course.  For the predication tool to be useful it had to be both accurate and to provide results within the first weeks of the class.  While mulitiple tools were found to be accurate, some were only accurate when administered too late in the course to provide enough time to allow at-risk students to obtain the necessary help to succeed.  Initial studies suggest one tool, a conceptual-based writing quiz administered on the fifth day of class, is both accurate and provides results early enough to make a difference to at-risk students.  The writing-based exercise was graded using a holistic approach in which not only the correctness but also the richness of response were considered.  In other words, even if a student's response was flawed with an evident misconception regarding a basic circuit concept, as long as the response displayed evidence of the student's ability to meaningfully reason, it would not be placed in the lowest scoring category.  93% of students scoring at the lowest level on the writing exercise were found to score below the passing level on the course's first exam given approximately five weeks later, whereas 94% of those scoring above the lowest level on the writing exam scored above the passing level on exam 1.  Clearly, initial evidence suggests the use of the writing exercise is a powerful tool for identifying students in need of additional assistance.  It is acknowledged that evaluating writing samples of students and providing tailored feedback on these writing samples is time consuming.  Due to the time intensive nature of grading and the value students place on immediate feedback, an initial attempt was made to use existing Natural Language Processing (NLP) techniques coded in software to classify responses as belonging to students in the at-risk class or to those outside of the at-risk class.  NLP technologies are widely used in internet search engines and in voice activated assistants such as Alexa and Siri.  An un-optimized NLP algorithm was shown to achieve a balanced accuracy of 86% in the binary classification task of separating at-risk students from the non at-risk class.  This promising result suggests that further research effort be guided towards leveraging state-of-the-art NLP algorithms to not only classify student writings but also to provide individualized feedback to students regarding their understanding of fundamental concepts as determined through their writing.  The use of the general techniques employed in this project can extend to many STEM courses.  Certainly the use of writing in typical problem-based courses should be further explored as should the use of NLP to make such writing exercises scalable to high-enrollment courses.  Finally, a series of outreach activities intended to help fourth-grade students begin to form proper conceptual models for basic concepts in electrical circuits was developed and delivered.  The activities are meant to complement existing materials often delivered to fourth-grade students during their common module on electricity and magnetism.  The activities were found to be both effective and engaging, with approximately two hundred students taking part.       Last Modified: 06/27/2019       Submitted by: James P Becker]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
