<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>The EPP-Supported Neutrino Program at MIT</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>05/15/2015</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>675000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>886429</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03010000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>PHY</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Physics</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Randy Ruchti</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>One of the major intellectual achievements of the 20th century was the development of the Standard Model (SM) of particle physics. This model succeeded in classifying all of the elementary particles known at the time into a hierarchy of groups having similar quantum properties. The validity of this model to date was recently confirmed by the discovery of the Higgs boson at the Large Hadron Collider at CERN. However, the Standard Model as it currently exists leaves open many questions about the universe, including such fundamental questions as to why the Higgs mass has the value it has and why there is no antimatter in the universe. One of the primary areas to search for answers to these and other open questions about the universe, how it came to be, and why it is the way it is, is to focus on a study of the properties of neutrinos and to use what we know and can learn about neutrinos as probes of science Beyond the Standard Model (BSM). Neutrinos are those elementary particles that interact with practically nothing else in the universe. They have no electric charge and were once thought to be massless. Like other elementary particles, they were believed to have an antimatter counterpart, the antineutrino. Moreover, the Standard Model predicted that there were actually three different kinds of neutrinos that were distinguishable through the different interactions that they did undergo whenever there was an interaction. But recent measurements have totally changed our picture of neutrinos. We now know that neutrinos do have a mass and because they do, they can actually change from one type to another. Detailed measurements of these changes, along with other current neutrino experiments, form one of the most promising ways to probe for new physics beyond the Standard Model.  This project will focus on the development of a detector based on liquid argon to search for the so-called sterile neutrino, whose existence is suggested by BSM theories.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;There is currently a large interest in experimental particle physics in Liquid Argon Time Projection Chambers (LArTPC) spurred in part by the proposed Long Baseline Neutrino Experiment (LBNE) project at Fermi National Accelerator Laboratory (FNAL) and in neutrino physics in general. This award supports work which refines LArTPC technology, using the Liquid Argon Near Detector (Lar1ND) and the MicroBooNE experiment at FNAL. Both of these experiments will further the study of potential signals of sterile neutrinos.   Sterile neutrinos are proposed BSM particles that could explain aspects of cosmology and astrophysics such as Dark Matter. MicroBooNE will make a variety of interesting physics measurements, as well as serving as a proving ground for new hardware techniques relevant for future experiments. Among MicroBooNE's primary physics goals is to provide a cross-check of the "low-energy excess" of electron neutrino events previously identified by the MiniBooNE experiment.  There have been recent "hints" that there may be a new type of neutrino, the so-called sterile neutrino. The MicroBoone experiment, with the superior LArTPC, should clarify the situation: either rule out or confirm the sterile neutrino evidence.  The PI's Group has broader impacts programs that address development of a globally competitive STEM workforce; increased participation of women and minorities; improved teacher development; improved&lt;br/&gt;undergraduate education;and increased public scientific literacy.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>05/13/2015</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>03/20/2018</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1505855</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Janet</FirstName>
<LastName>Conrad</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>M</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Janet M Conrad</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>conrad@mit.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6173246281</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000273390</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/13/2015</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Massachusetts Institute of Technology</Name>
<CityName>Cambridge</CityName>
<ZipCode>021394301</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6172531000</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>77 MASSACHUSETTS AVE</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[NE18-901]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
<StateCode>MA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MA07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>001425594</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>MASSACHUSETTS INSTITUTE OF TECHNOLOGY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>001425594</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Massachusetts Institute of Technology]]></Name>
<CityName>Cambridge</CityName>
<StateCode>MA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>021394307</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[77 Massachusetts Ave]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MA07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1221</Code>
<Text>HEP-High Energy Physics</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1253</Code>
<Text>OFFICE OF MULTIDISCIPLINARY AC</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7621</Code>
<Text>PHYSICS-BROADEN PARTICIPATION</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1221</Code>
<Text>ELEMENTARY PARTICLE ACCEL USER</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1515</Code>
<Text>MINORITY GRADUATE EDUC ACTIVIT</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7483</Code>
<Text>PHYSICS OF THE UNIVERSE</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0115</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0116</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0117</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0118</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2015~225000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2016~293340</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2017~295253</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2018~72836</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>This grant supports the Elementary Particle Physics (EPP)-funded research of the Massachusetts Institute of Technology Neutrino Group, headed by Prof. Janet Conrad. The group focuses on beyond-Standard-Model searches in the neutrino sector. In particular, we search for sterile neutrinos--a key goal of the Particle Physics Prioritization Panel, P5 (recommendation 15).</p> <p>The primary program is the MicroBooNE Experiment, which makes use of a state-of-the-art liquid argon detector that began taking data in 2015. The goal of this experiment is to study the MiniBooNE anomaly, which is an excess of electron-neutrino-like events observed at short-baseline in a muon-neutrino-beam that has been identified as a potential sterile neutrino signal. This is called the "Low Energy Excess" (LEE). We specialize in deep learning teachniques for this analysis.&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; This result is expected to be presented in 2020.</p> <p>MicroBooNE is the first large LArTPC to be constructed in the US. As a result, all of our work on this is leading the way for experiments to come. These include the Shote Baseline (SBN) program and also DUNE, which is the highest priority experiment in our field.&nbsp;&nbsp; Related to this,&nbsp; the group also participates in R&amp;D for future liquid argon-based experiments. We specialize in collection of scintillation light in liquid argon. We have engaged in R&amp;D efforts for DUNE through a test experiment called ProtoDUNE.&nbsp; This work also relates to a new experiment, Coherent Captain Mills (CCM), which is, in itself, a test experiment for the SBND programs.&nbsp;&nbsp; We are founding members of CCM.</p> <p>We are leaders in machine learning applied to neutrino physics. Other experiments, are learning from our techniques and following our lead. The impact of this work extends beyond neutrino physics.&nbsp;&nbsp; Of the 47 citations of the convolution neural net paper published by our MicroBooNE group, 7 are from the computer sciences.&nbsp;&nbsp; In the final report submitted to NSF we provide a reference to a talk by a research scientist from Facebook on Object Detection and Image Segmentation that discusses our MicroBooNE papers.</p> <p>As a result of this cutting-edge research employing data science, we have trained students to move to industry as well as into academia.&nbsp;&nbsp; One of our undergraduates now works at Google.&nbsp;&nbsp; Another is performing Deep Learning analysis for the New England Patriots Football Team.</p> <p>A secondary program on this grant, but one with enormous impact, is the continued analysis of the MiniBooNE LEE data.&nbsp;&nbsp; MiniBooNE has been a part of our research program since 1999, and the detector took data over a 17 year span from 2002 to 2019. &nbsp; &nbsp; During this grant period, MiniBooNE doubled the statistics of the neutrino run that was published in 2007.&nbsp;&nbsp; The resulting paper has more than 175 citations to date.&nbsp;&nbsp; The MiniBooNE LEE anomaly has persisted and this is the impetus for the entire SBN program, not just MicroBooNE.</p> <p>Another secondary program that has been very fruitful during this time period has been our work on global fits to short baseline oscillation data, including MiniBooNE, the reactor experiments, the source experiments and others. This work combines results that have indicated anomalies with null signals to narrow the parameter space of future searches. The results of this phenomenological work has guided our efforts on MicroBooNE, our primary program.&nbsp;&nbsp; It is a driver of the design choices for the entire SBN program, which has the search for the MiniBooNE LEE as its primary goal.&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; We are the only experimental group performing these global fits.&nbsp; Thus, our work has a unique place in the community.</p> <p>The global fit work has required us to form a bridge to the statistics community, and this represents a new and interesting broader impact.&nbsp; One student who received his Ph.D. on work that includes the global fits is now a postdoctoral fellow with the Institute of Data Science and Society (IDSS).&nbsp; This is the heart of the academic program in statistics at MIT.&nbsp; One of our undergraduates from MicroBooNE is now receiving a masters in statistics from IDSS.</p> <p>The group supported by this grant is diverse.&nbsp; Among the undergraduate and graduate students supported by this grant are two Hispanics and seven women.&nbsp;&nbsp; Also, this grant has supported several "first generation" students--students who are first in their families to attend university.</p> <p>Conrad is heavily invested in increasing the number of women in the field of neutrino physics and in academia in general.&nbsp; She often attends conferences where she can advise women on their careers.&nbsp; She is especially proud to be active in the Path to Professorship Program at MIT.&nbsp;&nbsp; This program mentors women who are advanced graduate students, postdocs and early faculty, primarily from the New England area through a two-day conference.&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; Ordinarily Conrad serves on the panel on "networking," but this year she was chosen as the keynote speaker.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 11/29/2019<br>      Modified by: Janet&nbsp;M&nbsp;Conrad</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ This grant supports the Elementary Particle Physics (EPP)-funded research of the Massachusetts Institute of Technology Neutrino Group, headed by Prof. Janet Conrad. The group focuses on beyond-Standard-Model searches in the neutrino sector. In particular, we search for sterile neutrinos--a key goal of the Particle Physics Prioritization Panel, P5 (recommendation 15).  The primary program is the MicroBooNE Experiment, which makes use of a state-of-the-art liquid argon detector that began taking data in 2015. The goal of this experiment is to study the MiniBooNE anomaly, which is an excess of electron-neutrino-like events observed at short-baseline in a muon-neutrino-beam that has been identified as a potential sterile neutrino signal. This is called the "Low Energy Excess" (LEE). We specialize in deep learning teachniques for this analysis.    This result is expected to be presented in 2020.  MicroBooNE is the first large LArTPC to be constructed in the US. As a result, all of our work on this is leading the way for experiments to come. These include the Shote Baseline (SBN) program and also DUNE, which is the highest priority experiment in our field.   Related to this,  the group also participates in R&amp;D for future liquid argon-based experiments. We specialize in collection of scintillation light in liquid argon. We have engaged in R&amp;D efforts for DUNE through a test experiment called ProtoDUNE.  This work also relates to a new experiment, Coherent Captain Mills (CCM), which is, in itself, a test experiment for the SBND programs.   We are founding members of CCM.  We are leaders in machine learning applied to neutrino physics. Other experiments, are learning from our techniques and following our lead. The impact of this work extends beyond neutrino physics.   Of the 47 citations of the convolution neural net paper published by our MicroBooNE group, 7 are from the computer sciences.   In the final report submitted to NSF we provide a reference to a talk by a research scientist from Facebook on Object Detection and Image Segmentation that discusses our MicroBooNE papers.  As a result of this cutting-edge research employing data science, we have trained students to move to industry as well as into academia.   One of our undergraduates now works at Google.   Another is performing Deep Learning analysis for the New England Patriots Football Team.  A secondary program on this grant, but one with enormous impact, is the continued analysis of the MiniBooNE LEE data.   MiniBooNE has been a part of our research program since 1999, and the detector took data over a 17 year span from 2002 to 2019.     During this grant period, MiniBooNE doubled the statistics of the neutrino run that was published in 2007.   The resulting paper has more than 175 citations to date.   The MiniBooNE LEE anomaly has persisted and this is the impetus for the entire SBN program, not just MicroBooNE.  Another secondary program that has been very fruitful during this time period has been our work on global fits to short baseline oscillation data, including MiniBooNE, the reactor experiments, the source experiments and others. This work combines results that have indicated anomalies with null signals to narrow the parameter space of future searches. The results of this phenomenological work has guided our efforts on MicroBooNE, our primary program.   It is a driver of the design choices for the entire SBN program, which has the search for the MiniBooNE LEE as its primary goal.    We are the only experimental group performing these global fits.  Thus, our work has a unique place in the community.  The global fit work has required us to form a bridge to the statistics community, and this represents a new and interesting broader impact.  One student who received his Ph.D. on work that includes the global fits is now a postdoctoral fellow with the Institute of Data Science and Society (IDSS).  This is the heart of the academic program in statistics at MIT.  One of our undergraduates from MicroBooNE is now receiving a masters in statistics from IDSS.  The group supported by this grant is diverse.  Among the undergraduate and graduate students supported by this grant are two Hispanics and seven women.   Also, this grant has supported several "first generation" students--students who are first in their families to attend university.  Conrad is heavily invested in increasing the number of women in the field of neutrino physics and in academia in general.  She often attends conferences where she can advise women on their careers.  She is especially proud to be active in the Path to Professorship Program at MIT.   This program mentors women who are advanced graduate students, postdocs and early faculty, primarily from the New England area through a two-day conference.    Ordinarily Conrad serves on the panel on "networking," but this year she was chosen as the keynote speaker.       Last Modified: 11/29/2019       Submitted by: Janet M Conrad]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
