<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Tuning the Photovoltaic Performance of Benzodithiophene and Benzodifuran Polymeric Semiconductors by Molecular Design</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2015</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>239996.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>239996</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03070000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DMR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Materials Research</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Andrew Lovinger</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>alovinge@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924933</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>NON-TECHNICAL SUMMARY:&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The development of new technologies that exploit the potential of renewable energy sources such as solar power is currently one of the most   targeted research directions.  Polymer solar cells developed in the PI's research group at the University of Texas at Dallas (UTD) are being explored as feasible alternatives for low cost, lightweight, large area, and flexible solar panels.  The proposed research will aim toward the synthesis and characterization of novel organic semiconducting polymeric materials with good performance in organic solar cells.  Its overall objective is to establish a correlation between structure and opto-electronic properties for new types of semiconducting polymers.  This award will support the interdisciplinary training of graduate and undergraduate students at the interface between chemistry, materials science, and semiconductor technologies. Other broader educational and diversity-enhancing impacts include mentoring of high school students over a one-year period to complete a science and engineering project.  The PI is also participating in a highly successful program at UTD which gives high-school students the opportunity to participate in summer research.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;TECHNICAL SUMMARY:&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project will allow the PI to extend and consolidate the interdisciplinary research and education program at the interface between polymer chemistry, materials science, and semiconductor technologies which she started through an NSF CAREER award. The overall objective of the proposed research is to establish a structure / opto-electronic properties correlation for benzodithiophene and benzodifuran donor-acceptor semiconducting polymers.  Benzodithiophene and benzodifuran will be employed as building blocks for the synthesis of donor-acceptor polymers with tunable opto-electronic properties. The planned research program targets the synthesis of the monomers and their corresponding polymers, followed by their structural, morphological and opto-electronic characterization and the testing of the materials in bulk heterojunction solar cells.  The experimental data obtained from solar cell testing will be used to fine-tune the structures of donor-acceptor semiconducting polymers.  The research program will have a broadly integrated approach, where students will gain expertise in organic/polymer synthesis, characterization, and solar cell fabrication and testing. The PI will capitalize on prior experience in polymer science and organic electronics, but also expand skills in morphological characterization of the active layer of bulk heterojunction solar cells. The PI's research program will be tightly integrated with an education component by training graduate and undergraduate students who will develop expertise in organic/polymer chemistry, thin-film characterization, and solar-cell fabrication and testing.  It will also be coupled with an outreach and diversity-enhancement program toward high-school students.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>04/16/2015</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>04/16/2015</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1505950</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Mihaela</FirstName>
<LastName>Stefan</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Mihaela Stefan</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>mci071000@utdallas.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>9728836581</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000499093</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/16/2015</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Texas at Dallas</Name>
<CityName>Richardson</CityName>
<ZipCode>750803021</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>9728832313</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>800 W. Campbell Rd., AD15</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Texas</StateName>
<StateCode>TX</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>32</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>TX32</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>800188161</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF TEXAS AT DALLAS</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>042000273</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[university of texas at dallas]]></Name>
<CityName>Richardson</CityName>
<StateCode>TX</StateCode>
<ZipCode>750803021</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[800 West Campbell Road]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Texas</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>32</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>TX32</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1773</Code>
<Text>POLYMERS</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8396</Code>
<Text>Clean Energy Technology</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8607</Code>
<Text>Solar Energy Capture&amp;Conver</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0115</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2015~239996</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><span style="font-family: Calibri; font-size: small;">Project Outcomes Report</span></p> <p><span style="font-family: Calibri; font-size: small;">Project Title: Tuning the Photovoltaic Performance of Benzodithiophene and Benzodifuran Polymeric Semiconductors by Molecular Design.</span></p> <p><span style="font-family: Calibri; font-size: small;">Award Number: 1505950</span></p> <p><span style="text-decoration: underline;"><span style="font-family: Calibri; font-size: small;">Intellectual Merit</span></span></p> <p><span style="font-family: Calibri; font-size: small;">The goal of the project is to advance the development of organic photovoltaic devices utilizing semiconducting materials based on benzodithiophene and benzodifuran as electron-donating units. Both of these units have shown a promising future as building units in either molecular or polymeric semiconductors. We further investigated the impact of the structure on the optical, electrochemical and morphological properties. </span></p> <p><span style="font-family: Calibri; font-size: small;">We successfully developed two isomeric small molecules based on benzodithiophene and benzothiadiazole units. The distance between benzodithiophene and benzothiadiazole units were varied by changing the position of the benzothiadiazole unit. The impact of such structure variation was systematically investigated in terms of the optical and electrochemical properties, which further influenced the photovoltaic performance when these two molecules were employed as p-type materials in photovoltaic devices. Placing benzothiadiazole unit beside benzodithiophene, resulted in broader absorption and higher crystallinity, which contributed to the better short circuit current and fill factor. The crystallinity of two molecules were studied by atomic force microscopy and electron transmission microscopy.</span></p> <p><span style="font-family: Calibri; font-size: small;">Different from building units synthesized from thiophene, furan based building units received much less attention. We established new donor-acceptor alternative copolymer featuring benzodifuran and furan substituted diketopyrrolopyrrole. Both of the building units can be synthesized from furan, the derivative of renewable energy source furfural. We systematically studied its optical, electrochemical and morphological properties, as well as its performance in solar cell devices. After careful optimization, we achieved&nbsp;good power conversion efficiency with high fill factor. Our research results demonstrated that conjugated polymers built from green furan units have the potential to show better electronic performance and could be considered as a replacement for thiophene derivatives. </span></p> <p><span style="text-decoration: underline;"><span style="font-family: Calibri; font-size: small;">Broad Impacts</span></span></p> <p><span>This project gave opportunities to graduate and undergraduate students to participate in multidisciplinary research at the interface of chemistry, materials science, and semiconductor technologies. Both graduate and undergraduate students had a chance to learn organic synthesis, optical, electrochemical and morphological characterizations, as well as organic photovoltaic device fabrications. <span>&nbsp;</span>High school students also participated in the research funded by this grant in the summer of 2016 and summer 2017. We also participated in outreach activities organized by the Chemistry Student Association at the Universit</span><strong>&nbsp;</strong><em></em></p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 08/29/2017<br>      Modified by: Mihaela&nbsp;Stefan</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Project Outcomes Report  Project Title: Tuning the Photovoltaic Performance of Benzodithiophene and Benzodifuran Polymeric Semiconductors by Molecular Design.  Award Number: 1505950  Intellectual Merit  The goal of the project is to advance the development of organic photovoltaic devices utilizing semiconducting materials based on benzodithiophene and benzodifuran as electron-donating units. Both of these units have shown a promising future as building units in either molecular or polymeric semiconductors. We further investigated the impact of the structure on the optical, electrochemical and morphological properties.   We successfully developed two isomeric small molecules based on benzodithiophene and benzothiadiazole units. The distance between benzodithiophene and benzothiadiazole units were varied by changing the position of the benzothiadiazole unit. The impact of such structure variation was systematically investigated in terms of the optical and electrochemical properties, which further influenced the photovoltaic performance when these two molecules were employed as p-type materials in photovoltaic devices. Placing benzothiadiazole unit beside benzodithiophene, resulted in broader absorption and higher crystallinity, which contributed to the better short circuit current and fill factor. The crystallinity of two molecules were studied by atomic force microscopy and electron transmission microscopy.  Different from building units synthesized from thiophene, furan based building units received much less attention. We established new donor-acceptor alternative copolymer featuring benzodifuran and furan substituted diketopyrrolopyrrole. Both of the building units can be synthesized from furan, the derivative of renewable energy source furfural. We systematically studied its optical, electrochemical and morphological properties, as well as its performance in solar cell devices. After careful optimization, we achieved good power conversion efficiency with high fill factor. Our research results demonstrated that conjugated polymers built from green furan units have the potential to show better electronic performance and could be considered as a replacement for thiophene derivatives.   Broad Impacts  This project gave opportunities to graduate and undergraduate students to participate in multidisciplinary research at the interface of chemistry, materials science, and semiconductor technologies. Both graduate and undergraduate students had a chance to learn organic synthesis, optical, electrochemical and morphological characterizations, as well as organic photovoltaic device fabrications.  High school students also participated in the research funded by this grant in the summer of 2016 and summer 2017. We also participated in outreach activities organized by the Chemistry Student Association at the Universit           Last Modified: 08/29/2017       Submitted by: Mihaela Stefan]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
