<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Biological Cell Lasers</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2015</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>450000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>450000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07010000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>ECCS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Electrical, Commun &amp; Cyber Sys</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Ruyan Guo</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>rguo@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927718</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Abstract Title: Biological cell lasers&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Abstract: &lt;br/&gt;Non-technical: Since the first laser human ever made was demonstrated a half century ago, numerous types of lasers have been developed and made a tremendous impact on modern science and technology. In medicine and biology, various lasers have been adopted and being applied. For example, lasers allow physicians to remove diseased tissues, seal damaged areas with high precision, and activate drugs in specific target organs for treatments. In all these cases, lasers are commonly used as devices and instruments that are separate from the patients. The goal of the proposed research is to invent a new type of laser that is made biologically compatible and readily amenable to living organisms and human body. Such bio-lasers can be integrated into the biological systems and thereby have a potential to offer new ways of using laser light in biomedical sensing and diagnosis, as well as therapy. This project also provides the opportunity to educate and train graduate students and postdoctoral fellows in the highly vibrant and multidisciplinary environment at the Wellman Center for Photomedicine. The graduate students and undergraduate students will have the opportunity to participate in this project, learn how to work across boundaries between disciplines through creativity and inspiration, and present their research in a conference, with support from this project. The outcome of this project is expected to inspire the general public, particularly children, and make them aware of the far-reaching impact and joy of science. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Technical: The previous NSF funding led to the first biological laser based on single human cells or bacteria. This proposed project will push the envelop of the field to the next significant level, with two specific aims to develop (1) microfluidic cell laser-on-a-chip with high controllability and high throughput for applications to intracellular sensing and cytometry and (2) stand-alone cell lasers that are operational in tissue without external cavities. This project continues to explore the new territory in the field of laser and show how the unique properties of cell lasers can be harnessed to develop novel photonic devices and technologies. The experimental approach is highly interdisciplinary as it brings together physical and biological sciences and engineering. This work will increase our understanding about the design, operation, and applications of cell lasers, and points to a way to realize "living laser", where all three basic elements, i.e. amplification, resonance, and pumping, are achieved with biological materials in vivo. The intrinsically biocompatible cell laser has the potential to make a transformative impact on the way light is used in biomedical applications. For example, lasing within the tissues and inside the cells may offer new possibilities of intracellular sensing and nonlinear microscopy for biological analysis and medical diagnosis. The ability to generate laser light in vivo may enable new approaches in light-controlled therapy and drug activation.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/01/2015</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/01/2015</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1505569</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Seok (Andy)</FirstName>
<LastName>Yun</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>H</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME>PhD</PI_SUFX_NAME>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Seok (Andy) H Yun</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>syun@mgh.harvard.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6177688704</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000079450</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/01/2015</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Massachusetts General Hospital</Name>
<CityName>Somerville</CityName>
<ZipCode>021451446</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>8572821670</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>Research Management</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[399 Revolution Drive]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
<StateCode>MA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MA07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>073130411</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>MASSACHUSETTS GENERAL HOSPITAL, THE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>825636988</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Massachusetts General Hospital]]></Name>
<CityName>Cambridge</CityName>
<StateCode>MA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>021394232</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[65 Landsdowne St. UP-5]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MA07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1517</Code>
<Text>EPMD-ElectrnPhoton&amp;MagnDevices</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>091E</Code>
<Text>Light generation &amp; detection</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0115</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2015~450000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Lasers have made tremendous impacts to our society ranging from supermarket barcode scanners to smartphone camera lightings. In hospitals, many different types of lasers are used for health monitoring, microscopy, and laser surgery. The global market for the medical laser devices is estimated to be $3.7B in 2013.</p> <p>Let us think about how these lasers look like. They have the form of a device or equipment. For analyzing biological cells and tissues, lasers are always separate from the samples. We challenged this paradigm. What if we can put lasers into the samples? Imagine a laser&nbsp;that is so small that it can be inserted into a cell or embedded into a tissue. Imagine lasers that are particles, disposables, and consumables. This NSF funding allowed us to open this this new paradigm.</p> <p>Our research and development supported by this project have led to the successful demonstration of several types of intracellular lasers and implantable biomaterial lasers. For example, we demonstrated how we can alter the genomes of a cell so that the cells produce appropriate materials that self-assemble to form optical resonators and gain media, capable of emitting laser light. We demonstrated a proof of concept illustrating how one can produce laser light from the eyeball (ex vivo pig eye) using implanted microsphere lasers.&nbsp;Intracellular micro-lasers offer a new opportunity for cellular labeling, enabling tracking of cells spatially over time. With further technical developments, cell-compatible micro lasers have potential to lead to new approaches in biomedical imaging and single-cell studies.</p> <p>As broader impacts, this project has served as a training platform for several undergraduate students and graduate students, as well as postdoctoral researchers. As part of activities, the principal investigator of this project has served as a founding co-chair of a new biannual conference on the topic of ?Lasers in micro, nano and bio Systems?. Nearly 100 researchers and students have participated in its first meeting in 2018.&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 10/21/2019<br>      Modified by: Seok (Andy)&nbsp;H&nbsp;Yun</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Lasers have made tremendous impacts to our society ranging from supermarket barcode scanners to smartphone camera lightings. In hospitals, many different types of lasers are used for health monitoring, microscopy, and laser surgery. The global market for the medical laser devices is estimated to be $3.7B in 2013.  Let us think about how these lasers look like. They have the form of a device or equipment. For analyzing biological cells and tissues, lasers are always separate from the samples. We challenged this paradigm. What if we can put lasers into the samples? Imagine a laser that is so small that it can be inserted into a cell or embedded into a tissue. Imagine lasers that are particles, disposables, and consumables. This NSF funding allowed us to open this this new paradigm.  Our research and development supported by this project have led to the successful demonstration of several types of intracellular lasers and implantable biomaterial lasers. For example, we demonstrated how we can alter the genomes of a cell so that the cells produce appropriate materials that self-assemble to form optical resonators and gain media, capable of emitting laser light. We demonstrated a proof of concept illustrating how one can produce laser light from the eyeball (ex vivo pig eye) using implanted microsphere lasers. Intracellular micro-lasers offer a new opportunity for cellular labeling, enabling tracking of cells spatially over time. With further technical developments, cell-compatible micro lasers have potential to lead to new approaches in biomedical imaging and single-cell studies.  As broader impacts, this project has served as a training platform for several undergraduate students and graduate students, as well as postdoctoral researchers. As part of activities, the principal investigator of this project has served as a founding co-chair of a new biannual conference on the topic of ?Lasers in micro, nano and bio Systems?. Nearly 100 researchers and students have participated in its first meeting in 2018.           Last Modified: 10/21/2019       Submitted by: Seok (Andy) H Yun]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
