<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>CAREER: The physiology and genetics of adaptation in a complex environment</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/16/2014</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>04/30/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>683365.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>683365</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>08090300</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>BIO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>IOS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Integrative Organismal Systems</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Theodore Morgan</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>tmorgan@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927868</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Organisms have a remarkable capacity to respond physiologically to their environment to maintain survival and health even in times of stress. This research program investigates the physiological responses of the model genetic organism Drosophila melanogaster to a complex environment. D. melanogaster recently expanded its range out of tropical Africa and into higher latitudes with more variable thermal environments. At the same time, D. melanogaster evolved a remarkable tolerance of ethanol and acetic acid in its fermenting fruit habitat. The natural history of this fruit fly allows for an investigation of how organisms are likely to respond to a complex and increasingly variable climate. In particular, this research will test hypotheses about how changes in cell membranes and metabolism maintain health, performance and fitness in a thermally-variable and alcohol-rich niche. The experiments investigate changes that occur within the lifespan of organisms to deal with the environment -- plastic physiologies -- and changes that have evolved to fit organisms to their environment via the process of natural selection physiological adaptations. The goal of this research is to identify the interactions among multiple genes that underlie these plastic and adaptive responses to a complex environment.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The proposed research will further our knowledge in areas identified by the Frontiers in Evolutionary Biology workshop (NSF 2005), provide insight on genetic, cellular and physiological mechanisms of environmental tolerance, and develop new methods for associating physiological traits with complex genetic variation at multiple genes. Data will be made publicly available using the DRYAD database (http://datadryad.org/), and genetic lines will be made available upon request after publication. Genetic lines judged to be of use for many labs will be placed in the Bloomington Drosophila Stock Center (http://flystocks.bio.indiana.edu/).&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The educational objectives draw on the PI's history of integrating her research and teaching. Objective 1 develops a novel curriculum for college-level biology classes that uses case studies to teach skills in information literacy, writing, quantitative thinking, and data representation. Curricula will be deposited in the publicly available database of the NSF National Center for Case Study Teaching (NCCST; http://sciencecases.lib.buffalo.edu/cs/collection/). Objective 2 will create an educational multimedia display to promote public literacy in the life sciences. Objective 3 advances a research training program for students that integrates genetics, evolution, and cellular and organismal physiology, and includes minority and female students.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>11/19/2014</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>04/28/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.074</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1505247</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Kristi</FirstName>
<LastName>Montooth</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Kristi Montooth</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>kmontooth2@unl.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>4024724855</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000532648</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>11/19/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</Name>
<CityName>Lincoln</CityName>
<ZipCode>685031435</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>4024723171</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>151 Prem S. Paul Research Center</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[2200 Vine St]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Nebraska</StateName>
<StateCode>NE</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NE01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>555456995</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>BOARD OF REGENTS OF THE UNIVERSITY OF NEBRASKA</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>068662618</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Nebraska-Lincoln]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>NE</StateCode>
<ZipCode>685880118</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Nebraska</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NE01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7378</Code>
<Text>EVOLUTIONARY GENETICS</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7657</Code>
<Text>Integrtv Ecological Physiology</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1045</Code>
<Text>CAREER-Faculty Erly Career Dev</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1187</Code>
<Text>PECASE- eligible</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9178</Code>
<Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9179</Code>
<Text>GRADUATE INVOLVEMENT</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0112</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0114</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0115</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0116</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2012~55021</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~216858</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2015~205739</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2016~205746</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Intellectual merit: The research supported by this award characterized physiological mechanisms by which organisms maintain healthy development and performance in the context of environmental stress, such as ethanol and temperature, and cellular stress caused by mutations or conditions that affect metabolism. We found that mitochondrial performance can be largely maintained during development through compensatory and plastic physiological changes in response to cellular energetic stress caused by mitochondrial-nuclear mutations and in response to environmental stress such as that caused by high temperature and ethanol. However, these compensatory physiological changes may come at costs to organisms post-development, such as costs to reproductive fitness and immune function. During development, one of these costs appears to be oxidative stress (e.g., elevated reactive oxygen species or free radicals). The results of this award have generated new hypotheses into how invertebrate mitochondria may use conserved uncoupling proteins (most famously studied in the brown fat of hibernating mammals) as a cellular defense mechanism to maintain function during times of oxidative stress. The award also supported development of protocols and new results focused on how genetic and environmental stressors affect embryogenesis and the larval life stage. Relative to the adult stage, these life stages are less studied in the fruit fly Drosophila, but represent ecologically important life stages; eggs and larvae develop in fermenting fruit that can reach quite high temperatures. We found that embryogenesis is a critical life stage that is very sensitive to both genetic and thermal stress, and that thermal plasticity in how mothers provision eggs may play a key role in offspring success.</p> <p>Broader impacts: The research supported by this award made significant contributions to the research and professional training of seven graduate students, four postdoctoral researchers, and over 20 undergraduate researchers. Many of these trainees were people of color or white women, groups that are underrepresented in STEM fields. Trainees have gone on to professions in medicine, conservation biology, genetic counseling, teaching, science communication, and academic research. Trainees developed and implemented numerous community engagement activities at the Nebraska State Museum, as well as an activity that is used at an annual women in science state-wide event. The primary investigator developed case-study curriculum modules for introductory biology courses and designed a new upper-division course that focused on active learning in the classroom, science literacy, and synthesis of information across disparate fields in the life science such as eco-physiology with molecular biology and disease genetics. Finally, the results of experiments supported by this award advance our understanding of important societal issues around mitochondrial function and its role in ethanol toxicity and disease, as well as how organisms respond to environmental variation and change.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 09/26/2019<br>      Modified by: Kristi&nbsp;Montooth</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Intellectual merit: The research supported by this award characterized physiological mechanisms by which organisms maintain healthy development and performance in the context of environmental stress, such as ethanol and temperature, and cellular stress caused by mutations or conditions that affect metabolism. We found that mitochondrial performance can be largely maintained during development through compensatory and plastic physiological changes in response to cellular energetic stress caused by mitochondrial-nuclear mutations and in response to environmental stress such as that caused by high temperature and ethanol. However, these compensatory physiological changes may come at costs to organisms post-development, such as costs to reproductive fitness and immune function. During development, one of these costs appears to be oxidative stress (e.g., elevated reactive oxygen species or free radicals). The results of this award have generated new hypotheses into how invertebrate mitochondria may use conserved uncoupling proteins (most famously studied in the brown fat of hibernating mammals) as a cellular defense mechanism to maintain function during times of oxidative stress. The award also supported development of protocols and new results focused on how genetic and environmental stressors affect embryogenesis and the larval life stage. Relative to the adult stage, these life stages are less studied in the fruit fly Drosophila, but represent ecologically important life stages; eggs and larvae develop in fermenting fruit that can reach quite high temperatures. We found that embryogenesis is a critical life stage that is very sensitive to both genetic and thermal stress, and that thermal plasticity in how mothers provision eggs may play a key role in offspring success.  Broader impacts: The research supported by this award made significant contributions to the research and professional training of seven graduate students, four postdoctoral researchers, and over 20 undergraduate researchers. Many of these trainees were people of color or white women, groups that are underrepresented in STEM fields. Trainees have gone on to professions in medicine, conservation biology, genetic counseling, teaching, science communication, and academic research. Trainees developed and implemented numerous community engagement activities at the Nebraska State Museum, as well as an activity that is used at an annual women in science state-wide event. The primary investigator developed case-study curriculum modules for introductory biology courses and designed a new upper-division course that focused on active learning in the classroom, science literacy, and synthesis of information across disparate fields in the life science such as eco-physiology with molecular biology and disease genetics. Finally, the results of experiments supported by this award advance our understanding of important societal issues around mitochondrial function and its role in ethanol toxicity and disease, as well as how organisms respond to environmental variation and change.             Last Modified: 09/26/2019       Submitted by: Kristi Montooth]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
