<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Searching and Discovering New Physics with Run-2 on ATLAS Experiment of LHC</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2015</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2020</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>509994.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>559994</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03010000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>PHY</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Physics</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Saul Gonzalez</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>sgonzale@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922093</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The Standard Model (SM) of elementary particle physics gives an excellent description of the strong and electroweak interactions, the forces that influence the structure and behavior of elementary particles such as the proton and neutron.  The SM also describes most of what we know about the visible matter in the Universe.  The Higgs Boson, discovered at the Large Hadron Collider (LHC) in Switzerland, was the last ingredient in this theory.  Yet the overwhelming success of the SM seems only to emphasize its limitations.  There are many open questions remaining.   Why are there three families of quarks, elementary particles that make up the proton and neutron, and leptons, elementary particles such as the electron and muon? What is the nature of space-time itself?  Do the extra dimensions suggested by string theories and string- inspired models really exist? Where do dark energy and dark matter fit into our current picture of the universe? Answers to these key questions can only be found by including new physics beyond the SM. This group will work with the ATLAS experiment at the LHC to look for this new physics by searching for new particles emerging from proton-proton collisions.  An exciting feature of this program is that a number of undergraduate and Masters students from Fresno and other Cal State institutions will be involved. They will participate not only in this analysis thrust but will also gain hands-on experience helping in a variety of hardware projects from other ATLAS collaborators.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;In this proposed research plan, Professor Gao and his group at California State University, Fresno will continue to search for particles from new physics in di-jet events. The use of di-jet data as a way to search for new physics is a classic approach with a long history, and requires precise understanding of the jet energy scales expected from the SM. The PI has considerable experience in jet physics and is well aware of the challenges this presents. He intends to build on successful prior work in which new variables were identified that should discriminate a potential new physics signal from QCD. Such variables, by construction, use the radiation patterns from partons in a multi-variate analysis of the structures observed.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/04/2015</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/07/2018</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1505840</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Yongsheng</FirstName>
<LastName>Gao</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Yongsheng Gao</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>yogao@csufresno.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5592784554</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000505549</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/04/2015</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>California State University-Fresno Foundation</Name>
<CityName>Fresno</CityName>
<ZipCode>937400001</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5592780840</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>5241 N. Maple Ave</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[M/S TA53]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>22</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CA22</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>150837003</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>CALIFORNIA STATE UNIVERSITY FRESNO FOUNDATION INC</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>150837003</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Cal State U Fresno]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>937261852</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>22</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CA22</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1221</Code>
<Text>HEP-High Energy Physics</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7483</Code>
<Text>PHYSICS OF THE UNIVERSE</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0115</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0116</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0117</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0118</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2015~169998</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2016~169998</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2017~169998</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2018~50000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><table border="0" cellspacing="0" cellpadding="0" width="100%"> <tbody> <tr> <td> <table border="0" cellspacing="0" cellpadding="0" width="100%"> <tbody> <tr> <td> <table border="0" cellspacing="0" cellpadding="0"> <tbody> <tr> <td><br /></td> <td><br /></td> <td><br /></td> <td><br /></td> <td><br /></td> <td><br /></td> <td><br /></td> <td><br /></td> <td><br /></td> <td><br /></td> <td><br /></td> <td><br /></td> <td><br /></td> <td><br /></td> <td><br /></td> </tr> <tr> <td><br /></td> <td> <p>&nbsp;</p> </td> <td> <p>&nbsp;</p> </td> <td> <p>&nbsp;</p> </td> <td> <p>&nbsp;</p> </td> <td> <p>&nbsp;</p> </td> <td> <p>&nbsp;</p> </td> <td> <p>&nbsp;</p> </td> <td> <p>&nbsp;</p> </td> <td> <p>&nbsp;</p> </td> <td> <p>&nbsp;</p> </td> <td> <p>&nbsp;</p> </td> <td> <p>&nbsp;</p> </td> <td> <p>&nbsp;</p> </td> <td> <p>&nbsp;</p> </td> </tr> </tbody> </table> <p>&nbsp;</p> <table border="0" cellspacing="0" cellpadding="0"> <tbody> <tr> <td><br /></td> <td><br /></td> <td><br /></td> <td><br /></td> <td><br /></td> <td><br /></td> <td><br /></td> <td><br /></td> <td><br /></td> <td> <table title="Toggle Spell Checker" border="0" cellspacing="0" cellpadding="0"> <tbody> <tr> <td><br /></td> <td><br /></td> </tr> </tbody> </table> </td> <td><br /></td> </tr> </tbody> </table> </td> </tr> <tr> <td> <p>The ATLAS (<span style="text-decoration: underline;">A</span> <span style="text-decoration: underline;">T</span>oroidal <span style="text-decoration: underline;">L</span>HC <span style="text-decoration: underline;">A</span>pparatu<span style="text-decoration: underline;">S</span>)   experiment at LHC is poised to address some of the deepest questions in the   field of particle physics. The answers we will learn could change our view of   the universe. ATLAS discovered the Higgs (&ldquo;God&rdquo; particle) in 2012 which was   named by Science magazine as the 2012 &ldquo;Breakthrough of the Year&rdquo; and resulted   in the award of 2013 Nobel Physics Prize to the two theoretical physicists   who developed the Higgs theory in 1960s. The ATLAS collaboration consists   of ~3000 physicists from ~190 institutions of 38 countries all over the world.   About 500 physicists from ~45 US national labs and universities are currently   working on ATLAS. They are from 4 national labs (Argonne National Lab (ANL),   Brookhaven National Lab (BNL), Lawrence Berkeley National Lab (LBNL), and   Stanford Linear Accelerator Center (SLAC)), and many top research   universities (U. of Chicago, Columbia, Duke, Harvard, Michigan, MIT, UPenn,   Stanford, UT-Austin, Washington, Wisconsin, Yale, etc.).</p> <p>The CSU is the   largest university system in the country with 23 campuses and ~490,000   students, including very large minority and first-generation college student   populations. CSU Fresno joined ATLAS in 2007 as the only CSU campus on ATLAS   or CMS, and was the only CSU campus involved in the Higgs discovery. This was   also the first research a CSU campus was involved in which has resulted in a   Nobel Prize. To provide the outstanding ATLAS opportunity to a wider CSU   community, Gao (PI of this proposal) has been building up the CSU Nuclear and   Particle Physics Consortium (NUPAC) since 2008. CSU NUPAC is a consortium of   CSU campuses which provide support to their students who are interested in   particle physics and ATLAS.&nbsp; It now   consists of 19 campuses: Bakersfield, Channel Islands, Chico, Dominguez   Hills, East Bay, Fresno, Humboldt, Long Beach, Los Angeles, Northridge,   Pomona, Sacramento, San Bernardino, San Diego, San Francisco, San Luis   Obispo, San Marcos, Sonoma, and Stanislaus. CSU Fresno has been the center of   NUPAC.</p> <p>The CSU Fresno ATLAS group consists of one faculty   (Yongsheng Gao, PI), one postdoc (Harinder Bawa), three IT engineers (Jay   Fowler, Geoff King, and John Wagenleitner), one visiting Ph.D student from   China (Wei Ding from Tsinghua University who is supported by his home   institutions in China to work in Fresno with the CSU Fresno ATLAS group), 3   Master students (Jason Gruzdas, Anand Saggu, and Jennifer Tyler) and 2   undergraduate students (Will Barden and Gabriel Sotto). The group&rsquo;s   activities on ATLAS includes: new physics searches with dijet final states, ATLAS   MC validation, build first US ATLAS computing cluster on cloud to explore   cloud solution for ATLAS, education and outreach, etc.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> </td> </tr> <tr> <td> <p>The activities of the   CSU Fresno ATLAS group include: new physics searches with dijet final states,   developing first US ATLAS cloud cluster and first US ATLAS Shared Tier 3   facility on cloud for Run 3, coordinator of ATLAS MC Validation, Distributed   Analysis Support Team (DAST) shifts, ATLAS control room data quality shifts,   contribution to operation and monitoring of pixel detector, trigger, Phase II   pixel upgrade, etc. Since 2015, the members of CSU Fresno ATLAS group have   given a total of over 200&nbsp; presentations   at ATLAS WG meetings, contributed to 17 ATLAS Communication Notes, 6 ATLAS   Conference Notes and proceedings, and 6 ATLAS publications in searching for   new physics with dijet final states in PL, PRD, and PRL. In addition, members   of CSU Fresno ATLAS group have given 10 presentations at international and   national conferences.</p> <p>Every   fall and spring semester since 2015, the PI has been offering two online   courses across the NUPAC campuses to prepare new CSU students to work at   CERN. The CSU students worked on ATLAS research projects at CERN move on to   teaching, high-tech companies, and physics Ph.D programs (Brown, U. of   Colorado at Boulder, Purdue, UCB, UCD, UCLA, UCSD, UCSC, Indiana, Umass at   Lowell, USC, Purdue, Wisconsin, etc.). This is significantly higher than the   ~20% fraction of other physics majors from CSU campuses to enter into Ph.D   programs. When students worked at CERN, they also attended the famous CERN   Summer Student Lecture Series given by top physicists from all over the   world. The ATLAS working experience prepares CSU students for their personal   and professional success in an increasingly competitive, global, and   multi-cultural society.</p> </td> </tr> </tbody> </table> <br /></td> </tr> <tr> <td><br /></td> </tr> <tr> <td><br /></td> </tr> </tbody> </table><br> <p>            Last Modified: 08/09/2020<br>      Modified by: Yongsheng&nbsp;Gao</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[                                                                                                                                                                    The ATLAS (A Toroidal LHC ApparatuS)   experiment at LHC is poised to address some of the deepest questions in the   field of particle physics. The answers we will learn could change our view of   the universe. ATLAS discovered the Higgs ("God" particle) in 2012 which was   named by Science magazine as the 2012 "Breakthrough of the Year" and resulted   in the award of 2013 Nobel Physics Prize to the two theoretical physicists   who developed the Higgs theory in 1960s. The ATLAS collaboration consists   of ~3000 physicists from ~190 institutions of 38 countries all over the world.   About 500 physicists from ~45 US national labs and universities are currently   working on ATLAS. They are from 4 national labs (Argonne National Lab (ANL),   Brookhaven National Lab (BNL), Lawrence Berkeley National Lab (LBNL), and   Stanford Linear Accelerator Center (SLAC)), and many top research   universities (U. of Chicago, Columbia, Duke, Harvard, Michigan, MIT, UPenn,   Stanford, UT-Austin, Washington, Wisconsin, Yale, etc.).  The CSU is the   largest university system in the country with 23 campuses and ~490,000   students, including very large minority and first-generation college student   populations. CSU Fresno joined ATLAS in 2007 as the only CSU campus on ATLAS   or CMS, and was the only CSU campus involved in the Higgs discovery. This was   also the first research a CSU campus was involved in which has resulted in a   Nobel Prize. To provide the outstanding ATLAS opportunity to a wider CSU   community, Gao (PI of this proposal) has been building up the CSU Nuclear and   Particle Physics Consortium (NUPAC) since 2008. CSU NUPAC is a consortium of   CSU campuses which provide support to their students who are interested in   particle physics and ATLAS.  It now   consists of 19 campuses: Bakersfield, Channel Islands, Chico, Dominguez   Hills, East Bay, Fresno, Humboldt, Long Beach, Los Angeles, Northridge,   Pomona, Sacramento, San Bernardino, San Diego, San Francisco, San Luis   Obispo, San Marcos, Sonoma, and Stanislaus. CSU Fresno has been the center of   NUPAC.  The CSU Fresno ATLAS group consists of one faculty   (Yongsheng Gao, PI), one postdoc (Harinder Bawa), three IT engineers (Jay   Fowler, Geoff King, and John Wagenleitner), one visiting Ph.D student from   China (Wei Ding from Tsinghua University who is supported by his home   institutions in China to work in Fresno with the CSU Fresno ATLAS group), 3   Master students (Jason Gruzdas, Anand Saggu, and Jennifer Tyler) and 2   undergraduate students (Will Barden and Gabriel Sotto). The group’s   activities on ATLAS includes: new physics searches with dijet final states, ATLAS   MC validation, build first US ATLAS computing cluster on cloud to explore   cloud solution for ATLAS, education and outreach, etc.         The activities of the   CSU Fresno ATLAS group include: new physics searches with dijet final states,   developing first US ATLAS cloud cluster and first US ATLAS Shared Tier 3   facility on cloud for Run 3, coordinator of ATLAS MC Validation, Distributed   Analysis Support Team (DAST) shifts, ATLAS control room data quality shifts,   contribution to operation and monitoring of pixel detector, trigger, Phase II   pixel upgrade, etc. Since 2015, the members of CSU Fresno ATLAS group have   given a total of over 200  presentations   at ATLAS WG meetings, contributed to 17 ATLAS Communication Notes, 6 ATLAS   Conference Notes and proceedings, and 6 ATLAS publications in searching for   new physics with dijet final states in PL, PRD, and PRL. In addition, members   of CSU Fresno ATLAS group have given 10 presentations at international and   national conferences.  Every   fall and spring semester since 2015, the PI has been offering two online   courses across the NUPAC campuses to prepare new CSU students to work at   CERN. The CSU students worked on ATLAS research projects at CERN move on to   teaching, high-tech companies, and physics Ph.D programs (Brown, U. of   Colorado at Boulder, Purdue, UCB, UCD, UCLA, UCSD, UCSC, Indiana, Umass at   Lowell, USC, Purdue, Wisconsin, etc.). This is significantly higher than the   ~20% fraction of other physics majors from CSU campuses to enter into Ph.D   programs. When students worked at CERN, they also attended the famous CERN   Summer Student Lecture Series given by top physicists from all over the   world. The ATLAS working experience prepares CSU students for their personal   and professional success in an increasingly competitive, global, and   multi-cultural society.                        Last Modified: 08/09/2020       Submitted by: Yongsheng Gao]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
