<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>CDS&amp;E/Collaborative Research: Fundamental Investigation of Zinc-Coating of Advanced High Strength Steels Directed by Multiscale Modeling and Experiments</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2015</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>307622.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>307622</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CMMI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Civil, Mechanical, &amp; Manufact Inn</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Joanne Culbertson</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>jculbert@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924602</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>New-generation advanced high strength steels need to be coated with a thin layer of zinc that provides corrosion protection to the substrate. Thus, zinc coating is a critical component that enables steels to maintain structural integrity for prolonged service times. Prediction and control of the coating process requires better understanding of interfacial reactions between zinc and steel substrate, which are very complex. This Computational and Data-Enabled Science and Engineering (CDS&amp;E) collaborative research award supports fundamental research that combines cutting-edge experimental techniques and multi-scale computer simulations to study the interfacial microstructures that develop during coating. The outcomes of this research will provide guidelines for improved coating of advanced high strength steel sheets which enable production of lighter and safer vehicles, and ultimately contribute to reducing emissions of green-house gases. This project also provides an opportunity to educate engineering students with cross-discipline computational and experimental skills.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The zinc-steel interfacial structures determine the success or failure of forming, welding, and corrosion protection capabilities of advanced high strength steels. There is a lack of fundamental knowledge regarding the process-microstructure-property relationships in zinc-coated steels produced by galvanizing and galvannealing, due to the fact that complex metallurgical reactions occur in a region less than 100 nanometers. The research team will utilize focused ion beam to prepare specimens for transmission electron microscopy analyses to resolve complicated, fine-scale interfacial microstructures and to reveal the chemistry of the interfacial entities. The data will be used to calibrate and validate cross-length scale models, spanning from the electronic to mesoscale. Density functional theory calculations will be performed to determine structures and properties of oxides and intermetallics. The obtained data will be used to develop multicomponent interatomic potentials based on the modified embedded-atom method. These potentials will be employed in large-scale atomistic simulations to determine energetics data for the formation of oxides and intermetallics. The experimental and atomistic modeling data will be fed to unprecedented multicomponent, multi-phase field models to simulate formation and evolution of microstructures of internal/external oxidation, inhibition layer, and intermetallics. The iterations between experiments and models will provide a unique approach to facilitate the discovery of new coating processes for advanced high strength steels.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/14/2015</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/14/2015</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1506944</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Bin</FirstName>
<LastName>Li</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Bin Li</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>binl@unr.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>7757844507</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000683207</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/14/2015</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Board of Regents, NSHE, obo University of Nevada, Reno</Name>
<CityName>Reno</CityName>
<ZipCode>895570001</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>7757844040</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1664 North Virginia Street</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[Sponsored Projects / MS 325]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Nevada</StateName>
<StateCode>NV</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NV02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>146515460</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>NEVADA SYSTEM OF HIGHER EDUCATION</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>067808063</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Board of Regents, NSHE, obo University of Nevada, Reno]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>NV</StateCode>
<ZipCode>895570001</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Nevada</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NV02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1765</Code>
<Text>CONDENSED MATTER &amp; MAT THEORY</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>8084</Code>
<Text>CDS&amp;E</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1765</Code>
<Text>CONDENSED MATTER &amp; MAT THEORY</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7433</Code>
<Text>CyberInfra Frmwrk 21st (CIF21)</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8084</Code>
<Text>CDS&amp;E</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0115</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2015~307622</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Auto-graded steel sheets need to be galvanized or coated with a thin layer of Zn with a thickness about 10 microns. Hot-dip galvanizing of steels is the most common and economical industrial processing. The Zn coating provides barrier and galvanic protection of the steel substrate and thus improves corrosion resistance of steels. During galvanizing, complex metallurgical reactions take place at the interface (~100 nm) between the steel substrate and the liquid Zn, including formation of an inhibition layer which is a crucial intermetallic phase preventing formation of brittle Fe-Zn crystals. In order to lightweight vehicles, improve fuel efficiency and reduce green-house gas emissions, steelmakers are developing new generation advanced high strength steels (AHSSs) automotive applications. These AHSSs have higher concentrations of Mn and Si that are important alloying elements for higher strengths. However, selective oxidation of Mn and Si during heat treating before galvanizing causes concerns to the galvanizability of new AHSSs.</p> <p>This NSF awarded project characterize interfacial structures of galvanized high strength steels using experimental techniques and calculate the surface and interfacial energies of complex phases that are present at the interface between the Zn coating and the steel substrate using atomistic simulations and first principles calculations. Specifically, a multi-component modified embedded atom method (MEAM) potentials for Fe-Al-Mn-Zn-Si-C-O developed by one of the collaborative teams are used to compute the surface and interface energetics. The data obtained from this research is used for developing phase field modeling of galvanizing processes.</p> <p>Site-specific experiments have been carried out to characterize the interface of a galvanized dual-phase (DP) steel with a 0.2 <em>wt</em>% Al bath concentration. Focused ion beam (FIB) was used to prepare specimens in the interface region between the coating and the substrate. Transmission electron microscopy (TEM), scanning TEM (STEM), and high resolution TEM (HRTEM) have been performed to resolve the phases and the structures at the interface between the Zn coating and the steel substrate. The results showed that a continuous MnO film with a thickness of ~20 nm was present on the surface of the substrate while no Si oxides were resolved. Internal oxide particles were observed as well in the sub-surface region. Despite the presence of the continuous oxide film, a well-developed inhibition layer was observed right on top of the oxide film. The inhibition layer has a thickness of ~100 nm (Materials Characterization 120(2016)63-68). In stark contrast, when the Al bath concentration is reduced to 0.125 <em>wt</em>%, the surface MnO oxide was lifted off the surface of the substrate and subsequently entrapped in the Zn-Fe phase during galvanizing. A discontinuous inhibition layer was formed directly on top of the substrate. In regions where the inhibition layer was absent, Zn-Fe crystals grew directly on top of the substrate (Met Mater Trans A 50(2019)3748-3757). These outcomes provide valuable information to steel manufacturing processes.</p> <p>Extensive atomistic simulations and first principles calculations have been conducted to compute the surface and interface energetics between an Fe substrate and the inhibition layer. The results from the MEAM potential for Fe-Al show that Fe<sub>3</sub>Al<sub>8</sub> is the stable crystal structure rather than Fe<sub>2</sub>Al<sub>5</sub>, yet Fe<sub>2</sub>Al<sub>5</sub> has long been considered the stable phase of the inhibition layer. First principles calculations show that indeed, Fe<sub>3</sub>Al<sub>8</sub> has a lower ground state energy than Fe<sub>2</sub>Al<sub>5</sub>. Thus, most likely, Fe<sub>3</sub>Al<sub>8</sub> should be the stable phase for the inhibition layer. Interfacial energetics calculations by using MEAM show that the low energy configurations of the Fe-Fe<sub>3</sub>Al<sub>8</sub> interfaces have negative interfacial energies. This important outcome well explains why during galvanizing, formation of the inhibition layer occurs very rapidly. The energetics is very sensitive to the atomic configuration of the surfaces and interfaces and the lowest energy configurations have been determined (Figure_1). The multi-component MEAM potential can be applied to a wide variety of fundamental research including various metallic and/or non-metallic materials systems.</p> <p>Multiple graduate and undergraduate students have been supported or involved in this project which has been crucial for the development of computational materials science program at University of Nevada, Reno.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 12/01/2019<br>      Modified by: Bin&nbsp;Li</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Image         </div> <div class="galControls onePhoto" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation onePhoto" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1506944/1506944_10387888_1575177185335_Outcomes_Figure_3--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1506944/1506944_10387888_1575177185335_Outcomes_Figure_3--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Fe_Fe3Al8"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1506944/1506944_10387888_1575177185335_Outcomes_Figure_3--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Fe_Fe3Al8"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">The interfacial structure between Fe and Fe3Al8 obtained from atomistic simulations using the developed MEAM potential.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Kefan Chen</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Bin&nbsp;Li</div> <div class="imageTitle">Fe_Fe3Al8</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Auto-graded steel sheets need to be galvanized or coated with a thin layer of Zn with a thickness about 10 microns. Hot-dip galvanizing of steels is the most common and economical industrial processing. The Zn coating provides barrier and galvanic protection of the steel substrate and thus improves corrosion resistance of steels. During galvanizing, complex metallurgical reactions take place at the interface (~100 nm) between the steel substrate and the liquid Zn, including formation of an inhibition layer which is a crucial intermetallic phase preventing formation of brittle Fe-Zn crystals. In order to lightweight vehicles, improve fuel efficiency and reduce green-house gas emissions, steelmakers are developing new generation advanced high strength steels (AHSSs) automotive applications. These AHSSs have higher concentrations of Mn and Si that are important alloying elements for higher strengths. However, selective oxidation of Mn and Si during heat treating before galvanizing causes concerns to the galvanizability of new AHSSs.  This NSF awarded project characterize interfacial structures of galvanized high strength steels using experimental techniques and calculate the surface and interfacial energies of complex phases that are present at the interface between the Zn coating and the steel substrate using atomistic simulations and first principles calculations. Specifically, a multi-component modified embedded atom method (MEAM) potentials for Fe-Al-Mn-Zn-Si-C-O developed by one of the collaborative teams are used to compute the surface and interface energetics. The data obtained from this research is used for developing phase field modeling of galvanizing processes.  Site-specific experiments have been carried out to characterize the interface of a galvanized dual-phase (DP) steel with a 0.2 wt% Al bath concentration. Focused ion beam (FIB) was used to prepare specimens in the interface region between the coating and the substrate. Transmission electron microscopy (TEM), scanning TEM (STEM), and high resolution TEM (HRTEM) have been performed to resolve the phases and the structures at the interface between the Zn coating and the steel substrate. The results showed that a continuous MnO film with a thickness of ~20 nm was present on the surface of the substrate while no Si oxides were resolved. Internal oxide particles were observed as well in the sub-surface region. Despite the presence of the continuous oxide film, a well-developed inhibition layer was observed right on top of the oxide film. The inhibition layer has a thickness of ~100 nm (Materials Characterization 120(2016)63-68). In stark contrast, when the Al bath concentration is reduced to 0.125 wt%, the surface MnO oxide was lifted off the surface of the substrate and subsequently entrapped in the Zn-Fe phase during galvanizing. A discontinuous inhibition layer was formed directly on top of the substrate. In regions where the inhibition layer was absent, Zn-Fe crystals grew directly on top of the substrate (Met Mater Trans A 50(2019)3748-3757). These outcomes provide valuable information to steel manufacturing processes.  Extensive atomistic simulations and first principles calculations have been conducted to compute the surface and interface energetics between an Fe substrate and the inhibition layer. The results from the MEAM potential for Fe-Al show that Fe3Al8 is the stable crystal structure rather than Fe2Al5, yet Fe2Al5 has long been considered the stable phase of the inhibition layer. First principles calculations show that indeed, Fe3Al8 has a lower ground state energy than Fe2Al5. Thus, most likely, Fe3Al8 should be the stable phase for the inhibition layer. Interfacial energetics calculations by using MEAM show that the low energy configurations of the Fe-Fe3Al8 interfaces have negative interfacial energies. This important outcome well explains why during galvanizing, formation of the inhibition layer occurs very rapidly. The energetics is very sensitive to the atomic configuration of the surfaces and interfaces and the lowest energy configurations have been determined (Figure_1). The multi-component MEAM potential can be applied to a wide variety of fundamental research including various metallic and/or non-metallic materials systems.  Multiple graduate and undergraduate students have been supported or involved in this project which has been crucial for the development of computational materials science program at University of Nevada, Reno.          Last Modified: 12/01/2019       Submitted by: Bin Li]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
