<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Equation of State for Hydrodynamic Compression in Turbulent Z-Pinch</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2015</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2020</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>285000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>285000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03010000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>PHY</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Physics</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Vyacheslav (Slava) Lukin</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>vlukin@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927382</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This project investigates the speculative possibility of storing energy in turbulent fluid eddies, and then suddenly releasing this energy. When gas is compressed, its temperature increases. However, the increase in temperature might be less if there are other degrees of freedom that absorb the energy.  Suppose, for example, that the gas energy resides mainly in whirling eddies, rather than in completely random motion. We ask the question whether there are conditions under which compression of the gas might increase this eddy energy. The significance of this question is that energy in eddies acts differently than random energy because neighboring molecules tend to move in the same direction. That means that there would be fewer times that gas molecules would make high-impact head-on collisions.  Important processes such as nuclear fusion depend on this relative motion, so the fusion reactions would be fewer in gases where the energy resides in whirling eddies rather than in random thermal motion. If this were true, then one might also speculate that the effect could be used advantageously in controlling nuclear fusion in a highly compressed plasma.  &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project investigates the possibility of storing and then suddenly releasing the energy that can be deposited into turbulent fluid eddies in a plasma. It is conjectured that, under compression on a time scale in which viscosity may be neglected, the energy in such eddies might increase. Also, if the energy resides in hydrodynamic eddies rather than ion temperature, it means that it is unavailable to electrons through collisions. Thus, this energy cannot be easily captured by electrons and radiated. If the compression increases eddy energy more than the random energy, a new paradigm for storing energy in a highly compressed plasma might be advanced in which the energy content is increased under compression in a non-radiating plasma, and then suddenly released under viscous dissipation. To test these speculations, particle-in-cell simulations will be performed to describe compressing turbulent eddies, with guidance obtained from Z-pinch experiments that already appear to exhibit certain features of a turbulent inviscid plasma.  This work will involve a collaboration between Princeton University and the Weizmann Institute of Science in Israel, and will be performed under the umbrella of the Memorandum of Understanding on Research Cooperation between NSF and the US-Israel Binational Science Foundation. This project is co-sponsored by the NSF's Physics Division and the Office of International Science and Engineering.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/22/2015</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/12/2017</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1506122</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Nathaniel</FirstName>
<LastName>Fisch</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>J</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Nathaniel J Fisch</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>fisch@princeton.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6092432643</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000187031</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/22/2015</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Princeton University</Name>
<CityName>Princeton</CityName>
<ZipCode>085442020</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6092583090</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>Off. of Research &amp; Proj. Admin.</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[P.O. Box 36]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New Jersey</StateName>
<StateCode>NJ</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>12</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NJ12</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>002484665</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>TRUSTEES OF PRINCETON UNIVERSITY, THE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>002484665</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Princeton University]]></Name>
<CityName>Princeton</CityName>
<StateCode>NJ</StateCode>
<ZipCode>085442020</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[4 Ivy Lane, Peyton Hall]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New Jersey</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>12</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NJ12</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1242</Code>
<Text>PLASMA PHYSICS</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7298</Code>
<Text>International Research Collab</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1062</Code>
<Text>BASIC PLASMA SCIENCE &amp; ENGINEERING</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>5905</Code>
<Text>ISRAEL</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0115</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0116</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0117</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2015~95000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2016~95000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2017~95000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><strong>Major goals of the project</strong></p> <p>This project investigates the speculative possibility of storing energy in turbulent fluid eddies of plasma, and then suddenly releasing this energy. It is speculated that, under compression on a time scale in which viscosity may be neglected, the energy in those eddies might increase. &nbsp;An important aspect of this project is to explain experiments on the Weizmann Z-pinch, where very fine measurements&nbsp; of turbulent kinetic energy were obtained as well as the compression of turbulent eddies.&nbsp; In fact, the very curious Weizmann data provided the motivation for this work. &nbsp;&nbsp;The&nbsp;main scientific goal of the work is now to advance our understanding of a fundamental question &nbsp;-- namely what is the effective equation of state for compression of turbulent medium, where most of the energy is contained in the turbulent kinetic energy. &nbsp;It is an effective equation of state, because really there are no state functions, except that fundamental questions such as compressibility and stored energy still need to be answered on relevant time scales. There are a number of applications to various fields. &nbsp;Important processes, such as nuclear fusion depend on the relative motion of ions, so the fusion reactions would be fewer in plasma where the energy resides in whirling eddies rather than in random thermal motion. Also, the residing of energy in hydrodynamic eddies rather than ion temperature means that it is unavailable to electrons through collisions. Thus, this energy cannot be easily captured by electrons and radiated.&nbsp; Thus, if compression might increase eddy energy more than random energy, a new paradigm for attaining nuclear fusion in highly compressed plasma might be advanced, in which the energy content is increased under compression in non-fusing non-radiating plasma, and then suddenly released under viscous dissipation. &nbsp;In the process of invesigating tubulent compression in Z-pinch plasma, many other aspects of magnetized and compressing plasma are uncovered as well.</p> <p><strong>Project Outcomes in the Last Year</strong></p> <p>During the Year 09/01/2019?08/31/2020, there were several research outcomes. There were four papers acknowledging NSF funding published in that timeframe [1-4] and two that were submitted but published just after that timeframe [5-6].&nbsp;&nbsp; One of the highlights was the collaboration with the Weizmann group [2], explaining the curious, but very carefully measured, phenomena of the expansion of current channel in a Z-pinch plasma even as the plasma is compressed.&nbsp; The explanation lay not in any resistive diffusion effects, but rather in the careful derivation that respects conservation of magnetic flux, not current, in advecting through non-metric compression conducting plasma. This joint work with the Weizmann group was published as an Editor?s Pick in Physics of Plasmas.&nbsp; Another highlight was our identification of a new heat pump effect in magnetized plasma with an external potential field such as gravity [4].&nbsp; We use gravity as a proxy for the centrifugal forces that occur in magnetized plasma under&nbsp; E x B rotation.&nbsp; The effect identified here occurs in a multi-species magnetized plasma because of the incompressibility of the charge density, even as the number density is compressibile.&nbsp; Thus, when a few high ion charge state ions exchange places via collisions with low ion charge state ions, they are inserted into a larger volume and so are expansion cooled as the the low ion charge state ions are heated under compression.&nbsp; This is a magnetized plasma counterpart to the piezothermal effect in a neutral gas [390].&nbsp; Yet a further highlight is the role that dimensionality plays on turbulent compression, which relates directly to to the equation of state of two-dimensional hydrodynamic compression in a turbulent Z-pinch [6].&nbsp; The archival publications below [1-6] credit our NSF funding, and serve towards the Ph.D. dissertations of graduate students Ian Ochs, Elijah Kolmes, and Mikhail Mlodik.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>1. R. Gueroult, J. M.~Rax,&nbsp; and N. J. Fisch, <em>A necessary condition for perpendicular electric field control in magnetized plasmas,</em> Physics of Plasmas <strong>26</strong>, 122106&nbsp; (December, 2019).</p> <p>2. I. E. Ochs, C. Stollberg,&nbsp; E. Kroupp, Y. Maron,&nbsp; A. Fruchtman, E. J. Kolmes, M. E. Mlodik and N. J. Fisch, <em>Current channel evolution in ideal Z pinch for general velocity profiles</em>, Physics of Plasmas <strong>26</strong>, 122706 (December, 2019).&nbsp;&nbsp; <strong>Editor's Pick.</strong></p> <p>3. E. J. Kolmes, I. E. Ochs, M. E. Mlodik, and N. J. Fisch, <em>Maximum-Entropy States for Magnetized Ion Transport</em>, Physics Letters A&nbsp; <strong>384</strong>, 126262&nbsp; (May, 2020).</p> <p>4. M. E. Mlodik, E. J. Kolmes, I. E. Ochs, and N. J. Fisch, <em>Heat pump via charge incompressibility &nbsp; in a collisional magnetized multi-ion plasma</em>, Phys. Rev. E <strong>102</strong>, 013212&nbsp; (July, 2020).</p> <p>5. E. J. Kolmes, V. I. Geyko, and N. J. Fisch, <em>Fluid Model for the Piezothermal Effect</em>, Physics Letters A <strong>384</strong>, 126700 (September, 2020).</p> <p>6. S. Davidovits and N. J. Fisch, <em>Preferential turbulence enhancement in two-dimensional  compressions</em>, Physical Review E <strong>102</strong>, 053213&nbsp; (November, 2020).</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 05/13/2021<br>      Modified by: Nathaniel&nbsp;J&nbsp;Fisch</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Major goals of the project  This project investigates the speculative possibility of storing energy in turbulent fluid eddies of plasma, and then suddenly releasing this energy. It is speculated that, under compression on a time scale in which viscosity may be neglected, the energy in those eddies might increase.  An important aspect of this project is to explain experiments on the Weizmann Z-pinch, where very fine measurements  of turbulent kinetic energy were obtained as well as the compression of turbulent eddies.  In fact, the very curious Weizmann data provided the motivation for this work.   The main scientific goal of the work is now to advance our understanding of a fundamental question  -- namely what is the effective equation of state for compression of turbulent medium, where most of the energy is contained in the turbulent kinetic energy.  It is an effective equation of state, because really there are no state functions, except that fundamental questions such as compressibility and stored energy still need to be answered on relevant time scales. There are a number of applications to various fields.  Important processes, such as nuclear fusion depend on the relative motion of ions, so the fusion reactions would be fewer in plasma where the energy resides in whirling eddies rather than in random thermal motion. Also, the residing of energy in hydrodynamic eddies rather than ion temperature means that it is unavailable to electrons through collisions. Thus, this energy cannot be easily captured by electrons and radiated.  Thus, if compression might increase eddy energy more than random energy, a new paradigm for attaining nuclear fusion in highly compressed plasma might be advanced, in which the energy content is increased under compression in non-fusing non-radiating plasma, and then suddenly released under viscous dissipation.  In the process of invesigating tubulent compression in Z-pinch plasma, many other aspects of magnetized and compressing plasma are uncovered as well.  Project Outcomes in the Last Year  During the Year 09/01/2019?08/31/2020, there were several research outcomes. There were four papers acknowledging NSF funding published in that timeframe [1-4] and two that were submitted but published just after that timeframe [5-6].   One of the highlights was the collaboration with the Weizmann group [2], explaining the curious, but very carefully measured, phenomena of the expansion of current channel in a Z-pinch plasma even as the plasma is compressed.  The explanation lay not in any resistive diffusion effects, but rather in the careful derivation that respects conservation of magnetic flux, not current, in advecting through non-metric compression conducting plasma. This joint work with the Weizmann group was published as an Editor?s Pick in Physics of Plasmas.  Another highlight was our identification of a new heat pump effect in magnetized plasma with an external potential field such as gravity [4].  We use gravity as a proxy for the centrifugal forces that occur in magnetized plasma under  E x B rotation.  The effect identified here occurs in a multi-species magnetized plasma because of the incompressibility of the charge density, even as the number density is compressibile.  Thus, when a few high ion charge state ions exchange places via collisions with low ion charge state ions, they are inserted into a larger volume and so are expansion cooled as the the low ion charge state ions are heated under compression.  This is a magnetized plasma counterpart to the piezothermal effect in a neutral gas [390].  Yet a further highlight is the role that dimensionality plays on turbulent compression, which relates directly to to the equation of state of two-dimensional hydrodynamic compression in a turbulent Z-pinch [6].  The archival publications below [1-6] credit our NSF funding, and serve towards the Ph.D. dissertations of graduate students Ian Ochs, Elijah Kolmes, and Mikhail Mlodik.     1. R. Gueroult, J. M.~Rax,  and N. J. Fisch, A necessary condition for perpendicular electric field control in magnetized plasmas, Physics of Plasmas 26, 122106  (December, 2019).  2. I. E. Ochs, C. Stollberg,  E. Kroupp, Y. Maron,  A. Fruchtman, E. J. Kolmes, M. E. Mlodik and N. J. Fisch, Current channel evolution in ideal Z pinch for general velocity profiles, Physics of Plasmas 26, 122706 (December, 2019).   Editor's Pick.  3. E. J. Kolmes, I. E. Ochs, M. E. Mlodik, and N. J. Fisch, Maximum-Entropy States for Magnetized Ion Transport, Physics Letters A  384, 126262  (May, 2020).  4. M. E. Mlodik, E. J. Kolmes, I. E. Ochs, and N. J. Fisch, Heat pump via charge incompressibility   in a collisional magnetized multi-ion plasma, Phys. Rev. E 102, 013212  (July, 2020).  5. E. J. Kolmes, V. I. Geyko, and N. J. Fisch, Fluid Model for the Piezothermal Effect, Physics Letters A 384, 126700 (September, 2020).  6. S. Davidovits and N. J. Fisch, Preferential turbulence enhancement in two-dimensional  compressions, Physical Review E 102, 053213  (November, 2020).             Last Modified: 05/13/2021       Submitted by: Nathaniel J Fisch]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
