<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Explorations in Early Universe Cosmology and Dark Matter</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/15/2015</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>180000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>180000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03010000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>PHY</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Physics</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Keith Dienes</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>kdienes@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032925314</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This award funds the research activities of Professor Daniel Boyanovsky at the Department of Physics, University of Pittsburgh. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Our understanding of the early and present Universe has been revolutionized by observations of the Cosmic Microwave Background and galaxies, supporting the main paradigm  of inflationary cosmology:  quantum-mechanical fluctuations of primordial origin seed the formation of galaxies.  These observations, along with the discovery of the Higgs Boson and the experimental confirmation of the theory of strong and electroweak interactions, confirm the Standard Models of Cosmology and Particle Physics.  Along with these discoveries new challenging aspects emerge:  95% of the energy density in the Universe is in the form of Dark Matter and Dark Energy.  Furthermore, neutrinos, the most elusive particles in nature, are found to be massive and undergo mixing and oscillations among the different types --- a phenomenon beyond the Standard Model. These discoveries bring an unprecedented convergence of particle physics, astrophysics, and cosmology in which observations of galaxies along with accelerator and reactor experiments will yield insights beyond the Standard Models, with the tantalizing possibility that a new species of neutrinos may explain Dark Matter.  Professor Boyanovsky's research program seeks a fundamental understanding on two fronts:  (i) the production and properties of a new species of neutrinos as possible Dark-Matter candidates, and (ii) a firmer assessment of the quantum fluctuations generated in the primordial Universe that ultimately seed the formation of galaxies. The program is at the forefront of particle astrophysics and cosmology, complements robust experimental and observational efforts, and is truly interdisciplinary as it implements methods from other fields in physics. Research in these areas thus advances the national interest by promoting the progress of science in one of the most fundamental and stimulating endeavors of deep intellectual merit:   the discovery of novel phenomena and the understanding of the evolution of our Universe and the origin of galaxies beginning from the smallest constituents.  Through this cross-fertilization of concepts and methods, this research program also provides students with a broader perspective and unique opportunity to acquire a truly interdisciplinary educational experience. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Specifically, Professor Boyanovsky will study mechanisms for production, evolution, and gravitational clustering of new species of neutrinos during the early stages of the Early Universe by implementing methods from out-of-equilibrium quantum field theory and from quantum kinetics. These powerful methods will allow a systematic assessment of the new species of neutrinos as a Dark-Matter candidate. In cosmology, the program will focus on a deeper understanding of quantum processes and correlations during the inflationary stage in the early Universe. In particular, Professor Boyanovsky will study modifications of the spectrum of fluctuations from interactions and pre- and post-inflationary dynamics and their potential for detection with forthcoming observations.  The study of processes during the period of rapid inflationary expansion requires novel tools.  New methods based on concepts borrowed from quantum optics, such as quantum master equations, and out-of-equilibrium effective field theory, will provide a deeper and more fundamental assessment of possible observational consequences.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/18/2015</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/18/2015</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1506912</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Daniel</FirstName>
<LastName>Boyanovsky</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Daniel Boyanovsky</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>boyan@pitt.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>4126249037</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000441737</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/18/2015</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Pittsburgh</Name>
<CityName>Pittsburgh</CityName>
<ZipCode>152133203</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>4126247400</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>300 Murdoch Building</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[3420 Forbes Avenue]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Pennsylvania</StateName>
<StateCode>PA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>18</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>PA18</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>004514360</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF PITTSBURGH, THE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>004514360</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Pittsburgh]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>PA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>152132303</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Pennsylvania</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>18</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>PA18</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1288</Code>
<Text>Particle Astrophysics &amp; Cosmol</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7483</Code>
<Text>PHYSICS OF THE UNIVERSE</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0115</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2015~180000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The main questions at the forefront of current physics and astronomy concern the nature and evolution of the Universe that we observe. The last two decades provided strong evidence that more than 80% of the energy-matter in the Universe is unknown--dark energy and dark matter. Furthermore, satellite observations of the radiation left over from the Big Bang, confirm a main paradigm in modern cosmology: that the Universe that we see today was born out of small quantum mechanical fluctuations that were amplified during an early period of rapid expansion. Our program seeks a fundamental understanding of these phenomena and complement robust observational and experimental efforts. Our goal is to implement concepts and methods from various branches in physics to provide a new theoretical framework to study the origin and evolution of the Universe, along with possible particles that could provide an explanation for dark matter. Our research program is truly interdisciplinary with connections to fascinating aspects of quantum information.&nbsp; There are two main outcomes of this research program, i) the results of the research program, ii) the educational component. The outcomes of&nbsp; the research program are summarized by&nbsp; novel and systematic frameworks to study the fundamental aspects of the very early Universe, during a rapid period of expansion that determines the fate of the observable Universe.&nbsp; We have shown how different processes contribute to the signals that result from this era and how they could be identified in forthcoming observations. We have also introduced a novel formulation that allows to understand from first principles the production and evolution of possible dark matter candidates and the properties that make them suitable seeds for the formation of galaxies. We recognized important similarities between some of these research avenues and timely aspects of quantum computing with novel architectures. We adapted many of the results obtained within the realm of cosmology and particle physics to study how information can be maintained, or lost, in new platforms for quantum computing. Therefore the research outcomes have been truly interdisciplinary with a much broader impact across different areas. In education: several students participated in the research program providing them with an opportunity for interdisciplinary study and research. The main goal in the educational component is to nourish the intellect of the bright students, provide them with an enriching and fulfilling educational experience and steering them into becoming critical thinkers. We are proud to report on the outcome of this educational endeavor: students that participated in our program have moved on to fulifilling careers, mostly outside academia. They are becoming very productive members of our society and contributing to its future. The interdisciplinary aspects of the research program motivated them to pursue ideas and interests beyond those of the research areas, they acquired more than just specific skills but also developed a broader view of science and its impact in our society. They also acquired self-confidence and a work ethos of the highest standards.</p> <p>The intellectual merit of both parts of our program, the research and the educational components are clear. The public at large is fascinated with the question of how the Universe came into being,&nbsp; how galaxies formed what are the mysterious dark matter and dark energy that make up over 80% of the Universe and whose origin is still unkown. These overarching questions are precisely the motivations and intellectual stimulus that fuel our program. Our challenge as educators is to channel&nbsp; the intellectual drive of bright and motivated students to shape and form them in the mold of the greatest thinkers. We take pride in providing students an enriching educational experience, giving them tools but above and beyond this, challenging them into deeper and more critical thinking. These objectives are, undoubtedly, of great intellectual merit, since these students will be the future thinkers whose will power and training will ensure the success of our society. The program is of broad appeal and has produced results broadly across fields. The methods developed and applied to various different situations have had broad interdisciplinary impact. Finally, the educational component has the broadest reach, transcending the particular research field, because the students that participated in this program have benefited directly, becoming professionals that are ready to contribute to the future of our society.&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 08/01/2018<br>      Modified by: Daniel&nbsp;Boyanovsky</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The main questions at the forefront of current physics and astronomy concern the nature and evolution of the Universe that we observe. The last two decades provided strong evidence that more than 80% of the energy-matter in the Universe is unknown--dark energy and dark matter. Furthermore, satellite observations of the radiation left over from the Big Bang, confirm a main paradigm in modern cosmology: that the Universe that we see today was born out of small quantum mechanical fluctuations that were amplified during an early period of rapid expansion. Our program seeks a fundamental understanding of these phenomena and complement robust observational and experimental efforts. Our goal is to implement concepts and methods from various branches in physics to provide a new theoretical framework to study the origin and evolution of the Universe, along with possible particles that could provide an explanation for dark matter. Our research program is truly interdisciplinary with connections to fascinating aspects of quantum information.  There are two main outcomes of this research program, i) the results of the research program, ii) the educational component. The outcomes of  the research program are summarized by  novel and systematic frameworks to study the fundamental aspects of the very early Universe, during a rapid period of expansion that determines the fate of the observable Universe.  We have shown how different processes contribute to the signals that result from this era and how they could be identified in forthcoming observations. We have also introduced a novel formulation that allows to understand from first principles the production and evolution of possible dark matter candidates and the properties that make them suitable seeds for the formation of galaxies. We recognized important similarities between some of these research avenues and timely aspects of quantum computing with novel architectures. We adapted many of the results obtained within the realm of cosmology and particle physics to study how information can be maintained, or lost, in new platforms for quantum computing. Therefore the research outcomes have been truly interdisciplinary with a much broader impact across different areas. In education: several students participated in the research program providing them with an opportunity for interdisciplinary study and research. The main goal in the educational component is to nourish the intellect of the bright students, provide them with an enriching and fulfilling educational experience and steering them into becoming critical thinkers. We are proud to report on the outcome of this educational endeavor: students that participated in our program have moved on to fulifilling careers, mostly outside academia. They are becoming very productive members of our society and contributing to its future. The interdisciplinary aspects of the research program motivated them to pursue ideas and interests beyond those of the research areas, they acquired more than just specific skills but also developed a broader view of science and its impact in our society. They also acquired self-confidence and a work ethos of the highest standards.  The intellectual merit of both parts of our program, the research and the educational components are clear. The public at large is fascinated with the question of how the Universe came into being,  how galaxies formed what are the mysterious dark matter and dark energy that make up over 80% of the Universe and whose origin is still unkown. These overarching questions are precisely the motivations and intellectual stimulus that fuel our program. Our challenge as educators is to channel  the intellectual drive of bright and motivated students to shape and form them in the mold of the greatest thinkers. We take pride in providing students an enriching educational experience, giving them tools but above and beyond this, challenging them into deeper and more critical thinking. These objectives are, undoubtedly, of great intellectual merit, since these students will be the future thinkers whose will power and training will ensure the success of our society. The program is of broad appeal and has produced results broadly across fields. The methods developed and applied to various different situations have had broad interdisciplinary impact. Finally, the educational component has the broadest reach, transcending the particular research field, because the students that participated in this program have benefited directly, becoming professionals that are ready to contribute to the future of our society.        Last Modified: 08/01/2018       Submitted by: Daniel Boyanovsky]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
