<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Global Harmonic Analysis</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2015</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>346138.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>346138</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DMS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Christopher Stark</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>cstark@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924869</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The PI shall prove rigorous results about the relations between classical and quantum mechanics. Schrodinger introduced quantum mechanics in 1927 to solve the puzzle of how an electron can be moving and stationary at the same time. His answer was that a quantum particle with a definite energy can only exist in a stationary state, the physics word for an eigenfunction of the Schrodinger operator governing the physics. The problem is that eigenfunctions are very hard to visualize and understand. Global Harmonic Analysis is about making rigorous relations between these eigenfunctions and the classical mechanics underlying the physical system. The projects in the proposal address two opposite kinds of questions: (i) how large can the eigenfunction be, and how are the points where it is large distributed? These are the points where it is  most probable to find the particle. (ii) How are the points where the eigenfunction is zero distributed? These are the  points where it is least likely to find the particle. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Global Harmonic Analysis is the use of the long-time dynamics of the geodesic flow of a Riemannian manifold to understand the high-frequency asymptotics of eigenfunctions. Two of the most important problems are (1) to analyze Lp norms of eigenfunctions and (2) to analyze nodal sets and critical point sets. For large p, Sogge and the PI have shown that the universal Lp bounds are only obtained if there exists a self-focal point x where a positive measure of geodesics from x loop back to x. In recent work, The PI showed that if the metric is real analytic, then all geodesics loop back and the first return map preserves a finite measure on the unit tangent space at x in the class of Lebesgue measure. In two dimensions, it follows that all geodesics through x are smoothly closed. One project is to generalize the last result to higher dimensions and smooth metrics. It is also very interesting to study low Lp norms and we are working with the Kakeya-Nikodym maximal function to do that. Regarding nodal and critical point sets, J. Jung and the PI have recently shown that the number of nodal domains of Neumann or Dirichlet eigenfunctions on non-positively curved surfaces with non-empty concave boundary must tend to infinity with the eigenvalue. It was also showed that the eigenfunctions have many critical points. In future work, the PI shall prove a more quantitative result and to study the higher dimensional case. The PI is also using holomorphic extensions of eigenfunction in the real analytic case to gain more control over nodal and critical point sets.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>05/20/2015</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/14/2017</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1506591</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Steve</FirstName>
<LastName>Zelditch</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Steve Zelditch</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>zelditch@math.northwestern.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>4438382046</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000467690</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/20/2015</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Northwestern University</Name>
<CityName>Chicago</CityName>
<ZipCode>606114579</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>3125037955</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>750 N. Lake Shore Drive</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[Rubloff 7th Floor]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Illinois</StateName>
<StateCode>IL</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>IL07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>160079455</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>NORTHWESTERN UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>005436803</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Northwestern University]]></Name>
<CityName>Evanston</CityName>
<StateCode>IL</StateCode>
<ZipCode>602082730</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[2033 Sheridan Road]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Illinois</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>09</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>IL09</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1265</Code>
<Text>GEOMETRIC ANALYSIS</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0115</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0116</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0117</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2015~113892</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2016~115362</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2017~116884</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>&nbsp;</p> <p>My work is mainly concerned with the mathematical study of quantum mechanics. The foundations</p> <p>of quantum mechanics were laid in the 1920&rsquo;s by Schrodinger, Dirac, Weyl, Fock and many others.</p> <p>Yet it remains obscure how to interpret the results physically to this day. Quantum mechanics replaced the classical mechanics of point particles moving in force fields by wave functions propagating in an infinite dimensional space. This replacement solved the foundational riddle of&nbsp;</p> <p>how a quantum particle can be moving and yet be stationary at the same time. However, the replacement also eliminated geometric intuition. The best path to geometric intuition in quantum mechanics is through the semi-classical limit as the Planck constant tends to zero, wherein quantum mechanics tends to classical mechanics. Mathematically, we try to picture the quantum particle in terms of its nodal (zero) set, respectively&nbsp; in terms of its peak points. These are respectively the least or most probable points for the quantum particle. The study of nodal sets and Lp norms as the eigenvalue tends to infinity gives the best picture we possess of&nbsp; the quantum particle.&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>Moreover, there are two types of representations of quantum mechanics: the real (Schrodinger)</p> <p>representation or the complex analytic (Bargmann-Fock) representation. Much of my work is to compare how nodal sets and Lp norms behave in the two settings. For instance, Peng Zhou and I recently proved that there exist universal Gaussian error function behavior in the complex domain at the boundary of the allowed region. Yet Boris Hanin and I proved that in the Schrodinger representation, the analogous interface behavior was in terms of Airy functions introduced to study the rainbow.&nbsp; Hence, there are universal ways that wave functions behave in the two representations and a universal way to compare them.&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>These results have to do with the `static&rsquo; aspects of quantum mechanics. But the analysis requires a study of the dynamical aspects as well: that is, how wave functions move in time. Physics describe their evolution in terms of propagators. The key objects I study are the propagators in the Schrodinger and Bargmann-Fock settings. By controlling the propagation I can determine the behavior of zeros and peak points.&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 09/01/2019<br>      Modified by: Steve&nbsp;Zelditch</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[    My work is mainly concerned with the mathematical study of quantum mechanics. The foundations  of quantum mechanics were laid in the 1920?s by Schrodinger, Dirac, Weyl, Fock and many others.  Yet it remains obscure how to interpret the results physically to this day. Quantum mechanics replaced the classical mechanics of point particles moving in force fields by wave functions propagating in an infinite dimensional space. This replacement solved the foundational riddle of   how a quantum particle can be moving and yet be stationary at the same time. However, the replacement also eliminated geometric intuition. The best path to geometric intuition in quantum mechanics is through the semi-classical limit as the Planck constant tends to zero, wherein quantum mechanics tends to classical mechanics. Mathematically, we try to picture the quantum particle in terms of its nodal (zero) set, respectively  in terms of its peak points. These are respectively the least or most probable points for the quantum particle. The study of nodal sets and Lp norms as the eigenvalue tends to infinity gives the best picture we possess of  the quantum particle.      Moreover, there are two types of representations of quantum mechanics: the real (Schrodinger)  representation or the complex analytic (Bargmann-Fock) representation. Much of my work is to compare how nodal sets and Lp norms behave in the two settings. For instance, Peng Zhou and I recently proved that there exist universal Gaussian error function behavior in the complex domain at the boundary of the allowed region. Yet Boris Hanin and I proved that in the Schrodinger representation, the analogous interface behavior was in terms of Airy functions introduced to study the rainbow.  Hence, there are universal ways that wave functions behave in the two representations and a universal way to compare them.      These results have to do with the `static? aspects of quantum mechanics. But the analysis requires a study of the dynamical aspects as well: that is, how wave functions move in time. Physics describe their evolution in terms of propagators. The key objects I study are the propagators in the Schrodinger and Bargmann-Fock settings. By controlling the propagation I can determine the behavior of zeros and peak points.           Last Modified: 09/01/2019       Submitted by: Steve Zelditch]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
