<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Spins and Knots: The Rise of Topology in F-Orbital Materials</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2015</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>302796.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>302796</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03070000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DMR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Materials Research</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Daryl Hess</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>dhess@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924942</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>NON-TECHNICAL SUMMARY&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award supports theoretical research and educational activities aimed at achieving a fundamental understanding of how strong electron-electron interactions can bring about novel states of matter, such as topological insulators and topological superconductors. Topological insulators are insulating materials that do not conduct electricity in the bulk but are surrounded by metallic states that cover the surfaces, edges, and interfaces. Similarly, topological superconductors are thought to be like ordinary superconductors in the bulk in that they conduct electricity without loss, but their surfaces and edges are enveloped in a fundamentally new quantum state of electrons with unusual properties.  These exotic surface and edge states are not only fundamentally interesting in their own right, but they can also be potentially manipulated for a variety of applications ranging from high-speed quantum computing to ultra-sensitive magnetic devices. This project aims to identify new materials with topological properties in a family of materials where the strong electron-electron interactions give rise to heavy carriers whose masses can be several hundred times the mass of a bare electron. This project aims at formulating the basic principles which will help experimentalists design novel materials and will be performed in close collaboration with several experimental groups. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Active learning approach will be the touchstone of the educational component of the project. The PI will redesign an existing freshman course, "Seven Ideas That Shook the Universe", around peer discussions to improve student understanding, involvement and performance. The PI will also create a continuation of this course, "Seven Ideas That Are Shaping the Future", by focusing on current developments in physics. The interactive activities developed for both courses will be made available online. In order to attract more physics majors and graduate students to condensed matter physics, the PI will prepare engaging research plans for students. The plans will help the students grasp deeper conceptual issues underlying the problem at hand, get first-hand experience in cutting-edge research, and develop their problem-solving skills. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;TECHNICAL SUMMARY&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award supports theoretical research and educational activities aimed at achieving a fundamental understanding of how strong electron-electron interactions can bring about novel states of matter, such as topological insulators and topological superfluids. The main objectives are to study novel electronic phases in newly discovered topological Kondo insulators, to discover candidates for topological superconductors, and to promote their eventual technological application by examining non-equilibrium dynamics of topological superfluids. The main part of this project will focus on materials which contain elements with f-electronic orbitals. The coupling between magnetic and electronic degrees of freedom, which operates in the background of strong spin-orbit interaction and strong electronic correlations, plays a defining role in these materials and provides a unique insight into the properties of f-electron topological insulators and superconductors. This project aims at formulating the basic principles which will help experimentalists design novel materials and will be performed in close collaboration with several experimental groups.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Active learning approach will be the touchstone of the educational component of the project. The PI will redesign an existing freshman course, "Seven Ideas That Shook the Universe", around peer discussions to improve student understanding, involvement and performance. The PI will also create a continuation of this course, "Seven Ideas That Are Shaping the Future", by focusing on current developments in physics. The interactive activities developed for both courses will be made available online. In order to attract more physics majors and graduate students to condensed matter physics, the PI will prepare engaging research plans for students. The plans will help the students grasp deeper conceptual issues underlying the problem at hand, get first-hand experience in cutting-edge research, and develop their problem-solving skills.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/07/2015</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/07/2015</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1506547</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Maxim</FirstName>
<LastName>Dzero</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>O</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Maxim O Dzero</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>mdzero@kent.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>3306728965</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000596164</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/07/2015</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Kent State University</Name>
<CityName>KENT</CityName>
<ZipCode>442420001</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>3306722070</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>OFFICE OF THE COMPTROLLER</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[PO BOX 5190]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Ohio</StateName>
<StateCode>OH</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>13</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>OH13</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>041071101</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>KENT STATE UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>041071101</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Kent State University]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>OH</StateCode>
<ZipCode>442420001</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Ohio</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>13</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>OH13</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1765</Code>
<Text>CONDENSED MATTER &amp; MAT THEORY</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7203</Code>
<Text>QUANTUM INFORMATION SCIENCE</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7237</Code>
<Text>NANO NON-SOLIC SCI &amp; ENG AWD</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8609</Code>
<Text>Other Energy Research</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0115</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2015~302796</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The initial goal of the project was to develop ideas and concepts which will, in turn, help the research community to facilitate the development of novel materials and heterostructures with an ultimate goal ofl finding their place in the electronic devices of the future. One of the main outcomes of the project is the detailed conceptual understanding of how the electronic states carry the charge on the surface in external magnetic field of an intriguing material - &nbsp;samarium hexaboride (SmB6) - a prominant candidate for a topological Kondo insulator. An interesting property of that material is that below certain temperature the bulk of that material becomes perfectly insulating, while only its surfaces remain metallic. This very property opens many avenues for using SmB6 : a fine tunable oscillator device is one example, but there are many more. Understanding of how susceptible the metallic surface states under external infulences as well as disorder is a key to using this material in electronic devices with designable properties.</p> <p>Another important outcome of this project concerns the physical properties of superconductors - materials which carry electronic current without dissipating heat - under storng perturbations which drive them far from their equilibrium state. Many years of reseach in the field of superconductivity showed that predicting the fate of a superconductor under the action of strong external perturbations proved to be an extremenly difficult problem. However, during the last decade the community has witnessed a substantial advances in the solution of that problem: as it turned out under certain (not too limiting assumptions) the problem admitted an exact solution! One of the challenges for the PI in this project was to check whether the results from the exact integrability can be used for the superconductors which are driven far from equilibrium and do not admit an exact solution. The problem is conceptually similar to the planetary motion in the solar system: the motion of the Earth around the Sun is very well described by the exact solution of the so-called Kepler problem (two-body problem), however, it is clear that two-body problem is just an approximation which happens to work very well. Indeed, the Earth is also subjected to the gravitational pulls from the other planets, so naively one would not expect the two-body approximation to work very well, but it does! The PI and his graduate student have discovered that in some cases the dynamics of the superconductor is still governed by solutions found using exact solution, while the initial model could not be solved exactly. Our results show that even in the case when the problem at hand seems to be too complicated to solve, one can employ the exact integrability methods, often developed by mathematicians in contexts, completely different from physics, to develop a physical undersdaning of a system's responses.&nbsp;</p> <p>Broader impacts of the carried research was an important part of the carried activities. During the time of the award, the PI was teaching the undergradute courses University Physics I &amp; II in the studio format (also known as a 'flipped classroom'). Within this format, the lectures and labs are merged together: the class met three times a week for two hours. During the class once a month, the PI had spent 10-15 minutes introducing his students to the discoveries which were awarded Nobel Prize in Physics. &nbsp;These bits will help the PI to prepare a completely new course which can be considered as a modern addition to an immensily popular course <em>Seven Ideas That Shook the Universe</em> which was taught at Kent State University for many years. In addition, at the beggining of each semester, the PI gave presentations describing his current reasearch ideas and activities (at the very basic level) to the undergraduate students interested in majoring in Physics.&nbsp;</p> <p>Lastly, an important outcome of this award for the broader impacts part concerns the emergent collaboratrion between the PI and his colleagues from the Deparment of Psychology at Kent State University. The goal of this collaboration is to increase the involvement and preparation of the undegradute students.&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 10/14/2019<br>      Modified by: Maxim&nbsp;O&nbsp;Dzero</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The initial goal of the project was to develop ideas and concepts which will, in turn, help the research community to facilitate the development of novel materials and heterostructures with an ultimate goal ofl finding their place in the electronic devices of the future. One of the main outcomes of the project is the detailed conceptual understanding of how the electronic states carry the charge on the surface in external magnetic field of an intriguing material -  samarium hexaboride (SmB6) - a prominant candidate for a topological Kondo insulator. An interesting property of that material is that below certain temperature the bulk of that material becomes perfectly insulating, while only its surfaces remain metallic. This very property opens many avenues for using SmB6 : a fine tunable oscillator device is one example, but there are many more. Understanding of how susceptible the metallic surface states under external infulences as well as disorder is a key to using this material in electronic devices with designable properties.  Another important outcome of this project concerns the physical properties of superconductors - materials which carry electronic current without dissipating heat - under storng perturbations which drive them far from their equilibrium state. Many years of reseach in the field of superconductivity showed that predicting the fate of a superconductor under the action of strong external perturbations proved to be an extremenly difficult problem. However, during the last decade the community has witnessed a substantial advances in the solution of that problem: as it turned out under certain (not too limiting assumptions) the problem admitted an exact solution! One of the challenges for the PI in this project was to check whether the results from the exact integrability can be used for the superconductors which are driven far from equilibrium and do not admit an exact solution. The problem is conceptually similar to the planetary motion in the solar system: the motion of the Earth around the Sun is very well described by the exact solution of the so-called Kepler problem (two-body problem), however, it is clear that two-body problem is just an approximation which happens to work very well. Indeed, the Earth is also subjected to the gravitational pulls from the other planets, so naively one would not expect the two-body approximation to work very well, but it does! The PI and his graduate student have discovered that in some cases the dynamics of the superconductor is still governed by solutions found using exact solution, while the initial model could not be solved exactly. Our results show that even in the case when the problem at hand seems to be too complicated to solve, one can employ the exact integrability methods, often developed by mathematicians in contexts, completely different from physics, to develop a physical undersdaning of a system's responses.   Broader impacts of the carried research was an important part of the carried activities. During the time of the award, the PI was teaching the undergradute courses University Physics I &amp; II in the studio format (also known as a 'flipped classroom'). Within this format, the lectures and labs are merged together: the class met three times a week for two hours. During the class once a month, the PI had spent 10-15 minutes introducing his students to the discoveries which were awarded Nobel Prize in Physics.  These bits will help the PI to prepare a completely new course which can be considered as a modern addition to an immensily popular course Seven Ideas That Shook the Universe which was taught at Kent State University for many years. In addition, at the beggining of each semester, the PI gave presentations describing his current reasearch ideas and activities (at the very basic level) to the undergraduate students interested in majoring in Physics.   Lastly, an important outcome of this award for the broader impacts part concerns the emergent collaboratrion between the PI and his colleagues from the Deparment of Psychology at Kent State University. The goal of this collaboration is to increase the involvement and preparation of the undegradute students.           Last Modified: 10/14/2019       Submitted by: Maxim O Dzero]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
