<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Programmed Assembly of Conductive Protein Crystals</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2015</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>357437.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>357437</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03070000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DMR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Materials Research</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Germano Iannacchione</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>giannacc@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032920000</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Non-Technical: This award by the Biomaterials Program in the Division of Materials Research to Colorado State University is to design new materials by encoding the assembly of building block proteins. This award is cofunded by US Army Natick Soldier Research, Development &amp; Engineering Center. The intended crystalline biomaterials are so precisely organized that they will diffract X-rays, allowing high-resolution determination of the molecular structure details. While there are many possible applications for such materials, this proposal focuses on (1) determining the extent to which the position of constituent building blocks can be programmed, and (2) assessing applications for the protein crystal pore network. Specifically, the project will produce and characterize close-packed hexagonal arrays of nanowires that may form useful ultra-high surface area materials for catalysis or battery applications. Porous protein crystals may also offer advantages as multifunctional delivery materials, combining high capacity with the possibility of extensive nanostructure control. The project provides educational opportunities from high school and the University due to integration with AP Chemistry and Biomolecular Engineering courses, as well as broad dissemination via an open-source software platform (SHARPEN) for protein modeling and design.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Technical: The proposed research will study proteins as building blocks to assemble crystalline materials in which it is possible to exert sub-nanometer control over the location of constituent domains. This research will also exploit the highly anisotropic pore structure of existing protein crystals in pursuit of nanostructured material applications. The project will produce and characterize close-packed hexagonal arrays of nanowires via synthesis of conductive polymers or the capture of carbon nanotubes within a parallel array of nanopores. Additionally, the research will determine the suitability of porous crystals to serve as depots for the controlled release of antimicrobial peptides under challenging operational conditions. Specifically, the project will assess the extent to which protein crystals with very different pore sizes adsorb antimicrobial peptides, conditionally gate guest peptide release, and withstand demanding conditions including denaturants, heat, freeze-thaw cycles, and desiccation. This proposal also includes a software engineering effort to improve accessibility of the SHARPEN platform, further extending the impact of protein design methodology improvements. Research training will encompass cutting-edge areas of bionanotechnology, molecular modeling, and nanostructure imaging.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/31/2015</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>09/06/2017</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1506219</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Christopher</FirstName>
<LastName>Snow</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>D</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Christopher D Snow</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>christopher.snow@colostate.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>9704916355</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000649403</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/31/2015</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Colorado State University</Name>
<CityName>Fort Collins</CityName>
<ZipCode>805232002</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>9704916355</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>601 S Howes St</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Colorado</StateName>
<StateCode>CO</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CO02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>785979618</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>COLORADO STATE UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>948905492</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Colorado State University]]></Name>
<CityName>Fort Collins</CityName>
<StateCode>CO</StateCode>
<ZipCode>805214593</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[200 West Lake Street]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Colorado</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CO02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7623</Code>
<Text>BIOMATERIALS PROGRAM</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>O358</Code>
<Text/>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1711</Code>
<Text>MATERIALS EDUCATION AND RESEARCH</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7237</Code>
<Text>NANO NON-SOLIC SCI &amp; ENG AWD</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7573</Code>
<Text>BIO-RELATED MATERIALS RESEARCH</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7623</Code>
<Text>BIOMATERIALS PROGRAM</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0115</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0116</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0117</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2015~157437</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2016~100000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2017~100000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><strong>Scientific Impact.</strong> This grant played a central role in developing porous protein crystals as a new platform technology. Key results include:</p> <p>A.  The refinement of reliable methods for converting fragile protein   crystals into robust, crosslinked, highly-ordered scaffold materials   suitable for downstream applications. The resulting crystals are   remarkably stable with respect to challenging solution conditions   (Figure 1). A full technical description of the numerous crosslinking   chemistry variations tested is in preparation for publication.</p> <p>B. The development of methods for controlled loading and release of guest macromolecules from these crystals was published (<em>Small</em>).   Functional guest enzymes were also been loaded. Specifically, we   demonstrated that an enzyme pathway can function (Figure 2) inside of a   host crystal. This work will shortly be published. We also pursued a quantitative understanding of guest macromolecule diffusion and adsorption inside the crystals (<em>J. Phys. Chem. B</em>).   Finally, we determined that guest DNA is adsorbed with extraordinarily   high affinity, a discovery that raises the possibility of DNA storage   and protection applications.</p> <p>C. The development of  computational methods for designing new  biomolecular crystal forms. The  first of two planned computational  crystal design papers was published (<em>Crystal Growth and Design</em>).</p> <p>D. Designing new crystal forms was a challenging primary goal for  this project.  We started by redesigning the interface of our primary  porous protein  crystal and obtained high-resolution x-ray structures  thereof. More  dramatically, we recently obtained small crystals for  biomolecular  co-crystal variants that were designed to have altered  solvent pore  geometry (Figure 1).</p> <p>E. We developed  chemistry for incorporating electrically conductive  materials into the  solvent channels of protein crystals. Controlling  the nucleation and  growth of non-biological guest materials proved to  be quite challenging.  Nonetheless, we were able to characterize two  conductive guest  materials: polypyrrole and gold.</p> <p>In sum, this grant contributed a critical scientific foundation of understanding for host-guest protein crystals as a material.</p> <p><strong>Technology Impact. </strong>In  addition to the  aforementioned scientific impact, this grant included a  large focus on  demonstrating the potential of engineered porous  crystals for  applications. The general idea was to provide proof of  concept  demonstrations or feasibility tests that highlight the unusual   attributes of porous protein crystals as materials. In brief, materials   that are composed entirely of proteins should enjoy certain advantages   in terms of biocompatibility. Also, the crosslinked honeycomb topology   of the crystal can be quite robust with respect to mechanical or  solvent  challenge. Finally, the close-packed array of 13-nm nanopores  in the  crystal (80% solvent) leads to a very high theoretical capacity  for  securely containing guest molecules.</p> <p>A. As a practical  consideration, we developed methods for reliably  growing crystals with  varying size and aspect ratio. The porous  crystals can be grown with  diameter of hundreds of nanometers up to 1  millimeter. The aspect ratio  of these hexagonal prisms can be varied  from thin plates to long rods.</p> <p>B.  To broaden the applications for engineered crystals, we developed   methods to attach the crystals to larger materials. In particular, we   elucidated chemistry to attach the crystals to cotton (and withstand   laundering). These crystals can be subsequently loaded with functional   enzymes (Figure 4). This work is in preparation for resubmission. This   result opens the door for applications related to multifunctional   textiles.</p> <p>C. We demonstrated that, as expected, the crosslinked crystals are highly biocompatible (<em>ACS Biomater. Sci. Eng</em>.). Biocompatibility opens the door for subsequent applications in biosensing and drug delivery.</p> <p><strong>Broader Impact.</strong> This project consisted of a diverse  set of scientific goals, and thus  supported a diverse set of graduate  and undergraduate researchers. In  particular, three successful doctoral  degree recepients in the last  calendar year contributed to this  project, along with a new Ph.D.  student who took up the reins this last  year. Of the recent graduates,  one has obtained a prestigious  postdoctoral fellowship at the Protein  Design Institute, and two found  industry positions without delay.  Several undergraduate researchers  also contributed to the project,  including two senior honors thesis  contributions. Several of these  students now have industry positions  for which they credit their  research experience. High school interns  were also provided with summer  research experiences. Finally, the PI  served as the faculty advisor for a  new Colorado State University  undergraduate organization, formed to  compete in BIOMOD, the  international biomolecular design competition.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 12/30/2018<br>      Modified by: Christopher&nbsp;D&nbsp;Snow</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Images (<span id="selectedPhoto0">1</span> of <span class="totalNumber"></span>)           </div> <div class="galControls" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1506219/1506219_10402445_1546107026473_ScreenShot2018-11-04at2.50.47PM--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1506219/1506219_10402445_1546107026473_ScreenShot2018-11-04at2.50.47PM--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Figure 4. Porous microcrystals attached to cotton"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1506219/1506219_10402445_1546107026473_ScreenShot2018-11-04at2.50.47PM--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Figure 4. Porous microcrystals attached to cotton"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Figure 4. Crosslinked, fluorescein-labeled large-pore protein crystals (green) attached to cotton (gray) after a 36-minute incubation with sulforhodamine-labeled P450 enzymes (red)</div> <div class="imageCredit">Luke Hartje</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Christopher&nbsp;D&nbsp;Snow</div> <div class="imageTitle">Figure 4. Porous microcrystals attached to cotton</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1506219/1506219_10402445_1546191400911_Abby_new_crystals--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1506219/1506219_10402445_1546191400911_Abby_new_crystals--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Figure 3. Re-engineered porous biomolecular crystals"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1506219/1506219_10402445_1546191400911_Abby_new_crystals--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Figure 3. Re-engineered porous biomolecular crystals"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Figure 3. Small crystals obtained for a designed porous biomolecular crystal.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Abby Ward</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Christopher&nbsp;D&nbsp;Snow</div> <div class="imageTitle">Figure 3. Re-engineered porous biomolecular crystals</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1506219/1506219_10402445_1546191642054_enzyme-loaded-crystals--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1506219/1506219_10402445_1546191642054_enzyme-loaded-crystals--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Figure 2. Porous host crystals for functional guest enzymes"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1506219/1506219_10402445_1546191642054_enzyme-loaded-crystals--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Figure 2. Porous host crystals for functional guest enzymes"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Figure 2. Spinning disk confocal microscope imaging of a enzyme pathway (glucose oxidase and horseradish peroxidase) functioning inside a host crystal that can conduct substrate and product.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Ann Kowalski</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Christopher&nbsp;D&nbsp;Snow</div> <div class="imageTitle">Figure 2. Porous host crystals for functional guest enzymes</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1506219/1506219_10402445_1546192055769_crystal_stability--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1506219/1506219_10402445_1546192055769_crystal_stability--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Figure 1. Stability of crosslinked porous protein crystals"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1506219/1506219_10402445_1546192055769_crystal_stability--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Figure 1. Stability of crosslinked porous protein crystals"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Figure 1. Crosslinked porous crystals are quite stable. Here we show crystals after 2 minutes in:(a) H2O, (b) 100% acetone, (c) 100% DMSO, (d) 100 degrees Celcius H2O, (e) aqua regia, a 3:1 v/v mixture of HCl and HNO3, and (f) pH 11 NaOH buffer.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Ann Kowalski</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Christopher&nbsp;D&nbsp;Snow</div> <div class="imageTitle">Figure 1. Stability of crosslinked porous protein crystals</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Scientific Impact. This grant played a central role in developing porous protein crystals as a new platform technology. Key results include:  A.  The refinement of reliable methods for converting fragile protein   crystals into robust, crosslinked, highly-ordered scaffold materials   suitable for downstream applications. The resulting crystals are   remarkably stable with respect to challenging solution conditions   (Figure 1). A full technical description of the numerous crosslinking   chemistry variations tested is in preparation for publication.  B. The development of methods for controlled loading and release of guest macromolecules from these crystals was published (Small).   Functional guest enzymes were also been loaded. Specifically, we   demonstrated that an enzyme pathway can function (Figure 2) inside of a   host crystal. This work will shortly be published. We also pursued a quantitative understanding of guest macromolecule diffusion and adsorption inside the crystals (J. Phys. Chem. B).   Finally, we determined that guest DNA is adsorbed with extraordinarily   high affinity, a discovery that raises the possibility of DNA storage   and protection applications.  C. The development of  computational methods for designing new  biomolecular crystal forms. The  first of two planned computational  crystal design papers was published (Crystal Growth and Design).  D. Designing new crystal forms was a challenging primary goal for  this project.  We started by redesigning the interface of our primary  porous protein  crystal and obtained high-resolution x-ray structures  thereof. More  dramatically, we recently obtained small crystals for  biomolecular  co-crystal variants that were designed to have altered  solvent pore  geometry (Figure 1).  E. We developed  chemistry for incorporating electrically conductive  materials into the  solvent channels of protein crystals. Controlling  the nucleation and  growth of non-biological guest materials proved to  be quite challenging.  Nonetheless, we were able to characterize two  conductive guest  materials: polypyrrole and gold.  In sum, this grant contributed a critical scientific foundation of understanding for host-guest protein crystals as a material.  Technology Impact. In  addition to the  aforementioned scientific impact, this grant included a  large focus on  demonstrating the potential of engineered porous  crystals for  applications. The general idea was to provide proof of  concept  demonstrations or feasibility tests that highlight the unusual   attributes of porous protein crystals as materials. In brief, materials   that are composed entirely of proteins should enjoy certain advantages   in terms of biocompatibility. Also, the crosslinked honeycomb topology   of the crystal can be quite robust with respect to mechanical or  solvent  challenge. Finally, the close-packed array of 13-nm nanopores  in the  crystal (80% solvent) leads to a very high theoretical capacity  for  securely containing guest molecules.  A. As a practical  consideration, we developed methods for reliably  growing crystals with  varying size and aspect ratio. The porous  crystals can be grown with  diameter of hundreds of nanometers up to 1  millimeter. The aspect ratio  of these hexagonal prisms can be varied  from thin plates to long rods.  B.  To broaden the applications for engineered crystals, we developed   methods to attach the crystals to larger materials. In particular, we   elucidated chemistry to attach the crystals to cotton (and withstand   laundering). These crystals can be subsequently loaded with functional   enzymes (Figure 4). This work is in preparation for resubmission. This   result opens the door for applications related to multifunctional   textiles.  C. We demonstrated that, as expected, the crosslinked crystals are highly biocompatible (ACS Biomater. Sci. Eng.). Biocompatibility opens the door for subsequent applications in biosensing and drug delivery.  Broader Impact. This project consisted of a diverse  set of scientific goals, and thus  supported a diverse set of graduate  and undergraduate researchers. In  particular, three successful doctoral  degree recepients in the last  calendar year contributed to this  project, along with a new Ph.D.  student who took up the reins this last  year. Of the recent graduates,  one has obtained a prestigious  postdoctoral fellowship at the Protein  Design Institute, and two found  industry positions without delay.  Several undergraduate researchers  also contributed to the project,  including two senior honors thesis  contributions. Several of these  students now have industry positions  for which they credit their  research experience. High school interns  were also provided with summer  research experiences. Finally, the PI  served as the faculty advisor for a  new Colorado State University  undergraduate organization, formed to  compete in BIOMOD, the  international biomolecular design competition.       Last Modified: 12/30/2018       Submitted by: Christopher D Snow]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
