<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Structure and dynamics of flexible and active packings</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2015</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>419511.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>419511</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03070000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DMR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Materials Research</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Germano Iannacchione</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>giannacc@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032920000</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Non-technical Abstract&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The properties of a material typically depend on how a fixed set of constituents are arranged and interact via intermolecular forces.  In this research we study two types of materials that do not fit this paradigm.  This first type of material is fibrous matter, made up of long, flexible filaments.  The constraints of packing or weaving together can cause individual filaments to bend and twist thus modifying the way in which an individual filament interacts with other filaments. Fibrous materials are the main constituent of plant matter, as well as human products ranging from paper to fabrics and insulants, so a basic understanding of this ubiquitous class of materials is important.  The second type of material is composed of assemblies of so-called active particles, which when energized have a tendency to move in some direction along their body. At one level, this is intended to illuminate behaviors seen in living systems such as flocking, swarming and group locomotion. On the other hand, we hope to use some of these behaviors to create materials with new functionalities.  The proposed work gives graduate and undergraduate students exposure to a variety of techniques and the opportunity to work in emerging areas of physics. The PI is an organizer of an annual summer school hosted at UMass Amherst for early-career graduate students in soft matter and statistical physics. During the project, the PI will also create and disseminate lesson plans for introductory physics courses taught in a team-based format. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Technical  Abstract&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Nonequilibrium systems made up of macroscopic entities that do not undergo thermal fluctuations are an important part of our technological, physical and biological world.   The experiments proposed here study two broad classes of model nonthermal systems.  (i) Systems of flexible filaments, where in addition to the rich physics of rigid nonthermal packing, we gain new geometrical elements, such as the possibility of entanglements between filaments. A particular focus will be the roles of friction and elasticity in determining the strength of a mat of fibres.  (ii) Systems of active particles, driven by external noise that provide propulsion at the level of individual particles. The central scientific question will be to identify the separate roles of the symmetry of the particle mobility and interaction, which in previous studies have been chosen to coincide.  The PI will study bulk packings, assembled either spontaneously, or templated. These will be studied in 2D by imaging directly and in 3D, by laser-sheet or x-ray imaging. The proposed work gives graduate and undergraduate students exposure to a variety of techniques and the opportunity to work in newly-emerging areas of physics. The PI is also an organizer of an annual summer school hosted at UMass Amherst for early-career graduate students in soft matter physics. During the project, the PI will also create and disseminate lesson plans for introductory physics courses taught in a team-based format.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/14/2015</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/14/2015</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1506750</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Narayanan</FirstName>
<LastName>Menon</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Narayanan Menon</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>menon@physics.umass.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>4135450852</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000297002</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/14/2015</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Massachusetts Amherst</Name>
<CityName>Hadley</CityName>
<ZipCode>010359450</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>4135450698</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>Research Administration Building</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[100 Venture Way, Suite 201]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
<StateCode>MA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MA02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>153926712</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF MASSACHUSETTS</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>079520631</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Massachusetts Amherst]]></Name>
<CityName>Amherst</CityName>
<StateCode>MA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>010039337</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[666 N. Pleasant Street]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MA02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1710</Code>
<Text>CONDENSED MATTER PHYSICS</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0115</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2015~419511</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p style="text-align: center;"><strong>Outcomes Report for NSF-DMR 1507650</strong></p> <p style="text-align: center;"><strong>Structure and dynamics of flexible and active packings</strong></p> <p style="text-align: center;"><strong>Narayanan Menon</strong></p> <p>The mechanics and properties of assemblages of matter put together from macroscopic ingredients is much more poorly understood than that made of atoms and molecules with no intermediate-zied building blocks. This NSF-DMR grant enabled us to explore the assembly and properties of two distinct classes of macroscopic materials &ndash; &lsquo;active&rsquo; materials, and deformable objects like thin sheets and filaments.</p> <p>The field of active matter is inspired by the collective motions of living things such as bacteria, birds or buffaloes that organize themselves into larger grouping like biofilms, flocks and herds.&nbsp; Among the many differences between these entities and most objects that physics traditionally considers is that each particle has the ability to soak up fuel from its surroundings and move in a specific direction aligned by its body; in this respect it is distinct from a molecule being buffeted by constant random kicks from its environments.&nbsp; In our experiments, we chose to use particles shaken on a horizontal, vibrating, surface. These particles had some asymmetry in their shapes so that even a random vibration caused them to move preferentially in one direction.&nbsp;&nbsp; In our work, we established that such a system is correctly described by the same equations that have been developed theoretically to describe other active particles. What makes this development significant is that this system is simple enough that we can vary the surface features to control the extent to which the particle is &lsquo;active&rsquo; while independently controlling the overall shape of the particle.&nbsp; We have now gone beyond the biological inspirations of the field by building shapes such as squares, and controlling their activity separately to create particle assemblies that stick together in noisy environments, or fly apart, or march coherently in one direction.&nbsp; All of these have potential for applications.</p> <p>The second class of materials we worked on focused on materials that are highly deformable not because of intrinsic material softness, but because they are shaped into a sheet or a filament, where one or two dimensions are extremely thin. &nbsp;While these materials are extremely common in nature and in technology, because they can undergo large changes in shape, their mechanics is challenging to understand.&nbsp; In the course of this grant funding, we have investigated the mechanics by which a filament recovers its shape when released from a highly distorted initial condition, the conformation that filament takes on when it is put in contact with a drop, and the various ways in which it arranges itself when confined to a curved surface, such as that of a sphere.&nbsp; In working with thin sheets, we followed up previous work of ours in which we had explored the geometrical principles governing the wrapping of a sheet around a curved object such as a drop. &nbsp;During this funding period, we discovered a method for wrapping droplets extremely rapidly and accurately to form a variety of 3-dimensional enclosures.</p> <p>Finally, some opportunities came up for exploring some fundamental problems in the sedimentation of nonspherical objects.&nbsp; Our experiments, and accompanying theory by collaborators explained the range of phenomena that can arise from the sedimentation of pairs of spheroidal objects.</p> <p>Apart from the applications that can arise from our technical discoveries, we involved a large number of graduate students and undergraduates in this work.&nbsp; Two PhD theses were completed by UMass students, and two more by students of collaborators.&nbsp; Of the seven undergraduate students involved in this work, two &nbsp;were women, and two were minority students. &nbsp;The PI also continued ongoing outreach activities that include organizing an annual soft matter Summer School at UMass, which is now in its 13<sup>th</sup> year. &nbsp;The PI also provided the experimental, hands-on component for a programme for high school teachers entitled <em>Patterns Around Us </em>that has been offered since 2013. Finally, the PI was also part of the local organizing committee for an APS Conference for Undergraduate Women in Physics hosted at UMass in 2019.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 01/26/2020<br>      Modified by: Narayanan&nbsp;Menon</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Images (<span id="selectedPhoto0">1</span> of <span class="totalNumber"></span>)           </div> <div class="galControls" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2020/1506750/1506750_10388287_1580094576254_asymmetricevolution--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2020/1506750/1506750_10388287_1580094576254_asymmetricevolution--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Filament unfurling"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2020/1506750/1506750_10388287_1580094576254_asymmetricevolution--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Filament unfurling"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">An elastic filament at a viscous interface relaxing. Asymmetric initial conditions relax especially quickly.S. Ganga Prasath, J. Marthelot, R Govindarajan, N Menon Relaxation of a highly deformed elastic filament at a fluid interface Phys. Rev. Fluids 1, 033903 (2016)</div> <div class="imageCredit">S. Gangaprasath</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Narayanan&nbsp;Menon</div> <div class="imageTitle">Filament unfurling</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2020/1506750/1506750_10388287_1580096028433_Dynamics--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2020/1506750/1506750_10388287_1580096028433_Dynamics--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Wrapping with a splash"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2020/1506750/1506750_10388287_1580096028433_Dynamics--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Wrapping with a splash"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Wrapping with a splash: High-speed encapsulation with ultrathin sheets, Deepak Kumar, Joseph D. Paulsen, Thomas P. Russell, Narayanan Menon  Science, 775-778 (2018).</div> <div class="imageCredit">Deepak Kumar</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Narayanan&nbsp;Menon</div> <div class="imageTitle">Wrapping with a splash</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[Outcomes Report for NSF-DMR 1507650 Structure and dynamics of flexible and active packings Narayanan Menon  The mechanics and properties of assemblages of matter put together from macroscopic ingredients is much more poorly understood than that made of atoms and molecules with no intermediate-zied building blocks. This NSF-DMR grant enabled us to explore the assembly and properties of two distinct classes of macroscopic materials &ndash; ‘active’ materials, and deformable objects like thin sheets and filaments.  The field of active matter is inspired by the collective motions of living things such as bacteria, birds or buffaloes that organize themselves into larger grouping like biofilms, flocks and herds.  Among the many differences between these entities and most objects that physics traditionally considers is that each particle has the ability to soak up fuel from its surroundings and move in a specific direction aligned by its body; in this respect it is distinct from a molecule being buffeted by constant random kicks from its environments.  In our experiments, we chose to use particles shaken on a horizontal, vibrating, surface. These particles had some asymmetry in their shapes so that even a random vibration caused them to move preferentially in one direction.   In our work, we established that such a system is correctly described by the same equations that have been developed theoretically to describe other active particles. What makes this development significant is that this system is simple enough that we can vary the surface features to control the extent to which the particle is ‘active’ while independently controlling the overall shape of the particle.  We have now gone beyond the biological inspirations of the field by building shapes such as squares, and controlling their activity separately to create particle assemblies that stick together in noisy environments, or fly apart, or march coherently in one direction.  All of these have potential for applications.  The second class of materials we worked on focused on materials that are highly deformable not because of intrinsic material softness, but because they are shaped into a sheet or a filament, where one or two dimensions are extremely thin.  While these materials are extremely common in nature and in technology, because they can undergo large changes in shape, their mechanics is challenging to understand.  In the course of this grant funding, we have investigated the mechanics by which a filament recovers its shape when released from a highly distorted initial condition, the conformation that filament takes on when it is put in contact with a drop, and the various ways in which it arranges itself when confined to a curved surface, such as that of a sphere.  In working with thin sheets, we followed up previous work of ours in which we had explored the geometrical principles governing the wrapping of a sheet around a curved object such as a drop.  During this funding period, we discovered a method for wrapping droplets extremely rapidly and accurately to form a variety of 3-dimensional enclosures.  Finally, some opportunities came up for exploring some fundamental problems in the sedimentation of nonspherical objects.  Our experiments, and accompanying theory by collaborators explained the range of phenomena that can arise from the sedimentation of pairs of spheroidal objects.  Apart from the applications that can arise from our technical discoveries, we involved a large number of graduate students and undergraduates in this work.  Two PhD theses were completed by UMass students, and two more by students of collaborators.  Of the seven undergraduate students involved in this work, two  were women, and two were minority students.  The PI also continued ongoing outreach activities that include organizing an annual soft matter Summer School at UMass, which is now in its 13th year.  The PI also provided the experimental, hands-on component for a programme for high school teachers entitled Patterns Around Us that has been offered since 2013. Finally, the PI was also part of the local organizing committee for an APS Conference for Undergraduate Women in Physics hosted at UMass in 2019.       Last Modified: 01/26/2020       Submitted by: Narayanan Menon]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
