<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Chemistry of Nickel(III/II)-Thiolate Complexes: Insight into the Structure and Mechanism of Ni-Containing SOD</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2015</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>09/30/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>465170.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>471542</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03090000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CHE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Chemistry</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Max Funk</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>mfunk@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032920000</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>With this award, the Chemistry of Life Processes Program in the Division of Chemistry is funding Professor Todd C. Harrop at the University of Georgia to study model nickel-thiolate complexes that mimic the imporant enzyme superoxide dismutase.   Nickel-containing superoxide dismutase (NiSOD) is the only redox-active nickel-enzyme that is present in aerobes despite the presence of ROS (reactive oxygen species)-sensitive cysteine-S-ligands at its active site. This project involves the preparation and investigation of synthetic models of the nickel-containing active site of NiSOD that are capable of aerobic function. In particular, the project will examine the role of the entities that are bound to nickel, in dictating the catalytic properties of the active site. Plans are in place to provide hands-on research opportunities in the fundamental chemical sciences to groups traditionally underrepresented in the STEM disciplines. One such plan, with which there was prior success, is to provide a summer research internship and lifelong career mentorship to undergraduate chemistry majors from Historically Black Colleges and Universities (HBCUs) in the southeast region. The PI and his group will also participate in the University of Georgia Young Dawgs program where high school students from the Clarke County public school system are provided STEM research internships.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The objective of this research is to prepare synthetic model complexes of the nickel center found at the active site of NiSOD, and to investigate the mechanistic role that the coordinated peptide-N and cysteinate-S ligands play in the redox mechanism of this enzyme. Nickel-cysteine sites in biology are central catalysts that participate in reactions of global impact including the detoxification of reactive oxygen species (ROS), fixation of cellular carbon, and the generation of alternative energy supplies, i.e., hydrogen evolution/consumption. Nickel enzymes and their corresponding synthetic models are thus ideal systems to promote chemical transformations of high economic and environmental importance. However, the majority of these nickel-enzymes are found in strict anaerobic organisms.  Despite the sensitive nature of cysteine-S with ROS, these donor atoms appear inert to ROS during turnover in the enzyme. Advanced synthetic techniques will be employed to construct N/S-containing ligand frames and their corresponding Ni(III/II) complexes that accurately reproduce the NiSOD active site. Key factors in the design of these constructs are the incorporation of an axial N-donor and the ability to fine-tune the nucleophilicity of the S-ligands in order to promote Ni-based versus S-based redox chemistry. Spectroscopic, structural and computational techniques will be utilized. The project aims to determine the geometric and electronic structural properties of these Ni(III/II)-N/S complexes and investigate their reactivity with ROS and other reactive small molecules, such as NO, to shed light on the redox mechanism taking place at this unique nickel site.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/30/2015</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>11/22/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1506375</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Todd</FirstName>
<LastName>Harrop</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>C</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Todd C Harrop</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>tharrop@uga.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>7065423486</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000535292</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/30/2015</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Georgia Research Foundation Inc</Name>
<CityName>ATHENS</CityName>
<ZipCode>306021589</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>7065425939</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>310 East Campus Rd</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[Tucker Hall Room 409]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Georgia</StateName>
<StateCode>GA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>10</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>GA10</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>004315578</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF GEORGIA RESEARCH FOUNDATION, INC.</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Georgia]]></Name>
<CityName>Athens</CityName>
<StateCode>GA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>306025016</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[200 D. W. Brooks Drive]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Georgia</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>10</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>GA10</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>6883</Code>
<Text>Chemistry of Life Processes</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0115</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0116</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0117</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2015~316167</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2016~149003</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2017~6372</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The goal of this research was to advance our understanding of the chemistry of metal-sulfur enzyme active sites and their role in redox catalysis. One such enzyme that falls in this class is the Ni-containing (active site metal catalyst) superoxide dismutase (or NiSOD). SODs are widespread throughout the aerobic world and are the first line of defense against oxygen-derived free radicals, i.e., reactive oxygen species (ROS). In NiSOD, nature has assembled a most unusual active site that contains ligands (atoms bound to the metal to engender function) derived from sulfur (cysteine amino acid residues) that are extremely reactive with and destroyed by ROS. In this project a series of smaller (lower molecular weight) analogues of this enzyme were prepared through synthetic methods and their properties were investigated by numerous characterization techniques (spectroscopic, electrochemical, and theoretical) to highlight the crucial structural/electronic features that are necessary to promote Ni-based ROS destruction versus ROS destruction of the sulfur-rich active site of this enzyme. Collectively, the results of the synthetic models that we designed/synthesized/characterized suggest the following in regards to the mechanism of NiSOD and for a variety of Ni-redox enzymes that participate in reactions of gloval significance: (i) sterically robust groups or Lewis acid (i.e., protons or other metal ions) binding to coordinated sulfur ligands decrease the nucleophilicity (ROS reactivity) of the coordinated thiolates, hence protecting S from modification by ROS as a result of decreased S-character in the redox-active molecular orbital; and (ii) increasing the Lewis acidity (electron demand) of Ni via modification of the coordinated S-thiolates promotes coordination of basic N-donors in the axial position, which increases the Ni-character in the redox-active MO. These two properties promote redox activity solely at the Ni center during catalysis, i.e. posies it to interact with and destroy ROS.</p> <p>The broad impact of this project lies in the fact that redox-active enzymes with Ni centers are central to advancing our understanding of biocatalysts that participate in reactions of energetic (hydrogen, methane), physiological (oxygen and oxygen-derived species, e.g., free radicals), and environmental (methane, carbon monoxide, carbon dioxide) significance. Central to the function of these enzymes is the presence of one or more Ni-S-cysteine coordination units at their active sites. Redox-active Ni-enzymes are thus important sites to study because they participate in chemical transformations of global significance. The primary objective of this work was to create fundamental design principles and develop new synthetic strategies to access N/S-containing ligand frames and their corresponding Ni(III/II) complexes that faithfully model the structure and properties of NiSOD in order to understand its mechanism. NiSOD is the prototypical enzyme to model as it is isolated in its active Ni(III/II) forms under ambient aerobic conditions. In addition to understanding the mechanism of this unique Ni-enzyme, the knowledge gained from creating these small molecule models has afforded new design principles/strategies for the creation of robust and inexpensive coordination complexes to perform controlled redox chemistry.</p> <p>Additional broad impacts are the training and preparation of the future generation of chemical scientists. Overall, this project resulted in the advising/training of undergraduate/graduate students, largely from underrepresented groups, in the chemical sciences. This project fully or partially supported the research of 6 Ph.D. graduate students (4 graduated with Ph.D. degrees during the grant period; 4 are female; 1 is a male immigrant from Vietnam). All 4 Ph.D. graduates were immediately employed after graduation as either post-doctoral associates at other universities (one at MIT and received a highly competitive National Institutes of Health Postdoctoral Fellowship), or earned lecturer/instructor positions in chemistry departments at research-intensive universities in the US. A total of 4 undergraduate researchers (3 female) were supported by this award. After earning their B.S. degrees, these students ended up as: (i) a forensic investigator for the Georgia Bureau of Investigation; (ii) dental school student; (iii) veterinary technician; (iv) and a chemistry Ph.D. student at the University of Virginia. Additionally, significant educational changes to the Experimental Methods Laboratory (taken by all B.S.-CHEM majors at the University of Georgia = UGA; enrollment = 15-20) were made by the PI to highlight the utility of transition metal activation of oxygen utilizing UV-vis, EPR, and O<sub>2</sub>-binding assays. The offering of a new undergraduate class at UGA (CHEM 4400: Special Topics in Bioinorganic Chemistry) also resulted during this period. Because of high instructor ratings, CHEM 4400 is now permanently on the UGA list of courses and will be taught every other year by the PI. Lastly, researchers supported by this project have participated in the UGA Young Dawgs program, which provides research internships to local Clarke County (and other Georgia counties) junior/senior high school students with UGA physical/biological science labs. Most of the PI?s group has also volunteered as judges for the annual Georgia Science and Engineering Fair held at UGA.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 08/31/2020<br>      Modified by: Todd&nbsp;C&nbsp;Harrop</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Image         </div> <div class="galControls onePhoto" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation onePhoto" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2020/1506375/1506375_10381773_1598904857306_inocaj_v056i014_2--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2020/1506375/1506375_10381773_1598904857306_inocaj_v056i014_2--rgov-800width.jpg" title="NiSOD Model and Reactivity"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2020/1506375/1506375_10381773_1598904857306_inocaj_v056i014_2--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="NiSOD Model and Reactivity"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Comparison of the structure of NiSOD and NiSOD model complex. UV-vis, X-ray structures and DFT theoretical investigation of the model reveal unusual oxidation chemistry in the model. Cover of Inorganic Chemistry, volume 56, number 14 (July 17, 2017).</div> <div class="imageCredit">Todd Harrop, Phan Truong, American Chemical Society</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Public Domain</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Todd&nbsp;C&nbsp;Harrop</div> <div class="imageTitle">NiSOD Model and Reactivity</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The goal of this research was to advance our understanding of the chemistry of metal-sulfur enzyme active sites and their role in redox catalysis. One such enzyme that falls in this class is the Ni-containing (active site metal catalyst) superoxide dismutase (or NiSOD). SODs are widespread throughout the aerobic world and are the first line of defense against oxygen-derived free radicals, i.e., reactive oxygen species (ROS). In NiSOD, nature has assembled a most unusual active site that contains ligands (atoms bound to the metal to engender function) derived from sulfur (cysteine amino acid residues) that are extremely reactive with and destroyed by ROS. In this project a series of smaller (lower molecular weight) analogues of this enzyme were prepared through synthetic methods and their properties were investigated by numerous characterization techniques (spectroscopic, electrochemical, and theoretical) to highlight the crucial structural/electronic features that are necessary to promote Ni-based ROS destruction versus ROS destruction of the sulfur-rich active site of this enzyme. Collectively, the results of the synthetic models that we designed/synthesized/characterized suggest the following in regards to the mechanism of NiSOD and for a variety of Ni-redox enzymes that participate in reactions of gloval significance: (i) sterically robust groups or Lewis acid (i.e., protons or other metal ions) binding to coordinated sulfur ligands decrease the nucleophilicity (ROS reactivity) of the coordinated thiolates, hence protecting S from modification by ROS as a result of decreased S-character in the redox-active molecular orbital; and (ii) increasing the Lewis acidity (electron demand) of Ni via modification of the coordinated S-thiolates promotes coordination of basic N-donors in the axial position, which increases the Ni-character in the redox-active MO. These two properties promote redox activity solely at the Ni center during catalysis, i.e. posies it to interact with and destroy ROS.  The broad impact of this project lies in the fact that redox-active enzymes with Ni centers are central to advancing our understanding of biocatalysts that participate in reactions of energetic (hydrogen, methane), physiological (oxygen and oxygen-derived species, e.g., free radicals), and environmental (methane, carbon monoxide, carbon dioxide) significance. Central to the function of these enzymes is the presence of one or more Ni-S-cysteine coordination units at their active sites. Redox-active Ni-enzymes are thus important sites to study because they participate in chemical transformations of global significance. The primary objective of this work was to create fundamental design principles and develop new synthetic strategies to access N/S-containing ligand frames and their corresponding Ni(III/II) complexes that faithfully model the structure and properties of NiSOD in order to understand its mechanism. NiSOD is the prototypical enzyme to model as it is isolated in its active Ni(III/II) forms under ambient aerobic conditions. In addition to understanding the mechanism of this unique Ni-enzyme, the knowledge gained from creating these small molecule models has afforded new design principles/strategies for the creation of robust and inexpensive coordination complexes to perform controlled redox chemistry.  Additional broad impacts are the training and preparation of the future generation of chemical scientists. Overall, this project resulted in the advising/training of undergraduate/graduate students, largely from underrepresented groups, in the chemical sciences. This project fully or partially supported the research of 6 Ph.D. graduate students (4 graduated with Ph.D. degrees during the grant period; 4 are female; 1 is a male immigrant from Vietnam). All 4 Ph.D. graduates were immediately employed after graduation as either post-doctoral associates at other universities (one at MIT and received a highly competitive National Institutes of Health Postdoctoral Fellowship), or earned lecturer/instructor positions in chemistry departments at research-intensive universities in the US. A total of 4 undergraduate researchers (3 female) were supported by this award. After earning their B.S. degrees, these students ended up as: (i) a forensic investigator for the Georgia Bureau of Investigation; (ii) dental school student; (iii) veterinary technician; (iv) and a chemistry Ph.D. student at the University of Virginia. Additionally, significant educational changes to the Experimental Methods Laboratory (taken by all B.S.-CHEM majors at the University of Georgia = UGA; enrollment = 15-20) were made by the PI to highlight the utility of transition metal activation of oxygen utilizing UV-vis, EPR, and O2-binding assays. The offering of a new undergraduate class at UGA (CHEM 4400: Special Topics in Bioinorganic Chemistry) also resulted during this period. Because of high instructor ratings, CHEM 4400 is now permanently on the UGA list of courses and will be taught every other year by the PI. Lastly, researchers supported by this project have participated in the UGA Young Dawgs program, which provides research internships to local Clarke County (and other Georgia counties) junior/senior high school students with UGA physical/biological science labs. Most of the PI?s group has also volunteered as judges for the annual Georgia Science and Engineering Fair held at UGA.       Last Modified: 08/31/2020       Submitted by: Todd C Harrop]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
