<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Collaborative Research: Small molecules as chemical probes of protein dynamics and protein-protein interactions</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/15/2015</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>239362.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>239362</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03090000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CHE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Chemistry</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Catalina Achim</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>cachim@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922048</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Understanding details of how living cells signal and coordinate complex cellular activities is an unsolved problem of high fundamental significance. It is known that cells are comprised of an array of molecules, and therefore the interactions among these molecules at a specific time and location are potentially responsible for functional outcomes. It remains challenging to quantify intermolecular interactions between a pair of molecules at atomic scale, owing largely to a poor understanding of underlying dynamic motions. Importantly, many such structural motions in biomolecules such as proteins cannot be directly inferred from high-resolution static experimental structures, and therefore novel methods to probe dynamic motions are needed. In this project, the unique combination of atomically-resolved molecular simulations with various experimental techniques establishes new approaches to study protein-protein interactions, and the small molecules developed may lead to tools for controlling such interactions. The graduate and postdoctoral researchers working on this project acquire interdisciplinary training in computer simulation approaches for proteins and experimental approaches involving protein characterization and spectroscopic methods, thereby gaining an appreciation for ways in which theory and experiment can inform each other. The outreach activities of this project educate and train high school students and teachers in STEM disciplines via hands-on lab experiences. The resulting tools such as software, structural models, and protein constructs are demonstrated in chemical engineering, biophysics, and pharmacology courses, and are disseminated among the broader scientific community via workshops, symposia, and meetings.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This research project employs large-scale molecular simulation techniques on all-atom models of proteins to infer underlying dynamics, discover hidden conformational states, and quantify interactions at protein-protein interfaces. A variety of computational approaches are pursued including classical molecular dynamics simulations in explicit solvent, methods for enhanced conformational sampling and thermodynamic characterization of proteins, and Monte Carlo protocols for small molecule docking. To gain a better understanding of dynamics and interactions, the modeling and simulation effort are integrated with many experimental (biochemical, biophysical, and spectroscopic) techniques at various levels. These combined tools are used to study regulators of G-protein signaling (RGS) proteins using thiadiazolidinone (TDZD) analogues as small molecule chemical probes. The focus is to quantify differences in dynamics of three-different RGS proteins that result in differences in specificity and potency for different small molecules, and discover the mechanisms by which small molecules affect and inhibit interactions between various RGS proteins and activated G-alpha subunits of G-proteins. The quantification of mechanisms and interactions in this family of proteins may reveal the extent to which dynamic motions play a role in regulating protein-protein interactions, and the unique ways in which such motions can be exploited for targeting protein-protein interfaces.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/10/2015</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/10/2015</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1507588</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Richard</FirstName>
<LastName>Neubig</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>R</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Richard R Neubig</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>rneubig@msu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5173537145</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000681647</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/10/2015</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Michigan State University</Name>
<CityName>East Lansing</CityName>
<ZipCode>488242600</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5173555040</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>Office of Sponsored Programs</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[426 Administration Bldg, Rm2]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Michigan</StateName>
<StateCode>MI</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>08</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MI08</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>193247145</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>MICHIGAN STATE UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>053343976</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Michigan State University]]></Name>
<CityName>East Lansing</CityName>
<StateCode>MI</StateCode>
<ZipCode>488246251</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[1355 Bogue St]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Michigan</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>08</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MI08</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>6883</Code>
<Text>Chemistry of Life Processes</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9263</Code>
<Text>COMPUTATIONAL SCIENCE &amp; ENGING</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0115</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2015~239362</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The control of biological functions frequently depends on the binding of one protein to another &ndash; so called protein-protein interactions (PPIs). This permits the stimulation of inhibition of cell communication, control of gene expression, and neural function. Understanding the factors that control PPIs and how they can be modulated by chemicals is fundamental to our ability to control critical biological processes. In general PPIs have been considered hard targets for chemical modulation since the protein interfaces that make them up a relatively flat and without good pockets for chemicals to bind. In this project, we showed that one can not fully understand the binding of chemicals to a protein without taking into account how the protein moves in time (i.e. protein dynamics). With this project, we showed that protein dynamics can control the ability to inhibit a PPI. A more dynamic protein is more readily inhibited because the chemical can access internal sites (cryptic pockets) that are not available in a more stable protein that lacks robust dynamic changes. This both controls the specificity of the compounds &ndash; they are more potent at a dynamic protein target. Also, the dynamic protein target exposes new sites which may be targeted by compounds that won&rsquo;t be able to bind to the outside surface of the protein. This provides new ways to control PPIs which underlie much of biological function. <strong>Given the unique collaborative nature of this project integrating modeling and experiments, student researchers gained appreciation for ways in which the theory and the experiment can inform each other and provide enhanced insights into biophysical problems of broad interest. The results from our investigations were disseminated broadly through multiple peer-reviewed journal publications and conference presentations at local, national, and international venues. The outcomes of this project further led to significant enhancements of STEM courses taught in bioengineering, chemical engineering, and pharmacology. The project also led to successful completion of PhD degrees for three students, all of whom went on to do advanced postdoctoral research work. Overall, the project will have a lasting impact beyond the lifetime of award through research outcomes of broader significance and via the well-trained next generation workforce who will become future leaders in respective science and engineering disciplines.</strong></p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 10/22/2019<br>      Modified by: Richard&nbsp;R&nbsp;Neubig</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The control of biological functions frequently depends on the binding of one protein to another &ndash; so called protein-protein interactions (PPIs). This permits the stimulation of inhibition of cell communication, control of gene expression, and neural function. Understanding the factors that control PPIs and how they can be modulated by chemicals is fundamental to our ability to control critical biological processes. In general PPIs have been considered hard targets for chemical modulation since the protein interfaces that make them up a relatively flat and without good pockets for chemicals to bind. In this project, we showed that one can not fully understand the binding of chemicals to a protein without taking into account how the protein moves in time (i.e. protein dynamics). With this project, we showed that protein dynamics can control the ability to inhibit a PPI. A more dynamic protein is more readily inhibited because the chemical can access internal sites (cryptic pockets) that are not available in a more stable protein that lacks robust dynamic changes. This both controls the specificity of the compounds &ndash; they are more potent at a dynamic protein target. Also, the dynamic protein target exposes new sites which may be targeted by compounds that won?t be able to bind to the outside surface of the protein. This provides new ways to control PPIs which underlie much of biological function. Given the unique collaborative nature of this project integrating modeling and experiments, student researchers gained appreciation for ways in which the theory and the experiment can inform each other and provide enhanced insights into biophysical problems of broad interest. The results from our investigations were disseminated broadly through multiple peer-reviewed journal publications and conference presentations at local, national, and international venues. The outcomes of this project further led to significant enhancements of STEM courses taught in bioengineering, chemical engineering, and pharmacology. The project also led to successful completion of PhD degrees for three students, all of whom went on to do advanced postdoctoral research work. Overall, the project will have a lasting impact beyond the lifetime of award through research outcomes of broader significance and via the well-trained next generation workforce who will become future leaders in respective science and engineering disciplines.          Last Modified: 10/22/2019       Submitted by: Richard R Neubig]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
