<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Near the onset of rigidity in living and nonliving matter</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2015</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>315000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>315000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03070000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DMR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Materials Research</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Daryl Hess</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>dhess@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924942</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>NONTECHNICAL SUMMARY &lt;br/&gt;Have you ever played a game of "Pick up Sticks" and wondered how an entire structure of randomly arranged sticks can collapse with the removal of just one stick? And have you ever wondered how a skin cell changes shape to crawl towards a wound to heal it?  The notion of the onset of mechanical rigidity in both living and nonliving matter will help answer both of these seemingly disparate questions. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;To explore the emergence (and destruction) of mechanical rigidity in nonliving matter, the proposed modeling will be based on a collection of frictionless, repulsive soft spheres; while in living matter, it will utilize a disordered spring network. The PI's group will test both models by investigating what properties - friction, particle/filament shape, type of crosslinking between filaments, local mechanical stability - affect the nature of the rigidity transition. These models will be used to describe mechanical stability of two- and three-dimensional systems including granular systems, filamentous cytoskeletal networks, and biological tissue in the brain. The proposed work, therefore, extends the reach of materials science to living systems to help drive the emerging field of quantitative biology.  &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The results of the proposed research will be used for development of a new course material on rigidity in both living and nonliving systems at undergraduate and graduate levels. The proposed collaborations with Syracuse Museum of Science and Technology and the YWCA will educate the public about the intrigue of soft matter. The PI will use her knowledge and experience to recruit women to the physical sciences by presenting scientific advances used to decouple the biological clock and the tenure clock to senior graduate students and post-docs. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;TECHNICAL SUMMARY &lt;br/&gt;How does a collection of randomly packed frictional particles at the threshold of mechanical rigidity destabilize with the deletion of just one contact? And how does a collection of cytoskeletal filaments attain mechanical rigidity to extend the reach of a cell? In nonliving matter, the model will be based on a collection of frictionless, repulsive soft spheres; while in living matter, it will utilize a disordered spring network. The PI's group will test the robustness of both models by investigating what properties - friction, particle/filament shape, type of crosslinking between filaments, local mechanical stability - affect the nature of the rigidity transition. To test for this robustness in nonliving systems, the local properties of mechanical stability at the onset of rigidity for frictionless, repulsive soft discs in two dimensions will be studied by using concept of jamming graph. Armed with the information of constraint counting, geometry, and force-balance, the PI's group will develop a model for the onset of rigidity in frictionless, particulate matter. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The emergence (and destruction) of rigidity abounds in living matter as well. The actin filament cytoskeletal network adjusts its morphology to support the cell structurally. The proposed research will narrow the existing theoretical gap between morphology and mechanics by building disordered spring network models that encode more of the network morphology, such as anisotropy and angle-constraining crosslinks, to determine which aspects are more relevant to the onset of rigidity than others. Moreover, quantitative modeling of biological tissue in the brain will be developed using vertex models, which are related to disordered spring networks. The PI's group will investigate the interplay between morphology and mechanics to determine how glial cells structurally support bundles of neurons. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The results of the proposed research will be used for development of a new course material on rigidity in both living and nonliving systems at undergraduate and graduate levels. The proposed collaborations with Syracuse Museum of Science and Technology and the YWCA will educate the public about the intrigue of soft matter. The PI will be involved in the recruitment of women to the physical sciences by presenting scientific advances used to decouple the biological clock and the tenure clock to senior graduate students and post-docs.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/24/2015</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/24/2015</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1507938</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Jennifer</FirstName>
<LastName>Schwarz</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Jennifer Schwarz</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>jschwarz@physics.syr.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>3154433887</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000234038</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/24/2015</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Syracuse University</Name>
<CityName>SYRACUSE</CityName>
<ZipCode>132441200</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>3154432807</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>OFFICE OF SPONSORED PROGRAMS</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[211 Lyman Hall]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>24</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NY24</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>002257350</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>SYRACUSE UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>002257350</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Syracuse University]]></Name>
<CityName>Syracuse</CityName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<ZipCode>132441130</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>24</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NY24</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1712</Code>
<Text>DMR SHORT TERM SUPPORT</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7573</Code>
<Text>BIO-RELATED MATERIALS RESEARCH</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8091</Code>
<Text>BRAIN Initiative Res Support</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0115</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2015~315000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>From shearing a loose packing of granular particles to shearing a loosely-connected fibrous network of collagen, floppy-to-rigid transitions abound in nature. Since floppy-to-rigid transitions have important implications for the mechanical stability of such systems, we have developed a means to identify rigid clusters, e.g. contacting particles that are rigid with respect to each other, in frictional particle packings. We then studied the transition in terms of the emergence of a system-spanning rigid cluster. In doing so, we discovered that such rigid clusters, particularly system-spanning ones, exhibit &ldquo;partial rigidity&rdquo;, i.e. holes in the rigid clusters containing contacting particles that are floppy with respect to each other.&nbsp;&nbsp;This discovery may have profound implications for the mechanical stability of frictional particle packings. Moreover, the very notion of rigid clusters represents a shift in focus from force-chains that have long been studied in granular packings and, yet, their link to predicting packings mechanics remains rather elusive. Rigid clusters in granular packings may be the missing piece of information needed to enhance the predictive power of modeling.&nbsp;</p> <p><span>We have also studied the interplay of rigidity and shape-change in soft materials and constructed a new approach to understand how creases (cusped folds) form at the exposed surface of a soft slab that is being compressed along a direction perpendicular to the exposed surface. Our approach allows for the first analytical prediction of the critical compressive strain above which creases are generated and will ultimately help understand how crease patterns emerge. Crease patterns are numerous in nature ranging from those in pumpkins and other plants to shape-changes in animal morphogenesis.&nbsp;Moreover, by studying shape-change in the developing mouse cerebellum (whose shape-change morphology is distinct from creasing), we have also devised a new paradigm for morphogenesis going beyond purely elastic materials and involving a proliferating fluid layer known as the cerebellar cortex. Our new paradigm may have far-reaching implications for how the brain and other central nervous system components develop.&nbsp;Understanding the brain as a developing material should help inform how it works.&nbsp;</span></p> <p>The PI has led a number of discussions on the decoupling of the tenure clock and the biological clock to encourage younger women to continue to pursue a career in academia.&nbsp; The PI's mission to help decouple the two clocks will hopefully encourage more women to become professors in the sciences. With a proliferation of women in such leadership/mentorship positions, hopefully more younger women will be encouraged to also become leaders/mentors, not just in the sciences, but in society at large as they continue on their own career path beyond college.&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 11/30/2018<br>      Modified by: Jennifer&nbsp;Schwarz</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ From shearing a loose packing of granular particles to shearing a loosely-connected fibrous network of collagen, floppy-to-rigid transitions abound in nature. Since floppy-to-rigid transitions have important implications for the mechanical stability of such systems, we have developed a means to identify rigid clusters, e.g. contacting particles that are rigid with respect to each other, in frictional particle packings. We then studied the transition in terms of the emergence of a system-spanning rigid cluster. In doing so, we discovered that such rigid clusters, particularly system-spanning ones, exhibit "partial rigidity", i.e. holes in the rigid clusters containing contacting particles that are floppy with respect to each other.  This discovery may have profound implications for the mechanical stability of frictional particle packings. Moreover, the very notion of rigid clusters represents a shift in focus from force-chains that have long been studied in granular packings and, yet, their link to predicting packings mechanics remains rather elusive. Rigid clusters in granular packings may be the missing piece of information needed to enhance the predictive power of modeling.   We have also studied the interplay of rigidity and shape-change in soft materials and constructed a new approach to understand how creases (cusped folds) form at the exposed surface of a soft slab that is being compressed along a direction perpendicular to the exposed surface. Our approach allows for the first analytical prediction of the critical compressive strain above which creases are generated and will ultimately help understand how crease patterns emerge. Crease patterns are numerous in nature ranging from those in pumpkins and other plants to shape-changes in animal morphogenesis. Moreover, by studying shape-change in the developing mouse cerebellum (whose shape-change morphology is distinct from creasing), we have also devised a new paradigm for morphogenesis going beyond purely elastic materials and involving a proliferating fluid layer known as the cerebellar cortex. Our new paradigm may have far-reaching implications for how the brain and other central nervous system components develop. Understanding the brain as a developing material should help inform how it works.   The PI has led a number of discussions on the decoupling of the tenure clock and the biological clock to encourage younger women to continue to pursue a career in academia.  The PI's mission to help decouple the two clocks will hopefully encourage more women to become professors in the sciences. With a proliferation of women in such leadership/mentorship positions, hopefully more younger women will be encouraged to also become leaders/mentors, not just in the sciences, but in society at large as they continue on their own career path beyond college.              Last Modified: 11/30/2018       Submitted by: Jennifer Schwarz]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
