<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>ABR: Functional Biomimetic Architectures</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/15/2015</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>444960.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>444960</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03090000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CHE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Chemistry</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Lin He</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>lhe@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924956</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>With this award, the Macromolecular, Supramolecular and Nanochemistry Program of the Chemistry Division is funding Professor Kent Kirshenbaum at New York University to extend recent discoveries of synthetic polymers that mimic biological macromolecules. The underlying hypothesis is that synthetic polymer systems can be imbued with a "folding code" a predictable relationship between the sequence of the units in the polymer and a unique three-dimensional structure. The study will yield new families of functional folded molecules that can be used to create advanced materials and will lead to innovative strategies for drug discovery.&lt;br/&gt; &lt;br/&gt;The focus will be investigations of peptoids, which are sequence-specific polymers composed of diverse N-substituted glycine monomer units. Previous studies have demonstrated that certain peptoids exhibit a propensity to adopt discrete stable conformations, resembling the helical and turn motifs found in polypeptides. The goals for this renewal are to move beyond rudimentary peptoid secondary structures to create synthetic peptoid macromolecules that resemble the complex tertiary structures of proteins and consequently allow the design of new functional capabilities. The long-term objectives are to establish a predictable relationship between the sequence, the structure and the function of peptoid polymers. A collaboration with York College in New York City will provide research opportunities for students in under-represented groups. In addition, the project will continue science outreach programs by the "Experimental Cuisine Collective" at NYU, which introduces concepts in macromolecular sciences through the popular context of food and cooking. The broader impacts feature societal benefits attained through training the next generation of polymer scientists, along with addressing unmet needs in molecular pharmacology and synthetic biology.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/14/2015</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/14/2015</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1507946</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Kent</FirstName>
<LastName>Kirshenbaum</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Kent Kirshenbaum</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>kent@nyu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2129988486</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000455085</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/14/2015</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>New York University</Name>
<CityName>NEW YORK</CityName>
<ZipCode>100121019</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2129982121</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>70 WASHINGTON SQUARE S</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>10</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NY10</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>041968306</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>NEW YORK UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>041968306</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[New York University]]></Name>
<CityName>New York</CityName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<ZipCode>100036688</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[100 Washington Square East]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>10</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NY10</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>6885</Code>
<Text>Macromolec/Supramolec/Nano</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7237</Code>
<Text>NANO NON-SOLIC SCI &amp; ENG AWD</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0115</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2015~444960</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Our project has pursued an exciting new path in biomimetic chemistry. The outcomes of the project have identified new ways to design synthetic molecules to fold and function like proteins. Nature uses proteins to meet an astonishing variety of different tasks within the cell. Chemists aspire to learn how to craft large molecules with similar sophisticated functions. In order to do so, we have studied a promising new family of chain-like molecules called peptoids. Peptoids resemble proteins in many ways, but because they are completely synthetic, they are resistant to degradation and can be generated with a vast array of different chemical features.&nbsp;</p> <p><strong>Intellectual Merit</strong></p> <p>During the course of our project, we&nbsp; advanced our ability to create a robust and predictable relationship between the structure and function of folded peptoid oligomers<em>.</em>&nbsp;This has allowed us to identify a number of valuable new applications for peptoids. For example, we have learned how to build cyclic peptoids that are constrained to adopt pre-determined three-dimensional forms. We demonstrated that that these cyclic peptoids could bind to the surface of a protein involved in driving the growth of prostate cancer. We were excited to publish a high profile report that indicated the early potential of the peptoid to block the growth of cancerous cells. In another example, we designed peptoid molecules that can complex therapeutic nucleic acids and facilitate their deliver to the interior of a cell, where it can alter gene expression patterns. Both of these outcomes, along with a range of other exciting results during the project period, establish the potential of peptoids to address a variety of challenges in biomedical sciences and materials chemistry.&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p><strong>Broader Impacts:</strong></p> <p>We have embraced a range of activities that address the broader impacts criteria established by the NSF. These include: enabling technology transfer to non-academic partners; training of chemists at all levels, from high school students to post-doctoral scholars; efforts to foster an international community of chemists devoted to exploring peptoids and other biomimetic macromolecules; and science outreach activities in macromolecular chemistry, particularly at the interface of chemistry and cuisine.</p> <p>We developed a robust intellectual property portfolio that derives from this NSF sponsored project. Several of our peptoid patents have been licensed by industrial partners interested in establishing the commercial potential for these molecules.&nbsp;</p> <p>We have inspired a cadre of young scientists&nbsp; from diverse backgrounds to pursue the new field of biomimetic chemistry, and to delve into problems at the interface of chemical and biomedical sciences. Several of these researchers are on the path to become independent investigators, and are eager to develop their own creative notions about how to craft functional peptoid molecules.&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 03/12/2020<br>      Modified by: Kent&nbsp;Kirshenbaum</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Our project has pursued an exciting new path in biomimetic chemistry. The outcomes of the project have identified new ways to design synthetic molecules to fold and function like proteins. Nature uses proteins to meet an astonishing variety of different tasks within the cell. Chemists aspire to learn how to craft large molecules with similar sophisticated functions. In order to do so, we have studied a promising new family of chain-like molecules called peptoids. Peptoids resemble proteins in many ways, but because they are completely synthetic, they are resistant to degradation and can be generated with a vast array of different chemical features.   Intellectual Merit  During the course of our project, we  advanced our ability to create a robust and predictable relationship between the structure and function of folded peptoid oligomers. This has allowed us to identify a number of valuable new applications for peptoids. For example, we have learned how to build cyclic peptoids that are constrained to adopt pre-determined three-dimensional forms. We demonstrated that that these cyclic peptoids could bind to the surface of a protein involved in driving the growth of prostate cancer. We were excited to publish a high profile report that indicated the early potential of the peptoid to block the growth of cancerous cells. In another example, we designed peptoid molecules that can complex therapeutic nucleic acids and facilitate their deliver to the interior of a cell, where it can alter gene expression patterns. Both of these outcomes, along with a range of other exciting results during the project period, establish the potential of peptoids to address a variety of challenges in biomedical sciences and materials chemistry.      Broader Impacts:  We have embraced a range of activities that address the broader impacts criteria established by the NSF. These include: enabling technology transfer to non-academic partners; training of chemists at all levels, from high school students to post-doctoral scholars; efforts to foster an international community of chemists devoted to exploring peptoids and other biomimetic macromolecules; and science outreach activities in macromolecular chemistry, particularly at the interface of chemistry and cuisine.  We developed a robust intellectual property portfolio that derives from this NSF sponsored project. Several of our peptoid patents have been licensed by industrial partners interested in establishing the commercial potential for these molecules.   We have inspired a cadre of young scientists  from diverse backgrounds to pursue the new field of biomimetic chemistry, and to delve into problems at the interface of chemical and biomedical sciences. Several of these researchers are on the path to become independent investigators, and are eager to develop their own creative notions about how to craft functional peptoid molecules.           Last Modified: 03/12/2020       Submitted by: Kent Kirshenbaum]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
