<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>RUI: Norfolk State University's Research Participation in GlueX and CLAS12 at Jefferson Lab</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2015</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>135791.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>135791</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03010000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>PHY</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Physics</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Allena K. Opper</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>aopper@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032928958</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The neutrons and protons that make up the nucleus of every atom are themselves made up of constituent particles called quarks and gluons, and held together by what we call the strong nuclear force.  This award supports research to the study of the strong interactions between those elementary constituents of matter. More specifically, it is aimed at understanding the properties of the theory of the strong force, named Quantum Chromodynamics or QCD, at energies where nucleons are formed and it is most relevant,. To this end, the PI and the students supported by this award will perform experiments at The Thomas Jefferson National Accelerator Facility (Jefferson Lab,) in Newport News, VA. NSU faculty and undergraduate students will participate in the construction of hardware and in the analysis of data from experiments in the forefront of intermediate energy nuclear physics. Norfolk State University is one of the leading Historically Black Colleges and Universities. NSU graduates more African-American physics majors than all of the other Virginia universities combined. It is a goal of this project to strengthen the national participation of undergraduate minorities in nuclear and particle physics research.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;In the recent years, numerical solutions of QCD (Lattice-QCD) have provided with a mass spectrum of light-mass mesons. Therefore, it is time for improving our experimental determination of the poorly known light-mass meson spectrum to compare with predictions. Since the interaction carrier of the strong interaction, the gluon, is sensitive to the strong interaction, it is also possible that gluons can be externally observable in the meson spectrum as exotic mesons (particles made of a quark, an antiquark and a gluon). One main question in meson spectroscopy is: Can we find hints of the gluon in the meson spectrum?  The PI is analyzing data from meson spectroscopy experiments performed with the CEBAF Large Acceptance Spectrometer (CLAS) in Jefferson Lab's Hall B to search for those hints. He is also involved in two new experiments named GlueX and CLAS12, at the Jefferson Lab 12 GeV upgrade. Partial Wave Analysis (PWA) is the technique used for that analysis. The first PWA results have been published and more PWA results are progressing in several channels. The main work is in developing and upgrading new techniques of amplitude and partial wave analysis.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>09/04/2015</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/21/2017</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1507208</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Carlos</FirstName>
<LastName>Salgado</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>W</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Carlos W Salgado</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>salgado@jlab.org</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>7572697859</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000319502</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/04/2015</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Norfolk State University</Name>
<CityName>Norfolk</CityName>
<ZipCode>235048060</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>7578239053</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>700 Park Avenue</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[OSP; MCAR, Suite 601]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Virginia</StateName>
<StateCode>VA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>VA03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>074754805</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>NORFOLK STATE UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>003133790</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Norfolk State University]]></Name>
<CityName>Norfolk</CityName>
<StateCode>VA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>235048060</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[700 Park Avenue]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Virginia</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>VA03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1232</Code>
<Text>Nuclear &amp; Hadron Quantum Chrom</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9229</Code>
<Text>RES IN UNDERGRAD INST-RESEARCH</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9251</Code>
<Text>REU SUPP-Res Exp for Ugrd Supp</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0115</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0116</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0117</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2015~45079</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2016~45223</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2017~45489</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><div class="page" title="Page 1"> <div class="section"> <div class="layoutArea"> <div class="column"><!-- p.p1 {margin: 0.0px 0.0px 0.0px 0.0px; font: 12.0px 'Helvetica Neue'; color: #454545} --> <p class="p1">Norfolk State University (NSU) has participated for many years on the study of the sub-atomic structure of matter at the Thomas Jefferson National Accelerator Facility (JLab) in Newport News, Virginia. This particular project was performed from 2015 to 2018 as collaborators in the GlueX and MesonEx (CLAS12) experiments at JLab. Those experiments were (and are) collecting data to allow for a better understanding of a new form of sub-atomic particles, called exotic mesons, that could greatly enlighten the interactions among quarks (the strong force). NSU faculty and undergraduate students participated in the construction of hardware, development of software and in the analysis of data from those experiments. More specifically, our group developed a software infrastructure to perform the analysis of photo-produced multi-particle final states from GlueX and MesonX. Our objective is to identify the exotic mesons studying their decay products and from them, determine their properties (quantum numbers).<span>&nbsp; </span>To perform this analysis we explored new statistical techniques, hardware options and software programing.<span>&nbsp; </span>Exotic mesons are important because they will show an external manifestation of the strong force that otherwise is confined inside the particles. NSU is one of the leading Historically Black Colleges and Universities (HBCU). HBCU's have been more successful than majority institutions in retaining minority students at the undergraduate level.<span>&nbsp; </span>A key objective of the project was to provide research experiences to undergraduate students. A total of nine students were trained and involved in the project. The undergraduate participation corresponded with our goal of strengthen the participation of underrepresented minorities in nuclear and particle physics research.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> </div> </div> </div> </div><br> <p>            Last Modified: 12/09/2018<br>      Modified by: Carlos&nbsp;W&nbsp;Salgado</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[    Norfolk State University (NSU) has participated for many years on the study of the sub-atomic structure of matter at the Thomas Jefferson National Accelerator Facility (JLab) in Newport News, Virginia. This particular project was performed from 2015 to 2018 as collaborators in the GlueX and MesonEx (CLAS12) experiments at JLab. Those experiments were (and are) collecting data to allow for a better understanding of a new form of sub-atomic particles, called exotic mesons, that could greatly enlighten the interactions among quarks (the strong force). NSU faculty and undergraduate students participated in the construction of hardware, development of software and in the analysis of data from those experiments. More specifically, our group developed a software infrastructure to perform the analysis of photo-produced multi-particle final states from GlueX and MesonX. Our objective is to identify the exotic mesons studying their decay products and from them, determine their properties (quantum numbers).  To perform this analysis we explored new statistical techniques, hardware options and software programing.  Exotic mesons are important because they will show an external manifestation of the strong force that otherwise is confined inside the particles. NSU is one of the leading Historically Black Colleges and Universities (HBCU). HBCU's have been more successful than majority institutions in retaining minority students at the undergraduate level.  A key objective of the project was to provide research experiences to undergraduate students. A total of nine students were trained and involved in the project. The undergraduate participation corresponded with our goal of strengthen the participation of underrepresented minorities in nuclear and particle physics research.              Last Modified: 12/09/2018       Submitted by: Carlos W Salgado]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
