<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Supramolecular Chemistry of Amyloidogenic Peptides</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2015</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>465000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>465000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03090000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CHE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Chemistry</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Max Funk</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>mfunk@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032920000</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>With this award, the Chemistry of Life Processes Program in the Division of Chemistry is funding Professor James Nowick of the University of California-Irvine to utilize chemical synthesis to create model systems that assemble in the same fashion as the more complex biomolecules, and thereby serve as model systems for the aggregation of proteins.  Molecular assemblies known as amyloid assemblies formed by peptides and proteins have been implicated in a variety of diseases, such as Alzheimer's disease, frontotemporal dementias, Parkinson's disease, and type 2 diabetes. This project seeks to learn more about the structures of these amyloid oligomers.  The  chemical model systems being generated have the advantage that they can form  crystals, allowing the structures of the oligomers to be determined with exquisite precision by X-ray crystallography. By determining the structures of these chemical model systems, the researchers will gain insights into the molecular assemblies formed by associated peptides and proteins. This project will achieve broader impact through the knowledge gained in the research, the training of students at the graduate and undergraduate level, K-12 educational outreach, and contributions to STEM education. Graduate students and undergraduates who assist in the project will receive training value cross-disciplinary training.  A large number K-12 students are being targeted through the UCI Chemistry Outreach Program. The PI will continue to contribute to STEM education on the US and global level through UCI's OpenChem Initiative, by teaching and creating video content for the public. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The Nowick research group has developed a new strategy to elucidate the structures of oligomers formed by amyloidogenic peptides: incorporating the peptides into macrocycles and using a single N-methyl group to prevent uncontrolled aggregation to fibrils. The resulting macrocyclic beta-sheet peptides assemble to form well-defined oligomers, and a sizeable fraction of the peptides form crystals suitable for X-ray crystallography. This approach will be used to elucidate the structures of oligomers from amyloidogenic peptides derived from the protein tau, the protein alpha-synuclein, and the islet amyloid polypeptide (IAPP, amylin). The structures of the oligomers that form will be determined at atomic resolution by X-ray crystallography, and the crystallographic structures of the oligomers will be correlated with the oligomerization state in solution by size-exclusion chromatography and other techniques such as NMR spectroscopy. The relationship between the biological properties of these oligomers and those of natural amyloidogenic peptides and proteins will be assessed by dot-blot assays. These studies aim to provide a better understanding of the relationship between oligomer sequence and three dimensional structure, and the implications of these upon stability and biological properties.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/29/2015</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/27/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1507840</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>James</FirstName>
<LastName>Nowick</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>S</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>James S Nowick</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>jsnowick@uci.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>9498246091</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000161366</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/29/2015</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of California-Irvine</Name>
<CityName>Irvine</CityName>
<ZipCode>926977600</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>9498247295</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>160 Aldrich Hall</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT/>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG/>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>046705849</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF CALIFORNIA, IRVINE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>071549000</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of California-Irvine]]></Name>
<CityName>Irvine</CityName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>926972025</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[Department of Chemistry]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>45</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF/>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>6883</Code>
<Text>Chemistry of Life Processes</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0115</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0116</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2015~305000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2016~160000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The research objective of grant CHE-1507840, titled &ldquo;Supramolecular Assembly of Amyloid Oligomers&rdquo; was to learn more about the structures of amyloid oligomers through the use of chemical model systems based on macrocyclic &beta;-sheet peptides. Amyloid oligomers are the toxic and damaging assemblies of proteins associated with amyloid diseases, such as Alzheimer&rsquo;s disease and type 2 diabetes.</p> <p>Broader impact was achieved through training graduate and undergraduate students in research, educational outreach to K&ndash;12 schools through the UCI Chemistry Outreach Program, and creating full videos of the upper-division course <em>Advanced Organic Chemistry</em> and by making this video content available to viewers in the US and around the world through YouTube and UCI's <em>OpenCourseWare</em> website.</p> <p>Under the support of CHE-1507840, my laboratory gained insights into the structures of the oligomers and other supramolecular assemblies formed by amyloidogenic peptides and proteins, and we disseminated our findings through publications and talks at meetings and at other academic institutions. In these studies, we incorporated aggregation-prone fragments of amyloidogenic peptides and proteins into macrocyclic &beta;-sheet peptides and probed their assembly through X-ray crystallography and NMR spectroscopy. Two patterns of supramolecular assembly emerged from these studies: the formation of compact oligomers composed of dimer or trimer subunits, and the formation of extended fibril-like networks containing layered &beta;-sheets.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 08/06/2021<br>      Modified by: James&nbsp;S&nbsp;Nowick</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The research objective of grant CHE-1507840, titled "Supramolecular Assembly of Amyloid Oligomers" was to learn more about the structures of amyloid oligomers through the use of chemical model systems based on macrocyclic &beta;-sheet peptides. Amyloid oligomers are the toxic and damaging assemblies of proteins associated with amyloid diseases, such as Alzheimer’s disease and type 2 diabetes.  Broader impact was achieved through training graduate and undergraduate students in research, educational outreach to K&ndash;12 schools through the UCI Chemistry Outreach Program, and creating full videos of the upper-division course Advanced Organic Chemistry and by making this video content available to viewers in the US and around the world through YouTube and UCI's OpenCourseWare website.  Under the support of CHE-1507840, my laboratory gained insights into the structures of the oligomers and other supramolecular assemblies formed by amyloidogenic peptides and proteins, and we disseminated our findings through publications and talks at meetings and at other academic institutions. In these studies, we incorporated aggregation-prone fragments of amyloidogenic peptides and proteins into macrocyclic &beta;-sheet peptides and probed their assembly through X-ray crystallography and NMR spectroscopy. Two patterns of supramolecular assembly emerged from these studies: the formation of compact oligomers composed of dimer or trimer subunits, and the formation of extended fibril-like networks containing layered &beta;-sheets.          Last Modified: 08/06/2021       Submitted by: James S Nowick]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
