<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Macromolecular juggling by a prokaryotic Fe-S assembly system</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2015</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>480000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>480000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03090000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CHE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Chemistry</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Catalina Achim</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>cachim@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922048</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>With this award, The Chemistry of Life Processes Program in the Chemistry Division is funding Dr. David Barondeau from Texas A&amp;M University to investigate the enzymology of iron-sulfur (Fe-S) cluster biosynthesis. Iron-sulfur (Fe-S) clusters are one of the most versatile auxiliary cofactors used by proteins to facilitate biological processes, and there are literally hundreds of different examples.  Many of these Fe-S proteins have unknown functions.  Remarkably, despite tremendous diversity in the structures of these proteins, conserved sets of assembly proteins serve to build and deliver Fe-S clusters to all Fe-S containing proteins.  These elaborate multi-component systems have evolved to protect organisms from the toxic effects of free iron and sulfide ions while promoting the efficient biosynthesis of these cofactors.   One of the major limitations in studying Fe-S cluster biosynthesis has been the lack of specific probes that allow real-time analysis of cluster synthesis and transfer reactions. To overcome this limitation, labeling methods were developed that directly report on Fe-S content for labeled proteins in a background of unlabeled Fe-S proteins and other species. This methodology facilitates advanced time dependent experiments with complex Fe-S assembly assays, which are required for the rigorous evaluation of the role of protein components in Fe-S cluster biosynthetic pathways. This project will train graduate and undergraduate students in biochemical methods, protein labeling, and enzymology. High school students will also gain exposure to science.  Overall, the proposed studies outlined in this grant are designed to provide insight into the chemistry of this important assembly pathway and generate robust tools that will be useful in investigating the function of other Fe-S containing systems.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Currently, there is limited mechanistic information about how this system synthesizes different types of Fe-S clusters, identifies and discriminates protein targets for cluster transfer, and mediates ligand exchange from the assembly complex to target proteins.  Fluorescent tagging approaches were developed in which the fluorescence is sensitive to different cluster types, ligand environments, and cluster oxidation states.  This fluorescent reporter technology will be instrumental in untangling the intricate network of transfer pathways and identifying factors affecting flux through branch points.  High sensitivity, suitability with high-throughput methodology, and compatibility with anaerobic techniques are additional benefits of this approach.  Here a complex biosynthetic assay will be developed and used to test specific hypotheses for the roles of accessory proteins, chaperones, and regulatory proteins in Fe-S cluster biosynthesis.  Fluorophore labels also permit anisotropy experiments that monitor protein association and dissociation during cluster assembly and transfer reactions.  This fluorophore labeling methodology will contribute to the study of Fe-S cluster biosynthesis by tracking both the composition of the protein complex and the protein the Fe-S cluster is bound to during transfer reactions.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/08/2015</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/29/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1508269</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>David</FirstName>
<LastName>Barondeau</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>P</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>David P Barondeau</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>barondeau@tamu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>9796902816</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000499920</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/08/2015</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Texas A&amp;M University</Name>
<CityName>College Station</CityName>
<ZipCode>778454375</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>9798626777</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>400 Harvey Mitchell Pkwy South</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[Suite 300]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Texas</StateName>
<StateCode>TX</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>17</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>TX17</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>020271826</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>TEXAS A &amp; M UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>042915991</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Texas A&M University Main Campus]]></Name>
<CityName>College Station</CityName>
<StateCode>TX</StateCode>
<ZipCode>778423012</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[301 Old Main Drive]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Texas</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>17</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>TX17</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>6883</Code>
<Text>Chemistry of Life Processes</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1982</Code>
<Text>BIOLOGICAL CHEMISTRY</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9183</Code>
<Text>GENERAL FOUNDATIONS OF BIOTECHNOLOGY</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0115</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0116</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2015~320000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2016~160000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Iron-sulfur (Fe-S) clusters are protein cofactors that are essential for most life forms. These cofactors have key roles in energy generation and the synthesis of DNA, proteins, metabolites, natural products, and other protein cofactors. The ISC biosynthetic pathway first facilitates the formation of iron-sulfur clusters on an assembly complex and then transfers these clusters to target proteins using an elaborate distribution network. A detailed understanding of this Fe-S cluster biosynthetic pathway might enable metabolic engineering efforts in prokaryotes to produce natural products and other commodities, selectively inhibit pathogenic organisms, and, since defects in this pathway are directly linked to human disease, the development of therapeutics. Despite this importance, many mechanistic details for the Fe-S assembly pathway have remained elusive. The goals of this project were to develop and apply new tools to investigate and provide insight into this important process. First, our team applied time-resolved methods, both stopped-flow UV-Vis spectroscopy and native mass spectrometry, to track the development and decay of intermediates in the assembly of Fe-S clusters. The cysteine desulfurase enzyme catalyzes a reaction that provides sulfur for the synthesis of Fe-S clusters. We found that the development and decay of certain sulfur-based intermediates associated with the cysteine desulfurase were accelerated by the Friedreich&rsquo;s ataxia protein frataxin in the eukaryotic system but unaffected by the equivalent protein in the prokaryotic system. To explain this result, we provided the first crystal structure and electron microscopy reconstructions of a mitochondrial cysteine desulfurase enzyme complex. The structure revealed a very different architecture from the prokaryotic enzyme and a rationale for the functional differences between the two systems. We also used a novel native mass spectrometric approach to provide evidence for iron-based intermediates in cluster synthesis. Second, our team developed new fluorophore labeling approaches to track the transfer of iron-sulfur clusters. These tools allowed the unprecedented tracking of iron-sulfur cluster transfer reactions in complex networks, the identification of protein-based [2Fe-2S] cluster intermediates, and the roles of components in the cluster distribution pathway. In addition, our team trained undergraduate students from both Texas A&amp;M University and other schools in anaerobic biochemistry and structural biology, provided outreach with public lectures during local library and Texas A&amp;M University chemistry open house events, and performed chemistry-based demonstrations at local child advocacy and open house events aimed at pre-high school age individuals.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 12/13/2019<br>      Modified by: David&nbsp;P&nbsp;Barondeau</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Iron-sulfur (Fe-S) clusters are protein cofactors that are essential for most life forms. These cofactors have key roles in energy generation and the synthesis of DNA, proteins, metabolites, natural products, and other protein cofactors. The ISC biosynthetic pathway first facilitates the formation of iron-sulfur clusters on an assembly complex and then transfers these clusters to target proteins using an elaborate distribution network. A detailed understanding of this Fe-S cluster biosynthetic pathway might enable metabolic engineering efforts in prokaryotes to produce natural products and other commodities, selectively inhibit pathogenic organisms, and, since defects in this pathway are directly linked to human disease, the development of therapeutics. Despite this importance, many mechanistic details for the Fe-S assembly pathway have remained elusive. The goals of this project were to develop and apply new tools to investigate and provide insight into this important process. First, our team applied time-resolved methods, both stopped-flow UV-Vis spectroscopy and native mass spectrometry, to track the development and decay of intermediates in the assembly of Fe-S clusters. The cysteine desulfurase enzyme catalyzes a reaction that provides sulfur for the synthesis of Fe-S clusters. We found that the development and decay of certain sulfur-based intermediates associated with the cysteine desulfurase were accelerated by the Friedreich’s ataxia protein frataxin in the eukaryotic system but unaffected by the equivalent protein in the prokaryotic system. To explain this result, we provided the first crystal structure and electron microscopy reconstructions of a mitochondrial cysteine desulfurase enzyme complex. The structure revealed a very different architecture from the prokaryotic enzyme and a rationale for the functional differences between the two systems. We also used a novel native mass spectrometric approach to provide evidence for iron-based intermediates in cluster synthesis. Second, our team developed new fluorophore labeling approaches to track the transfer of iron-sulfur clusters. These tools allowed the unprecedented tracking of iron-sulfur cluster transfer reactions in complex networks, the identification of protein-based [2Fe-2S] cluster intermediates, and the roles of components in the cluster distribution pathway. In addition, our team trained undergraduate students from both Texas A&amp;M University and other schools in anaerobic biochemistry and structural biology, provided outreach with public lectures during local library and Texas A&amp;M University chemistry open house events, and performed chemistry-based demonstrations at local child advocacy and open house events aimed at pre-high school age individuals.          Last Modified: 12/13/2019       Submitted by: David P Barondeau]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
