<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Hindered Urea Bond Based Dynamic Chemistry and Polymer Synthesis</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>06/15/2015</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>11/30/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>220000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>220000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03090000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CHE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Chemistry</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Lin He</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>lhe@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924956</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>With this award, the Macromolecular, Supramolecular and Nanochemistry Program of the Division of Chemistry is supporting Professor Jianjun Cheng of the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign to investigate the reversible bond-forming and bond-breaking processes of a novel type of polymers.  Polymers containing reversible dynamic bonds may possess very useful properties such as self-healing, shape memory and environmental adaptation.  For example, when there is a crack in the polymeric materials, polymers bearing dynamic bonds may allow self-repairing of the crack and restoration of material?s original mechanical strength.  The knowledge gained from this research is disseminated through various endeavors including publications in scientific journals and presentations in summer camp programs and Engineering Open-House at the University of Illinois.  This project provides research training opportunity to graduate and undergraduate students, including members of underrepresented groups, in the areas of organic synthesis and polymer chemistry.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The reaction of an isocyanate and an amine is one of the most classical reactions in polymer chemistry that allows the preparation of polyurea, an inexpensive, widely used engineering polymer with very stable bulk property.  While urea bond is a very robust covalent bond, it can be weakened by the presence of bulky substituent on one of the nitrogen atoms of the urea group because of bond distortion.  Hindered urea bonds (HUBs) may undergo both fast association and dissociation reactions.  Professor Cheng's group systematically studies the bond association and dissociation properties of various hindered urea structures, optimizes the dynamicity, and explores the properties and applications of HUB-bearing polymers. This work aims to yield polyureas and poly(urethane-urea)s capable of dynamic property change and autonomous repairing at low temperature without catalysts.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>05/16/2015</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/16/2015</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1508710</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Jianjun</FirstName>
<LastName>Cheng</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Jianjun Cheng</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>jianjunc@uiuc.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2172443924</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000064367</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/16/2015</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign</Name>
<CityName>Champaign</CityName>
<ZipCode>618207406</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2173332187</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1901 South First Street</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[Suite A]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Illinois</StateName>
<StateCode>IL</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>13</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>IL13</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>041544081</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF ILLINOIS</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>041544081</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign]]></Name>
<CityName>Urbana</CityName>
<StateCode>IL</StateCode>
<ZipCode>618013620</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[506 S Wright Street]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Illinois</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>13</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>IL13</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>6885</Code>
<Text>Macromolec/Supramolec/Nano</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0115</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2015~220000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p class="TAMainText">Dynamic covalent bonds (DCBs) featuring reversible bonding/debonding properties have found various applications in dynamic combinational library, self-assembly, and dynamic polymers design such as self-healing, malleable, shape-memory or environmentally-adaptive materials<a title="Wojtecki, 2011 #44" href="file:///C:/Users/peter/Desktop/Project%20outcomes.docx#_ENREF_6"></a>. However, most DCBs developed so far require either catalyst or harsh environmental conditions to facilitate bond reversion and dynamic property change in bulk materials. Furthermore, these chemistries usually involve special building blocks, which are uncommonly seen and costly to make in industry.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>We previously successfully developed a new type of dynamic covalent chemistry named &lsquo;hindered urea bond (HUB)&rsquo;. By tweaking the structure of conventional urea bond with an additional hindered substituent on the nitrogen atom, the bond is weakened and shows reversible bonding/debonding process. HUB tackles issues described above and shows advantages over most currently used DCBs, which may open up the broad use of DCBs in the future. Supported by CHE-MSN award (CHE-1508710), we gained better understanding and explored more potential of HUB chemistry through systematic study through the following three aspects as we proposed: 1) We studied combination of isocyanate and amine to examine the effect of various factors to the dynamic properties of HUB, including aromaticity, substituent bulkiness, induction effect, hydrogen bonding, etc. Especially, we found that the aromatic isocyanate gives HUB with higher binding constants and dissociation kinetics. This is extremely important for future designs of more thermodynamically stable but more dynamic materials. We also found that the hydrogen bonding can slow down the dynamic properties of the HUBs, which provides another way to tune the dynamicity of HUBs other than substituents hinderness. We also studied the response of HUBs to various triggers. We demonstrated that the HUBs respond to water, amine, or hydrogen peroxide to either degrade or stabilize. This shows HUB to be promising in the designs of trigger responsive materials; 2) We studied more behaviors of HUBs in polymeric materials. We examined the dynamic exchange of HUBs in polymeric chains, and developed various applications by taking advantages of the reversible properties, such as malleable thermosets, hot-melt adhesives, sacrificial materials, shape memory polymers, and 3D printing materials. We also tackle an important technical issue in the applications of HUB materials. Previous HUB polymers show severe degradation problems at high temperature, which is extremely harmful for thermal processing. However, by tuning of monomer structure, the problem is well solved, and the thermal stability of HUB polymers is significantly enhanced. We also gained further understanding of the ring chain equilibriums in the HUB polymers, and developed a novel one-component precursor to cure the polyurea materials; 3) We developed two new methods to remove the hindered substituents and turn off the dynamic properties of HUBs. These are significant in the applications which require the shutdown of reversible exchange of HUBs after the final target states have been achieved, for example, in the macrocycle synthesis. Overall, during the life of the award period, the whole picture of HUB behaviors including reversible exchange, triggered responsiveness, dynamic properties tuning, etc. in small molecules, linear polymer, and crosslinked polymers is more clear to us. It is very important for the HUB chemistry to become the platform for future DCBs materials designs and applications for us and other research groups.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 01/06/2018<br>      Modified by: Jianjun&nbsp;Cheng</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[Dynamic covalent bonds (DCBs) featuring reversible bonding/debonding properties have found various applications in dynamic combinational library, self-assembly, and dynamic polymers design such as self-healing, malleable, shape-memory or environmentally-adaptive materials. However, most DCBs developed so far require either catalyst or harsh environmental conditions to facilitate bond reversion and dynamic property change in bulk materials. Furthermore, these chemistries usually involve special building blocks, which are uncommonly seen and costly to make in industry.     We previously successfully developed a new type of dynamic covalent chemistry named ?hindered urea bond (HUB)?. By tweaking the structure of conventional urea bond with an additional hindered substituent on the nitrogen atom, the bond is weakened and shows reversible bonding/debonding process. HUB tackles issues described above and shows advantages over most currently used DCBs, which may open up the broad use of DCBs in the future. Supported by CHE-MSN award (CHE-1508710), we gained better understanding and explored more potential of HUB chemistry through systematic study through the following three aspects as we proposed: 1) We studied combination of isocyanate and amine to examine the effect of various factors to the dynamic properties of HUB, including aromaticity, substituent bulkiness, induction effect, hydrogen bonding, etc. Especially, we found that the aromatic isocyanate gives HUB with higher binding constants and dissociation kinetics. This is extremely important for future designs of more thermodynamically stable but more dynamic materials. We also found that the hydrogen bonding can slow down the dynamic properties of the HUBs, which provides another way to tune the dynamicity of HUBs other than substituents hinderness. We also studied the response of HUBs to various triggers. We demonstrated that the HUBs respond to water, amine, or hydrogen peroxide to either degrade or stabilize. This shows HUB to be promising in the designs of trigger responsive materials; 2) We studied more behaviors of HUBs in polymeric materials. We examined the dynamic exchange of HUBs in polymeric chains, and developed various applications by taking advantages of the reversible properties, such as malleable thermosets, hot-melt adhesives, sacrificial materials, shape memory polymers, and 3D printing materials. We also tackle an important technical issue in the applications of HUB materials. Previous HUB polymers show severe degradation problems at high temperature, which is extremely harmful for thermal processing. However, by tuning of monomer structure, the problem is well solved, and the thermal stability of HUB polymers is significantly enhanced. We also gained further understanding of the ring chain equilibriums in the HUB polymers, and developed a novel one-component precursor to cure the polyurea materials; 3) We developed two new methods to remove the hindered substituents and turn off the dynamic properties of HUBs. These are significant in the applications which require the shutdown of reversible exchange of HUBs after the final target states have been achieved, for example, in the macrocycle synthesis. Overall, during the life of the award period, the whole picture of HUB behaviors including reversible exchange, triggered responsiveness, dynamic properties tuning, etc. in small molecules, linear polymer, and crosslinked polymers is more clear to us. It is very important for the HUB chemistry to become the platform for future DCBs materials designs and applications for us and other research groups.             Last Modified: 01/06/2018       Submitted by: Jianjun Cheng]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
