<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Contingency-Constrained Unit Commitment with High Penetration of Intermittent Renewables</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2015</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>360000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>360000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07010000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>ECCS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Electrical, Commun &amp; Cyber Sys</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Radhakisan Baheti</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Reliability is a major concern for power systems, and engineers have been striving hard to keep lights on under all kinds of uncertainty, including contingencies caused by a sudden failure of a generator or a transmission line. The North American Electric Reliability Corporation (NERC) N-1 rule requires that no such single failure should result in system infeasibility, and this rule has been embedded in certain versions of the unit commitment process. The resulting contingency-constrained unit commitment(CCUC) is extremely complex, and the issue is now compounded by the drastic increase in intermittent renewables such as wind or solar. In Spain, for example, it is not uncommon that a drop of wind generation within just a few hours is equivalent to the shutdown of four nuclear units, and this has presented major challenges to system operators. Consideration of contingencies in the presence of intermittent renewables is thus a critical and urgent issue. In collaboration with ISO-NE, Southern California Edison and Alstom Grid, this proposal is on CCUC with high penetration of intermittent renewables. The problem is challenging in view of different types of uncertainties and their magnitudes, the large number of contingencies, the combinatorial nature of mixed-integer optimization, and the largeness of power systems. Our focus will be on novel formulations of interval CCUC, and on advanced optimization methods. The proposed research will have the broader impacts on managing other uncertainties, e.g., N-2 contingencies, and on other complex problems such as microgrid energy optimization. For these problems, difficulties associated with uncertain weather, electricity demand and microgrid-associated intermittent renewables can be modeled by the interval formulation. The resulting mixed-integer linear optimization problems can then benefit from our advanced optimization methods. Furthermore, the research will educate graduate and undergraduate students and professionals through courses, seminars, publications and online materials.  It will also benefit high school students through their teachers? involvement in the daVinci summer project at UConn. The participations of under-represented groups will be actively sought.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Specifically, Task 1 is on formulating CCUC for the co-optimization of energy and reserve considering N-1 contingencies and intermittent renewables. The novel idea lies in using intervals to describe transmission contingencies based on generation shift factors (GSFs), as opposed to analyzing contingencies one at a time. A line flow is a weighted sum of net nodal injections, where weights are GSFs. When a transmission line is tripped, GSFs will be changed. Various transmission contingencies can thus be described by varying values of GSFs, and be modeled by intervals. Conservativeness of this modeling will be alleviated through shrinking ranges of GSFs based on identifying and eliminating redundant contingency transmission constraints, and through improving interval arithmetic, e.g., by using affine arithmetic. Generator contingencies and intermittent renewables will then be incorporated within the interval optimization framework. To effectively solve the problem, Task 2 is on developing a new generation of optimization methods. The key is to synergistically integrate our latest surrogate Lagrangian relaxation(SLR), which exploits separability, with branch-and-cut, which exploits linearity. While SLR requires iterations, by novel exploitation of the invariant nature of subproblem convex hulls across iterations, the overall CPU time and solution quality will be drastically improved. In addition, parallel implementation of our approach will be explored. The method will be tested using realistic data sets from ISO-NE and CAISO.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/06/2015</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/06/2015</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1509666</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Peter</FirstName>
<LastName>Luh</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>B</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Peter B Luh</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>peter.luh@uconn.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>8604864821</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000092152</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/06/2015</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Connecticut</Name>
<CityName>Storrs</CityName>
<ZipCode>062691133</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>8604863622</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>438 Whitney Road Ext.</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[Unit 1133]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Connecticut</StateName>
<StateCode>CT</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CT02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>614209054</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF CONNECTICUT</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>004534830</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Connecticut]]></Name>
<CityName>Storrs</CityName>
<StateCode>CT</StateCode>
<ZipCode>062694157</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[371 Fairfield Way]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Connecticut</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CT02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7607</Code>
<Text>EPCN-Energy-Power-Ctrl-Netwrks</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>092E</Code>
<Text>Control systems &amp; applications</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>155E</Code>
<Text>Electric power networks</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0115</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2015~360000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>This project is to enable optimized integration of renewable resources such as wind and solar into the power grid alongside with conventional power generating units to keep lights on at all times.&nbsp; Major challenges to achieve this goal are the largeness of the power grids (e.g., the Midcontinent Independent System Operator operates more than a thousand generators and fifteen thousand virtual transactions), the largeness of the associated problems, uncertainties of the renewable generation, and the combinatorial complexity in view of the presence of many discrete decision variables.&nbsp; Our innovative Markovian approach successfully overcame modeling difficulties introduced by uncertainties through exploiting the memoryless property of Markov chains so as to predict future wind or solar generation by only knowing the current state without the need to consider the past.&nbsp; The overall formulation is linear, with a mix of discrete and real decision variables.&nbsp; To solve the problem, our innovative decomposition and coordination approach successfully overcomes the solution process complexity by decomposing the problem into smaller subproblems, which are solved with drastically reduced complexity.&nbsp; Subproblem solutions are then iteratively coordinated according to the market economy concept of demand and supply, e.g., prices are increased when there is a shortage of power to incentivize generation.&nbsp; To accelerate convergence, ?absolute-value? penalties are introduced to ?push? violations of constraints to zero fast.&nbsp; On top of the above, formulation tightening, a critically important but much overlooked direction, is also explored.&nbsp; The idea is that if constraints of a subproblem can be transformed to directly delineate the subproblem convex hull (i.e., the formulation is ?tight?), then these subproblems can be directly solved by using linear programming methods without combinatorial difficulties.&nbsp; We developed, for the first time, an innovative and systematic approach to tighten unit subproblem formulations in the data pre-process stage.&nbsp; The idea is to derive vertices of the convex hull without binary requirements.&nbsp; From them, vertices of the original convex hull can be innovatively obtained.&nbsp; These vertices are converted to tightened constraints, which are then parameterized based on unit parameters for general use, tremendously reducing online computational requirements.&nbsp; The project resulted in many publications, some of which come with optimization codes that can be readily adopted and generalized for various optimization purposes.&nbsp; The results have also been presented at many conferences, workshops, invited seminars, and at UConn School of Engineering?s annual da Vinci workshop to educate high school teachers and counselors so as to pass the knowledge and excitement to high school students.&nbsp; &nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 10/30/2019<br>      Modified by: Peter&nbsp;B&nbsp;Luh</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ This project is to enable optimized integration of renewable resources such as wind and solar into the power grid alongside with conventional power generating units to keep lights on at all times.  Major challenges to achieve this goal are the largeness of the power grids (e.g., the Midcontinent Independent System Operator operates more than a thousand generators and fifteen thousand virtual transactions), the largeness of the associated problems, uncertainties of the renewable generation, and the combinatorial complexity in view of the presence of many discrete decision variables.  Our innovative Markovian approach successfully overcame modeling difficulties introduced by uncertainties through exploiting the memoryless property of Markov chains so as to predict future wind or solar generation by only knowing the current state without the need to consider the past.  The overall formulation is linear, with a mix of discrete and real decision variables.  To solve the problem, our innovative decomposition and coordination approach successfully overcomes the solution process complexity by decomposing the problem into smaller subproblems, which are solved with drastically reduced complexity.  Subproblem solutions are then iteratively coordinated according to the market economy concept of demand and supply, e.g., prices are increased when there is a shortage of power to incentivize generation.  To accelerate convergence, ?absolute-value? penalties are introduced to ?push? violations of constraints to zero fast.  On top of the above, formulation tightening, a critically important but much overlooked direction, is also explored.  The idea is that if constraints of a subproblem can be transformed to directly delineate the subproblem convex hull (i.e., the formulation is ?tight?), then these subproblems can be directly solved by using linear programming methods without combinatorial difficulties.  We developed, for the first time, an innovative and systematic approach to tighten unit subproblem formulations in the data pre-process stage.  The idea is to derive vertices of the convex hull without binary requirements.  From them, vertices of the original convex hull can be innovatively obtained.  These vertices are converted to tightened constraints, which are then parameterized based on unit parameters for general use, tremendously reducing online computational requirements.  The project resulted in many publications, some of which come with optimization codes that can be readily adopted and generalized for various optimization purposes.  The results have also been presented at many conferences, workshops, invited seminars, and at UConn School of Engineering?s annual da Vinci workshop to educate high school teachers and counselors so as to pass the knowledge and excitement to high school students.             Last Modified: 10/30/2019       Submitted by: Peter B Luh]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
