<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>UNS: Collaborative Research: 30%-Efficient III-V/Silicon Tandem Solar Cells</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/15/2015</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>140850.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>140850</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07020000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CBET</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Chem, Bioeng, Env, &amp; Transp Sys</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Carole Read</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>cread@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922418</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>PI:  Minjoo Larry Lee / Zachary C. Holman&lt;br/&gt;Proposal Number:  1509687/ 1509864&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The sun represents the most abundant potential source of sustainable energy on earth.  Currently, solar cells based on crystalline silicon materials dominate the photovoltaics market for production of electricity from the sun because they offer the highest solar energy conversion efficiency at the lowest manufacturing cost.  However, to accelerate the penetration of solar energy in the renewable electricity market, the solar energy conversion efficiency of silicon-based solar cells must ultimately increase beyond its practical limit of 24%.  The goal of this project is develop a silicon-based solar cell which contains Group III and V elements from the Periodic Table, arranged in layers which have the potential to increase the solar energy conversion efficiency to 30%.  The fundamental science underlying the performance of this the III-V/silicon tandem cell will be used to develop the best strategy for eventual manufacture.   As part of the educational activities of this project, the principal investigators will be actively involved in an outreach program that seeks to broaden the participation of under-represented groups in engineering by using solar research as a platform for involvement in both technical and career-development sessions at Veterans meetings and the Society of Hispanic Professional Engineers conference.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Photovoltaic devices that contain multiple p-n junctions are currently the only route to achieve solar energy conversion efficiencies that exceed the Shockley-Queisser single p-n junction limit that caps the theoretical performance of crystalline silicon solar cells currently in commercial use.  The overall goal of this proposed research is to develop a fundamental understanding of two-terminal tandem solar cell performance through controlled growth of Group III-V elements on silicon. The fabrication strategy is guided by fundamental studies and is designed to optimize the material and device architecture to achieve 30% solar energy conversion efficiency, which is beyond the 24% practical limit of single-junction crystalline silicon solar cells. Towards this end, the model Group III-V material selected for study is GaAsP, since it has a direct and tunable bandgap, and can be grown on a transparent, compositionally graded buffer on a GaP/Si template. The bottom cell of the tandem device will be based on an amorphous silicon/crystalline silicon heterojunction solar cell, where the front amorphous silicon layers will be replaced with the GaP template layer upon which the top cell is grown.  The research plan has three objectives. The first objective is to understand and control the formation of threading dislocations in the GaAsP absorber, and to develop optimized window and back-surface field layers for the top cell that will both increase transmission into the GaAsP absorber and reduce surface recombination. The second objective is to understand and improve the passivation of GaP on silicon and the transport of electrons across the conduction band offset.  The third objective is to maximize the conversion of infrared light into current in the bottom cell by designing single-side light-trapping textures and dielectric/metal rear reflectors, and then tune the thicknesses, doping densities, and bandgaps of the III-V supporting layers to both form a recombination junction between the sub-cells and match their currents. The research outcomes will advance fundamental scientific understanding of multi-junction solar cell performance while developing fabrication strategies that will enable for scalable industrial manufacture of devices potentially capable of delivering 30% solar energy conversion efficiency.  The principal investigators will also use the research outcomes to enhance instructional materials in photovoltaics course offerings at Yale University and Arizona State University.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/14/2015</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/14/2015</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1509864</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Zachary</FirstName>
<LastName>Holman</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>C</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Zachary C Holman</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>zachary.holman@asu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>4809659959</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000550302</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/14/2015</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Arizona State University</Name>
<CityName>TEMPE</CityName>
<ZipCode>852816011</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>4809655479</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>ORSPA</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[660 South Mill Avenue, Suite 310]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Arizona</StateName>
<StateCode>AZ</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>09</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>AZ09</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>943360412</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>ARIZONA STATE UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>806345658</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Arizona State University]]></Name>
<CityName>TEMPE</CityName>
<StateCode>AZ</StateCode>
<ZipCode>852876011</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[P.O. Box 876011]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Arizona</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>09</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>AZ09</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7644</Code>
<Text>EchemS-Electrochemical Systems</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>146E</Code>
<Text>Solar energy</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0115</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2015~140850</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Silicon solar cells have a maximum theoretical efficiency of 29.4%, and the only demonstrated approach to exceed this single-junction limit is to add junctions to form a tandem or multi-junction solar cell. The overarching goal of this project was thus to pave the way to the first 30% efficient III-V/Si two-terminal solar cell through fundamental investigation of two parallel problems. The first is to gain greater understanding of dislocations in GaAsP cells on silicon and how to design such cells for high efficiency; the second is to understand and design silicon solar cells that use GaP as the front-surface passivation layer while maximizing quantum efficiency in the near-infrared spectral range.</p> <p>The main technical challenge of III-V/Si tandem technology has historically been high threading dislocation density (TDD) in the III-V top cell, which in this project was composed of GaAsP tuned to a bandgap energy (E<sub>g</sub>) of 1.7 eV. The high TDD results from lattice mismatch between the silicon bottom cell and GaAsP top cell, and it causes high dark current, low open-circuit voltage (V<sub>oc</sub>), and low efficiency.</p> <p>Understand the origin of threading dislocations, and, therefore, controlling their formation during III-V growth, is critical to fabricate an efficient top cell. The well-known dislocation dynamics model proposed by Fitzgerald provides a general framework to achieve lower TDD: It predicts lower TDD with higher growth temperature due to higher dislocation glide velocities, and, in an ideal scenario, strain relaxation is accomplished by a low density of threads, each of which glides over long distances. However, the model neglects dislocation nucleation, which can lead to increased TDD if not managed properly.</p> <p>In this project, we first investigated the effect of growth temperature on TDD of thick, relaxed GaP buffer layers on GaP/Si templates, demonstrating the strong effect of growth temperature on dislocation nucleation and glide during initial relaxation. We then verified that the TDD of GaAsP/GaP/Si depends strongly on the TDD of the relaxed GaP buffer, underscoring the importance of controlling the initial strain relaxation in achieving high efficiency. Finally, through GaAsP graded buffer growth optimization, we demonstrated 11%-efficient, 1.7-eV GaAsP solar cells with record-low TDD of 4.0-4.6 x 10<sup>6</sup> cm<sup>-2</sup> and V<sub>oc</sub> deficit (defined as E<sub>g</sub>/q-V<sub>oc</sub>) of 0.54-0.55 V. With an additional anti-reflection coating, 15.3%-efficient GaAsP solar cells were achieved due to reduced front-surface reflectance that boosted the short-circuit current density from 13 mA/cm<sup>2</sup> to 17 mA/cm<sup>2</sup>. With further optimization of our dual-layer anti-reflection coating and growth process, we finally achieved a record 16.5%-efficient GaAsP top cell.</p> <p>The second technical challenge, which has received less attention to date, is the relatively low performance of the silicon bottom cell after tandem formation. The poor performance of state-of-the-art silicon bottom cells are due to material degradation caused by contamination during III-V growth and to poor light trapping because texturing (the front of) the silicon cells is incompatible with III-V epitaxy.</p> <p>To prevent degrading the bulk quality of the silicon wafer during III-V growth, we applied a SiN<sub>x</sub> barrier layer to its rear surface prior to MBE growth. For subsequent silicon cell fabrication, we developed a protection scheme for the epitaxial III-V material after considerable trial and error. This was necessary because the chemicals used to etch, texture, and clean silicon strongly attack the already-grown III-V layers. This resulted in rear-side textured silicon bottom cells within a simulated tandem structure (a tandem without an electrically active top cell). Compared to a planar silicon bottom cell, the textured silicon bottom cell has a significant boost in external quantum efficiency (EQE). This led to a silicon bottom cell with an efficiency of &gt; 7.8%, which is the highest-efficiency silicon bottom cell with III-V layers grown on top.&nbsp; &nbsp;</p> <p>The third challenge for III-V/Si tandems is to integrate both sub-cells with a tunnel junction. We designed and fabricated (p<sup>+</sup>)AlGaAsP/(n)GaAs/(n<sup>+</sup>)GaAsP tunnel diodes. The tunnel junction developed in this project has a voltage loss &lt; 1 mV at 20 mA/cm<sup>2&nbsp;</sup>-- the targeted one-sun current density of the envisioned tandem cell. This low-loss tunnel junction provides the last piece of the puzzle to form a III-V/Si tandem.</p> <p>Unfortunately, the project ended just as we cleared the third hurdle and we ran out of time to put the pieces together to assemble a fully functional tandem. However, with all of the essential components demonstrated and performing well, our modeling shows that a realistic 25%-efficient tandem device is within easy reach. Furthermore, the knowledge and know-how gained from this project point the way to a future 30%-efficient tandem and perhaps important developments in other III-V/Si integrated optoelectronic devices.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 10/30/2018<br>      Modified by: Zachary&nbsp;C&nbsp;Holman</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Silicon solar cells have a maximum theoretical efficiency of 29.4%, and the only demonstrated approach to exceed this single-junction limit is to add junctions to form a tandem or multi-junction solar cell. The overarching goal of this project was thus to pave the way to the first 30% efficient III-V/Si two-terminal solar cell through fundamental investigation of two parallel problems. The first is to gain greater understanding of dislocations in GaAsP cells on silicon and how to design such cells for high efficiency; the second is to understand and design silicon solar cells that use GaP as the front-surface passivation layer while maximizing quantum efficiency in the near-infrared spectral range.  The main technical challenge of III-V/Si tandem technology has historically been high threading dislocation density (TDD) in the III-V top cell, which in this project was composed of GaAsP tuned to a bandgap energy (Eg) of 1.7 eV. The high TDD results from lattice mismatch between the silicon bottom cell and GaAsP top cell, and it causes high dark current, low open-circuit voltage (Voc), and low efficiency.  Understand the origin of threading dislocations, and, therefore, controlling their formation during III-V growth, is critical to fabricate an efficient top cell. The well-known dislocation dynamics model proposed by Fitzgerald provides a general framework to achieve lower TDD: It predicts lower TDD with higher growth temperature due to higher dislocation glide velocities, and, in an ideal scenario, strain relaxation is accomplished by a low density of threads, each of which glides over long distances. However, the model neglects dislocation nucleation, which can lead to increased TDD if not managed properly.  In this project, we first investigated the effect of growth temperature on TDD of thick, relaxed GaP buffer layers on GaP/Si templates, demonstrating the strong effect of growth temperature on dislocation nucleation and glide during initial relaxation. We then verified that the TDD of GaAsP/GaP/Si depends strongly on the TDD of the relaxed GaP buffer, underscoring the importance of controlling the initial strain relaxation in achieving high efficiency. Finally, through GaAsP graded buffer growth optimization, we demonstrated 11%-efficient, 1.7-eV GaAsP solar cells with record-low TDD of 4.0-4.6 x 106 cm-2 and Voc deficit (defined as Eg/q-Voc) of 0.54-0.55 V. With an additional anti-reflection coating, 15.3%-efficient GaAsP solar cells were achieved due to reduced front-surface reflectance that boosted the short-circuit current density from 13 mA/cm2 to 17 mA/cm2. With further optimization of our dual-layer anti-reflection coating and growth process, we finally achieved a record 16.5%-efficient GaAsP top cell.  The second technical challenge, which has received less attention to date, is the relatively low performance of the silicon bottom cell after tandem formation. The poor performance of state-of-the-art silicon bottom cells are due to material degradation caused by contamination during III-V growth and to poor light trapping because texturing (the front of) the silicon cells is incompatible with III-V epitaxy.  To prevent degrading the bulk quality of the silicon wafer during III-V growth, we applied a SiNx barrier layer to its rear surface prior to MBE growth. For subsequent silicon cell fabrication, we developed a protection scheme for the epitaxial III-V material after considerable trial and error. This was necessary because the chemicals used to etch, texture, and clean silicon strongly attack the already-grown III-V layers. This resulted in rear-side textured silicon bottom cells within a simulated tandem structure (a tandem without an electrically active top cell). Compared to a planar silicon bottom cell, the textured silicon bottom cell has a significant boost in external quantum efficiency (EQE). This led to a silicon bottom cell with an efficiency of &gt; 7.8%, which is the highest-efficiency silicon bottom cell with III-V layers grown on top.     The third challenge for III-V/Si tandems is to integrate both sub-cells with a tunnel junction. We designed and fabricated (p+)AlGaAsP/(n)GaAs/(n+)GaAsP tunnel diodes. The tunnel junction developed in this project has a voltage loss &lt; 1 mV at 20 mA/cm2 -- the targeted one-sun current density of the envisioned tandem cell. This low-loss tunnel junction provides the last piece of the puzzle to form a III-V/Si tandem.  Unfortunately, the project ended just as we cleared the third hurdle and we ran out of time to put the pieces together to assemble a fully functional tandem. However, with all of the essential components demonstrated and performing well, our modeling shows that a realistic 25%-efficient tandem device is within easy reach. Furthermore, the knowledge and know-how gained from this project point the way to a future 30%-efficient tandem and perhaps important developments in other III-V/Si integrated optoelectronic devices.          Last Modified: 10/30/2018       Submitted by: Zachary C Holman]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
