<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>The Geometry and Global Analysis of Arithmetic Manifolds</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/31/2014</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>9109.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>9109</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DMS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>James Matthew Douglass</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>mdouglas@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922467</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The PI will use techniques from analytic number theory to investigate the global harmonic analysis and topology of arithmetic manifolds.  His first proposed line of investigation is to apply Arthur's endoscopic classification of automorphic representations of the classical groups to the problem of estimating the multiplicities with which nontempered Archimedean representations occur at a given level.  The PI aims to establish a number of cases of a conjecture of Sarnak and Xue on these multiplicities, and give sharp asymptotics for the growth rate of Betti number of arithmetic manifolds in congruence towers.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The PI's second proposed investigation is into the concentration of higher rank eigenfunctions on compact locally symmetric spaces, and in particular the question of how large the L^p norms of such an eigenfunction or its restriction to various subspaces can be.  The first step of this is to derive the correct 'convex bounds' for these L^p norms, which will be sharp in the case of non-negative curvature and for spectral clusters in the general case, by combining techniques from semiclassical analysis and representation theory.  The second component is to improve these convex bounds (in particular, to produce a saving in the exponents) in as many cases as possible by introducing arithmetic amplification as in the work of Iwaniec and Sarnak.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Arithmetic manifolds are central objects in number theory, as they encode information about objects which were first studied by the Greeks such as prime numbers and the solutions of polynomial equations in integers or rational numbers.  They also allow one to study special cases of questions in geometry, analysis and mathematical physics using powerful tools from number theory.  An example of this is the recent progress on the Quantum Unique Ergodicity conjecture of Rudnick and Sarnak, which helps us to understand the way in which quantum mechanics starts to resemble classical mechanics at high energies.  The PI's proposed investigation of the concentration of eigenfunctions would improve our understanding of this phenomenon.  In addition, the `non-tempered' automorphic forms that the PI will study play an important role in many problems of counting and dynamics, and the project may have interesting consequences in these areas.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>11/07/2014</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>11/07/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1509331</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Simon</FirstName>
<LastName>Marshall</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>L</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Simon L Marshall</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>marshall@math.wisc.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6082634831</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000601830</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>11/07/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Wisconsin-Madison</Name>
<CityName>MADISON</CityName>
<ZipCode>537151218</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6082623822</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>21 North Park Street</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[Suite 6401]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Wisconsin</StateName>
<StateCode>WI</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>WI02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>161202122</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF WISCONSIN SYSTEM</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>041188822</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Wisconsin-Madison]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>WI</StateCode>
<ZipCode>537151218</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Wisconsin</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>WI02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1264</Code>
<Text>ALGEBRA,NUMBER THEORY,AND COM</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0112</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2012~9109</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><span>This project concerns research in number theory, a branch of mathematics that has connections to many other subjects, including communications systems, data security, and physics. &nbsp;It specifically concerns automorphic forms, which are functions with rich symmetry and which capture information about the primes. &nbsp;The aim of the project is to explore relations between automorphic forms, geometry, and analysis. &nbsp;There is already a rich theory connecting these subjects, and the project aims to develop this further by using methods from harmonic analysis, and recent breakthroughs that provide a partial classification of automorphic forms.</span></p> <p><span>The project achieved several noteable results, including strong (and conjecturally sharp) upper bounds for the growth of cohomology in congruence towers of arithmetic complex hyperbolic manifolds, a general result improving over the trivial upper bound for the supremum norms of Maass forms, and&nbsp;a general result on the existence of Laplace eigenfunctions on negatively curved symmetric spaces whose supremum norms grow like a power of their eigenvalue. &nbsp;The last result in particular is quite interesting, as it provides a counterpoint to many results and expectations that the quantum dynamics on negatively curved manifolds should be chaotic.</span></p> <p><span>As part of the award, the PI also mentored graduate students and postdocs, and disseminated the findings of his research at conferences and seminars.</span></p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 07/23/2017<br>      Modified by: Simon&nbsp;L&nbsp;Marshall</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ This project concerns research in number theory, a branch of mathematics that has connections to many other subjects, including communications systems, data security, and physics.  It specifically concerns automorphic forms, which are functions with rich symmetry and which capture information about the primes.  The aim of the project is to explore relations between automorphic forms, geometry, and analysis.  There is already a rich theory connecting these subjects, and the project aims to develop this further by using methods from harmonic analysis, and recent breakthroughs that provide a partial classification of automorphic forms.  The project achieved several noteable results, including strong (and conjecturally sharp) upper bounds for the growth of cohomology in congruence towers of arithmetic complex hyperbolic manifolds, a general result improving over the trivial upper bound for the supremum norms of Maass forms, and a general result on the existence of Laplace eigenfunctions on negatively curved symmetric spaces whose supremum norms grow like a power of their eigenvalue.  The last result in particular is quite interesting, as it provides a counterpoint to many results and expectations that the quantum dynamics on negatively curved manifolds should be chaotic.  As part of the award, the PI also mentored graduate students and postdocs, and disseminated the findings of his research at conferences and seminars.       Last Modified: 07/23/2017       Submitted by: Simon L Marshall]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
