<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Fundamentals of Wireless Communication Systems Using Orbital Angular Momenta</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2015</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2020</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>396560.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>396560</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07010000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>ECCS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Electrical, Commun &amp; Cyber Sys</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Mohammod Ali</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>moali@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924632</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Wireless data services have seen an enormous growth over the past two decades: not only has the number of users and connected devices increased dramatically, but also the connection speed has grown by a factor of 1000. All of this had led to an unprecedented variety of wireless services that changes the way that people are working, interacting, and spending their spare time. However, the continued increase in data rates has also created great challenges, since the spectrum used for signal transmission is a limited and precious resource. For this reason, it is essential to both use new spectrum, and to exploit available spectrum as efficiently as possible. Advances in chip manufacturing have opened the possibility for low-cost communications systems using millimeter waves, which have much shorter wavelength than currently used cellular systems, and where a lot of spectrum is available. Still, given the increase in data usage, also this spectrum has to be used efficiently.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;One way to drastically improve spectral efficiency is to transmit multiple data streams together, using the same spectrum. However, in a normal setting, the receiver obtains then a mixture of those data streams, and they would interfere with each other. It is thus necessary to transmit the data streams in a way that allows the receiver to disentangle them. This project investigates a recently discovered such transmission method that is especially suitable for wireless links where the transmitter and receiver can see each other, and are fixed - such situations can occur, e.g., for wireless backhaul (essentially, the connection from the base station to the internet), or wireless communication between servers in a data center. The method transmits different data streams on waves that have different orbital angular momenta (OAM), which describe the phase twist of a propagating wave. The current project investigates the fundamental science, as well as potential practical problems of OAM systems, and aims to assess their potential as a revolutionary method for drastically improving speed and efficiency of wireless data connections.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;To make the above description more precise, OAM describes a phase twist of a propagating wave, and is different from the well-known polarization. Beams with different OAM are orthogonal to each other when propagating along the same beam axis, so that beams emanating from the same aperture, using the same time-frequency resources, can carry independent data streams. The project investigates the fundamentals as well as the real-world behavior of OAM multiplexing systems operating in the millimeter wave frequency range, specifically, 1) Explore the basic factors limiting OAM communication system capacity, in particular the pathloss of different OAM beams, and investigate measures to optimize the system capacity; 2) Investigate fundamental issues of OAM beam propagation, including the impact of attenuation and mode conversion by specular reflection and diffuse scattering; 3) Evaluate residual crosstalk between OAM channels, arising from various propagation environments; 4) Find new methods for compensating OAM channel degradation, in particular compensating for multipath propagation and atmospheric distortions; and 5) Analyze the connection between OAM and spatial multiplexing, and see how they can be combined in a manner that is most beneficial for implementation.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/01/2015</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/01/2015</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1509965</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Alan</FirstName>
<LastName>Willner</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>E</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Alan E Willner</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>willner@usc.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2137404664</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000126189</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/01/2015</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Andreas</FirstName>
<LastName>Molisch</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Andreas Molisch</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>molisch@usc.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2137404670</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000526999</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/01/2015</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Southern California</Name>
<CityName>Los Angeles</CityName>
<ZipCode>900890001</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2137407762</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>University Park</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[3720 S. Flower St.]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>37</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CA37</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>072933393</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF SOUTHERN CALIFORNIA</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>072933393</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Southern California]]></Name>
<CityName>Los Angeles</CityName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>900892565</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[3740 McClintock Avenue]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>37</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CA37</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7564</Code>
<Text>CCSS-Comms Circuits &amp; Sens Sys</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>153E</Code>
<Text>Wireless comm &amp; sig processing</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0115</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2015~396560</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The wireless world is driven by a demand for ever-increasing data rates. &nbsp;One way to increase the rates is the use of the millimeter-wave regime, which offers a larger bandwidth when compared to conventional frequency bands (centimeter-wave frequencies). However, using only a new frequency regime still might not be enough to satisfy demand for data rates, so complementary methods are required. In particular, a valuable approach is in sending multiple different data streams in the same spectrum. In this way, more data is transmitted but occupying the same amount of spectrum, thus the ?spectral efficiency? is increased. The technique of orbital angular momenta (OAM), which gives waves different amount of ?twist?, allows us to achieve transmitting different data in the same spectrum. In this project, we explored the use of OAM in wireless, and particular millimeter-wave and free-space optical, systems with real-world obstacles and impairments.</p> <p>Firstly, we performed a variety of experiments that demonstrated wireless links using OAM in the millimeter-wave regime to increase the spectral efficiency. From the results of our experiment, we showed that influence of one OAM beam on another was low, allowing decoding of the different data streams without the need for further processing by (complicated and costly) interference cancellers. We demonstrated various ways to generate and ?point? OAM beams towards the receiver. We also tested different modulation formats, i.e., ways how data can be assigned to waveforms that are sent over the air. Because waves might reach the receiver not only via a direct connection from the transmitter, but also via other objects from which they are reflected (this is called ?multi-path propagation?), which leads to interference between a symbol and the ones that have been sent before, we explored a method called orthogonal frequency division multiplexing (OFDM) to combat it.</p> <p>Besides the millimeter-wave regime, the optical regime is another frequency band that can be used for wireless communication links. The use of OAM modes in optical wireless communication links was explored as well when the light had to go through different media. We multiplexed four green (532-nm wavelength) OAM beams, each carrying an independent data channel, to increase the system capacity of underwater optical communications. We experimentally demonstrated an OAM-multiplexed, free-space optical (FSO) communication link between a ground transmitter and a ground receiver via a moving unmanned-aerial-vehicle. Different impairments in OAM-based optical links were investigated. We experimentally investigated the scattering effect on an OAM-multiplexed optical wireless communication link. The power loss, mode purity, cross talk, and bit error rate performance were measured and analyzed for different OAM modes under different scattering levels. The turbulence effect on the OAM-based optical links was mitigated using different methods. We demonstrated simultaneous turbulence mitigation and channel demultiplexing in an OAM-multiplexed optical link using the adaptive wavefront shaping and diffusing method. We demonstrated the mitigation of atmospheric turbulence effects using phase patterns that apply the inverse transmission matrix for pre-compensation in a free-space OAM-multiplexed optical link.&nbsp;</p> <p>Furthermore, more kinds of spatial modes were used in wireless communication links. We investigated the potential of using ?self-healing? Bessel-Gaussian beams carrying OAM to overcome limitations in obstructed free-space optical and millimeter-wave communication links. We demonstrated the multiplexing of Hermite-Gaussian or Laguerre-Gaussian (LG) modes in FSO communication links. We also investigated other ways to exploit OAM, including free-space quantum communication, and securing a link by ?hiding? a low-intensity free-space optical beam when it coaxially propagates on the same wavelength with a high-intensity optical beam.&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>All of these investigations demonstrated the value of OAM for high-speed data communication, allowing to operate at high carrier frequencies (millimeter-wave or even optical) and additionally sending multiple data streams in the same spectrum, under realistic operating conditions. OAM is thus found to be a promising method for Beyond 5G wireless data systems.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 11/29/2020<br>      Modified by: Andreas&nbsp;Molisch</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The wireless world is driven by a demand for ever-increasing data rates.  One way to increase the rates is the use of the millimeter-wave regime, which offers a larger bandwidth when compared to conventional frequency bands (centimeter-wave frequencies). However, using only a new frequency regime still might not be enough to satisfy demand for data rates, so complementary methods are required. In particular, a valuable approach is in sending multiple different data streams in the same spectrum. In this way, more data is transmitted but occupying the same amount of spectrum, thus the ?spectral efficiency? is increased. The technique of orbital angular momenta (OAM), which gives waves different amount of ?twist?, allows us to achieve transmitting different data in the same spectrum. In this project, we explored the use of OAM in wireless, and particular millimeter-wave and free-space optical, systems with real-world obstacles and impairments.  Firstly, we performed a variety of experiments that demonstrated wireless links using OAM in the millimeter-wave regime to increase the spectral efficiency. From the results of our experiment, we showed that influence of one OAM beam on another was low, allowing decoding of the different data streams without the need for further processing by (complicated and costly) interference cancellers. We demonstrated various ways to generate and ?point? OAM beams towards the receiver. We also tested different modulation formats, i.e., ways how data can be assigned to waveforms that are sent over the air. Because waves might reach the receiver not only via a direct connection from the transmitter, but also via other objects from which they are reflected (this is called ?multi-path propagation?), which leads to interference between a symbol and the ones that have been sent before, we explored a method called orthogonal frequency division multiplexing (OFDM) to combat it.  Besides the millimeter-wave regime, the optical regime is another frequency band that can be used for wireless communication links. The use of OAM modes in optical wireless communication links was explored as well when the light had to go through different media. We multiplexed four green (532-nm wavelength) OAM beams, each carrying an independent data channel, to increase the system capacity of underwater optical communications. We experimentally demonstrated an OAM-multiplexed, free-space optical (FSO) communication link between a ground transmitter and a ground receiver via a moving unmanned-aerial-vehicle. Different impairments in OAM-based optical links were investigated. We experimentally investigated the scattering effect on an OAM-multiplexed optical wireless communication link. The power loss, mode purity, cross talk, and bit error rate performance were measured and analyzed for different OAM modes under different scattering levels. The turbulence effect on the OAM-based optical links was mitigated using different methods. We demonstrated simultaneous turbulence mitigation and channel demultiplexing in an OAM-multiplexed optical link using the adaptive wavefront shaping and diffusing method. We demonstrated the mitigation of atmospheric turbulence effects using phase patterns that apply the inverse transmission matrix for pre-compensation in a free-space OAM-multiplexed optical link.   Furthermore, more kinds of spatial modes were used in wireless communication links. We investigated the potential of using ?self-healing? Bessel-Gaussian beams carrying OAM to overcome limitations in obstructed free-space optical and millimeter-wave communication links. We demonstrated the multiplexing of Hermite-Gaussian or Laguerre-Gaussian (LG) modes in FSO communication links. We also investigated other ways to exploit OAM, including free-space quantum communication, and securing a link by ?hiding? a low-intensity free-space optical beam when it coaxially propagates on the same wavelength with a high-intensity optical beam.      All of these investigations demonstrated the value of OAM for high-speed data communication, allowing to operate at high carrier frequencies (millimeter-wave or even optical) and additionally sending multiple data streams in the same spectrum, under realistic operating conditions. OAM is thus found to be a promising method for Beyond 5G wireless data systems.          Last Modified: 11/29/2020       Submitted by: Andreas Molisch]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
