<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Strengthening power system dynamic operation with the advent of increased renewable generation: Location and control of fast energy storage systems</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2015</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>355372.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>355372</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07010000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>ECCS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Electrical, Commun &amp; Cyber Sys</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Radhakisan Baheti</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This research project seeks to increase power system robustness through the use of fast energy storage systems so the grid is better prepared to withstand failures and abnormal operation, which may lead to blackouts. The theoretical work of this project will also contribute to establishing a basis for dynamics studies for the future power system infrastructure. Several power system problems can be studied using the proposed mathematical development, such as controller designs for renewable generation, smart grid dynamic operation, electricity markets, and others. Besides advancing research knowledge on power system dynamics, this project will bring further development in control theory that is applicable to many other systems and industrial processes from the fields of electrical engineering, mechanical engineering, chemical engineering, and management. The PIs plan to leverage research results for curriculum development in new courses on power system dynamics and control. The researchers will also have support from the Office of Diversity, College of Engineering, and the Office of Information Technology at the University of Tennessee, Knoxville.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project will investigate a criterion to identify the best locations of fast energy storage systems (FESS) to improve power system dynamic performance and design appropriate controls for FESS. The future power grid is likely to be characterized by a high penetration of renewable energy interfaced to the grid through power electronics, and this may result in poor dynamic performance due to the reduction of inertia and a high variability on the generation side. To measure dynamic performance improvement, features such as frequency nadir, rate of change of frequency, and low frequency oscillation damping, among others, are considered. This work would be among the first to propose a solution for the FESS location problem while considering the full mathematical complexities of power system dynamics (large dimensionality, dynamics in different time scales, linear and nonlinear elements, and others). Although the modeling of this problem is highly complex, one of the proposal hypotheses is the existence of a criterion for FESS location based on specific physical characteristics of a power system, such as distribution of inertia, distribution of response speed of synchronous generators, and grid topology. Data analytics will be used to identify correlations between the optimal location and power system characteristics and, based on the numerical results, the theoretical development of the criterion will be derived. This characterization would allow planners to carefully strengthen the grid dynamics with the advent of increased renewable generation. In addition, this research seeks to establish three control strategies for FESS: (a) a continuous control scheme; (b) a discrete control scheme that determines the specific time when FESS need to change their discrete states (three states are considered: idle, discharge, and charge); and (c) a hybrid control scheme that combines the discrete state transitions and the continuous stored energy control within a particular discrete state. The hybrid control scheme is expected to provide the best dynamic improvement and, at the same time, is expected to extend the lifespan of FESS. The potential of phasor measurement units (PMUs) is considered to facilitate coordinating control loops among FESS, conventional generation, and renewable generation.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/04/2015</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/04/2015</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1509114</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Kevin</FirstName>
<LastName>Tomsovic</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>L</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Kevin L Tomsovic</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>tomsovic@tennessee.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>8659743461</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000332428</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/04/2015</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Seddik</FirstName>
<LastName>Djouadi</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Seddik Djouadi</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>mdjouadi@utk.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>8659745447</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000488750</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/04/2015</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Hector</FirstName>
<LastName>Pulgar</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Hector Pulgar</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>hpulgar@utk.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>8659743466</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000683454</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/04/2015</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Tennessee Knoxville</Name>
<CityName>Knoxville</CityName>
<ZipCode>379163801</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>8659743466</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1331 CIR PARK DR</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Tennessee</StateName>
<StateCode>TN</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>TN02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>003387891</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF TENNESSEE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>003387891</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Tennessee Knoxville]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>TN</StateCode>
<ZipCode>379960003</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Tennessee</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>TN02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7607</Code>
<Text>EPCN-Energy-Power-Ctrl-Netwrks</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EPSCoR Co-Funding</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>155E</Code>
<Text>Electric power networks</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0115</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2015~355372</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><span>This work was among the first to propose a solution for the fast-energy-storage-systems (FESS) location problem while considering the full mathematical complexities of power system dynamics (large dimensionality, dynamics in different time scales, both continuous and discrete dynamics, linear and nonlinear elements, and others). Although the modeling of this problem was highly complex, one of the research hypotheses was the existence of a criterion for FESS location based on specific physical characteristics of a power system, such as, distribution of inertia, distribution of response speed of synchronous generators, grid topology, and others. This work has sparkled interested of other research groups and today the concept of inertia distribution has become relevant to enhance the power system dynamic operation. In fact, currently, one of the ongoing activities of the North American Electric Reliability Corporation (NERC) is to study the correlation between system inertia and inter-area oscillations in the Western Electricity Coordinating Council (WECC) system. For radial systems, this project has laid foundations to study analytically the location of control actuators that can enhance the system stability; this location is highly based on the distribution of inertia throughout the system and the voltage set-point of synchronous generators. For meshed systems, this project has elaborated a framework to identify the location based on a machine learning process; depending on the particular characteristics of the system, only a few characteristics are required to identify the optimal location of controllers; the most important characteristic is the inertia distribution.</span></p> <p><span style="font-family: Calibri; font-size: small;">&nbsp;</span></p> <p><span>With the results of this project, the current and future power grid will be strengthened by using FESS optimally placed within the grid. As a result, society can be benefited in two general aspects: (a) the integration of larger volume of renewable generation would be eased due to a more robust grid design, and (b) a robust grid implies a more reliable delivery of electricity and a more resilient grid to withstand perturbations&mdash;resulting in fewer blackouts. In consequence, a more resilient grid would avoid public alarm and negative economic consequences as those reported after the 2003 Northeast Blackout. The results of this research project have been disseminated to the public, industry and academic community through talks to high school students and teachers, presentation in academic/industry conferences, academic journals, and industry meetings.</span></p> <p><strong>&nbsp;</strong><em>&nbsp;</em></p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 10/11/2019<br>      Modified by: Hector&nbsp;Pulgar</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ This work was among the first to propose a solution for the fast-energy-storage-systems (FESS) location problem while considering the full mathematical complexities of power system dynamics (large dimensionality, dynamics in different time scales, both continuous and discrete dynamics, linear and nonlinear elements, and others). Although the modeling of this problem was highly complex, one of the research hypotheses was the existence of a criterion for FESS location based on specific physical characteristics of a power system, such as, distribution of inertia, distribution of response speed of synchronous generators, grid topology, and others. This work has sparkled interested of other research groups and today the concept of inertia distribution has become relevant to enhance the power system dynamic operation. In fact, currently, one of the ongoing activities of the North American Electric Reliability Corporation (NERC) is to study the correlation between system inertia and inter-area oscillations in the Western Electricity Coordinating Council (WECC) system. For radial systems, this project has laid foundations to study analytically the location of control actuators that can enhance the system stability; this location is highly based on the distribution of inertia throughout the system and the voltage set-point of synchronous generators. For meshed systems, this project has elaborated a framework to identify the location based on a machine learning process; depending on the particular characteristics of the system, only a few characteristics are required to identify the optimal location of controllers; the most important characteristic is the inertia distribution.     With the results of this project, the current and future power grid will be strengthened by using FESS optimally placed within the grid. As a result, society can be benefited in two general aspects: (a) the integration of larger volume of renewable generation would be eased due to a more robust grid design, and (b) a robust grid implies a more reliable delivery of electricity and a more resilient grid to withstand perturbations&mdash;resulting in fewer blackouts. In consequence, a more resilient grid would avoid public alarm and negative economic consequences as those reported after the 2003 Northeast Blackout. The results of this research project have been disseminated to the public, industry and academic community through talks to high school students and teachers, presentation in academic/industry conferences, academic journals, and industry meetings.              Last Modified: 10/11/2019       Submitted by: Hector Pulgar]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
