<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>UNS: Extension of Lean Flammability Limit  by Plasma Enhancement in Stratified Flames</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2015</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>300000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>300000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07020000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CBET</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Chem, Bioeng, Env, &amp; Transp Sys</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Harsha Chelliah</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>1510709 (Chen)&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Low temperature, lean combustion enables low emission levels and high efficiencies of combustion devices such automobiles and jet engines.  The proposed study investigates the effect of electrical field on the fuel-lean combustion and seeks to extend the limit where extra-low temperature combustion is viable.  It also integrates the research activities with the education programs of undergraduate and graduate students, aiming to provide a fundamental understanding of promising technologies to the next generation of engineers and scientists in the field of combustion science.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The mechanisms of flame support under stratified conditions are investigated with a combined numerical simulations and experimental approach, on the effect of an external electric field on the lean flammability limit and flame speed of a stratified methane flame.  The goals are to investigate to what extent stable combustion can be maintained in practical devices while sustaining ultra-lean conditions and, specifically, to elucidate the relative contributions of thermal and chemical effects associated with transport in the vicinity of the flame. The experimental component will be used for validation of the models used in the simulations and to confirm the efficacy of the injection and ignition strategies. The new knowledge gained will form the basis for further gains in engine efficiency.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/01/2015</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/01/2015</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1510709</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Robert</FirstName>
<LastName>Dibble</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>W</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Robert W Dibble</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>rdibble@me.berkeley.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5106424901</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000412676</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/01/2015</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Jyh-Yuan</FirstName>
<LastName>Chen</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Jyh-Yuan Chen</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>jychen@me.berkeley.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5106423286</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000474151</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/01/2015</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of California-Berkeley</Name>
<CityName>BERKELEY</CityName>
<ZipCode>947101749</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5106433891</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>Sponsored Projects Office</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[1608 Fourth Street, Suite 220]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>13</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CA13</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>124726725</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>REGENTS OF THE UNIVERSITY OF CALIFORNIA, THE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>071549000</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of California-Berkeley]]></Name>
<CityName>Berkeley</CityName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>947201740</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[246 Hesse Hall]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>13</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CA13</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1407</Code>
<Text>CFS-Combustion &amp; Fire Systems</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>148E</Code>
<Text>Combustion</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0115</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2015~300000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>This work has included a vast array of both numerical modeling and experiments to determine the combustion improvement of mixture stratification relative to homogenous mixtures with and without applied electric fields.<br /><br />Numerical modeling in this work has shown that there is a flame speed enhancement when a flame is back supported from a rich burn mixture propagating into a leaner mixture. However, numerous models including zero and one dimensional models did not support an extension of the lean flammability limit. When the flame reached a mixture beyond the lean flammability limit, the flame did not continue to propagate through the mixture. In regards to electric field numerical modeling of both a zero and a one dimensional model, applying an electric field did not have a lasting effect on the flame beyond a brief ambipolar diffusion of electrons which quickly negated the electric field in the flame region. This diffusion did not lead to an increase in the flame speed or other enhanced combustion effect. This numerical finding is in line with prior experimental work performed on a flat plate burner, where a 1-D flame subject to a uniform DC electric field did not influence the fundamental combustion characteristics.<br /><br />The experimental work of this project included building a stratification layer assembly to compare with the spherical flame numerical modeling. The experiments found a noticeable flame speed enhancement when a flame propagated from a rich into a lean mixture although to a lesser extent than the numerical modeling predicted. With a fuel rich methane-air mixture propagating into a fuel lean methane-air mixture, the effect was noticeable and on the same order of magnitude as the numerical simulation. However, the experiments were unable to reproduce the findings of the MIT work of a flame propagating from a rich mixture into a severely lean mixture beyond the lean flammability limit. No clear extension of the lean flammability limit was observed either through optical or emission measurements. In addition to the stratified experiments, numerous applied electric field experiments were performed. It was observed that the flame was accelerated towards high voltages and therefore propagating through a negative electric field, in agreement with past work. Both a negative and a positive applied electric field enhanced the flame combustion characteristics of the spherically propagating flame, while the negative electric field had a greater effect on the flame surface distortions and the flame speed than the positive electric field. Limited combined work of a stratified flame propagating in the presence of an electric field was possible, partially due to the complexity of the setup necessary to properly control the subsequent interactions with the resources available.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 09/02/2019<br>      Modified by: Jyh-Yuan&nbsp;Chen</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ This work has included a vast array of both numerical modeling and experiments to determine the combustion improvement of mixture stratification relative to homogenous mixtures with and without applied electric fields.  Numerical modeling in this work has shown that there is a flame speed enhancement when a flame is back supported from a rich burn mixture propagating into a leaner mixture. However, numerous models including zero and one dimensional models did not support an extension of the lean flammability limit. When the flame reached a mixture beyond the lean flammability limit, the flame did not continue to propagate through the mixture. In regards to electric field numerical modeling of both a zero and a one dimensional model, applying an electric field did not have a lasting effect on the flame beyond a brief ambipolar diffusion of electrons which quickly negated the electric field in the flame region. This diffusion did not lead to an increase in the flame speed or other enhanced combustion effect. This numerical finding is in line with prior experimental work performed on a flat plate burner, where a 1-D flame subject to a uniform DC electric field did not influence the fundamental combustion characteristics.  The experimental work of this project included building a stratification layer assembly to compare with the spherical flame numerical modeling. The experiments found a noticeable flame speed enhancement when a flame propagated from a rich into a lean mixture although to a lesser extent than the numerical modeling predicted. With a fuel rich methane-air mixture propagating into a fuel lean methane-air mixture, the effect was noticeable and on the same order of magnitude as the numerical simulation. However, the experiments were unable to reproduce the findings of the MIT work of a flame propagating from a rich mixture into a severely lean mixture beyond the lean flammability limit. No clear extension of the lean flammability limit was observed either through optical or emission measurements. In addition to the stratified experiments, numerous applied electric field experiments were performed. It was observed that the flame was accelerated towards high voltages and therefore propagating through a negative electric field, in agreement with past work. Both a negative and a positive applied electric field enhanced the flame combustion characteristics of the spherically propagating flame, while the negative electric field had a greater effect on the flame surface distortions and the flame speed than the positive electric field. Limited combined work of a stratified flame propagating in the presence of an electric field was possible, partially due to the complexity of the setup necessary to properly control the subsequent interactions with the resources available.       Last Modified: 09/02/2019       Submitted by: Jyh-Yuan Chen]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
