<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>UNS: Intracellular Drug Delivery Mediated by Laser-activated Nanoparticles</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2015</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>329011.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>329011</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07020000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CBET</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Chem, Bioeng, Env, &amp; Transp Sys</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>William Olbricht</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>wolbrich@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924842</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>CBET - 1510028&lt;br/&gt;PI: Prausnitz, Mark&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project will explore a novel way to make cell membranes temporarily permeable so that drug molecules are able to enter the cell and carry out their therapeutic functions.  The method relies on irradiating nanoparticles interspersed between the cells with pulsed laser energy.  Preliminary data show that irradiating the nanoparticles leads to a significant increase in the cellular uptake of a fluorescent molecule without loss of cell viability.  The research could lead to a new way to enhance the delivery of biomolecules to targeted cells for therapeutic, diagnostic and laboratory applications.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project will test the hypothesis that the laser energy raises the nanoparticle temperature and vaporizes surrounding liquid, producing local stress fields that can temporarily and non-destructively permeabilize cell membranes, thereby allowing intracellular uptake of exogenous molecules by living cells.  A series of experiments will quantify the spatio-temporal characteristics of the forms of energy released by laser-activated nanoparticles to test the hypothesis that the dominant characteristic of energy transduction by a nanoparticle is the rapid generation of an enveloping vapor bubble that condenses slowly after formation.  The research also will determine which features of the particle transduction outputs correlate to high intracellular uptake and cell viability to test the hypothesis that cellular bioeffects are controlled by acoustic and thermal effects occurring on the scale of a cell diameter.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/21/2015</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/21/2015</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1510028</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Mark</FirstName>
<LastName>Prausnitz</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>R</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Mark R Prausnitz</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>mark.prausnitz@chbe.gatech.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>4048945135</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000463717</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/21/2015</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Georgia Tech Research Corporation</Name>
<CityName>Atlanta</CityName>
<ZipCode>303320420</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>4048944819</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>Office of Sponsored Programs</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Georgia</StateName>
<StateCode>GA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>GA05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>097394084</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>GEORGIA TECH RESEARCH CORPORATION</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>097394084</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Georgia Institute of Technology]]></Name>
<CityName>Atlanta</CityName>
<StateCode>GA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>303320002</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[225 North Avenue]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Georgia</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>GA05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1415</Code>
<Text>PMP-Particul&amp;MultiphaseProcess</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>5345</Code>
<Text>Engineering of Biomed Systems</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>055E</Code>
<Text>Particle science and technology</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0115</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2015~329011</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p class="Default"><strong><span>Intracellular drug delivery by nanoparticle-mediated photoporation</span></strong></p> <p>Delivering drug molecules inside cells have applications in several fields such as treatment of cancer. However, the biggest challenge is the presence of protective cell membrane, which restricts the flow of large molecules in and out of the cells. Using nanoparticleS and laser light to create pores into the cell membrane helps overcome this challenge allowing the movement of drug molecules from outside to the inside of the cell<strong>. &nbsp;</strong>A typical experiment is conducted with cells, nanoparticles and fluorescing uptake markers suspended in a nutrition-rich media, kept inside a cylindrical glass cuvette that is irradiated with a laser beam. Our studies are focused on understanding the role of initial experimental parameters (e.g. nanoparticle, cell suspension media, etc.) and optimizing this method to deliver wide size range of molecules.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>The experimental and theoretical results show that cellular responses (a combination of cells with molecular uptake, cell death and cell loss) to laser exposure increase with the increase &nbsp;in the ability of nanoparticles to absorb laser light, however this correlation can be influenced by nanoparticles shape, size and concentration. Therefore, next we designed experiments to study the effect of changing total energy, energy per particle and energy per mass delivered. We found that no single energy parameter dominated over the other. Thus, there is no single parameter that controls nanoparticle-mediated pores creation in the cell membrane. Additionally we investigated the effect of changing cell suspension media and found that adding serum and certain polymers during laser exposure can help keeping cells alive. In terms of increasing the efficiency of this platform technology to deliver high molecular weight compounds, we were successful in delivering wide size range of molecules to more than 50% of cells. This size range was up to a size similar to plasmid DNAs that can be used for gene therapy in diseases such as cancer.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p class="Default">&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 09/09/2019<br>      Modified by: Mark&nbsp;R&nbsp;Prausnitz</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[Intracellular drug delivery by nanoparticle-mediated photoporation  Delivering drug molecules inside cells have applications in several fields such as treatment of cancer. However, the biggest challenge is the presence of protective cell membrane, which restricts the flow of large molecules in and out of the cells. Using nanoparticleS and laser light to create pores into the cell membrane helps overcome this challenge allowing the movement of drug molecules from outside to the inside of the cell.  A typical experiment is conducted with cells, nanoparticles and fluorescing uptake markers suspended in a nutrition-rich media, kept inside a cylindrical glass cuvette that is irradiated with a laser beam. Our studies are focused on understanding the role of initial experimental parameters (e.g. nanoparticle, cell suspension media, etc.) and optimizing this method to deliver wide size range of molecules.     The experimental and theoretical results show that cellular responses (a combination of cells with molecular uptake, cell death and cell loss) to laser exposure increase with the increase  in the ability of nanoparticles to absorb laser light, however this correlation can be influenced by nanoparticles shape, size and concentration. Therefore, next we designed experiments to study the effect of changing total energy, energy per particle and energy per mass delivered. We found that no single energy parameter dominated over the other. Thus, there is no single parameter that controls nanoparticle-mediated pores creation in the cell membrane. Additionally we investigated the effect of changing cell suspension media and found that adding serum and certain polymers during laser exposure can help keeping cells alive. In terms of increasing the efficiency of this platform technology to deliver high molecular weight compounds, we were successful in delivering wide size range of molecules to more than 50% of cells. This size range was up to a size similar to plasmid DNAs that can be used for gene therapy in diseases such as cancer.            Last Modified: 09/09/2019       Submitted by: Mark R Prausnitz]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
