<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>UNS:EFFECT OF METAL OXIDE INTERACTIONS ON OXYGEN EVOLUTION REACTION FOR WATER ELECTROLYSIS</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/15/2015</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>380682.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>380682</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07020000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CBET</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Chem, Bioeng, Env, &amp; Transp Sys</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Robert McCabe</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>rmccabe@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924826</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Previous work by the principal investigator (PI) has identified a promising catalyst formulation for the production of hydrogen via the oxygen evolution reaction (OER) in highly-acidic electrocatalytic environments. The catalyst partially substitutes lower-cost tin (Sn) for the expensive noble metals iridium (Ir) and ruthenium (Ru). The goal of the present study is to further understand the reasons for the high performance and stability of the the Sn-containing catalysts as a guide for developing even better catalysts.  The proposed work will contribute to improved, lower cost, electrocatalysts for a variety of energy applications and will develop  creative educational tools for high school students in addition to undergraduate and graduate opportunities for underrepresented minorities.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The present proposal expands the PI's previous work with fluorine-doped mixed oxide SnIr catalysts to gain fundamental understanding of the reasons for their high performance with reduced noble metal loading. Both theoretical and experimental approaches will be employed focusing on a range of SnIr catalysts with varying Sn-to-Ir ratio, and with various levels of F-doping.  By combining surface and bulk experimental probes with Density Functional Theory (VASP code)computational methods, they will obtain fundamental understanding of both the geometric and electronic structures responsible for the stability and performance attributes of the F-doped mixed oxide catalysts.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The proposed work has the potential to broadly impact our understanding of water electrolysis as promoted by catalysts containing reduced amounts of expensive precious metals compared to current catalyst technology, thereby aiding progress in areas related to fuel cells, hydrogen production, and overall energy sustainability.  The research will also provide education and training opportunities for undergraduate and graduate students, including recruiting minority students from North Carolina Agriculture and Technical State University.  In addition, the PI will undertake an ambitious program to engage high school students in the challenges and opportunities around water hydrolysis including audio-visual animation and hands-on demonstrations.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>09/04/2015</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>09/04/2015</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1511390</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Prashant</FirstName>
<LastName>Kumta</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>N</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Prashant N Kumta</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>pkumta@engr.pitt.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>4126480223</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000435167</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/04/2015</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Oleg</FirstName>
<LastName>Velikokhatnyi</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>I</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Oleg I Velikokhatnyi</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>olv3@pitt.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>4126249604</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000628264</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/04/2015</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Moni</FirstName>
<LastName>Datta</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>K</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Moni K Datta</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>mkd16@pitt.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>4126249729</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000628265</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/04/2015</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Pittsburgh</Name>
<CityName>Pittsburgh</CityName>
<ZipCode>152133203</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>4126247400</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>300 Murdoch Building</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[3420 Forbes Avenue]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Pennsylvania</StateName>
<StateCode>PA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>18</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>PA18</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>004514360</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF PITTSBURGH, THE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>004514360</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Pittsburgh]]></Name>
<CityName>Pittsburgh</CityName>
<StateCode>PA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>152132303</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[3700 OHara Street]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Pennsylvania</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>18</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>PA18</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1401</Code>
<Text>Catalysis</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>044E</Code>
<Text>CATALYSIS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0115</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2015~380682</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The major goal of this proposal is to develop highly efficient ultra-low noble metal content (e.g. Pt, IrO<sub>2</sub>, RuO<sub>2</sub>) and noble metal and even precious group metal free (PGM-free) oxygen evolution reaction (OER) electrocatalyst for proton exchange membrane (PEM) based acid mediated water electrolysis. This in turn will reduce the capital cost while significantly improving the efficiency (&le;43kWh/kg H<sub>2</sub>)<sub>&nbsp;</sub>than the state-of-the art commercial PGM based PEM electrolyzers and expectedly meeting the hydrogen production cost goal ($2/Kg H<sub>2</sub>). In the direction of developing highly active and efficient ultra-low noble metal and PGM-free electrocatalysts, the fundamental relationships between the electrocatalyst atomic level crystal structure and compositions on the electrocatalyst surface as well as within the bulk, and surface related electrochemical properties have been correlated to understand the fundamental structure-property relationships in the 2D thin film system. In this direction, first principles based theoretical calculation (e.g. density functional theory, DFT) has been utilized to identify the suitable electrocatalysts and compositions followed by advanced experimental electrocatalyst synthesis, and characterization. Such atomic and electronic structure-property relationships is very helpful for the identification, design and synthesis of suitable electro-catalysts in 0D, 1D and 3D nanostructured dimensions and configurations as well as in the preferred oriented crystallographic state. The processing-structure-property correlations will also serve to ultimately develop low cost PGM-free based electro-catalysts. The theoretical and experimental studies will thus work synergistically to determine not only the bulk and surface atomic and electronic level structures and compositions that are effective in terms of electrocatalytic response but also help to understand the underlying detailed mechanisms contributing to the electrocatalytic activity.. Understanding of the mechanisms will then serve to effectively fine tune and design the electrocatalyst system helping to unravel the fundamental pathways leading to the identification of PGM-free commercially viable electrocatalyst for PEM based acid mediated electrolyzers.</p> <p>In order to understand the process/synthesis-atomic/electronic structure-electrochemical property relationships, a fundamental theoretical and experimental study has been conducted to integrate theory, modeling, synthesis, structural and electrochemical characterization of the electrocatalysts to advance the science and technology of electrocatalysts. In this direction, theoretically predicted F doped (Mn,Ir)O<sub>2</sub>:F, (Sn,Ir)O<sub>2</sub>:F, and (Sn,Nb,Ir)O<sub>2</sub>:F have been synthesized in 2D thin film and suitable correlation between processing-structure property have been developed. The theoretical and experimental outcomes and understandings of structure-property relationship of 2D thin film obtained has been utilized to synthesize highly active low overpotential electrocatalysts in different "materials length scales" e. g. vertically aligned 1D nanorod/nanotube structure of (Sn,Ir)O<sub>2</sub>:F and (Mn,Ir)O<sub>2</sub>:F were synthesized which expedite the reaction kinetics resulting in superior electrocatalytic activity towards water splitting compared to the 2D structures. Low noble metal containing 1D nanotube of (Mn,Ir)O2:10F and (Sn,Ir)O2:F solid solution indeed show excellent promise for replacing the state of the art OER electro-catalysts IrO2/RuO2 on the grounds of its excellent electrochemical performance. This study portends significant reduction in noble metal content for OER electro-catalyst along with a significant improvement in electrochemical activity. Together, these will be of immense help in reducing the capital cost of water electrolysis cells for economic and efficient hydrogen production from acid based PEM water electrolysis for meeting the incessantly growing global energy demands, employing non-carbonaceous clean energy source in an efficient and economic manner.</p> <p>The 2D thin film data has also been utilized to synthesize for the very first time highly active low overpotential 3D nanostructured non noble metal containing Cu-Mn-oxides based PGM-free electrocatalyst. In addition, PGM-free F doped cobalt nickel phosphide (CoNiP:F), and Mn-metal oxide electro-catalyst were computationally identified and experientially validated for oxygen evolution reaction (OER) for PEM water electrolysis,. The first-principles calculations of the total energies and electronic structures identified Co-Ni-P and Mn-metal oxide based electro-catalysts. Both F doped CoNiP and Mn-metal oxide were thus explored as high performance electro-catalysts possessing unique electronic structures mimicking the PGM electrocatalysts. Development of PGM-free electrocatalyst marks a hallmark advancement in the identification and development of novel noble metal-free 0D and 3D nanostructured electro-catalysts (Cu-Mn-oxide, CoNiP and Mn metal-oxide) possessing unique electronic/molecular structure exhibiting remarkable stability and outstanding electrochemical activity higher than IrO2 for OER, the currently accepted gold standard electro-catalysts. Hence, these systems can replace IrO2 with possible further modification leading to further improvements. In the opinion of the PIs, the system represents a fundamental breakthrough in the pursuit of PGM-free electrocatalysts for economic and efficient hydrogen production from acid based PEM water electrolysis, while also enabling proficient power generation from fuel cells (PEMFCs, DMFCs). The experimental results obtained in this project validate the theoretical predictions thus serving as a pathway for not only identifying new commercially viable electrocatalysts with significant reduction in noble metal content but also even completely eliminating use of any precious metals. The project thus has significant potential for advancing the science and technology of PGM-free electrocatalysts for acid mediated PEM based water electrolysis..</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 01/17/2019<br>      Modified by: Prashant&nbsp;N&nbsp;Kumta</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Images (<span id="selectedPhoto0">1</span> of <span class="totalNumber"></span>)           </div> <div class="galControls" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1511390/1511390_10395971_1544028499713_Fig-1-final--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1511390/1511390_10395971_1544028499713_Fig-1-final--rgov-800width.jpg" title="TEM images of as-synthesized (Mn0.8Ir0.2)O2:10F NRs,"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1511390/1511390_10395971_1544028499713_Fig-1-final--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="TEM images of as-synthesized (Mn0.8Ir0.2)O2:10F NRs,"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">(a-b) TEM images of as-synthesized (Mn0.8Ir0.2)O2:10F NRs,  (c-d) HRTEM images of a representative (Mn0.8Ir0.2)O2:10F NR, highlighting lattice fringe of the 0.69 nm that correspond to the (110) plane, (e) line scan analysis across a representative (Mn0.8Ir0.2)O2:10F NR, and (f)  EDS elemental mappin</div> <div class="imageCredit">Shrinath Ghadge</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Moni&nbsp;K&nbsp;Datta</div> <div class="imageTitle">TEM images of as-synthesized (Mn0.8Ir0.2)O2:10F NRs,</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1511390/1511390_10395971_1544028747469_Fig-2-final--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1511390/1511390_10395971_1544028747469_Fig-2-final--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Vertically aligned (Sn,Ir)O2:F solid solution nanotubes"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1511390/1511390_10395971_1544028747469_Fig-2-final--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Vertically aligned (Sn,Ir)O2:F solid solution nanotubes"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Highly efficient and robust oxygen evolution electrocatalysts for proton exchange membrane based water electrolysis</div> <div class="imageCredit">Shrinath Ghadge</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Moni&nbsp;K&nbsp;Datta</div> <div class="imageTitle">Vertically aligned (Sn,Ir)O2:F solid solution nanotubes</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1511390/1511390_10395971_1544037111472_Cu-Mn-O--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1511390/1511390_10395971_1544037111472_Cu-Mn-O--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Projected d-band DOS for Cu1.5Mn1.5O4"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1511390/1511390_10395971_1544037111472_Cu-Mn-O--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Projected d-band DOS for Cu1.5Mn1.5O4"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">D-band electronic DOS for Pt, IrO2, Cu1.5Mn1.5O4 and F-doped Cu1.5Mn1.5O4. Red dashed line indicates the d-band center position for Pt and IrO2. Blue arrows denote d-band centers for Cu1.5Mn1.5O4 and F-doped Cu1.5Mn1.5O4. Fermi level is set to zero.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Oleg Velikokhatnyi</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Oleg&nbsp;I&nbsp;Velikokhatnyi</div> <div class="imageTitle">Projected d-band DOS for Cu1.5Mn1.5O4</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1511390/1511390_10395971_1544037322773_conip10-10_NiNiboth_dG--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1511390/1511390_10395971_1544037322773_conip10-10_NiNiboth_dG--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Gibbs free energy for OER in CoNiP"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1511390/1511390_10395971_1544037322773_conip10-10_NiNiboth_dG--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Gibbs free energy for OER in CoNiP"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Calculated Gibbs free energy for elementary steps of OER in pure and F-doped CoNiP</div> <div class="imageCredit">Oleg Velikokhatnyi</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Oleg&nbsp;I&nbsp;Velikokhatnyi</div> <div class="imageTitle">Gibbs free energy for OER in CoNiP</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The major goal of this proposal is to develop highly efficient ultra-low noble metal content (e.g. Pt, IrO2, RuO2) and noble metal and even precious group metal free (PGM-free) oxygen evolution reaction (OER) electrocatalyst for proton exchange membrane (PEM) based acid mediated water electrolysis. This in turn will reduce the capital cost while significantly improving the efficiency (&le;43kWh/kg H2) than the state-of-the art commercial PGM based PEM electrolyzers and expectedly meeting the hydrogen production cost goal ($2/Kg H2). In the direction of developing highly active and efficient ultra-low noble metal and PGM-free electrocatalysts, the fundamental relationships between the electrocatalyst atomic level crystal structure and compositions on the electrocatalyst surface as well as within the bulk, and surface related electrochemical properties have been correlated to understand the fundamental structure-property relationships in the 2D thin film system. In this direction, first principles based theoretical calculation (e.g. density functional theory, DFT) has been utilized to identify the suitable electrocatalysts and compositions followed by advanced experimental electrocatalyst synthesis, and characterization. Such atomic and electronic structure-property relationships is very helpful for the identification, design and synthesis of suitable electro-catalysts in 0D, 1D and 3D nanostructured dimensions and configurations as well as in the preferred oriented crystallographic state. The processing-structure-property correlations will also serve to ultimately develop low cost PGM-free based electro-catalysts. The theoretical and experimental studies will thus work synergistically to determine not only the bulk and surface atomic and electronic level structures and compositions that are effective in terms of electrocatalytic response but also help to understand the underlying detailed mechanisms contributing to the electrocatalytic activity.. Understanding of the mechanisms will then serve to effectively fine tune and design the electrocatalyst system helping to unravel the fundamental pathways leading to the identification of PGM-free commercially viable electrocatalyst for PEM based acid mediated electrolyzers.  In order to understand the process/synthesis-atomic/electronic structure-electrochemical property relationships, a fundamental theoretical and experimental study has been conducted to integrate theory, modeling, synthesis, structural and electrochemical characterization of the electrocatalysts to advance the science and technology of electrocatalysts. In this direction, theoretically predicted F doped (Mn,Ir)O2:F, (Sn,Ir)O2:F, and (Sn,Nb,Ir)O2:F have been synthesized in 2D thin film and suitable correlation between processing-structure property have been developed. The theoretical and experimental outcomes and understandings of structure-property relationship of 2D thin film obtained has been utilized to synthesize highly active low overpotential electrocatalysts in different "materials length scales" e. g. vertically aligned 1D nanorod/nanotube structure of (Sn,Ir)O2:F and (Mn,Ir)O2:F were synthesized which expedite the reaction kinetics resulting in superior electrocatalytic activity towards water splitting compared to the 2D structures. Low noble metal containing 1D nanotube of (Mn,Ir)O2:10F and (Sn,Ir)O2:F solid solution indeed show excellent promise for replacing the state of the art OER electro-catalysts IrO2/RuO2 on the grounds of its excellent electrochemical performance. This study portends significant reduction in noble metal content for OER electro-catalyst along with a significant improvement in electrochemical activity. Together, these will be of immense help in reducing the capital cost of water electrolysis cells for economic and efficient hydrogen production from acid based PEM water electrolysis for meeting the incessantly growing global energy demands, employing non-carbonaceous clean energy source in an efficient and economic manner.  The 2D thin film data has also been utilized to synthesize for the very first time highly active low overpotential 3D nanostructured non noble metal containing Cu-Mn-oxides based PGM-free electrocatalyst. In addition, PGM-free F doped cobalt nickel phosphide (CoNiP:F), and Mn-metal oxide electro-catalyst were computationally identified and experientially validated for oxygen evolution reaction (OER) for PEM water electrolysis,. The first-principles calculations of the total energies and electronic structures identified Co-Ni-P and Mn-metal oxide based electro-catalysts. Both F doped CoNiP and Mn-metal oxide were thus explored as high performance electro-catalysts possessing unique electronic structures mimicking the PGM electrocatalysts. Development of PGM-free electrocatalyst marks a hallmark advancement in the identification and development of novel noble metal-free 0D and 3D nanostructured electro-catalysts (Cu-Mn-oxide, CoNiP and Mn metal-oxide) possessing unique electronic/molecular structure exhibiting remarkable stability and outstanding electrochemical activity higher than IrO2 for OER, the currently accepted gold standard electro-catalysts. Hence, these systems can replace IrO2 with possible further modification leading to further improvements. In the opinion of the PIs, the system represents a fundamental breakthrough in the pursuit of PGM-free electrocatalysts for economic and efficient hydrogen production from acid based PEM water electrolysis, while also enabling proficient power generation from fuel cells (PEMFCs, DMFCs). The experimental results obtained in this project validate the theoretical predictions thus serving as a pathway for not only identifying new commercially viable electrocatalysts with significant reduction in noble metal content but also even completely eliminating use of any precious metals. The project thus has significant potential for advancing the science and technology of PGM-free electrocatalysts for acid mediated PEM based water electrolysis..          Last Modified: 01/17/2019       Submitted by: Prashant N Kumta]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
