<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>UNS: A Novel Cell Selection System Using Evolved, Natural-Product Responsive Caspases</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/15/2015</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2020</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>600000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>606000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07020000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CBET</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Chem, Bioeng, Env, &amp; Transp Sys</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Steve Zehnder</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>szehnder@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927014</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>1511367 &lt;br/&gt;Hardy, Jeanne A.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Various plants make many different chemicals that are of use to human beings in personal healthcare products, neutraceuticals, flavors and fragrances, oils and fats and other high-value foods and pharmaceutical ingredients. In this project it is proposed to increase productivity of plant cell cultures by eliminating the non-producing cells and by keeping the high-producing cells alive with the help of a mammalian protein. This cell-killing protein has a binding site that can be manipulated so that it binds a specific chemical. When that compound binds it inactivates the protein. In cells that make lots of the desired chemical, the cell-killing protein is turned off and cells remain alive. This system will first be developed for plant culture based production of Taxol, a chemotherapy drug.  The approach is expected to be applicable to many valuable chemicals produced by plant cells.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Plant natural products represent a promising sector of rare and unique chemical entities impacting healthcare, energy, agriculture, food and nutraceuticals. Production and supply of desirable natural products is often challenging due to their chemical complexity, incompletely characterized biosynthetic pathways and prohibitive numbers of steps in their synthetic preparation. The synthesis of compounds with plant cell hosts often is suboptimal due to low production levels and cellular heterogeneity, with some cells producing high levels and other cells producing no product. In this project a completely novel approach has been designed that enables selection of high-producing cells from heterogeneous plant cultures. This approach relies on the finding that particular mammalian proteases sentence plant cells to death. A fluorescent reporter will be used to engineer an existing protease allosteric site to recognize and be inhibited by paclitaxel (Taxol). This protease that can be inhibited by Taxol, will selectively kill non-paclitaxel producing cells, while leaving productive cells intact. The approach likely will be useful not only for the production of Taxol but for a broad range of plant culture systems.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award by the Biotechnology and Biochemical Engineering Program of the CBET Division is co-funded by the Cellular Dynamics and Function Program of the Division of Molecular and Cellular Biology.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>09/13/2015</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>09/11/2019</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1511367</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Susan</FirstName>
<LastName>Roberts</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>C</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Susan C Roberts</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>scroberts@wpi.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5088315669</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000093578</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/13/2015</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Jeanne</FirstName>
<LastName>Hardy</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>A</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Jeanne A Hardy</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>hardy@chem.umass.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>4135453486</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000069622</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/13/2015</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Massachusetts Amherst</Name>
<CityName>Hadley</CityName>
<ZipCode>010359450</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>4135450698</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>Research Administration Building</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[100 Venture Way, Suite 201]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
<StateCode>MA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MA02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>153926712</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF MASSACHUSETTS</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>079520631</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Massachusetts Amherst]]></Name>
<CityName>Amherst</CityName>
<StateCode>MA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>010039305</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[70 Butterfield Terrace]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MA02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1114</Code>
<Text>Cellular Dynamics and Function</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1491</Code>
<Text>Cellular &amp; Biochem Engineering</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7275</Code>
<Text>Cross-BIO Activities</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>009E</Code>
<Text>Metabolic engineering</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1114</Code>
<Text>CELLULAR SYSTEMS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>144E</Code>
<Text>Synthetic biology</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1757</Code>
<Text>Quantitative sys bio and biotech</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8007</Code>
<Text>BioMaPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9251</Code>
<Text>REU SUPP-Res Exp for Ugrd Supp</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0115</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0117</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2015~600000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2017~6000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>This project was a collaborative project between the laboratories of Jeanne Hardy, a caspase expert, at the University of Massachusetts and Susan Roberts, an expert in the cell-based production of paclitaxel and other industrially relevant plant specialized metabolites via plant cell culture, at Worcester Polytechnic Institute. The major goals of this project was to develop a technology that will improve our ability to produce important plant-derived compounds in plant cell culture. Specifically, we have worked to develop a technology that will allow us to sense which cells are producing a lot of the desired compound and which cells produce little. In this case the sensor is a protein called a caspase and when it is active it can cause plant cells to die. When the compound is present it binds to an engineered caspase and keeps the caspase in a dormant state, so those cells live. When the compound is absent the caspase is active and the cells die. The work from this grant has been to develop this system in cells from the Pacific Yew tree (<em>Taxus</em> cells). These cells are of commercial interest as they naturally produce paclitaxel, a widely used compound that can cause defective cells to die. During the course of this work, we made several advances: i) we developed new methods for visualizing and quantifying the amount to paclitaxel in various strains of Taxus cells, ii) we measured the affinities of various compounds related to paclitaxel for a large number of proteases, both caspases and viral protease that are involved in cell death, iii) developed a method for the genetic selection of proteases that are inhibited by small molecules, iv) characterize various several viral protease biochemical properties. This work has resulted in the publication of five scientific publications in both the plant biology and biochemical literature with two more in preparation.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>This grant has also had significant training impacts, especially on two talented graduate students who worked collaboratively over the course of this work and participated in cross-disciplinary training in both laboratories. Both of these students completed highly productive PhD degrees. Due to the translational nature of this work, Hill from the Hardy lab was selected as a UMass Isenberg Scholar and participated actively in the Business Foundation Series for Scientists and Engineers. As part of these programs Hill engaged in a number of industrial outreach efforts at both Phyton Biotech and Pfizer to discuss implementation and adoption of our engineered caspase technology for selection of cells producing high levels of industrially-valuable plant specialized metabolites. Hill is now a scientist working at MOMA Therapeutics. McKee, a graduate student in the Roberts lab is now a Post-doctoral fellow at the Whitehead Institute at MIT where she is using many of the skills developed during her work on this project. In addition to the training of graduate students, this project included training for a number of undergraduate students. We provided training to 6 undergraduates. I highlight one of these students. Hill served as a mentor to Huang, an undergraduate researcher in the Hardy lab, who is now a graduate student at the University of California at Berkeley in the laboratory of one of the winners of the Nobel Prize in Chemistry. This proposal has also had significant broader impacts. Hardy Leads the UMass Biotech Training Program and an Every Other Thursday Mutual Mentoring Program. Roberts is heavily invested in demystifying plant science to the general public through presentations such as the one that Roberts gave as part of the Sci Tech Series, led by Mount Holyoke College and sponsored by the NSF. Hardy was selected as the inaugural winner of the Mahoney Life Sciences Prize. As part of this prize, her work was highlighted in the UMass Magazine and a number of professionally produced videos highlighting Hardy?s work on proteases are now available to the general public on YouTube. Notably both PIs and both graduate students, as well as the vast majority of the undergrads working on this project were members of groups traditionally underrepresented in science and engineering.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 01/14/2021<br>      Modified by: Jeanne&nbsp;A&nbsp;Hardy</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ This project was a collaborative project between the laboratories of Jeanne Hardy, a caspase expert, at the University of Massachusetts and Susan Roberts, an expert in the cell-based production of paclitaxel and other industrially relevant plant specialized metabolites via plant cell culture, at Worcester Polytechnic Institute. The major goals of this project was to develop a technology that will improve our ability to produce important plant-derived compounds in plant cell culture. Specifically, we have worked to develop a technology that will allow us to sense which cells are producing a lot of the desired compound and which cells produce little. In this case the sensor is a protein called a caspase and when it is active it can cause plant cells to die. When the compound is present it binds to an engineered caspase and keeps the caspase in a dormant state, so those cells live. When the compound is absent the caspase is active and the cells die. The work from this grant has been to develop this system in cells from the Pacific Yew tree (Taxus cells). These cells are of commercial interest as they naturally produce paclitaxel, a widely used compound that can cause defective cells to die. During the course of this work, we made several advances: i) we developed new methods for visualizing and quantifying the amount to paclitaxel in various strains of Taxus cells, ii) we measured the affinities of various compounds related to paclitaxel for a large number of proteases, both caspases and viral protease that are involved in cell death, iii) developed a method for the genetic selection of proteases that are inhibited by small molecules, iv) characterize various several viral protease biochemical properties. This work has resulted in the publication of five scientific publications in both the plant biology and biochemical literature with two more in preparation.     This grant has also had significant training impacts, especially on two talented graduate students who worked collaboratively over the course of this work and participated in cross-disciplinary training in both laboratories. Both of these students completed highly productive PhD degrees. Due to the translational nature of this work, Hill from the Hardy lab was selected as a UMass Isenberg Scholar and participated actively in the Business Foundation Series for Scientists and Engineers. As part of these programs Hill engaged in a number of industrial outreach efforts at both Phyton Biotech and Pfizer to discuss implementation and adoption of our engineered caspase technology for selection of cells producing high levels of industrially-valuable plant specialized metabolites. Hill is now a scientist working at MOMA Therapeutics. McKee, a graduate student in the Roberts lab is now a Post-doctoral fellow at the Whitehead Institute at MIT where she is using many of the skills developed during her work on this project. In addition to the training of graduate students, this project included training for a number of undergraduate students. We provided training to 6 undergraduates. I highlight one of these students. Hill served as a mentor to Huang, an undergraduate researcher in the Hardy lab, who is now a graduate student at the University of California at Berkeley in the laboratory of one of the winners of the Nobel Prize in Chemistry. This proposal has also had significant broader impacts. Hardy Leads the UMass Biotech Training Program and an Every Other Thursday Mutual Mentoring Program. Roberts is heavily invested in demystifying plant science to the general public through presentations such as the one that Roberts gave as part of the Sci Tech Series, led by Mount Holyoke College and sponsored by the NSF. Hardy was selected as the inaugural winner of the Mahoney Life Sciences Prize. As part of this prize, her work was highlighted in the UMass Magazine and a number of professionally produced videos highlighting Hardy?s work on proteases are now available to the general public on YouTube. Notably both PIs and both graduate students, as well as the vast majority of the undergrads working on this project were members of groups traditionally underrepresented in science and engineering.       Last Modified: 01/14/2021       Submitted by: Jeanne A Hardy]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
