<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Novel Ferromagnetic Domains and Quantum Criticality with Bose Condensates in a Shaken Optical Lattice</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/15/2015</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>456657.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>456657</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03010000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>PHY</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Physics</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>John D. Gillaspy</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>jgillasp@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927173</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>While atoms have been long recognized as the building blocks of the world we see and the environment we live in, their behavior at low temperatures has never ceased to surprise us. Examples include superfluids that flow without friction and quantum magnetic materials that permit read, write and storage of ample information. A recent work led by the principal investigator showed that both superfluidity and ferromagnetism (the type of magnetism in bar magnets) manifest simultaneously in atoms when shaken back and forth by laser beams, like ping-pong balls riding the ripples on a lake. The intriguing dynamics of magnetic domains observed in the atomic superfluids suggests new strategies to efficiently store and process information in the quantum regime. The major science goal of this project is to simulate and study a new type of 4-pole magnet in a two-dimensional lattice, which promises much richer properties than the 2-pole (south and north pole) magnetism in conventional materials. The science program is complimented by an extensive outreach effort under the S.M.A.R.T. (Science, Mathematics, And Research Training) project. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The proposed 4-pole magnetic phase will arise when an atomic superfluid is transferred into a two-dimensional shaken optical lattice, generated by overlapping two perpendicular optical standing waves. When the shaking amplitude is carefully tuned above a critical value, the superfluid is anticipated to split into 4 poles with ferromagnetic interactions. The formation of the 4-pole domain will be detected and studied by direct in situ imaging of the atomic sample. Compared to the conventional 2-pole magnets, the 4-pole magnets offer novel domain and vertex structures and are uniquely related to the four-color theorem in graph theory and the Potts model of statistical physics. Furthermore the phase transition into the ferromagnetic phase is associated with a variety of quantum phenomena, including Rashba superfluids, the Berezinskii-Kosterlitz-Thouless transition, and the Kibble-Zurek mechanism. Exploration of this quantum physics may have both academic and practical payoffs, including the development of a theoretical framework to understand quantum critical dynamics, simulations of N-pole ferromagnetic magnets, fabrication of programmable magnetic materials, and potentially even quantum information storage and processing.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/09/2015</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/18/2017</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1511696</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Cheng</FirstName>
<LastName>Chin</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Cheng Chin</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>cchin@uchicago.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>7737027192</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000488317</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/09/2015</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Chicago</Name>
<CityName>Chicago</CityName>
<ZipCode>606372612</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>7737028669</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>6054 South Drexel Avenue</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[Suite 300]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Illinois</StateName>
<StateCode>IL</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>IL01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>005421136</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF CHICAGO, THE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>005421136</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Chicago]]></Name>
<CityName>Chicago</CityName>
<StateCode>IL</StateCode>
<ZipCode>606371454</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[929 East 57th St]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Illinois</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>IL01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1241</Code>
<Text>AMO Experiment/Atomic, Molecul</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0115</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0116</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0117</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2015~180956</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2016~135813</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2017~139888</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Supported by NSF, we observed a new quantum phenomena in the past year, which we called Bose fireworks, a stimulated scattering of bosonic matterwaves from Bose-Einstein condensate with oscillating scattering length length.See Figure 1.</p> <p>Scattering  is used to probe matter and its interactions in all areas of physics.  In ultracold atomic gases, control over pairwise interactions enables us  to investigate scattering in quantum many-body systems. Previous experiments on colliding Bose&ndash;Einstein condensates have revealed matter&ndash;wave interference, haloes of scattered atoms, four-wave mixingand correlations between counter-propagating pairs. However, a regime with strong stimulation of spontaneous collisions analogous to superradiance has proved elusive. Here we find that  runaway stimulated collisions in Bose&ndash;Einstein condensates with  periodically modulated interaction strength cause the collective  emission of matter-wave jets that resemble fireworks. Jets appear only  above a threshold modulation amplitude and their correlations are  invariant even when the number of ejected atoms grows exponentially. See Figure 2 for the jet pattern that we extrated based on pattern recognition.</p> <p>We show that the structures and atom occupancies of the jets stem  from the quantum fluctuations of the condensate. Our findings  demonstrate the conditions required for runaway stimulated collisions  and reveal the quantum nature of matter-wave emission, see Figure 3 as an illustration to general readers.</p> <div id="abstract-section" class="serif article-section js-article-section cleared clear"></div><br> <p>            Last Modified: 08/12/2018<br>      Modified by: Cheng&nbsp;Chin</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Images (<span id="selectedPhoto0">1</span> of <span class="totalNumber"></span>)           </div> <div class="galControls" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1511696/1511696_10385579_1533683962814_BoseFireworks--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1511696/1511696_10385579_1533683962814_BoseFireworks--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Observation of Bose fireworks"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1511696/1511696_10385579_1533683962814_BoseFireworks--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Observation of Bose fireworks"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">By modulating the interactions between atoms, matterwaves in the Bose-Einstein condensate (center) emit in all directions and form jet-like structure.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Nature 551, 356 (2017)</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Public Domain</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Cheng&nbsp;Chin</div> <div class="imageTitle">Observation of Bose fireworks</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1511696/1511696_10385579_1533684125344_atoms--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1511696/1511696_10385579_1533684125344_atoms--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Correlations of Bose fireworks"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1511696/1511696_10385579_1533684125344_atoms--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Correlations of Bose fireworks"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Based on pattern recognition, we identify a complex correlation pattern in the emission of Bose fireworks.</div> <div class="imageCredit">ArXiv:1803.01786</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Public Domain</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Cheng&nbsp;Chin</div> <div class="imageTitle">Correlations of Bose fireworks</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1511696/1511696_10385579_1533684375787_JFI_Image_Contest_multicolor--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1511696/1511696_10385579_1533684375787_JFI_Image_Contest_multicolor--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Emergence of Bose fireworks"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1511696/1511696_10385579_1533684375787_JFI_Image_Contest_multicolor--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Emergence of Bose fireworks"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">A sequence of images show the evolution of matterwave emission from the driven Bose condensate (left to right). The emission pattern results from Bose stimulation and resembles fireworks.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Nature 551, 356 (2017)</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Cheng&nbsp;Chin</div> <div class="imageTitle">Emergence of Bose fireworks</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Supported by NSF, we observed a new quantum phenomena in the past year, which we called Bose fireworks, a stimulated scattering of bosonic matterwaves from Bose-Einstein condensate with oscillating scattering length length.See Figure 1.  Scattering  is used to probe matter and its interactions in all areas of physics.  In ultracold atomic gases, control over pairwise interactions enables us  to investigate scattering in quantum many-body systems. Previous experiments on colliding Bose&ndash;Einstein condensates have revealed matter&ndash;wave interference, haloes of scattered atoms, four-wave mixingand correlations between counter-propagating pairs. However, a regime with strong stimulation of spontaneous collisions analogous to superradiance has proved elusive. Here we find that  runaway stimulated collisions in Bose&ndash;Einstein condensates with  periodically modulated interaction strength cause the collective  emission of matter-wave jets that resemble fireworks. Jets appear only  above a threshold modulation amplitude and their correlations are  invariant even when the number of ejected atoms grows exponentially. See Figure 2 for the jet pattern that we extrated based on pattern recognition.  We show that the structures and atom occupancies of the jets stem  from the quantum fluctuations of the condensate. Our findings  demonstrate the conditions required for runaway stimulated collisions  and reveal the quantum nature of matter-wave emission, see Figure 3 as an illustration to general readers.        Last Modified: 08/12/2018       Submitted by: Cheng Chin]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
