<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Innovative Science Technology Engineering and Mathematics Strategy Project</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>06/01/2015</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>1198404.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>1198404</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>11090000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>EHR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DRL</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Research On Learning</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Julia Clark</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This project will advance efforts of the Innovative Technology Experiences for Students and Teachers (ITEST) program to better understand and promote practices that increase students' motivations and capacities to pursue careers in fields of science, technology, engineering, or mathematics (STEM) by engaging in hands-on field experience, laboratory/project-based entrepreneurship tasks and mentorship experiences. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The Innovative Science Technology Engineering and Mathematics Strategies Project of Morehouse College is designed to provide underrepresented minority students with science, technology, engineering, and mathematics (STEM) challenging technological learning experiences that will increase the students' exposure to innovation and creativity in the STEM disciplines. The project will explore the influence of these challenging opportunities on student's interest by 1) Increasing student awareness and knowledge of educational opportunities and careers in STEM disciplines; 2) Increasing student knowledge, skills and practices in STEM application; and 3) Increasing participation of underrepresented populations in STEM careers. This project will address these potential educational needs for minority students at a critical stage of their educational development by having students begin the program in grades 7-9 and supporting their development for a three (3) year period. The students will be engaged in a long-term (3 year) STEM technology program that will include a 4-week summer program, hands-on field experience, laboratory/project-based entrepreneurship tasks and mentorship, and parental involvement. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;A mixed-methods approach to project evaluation will be applied using both quantitative and qualitative measures design for a panel of formative and summative assessment instruments including project implementation, content knowledge, process knowledge, and attitudes. Whenever feasible, baseline date will be included. A database will be developed for milestones including dissemination efforts. Evaluation of the program will include both descriptive statistics and outcome analysis.  The research questions are: (1) What sets of experiences effectively and efficiently support student competency, motivation, and persistence for productive participation in the STEM and STEM cognate workforce in the future? (2) What roles might industry workforce members play in motivating students to become aware of, interested in, and prepared for careers in STEM and STEM cognate workforce? (3) What strategies might parents, caregivers, and mentors adopt in the modern digital and computer age that develop student understanding of and appreciation for the scientific, technical, mathematical, and engineering basis of technological developments? and (4) Given the shifting demographics reflected in our current classrooms and in our country, what are effective and productive ways to ensure broadening participation by engaging diverse underrepresented populations in STEM programs and careers?</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/03/2015</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/03/2015</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.076</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1512957</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Willie</FirstName>
<LastName>Rockward</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>S</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Willie S Rockward</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>willie.rockward@morgan.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>4438853226</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000358038</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/03/2015</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Cynthia</FirstName>
<LastName>Trawick</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>E</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Cynthia E Trawick</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>ctrawick@morehouse.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>4046537860</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000078276</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/03/2015</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Tiffany</FirstName>
<LastName>Bussey</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>R</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Tiffany R Bussey</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>tiffany.bussey@morehouse.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>4046812800</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000683917</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/03/2015</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Morehouse College</Name>
<CityName>Atlanta</CityName>
<ZipCode>303143773</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>4706390633</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>830 Westview Drive S W</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Georgia</StateName>
<StateCode>GA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>GA05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>075861773</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>MOREHOUSE COLLEGE (INC.)</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>075861773</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Morehouse College]]></Name>
<CityName>Atlanta</CityName>
<StateCode>GA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>303143773</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[830 Westview Drive S.W.]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Georgia</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>GA05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7227</Code>
<Text>ITEST-Inov Tech Exp Stu &amp; Teac</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<Appropriation>
<Code>13XX</Code>
<Name>H-1B FUND, EHR, NSF</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>045176</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2015~1198404</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The Innovative Science Technology Engineering and Mathematics Strategy Project (<em>i</em>STEM) of Morehouse College was designed to provide underrepresented minority students with challenging learning experiences that increased the students' exposure to innovation and creativity in the STEM disciplines. Sixty seven committed middle and high school students from underrepresented populations have participated over the course of 3 years.&nbsp; iSTEM addressed potential educational needs for minority students at a critical stage of their educational development by having students begin the program in grades 6-8 and supporting their development for a three (3) year period. The students were engaged in a long-term (3 year) STEM technology program that included 5-week summer programs, hands-on&nbsp; field experiences, laboratory/project-based entrepreneurship tasks,&nbsp; mentorship, and parental involvement. This program leveraged and extended NSF funded DR K-12 and Noyce programs by having the DRK-12 and Noyce scholars serve as near peer educators for&nbsp; <em>i</em>STEM participants.&nbsp; The working team for this project was composed of Morehouse faculty from STEM departments, the Center for Teacher Preparation and Leadership center, along with an Academic Advisor Specialist and 6-12th grade STEM faculty.&nbsp; This group met two to three times per month. They developed the curriculum for the iSTEM program that takes into consideration the pre-college faculty understanding of their students? current competencies as well as the Morehouse faculty understanding of the students? competencies that are critical for success in STEM careers.&nbsp; The program consisted of four major program components including Saturday Academy, Parent Workshops, Field Trips, and the Summer Academy.&nbsp;&nbsp; These collaborations resulted in development and implementation of all four components.&nbsp; The iSTEM program was successful in increasing student awareness of STEM educational opportunities and careers, increasing student knowledge and skills in STEM, increasing participation of underrepresented minorities in &nbsp;STEM, and increasing student exposure to innovation and creativity in &nbsp;STEM disciplines.&nbsp; A STEM careers discoveries class was added to the program where students researched STEM careers including the educational requirements for these careers and professional activity in the field.&nbsp; Students developed individual career profiles that included goal setting for high school and college.&nbsp; They selected colleges and programs to apply for and found out what the admissions requirements were so that they could prepare to meet them. Student in the program developed mentee relationships with STEM professionals to help guide them in the process. Students were provided with technology rich experiences that allowed them to discipline-based knowledge and practices by engagement with the Morehouse College Maker Space.&nbsp; The Morehouse College Maker Space is a cooperative laboratory workspace where students and faculty can construct objects, conduct research, collaborate, and gain practical hands-on experience with new technologies while engaging in applied learning. Students received training on the equipment in the Maker Space in order to develop their projects including the use of 3-D designs and production using 3-D printer.&nbsp; Students were also provided with opportunities to develop critical thinking and communication skills needed for entering STEM workforce sectors by engaging in critical thinking such as: brainstorming on projects, gathering pertinent background information, drafting hypothesis, discussing pros and cons of potential solutions, reviewing and including new background information, finalizing hypothesis, and concluding on best potential solutions.&nbsp;&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 06/26/2019<br>      Modified by: Cynthia&nbsp;E&nbsp;Trawick</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The Innovative Science Technology Engineering and Mathematics Strategy Project (iSTEM) of Morehouse College was designed to provide underrepresented minority students with challenging learning experiences that increased the students' exposure to innovation and creativity in the STEM disciplines. Sixty seven committed middle and high school students from underrepresented populations have participated over the course of 3 years.  iSTEM addressed potential educational needs for minority students at a critical stage of their educational development by having students begin the program in grades 6-8 and supporting their development for a three (3) year period. The students were engaged in a long-term (3 year) STEM technology program that included 5-week summer programs, hands-on  field experiences, laboratory/project-based entrepreneurship tasks,  mentorship, and parental involvement. This program leveraged and extended NSF funded DR K-12 and Noyce programs by having the DRK-12 and Noyce scholars serve as near peer educators for  iSTEM participants.  The working team for this project was composed of Morehouse faculty from STEM departments, the Center for Teacher Preparation and Leadership center, along with an Academic Advisor Specialist and 6-12th grade STEM faculty.  This group met two to three times per month. They developed the curriculum for the iSTEM program that takes into consideration the pre-college faculty understanding of their students? current competencies as well as the Morehouse faculty understanding of the students? competencies that are critical for success in STEM careers.  The program consisted of four major program components including Saturday Academy, Parent Workshops, Field Trips, and the Summer Academy.   These collaborations resulted in development and implementation of all four components.  The iSTEM program was successful in increasing student awareness of STEM educational opportunities and careers, increasing student knowledge and skills in STEM, increasing participation of underrepresented minorities in  STEM, and increasing student exposure to innovation and creativity in  STEM disciplines.  A STEM careers discoveries class was added to the program where students researched STEM careers including the educational requirements for these careers and professional activity in the field.  Students developed individual career profiles that included goal setting for high school and college.  They selected colleges and programs to apply for and found out what the admissions requirements were so that they could prepare to meet them. Student in the program developed mentee relationships with STEM professionals to help guide them in the process. Students were provided with technology rich experiences that allowed them to discipline-based knowledge and practices by engagement with the Morehouse College Maker Space.  The Morehouse College Maker Space is a cooperative laboratory workspace where students and faculty can construct objects, conduct research, collaborate, and gain practical hands-on experience with new technologies while engaging in applied learning. Students received training on the equipment in the Maker Space in order to develop their projects including the use of 3-D designs and production using 3-D printer.  Students were also provided with opportunities to develop critical thinking and communication skills needed for entering STEM workforce sectors by engaging in critical thinking such as: brainstorming on projects, gathering pertinent background information, drafting hypothesis, discussing pros and cons of potential solutions, reviewing and including new background information, finalizing hypothesis, and concluding on best potential solutions.         Last Modified: 06/26/2019       Submitted by: Cynthia E Trawick]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
