<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Optimal Decision Strategies for Large Spatio-Temporal Decision Problems</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/15/2015</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2020</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>149998.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>149998</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DMS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Gabor Szekely</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>gszekely@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032928869</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>A number of current public health, ecological, and environmental crises can be conceptualized as spatio-temporal decision problems wherein a harmful replicating agent is spreading across space and, simultaneously, a decision maker must select when, where, and how to allocate limited resources targeted at controlling the spread of the agent.  Examples include the spread of an infectious disease across people in a social network, the spread of a computer virus across machines in a network, and the spread of an invasive species across an ecological landscape.  The costs of these epidemics are enormous.  For example, 32% of global deaths are attributed to infectious diseases, the cost of computer viruses to U.S. businesses is estimated to exceed 60 billion dollars per year, and the cost of invasive species is estimated to exceed 100 billion dollars per year and to affect 100 million acres of land.  Thus, improvements to spatio-temporal decision making could have tremendous benefits to all sectors of society. Technological advances have made it increasingly easy to collect, store, and manipulate large amounts of data.  This research project takes first steps toward methods that use accumulating data on the spread of a replicating agent to inform resource allocation over time.  The methodology adjusts for non-stationary agent dynamics, changing availability of resources, and uncertain or incomplete measurements.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;A key component of controlling the spread of a replicating agent over space and time is deciding where, when, and how to apply interventions.  This control process is formalized as an allocation strategy which comprises a sequence of functions, one per time point, that map up-to-date information on the spread of the agent to a distribution over subsets of locations to receive an intervention.  The project formally defines an optimal allocation strategy using potential outcomes, and demonstrates that spatial proximity induces causal interference among locations, thereby preventing direct application of existing methods for sequential treatment assignment.  A parametric estimator of the optimal strategy within a pre-specified class of allocation strategies using a systems dynamics model and simulation-optimization is developed.  This estimator has low variance and can be applied in a data-impoverished setting, however it may suffer from high bias if the systems dynamics model is misspecified.  A semi-parametric estimator of the optimal allocation strategy which does not require correct specification of a systems dynamics model is also developed.  Because the semi-parametric estimator relies on fewer assumptions about the underlying systems dynamics, it is potentially robust to model misspecification but may have high variance.  To balance bias and variance, and optimize finite sample performance, shrinkage of the semi-parametric estimator toward the parametric estimator will be investigated.  The methodologies will be illustrated with an application to the spread of white-nose syndrome in bats.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>09/11/2015</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/30/2019</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1513579</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Brian</FirstName>
<LastName>Reich</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>J</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Brian J Reich</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>brian_reich@ncsu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>9195137686</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000337671</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/11/2015</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Eric</FirstName>
<LastName>Laber</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>B</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Eric B Laber</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>eric.laber@duke.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>7343309675</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000599601</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/11/2015</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Jamian</FirstName>
<LastName>Pacifici</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>K</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Jamian K Pacifici</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>jkpacifi@ncsu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>9195152444</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000673857</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/11/2015</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>North Carolina State University</Name>
<CityName>Raleigh</CityName>
<ZipCode>276957514</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>9195152444</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>2601 Wolf Village Way</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[Admin. III, STE 240]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>North Carolina</StateName>
<StateCode>NC</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NC04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>042092122</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>NORTH CAROLINA STATE UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>142363428</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[North Carolina State University]]></Name>
<CityName>Raleigh</CityName>
<StateCode>NC</StateCode>
<ZipCode>276958204</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[2701 Sullivan Drive]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>North Carolina</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NC02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1269</Code>
<Text>STATISTICS</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9251</Code>
<Text>REU SUPP-Res Exp for Ugrd Supp</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0115</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0116</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0117</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2015~49609</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2016~49224</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2017~51165</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The primary goal of this proposal was to develop new methods for data-driven decision making &nbsp;in problems evolving over space and time. &nbsp;Such problems include the deployment of resources during a humanitarian crises, monitoring and managing a replicating agent on a network (such as an infectious disease or mis-information on a social media platform), and planning in transportation networks. &nbsp;Formalizing optimal decision making in these problems is complex due to spillover effects, i.e., applying an intervention in one location can impact the outcomes in another. &nbsp;We developed a formal causal inference framework for spatial-temporal decision problems and derived conditions under which an optimal decision strategy (one that maximizes cumulative utility under resource constraints) can be learned from observed data. &nbsp;Under these conditions, we derived parametric and semi-parametric estimators of optimal decision strategies that are scalable to very large systems, e.g., networks with hundreds of thousands of nodes. &nbsp;We derived new theoretical results for these estimators including convergence rates and methods for uncertainty quantification thereby establishing a solid mathematical foundation for future work in this area. &nbsp;</p> <p>The value of this work goes beyond new contributions to science. &nbsp;We illustrated the application of these method to: infectious diseases, including influenza, Ebola virus diseases, and Malaria; wildlife management, including White Nose Syndrome in Bats and mallard license allocation; and logistics, including airline scheduling. &nbsp;The proposed methods consistently demonstrated improved performance relative to standard practice in empirical experiments. &nbsp;</p> <p>This work has also generated several promising new lines of research. &nbsp;These include feature construction for reinforcement learning on networks, online estimation of hidden networks (with applications to hard-to-reach populations), and safe reinforcement learning under constraints. &nbsp; We plan to pursue these lines of research in future projects. &nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 01/11/2021<br>      Modified by: Eric&nbsp;B&nbsp;Laber</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The primary goal of this proposal was to develop new methods for data-driven decision making  in problems evolving over space and time.  Such problems include the deployment of resources during a humanitarian crises, monitoring and managing a replicating agent on a network (such as an infectious disease or mis-information on a social media platform), and planning in transportation networks.  Formalizing optimal decision making in these problems is complex due to spillover effects, i.e., applying an intervention in one location can impact the outcomes in another.  We developed a formal causal inference framework for spatial-temporal decision problems and derived conditions under which an optimal decision strategy (one that maximizes cumulative utility under resource constraints) can be learned from observed data.  Under these conditions, we derived parametric and semi-parametric estimators of optimal decision strategies that are scalable to very large systems, e.g., networks with hundreds of thousands of nodes.  We derived new theoretical results for these estimators including convergence rates and methods for uncertainty quantification thereby establishing a solid mathematical foundation for future work in this area.    The value of this work goes beyond new contributions to science.  We illustrated the application of these method to: infectious diseases, including influenza, Ebola virus diseases, and Malaria; wildlife management, including White Nose Syndrome in Bats and mallard license allocation; and logistics, including airline scheduling.  The proposed methods consistently demonstrated improved performance relative to standard practice in empirical experiments.    This work has also generated several promising new lines of research.  These include feature construction for reinforcement learning on networks, online estimation of hidden networks (with applications to hard-to-reach populations), and safe reinforcement learning under constraints.   We plan to pursue these lines of research in future projects.            Last Modified: 01/11/2021       Submitted by: Eric B Laber]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
