<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>CIF: Medium: Collaborative Research: Feedback Communication: Models, Designs, and Fundamental Limits</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>06/01/2015</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>392777.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>392777</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>05010000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>CSE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CCF</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division of Computing and Communication Foundations</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Phillip Regalia</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>pregalia@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922981</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Claude Shannon?s ?A Mathematical Theory of Communication? is the landmark event that paved the way for the development of modern communication systems. Shannon analyzed the fundamental redundancy that must be added to data in order to achieve reliable communication in the presence of noise. Since then his vision has guided the practical design of virtually all aspects of modern communication systems such as forward error correction, spectrally-efficient communication, multiuser and inter-symbol interference, multiple-antenna systems, opportunistic communication, and joint compression/transmission. However, while feedback is present in virtually all modern communication systems, the field of information theory has had relatively little impact on how feedback is employed in practice.  The proposed work will advance knowledge by developing a more complete understanding of how feedback should be employed in communication systems and what quantitative improvements in delay, complexity, and transmitted power one can expect from its effective use, under realistic delay constraints such as those found in high-speed wireless data. In summary, the successful completion of the project is expected to contribute new mathematical tools, designs, viewpoints, and models to the field of information theory.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The goal of this research is to bring the insight, design guidance, and performance bounds for which information theory is known to bear on the design of systems with feedback. By providing new design principles and feedback codes, this research has the potential not only to advance basic science but also to improve the efficiency and reliability of our communications infrastructure, including consumer technology such as WiFi and smartphones. Given the proliferation of personal communication devices, such improvements would augment the efficiency with which crucial resources such as energy and radio frequency bandwidth are currently utilized.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>05/28/2015</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/08/2017</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.070</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1513858</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Aaron</FirstName>
<LastName>Wagner</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>B</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Aaron B Wagner</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>wagner@ece.cornell.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6072551017</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000332581</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/28/2015</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Cornell University</Name>
<CityName>Ithaca</CityName>
<ZipCode>148502820</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6072555014</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>373 Pine Tree Road</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>23</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NY23</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>872612445</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>CORNELL UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>002254837</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Cornell University]]></Name>
<CityName>Ithaca</CityName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<ZipCode>148533801</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[388 Rhodes Hall]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>23</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NY23</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7797</Code>
<Text>Comm &amp; Information Foundations</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7924</Code>
<Text>MEDIUM PROJECT</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7935</Code>
<Text>COMM &amp; INFORMATION THEORY</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0115</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0117</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2015~257346</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2017~135431</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Most real-world telecommunications systems are two-way: one can send as well as receive information. When one of the two lines is idle, it can be used to facilitate information in the reverse direction. This has long been recognized in practice, but the theory guiding the use of such "feedback" links has been lacking.&nbsp; Feedback links are difficult to analyze, and there are several classical theoretical results indicating that feedback links are actually not useful at all.<br /><br />This project provided a new understanding of how to use feedback links to facilitate communication. The idea is that a transmitter should monitor the transmission using the feedback link and use a timid or cautious signaling scheme so long as the transmission is proceeding well and a bold signaling scheme if it looks likely that the decoder will not decode the signal correctly. This is akin to the way sports teams use risky plays when they are losing late in a game.<br /><br />This project analyzed the above ideas in its most sophisticated form using the theory of controlled diffusions. It also showed that whenever feedback links are useful for improving performance in a given communications system, the above idea can be applied. It also showed that for some channel communications scenarios in which the above idea cannot be applied, feedback links to do not help forward communications in a particularly strong sense.&nbsp; We now have a better understanding of how to design telecommunications systems as a result of this project.<br /><br />The project also resulted in new infrastructure for research and teaching in telecommunications. Research and teaching in telecommunications is often quite theoretical, in part due to the cost of creating viable labs. This project created a laboratory channel "in the cloud" that allows students to send signals through channels without requiring physical access to the channel and without the overhead of learning technical details of radio hardware such as GNU Radio. This has allowed students to conduct capstone design projects using real channels that otherwise would have been done entirely via computer simulation.<br /><br /></p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 09/30/2019<br>      Modified by: Aaron&nbsp;B&nbsp;Wagner</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Most real-world telecommunications systems are two-way: one can send as well as receive information. When one of the two lines is idle, it can be used to facilitate information in the reverse direction. This has long been recognized in practice, but the theory guiding the use of such "feedback" links has been lacking.  Feedback links are difficult to analyze, and there are several classical theoretical results indicating that feedback links are actually not useful at all.  This project provided a new understanding of how to use feedback links to facilitate communication. The idea is that a transmitter should monitor the transmission using the feedback link and use a timid or cautious signaling scheme so long as the transmission is proceeding well and a bold signaling scheme if it looks likely that the decoder will not decode the signal correctly. This is akin to the way sports teams use risky plays when they are losing late in a game.  This project analyzed the above ideas in its most sophisticated form using the theory of controlled diffusions. It also showed that whenever feedback links are useful for improving performance in a given communications system, the above idea can be applied. It also showed that for some channel communications scenarios in which the above idea cannot be applied, feedback links to do not help forward communications in a particularly strong sense.  We now have a better understanding of how to design telecommunications systems as a result of this project.  The project also resulted in new infrastructure for research and teaching in telecommunications. Research and teaching in telecommunications is often quite theoretical, in part due to the cost of creating viable labs. This project created a laboratory channel "in the cloud" that allows students to send signals through channels without requiring physical access to the channel and without the overhead of learning technical details of radio hardware such as GNU Radio. This has allowed students to conduct capstone design projects using real channels that otherwise would have been done entirely via computer simulation.         Last Modified: 09/30/2019       Submitted by: Aaron B Wagner]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
