<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>RAPID: Tele-Nursing Robots for Remote Treatment of Ebola Patients</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>12/01/2014</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>11/30/2015</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>73025.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>73025</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>05020000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>CSE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>IIS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Information &amp; Intelligent Systems</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Gregory Chirikjian</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Healthcare workers in the Ebola crisis are at risk for infection due to routine interactions &lt;br/&gt;with patients. These workers wear protective gear to protect them while handling contaminated material. But this gear can be challenging to remove safely. This award envisions that remote-controlled robots could perform common nursing duties inside hazardous clinical areas. If successful, this approach could significantly reduce the frequency with which healthcare workers are exposed to contagions and other biohazards. This project will develop a prototype mobile manipulator robot, a human operator?s console, and operator assistance algorithms to automate or partially-automate tedious and error-prone tasks. Medical professionals will be consulted at the start of the study to establish a prioritized list of clinical tasks for Ebola treatment, and at the end of the study to evaluate the prototype.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The research will explore the tele-nursing concept across the fields of mechanical design, sensors, motion planning and control, human-robot interaction, and robot system integration. Tele-operation of complex tasks, in particular, bimanual manipulation in highly non-engineered environments, is still a major research challenge, while contribution will be made also in algorithms for operator assistance for human-guided manipulation.  The research is directly applicable to other infectious disease scenarios as well.  Improving operator interfaces may also further our knowledge of human-controlled robots in other fields, such as household service, space robots, and material handling in industry and logistics.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>12/02/2014</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>12/02/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.070</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1513221</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Kris</FirstName>
<LastName>Hauser</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Kris Hauser</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>kkhauser@illinois.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5103840564</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000554065</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>12/02/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Duke University</Name>
<CityName>Durham</CityName>
<ZipCode>277054010</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>9196843030</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>2200 W. Main St, Suite 710</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[Erwin Square]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>North Carolina</StateName>
<StateCode>NC</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NC01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>044387793</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>DUKE UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>044387793</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Duke University]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>NC</StateCode>
<ZipCode>277054677</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>North Carolina</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NC04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1640</Code>
<Text>Information Technology Researc</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>8013</Code>
<Text>NRI-National Robotics Initiati</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>001Z</Code>
<Text>Ebola</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1640</Code>
<Text>INFORMATION TECHNOLOGY RESEARC</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7914</Code>
<Text>RAPID</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8013</Code>
<Text>High Risk/Reward Innovative Research</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0115</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2015~73025</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The purpose of this project was to develop a robotic prototype for tele-nursing that may be able to aid nurses and other healthcare workers in providing routine care to highly infectious patients, such as those infected with Ebola, without exposing workers to dangerous pathogens.The goal was to produce a platform for less than $75,000 using a combination of off-the-shelf and custom components.</p> <p>A hardware prototype named TRINA (Tele-Robotic Intelligent Nursing Assistant) was designed and assembled. It allows a nurse to communicate with the patient through video and audio, navigate around obstacles, push carts, manipulate objects with both one or two hands, and hand objects to/from the patient. Experience with the prototype indicates that the operator interface is of primary importance to produce an effectively controllable robot, particularly because of the large numbers of degrees of freedom of the robot (24) are overwhelming to coordinate, and the robot has relatively low dexterity. It is suggested that future research in tele-robotics focus on 1) algorithms for semi-autonomous assistance to reduce the learning curve and tedium of operating the robot, 2) improving the dexterity and precision of mobile manipulators, and 3) robust systems that can operate under real-world nursing conditions (wet, messy, high-stress).</p> <p>The intellectual merit of this project addressed the tele-robotics problem of providing the capacity for operators to perform manipulation tasks with a robot in highly unstructured environments, to study how untrained users perform using such a system, and to study how patients may react to being treated with such a system.&nbsp; A mobile robot with manipulation and telepresence capabilities, along with an operator's workstation, were developed at Duke University over the course of this one year project. Preliminary studies indicate that the use of semi-autonomous functionality improves the performance of the device, and the use of a telepresence screen, so the patient can see and hear the nurse, improves acceptance and intimacy with the operator. The hardware and software platform is expected to continue to be involved in research for years to come.</p> <p>The broader impacts of this work include the involvement of 8 undergraduates in research, support of a female postdoctoral scholar, establishment of new collaborations between Duke Pratt School of Engineering and Duke School of Nursing, and contributions to robotics research infrastructure at Duke.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 02/03/2016<br>      Modified by: Kris&nbsp;Hauser</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Images (<span id="selectedPhoto0">1</span> of <span class="totalNumber"></span>)           </div> <div class="galControls" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2016/1513221/1513221_10344555_1454479853700_ebolabot--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2016/1513221/1513221_10344555_1454479853700_ebolabot--rgov-800width.jpg" title="TRINA platform"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2016/1513221/1513221_10344555_1454479853700_ebolabot--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="TRINA platform"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">The first prototype of the Tele-Robotic Intelligent Nursing Assistant. The robot consists of a two-armed manipulator on an omnidirectional mobile base, two 3-fingered grippers, and several 3D cameras.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Duke University Intelligent Motion Lab</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Kris&nbsp;Hauser</div> <div class="i...]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The purpose of this project was to develop a robotic prototype for tele-nursing that may be able to aid nurses and other healthcare workers in providing routine care to highly infectious patients, such as those infected with Ebola, without exposing workers to dangerous pathogens.The goal was to produce a platform for less than $75,000 using a combination of off-the-shelf and custom components.  A hardware prototype named TRINA (Tele-Robotic Intelligent Nursing Assistant) was designed and assembled. It allows a nurse to communicate with the patient through video and audio, navigate around obstacles, push carts, manipulate objects with both one or two hands, and hand objects to/from the patient. Experience with the prototype indicates that the operator interface is of primary importance to produce an effectively controllable robot, particularly because of the large numbers of degrees of freedom of the robot (24) are overwhelming to coordinate, and the robot has relatively low dexterity. It is suggested that future research in tele-robotics focus on 1) algorithms for semi-autonomous assistance to reduce the learning curve and tedium of operating the robot, 2) improving the dexterity and precision of mobile manipulators, and 3) robust systems that can operate under real-world nursing conditions (wet, messy, high-stress).  The intellectual merit of this project addressed the tele-robotics problem of providing the capacity for operators to perform manipulation tasks with a robot in highly unstructured environments, to study how untrained users perform using such a system, and to study how patients may react to being treated with such a system.  A mobile robot with manipulation and telepresence capabilities, along with an operator's workstation, were developed at Duke University over the course of this one year project. Preliminary studies indicate that the use of semi-autonomous functionality improves the performance of the device, and the use of a telepresence screen, so the patient can see and hear the nurse, improves acceptance and intimacy with the operator. The hardware and software platform is expected to continue to be involved in research for years to come.  The broader impacts of this work include the involvement of 8 undergraduates in research, support of a female postdoctoral scholar, establishment of new collaborations between Duke Pratt School of Engineering and Duke School of Nursing, and contributions to robotics research infrastructure at Duke.       Last Modified: 02/03/2016       Submitted by: Kris Hauser]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
