<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Discovering Words in Speech</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>06/01/2015</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>144000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>144000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>04010000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>SBE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>SMA</Abbreviation>
<LongName>SBE Off Of Multidisciplinary Activities</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Josie S. Welkom</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>jwelkom@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927376</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The Directorate of Social, Behavioral and Economic Sciences offers postdoctoral research fellowships to provide opportunities for recent doctoral graduates to obtain additional training, to gain research experience under the sponsorship of established scientists, and to broaden their scientific horizons beyond their undergraduate and graduate training. Postdoctoral fellowships are further designed to assist new scientists to direct their research efforts across traditional disciplinary lines and to avail themselves of unique research resources, sites, and facilities, including at foreign locations. This postdoctoral fellowship trains a young scientist exploring &lt;br/&gt;the early process of language learning by studying how young infants discover words in spoken language. This project also assesses how language experience affects the word discovery process by studying bilingual-learning infants and adults. By including infants, results from the project further knowledge about how learners acquire linguistic regularities from spoken language and provide insights into the mechanisms underlying early language development, both of which inform efforts to understand language impairments. Additionally, by including bilingual and adult populations, the project highlights how bilingualism changes the process of language acquisition, particularly early on in development. Beyond the scientific contributions, this fellowship also 1) supports the mentorship of undergraduate students from underrepresented backgrounds, 2) engages the local community, including populations typically underrepresented in research, through direct participation in the research and through presentation of the results by the fellow, and 3) supports the fellow?s outreach plan to broaden the participation of students from diverse backgrounds in the sciences. Finally, this fellowship supports the training and development of the fellow, a Mexican-American woman and first generation college graduate that holds a personal commitment to advancing underrepresented populations in STEM.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Acquiring the words of the native language(s) typically begins by discovering them in speech. This process starts in the first year of life and is critical for language development. However, identifying the sounds that compose the words in spoken language is not trivial for the young child. The patterns that define words in natural languages are complex: they consist of multiple features and vary in their degree of reliability. Additionally, spoken words rarely occur in isolation, or with pauses to signal where they start and end. How do infants discover the structure of words given the complexities of spoken language? How does this process change as learners gain experience with language? To address these questions, this research manipulates the complexity of the language input, together with the language experience of the learner, to understand how infants discover words in speech. The studies in this project use an artificial language learning approach to study these questions. Study 1 examines how monolingual English learning infants (8 to 10 months of age) acquire a novel, complex word pattern embedded in fluent speech. Studies 2 and 3 assess how language experience affects learning by testing bilingual-learning infants (Study 2), and adults (Study 3). These studies outline how typically developing infants acquire linguistic patterns from spoken language, which is a necessary endeavor for understanding early language development. This project also informs efforts to understand communication and language disorders, and has the potential to be used in the future as a framework to study children with language and developmental delays.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>04/27/2015</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>04/27/2015</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.075</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1513834</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Jenny</FirstName>
<LastName>Saffran</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>R</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Jenny R Saffran</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>jsaffran@wisc.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6082629942</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000210932</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/27/2015</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Viridiana</FirstName>
<LastName>Benitez</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Viridiana Benitez</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>viridiana.benitez@asu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>4809655425</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000679893</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/27/2015</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Wisconsin-Madison</Name>
<CityName>MADISON</CityName>
<ZipCode>537151218</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6082623822</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>21 North Park Street</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[Suite 6401]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Wisconsin</StateName>
<StateCode>WI</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>WI02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>161202122</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF WISCONSIN SYSTEM</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>041188822</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Wisconsin-Madison]]></Name>
<CityName>Madison</CityName>
<StateCode>WI</StateCode>
<ZipCode>537151218</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[21 N. Park, Suiite 6401]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Wisconsin</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>WI02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>8208</Code>
<Text>SPRF-Broadening Participation</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0115</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2015~144000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>One of the first regularities that young infants must discover in speech is how sounds combine to form words. Discovering words in fluent speech supports learning the vocabulary of the native language, and facilitates language processing across development. Finding the words in speech, however, is no easy feat. One challenge is that learners must extract multiple word patterns from the same speech stream. Young learners must not only find the individual words that compose speech, but they also must be able to acquire the positional restrictions of the sounds that make up those words (the phonotactics of a language). In English, for example, the sounds /fr/ cannot occur at the end of a word but sometimes occur at the beginning of words (frog, afraid). Because phonotactic patterns vary across languages, young children must learn the phonotactics of their native language from the speech that they hear. How do language learners navigate discovering words together with phonotactics? The goal of this study was to understand how language learners navigate acquiring these multiple regularities from speech.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>I studied this question using an artificial language learning methodology. We presented 9-month-old English learning infants with an artificial language that contained two types of patterns, unique individual words, and a novel phonotactic pattern that most of the words followed. Past research has shown that infants at this age can rapidly find the individual words from a brief exposure to an artificial speech stream. I tested if infants can also find the phonotactic pattern of those words. We found that with a brief exposure to the artificial language, 9-month-olds did not show evidence of learning, suggesting that they had difficulty in extracting the novel phonotactic pattern from this brief exposure.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>What might have led to infants&rsquo; difficulty in discovering the patterns in the artificial speech stream? To gain insight into this question, we tested adults and manipulated the time of exposure to the language. We found that these older learners were able to track both the individual words and the phonotactic patterns of those words, but only when they had a longer exposure to the language. With a short exposure to the language, some adults, but not all, showed evidence of only learning the individual words. These findings suggest that listeners need longer exposure times to the speech stream when trying to discover multiple regularities, and that there are individual differences in how learners track multiple patterns. These findings begin to show both the capabilities and the limits of word discovery across development. This work has implications for key issues concerning the development of language, how experience with language matters, and the role of individual differences. &nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>In addition to the research activities, this fellowship also contributed to broadening the participation of underrepresented groups in psychological science. I was able to mentor undergraduate student researchers (including students belonging to groups traditionally underrepresented in science) through all aspects of the research process. Additionally, I engaged young students (middle-schoolers and high-schoolers) from underrepresented backgrounds in science workshops that I developed about the project and psychological science. Finally, the fellowship supported my mentorship and training as a member of an underrepresented group in the sciences. I was able to obtain a tenure-track faculty position at a research-intensive university where I will continue my research, teach and train undergraduate and graduate students in psychology, and make an impact by continuing to support underrepresented populations in the sciences.&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 09/21/2017<br>      Modified by: Viridiana&nbsp;Benitez</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ One of the first regularities that young infants must discover in speech is how sounds combine to form words. Discovering words in fluent speech supports learning the vocabulary of the native language, and facilitates language processing across development. Finding the words in speech, however, is no easy feat. One challenge is that learners must extract multiple word patterns from the same speech stream. Young learners must not only find the individual words that compose speech, but they also must be able to acquire the positional restrictions of the sounds that make up those words (the phonotactics of a language). In English, for example, the sounds /fr/ cannot occur at the end of a word but sometimes occur at the beginning of words (frog, afraid). Because phonotactic patterns vary across languages, young children must learn the phonotactics of their native language from the speech that they hear. How do language learners navigate discovering words together with phonotactics? The goal of this study was to understand how language learners navigate acquiring these multiple regularities from speech.     I studied this question using an artificial language learning methodology. We presented 9-month-old English learning infants with an artificial language that contained two types of patterns, unique individual words, and a novel phonotactic pattern that most of the words followed. Past research has shown that infants at this age can rapidly find the individual words from a brief exposure to an artificial speech stream. I tested if infants can also find the phonotactic pattern of those words. We found that with a brief exposure to the artificial language, 9-month-olds did not show evidence of learning, suggesting that they had difficulty in extracting the novel phonotactic pattern from this brief exposure.     What might have led to infants? difficulty in discovering the patterns in the artificial speech stream? To gain insight into this question, we tested adults and manipulated the time of exposure to the language. We found that these older learners were able to track both the individual words and the phonotactic patterns of those words, but only when they had a longer exposure to the language. With a short exposure to the language, some adults, but not all, showed evidence of only learning the individual words. These findings suggest that listeners need longer exposure times to the speech stream when trying to discover multiple regularities, and that there are individual differences in how learners track multiple patterns. These findings begin to show both the capabilities and the limits of word discovery across development. This work has implications for key issues concerning the development of language, how experience with language matters, and the role of individual differences.       In addition to the research activities, this fellowship also contributed to broadening the participation of underrepresented groups in psychological science. I was able to mentor undergraduate student researchers (including students belonging to groups traditionally underrepresented in science) through all aspects of the research process. Additionally, I engaged young students (middle-schoolers and high-schoolers) from underrepresented backgrounds in science workshops that I developed about the project and psychological science. Finally, the fellowship supported my mentorship and training as a member of an underrepresented group in the sciences. I was able to obtain a tenure-track faculty position at a research-intensive university where I will continue my research, teach and train undergraduate and graduate students in psychology, and make an impact by continuing to support underrepresented populations in the sciences.           Last Modified: 09/21/2017       Submitted by: Viridiana Benitez]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
