<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>The STEM Ambassador Program: A Scientist-Driven Public Engagement Model</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>01/01/2016</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>1255814.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>1358146</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>11090000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>EHR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DRL</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Research On Learning</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Ellen McCallie</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>emccalli@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032925115</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This project's interdisciplinary team will carry out research and training that will identify ways for professionals in science, technology, engineering, and mathematics (STEM) to engage with public audiences that currently lack the community connections, resources, time, or know-how to gain access to science education and to scientists.  The project will create real and on-line materials for scientists to convey the excitement, content, and relevance of their own research to public groups whose values, professions, or aesthetic and cultural backgrounds are connected to that research topic.  The project will also foster ways for scientists to understand that members of the public can provide valuable input to science.  Research and evaluation on the development of this innovative public engagement model "the STEM Ambassador Program (STEMAP)" will be conducted to provide insights into the effectiveness and extensibility of the STEMAP model.  This approach integrates three existing elements of science engagement that have previously not been linked: design thinking, informal science education communication skills from museum work, and connecting scientists' research with the existing values of particular community groups.  Robust evaluation will enhance effectiveness of in-person and online trainings; research will provide understanding of how different science learning models can be integrated and enhanced for public audiences and for scientists.  This project is funded by the Advancing Informal STEM Learning (AISL) program, which seeks to advance new approaches to, and evidence-based understanding of, the design and development of STEM learning in informal environments.  This includes providing multiple pathways for broadening access to and engagement in STEM learning experiences, advancing innovative research on and assessment of STEM learning in informal environments, and developing understandings of deeper learning by participants.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Science and society need innovative and transformative ways to interact synergistically. Given the deep knowledge and contagious passion for their research, STEM professionals can bring unique assets to directly engage public audiences, especially important the traditionally underserved public groups.  Members of the public in turn have the potential to provide novel ideas, data, and insights to support researchers.  The project's exploratory research will help understand how STEM professionals can broaden participation by themselves engaging unengaged publics with the excitement of science and science knowledge in ways that are congruent with academic rewards. The project team will integrate three existing NSF-funded models: a) Research Ambassador Program, b) Portal to the Public, and c) Design Thinking.  A cadre of faculty and graduate students will be trained in "STEM Ambassadors" workshops, in which social scientists and community group representatives will help STEM Ambassadors identify public groups with interests that connect to the scientist's research.  Engagement events will occur in community venues, e.g., churches, factories, and day care centers, etc.  Case studies and evaluation instruments answer research questions about: the role of empathy in the formation and change of identity; relationships between public audiences, mode of engagement, and identity shifts; and motivational drivers for STEM Ambassadors and public audiences. The intellectual merit is the training and evaluating of 50 STEM Ambassadors (via 100 outreach events involving approximately 5000 individuals from community groups); strategies that encourage STEM professionals to engage with underrepresented publics; and insights on how to integrate multiple education models.  STEMAP will disseminate its findings and new resources through the STEMAP website.  In addition, the dissemination efforts will be extended through: collaboration with the NSF-funded PoPNet Expansion Project and the Centers for Science and Mathematics Education (CSMEs); presentations at national science professional organizations, such as the AAAS, as well as through the CAISE Wiki and the National Alliance for Broader Impacts (NABI).  STEMAP will create a process for other NSF PIs to generate, evaluate, and articulate their research and its applications to public groups that lie far outside academia.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>09/01/2015</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/15/2018</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.076</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1514494</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Shelley</FirstName>
<LastName>Goldman</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>V</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Shelley V Goldman</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>sgoldman@stanford.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6507238422</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000200802</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/01/2015</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Rebecca</FirstName>
<LastName>Menlove</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>T</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Rebecca T Menlove</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>bmenlove@umnh.utah.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>8015851073</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000424663</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/01/2015</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Nalini</FirstName>
<LastName>Nadkarni</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Nalini Nadkarni</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>nalini.nadkarni@utah.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>8015816903</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000595877</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/01/2015</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Utah</Name>
<CityName>SALT LAKE CITY</CityName>
<ZipCode>841128930</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>8015816903</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>75 S 2000 E</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[Second Floor]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Utah</StateName>
<StateCode>UT</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>UT02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>009095365</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF UTAH, THE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>009095365</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Utah]]></Name>
<CityName>Salt Lake City</CityName>
<StateCode>UT</StateCode>
<ZipCode>841128930</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[75 South 2000 East]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Utah</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>UT02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7259</Code>
<Text>AISL</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7259</Code>
<Text>INFORMAL SCIENCE EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0415</Code>
<Name>NSF Education &amp; Human Resource</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040106</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0418</Code>
<Name>NSF Education &amp; Human Resource</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040106</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2015~1255814</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2018~102332</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Although schools, science centers, and other traditional learning venues play an important role in science communication, not all members of the public can or do engage with science through traditional outlets. We created the STEM Ambassador Program (STEMAP) in 2016 to guide scientists to leverage their research, personal interests, and experiences to engage community members in discussions about science in the venues where they live, work, recreate, and worship.</p> <p>STEMAP is based on three existing education and design models. Training was piloted with three cohorts of faculty, graduate students, research staff, and postdocs from STEM (science, technology, engineering, math) departments at the University of Utah (UU) from 2016-2018 (46 scientists total). The program is a semester long (ca. 4 months) training consisting of 5 modules:</p> <p>Module 1, Connect: Individual scientists participate in interviews where he/she distills his/her research, personal interests, experiences, and desired social impact to generate an ?impact identity?. They brainstorm communities to engage that resonate with an impact identity (referred to hereafter as ?focal groups?).</p> <p>Module 2, Immerse: Scientists participate in a workshop where they prepare to build relationships in and learn about the focal group. Scientists independently conduct an ?immersion visit? where they visit the focal group?s venue to learn about the group?s shared norms, interests, and experiences.</p> <p>Module 3, Design: Scientists participate in a workshop where they draw on their immersion notes to design an engagement activity specific to the focal group. Scientists draft an engagement proposal and share it with the group for input.</p> <p>Module 4, Engage: Scientists participate in a workshop to build communication skills to implement the engagement activity. They carry out the activity in the focal group venue.&nbsp;</p> <p>Module 5, Reflect: Scientists review participant feedback and/or observational notes from the engagement activity and reflect on outcomes.&nbsp;</p> <p>UU scientists engaged in 44 venues, reaching an estimated 2,260 people. Engagement activities included:</p> <p>-a microbiologist who enjoys fermentation cooking collaborated with a chef to describe the microbes that ferment foods during a cooking class at a grocery store;</p> <p>-an urban planner studying water conservation engaged inmates in a horticulture job training program in discussions about waterwise landscaping practices;</p> <p>-a wildlife biologist collaborated with youth in a secure care facility on a science project identifying wildlife images taken by motion sensor cameras;</p> <p>-a geologist who enjoys rock-climbing engaged participants on a climbing trip in discussions about the geology of the climbing wall; and</p> <p>-an air quality researcher engaged Spanish and English-speaking families at an affordable daycare in hands-on activities and discussions about air pollution.&nbsp;&nbsp;</p> <p>The research and evaluation team conducted surveys and interviews with participating scientists, and analyzed a subset with a case studies approach. Focal group feedback was collected via surveys where possible. Nearly all scientists indicated on post-program surveys that the program was of value to them. The majority cited that the training improved their communication skills and led them to develop an interest in engaging new audiences.&nbsp; Scientists were successful in reaching members of the public who did not have many opportunities to engage with scientists. Although nearly all focal group members indicated an interest in science, just over half had opportunities to engage with scientists. Focal group participants felt the scientists did a good job communicating and wanted to learn more about their work.</p> <p>STEMAP was approached by and informally assisted seven principal investigators (PIs) for support in fulfilling NSF Broader Impact (BI) requirements for other grant proposals, and for trainings.</p> <p>&nbsp;After refining the program at UU, the team explored two pathways to offer STEMAP to other institutions.&nbsp; An online training was piloted with six scientists across the country and an online format with occasional in-person support was tested with four scientists at the University of Washington.</p> <p>This work revealed that scientists: 1) are willing to engage in non-traditional venues; and 2) can be supported in carrying out engagement activities in a range of settings through training that emphasizes relationship-building, learning about the focal group, and designing activities based on the group?s shared norms, interests, and experiences.</p> <p>STEMAP engagement outcomes were disseminated via the STEMAP website (<a href="http://www.stemap.org">www.stemap.org</a>), newsletter, social media (@stemapteam), a peer reviewed publication, and &nbsp;80 presentations at regional and national conferences and meetings. Finalized training materials were compiled into an implementation manual to guide others in carrying out the training.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 03/27/2020<br>      Modified by: Nalini&nbsp;Nadkarni</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Although schools, science centers, and other traditional learning venues play an important role in science communication, not all members of the public can or do engage with science through traditional outlets. We created the STEM Ambassador Program (STEMAP) in 2016 to guide scientists to leverage their research, personal interests, and experiences to engage community members in discussions about science in the venues where they live, work, recreate, and worship.  STEMAP is based on three existing education and design models. Training was piloted with three cohorts of faculty, graduate students, research staff, and postdocs from STEM (science, technology, engineering, math) departments at the University of Utah (UU) from 2016-2018 (46 scientists total). The program is a semester long (ca. 4 months) training consisting of 5 modules:  Module 1, Connect: Individual scientists participate in interviews where he/she distills his/her research, personal interests, experiences, and desired social impact to generate an ?impact identity?. They brainstorm communities to engage that resonate with an impact identity (referred to hereafter as ?focal groups?).  Module 2, Immerse: Scientists participate in a workshop where they prepare to build relationships in and learn about the focal group. Scientists independently conduct an ?immersion visit? where they visit the focal group?s venue to learn about the group?s shared norms, interests, and experiences.  Module 3, Design: Scientists participate in a workshop where they draw on their immersion notes to design an engagement activity specific to the focal group. Scientists draft an engagement proposal and share it with the group for input.  Module 4, Engage: Scientists participate in a workshop to build communication skills to implement the engagement activity. They carry out the activity in the focal group venue.   Module 5, Reflect: Scientists review participant feedback and/or observational notes from the engagement activity and reflect on outcomes.   UU scientists engaged in 44 venues, reaching an estimated 2,260 people. Engagement activities included:  -a microbiologist who enjoys fermentation cooking collaborated with a chef to describe the microbes that ferment foods during a cooking class at a grocery store;  -an urban planner studying water conservation engaged inmates in a horticulture job training program in discussions about waterwise landscaping practices;  -a wildlife biologist collaborated with youth in a secure care facility on a science project identifying wildlife images taken by motion sensor cameras;  -a geologist who enjoys rock-climbing engaged participants on a climbing trip in discussions about the geology of the climbing wall; and  -an air quality researcher engaged Spanish and English-speaking families at an affordable daycare in hands-on activities and discussions about air pollution.    The research and evaluation team conducted surveys and interviews with participating scientists, and analyzed a subset with a case studies approach. Focal group feedback was collected via surveys where possible. Nearly all scientists indicated on post-program surveys that the program was of value to them. The majority cited that the training improved their communication skills and led them to develop an interest in engaging new audiences.  Scientists were successful in reaching members of the public who did not have many opportunities to engage with scientists. Although nearly all focal group members indicated an interest in science, just over half had opportunities to engage with scientists. Focal group participants felt the scientists did a good job communicating and wanted to learn more about their work.  STEMAP was approached by and informally assisted seven principal investigators (PIs) for support in fulfilling NSF Broader Impact (BI) requirements for other grant proposals, and for trainings.   After refining the program at UU, the team explored two pathways to offer STEMAP to other institutions.  An online training was piloted with six scientists across the country and an online format with occasional in-person support was tested with four scientists at the University of Washington.  This work revealed that scientists: 1) are willing to engage in non-traditional venues; and 2) can be supported in carrying out engagement activities in a range of settings through training that emphasizes relationship-building, learning about the focal group, and designing activities based on the group?s shared norms, interests, and experiences.  STEMAP engagement outcomes were disseminated via the STEMAP website (www.stemap.org), newsletter, social media (@stemapteam), a peer reviewed publication, and  80 presentations at regional and national conferences and meetings. Finalized training materials were compiled into an implementation manual to guide others in carrying out the training.          Last Modified: 03/27/2020       Submitted by: Nalini Nadkarni]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
