<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>EAPSI: Exploring Nano-scale Thermal Transport in Semiconductor Thin Films for the Advancement of Modern Electronic Devices</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>06/01/2015</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2016</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>5070.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>5070</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Fellowship Award</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>01090000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>O/D</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Office Of The Director</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>OISE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Office Of Internatl Science &amp;Engineering</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Anne Emig</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>aemig@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927241</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Controlling heat dissipation in electronics is vital for a variety of technological applications. The recent growth of manufacturing and utilization of nano-scale electronics has led to the ever-increasing need to achieve smaller and denser circuits; thus serious thermal management issues have become the focus of current semiconductor material research. One such problem is that the interface between two semiconductor materials acts as a barrier to thermal transport, therefore dramatically decreasing thermal conductivity.  This project seeks to understand and ultimately control thermal transport at the nanometer scale by investigating heat transport between semiconductor interfaces. The dependence of thermal transport on thin-film thickness and interface roughness will also be examined. The EAPSI fellow will perform the experiment and data analysis in collaboration with Dr. Xuan Wang; an expert in the measurement technique of ultra-fast electron diffraction, at the Institute of Physics, Chinese Academy of Sciences in Beijing and at Jiao Tong University in Shanghai, China. The findings of this project may offer new insight into the processes of nano-scale thermal transport and aid in the development of future nano-devices.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project will utilize the experimental technique of Femtosecond Electron Diffraction (FED) to monitor the nano-film temperature evolution after ultrafast heating in real time for various nano-film thicknesses. The thermal boundary conductance and the effect of phonon confinement on thermal transport will be measured. FED directly records both thermal and coherent lattice dynamics in real time, thus gaining a more coherent picture of nano-scale transport dynamics compared to ultrafast optical measurements. An in-depth understanding of nano-scale thermal transport gained in this project will help to improve thermal management and enhance the speed and function of future nano-devices. This project will continue to develop FED in China and give rise to future research collaboration for the newly proposed Synergetic Extreme Condition User Facility in China, pushing FED to a world-class level. This NSF EAPSI award is funded in collaboration with the Chinese Ministry of Science and Technology.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/18/2015</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/18/2015</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.079</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1514658</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Matthew</FirstName>
<LastName>Gorfien</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>C</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Matthew C Gorfien</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress/>
<PI_PHON>7164807447</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000685320</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/18/2015</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Gorfien                 Matthew        C</Name>
<CityName>Tallahassee</CityName>
<ZipCode>323103706</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber/>
<StreetAddress/>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Florida</StateName>
<StateCode>FL</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>FL05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM/>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME/>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Gorfien                 Matthew        C]]></Name>
<CityName>Tallahassee</CityName>
<StateCode>FL</StateCode>
<ZipCode>323103706</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Florida</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>FL05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7316</Code>
<Text>EAPSI</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>5978</Code>
<Text>EAST ASIA AND PACIFIC PROGRAM</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7316</Code>
<Text>EAPSI</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9200</Code>
<Text>US CHINA COOP IN BASIC SCIENCE</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0115</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2015~5070</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>During the National Science Foundation&rsquo;s East Asia Pacific Summer Institute in China, I studied how heat is transported through material interfaces at the nano-scale size. The transportation of heat in electronics continues to be a major concern as circuits become smaller, denser, and operate at higher frequencies. &nbsp;As the size of electronic components approach the nanometer scale, there is a reduction in the thermal conductivity in semiconductor materials that are widely used in application of future electronics.&nbsp; The ability to measure and manipulate the thermal transport in nano-scale electronics will greatly increase our understanding, thus improving thermal management and enhancing the speed and function capabilities.</p> <p>I worked with Dr. Xuan Wang at the Institute of Physics, Chinese Academy of Sciences in Beijing, China to carry out Ultrafast Electron Diffraction (UED) experiments on semiconductor nano-films. UED is the ideal experimental technique for studying extremely short dynamical processes involving temperature changes inside nano-scale materials. This allows for the direct measurement of the transport of heat through nano-scale semiconductors by recording the temperature evolution of the material during ultrafast laser heating in real time.&nbsp; A widely used semiconductor Gallium Arsenide (GaAs) can be deposited in the form of a ten nanometer (nm) thick film on top of a much thicker Aluminum Gallium Arsenide substrate, providing a model system to study how the heat is transported though semiconductor material interfaces between the two materials. Using UED, the structure and temperature of the GaAs sample was measured by taking diffraction pattern images of the atomic planes in the sample during laser induced heating.&nbsp;</p> <p>The two month duration of this program was an excellent opportunity to work on the complicated experimental setup of UED and take some preliminary data required as a step in achieving a comprehensive understanding of nanoscale thermal transport.&nbsp; A great deal of knowledge was gained from working through the technical struggles of implementing a cutting edge experiment such as UED. The preliminary studies performed lead the way for future planned studies to improve the experimental capabilities and both this data and future data will be used during my doctoral dissertation research. &nbsp;As part of the data analysis, a computer program was also written to process each diffraction image in order to extract information about the diffraction streaks shown in the above figure. The preliminary results were presented during the defense of my prospectus of my dissertation research. The international collaboration formed during this program has continued to develop even beyond the scope of the project and the mutual sharing of culture and experiences has helped shape future scientific work conducted between research groups.&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 03/01/2016<br>      Modified by: Matthew&nbsp;C&nbsp;Gorfien</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Images (<span id="selectedPhoto0">1</span> of <span class="totalNumber"></span>)           </div> <div class="galControls" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2016/1514658/1514658_10370768_1456865797892_diffractionpattern--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2016/1514658/1514658_10370768_1456865797892_diffractionpattern--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Electron Diffraction Pattern"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2016/1514658/1514658_10370768_1456865797892_diffractionpattern--rgov...]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ During the National Science FoundationÆs East Asia Pacific Summer Institute in China, I studied how heat is transported through material interfaces at the nano-scale size. The transportation of heat in electronics continues to be a major concern as circuits become smaller, denser, and operate at higher frequencies.  As the size of electronic components approach the nanometer scale, there is a reduction in the thermal conductivity in semiconductor materials that are widely used in application of future electronics.  The ability to measure and manipulate the thermal transport in nano-scale electronics will greatly increase our understanding, thus improving thermal management and enhancing the speed and function capabilities.  I worked with Dr. Xuan Wang at the Institute of Physics, Chinese Academy of Sciences in Beijing, China to carry out Ultrafast Electron Diffraction (UED) experiments on semiconductor nano-films. UED is the ideal experimental technique for studying extremely short dynamical processes involving temperature changes inside nano-scale materials. This allows for the direct measurement of the transport of heat through nano-scale semiconductors by recording the temperature evolution of the material during ultrafast laser heating in real time.  A widely used semiconductor Gallium Arsenide (GaAs) can be deposited in the form of a ten nanometer (nm) thick film on top of a much thicker Aluminum Gallium Arsenide substrate, providing a model system to study how the heat is transported though semiconductor material interfaces between the two materials. Using UED, the structure and temperature of the GaAs sample was measured by taking diffraction pattern images of the atomic planes in the sample during laser induced heating.   The two month duration of this program was an excellent opportunity to work on the complicated experimental setup of UED and take some preliminary data required as a step in achieving a comprehensive understanding of nanoscale thermal transport.  A great deal of knowledge was gained from working through the technical struggles of implementing a cutting edge experiment such as UED. The preliminary studies performed lead the way for future planned studies to improve the experimental capabilities and both this data and future data will be used during my doctoral dissertation research.  As part of the data analysis, a computer program was also written to process each diffraction image in order to extract information about the diffraction streaks shown in the above figure. The preliminary results were presented during the defense of my prospectus of my dissertation research. The international collaboration formed during this program has continued to develop even beyond the scope of the project and the mutual sharing of culture and experiences has helped shape future scientific work conducted between research groups.           Last Modified: 03/01/2016       Submitted by: Matthew C Gorfien]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
