<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>EAPSI: Organization and Flow of Components Involved in Growth and Disease Development in Fungi</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>06/01/2015</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2016</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>70.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>70</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Fellowship Award</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>01090000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>O/D</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Office Of The Director</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>OISE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Office Of Internatl Science &amp;Engineering</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Anne Emig</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>aemig@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927241</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Fungi are the most economically important pathogens of crops. In particular, the rice blast disease results in losses of nearly $5 billion each year worldwide. China is the epicenter of this disease, and is investing many resources to combat it. The fungus that causes this disease penetrates and colonizes rice in a precise way that is not quite understood. This project will use high resolution microscopy to examine how proteins and other molecules are dynamically organized in growing fungal cells as well as in the infection structures of the rice blast pathogen, which will provide insight into future treatments of all fungal infections. It will be carried out in the laboratory of Dr. Zonghua Wang at the Fuzhou Agricultural &amp; Forestry University in Fuzhou, Fujian, China, and will assist in developing a permanent collaboration between the host and the proposer?s institutions based on shared research goals.  &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Fungi, including pathogens of plants and animals, generally colonize through the production of threadlike cells that grow at their tips, and are excellent models of cell growth. In recent years, genetic and live-cell microscopy techniques have converged to allow careful measurements of the movement of subcellular components. This project will bridge basic cell biology and molecular plant pathology to view the flow of proteins and lipids in fungal cells. Specifically, it is known that at least two separate secretory pathways exist that support fungal growth and pathogenicity, and to examine the differential dynamics of these pathways, photobleaching experiments will be performed on representative proteins from each route. Additionally, a specific lipid known to be involved in growth and development of fungi will be tracked, using a fluorescent marker, in infection structures of the rice blast pathogen Magnaporthe oryzae, to further previous research indicating that the distribution of this lipid may be crucial for the infection process of this organism. This NSF EAPSI award supports the research of a U.S. graduate student and is funded in collaboration with the Chinese Ministry of Science and Technology.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/18/2015</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/18/2015</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.079</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1514656</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Zachary</FirstName>
<LastName>Schultzhaus</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Zachary Schultzhaus</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress/>
<PI_PHON>7122536416</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000678238</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/18/2015</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>schultzhaus             Zachary</Name>
<CityName>College Station</CityName>
<ZipCode>778457315</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber/>
<StreetAddress/>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Texas</StateName>
<StateCode>TX</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>17</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>TX17</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM/>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME/>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[schultzhaus             Zachary]]></Name>
<CityName>College Station</CityName>
<StateCode>TX</StateCode>
<ZipCode>778457315</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Texas</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>17</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>TX17</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7316</Code>
<Text>EAPSI</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>5978</Code>
<Text>EAST ASIA AND PACIFIC PROGRAM</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7316</Code>
<Text>EAPSI</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9200</Code>
<Text>US CHINA COOP IN BASIC SCIENCE</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0115</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2015~70</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><span style="white-space: pre;"> </span>This project made use of fungi to study basic cell processes using a variety of imaging techniques, and also included work with a pathogen that causes a devastating plant disease in China, which was appropriate given that the host is a plant pathologist. The goals of this project were twofold. First, we wished to use the advanced microscopy capabilities of the host laboratory to examine proteins that are involved in the reorganization of shape and size of fungal and animal cells. Specifically, we wanted to see how quickly these proteins were "used" and "replaced" at sites of high activity, such as the region of the cell where growth was occurring. Over the duration of the award, we accomplished this through the use of a technique wherein proteins of interest were fluorescently labeled and viewed in the cells under a microscope, a subset was "bleached" using a laser (i.e. its fluorescent label "turned off"), and the speed of recovery of fluorescence (i.e. "new" protein) was measured. In all, we did similar experiments with eight proteins that perform a variety of functions in growing fungal cells. The subsequent analysis of this data is complete, and a future publication of it will provide information on how fungi orchestrate the complex process of cell growth.</p> <p><span style="white-space: pre;"> </span>Second, we wanted to begin exploring how a specific molecule, in this case a lipid, could assist a fungus as it invades a plant host. To do this, we labeled this lipid, in a similar manner to the proteins in the first goal, and viewed its distribution in living cells of the rice blast pathogen Magnaporthe oryzae. The host laboratory are worldwide experts in the biology of this pathogen, and several workers from this group assisted in these experiments, which showed that the distribution of this lipid is the same in this organism as it is in several other fungi, concentrating at sites of growth. Experiments that we are currently running will hopefully provide information on how this lipid is used in the process of plant cell invasion, which is a crucial component of the disease cycle for this pathogen.</p> <p><span style="white-space: pre;"> </span>The award has had the broader impact of strengthening the relationship between the home and the host laboratories, and several students from the host laboratory have visited the home laboratory as visiting scholars since the award period. The results from this project will also be presented at several conferences in 2016 and beyond.&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 03/13/2016<br>      Modified by: Zachary&nbsp;Schultzhaus</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[  This project made use of fungi to study basic cell processes using a variety of imaging techniques, and also included work with a pathogen that causes a devastating plant disease in China, which was appropriate given that the host is a plant pathologist. The goals of this project were twofold. First, we wished to use the advanced microscopy capabilities of the host laboratory to examine proteins that are involved in the reorganization of shape and size of fungal and animal cells. Specifically, we wanted to see how quickly these proteins were "used" and "replaced" at sites of high activity, such as the region of the cell where growth was occurring. Over the duration of the award, we accomplished this through the use of a technique wherein proteins of interest were fluorescently labeled and viewed in the cells under a microscope, a subset was "bleached" using a laser (i.e. its fluorescent label "turned off"), and the speed of recovery of fluorescence (i.e. "new" protein) was measured. In all, we did similar experiments with eight proteins that perform a variety of functions in growing fungal cells. The subsequent analysis of this data is complete, and a future publication of it will provide information on how fungi orchestrate the complex process of cell growth.   Second, we wanted to begin exploring how a specific molecule, in this case a lipid, could assist a fungus as it invades a plant host. To do this, we labeled this lipid, in a similar manner to the proteins in the first goal, and viewed its distribution in living cells of the rice blast pathogen Magnaporthe oryzae. The host laboratory are worldwide experts in the biology of this pathogen, and several workers from this group assisted in these experiments, which showed that the distribution of this lipid is the same in this organism as it is in several other fungi, concentrating at sites of growth. Experiments that we are currently running will hopefully provide information on how this lipid is used in the process of plant cell invasion, which is a crucial component of the disease cycle for this pathogen.   The award has had the broader impact of strengthening the relationship between the home and the host laboratories, and several students from the host laboratory have visited the home laboratory as visiting scholars since the award period. The results from this project will also be presented at several conferences in 2016 and beyond.        Last Modified: 03/13/2016       Submitted by: Zachary Schultzhaus]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
