<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Antecedents and Consequences of Cross-Race Friendships in Early and Middle Childhood</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2015</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>201965.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>201965</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>04010000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>SBE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>SMA</Abbreviation>
<LongName>SBE Off Of Multidisciplinary Activities</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Josie S. Welkom</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>jwelkom@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927376</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The Directorate of Social, Behavioral and Economic Sciences offers postdoctoral research fellowships to provide opportunities for recent doctoral graduates to obtain additional training, to gain research experience under the sponsorship of established scientists, and to broaden their scientific horizons beyond their undergraduate and graduate training. Postdoctoral fellowships are further designed to assist new scientists to direct their research efforts across traditional disciplinary lines and to avail themselves of unique research resources, sites, and facilities, including at foreign locations. This postdoctoral fellowship (under the "Broadening Participation" track of the SBE postdoctoral fellowships program) trains a young scientist exploring the effects of cross-race friendships in early and middle childhood. Despite its history of civil right progress, the U.S. continues to be plagued by racial inequalities, racial discrimination, and racial tensions. Finding solutions to these problems is critical to the country's social and economic wellbeing and will require cross-race cooperation based on trust, respect, and goodwill. Fostering cross-race friendships among youth is likely to facilitate cooperative work toward racial equality and justice.  Past research has shown that cross-race friendships reduce negative racial attitudes. More positive racial attitudes and interracial interactions may, in turn, reduce the future prevalence of discrimination, which is linked to negative physical and mental health outcomes. Studying ways to encourage the frequency and quality of cross-race friendships in childhood may provide educators, parents, and policy-makers with effective methods of encouraging positive racial attitudes and openness to cross-race friendships at a point in development during which such attitudes are flexible. Given that the prevalence of cross-race friendships decreases across childhood (Aboud, Mendelson, &amp; Purdy, 2003), the proposed work aims to understand the formation and function of cross-race friendships in early and middle childhood among youth from diverse racial backgrounds.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The specific aims of the two proposed studies are to: (1) understand the ways in which parents' and children's attitudes and behaviors predict children's willingness to initiate cross-race interaction and the nature of such interactions, (2) identify qualities of cross-race interactions that promote cross-race friendships, and (3) explore whether cross-race friendships uniquely and causally predict improvement in racial attitudes over and above other types of cross-race contact. The first study explores whether children's endorsement of racial stereotypes and their beliefs regarding whether individuals of different racial groups are different in underlying structural and fundamental ways (i.e., racial essentialism) relate to their willingness to adopt, and their treatment of, cross-race versus same-race pen pals. This study also examines whether parental characteristics, including their valuing of diversity, the messages that they send their children about race, and the racial diversity of their neighborhoods and social networks predict children's pen pal selection and behavior. The second study extends the first by using an experimental methodology to examine the causal effects of children?s cross-race interactions and friendships on their racial attitudes (i.e., stereotypes and essentialist views). Same and cross-race dyads are brought into a lab setting and randomly assigned to interact under conditions of: (1) mere contact, (2) academic cooperation, and (3) friendship induction. This study examines whether these contextual manipulations lead to friendship formation, and in turn, a reduction in racial stereotyping and racially essentialist attitudes. These studies extend the current understanding of the nature and benefits of cross-race friendships in childhood in three ways. First, study 1 examines the antecedents of children's willingness to befriend and behave positively toward cross-race individuals rather than focusing on how cross-race friendships predict attitudes, as has been the focus of much previous work. Second, instead of relying solely on correlational associations, study 2 explores the causal links between cross-race friendships and racial attitudes. Finally, both studies extend previous work by exploring the formation and benefits of cross-race friendships among a diverse population, including African American, Latino, and White children.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>05/08/2015</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/24/2015</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.075</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1514233</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Rebecca</FirstName>
<LastName>Bigler</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>S</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Rebecca S Bigler</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>Bigler@psy.utexas.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5124719917</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000384045</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/08/2015</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Amber</FirstName>
<LastName>Williams</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Amber Williams</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>amber6113@gmail.com</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2818043424</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000683389</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/08/2015</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Texas at Austin</Name>
<CityName>Austin</CityName>
<ZipCode>787595316</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5124716424</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>3925 W Braker Lane, Ste 3.340</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Texas</StateName>
<StateCode>TX</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>10</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>TX10</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>170230239</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF TEXAS AT AUSTIN</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>042000273</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Texas at Austin]]></Name>
<CityName>Austin</CityName>
<StateCode>TX</StateCode>
<ZipCode>787121532</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[101 E. 27th Street, Suite 5.300]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Texas</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>25</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>TX25</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>8208</Code>
<Text>SPRF-Broadening Participation</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>8209</Code>
<Text>SPRF-IBSS</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0115</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2015~201965</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Over the course of this award, my sponsor and I aimed to understand the factors that predict children's willingness to befriend individuals of a different racial background. Additionally, we hoped to recruit and provide research and professional development opportunities for underrepresented students. Fortunately, we were able to achieve these goals and have begun the process of disseminating our findings to research and lay communities.&nbsp;</p> <p>First, in terms of project data collection and intellectual merit, we interviewed each child participant approximately three times. In the first session, we asked them to choose four photos of children (out of 24 photos including 8 Latinx, 8 Black, and 8 White children) with whom they would like to be pen pals. They were told that we, the researchers, wanted them to participate in our pen pal program in order to better understand how children make friends. In the next two sessions, children were asked about their race-related beliefs and attitudes, including the racial composition of their closest friends, their affective feelings toward different racial groups, and their beliefs about the challenges and benefits of having friends of a different racial background. We also recruited children&rsquo;s parents and were able to get approximately 40 child participants&rsquo; parents to take part in our study. Thus, we have roughly 40 parent-child dyads in our dataset. Additionally, we had roughly 60 additional parents complete a survey exploring their own and their children&rsquo;s race-related beliefs and experiences. Thus approximately 200 individuals participated in our study overall.</p> <p>Preliminary results show that, on average, children chose more than two individuals of a different race and more than one individual of the same race as potential pen pals. Additionally, children chose on average about 1 Black pen pal, 1 Latino pen pal, and 1.5 White pen pals.&nbsp;In regression analyses, we found that children who felt more positively toward Black people as a group - so they attributed more positive characteristics to Black people - chose more Black children as potential pen pals. Finally, we found a significant correlation such that parents whose children had seen them kiss a Black person had kids who were happier to be in close proximity to a Black person.&nbsp;These results are preliminary; however, they indicate important information regarding how to promote cross-race friendships in childhood. Namely improving children&rsquo;s racial attitudes and parents acting as role models may be particularly important for encouraging cross-race friendships in childhood.&nbsp;</p> <p>Secondly, in terms of dissemination of research, I have co-authored a number of recently accepted publications on topics focusing on race and its impact on children and adolescents. Over the course of the award, I have had 4 papers accepted into peer-reviewed academic journals. These papers were published in journals including Child Development, Journal of Marriage and Family, and the Journal of Black Psychology. In addition, I presented academic work at 4 conferences over the course of the award. These conferences include the Society for Research in Child Development and the Cognitive Development Society. Additionally, my sponsor Dr. Rebecca Bigler presented our work from this project at the Society for the Study of Human Development. Finally, I presented the preliminary project results to parents outside the research community in a presentation in which I discussed effective ways to encourage children to engage in cross-race friendships.</p> <p>In terms of broader impacts, we were able to provide professional development and research opportunities to students, many of whom are underrepresented in the academy. Roughly 10 students, many of whom were Spanish-English bilingual, Latinx students, participated in the project as research assistants (RAs). Many of our students were Latinx due to the population demographics of our participants, most of whom were also Latinx and many of whom were more comfortable speaking Spanish than English. Additionally, we had White, Asian, and African American students participate as RAs. These students were trained to recruit parents, to interview children, and to enter data into SPSS (the statistics software most commonly used in psychology). We also provided professional development opportunities. I wrote recommendation letters for a student who wanted to participate in a summer internship, and she was able to intern at her first choice. Likewise, I provided a presentation to underrepresented students participating in a summer research program at UT Austin, in which I discussed career opportunities in academia post-graduate school/Ph.D.</p> <p>Thus, we feel confident that the project reached the goals we aimed to achieve. We will continue to disseminate the results gleaned from the project. This will include submitting empirical articles to peer-reviewed journals, and providing aggregate results to each of the organizations that allowed us to recruit in their schools. As appropriate, we will also discuss our findings with broader media outlets. We thank the National Science Foundation for the opportunity to conduct research so important to promoting a more equitable and just future.&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 10/29/2017<br>      Modified by: Amber&nbsp;Williams</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Over the course of this award, my sponsor and I aimed to understand the factors that predict children's willingness to befriend individuals of a different racial background. Additionally, we hoped to recruit and provide research and professional development opportunities for underrepresented students. Fortunately, we were able to achieve these goals and have begun the process of disseminating our findings to research and lay communities.   First, in terms of project data collection and intellectual merit, we interviewed each child participant approximately three times. In the first session, we asked them to choose four photos of children (out of 24 photos including 8 Latinx, 8 Black, and 8 White children) with whom they would like to be pen pals. They were told that we, the researchers, wanted them to participate in our pen pal program in order to better understand how children make friends. In the next two sessions, children were asked about their race-related beliefs and attitudes, including the racial composition of their closest friends, their affective feelings toward different racial groups, and their beliefs about the challenges and benefits of having friends of a different racial background. We also recruited children?s parents and were able to get approximately 40 child participants? parents to take part in our study. Thus, we have roughly 40 parent-child dyads in our dataset. Additionally, we had roughly 60 additional parents complete a survey exploring their own and their children?s race-related beliefs and experiences. Thus approximately 200 individuals participated in our study overall.  Preliminary results show that, on average, children chose more than two individuals of a different race and more than one individual of the same race as potential pen pals. Additionally, children chose on average about 1 Black pen pal, 1 Latino pen pal, and 1.5 White pen pals. In regression analyses, we found that children who felt more positively toward Black people as a group - so they attributed more positive characteristics to Black people - chose more Black children as potential pen pals. Finally, we found a significant correlation such that parents whose children had seen them kiss a Black person had kids who were happier to be in close proximity to a Black person. These results are preliminary; however, they indicate important information regarding how to promote cross-race friendships in childhood. Namely improving children?s racial attitudes and parents acting as role models may be particularly important for encouraging cross-race friendships in childhood.   Secondly, in terms of dissemination of research, I have co-authored a number of recently accepted publications on topics focusing on race and its impact on children and adolescents. Over the course of the award, I have had 4 papers accepted into peer-reviewed academic journals. These papers were published in journals including Child Development, Journal of Marriage and Family, and the Journal of Black Psychology. In addition, I presented academic work at 4 conferences over the course of the award. These conferences include the Society for Research in Child Development and the Cognitive Development Society. Additionally, my sponsor Dr. Rebecca Bigler presented our work from this project at the Society for the Study of Human Development. Finally, I presented the preliminary project results to parents outside the research community in a presentation in which I discussed effective ways to encourage children to engage in cross-race friendships.  In terms of broader impacts, we were able to provide professional development and research opportunities to students, many of whom are underrepresented in the academy. Roughly 10 students, many of whom were Spanish-English bilingual, Latinx students, participated in the project as research assistants (RAs). Many of our students were Latinx due to the population demographics of our participants, most of whom were also Latinx and many of whom were more comfortable speaking Spanish than English. Additionally, we had White, Asian, and African American students participate as RAs. These students were trained to recruit parents, to interview children, and to enter data into SPSS (the statistics software most commonly used in psychology). We also provided professional development opportunities. I wrote recommendation letters for a student who wanted to participate in a summer internship, and she was able to intern at her first choice. Likewise, I provided a presentation to underrepresented students participating in a summer research program at UT Austin, in which I discussed career opportunities in academia post-graduate school/Ph.D.  Thus, we feel confident that the project reached the goals we aimed to achieve. We will continue to disseminate the results gleaned from the project. This will include submitting empirical articles to peer-reviewed journals, and providing aggregate results to each of the organizations that allowed us to recruit in their schools. As appropriate, we will also discuss our findings with broader media outlets. We thank the National Science Foundation for the opportunity to conduct research so important to promoting a more equitable and just future.        Last Modified: 10/29/2017       Submitted by: Amber Williams]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
