<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Models for Trait-Mediated Dispersal in Ecology</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/15/2015</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>507778.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>507778</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DMS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Junping Wang</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>jwang@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924488</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The dispersal of organisms strongly influences their interactions with their environment and with populations of other organisms. The ecological effects of dispersal in turn influence the fitness of individuals, and hence influence natural selection, which drives evolution.  Thus, the effects of dispersal can feed back to influence the attributes and behaviors of organisms, including those that affect dispersal and its consequences.  Such attributes and behaviors are known as traits. They include tendencies to seek resources, avoid predators, or migrate seasonally, which can be viewed as dispersal strategies, but they also include the ways that organisms use information about their environment to decide how to move or how they communicate such information with other members of their species.  This project will use mathematical models to gain insight into the connections between the structure and variability of the environment and the dispersal traits that can be expected to evolve and persist. Mathematical models are necessary to gain such insight because the effects of dispersal and the feedbacks involved in its evolution are too subtle and complex to capture with verbal descriptions.  In past research, the investigators have gained a good understanding of which fixed dispersal traits are most favorable in the context of a single population in an environment that varies in space but not in time.  One aspect of this project is to address similar issues in the context of environments that are also changing in time. Another is to study more deeply how dispersal influences species interactions, especially when it interacts with variations in timing of life history events.  Both of those research directions are motivated in part by ecological problems related to global change.  Other aspects of the project focus on understanding behavioral traits related to dispersal; some of those may be relevant to conservation/restoration efforts and to understanding the movement of disease vectors.  Some parts of the project will be conducted in collaboration with postdoctoral fellows and thus should contribute to enhancing the scientific workforce.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The dispersal of organisms affects their fitness by determining their spatial distribution and interactions with other populations, which then creates selective pressure on traits related to dispersal.  This leads to complex feedbacks between the effects and evolution of dispersal traits that can only be understood by using mathematical or computational models.  Traditional models of dispersal typically assume it is a fixed behavior, independent of environmental conditions, such as simple diffusion.  However, organisms seek resources, avoid enemies, and engage in behaviors such as migration that require the use and transmission of information.  These conditional dispersal behaviors are traits, which can be shaped by evolution and can be viewed as strategies from the viewpoint of adaptive dynamics.  In previous work, the investigators used pairwise invasibility analysis of various models, including reaction-advection-diffusion equations, discrete diffusion systems, and their nonlocal integro-differential analogues, to show that for a single unstructured population in a spatially varying but temporally constant environment the evolutionarily stable strategies are those that produce an ideal free distribution.  The research team will use similar methods to gain understanding of the evolution of dispersal traits in the more realistic contexts of populations in environments that vary in both space and time, populations that are structured by stage or internal state, and systems of interacting populations.  To do that, the investigators will use additional types of models including integro-difference models as well as those used before.  It is expected that the detailed conclusions in those cases will often be different from those for an unstructured population in a temporally constant environment.  Some numerical experiments may be needed to suggest what the conclusions should be.  Hybrid models that include both dispersal and phenology will also be studied, as well as models for organisms with multiple dispersal modes.  The first of those is relevant to understanding how phenology shifts caused by global change could interact with spatial effects.  For example, how are the effects of isolation in time similar to those of isolation in space, and how do they differ?  The second is relevant to understanding the movement patterns of various organisms, including female mosquitoes that switch between seeking blood meals and seeking oviposition sites.  More broadly, understanding dispersal traits is relevant to conservation and pest management and to predicting the effects of global change on natural and agricultural ecosystems.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/06/2015</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/06/2015</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1514752</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Robert</FirstName>
<LastName>Cantrell</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>S</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Robert S Cantrell</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>rsc@math.miami.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>3052842348</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000256426</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/06/2015</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>George</FirstName>
<LastName>Cosner</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>C</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>George C Cosner</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>gcc@math.miami.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>3052843519</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000452640</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/06/2015</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Miami</Name>
<CityName>CORAL GABLES</CityName>
<ZipCode>331462926</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>3052843924</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1320 S. Dixie Highway Suite 650</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[Suite 100-A]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Florida</StateName>
<StateCode>FL</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>27</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>FL27</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>625174149</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF MIAMI</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>004146619</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Miami]]></Name>
<CityName>Coral Gables</CityName>
<StateCode>FL</StateCode>
<ZipCode>331462508</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[1365 Memorial Drive]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Florida</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>27</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>FL27</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1182</Code>
<Text>POP &amp; COMMUNITY ECOL PROG</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7275</Code>
<Text>Cross-BIO Activities</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7334</Code>
<Text>MATHEMATICAL BIOLOGY</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7454</Code>
<Text>MSPA-INTERDISCIPLINARY</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8007</Code>
<Text>BioMaPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0115</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2015~507778</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Intellectual merit:</p> <p>The goals of this project were all related to developing and mathematical models to describe the ways organisms might disperse throughout their environments, and then using the models to study the ecological effects of various types of dispersal behavior, and how those ecological effects feed back to influence the evolution of dispersal behavior. The underlying motivation was to gain a better understanding of the role that dispersal behavior plays in ecological processes and why organisms disperse in the ways that they do.</p> <p>One specific goal was to understand what kind of dispersal is optimal in environments that vary in both space and time. Earlier research has shown that in environments that vary in space but not in time it is possible for organisms to disperse in a way that allows them to exactly match the spatial distribution of resources by using the right combination of random and directed movement. Furthermore, that combination can be determined by using only information on the quality of the environment at the organism's current location. That type of dispersal behavior turns out to be favored by evolution in static environments. In this project we found out how it is possible for organisms to do the same thing in environments that vary in both space and time, and showed that again that such dispersal patterns are favored by evolution. However, when the environment varies in time, the organisms need to use information about the past history of the environment or about conditions in spatial locations other than where they are located.&nbsp; Getting that information requires organisms to use memory, share information with others, and/or be able to use their senses to determine conditions at somewhat distant locations.&nbsp;&nbsp; This is fundamentally different from the case of static environments and suggests that the evolution of sophisticated cognitive and sensory abilities may depend partly on having an environment that changes over time.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>Another goal was to construct and analyze mathematical models for dispersal in populations that can use more than one movement mode, for example either walking or flying, or either moving randomly to search for resources but moving directly toward them once they are detected. &nbsp;Such patterns of dispersal appear to be fairly common in nature. We constructed models combining dispersal with switching and population growth and analyzed them. That required some new mathematical ideas. Based on the general theory, we developed a specific mathematical model that describes a type of movement that has been observed in nature, with organisms switching between large scale random searching and directed movement toward favorable locations when those locations are detected. &nbsp;The model was able to approximately reproduce a type of dispersal behavior that has been observed in nature.</p> <p>In many cases the time scale of dispersal is much faster than the time scale of population growth or decline.&nbsp; We developed a type of mathematical population models based on that assumption. Those models are simpler to analyze than traditional models where everything happens on a single timescale, and in some cases they are more realistic.&nbsp; We used this modeling approach to obtain some new results on the evolution of optimal dispersal, but it could be used to study various other questions about dispersal.</p> <p>Broader impacts:&nbsp;</p> <p>The mathematical model in one of the papers arising from the project showed how harvesting may have indirect detrimental effects on populations that are not being harvested by disturbing them in ways which cause them to change their behavior, specifically when the disturbance causes populations to disperse more rapidly. This is relevant to managing populations because it suggests that such indirect effects should be considered in making decisions about harvesting in the context of protecting species that are not harvested from being harmed by the harvesting of other species in their community.&nbsp; Another paper based on methods developed in this project shows how habitat fragmentation can increase the risk of vector-borne diseases in some situations. That information may be relevant in trying to manage vector-borne diseases.</p> <p>In the course of the project we supported and trained two postdoctoral researchers. There were nine other students and postdoctoral researchers among our collaborators on papers from the project, including two undergraduates.&nbsp; Four of those collaborators were women. We are continuing to work with a junior faculty member at an undergraduate institution on a paper that was initiated as part of this project and which will acknowledge support from it.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 10/12/2019<br>      Modified by: George&nbsp;C&nbsp;Cosner</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Intellectual merit:  The goals of this project were all related to developing and mathematical models to describe the ways organisms might disperse throughout their environments, and then using the models to study the ecological effects of various types of dispersal behavior, and how those ecological effects feed back to influence the evolution of dispersal behavior. The underlying motivation was to gain a better understanding of the role that dispersal behavior plays in ecological processes and why organisms disperse in the ways that they do.  One specific goal was to understand what kind of dispersal is optimal in environments that vary in both space and time. Earlier research has shown that in environments that vary in space but not in time it is possible for organisms to disperse in a way that allows them to exactly match the spatial distribution of resources by using the right combination of random and directed movement. Furthermore, that combination can be determined by using only information on the quality of the environment at the organism's current location. That type of dispersal behavior turns out to be favored by evolution in static environments. In this project we found out how it is possible for organisms to do the same thing in environments that vary in both space and time, and showed that again that such dispersal patterns are favored by evolution. However, when the environment varies in time, the organisms need to use information about the past history of the environment or about conditions in spatial locations other than where they are located.  Getting that information requires organisms to use memory, share information with others, and/or be able to use their senses to determine conditions at somewhat distant locations.   This is fundamentally different from the case of static environments and suggests that the evolution of sophisticated cognitive and sensory abilities may depend partly on having an environment that changes over time.     Another goal was to construct and analyze mathematical models for dispersal in populations that can use more than one movement mode, for example either walking or flying, or either moving randomly to search for resources but moving directly toward them once they are detected.  Such patterns of dispersal appear to be fairly common in nature. We constructed models combining dispersal with switching and population growth and analyzed them. That required some new mathematical ideas. Based on the general theory, we developed a specific mathematical model that describes a type of movement that has been observed in nature, with organisms switching between large scale random searching and directed movement toward favorable locations when those locations are detected.  The model was able to approximately reproduce a type of dispersal behavior that has been observed in nature.  In many cases the time scale of dispersal is much faster than the time scale of population growth or decline.  We developed a type of mathematical population models based on that assumption. Those models are simpler to analyze than traditional models where everything happens on a single timescale, and in some cases they are more realistic.  We used this modeling approach to obtain some new results on the evolution of optimal dispersal, but it could be used to study various other questions about dispersal.  Broader impacts:   The mathematical model in one of the papers arising from the project showed how harvesting may have indirect detrimental effects on populations that are not being harvested by disturbing them in ways which cause them to change their behavior, specifically when the disturbance causes populations to disperse more rapidly. This is relevant to managing populations because it suggests that such indirect effects should be considered in making decisions about harvesting in the context of protecting species that are not harvested from being harmed by the harvesting of other species in their community.  Another paper based on methods developed in this project shows how habitat fragmentation can increase the risk of vector-borne diseases in some situations. That information may be relevant in trying to manage vector-borne diseases.  In the course of the project we supported and trained two postdoctoral researchers. There were nine other students and postdoctoral researchers among our collaborators on papers from the project, including two undergraduates.  Four of those collaborators were women. We are continuing to work with a junior faculty member at an undergraduate institution on a paper that was initiated as part of this project and which will acknowledge support from it.                      Last Modified: 10/12/2019       Submitted by: George C Cosner]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
