<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>EAPSI: Investigating the Stability of Particles in Topological Phases of Matter</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>06/01/2015</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2016</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>70.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>70</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Fellowship Award</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>01090000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>O/D</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Office Of The Director</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>OISE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Office Of Internatl Science &amp;Engineering</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Anne Emig</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>aemig@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927241</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>A fundamental challenge in science is to characterize states of matter.  A phase of matter is a family of states of matter which have very uniform physical properties.  Common phases include liquid, gas and solid, which are distinguished by varying temperature.  In the 1980?s, scientist discovered new phases of matter in two dimensional electron gas structures, namely fractional quantum hall states.  These states possessed particles with interesting statistical behavior, called anyons.  In particular, an exchange of two anyons resulted in a multiplication of the state by a complex phase.  These new states of matter belong to topologically ordered phases.  This project investigates the conjecture that the structure of anyons is stable within a topological phase.  This research will be conducted in collaboration with Dr. Yasuyuki Kawahigashi, professor in the Department of Mathematical Science at the University of Tokyo.  Dr. Kawahigashi is an expert in the theory of operator algebras and their applications to mathematical physics.  The collaboration allows us to further explore the operator algebraic perspective of topological phases and pursue rigorous results in the subject.  This research will advance efforts to realize universal quantum computing.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;We begin by studying exactly solvable Hamiltonian lattice models, in the thermodynamic limit, for which the anyon structure is completely known.  These models include Kitaev?s surface codes and Levin and Wen?s string-net models.  Each anyon is related to a superselection sector of the algebra of observables.  Analysis of the superselection sectors allows one to recover the complete anyon structure, including particle fusion and braiding.  Under physically allowable perturbations, we will study the stability of the superselection sectors and particle fusion and braiding.  The stability of anyons is the premise of a major program in fault-tolerant quantum computation, namely topological quantum computation.  The results of this project form the basis for the continued search for a universal quantum computer through topologically ordered states.  This NSF EAPSI award is funded in collaboration with the Japan Society for the Promotion of Science.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/16/2015</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/16/2015</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.079</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1515557</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Matthew</FirstName>
<LastName>Cha</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Matthew Cha</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress/>
<PI_PHON>8586529098</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000684182</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/16/2015</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Cha                     Matthew</Name>
<CityName>San Diego</CityName>
<ZipCode>921269500</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber/>
<StreetAddress/>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>52</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CA52</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM/>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME/>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Cha                     Matthew]]></Name>
<CityName>San Diego</CityName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>921269500</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>52</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CA52</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7316</Code>
<Text>EAPSI</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>5921</Code>
<Text>JAPAN</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>5978</Code>
<Text>EAST ASIA AND PACIFIC PROGRAM</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7316</Code>
<Text>EAPSI</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0115</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2015~70</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The behavior of a quantum system at low temperatures is governed by its low energy states.&nbsp; The set lowest energy states is called the ground state space.&nbsp; A complete understanding of the ground state space characterizes properties of the quantum phase of matter of a quantum system and has been used to determine if a system could implement a quantum computer.&nbsp; In particular, we are interested in quantum systems with topologically ordered ground state space.&nbsp; Suppose our quantum system was defined on a two-dimensional torus.&nbsp; The ground state space will be able to detect that the shape of the space, or its topology, is that of a torus, but unable to detect geometrical aspects regarding length or angles.&nbsp; The quantum double models introduced by Alexei Kitaev in 1997, provided the first examples of topologically ordered quantum ground states in the framework of quantum spin systems.&nbsp; It was shown that these models can be used to implement a universal fault-tolerant quantum computer at zero temperature. Inherently, quantum systems are very sensitive to noise and so fault-tolerance is diffuicult  achieve.&nbsp; Stability refers to properties of a quantum system that are robust in the presence of noise.</p> <p>The outcomes of our research are developing a suitable mathematical framework to study the stability of anyons in topological phases of matter.&nbsp; By applying mathematical tools developed to study local quantum field theory, we analyzed the superselection sectors in infinite quantum spin systems.&nbsp; As a main result, we define a superselection criterion which leads to invariant superselection sectors in a topological phase of matter.&nbsp; Our analysis was applied to the Kitaev's toric code model and recovered the well known anyon superselection structure.&nbsp; The benifit of our method is that anyon stability is an immediate consequence of the construction.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 03/16/2016<br>      Modified by: Matthew&nbsp;Cha</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The behavior of a quantum system at low temperatures is governed by its low energy states.  The set lowest energy states is called the ground state space.  A complete understanding of the ground state space characterizes properties of the quantum phase of matter of a quantum system and has been used to determine if a system could implement a quantum computer.  In particular, we are interested in quantum systems with topologically ordered ground state space.  Suppose our quantum system was defined on a two-dimensional torus.  The ground state space will be able to detect that the shape of the space, or its topology, is that of a torus, but unable to detect geometrical aspects regarding length or angles.  The quantum double models introduced by Alexei Kitaev in 1997, provided the first examples of topologically ordered quantum ground states in the framework of quantum spin systems.  It was shown that these models can be used to implement a universal fault-tolerant quantum computer at zero temperature. Inherently, quantum systems are very sensitive to noise and so fault-tolerance is diffuicult  achieve.  Stability refers to properties of a quantum system that are robust in the presence of noise.  The outcomes of our research are developing a suitable mathematical framework to study the stability of anyons in topological phases of matter.  By applying mathematical tools developed to study local quantum field theory, we analyzed the superselection sectors in infinite quantum spin systems.  As a main result, we define a superselection criterion which leads to invariant superselection sectors in a topological phase of matter.  Our analysis was applied to the Kitaev's toric code model and recovered the well known anyon superselection structure.  The benifit of our method is that anyon stability is an immediate consequence of the construction.       Last Modified: 03/16/2016       Submitted by: Matthew Cha]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
