<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>EAPSI: Investigating Intermolecular Interactions in the Formation of Polymer-Based Nanowires</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>06/01/2015</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2016</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>70.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>70</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Fellowship Award</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>01090000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>O/D</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Office Of The Director</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>OISE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Office Of Internatl Science &amp;Engineering</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Anne Emig</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>aemig@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927241</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Semiconducting polymers promise to deliver low cost electronic devices such as solar cells and transistors due  to  their  easy  processabililty.  Fabrication  conditions  have  been  identified  that  allows poly(3-hexyl thiophenes) (P3HT), an extensively studied semiconducting polymer, to crystallize into nanowires  (NWs),  which  can  improve  a  solar  cell?s  efficiency.  This project  aims  to  understand  the assembly of P3HT into NWs. Both the NW alignment and the orientation of the polymer chains with respect to the substrate are crucial parameters to control for ensuring efficient transport of charges in solar cells. In order to characterize the structural features of the NWs, near edge X-ray absorption fine structure (NEXAFS), a highly specialized  technique  capable of proving  the molecular  orientation  of thin films down to monolayers of the material will be used. Dr. Kilwon Cho, an expert in surface and electronic device characterization at Pohang University of Science and Technology, will be the host for this research, providing a U.S. graduate student vital access and expertize for NEXAFS analysis.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This  project  will  focus  on  the  surface  crystallization  of  P3HT  from  graphene  deposited  on supporting   substrates.   Utilizing  a  metastable   solution  of  P3HT,  with  a  strong  driving  force  for crystallization that is not sufficient to induce homogenous crystallization, NWs of P3HT will be formed selectively on graphene.  During the crystallization, the polymer chains in solution interact with graphene and the underlying substrate. A systematic study of the NW growth from graphene deposited on modified substrates  employing  surface  characterization  techniques  such  as  NEXAFS  will  unveil  the  surface properties   and  the  morphology   evolution   of  P3HT.  This will help us determine   the  effects  of intermolecular forces on the P3HT crystallization. Ultimately, the beneficial effects of the NWs will be assessed by the fabrication and characterization of solar cells. This NSF EAPSI award is funded in collaboration with the National Research Foundation of Korea.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award is jointly funded by NSF and the National Research Foundation of Korea.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>05/26/2015</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/26/2015</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.079</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1515637</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Daniel</FirstName>
<LastName>Acevedo</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>E</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Daniel E Acevedo</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress/>
<PI_PHON>7872143159</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000686089</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/26/2015</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Acevedo                 Daniel         E</Name>
<CityName>Amherst</CityName>
<ZipCode>010039263</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber/>
<StreetAddress/>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
<StateCode>MA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MA02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM/>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME/>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Acevedo                 Daniel         E]]></Name>
<CityName>Amherst</CityName>
<StateCode>MA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>010039263</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MA02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7316</Code>
<Text>EAPSI</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>5942</Code>
<Text>KOREA</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>5978</Code>
<Text>EAST ASIA AND PACIFIC PROGRAM</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7316</Code>
<Text>EAPSI</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0115</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2015~70</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Semiconducting polymers promise to deliver low cost electronic devices, such as solar cells and transistors, due to their easy processabililty in solution. Fabrication conditions have been identified that allow poly(3-hexyl thiophene) (P3HT), an extensively studied semiconducting polymer, to crystallize into nanowires (NWs), which can improve solar cells efficiency. This project aims to understand the assembly of P3HT into NWs. Both the NW alignment and the orientation of the polymer chains with respect to the substrate are crucial parameters to control for ensuring efficient charge transport in solar cells. The goal of the project is to simultaneously control the molecular and nanostructural organization of poly(3-hexylthiophene) (P3HT) through solution-based crystallization. Ideally the P3HT chains must be oriented &ldquo;face-on&rdquo; (i.e. the &pi; planes parallel to the substrate normal) with respect to the substrate allowing the polymer to crystallize into vertically aligned nanowires. Consequently, this control over the morphology would improve the performance of solar cells by providing pathways for out-of-plane charge transport.</p> <p>It was demonstrated that P3HT selectively crystallized into nanowires from graphene on MoO<sub>3</sub>, which can serve both as a template for nanowire growth and an anode for solar cells. The main requirement for selective crystallization was a metastable solution of P3HT at room temperature. The metastable state of the solutions suppresses homogenous nucleation of crystals while allowing for heterogeneous crystallization on nucleation sites. In the dissolved state, the polymer chains in solution interact with graphene, initially adsorbing &ldquo;face-on&rdquo;, but transitioning to &ldquo;edge-on&rdquo; (i.e. &pi; planes perpendicular to the substrate) as the film grew thicker and the solvent was removed. The transition of the P3HT orientation was confirmed by ultraviolet photoelectron spectroscopy and near-edge X-ray absorption fine structure at the Pohang Accelerator Laboratories. As determined by grazing incidence wide angle X-ray scattering, the initial face-on conformation is partially preserved by embedding the P3HT structures in an indene C<sub>60</sub> bisadduct (ICBA) matrix, when compared to pristine P3HT films. This study establishes a platform for generating vertically oriented nanowires to be employed in solar cells and thereby improving their power conversion efficiency. Results were achieved in a synergetic collaboration between the groups of Kilwon Cho at Pohang University of Science and Technology and Bumjoon J. Kim at Korea Advanced Institute of Science and Technology (KAIST), and the Pohang Accelerator Laboratories.</p> <p>At the end of the EAPSI Program, I had the pleasure of presenting my work at the NRF headquarters to the NRF staff members. Also, NRF Global PhD fellows were able to share their respective research results with the EAPSI participants. To reach a broader audience I traveled to the 2015 SACNAS National Conference. The Society of Advancing Chicanos and Native Americans in Science (SACNAS) gathers many of the nation&rsquo;s best scientists possessing similar backgrounds to mine. Therefore, I had the opportunity to provide underrepresented groups with the knowledge of international research opportunities. Coupled with SACNAS, the Society of Hispanic Professional Engineers (SHPE) allowed me to serve as role model to positively impact the Hispanic community. I received a travel award to the 2015 SHPE National Conference for being a finalist of the RISE Symposia Paper Competition, in which I also presented.&nbsp; Moreover, at the University of Massachusetts Amherst I presented an overview of my EAPSI experience to my peers in the North Eastern Alliance for the Graduate Studies and Professoriate and mentored two applicants through their application process. Finally on my private time I wrote a...]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Semiconducting polymers promise to deliver low cost electronic devices, such as solar cells and transistors, due to their easy processabililty in solution. Fabrication conditions have been identified that allow poly(3-hexyl thiophene) (P3HT), an extensively studied semiconducting polymer, to crystallize into nanowires (NWs), which can improve solar cells efficiency. This project aims to understand the assembly of P3HT into NWs. Both the NW alignment and the orientation of the polymer chains with respect to the substrate are crucial parameters to control for ensuring efficient charge transport in solar cells. The goal of the project is to simultaneously control the molecular and nanostructural organization of poly(3-hexylthiophene) (P3HT) through solution-based crystallization. Ideally the P3HT chains must be oriented "face-on" (i.e. the &pi; planes parallel to the substrate normal) with respect to the substrate allowing the polymer to crystallize into vertically aligned nanowires. Consequently, this control over the morphology would improve the performance of solar cells by providing pathways for out-of-plane charge transport.  It was demonstrated that P3HT selectively crystallized into nanowires from graphene on MoO3, which can serve both as a template for nanowire growth and an anode for solar cells. The main requirement for selective crystallization was a metastable solution of P3HT at room temperature. The metastable state of the solutions suppresses homogenous nucleation of crystals while allowing for heterogeneous crystallization on nucleation sites. In the dissolved state, the polymer chains in solution interact with graphene, initially adsorbing "face-on", but transitioning to "edge-on" (i.e. &pi; planes perpendicular to the substrate) as the film grew thicker and the solvent was removed. The transition of the P3HT orientation was confirmed by ultraviolet photoelectron spectroscopy and near-edge X-ray absorption fine structure at the Pohang Accelerator Laboratories. As determined by grazing incidence wide angle X-ray scattering, the initial face-on conformation is partially preserved by embedding the P3HT structures in an indene C60 bisadduct (ICBA) matrix, when compared to pristine P3HT films. This study establishes a platform for generating vertically oriented nanowires to be employed in solar cells and thereby improving their power conversion efficiency. Results were achieved in a synergetic collaboration between the groups of Kilwon Cho at Pohang University of Science and Technology and Bumjoon J. Kim at Korea Advanced Institute of Science and Technology (KAIST), and the Pohang Accelerator Laboratories.  At the end of the EAPSI Program, I had the pleasure of presenting my work at the NRF headquarters to the NRF staff members. Also, NRF Global PhD fellows were able to share their respective research results with the EAPSI participants. To reach a broader audience I traveled to the 2015 SACNAS National Conference. The Society of Advancing Chicanos and Native Americans in Science (SACNAS) gathers many of the nationÆs best scientists possessing similar backgrounds to mine. Therefore, I had the opportunity to provide underrepresented groups with the knowledge of international research opportunities. Coupled with SACNAS, the Society of Hispanic Professional Engineers (SHPE) allowed me to serve as role model to positively impact the Hispanic community. I received a travel award to the 2015 SHPE National Conference for being a finalist of the RISE Symposia Paper Competition, in which I also presented.  Moreover, at the University of Massachusetts Amherst I presented an overview of my EAPSI experience to my peers in the North Eastern Alliance for the Graduate Studies and Professoriate and mentored two applicants through their application process. Finally on my private time I wrote an article about my EAPSI experience on LinkedIn to further motivate others to pursue similar experiences.          Last Modified: 03/14/2016   ...]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
