<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>EAPSI: Inkjet Printed Paper-Based Chemical Sensor for Vitamin E</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>06/01/2015</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2016</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>5070.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>5070</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Fellowship Award</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>01090000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>O/D</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Office Of The Director</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>OISE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Office Of Internatl Science &amp;Engineering</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Anne Emig</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>aemig@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927241</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Measuring the amount of vitamin E present in blood is difficult because of the complex nature of blood, overall cost, amount of time, and instrumentation involved. The development of a chemical sensor ink, which is then printed onto paper, would be a novel approach to determining vitamin E levels in biological fluids. For years, people have been using ink jet printing in their homes and offices; however, it has transitioned from an office and home application to an application for chemical sensing. Modern inkjet printers support the creation of precise and contactless deposition of microscopic sized droplets of the chemical sensor onto paper. This award supports research that combines inkjet printing with molecular imprinted polymers (MIPs) to develop a new sensor that can be used to test levels of Vitamin E in bodily fluids. This research will be conducted in collaboration with Dr. Daniel Citterio at Keio University in Tokyo Japan, who is an expert in inkjet printing technology for the development of microfluidic paper-based analytical devises. Results from this collaboration could allow for a point of care testing system that would be accurate, precise, reproducible, and overall cheaper than current blood testing methods. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The proposed chemical sensor would utilize an aqueous, non-covalently crosslinked network, MIP as an ink to be printed onto paper based substrates. The key challenge that must be overcome is creating an MIP that is both aqueous and presents a strong and selective binding affinity for vitamin E. MIP will be formulated and printed onto paper so that vitamin E levels can be measured using a fluorescence response indicator. Dr. Citterio?s group was the first to demonstrate the function of using ink jet printing for the deposition of biochemical sensors by microfluidic patterning of the substrates. Creating such a technology could have multiple uses in many different fields as a new class of chemical sensors. The NSF EAPSI award is funded in collaboration with the Japan Society for the Promotion of Science.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/03/2015</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/03/2015</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.079</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1515412</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Casey</FirstName>
<LastName>Grenier</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>J</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Casey J Grenier</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress/>
<PI_PHON>6034919511</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000683807</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/03/2015</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Grenier                 Casey          J</Name>
<CityName>Pembroke</CityName>
<ZipCode>032753604</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber/>
<StreetAddress/>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New Hampshire</StateName>
<StateCode>NH</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NH02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM/>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME/>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Grenier                 Casey          J]]></Name>
<CityName>Pembroke</CityName>
<StateCode>NH</StateCode>
<ZipCode>032753604</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New Hampshire</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NH02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7316</Code>
<Text>EAPSI</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>5921</Code>
<Text>JAPAN</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>5978</Code>
<Text>EAST ASIA AND PACIFIC PROGRAM</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7316</Code>
<Text>EAPSI</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0115</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2015~5070</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Chemical sensors are used to identify varying levels of chemical information in a system that is otherwise impossible or difficult to measure. Synthesizing a flexible molecularly imprinted polymer (MIP) that is capable of rapid detection of templated compounds, which is also amenable to inkjet printing, allows for simple, robust, low cost, and novel measurements. Having created a network with the capability of having an &ldquo;on/off&rdquo; fluorescence response to the desired molecule demonstrates that this is a viable sensor for a variety of on-site measurements, including medical diagnostics at home or in a healthcare facility, point of care testing for several different drugs, and environmental analysis in the field.</p> <p>The polymer formulation was optimized upon arrival to Keio University by increasing the percentage of non-covalent crosslinks. This increase allowed for stronger binding constants of the polymer in solution. A fluorescence monomer was then designed and synthesized that would allow a fluorescence reaction to occur in the presence of organic solvent and be quenched in the presence of water. This system was decided upon because of the polymers functionality of the various co-monomers within the polymer, the characterization of the aqueous polymer in the presence of vitamin E, and the insolubility of vitamin E in water. Once the polymer binds with vitamin E it was observed the polymer would shrink in size and eventually collapse on itself and fall out of the aqueous solution, depending on the amount of vitamin E bound. With the polymer being hydrophobic in the collapsed form this allowed the fluorescence monomer to now give a signal fluorescence signal based on the amount of vitamin E bound will in the presence of organic solvent.&nbsp; This was observed in solution and on paper; however, the use of instrumentation was needed to verify and was not as profound as in solution.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 04/07/2016<br>      Modified by: Casey&nbsp;J&nbsp;Grenier</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Images (<span id="selectedPhoto0">1</span> of <span class="totalNumber"></span>)           </div> <div class="galControls" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2016/1515412/1515412_10367245_1460030832862_PredictedDataandPrototype--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2016/1515412/1515412_10367245_1460030832862_PredictedDataandPrototype--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Design of Sensor"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2016/1515412/1515412_10367245_1460030832862_PredictedDataandPrototype--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Design of Sensor"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">A) Depicts the designed sensor and predicted data. B) Printed MIP tagged with fluorescence within the channel, Uv light ? left side and natural light ? right side.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Casey Grenier</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Royalty-free (unrestricted use)</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Casey&nbsp;J&nbsp;Grenier</div> <div class="imageTitle">Design of Sensor</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2016/1515412/1515412_10367245_1460030751561_Theory--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2016/1515412/1515412_10367245_1460030751561_Theory--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Theory Behind the Polymer Sensor"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2016/1515412/1515412_10367245_1460030751561_Theory--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Theory Behind the Polymer Sensor"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Recognition of the template molecule res...]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Chemical sensors are used to identify varying levels of chemical information in a system that is otherwise impossible or difficult to measure. Synthesizing a flexible molecularly imprinted polymer (MIP) that is capable of rapid detection of templated compounds, which is also amenable to inkjet printing, allows for simple, robust, low cost, and novel measurements. Having created a network with the capability of having an "on/off" fluorescence response to the desired molecule demonstrates that this is a viable sensor for a variety of on-site measurements, including medical diagnostics at home or in a healthcare facility, point of care testing for several different drugs, and environmental analysis in the field.  The polymer formulation was optimized upon arrival to Keio University by increasing the percentage of non-covalent crosslinks. This increase allowed for stronger binding constants of the polymer in solution. A fluorescence monomer was then designed and synthesized that would allow a fluorescence reaction to occur in the presence of organic solvent and be quenched in the presence of water. This system was decided upon because of the polymers functionality of the various co-monomers within the polymer, the characterization of the aqueous polymer in the presence of vitamin E, and the insolubility of vitamin E in water. Once the polymer binds with vitamin E it was observed the polymer would shrink in size and eventually collapse on itself and fall out of the aqueous solution, depending on the amount of vitamin E bound. With the polymer being hydrophobic in the collapsed form this allowed the fluorescence monomer to now give a signal fluorescence signal based on the amount of vitamin E bound will in the presence of organic solvent.  This was observed in solution and on paper; however, the use of instrumentation was needed to verify and was not as profound as in solution.          Last Modified: 04/07/2016       Submitted by: Casey J Grenier]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
