<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Control and Function of Chromatin-Mediated Gene Silencing in Fusarium</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/15/2015</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>570000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>570000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>08070100</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>BIO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>MCB</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Molecular and Cellular Bioscience</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Karen Cone</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>kccone@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924967</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Normal development relies on regulated gene expression, which in many organisms is achieved by balanced activity of protein complexes that turn genes on or off at the right time and in the right place.  A major unsolved question is how silencing proteins locate and turn off their target genes.  The focus of this research is to discover how genes are targeted and inactivated by the silencing protein complex known as the "polycomb group" (PcG) complex.  As a study system, the project will use the fungus, Fusarium graminearum, which has economic importance as a source of beneficial natural products and biofuels and agronomic importance as a plant pathogen.  Thus, the results of the research could translate into better methods for manipulating the beneficial traits of the fungus, while minimizing its negative impact on crop plants. The project will have educational impacts by providing research training opportunities for underserved students, laboratory and professional development workshops for high school science teachers, and science presentations to the general public.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project addresses chromatin-based gene silencing by PcG proteins in a novel model organism, the filamentous fungus Fusarium graminearum. The work will take advantage of the fact that Fusarium uses one Polycomb Repressive Complex2 (PRC2) to deliver histone H3 lysine 27 trimethylation (H3K27me3) to specific genes. Preliminary data suggest that the gene recognition is mediated by PRC2 subunits or by interacting proteins and that the subsequently modified genes are sequestered as transcriptionally silent  "PRC2 bodies" with clear boundaries to euchromatin. The main objectives of this project are to uncover the mechanism for PRC2 targeting and to define the composition of PRC2 complexes. The aims will be achieved by multi-faceted approaches, including:  forward and reverse genetics by undirected selections and screens, gene deletions, and site-directed mutagenesis; biochemistry by chromatin immunoprecipitation, genome-wide expression analyses and mass spectrometry;  and cytology by examination of PRC2 bodies in association with DNA. In combination, these techniques will allow identification and characterization of PRC2 signals and proteins involved in gene silencing. Novel components of PRC2-mediated gene silencing in Fusarium will be characterized, and distribution of H3K27me3 and PRC2 in normal and mutant strains will be mapped. The research will provide key knowledge on PRC2-mediated silencing in eukaryotes.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/06/2015</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/11/2017</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.074</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1515998</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Michael</FirstName>
<LastName>Freitag</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Michael Freitag</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>freitagm@onid.orst.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5417374845</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000436924</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/06/2015</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Oregon State University</Name>
<CityName>Corvallis</CityName>
<ZipCode>973318507</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5417374933</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>OREGON STATE UNIVERSITY</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Oregon</StateName>
<StateCode>OR</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>OR04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>053599908</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>OREGON STATE UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>053599908</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Oregon State University]]></Name>
<CityName>Corvallis</CityName>
<StateCode>OR</StateCode>
<ZipCode>973318507</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Oregon</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>OR04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1112</Code>
<Text>Genetic Mechanisms</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7218</Code>
<Text>RET SUPP-Res Exp for Tchr Supp</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7465</Code>
<Text>NANOSCALE BIO CORE</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9178</Code>
<Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9179</Code>
<Text>GRADUATE INVOLVEMENT</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9251</Code>
<Text>REU SUPP-Res Exp for Ugrd Supp</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0115</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0117</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2015~370000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2017~200000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>How specific regions of chromosomes are activated for gene expression and subsequently turned off, and how this reversible ?silencing? is maintained is still not well understood. In many eukaryotes post-translational modifications of histone proteins seem to generate a code to help accomplish this task. One specific silencing histone modification, trimethylation of lysine 27 on histone H3 (H3K27me3) is catalyzed by a large protein complex, named PRC2 (Polycomb Repressive Complex 2). This complex is largely conserved in plants, fungi, and animals, yet how precisely PRC2 is targeted to specific chromatin regions is unclear. The emerging consensus is that there are many different ways to accomplish this task.</p> <p>Over the past three years, we determined that in the fungal model organism, <em>Fusarium graminearum</em>, a combination of DNA- and protein-based signals are targeting PRC2 to regions that must be trimethylated at H3K27 for proper development and differentiation. We also found that specific point mutations in the catalytic subunit of PRC2, KMT6, cause chromatin region-specific lack of H2K27me3, suggesting that PRC2 can be finely tuned by the way the complex subunits interact with each other. Little was known about these processes in fungi when we started our project, thus we helped to close important knowledge gaps that may also accelerate progress in plant and animal systems.</p> <p>By a forward genetic selection scheme, we discovered two novel proteins (DIS2 and DIS10) as essential for normal H3K27 methylation in <em>Fusarium</em>,<em> </em>but apparently not in the relatively closely related fungus, <em>Neurospora crassa</em>. DIS2 appears to be a true ?on/off? switch for the generation of facultative heterochromatin, by binding to H3K4me3 (transcriptionally active) or H3K27me3 (transcriptionally silent) regions. DIS10 appears to be a regionally important transcription factor that controls H3K27me3 in only a few genomic regions. The discovery of these two proteins helped us to generate a model for maintenance of silencing and return to the active transcriptional state in fungi. In other work, we also found numerous genes or proteins that were defective in metabolizing or transport of the drug that was used as the antibiotic in the selection process. This included novel mutations in genes encoding small nucleolar RNAs that are involved in chemical modifications of the ribosome, and mutations in translation elongation factors.</p> <p>In collaboration with others, we discovered that H3K27me3 in the fungus <em>Zymoseptoria tritici </em>generates a metastable chromatin state that allows for higher mutation rates, a large number of chromosomal aberrations and translocations, without concomitant effects on transcription. Thus we were, for the first time, able to separate effects of loss of H3K27me3 on transcription from effects on genome stability. This discovery helps to explain phenotypes observed in mammals and other fungi, for example <em>Neurospora</em>. In these organisms, H3K27me3 moves into regions with the constitutive gene silencing mark, H3K9me3, if either the H3K9 methyltransferase or an adapter protein, HP1, are absent. One consequence of this movement are genotoxic effects, which we can now explain by metastable chromatin generated by&nbsp;the presence of H3K27me3.&nbsp;</p> <p>This grant allowed for several key activities that ensured broader impacts of this work outside of the broad scientific merit. Absence of H3K27me3 in <em>Fusarium</em> results in overexpression of ~20% of all genes, including many gene clusters that control the production of secondary metabolites. We discovered a dozen new metabolites from <em>F. graminearum</em>, including three compounds that are entirely new; some of these compounds may find pharmaceutical applications in the long run. This project was instrumental for the education of one current graduate student, and one post-doctoral trainee who is continuing his training in Brazil. Over twenty undergraduate researchers helped to carry out the genetic selection, generated libraries of histone H3 mutants that will be useful for the research community, and worked on understanding the function of DIS2 and DIS10. Many of these students were recruited from experiential learning lab courses (48 and 72 students, respectively) in which we generated DIS2 and DIS10 or histone H3 point mutants; the courses were designed to ensure student retention in STEM fields. Outreach activities included two middle and high school teacher courses on ?Fungi and the Production of Secondary Metabolites?.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 10/08/2019<br>      Modified by: Michael&nbsp;Freitag</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ How specific regions of chromosomes are activated for gene expression and subsequently turned off, and how this reversible ?silencing? is maintained is still not well understood. In many eukaryotes post-translational modifications of histone proteins seem to generate a code to help accomplish this task. One specific silencing histone modification, trimethylation of lysine 27 on histone H3 (H3K27me3) is catalyzed by a large protein complex, named PRC2 (Polycomb Repressive Complex 2). This complex is largely conserved in plants, fungi, and animals, yet how precisely PRC2 is targeted to specific chromatin regions is unclear. The emerging consensus is that there are many different ways to accomplish this task.  Over the past three years, we determined that in the fungal model organism, Fusarium graminearum, a combination of DNA- and protein-based signals are targeting PRC2 to regions that must be trimethylated at H3K27 for proper development and differentiation. We also found that specific point mutations in the catalytic subunit of PRC2, KMT6, cause chromatin region-specific lack of H2K27me3, suggesting that PRC2 can be finely tuned by the way the complex subunits interact with each other. Little was known about these processes in fungi when we started our project, thus we helped to close important knowledge gaps that may also accelerate progress in plant and animal systems.  By a forward genetic selection scheme, we discovered two novel proteins (DIS2 and DIS10) as essential for normal H3K27 methylation in Fusarium, but apparently not in the relatively closely related fungus, Neurospora crassa. DIS2 appears to be a true ?on/off? switch for the generation of facultative heterochromatin, by binding to H3K4me3 (transcriptionally active) or H3K27me3 (transcriptionally silent) regions. DIS10 appears to be a regionally important transcription factor that controls H3K27me3 in only a few genomic regions. The discovery of these two proteins helped us to generate a model for maintenance of silencing and return to the active transcriptional state in fungi. In other work, we also found numerous genes or proteins that were defective in metabolizing or transport of the drug that was used as the antibiotic in the selection process. This included novel mutations in genes encoding small nucleolar RNAs that are involved in chemical modifications of the ribosome, and mutations in translation elongation factors.  In collaboration with others, we discovered that H3K27me3 in the fungus Zymoseptoria tritici generates a metastable chromatin state that allows for higher mutation rates, a large number of chromosomal aberrations and translocations, without concomitant effects on transcription. Thus we were, for the first time, able to separate effects of loss of H3K27me3 on transcription from effects on genome stability. This discovery helps to explain phenotypes observed in mammals and other fungi, for example Neurospora. In these organisms, H3K27me3 moves into regions with the constitutive gene silencing mark, H3K9me3, if either the H3K9 methyltransferase or an adapter protein, HP1, are absent. One consequence of this movement are genotoxic effects, which we can now explain by metastable chromatin generated by the presence of H3K27me3.   This grant allowed for several key activities that ensured broader impacts of this work outside of the broad scientific merit. Absence of H3K27me3 in Fusarium results in overexpression of ~20% of all genes, including many gene clusters that control the production of secondary metabolites. We discovered a dozen new metabolites from F. graminearum, including three compounds that are entirely new; some of these compounds may find pharmaceutical applications in the long run. This project was instrumental for the education of one current graduate student, and one post-doctoral trainee who is continuing his training in Brazil. Over twenty undergraduate researchers helped to carry out the genetic selection, generated libraries of histone H3 mutants that will be useful for the research community, and worked on understanding the function of DIS2 and DIS10. Many of these students were recruited from experiential learning lab courses (48 and 72 students, respectively) in which we generated DIS2 and DIS10 or histone H3 point mutants; the courses were designed to ensure student retention in STEM fields. Outreach activities included two middle and high school teacher courses on ?Fungi and the Production of Secondary Metabolites?.       Last Modified: 10/08/2019       Submitted by: Michael Freitag]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
