<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>CRCNS: Community Dynamic Imaging of Corticothalamic Projections</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>10/01/2015</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>09/30/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>750000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>750000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>05020000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>CSE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>IIS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Information &amp; Intelligent Systems</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Kenneth Whang</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>kwhang@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032925149</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Massive amounts of brain imaging data open an unprecedented window into the structure and function of the brain, yet the tools to aid the understanding of the data are lagging. The main goal of this research project is to understand the dynamics of brain function, particularly in the auditory system, through global yet very high spatial and temporal resolution imaging techniques and using the state-of-the-art analytical tools developed for analysis of dynamic social networks. The interdisciplinary neuroscience and computational team, building on promising initial results, will work to adapt these tools developed for understanding human and animal behavior to the context of brain networks and the processes that happen over them. Using this innovative approach, the team will study a particular brain pathway that connects two brain regions that are critical for normal hearing.  The project will not only lead to a greater understanding of brain function, but will also bring a new technique to the neuroscience toolbox which may help other investigators to study network properties of the brain. Graduate students and postdocs in computer science and neuroscience will collaborate across disciplinary boundaries, building new scientific approaches and insights.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Top-down projections are ubiquitous in sensory systems and are poorly understood.  In the current proposal, a model descending system, the auditory corticothalamic projection in the mouse, will be examined.  The research team will take advantage of recent methodological developments in the study of this system and ask: What is the impact of corticothalamic projections on network interactions across populations of thalamic neurons?   To answer this, a novel dynamic network analysis method known as Community Dynamic Analysis, or CommDy, will be used to analyze imaging data from a brain slice preparation that retains connectivity between the auditory cortex, auditory thalamus, and other related structures in the mouse.  Both calcium imaging data and flavoprotein autofluoresence imaging data will be used for this analysis.  Since this study represents the first use of CommDy in neuroscience, validation studies will be done in a simplified brain slice preparation containing bilateral motor cortices and the corpus callosum.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>09/14/2015</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>09/14/2015</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.070</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1515587</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Robert</FirstName>
<LastName>Kenyon</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>V</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Robert V Kenyon</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>kenyon@uic.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>3129960450</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000109769</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/14/2015</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Tanya</FirstName>
<LastName>Berger-Wolf</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Tanya Berger-Wolf</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>berger-wolf.1@osu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6142926665</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000296514</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/14/2015</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Daniel</FirstName>
<LastName>Llano</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Daniel Llano</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>d-llano@illinois.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2172440740</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000618131</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/14/2015</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign</Name>
<CityName>Champaign</CityName>
<ZipCode>618207406</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2173332187</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1901 South First Street</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[Suite A]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Illinois</StateName>
<StateCode>IL</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>13</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>IL13</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>041544081</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF ILLINOIS</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>041544081</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign]]></Name>
<CityName>Urbana</CityName>
<StateCode>IL</StateCode>
<ZipCode>618013620</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[506 South Wright Street]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Illinois</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>13</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>IL13</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7327</Code>
<Text>CRCNS-Computation Neuroscience</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7495</Code>
<Text>Robust Intelligence</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>8624</Code>
<Text>IntgStrat Undst Neurl&amp;Cogn Sys</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7327</Code>
<Text>CRCNS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7495</Code>
<Text>ROBUST INTELLIGENCE</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8089</Code>
<Text>Understanding the Brain/Cognitive Scienc</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8091</Code>
<Text>BRAIN Initiative Res Support</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0115</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2015~750000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>There were three sets of scientific results that emerged from the funded project.</p> <p><span style="text-decoration: underline;">&nbsp;</span></p> <p><span style="text-decoration: underline;">1. Development of Community Dynamic Image Analysis (CommDy) and its applications:</span></p> <p>We validated a novel form of network analysis (CommDy) using an imaging technique known as flavoprotein autofluorescence in an in vitro brain slice preparation and then used it to examine aging-related changes in the cerebral cortex in brain slices and in vivo. In brain slices obtained from the auditory cortex of young or aged mice, we found that aging was associated with significant fragmentation of cortical networks. Once validated on the in vitro preparation, we applied CommDy to study the impact of aging on cortical networks in vivo. To do this, we imaged flavoprotein autofluorescence signals from the motor cortex of awake young or aged mice. We then applied the same CommDy technique and measured a series of network parameters. We again found a marked diminishment of network connectivity with aging. These data suggest that CommDy will serve as a powerful new tool to investigate differences in dynamic network properties in the brain. An additional aspect of this work is the development of new tools to visualize neural networks. We have developed several software packages to visualize the data (downloadable software: <a href="https://sites.google.com/site/dybrainviz/">https://sites.google.com/site/dybrainviz/</a>).</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p><span style="text-decoration: underline;">2. Application of network analytical methods to examine the thalamic reticular nucleus:</span></p> <p>We developed a computational model of the thalamocortical system to investigate the potential role of the thalamic reticular nucleus in mediating communication between thalamic nuclei. Part of this work involved supercomputing applications to run thousands of simulations of a network model whereby multiple synaptic parameters were systematically varied. Using these large-scale simulations, we found that particular synapses between the thalamic reticular nucleus and thalamocortical projection neurons were critical for the propagation of activity across the cortex, while other connections, such as gap junctions between thalamic reticular cells, actually diminished the spread of activity across the cortex.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p><span style="text-decoration: underline;">3. Development of novel classifiers to understand the impact of corticothalamic activity:</span></p> <p>Using a combination of in vivo and in vitro approaches, we found that the layer 6 corticothalamic projection, via its branches to the thalamic reticular nucleus, controls whether signals propagate from the thalamus to the cortex. Using machine learning approaches, we developed classifiers of pre-stimulus activity in the layer 6 corticothalamic neurons to determine what aspects of pre-stimulus activity controlled whether signals passed from the thalamus to the cortex. We found that pre-stimulus gamma-range oscillatory activity was the strongest predictor of whether a signal would pass from thalamus to cortex.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p><em>Broader Impacts:</em> Three computer science graduate students and two neuroscience postdoctoral researchers received cross-disciplinary training in dynamic network theory applied to neuroscience, and novel visualization tools. The Llano lab also continued its outreach to children via its yearly participation in the Brain Awareness Day activities that provide hands-on neuroscience presentations for grade-school children.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 12/23/2019<br>      Modified by: Daniel&nbsp;Llano</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ There were three sets of scientific results that emerged from the funded project.     1. Development of Community Dynamic Image Analysis (CommDy) and its applications:  We validated a novel form of network analysis (CommDy) using an imaging technique known as flavoprotein autofluorescence in an in vitro brain slice preparation and then used it to examine aging-related changes in the cerebral cortex in brain slices and in vivo. In brain slices obtained from the auditory cortex of young or aged mice, we found that aging was associated with significant fragmentation of cortical networks. Once validated on the in vitro preparation, we applied CommDy to study the impact of aging on cortical networks in vivo. To do this, we imaged flavoprotein autofluorescence signals from the motor cortex of awake young or aged mice. We then applied the same CommDy technique and measured a series of network parameters. We again found a marked diminishment of network connectivity with aging. These data suggest that CommDy will serve as a powerful new tool to investigate differences in dynamic network properties in the brain. An additional aspect of this work is the development of new tools to visualize neural networks. We have developed several software packages to visualize the data (downloadable software: https://sites.google.com/site/dybrainviz/).     2. Application of network analytical methods to examine the thalamic reticular nucleus:  We developed a computational model of the thalamocortical system to investigate the potential role of the thalamic reticular nucleus in mediating communication between thalamic nuclei. Part of this work involved supercomputing applications to run thousands of simulations of a network model whereby multiple synaptic parameters were systematically varied. Using these large-scale simulations, we found that particular synapses between the thalamic reticular nucleus and thalamocortical projection neurons were critical for the propagation of activity across the cortex, while other connections, such as gap junctions between thalamic reticular cells, actually diminished the spread of activity across the cortex.     3. Development of novel classifiers to understand the impact of corticothalamic activity:  Using a combination of in vivo and in vitro approaches, we found that the layer 6 corticothalamic projection, via its branches to the thalamic reticular nucleus, controls whether signals propagate from the thalamus to the cortex. Using machine learning approaches, we developed classifiers of pre-stimulus activity in the layer 6 corticothalamic neurons to determine what aspects of pre-stimulus activity controlled whether signals passed from the thalamus to the cortex. We found that pre-stimulus gamma-range oscillatory activity was the strongest predictor of whether a signal would pass from thalamus to cortex.     Broader Impacts: Three computer science graduate students and two neuroscience postdoctoral researchers received cross-disciplinary training in dynamic network theory applied to neuroscience, and novel visualization tools. The Llano lab also continued its outreach to children via its yearly participation in the Brain Awareness Day activities that provide hands-on neuroscience presentations for grade-school children.          Last Modified: 12/23/2019       Submitted by: Daniel Llano]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
