<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>EAPSI:Effect of Humic Substances on Ammonium Oxidation Coupled to Iron Reduction in Paddy Soils</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>06/01/2015</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2016</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>5070.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>5070</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Fellowship Award</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>01090000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>O/D</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Office Of The Director</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>OISE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Office Of Internatl Science &amp;Engineering</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Anne Emig</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>aemig@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927241</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Humic substances could have a significant impact on iron cycling in paddy soils, resulting in impacts on nitrogen loss and retention in terrestrial ecosystems. This project will determine the effect of humic substances on the process of iron reduction coupled to ammonium oxidation and subsequent nitrogen loss in paddy soils. The abundance of humic substances in soils indicates the significant potential impact of humic substances on iron cycling and on nitrogen loss from paddy soils in China, where one-third of the world?s synthesized nitrogen fertilizer is produced. To determine the impact of humic substances on iron and nitrogen cycling in paddy soils, humic substance, iron, and nitrogen cycling will be stimulated in paddy soils and nitrogen loss will be measured. In addition, the stimulated microbial community will be analyzed to improve the understanding of the microorganisms responsible for nitrogen loss and retention and iron cycling in terrestrial ecosystems. This project will be completed in collaboration with Dr. Yong-Guan Zhu at the Institute for Urban Environment, Chinese Academy of Sciences. Dr. Zhu has extensive experience analyzing paddy soil iron and nitrogen cycling and microbial communities. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The stimulated microbial community will be analyzed by stimulating iron reduction coupled to ammonium oxidation in paddy soils and employing culture-independent (sequencing-by-synthesis of 16S rRNA gene sequences) and culture-dependent (soil enrichment followed by colony isolation) microbial community analysis of the paddy soils. The proposed research will improve the mechanistic understanding of terrestrial nitrogen and iron cycling and estimations of global nitrogen loss. This NSF EAPSI award supports the research of a U.S. graduate student and is funded in collaboration with the Chinese Ministry of Science and Technology.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/18/2015</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/18/2015</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.079</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1515326</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Olivia</FirstName>
<LastName>Healy</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Olivia Healy</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress/>
<PI_PHON>6824385277</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000683118</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/18/2015</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Healy                   Olivia</Name>
<CityName>Lincoln</CityName>
<ZipCode>685083358</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber/>
<StreetAddress/>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Nebraska</StateName>
<StateCode>NE</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NE01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM/>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME/>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Healy                   Olivia]]></Name>
<CityName>Lincoln</CityName>
<StateCode>NE</StateCode>
<ZipCode>685083358</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Nebraska</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NE01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7316</Code>
<Text>EAPSI</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>5978</Code>
<Text>EAST ASIA AND PACIFIC PROGRAM</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7316</Code>
<Text>EAPSI</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9200</Code>
<Text>US CHINA COOP IN BASIC SCIENCE</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0115</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2015~5070</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Humic substances could have a significant impact on iron cycling in paddy soils, resulting in impacts on nitrogen loss and retention in terrestrial ecosystems. The objective of this project were to determine the effect of humic substances on the process of metal reduction coupled to ammonium oxidation and subsequent nitrogen loss in paddy soils. The abundance of humic substances in soils indicates the significant potential impact of humic substances on metal cycling and on nitrogen loss from paddy soils in China, where one-third of the world&rsquo;s synthesized nitrogen fertilizer is produced. To determine the impact of humic substances on metal and nitrogen cycling in paddy soils, humic substances, metals, and nitrogen cycling were stimulated in paddy soils and nitrogen loss was measured. This project was completed in collaboration with Dr. Yong-Guan Zhu at the Institute for Urban Environment, Chinese Academy of Sciences.</p> <p>The potential for humic substances and metals to impact nitrogen loss through metal and nitrogen cycling in paddy soils was demonstrated though increased stimulation of metal cycling and nitrogen loss in the presence of humic substance analogues. The results of this research will be used to improve the mechanistic understanding of terrestrial nitrogen and metal cycling and estimations of global nitrogen loss. Relationships developed over the course of the project will be utilized in future international collaborations.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 03/15/2016<br>      Modified by: Olivia&nbsp;Healy</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Humic substances could have a significant impact on iron cycling in paddy soils, resulting in impacts on nitrogen loss and retention in terrestrial ecosystems. The objective of this project were to determine the effect of humic substances on the process of metal reduction coupled to ammonium oxidation and subsequent nitrogen loss in paddy soils. The abundance of humic substances in soils indicates the significant potential impact of humic substances on metal cycling and on nitrogen loss from paddy soils in China, where one-third of the worldÆs synthesized nitrogen fertilizer is produced. To determine the impact of humic substances on metal and nitrogen cycling in paddy soils, humic substances, metals, and nitrogen cycling were stimulated in paddy soils and nitrogen loss was measured. This project was completed in collaboration with Dr. Yong-Guan Zhu at the Institute for Urban Environment, Chinese Academy of Sciences.  The potential for humic substances and metals to impact nitrogen loss through metal and nitrogen cycling in paddy soils was demonstrated though increased stimulation of metal cycling and nitrogen loss in the presence of humic substance analogues. The results of this research will be used to improve the mechanistic understanding of terrestrial nitrogen and metal cycling and estimations of global nitrogen loss. Relationships developed over the course of the project will be utilized in future international collaborations.          Last Modified: 03/15/2016       Submitted by: Olivia Healy]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
