<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>EAPSI:The Evolution and Development of Extreme Weapons: Have Weapons Reached their Limit?</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>06/01/2015</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2016</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>5000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>5000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Fellowship Award</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>01090000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>O/D</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Office Of The Director</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>OISE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Office Of Internatl Science &amp;Engineering</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Anne Emig</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>aemig@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927241</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Animal weapons represent some of the world's most incredible morphology. Traits such as the massive antlers of elk, or the incredible tusks of elephants, occur in thousands of animal species. But despite this diversity of form, one thing remains constant across these traits: those individuals with the largest weapons win the most fights and, as a result, are expected to have the highest reproductive success. This should lead to strong directional selection for large weapons. However, when biologists go out in the wild and quantify how selection is acting on these weapons, this is not what they find. Instead, animal weapons are often characterized by weak net selection for large weapons. Contrary to what is expected, males with the largest weapons do not have the highest mating success. Why? In this award, potential limits to extreme weapons are explored through analyses of metabolism, biomechanics, and developmental mechanisms of exaggerated growth in frog-legged beetles. This work will be conducted in collaboration with Dr. Teruyuki Niimi at the National Institute for Basic Biology in Okazaki, Japan, one of the leading researchers in the field of exaggerated growth and animal weapons. This work will help advance understanding of a fundamantal puzzle in evolutionary developmental biology and enhance communication of basic science in public outreach on this strangely beautiful species in collaboration with a local children's museum. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Using the non-model system, frog legged beetles, two potential limits to extreme weapons will be examined. These are the metabolic costs associated with large, muscle filled weapons, and the biomechanical limits weapons experience as they get very large. These factors will be measured directly in the field to determine how they can curb the reproductive benefits associated with bearing large weapons. This work will be paired with genetic analyses focusing on the developmental basis of extreme growth in animal weapons. RNA knockdowns will be performed on candidate growth pathways to elucidate how exaggerated weapons develop and to gain a better understanding of potential targets of selection in extreme weapon systems. This NSF EAPSI award supports the research of a U.S. graduate student and is funded in collaboration with the Japan Society for the Promotion of Science.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/17/2015</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/17/2015</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.079</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1515085</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Devin</FirstName>
<LastName>O'Brien</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>M</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Devin M O'Brien</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress/>
<PI_PHON>5183662831</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000681065</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/17/2015</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>O'Brien                 Devin          M</Name>
<CityName>Missoula</CityName>
<ZipCode>598023809</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber/>
<StreetAddress/>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Montana</StateName>
<StateCode>MT</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>00</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MT00</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM/>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME/>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[O'Brien                 Devin          M]]></Name>
<CityName>Missoula</CityName>
<StateCode>MT</StateCode>
<ZipCode>598023809</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Montana</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>00</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MT00</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7316</Code>
<Text>EAPSI</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>5921</Code>
<Text>JAPAN</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>5978</Code>
<Text>EAST ASIA AND PACIFIC PROGRAM</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7316</Code>
<Text>EAPSI</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0115</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2015~5000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>EAPSI: The Evolution and Development of Extreme Weapons: Have Weapons Reached their Limit?&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>Sexually selected traits represent some of the earth&rsquo;s most stunning morphologies. Beautiful ornaments (like the long trains of peacocks) and harrowing weapons (like the antlers of elk) have captivated biologists for centuries. However, the wonder of these traits goes well beyond aesthetics. These structures are massive, comprising large portions of an individual&rsquo;s body mass and often exceeding their body length. The bizarre shape and immense size of these traits has prompted numerous studies of their evolution, but a bias exists. Despite the large body of work explicitly measuring how sexual selection acts on ornaments of female choice (one set of sexually selected traits, where females mate with males based on the quality of that trait, <em>e.g.</em> the elaborate colors of some birds), information regarding how sexual selection acts on weapons (another set of sexually selected traits used in male-male combat, like horns, antlers, and tusks) is almost nonexistent. Yes, both ornaments of female choice and weapons of male-male competition fall under the category of sexual selection, but they are drastically different. For example, to attract a mate, ornaments of female choice must look good to females, but that is it. They rarely function under physically strenuous conditions. Weapons are different. Each time a weapon is used, it is put to the test. The weapon is placed under immense physical strain each time the bearer engages in male-male competition. Furthermore, the few studies that have explicitly addressed the evolution of animal weapons deliver surprising results. Large weapons are often critical to an individual&rsquo;s fighting success, yet the net effect of selection on weapon size appears to be weak. That is, animals with the largest weapons have the highest fighting success, but not necessarily the highest mating success. With funding form the NSF EAPSI grant, I worked with with Dr. Teruyuki Niimi (National Institute of Basic Biology, Okazaki, Japan) to explore this discontinuity and answer the question of why we see weak net selection for animal weapons in modern populations.</p> <p>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; By measuring the mating success of frog legged beetles over the course of one complete breeding season (June-August) I was able to obtain an explicit estimation of how sexual selection is acting on big animal weapons. <strong>My results suggest that frog legged beetles are experiencing stabilizing selection for</strong> <strong>proportional weapon sizes</strong>. That is, those animals that have weapon sizes proportional to their body size, regardless of absolute weapon size, have the highest mating success in the population. This greatly differs form what we expect based on our understanding of ornaments of female choice, where we typically see strong selection for extremely large ornaments. This surprising result is likely driven by the need for animal weapons to function in the context of battle, unlike ornaments of female choice. If weapons were to become too large, they may actually become weaker due to the inability of muscle growth the keep up with increasingly long weapon sizes. These weak weapons would not perform well in the context of animal fights, and, as a result, their bearer would produce fewer offspring than their rivals. Further work will strive to explicitly identify the causes of this pattern of selection.&nbsp;&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 06/01/2016<br>      Modified by: Devin&nbsp;M&nbsp;O'brien</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ EAPSI: The Evolution and Development of Extreme Weapons: Have Weapons Reached their Limit?      Sexually selected traits represent some of the earthÆs most stunning morphologies. Beautiful ornaments (like the long trains of peacocks) and harrowing weapons (like the antlers of elk) have captivated biologists for centuries. However, the wonder of these traits goes well beyond aesthetics. These structures are massive, comprising large portions of an individualÆs body mass and often exceeding their body length. The bizarre shape and immense size of these traits has prompted numerous studies of their evolution, but a bias exists. Despite the large body of work explicitly measuring how sexual selection acts on ornaments of female choice (one set of sexually selected traits, where females mate with males based on the quality of that trait, e.g. the elaborate colors of some birds), information regarding how sexual selection acts on weapons (another set of sexually selected traits used in male-male combat, like horns, antlers, and tusks) is almost nonexistent. Yes, both ornaments of female choice and weapons of male-male competition fall under the category of sexual selection, but they are drastically different. For example, to attract a mate, ornaments of female choice must look good to females, but that is it. They rarely function under physically strenuous conditions. Weapons are different. Each time a weapon is used, it is put to the test. The weapon is placed under immense physical strain each time the bearer engages in male-male competition. Furthermore, the few studies that have explicitly addressed the evolution of animal weapons deliver surprising results. Large weapons are often critical to an individualÆs fighting success, yet the net effect of selection on weapon size appears to be weak. That is, animals with the largest weapons have the highest fighting success, but not necessarily the highest mating success. With funding form the NSF EAPSI grant, I worked with with Dr. Teruyuki Niimi (National Institute of Basic Biology, Okazaki, Japan) to explore this discontinuity and answer the question of why we see weak net selection for animal weapons in modern populations.              By measuring the mating success of frog legged beetles over the course of one complete breeding season (June-August) I was able to obtain an explicit estimation of how sexual selection is acting on big animal weapons. My results suggest that frog legged beetles are experiencing stabilizing selection for proportional weapon sizes. That is, those animals that have weapon sizes proportional to their body size, regardless of absolute weapon size, have the highest mating success in the population. This greatly differs form what we expect based on our understanding of ornaments of female choice, where we typically see strong selection for extremely large ornaments. This surprising result is likely driven by the need for animal weapons to function in the context of battle, unlike ornaments of female choice. If weapons were to become too large, they may actually become weaker due to the inability of muscle growth the keep up with increasingly long weapon sizes. These weak weapons would not perform well in the context of animal fights, and, as a result, their bearer would produce fewer offspring than their rivals. Further work will strive to explicitly identify the causes of this pattern of selection.            Last Modified: 06/01/2016       Submitted by: Devin M O'brien]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
