<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>EAPSI:Typhoon Impacts on Chemical Weathering in a Mountainous Island Watershed in Taiwan</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>06/01/2015</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2016</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>5070.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>5070</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Fellowship Award</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>01090000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>O/D</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Office Of The Director</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>OISE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Office Of Internatl Science &amp;Engineering</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Anne Emig</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>aemig@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927241</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>High standing islands such as Taiwan represent a major source of sediment and carbon transport to the oceans, but sparse data exist for chemical weathering rates and weathering sources in these terrains. Almost no data exist on the impact of typhoons and other extreme weather on chemical weathering rates. This award supports research that will determine chemical weathering rates within the Gaoping River watershed, and how they changed in response to Typhoon Mindulle (2004). It will also use several geochemical tools to constrain the sources of chemical weathering to the river, and how these sources may change in response to a typhoon. This research will be conducted under the supervision of Dr. Chen-Feng You at National Cheng Kung University, an expert in mass spectrometry techniques necessary for analysis, and an ideal collaborator for this study. Chemical weathering is a major control on atmospheric carbon dioxide levels over geological time, and high standing islands have been shown to have some of the highest weathering rates worldwide, yet the role of local weather in the global carbon cycle is poorly understood. This study will add new insight into the long term controls of earth?s climate and carbon cycle.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Determining typhoon impacts on chemical weathering will primarily be accomplished through geochemical analysis of river waters collected during Typhoon Mindulle. Different tributaries to the Gaoping River drain rocks with distinct strontium (Sr) isotope and elemental compositions. Thermal Ionization Mass Spectrometry will be used to determine Sr isotope ratios, and Ion Chromatography will be used to determine major ion composition of the river waters. These analyses will be used to determine the relative weathering inputs of different lithologies of the watershed. Dissolved silica is commonly used as a proxy for chemical weathering, and will be measured and used in conjunction with historical stream gauge records to determine total chemical weathering input into the river system over the course of the storm. These analyses will be compared to similar analyses conducted by Dr. You during normal dry and wet season flow in the Gaoping watershed to determine changes attributable to the typhoon. This NSF EAPSI award is funded in collaboration with the Ministry of Science and Technology of Taiwan.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/25/2015</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/25/2015</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.079</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1515319</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Kevin</FirstName>
<LastName>Meyer</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>J</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Kevin J Meyer</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress/>
<PI_PHON>2104788218</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000684226</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/25/2015</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Meyer                   Kevin          J</Name>
<CityName>Columbus</CityName>
<ZipCode>432122208</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber/>
<StreetAddress/>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Ohio</StateName>
<StateCode>OH</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>OH03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM/>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME/>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Meyer                   Kevin          J]]></Name>
<CityName>Columbus</CityName>
<StateCode>OH</StateCode>
<ZipCode>432122208</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Ohio</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>OH03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7316</Code>
<Text>EAPSI</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>5924</Code>
<Text>TAIWAN</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>5978</Code>
<Text>EAST ASIA AND PACIFIC PROGRAM</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7316</Code>
<Text>EAPSI</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0115</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2015~5070</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Water helps break down rock by dissolving its minerals in a process  called chemical weathing. Many of these minerals (known as silicate  minerals) take carbon dioxide out of the atmosphere when they dissolve,  and this is a primary control on global climate over millions of years.  Mountainous islands like Taiwan have some of the highest global chemical  weathering rates, and Taiwan is hit by an average of four typhoons each  year. Typhoons cause intense physical weathering, and physical  weathering exposes new mineral surfaces for chemical weathering to occur  on. However, little prior research has been conducted on how these  massive storms affect silicate weathering rates. No known prior research  has looked at the weathering sources and how these change during a  typhoon.</p> <p>This study analyzed the dissolved silica concentration in  river water collected during Typhoon Mindulle in 2004. Dissolved silica  indicates the total amount silicate weathering that has occured. By  knowing the amount of silica in the water and multiplying by the river's  flow rate, one can tell the total movement of silica through a river  through time. This helps to quantify the total carbon dioxide drawdown  from the atmosphere from silicate weathering, where a higher dissolved  silica flux indicates more CO2 drawdown. This study also used strontium  isotope analysis to determine the sources of weathering. Strontium  isotopes aren't affected by surface chemical reactions, only by the  source they come from. Therefore, by looking at the ratio of different  strontium isotopes, one can determine source mixing.</p> <p>This study  found that the dissolved silica flux drastically increases during storm  water flow. This flux is 20 to 50 times higher per second than normal flow  conditions. Since these storm flows can last for several days, typhoons  may represent a major cause of carbon dioxide uptake from the  atmosphere on mountainous islands over geological time. It's possible  that a single typhoon may move as much dissolved silica to the ocean as  several months of normal conditions.</p> <p>The strontium isotope analysis suggests chemical weathering source mixing between the main silicate minerals that make up the bulk of the rocks, and small amounts of carbonate minerals (~3%) inside the rock. It also suggests that there is a reservoir in the soil pore water that is highly reflective of the silicate mineral endmember, and that this reservoir is flushed into the river system during heavy rainfall. At the start of the storm, the isotope composition moves rapidly toward the silicate source, reflecting the flushing of this soil water by the rainfall. However, this source is depleted as the storm continues so the composition moves toward the carbonate mineral end-member. Three periods of intense rainfall also match well with increasing silicate mineral contributions from pulsing of soil water into the river.</p> <p>This study suggests that global contribution to carbon uptake from the atmosphere by storm derived silicate weathering is likely underestimated, and that additional studies of other extreme weather (hurricanes, monsoons, extreme flooding) on chemical weathering rates are needed to constrain this poorly understood climate dynamic. It also suggests that not all dissolved silica flux may be associated with weathering during the Typhoon, and that storage of dissolved chemical weathering products between storms may be released during the next storm.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 03/14/2016<br>      Modified by: Kevin&nbsp;J&nbsp;Meyer</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Image         </div> <div class="galControls onePhoto" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div...]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Water helps break down rock by dissolving its minerals in a process  called chemical weathing. Many of these minerals (known as silicate  minerals) take carbon dioxide out of the atmosphere when they dissolve,  and this is a primary control on global climate over millions of years.  Mountainous islands like Taiwan have some of the highest global chemical  weathering rates, and Taiwan is hit by an average of four typhoons each  year. Typhoons cause intense physical weathering, and physical  weathering exposes new mineral surfaces for chemical weathering to occur  on. However, little prior research has been conducted on how these  massive storms affect silicate weathering rates. No known prior research  has looked at the weathering sources and how these change during a  typhoon.  This study analyzed the dissolved silica concentration in  river water collected during Typhoon Mindulle in 2004. Dissolved silica  indicates the total amount silicate weathering that has occured. By  knowing the amount of silica in the water and multiplying by the river's  flow rate, one can tell the total movement of silica through a river  through time. This helps to quantify the total carbon dioxide drawdown  from the atmosphere from silicate weathering, where a higher dissolved  silica flux indicates more CO2 drawdown. This study also used strontium  isotope analysis to determine the sources of weathering. Strontium  isotopes aren't affected by surface chemical reactions, only by the  source they come from. Therefore, by looking at the ratio of different  strontium isotopes, one can determine source mixing.  This study  found that the dissolved silica flux drastically increases during storm  water flow. This flux is 20 to 50 times higher per second than normal flow  conditions. Since these storm flows can last for several days, typhoons  may represent a major cause of carbon dioxide uptake from the  atmosphere on mountainous islands over geological time. It's possible  that a single typhoon may move as much dissolved silica to the ocean as  several months of normal conditions.  The strontium isotope analysis suggests chemical weathering source mixing between the main silicate minerals that make up the bulk of the rocks, and small amounts of carbonate minerals (~3%) inside the rock. It also suggests that there is a reservoir in the soil pore water that is highly reflective of the silicate mineral endmember, and that this reservoir is flushed into the river system during heavy rainfall. At the start of the storm, the isotope composition moves rapidly toward the silicate source, reflecting the flushing of this soil water by the rainfall. However, this source is depleted as the storm continues so the composition moves toward the carbonate mineral end-member. Three periods of intense rainfall also match well with increasing silicate mineral contributions from pulsing of soil water into the river.  This study suggests that global contribution to carbon uptake from the atmosphere by storm derived silicate weathering is likely underestimated, and that additional studies of other extreme weather (hurricanes, monsoons, extreme flooding) on chemical weathering rates are needed to constrain this poorly understood climate dynamic. It also suggests that not all dissolved silica flux may be associated with weathering during the Typhoon, and that storage of dissolved chemical weathering products between storms may be released during the next storm.       Last Modified: 03/14/2016       Submitted by: Kevin J Meyer]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
