<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Building Cybersecurity Workforce and Capacity through Enhancing Defending Skill Sets</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>10/01/2015</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>09/30/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>348732.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>348732</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>11010000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>EHR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DGE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Graduate Education</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Victor Piotrowski</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>vpiotrow@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032925141</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The "Building Cybersecurity Workforce and Capacity through Enhancing Defending Skill Sets" project at Texas Tech University (TTU), in partnership with the Sandia National Lab (SNL), will investigate attacking/defending strategies employed by security professionals and experts.  The skillsets that will be identified by this project will be incorporated into instructional modules and materials that will provide students and professionals with the skills required to defend against cyberattacks.  This research project will introduce a simulated cyber battlefield that will consist of authentic challenges, scenarios, and strategies.  This authentic and engaging learning platform will allow instructors to teach the basic and advanced topics of cybersecurity to students using a realistic scenario-based approach. The cybersecurity attack and defend scenarios will be integrated into an undergraduate course curriculum that will support student learning and will enhance the effectiveness of teaching security related concepts and cyber defense techniques.  TTU and SNL have a demonstrated reputation of reaching underserved minority populations with innovative and advanced educational programs.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The project will consist of four major activities: (1) Conduct a set of task analyses to determine the skillsets the cybersecurity professionals employ, (2) Develop a set of instructional modules and materials based on the task analysis, (3) Design and offer scenario and competition-based workshops specifically tailored for undergraduate students, (4) Offer a two-day summer workshop for teachers and educators from colleges and universities with the aim of broadening the impacts.  The collaboration between three different departments with complementary expertise will allow researchers to utilize and share resources and expertise resulting in the development of curricular materials that will be based on best practices in cybersecurity.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>09/21/2015</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>09/21/2015</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.076</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1516636</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Akbar</FirstName>
<LastName>Siami Namin</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Akbar Siami Namin</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>akbar.namin@ttu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>8067423884</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000551307</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/21/2015</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Fethi</FirstName>
<LastName>Inan</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>A</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Fethi A Inan</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>fethi.inan@ttu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>8067423884</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000567639</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/21/2015</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Keith</FirstName>
<LastName>Jones</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>S</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Keith S Jones</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>keith.s.jones@ttu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>8068348745</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000588843</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/21/2015</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Texas Tech University</Name>
<CityName>Lubbock</CityName>
<ZipCode>794091035</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>8067423884</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>349 Administration Bldg</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Texas</StateName>
<StateCode>TX</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>19</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>TX19</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>041367053</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>TEXAS TECH UNIVERSITY SYSTEM</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>041367053</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Texas Tech University]]></Name>
<CityName>Lubbock</CityName>
<StateCode>TX</StateCode>
<ZipCode>794093104</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[Box: 43104]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Texas</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>19</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>TX19</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1668</Code>
<Text>CYBERCORPS: SCHLAR FOR SER</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7434</Code>
<Text>CNCI</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9178</Code>
<Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9179</Code>
<Text>GRADUATE INVOLVEMENT</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>SMET</Code>
<Text>SCIENCE, MATH, ENG &amp; TECH EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0415</Code>
<Name>NSF Education &amp; Human Resource</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040106</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2015~348732</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The objectives of this project were to (1) understand the cognitive work that cyber security professionals perform, (2) develop a set of instructional modules targeting the identified knowledge, skills, and abilities (KSAs) as their learning objectives, and (3) offer a professional development workshop for cyber security educators with the goal of (i) evaluating the course modules, and (ii) encouraging the participants to adopt the developed instructional modules in their classrooms.</p> <p>I) To accomplish the first objective, the research team employed several techniques: (1) they first interviewed cyber security experts from Sandia National Laboratories, the research partner of this project, with the goal of understanding the challenges associated with interviewing cyber security professionals about their work. The insights gleaned from those interviews were published in the Proceedings of the Human Factors and Ergonomics Society Annual Meeting; (2) taking into account what was learned from those interviews, the research team designed and executed a cognitive task analysis about how cyber security professionals develop attack scenarios. To do so, the research team attended professional hacking conferences (e.g., DEF CON and Black Hat) and recruited professional hackers to describe how they would develop hacking solutions for the provided attack scenarios. Analysis of their responses shed light on the cognitive work professional cyber attackers perform when they launch attacks. Specifically, attackers follow a multi-stage methodology to launch attacks including (i) reconnaissance, (ii) probing and scanning, and (iii) exploitation; (3) the research team also designed and executed two sets of interviews to understand cyber security professionals' knowledge, skills, and abilities (KSAs). To do so, the research team again attended professional hacking conferences and had cyber security professionals rate how important KSAs, derived from the National Initiative for Cybersecurity Education (NICE) framework, are to their work. The first set of interviews concerned KSAs that comprised the core of cyber defense. Participants rated 15 of these KSAs as being of higher-than-neutral importance. Overall, the data suggested that KSAs related to networks, vulnerabilities, programming, and interpersonal communication should be given higher priority when designing cyber security curricular. The results were published in the Association for Computing Machinery's (ACM) Transactions on Computing Education (TOCE). The second set of interviews concerned KSAs that were specific types of cyber defense work.&nbsp; Participants rated communication and other non-technical skills as being very important for all cyber defense jobs, and rated network and command line knowledge as most important for Computer Network Defense Analysts, and knowledge of vulnerabilities and threats are most important for Vulnerability Assessment and Management professionals. The results are under review for publication.</p> <p>II) To accomplish the second objective, the research team developed a set of course modules focusing on "Digital Forensics."&nbsp; The course is structured into five modules of (i) Reverse Engineering, (ii) Disk Forensics, (iii) Memory Forensics, (iv) Network Forensics, and (v) Android Forensics. Accordingly, for each module a set of lecture notes, hands-on experiences, and tutorials were created. The course was offered three times as an elective graduate level course with on-campus and distance sections. The lecture materials along with the artifacts and hands-on experiences are posted in a GitHub repository for public use. The instructor of the course also added additional materials and hands-on experience targeting "Mobile Forensics" and in particular the Android operating system. The courses were well received by the students. Most of the students stated that they had never taken any course related to digital forensics and it was a great experience for learning not only theoretical but also practical aspects of computer security in the context of digital forensics. A visualization and educational tool for malware analysis was developed and the tool is published at the ACM SIGSOFT International Symposium on Software Testing and Analysis (ISSTA). The results of the course evaluation are under submission for publication.</p> <p>III) To accomplish the third objective, the research team recruited over 16 cyber security educators from 2-year and 4-year colleges. During the 3 days of the workshop, the research team, in partnership with a team from the Sandia National Laboratories, presented (i) the findings of the research, (ii) the instructional modules and course materials along with hands-on experiences and practical sessions, and (iii) a practical session and hands-on experience with TracerFire (the cyber security training platform) developed by Sandia National Laboratories. In particular, the participants liked the materials presented by the Sandia team on TracerFire where each security incident is framed in a form of case that needs to be solved through team member collaboration. The evaluator of the project also conducted several interviews and surveys and collected useful information with the goal of (i) identifying the challenges professional teachers face when introducing a course in cyber security, and (ii) improving the course materials. The results of the workshop evaluation and survey questions are under submission for publication.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 12/25/2019<br>      Modified by: Akbar&nbsp;Siami Namin</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Images (<span id="selectedPhoto0">1</span> of <span class="totalNumber"></span>)           </div> <div class="galControls" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1516636/1516636_10401240_1577027723359_ScreenShot2019-12-22at9.09.44AM--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1516636/1516636_10401240_1577027723359_ScreenShot2019-12-22at9.09.44AM--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Results of the NICE KSA Questions"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1516636/1516636_10401240_1577027723359_ScreenShot2019-12-22at9.09.44AM--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Results of the NICE KSA Questions"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Results of the survey questions on identifying the importance of KSAs listed by the National Initiative for Cybersecurity Education (NICE) Workforce Framework</div> <div class="imageCredit">Akbar Siami Namin</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Akbar&nbsp;Siami Namin</div> <div class="imageTitle">Results of the NICE KSA Questions</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1516636/1516636_10401240_1577027989645_ScreenShot2019-12-22at9.19.07AM--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1516636/1516636_10401240_1577027989645_ScreenShot2019-12-22at9.19.07AM--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Results of Open-Ended Questions about Soft-Skills"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1516636/1516636_10401240_1577027989645_ScreenShot2019-12-22at9.19.07AM--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Results of Open-Ended Questions about Soft-Skills"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Soft skills reported in order of most to least frequent responses.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Akbar Siami Namin</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Akbar&nbsp;Siami Namin</div> <div class="imageTitle">Results of Open-Ended Questions about Soft-Skills</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1516636/1516636_10401240_1577028152023_ScreenShot2019-12-22at9.21.13AM--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1516636/1516636_10401240_1577028152023_ScreenShot2019-12-22at9.21.13AM--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Cybersecurity Tools Important for Professionals Cyber Security Experts"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1516636/1516636_10401240_1577028152023_ScreenShot2019-12-22at9.21.13AM--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Cybersecurity Tools Important for Professionals Cyber Security Experts"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Responses mentioned more than twice are reported. n refers to the number of respondents who mentioned they used that tool (or no tool) to accomplishthe cybersecurity task.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Akbar Siami Namin</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Akbar&nbsp;Siami Namin</div> <div class="imageTitle">Cybersecurity Tools Important for Professionals Cyber Security Experts</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The objectives of this project were to (1) understand the cognitive work that cyber security professionals perform, (2) develop a set of instructional modules targeting the identified knowledge, skills, and abilities (KSAs) as their learning objectives, and (3) offer a professional development workshop for cyber security educators with the goal of (i) evaluating the course modules, and (ii) encouraging the participants to adopt the developed instructional modules in their classrooms.  I) To accomplish the first objective, the research team employed several techniques: (1) they first interviewed cyber security experts from Sandia National Laboratories, the research partner of this project, with the goal of understanding the challenges associated with interviewing cyber security professionals about their work. The insights gleaned from those interviews were published in the Proceedings of the Human Factors and Ergonomics Society Annual Meeting; (2) taking into account what was learned from those interviews, the research team designed and executed a cognitive task analysis about how cyber security professionals develop attack scenarios. To do so, the research team attended professional hacking conferences (e.g., DEF CON and Black Hat) and recruited professional hackers to describe how they would develop hacking solutions for the provided attack scenarios. Analysis of their responses shed light on the cognitive work professional cyber attackers perform when they launch attacks. Specifically, attackers follow a multi-stage methodology to launch attacks including (i) reconnaissance, (ii) probing and scanning, and (iii) exploitation; (3) the research team also designed and executed two sets of interviews to understand cyber security professionals' knowledge, skills, and abilities (KSAs). To do so, the research team again attended professional hacking conferences and had cyber security professionals rate how important KSAs, derived from the National Initiative for Cybersecurity Education (NICE) framework, are to their work. The first set of interviews concerned KSAs that comprised the core of cyber defense. Participants rated 15 of these KSAs as being of higher-than-neutral importance. Overall, the data suggested that KSAs related to networks, vulnerabilities, programming, and interpersonal communication should be given higher priority when designing cyber security curricular. The results were published in the Association for Computing Machinery's (ACM) Transactions on Computing Education (TOCE). The second set of interviews concerned KSAs that were specific types of cyber defense work.  Participants rated communication and other non-technical skills as being very important for all cyber defense jobs, and rated network and command line knowledge as most important for Computer Network Defense Analysts, and knowledge of vulnerabilities and threats are most important for Vulnerability Assessment and Management professionals. The results are under review for publication.  II) To accomplish the second objective, the research team developed a set of course modules focusing on "Digital Forensics."  The course is structured into five modules of (i) Reverse Engineering, (ii) Disk Forensics, (iii) Memory Forensics, (iv) Network Forensics, and (v) Android Forensics. Accordingly, for each module a set of lecture notes, hands-on experiences, and tutorials were created. The course was offered three times as an elective graduate level course with on-campus and distance sections. The lecture materials along with the artifacts and hands-on experiences are posted in a GitHub repository for public use. The instructor of the course also added additional materials and hands-on experience targeting "Mobile Forensics" and in particular the Android operating system. The courses were well received by the students. Most of the students stated that they had never taken any course related to digital forensics and it was a great experience for learning not only theoretical but also practical aspects of computer security in the context of digital forensics. A visualization and educational tool for malware analysis was developed and the tool is published at the ACM SIGSOFT International Symposium on Software Testing and Analysis (ISSTA). The results of the course evaluation are under submission for publication.  III) To accomplish the third objective, the research team recruited over 16 cyber security educators from 2-year and 4-year colleges. During the 3 days of the workshop, the research team, in partnership with a team from the Sandia National Laboratories, presented (i) the findings of the research, (ii) the instructional modules and course materials along with hands-on experiences and practical sessions, and (iii) a practical session and hands-on experience with TracerFire (the cyber security training platform) developed by Sandia National Laboratories. In particular, the participants liked the materials presented by the Sandia team on TracerFire where each security incident is framed in a form of case that needs to be solved through team member collaboration. The evaluator of the project also conducted several interviews and surveys and collected useful information with the goal of (i) identifying the challenges professional teachers face when introducing a course in cyber security, and (ii) improving the course materials. The results of the workshop evaluation and survey questions are under submission for publication.       Last Modified: 12/25/2019       Submitted by: Akbar Siami Namin]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
