<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Analysis of Multidimensional Problems for Nonclassical Shocks and Classical Shock Reflection</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2015</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>140000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>140000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DMS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Victor Roytburd</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>vroytbur@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032928584</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>A shock wave is a propagating disturbance in a liquid, gas, or plasma (a fluid in physics terminology) that is characterized by an abrupt change in fluid properties, such as density or pressure, across the wave front. Shock waves are ubiquitous in nature, from quantum levels to cosmological scales.   They occur in a great variety of physically important phenomena, such as the air flow around an airliner's wing, flows of dense granular materials, fluids undergoing liquid-solid or vapor-liquid phase transitions, magneto-hydrodynamics, nonlinear elasticity, and many other important situations.  The mathematical theory describing realistic multi-dimensional dynamics for these phenomena is under-developed. This project will focus on several important problems whose solution holds the promise of elucidating general phenomena.  In particular, the project will consider the glancing shock reflection problem (that originated from the problem initially proposed by John von Neumann), formation of shocks in supersonic regimes, and others. The project will bring high-performance computing to bear on the understanding of these problems; the numerical solutions obtained have the potential to lead to advances in the theory.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project addresses the mathematical modeling and analysis of a number of multi-dimensional Riemann problems whose solutions contain classical or nonclassical shocks.  A common theme of much of the work in this project is the formulation of problems using asymptotic model equations that retain the essential physics present in the underlying governing equations.  These asymptotic models can then be solved numerically, enabling vastly greater numerical resolution to be achieved in regions where the solutions exhibit small-scale features.  The project addresses fundamental questions in compressible fluid flow and nonlinear hyperbolic systems, including those systems that admit small-scale dependent shocks (examples include models for magneto-hydrodynamics, phase transitions, complex fluids, etc.).  The mathematical theory of the Euler equations of gas dynamics, and more generally of hyperbolic conservation laws, is largely incomplete in more than one space dimension, and the project will attack a number of multidimensional problems that are likely to be amenable to solution.  Numerical solutions of these problems have the potential to lead to the development of the theory and resolve various paradoxes in the existing theories.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>09/04/2015</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>09/04/2015</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1516131</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Allen</FirstName>
<LastName>Tesdall</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Allen Tesdall</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>allen.tesdall@csi.cuny.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>7189822254</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000633682</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/04/2015</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>CUNY College of Staten Island</Name>
<CityName>Staten Island</CityName>
<ZipCode>103146609</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>7189822254</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>2800 Victory Boulevard</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[1A-211]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>11</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NY11</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>620128079</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>RESEARCH FOUNDATION OF THE CITY UNIVERSITY OF NEW YORK</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>073268849</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[CUNY College of Staten Island]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<ZipCode>103146609</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>11</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NY11</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1266</Code>
<Text>APPLIED MATHEMATICS</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8396</Code>
<Text>Clean Energy Technology</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8609</Code>
<Text>Other Energy Research</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0115</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2015~140000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The project addressed several aspects of the mathematics of shock waves:&nbsp; their modeling via mathematical equations, methods for solution of these equations, qualitative and quantitative features of the solutions, and the classification of a broad group of problems into types to facilitate their study.&nbsp; A common lay perception is that a shock wave is the thing that causes a loud noise when a military jet flies overhead, and while it is true that this is an example, it is by no means the most common or most important example.&nbsp; Shocks are a surprisingly ubiquitous feature of the natural (and human-made) world.&nbsp; They are important ingredients in the mathematical description of situations as varied as automobile traffic flow and magnetohydrodynamics.&nbsp; Yet the theory which deals with these problems is not fully developed, explaining why research of this type is necessary.<br /><br />The project investigated a broad class of problems whose solutions contain shock waves dependent upon small parameters such as viscosity, heat conduction, and other effects such as capillarity.&nbsp; Many physically important problems fit into this setting, including, for example, phase-transition dynamics and nonlinear elasticity (these have applications in biology, many areas of technology, and other areas).&nbsp; We have introduced and derived several classes of models which mathematically describe these "small-scale dependent shock" problems, and we have derived conditions that we can prove guarantee the satisfaction of certain desirable properties for a class of models.&nbsp; Such a classification of the models is essential for developing a general theory.&nbsp; <br /><br />Because the equations appearing in the models described above are too complicated to be solved exactly, they must be solved numerically, using computers.&nbsp; Standard methods developed for equations of similar type (so-called hyperbolic conservation laws), however, fail to accurately compute solutions of these small-scale dependent shock problems.&nbsp; For this reason, the project has developed a class of numerical methods which, we are able to show, accurately compute these solutions.&nbsp; We can prove that these numerical methods satisfy discrete versions of the desirable properties alluded to above.&nbsp; We have performed extensive numerical tests on models of interest demonstrating the robustness and accuracy of these methods.&nbsp; At the time of this writing, additional work has been done which is as yet unpublished.&nbsp; As this is done, addenda will be added to this report to reflect this.<br /><br />Besides the technical points noted, the project had broader impacts, particularly in the area of undergraduate research.&nbsp; The project provided training for two undergraduate students (one of these participated in an NSF REU while working on the project), thereby helping to increase the size of the pool of workers with advanced scientific, mathematical, and computational training.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 12/15/2019<br>      Modified by: Allen&nbsp;Tesdall</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The project addressed several aspects of the mathematics of shock waves:  their modeling via mathematical equations, methods for solution of these equations, qualitative and quantitative features of the solutions, and the classification of a broad group of problems into types to facilitate their study.  A common lay perception is that a shock wave is the thing that causes a loud noise when a military jet flies overhead, and while it is true that this is an example, it is by no means the most common or most important example.  Shocks are a surprisingly ubiquitous feature of the natural (and human-made) world.  They are important ingredients in the mathematical description of situations as varied as automobile traffic flow and magnetohydrodynamics.  Yet the theory which deals with these problems is not fully developed, explaining why research of this type is necessary.  The project investigated a broad class of problems whose solutions contain shock waves dependent upon small parameters such as viscosity, heat conduction, and other effects such as capillarity.  Many physically important problems fit into this setting, including, for example, phase-transition dynamics and nonlinear elasticity (these have applications in biology, many areas of technology, and other areas).  We have introduced and derived several classes of models which mathematically describe these "small-scale dependent shock" problems, and we have derived conditions that we can prove guarantee the satisfaction of certain desirable properties for a class of models.  Such a classification of the models is essential for developing a general theory.    Because the equations appearing in the models described above are too complicated to be solved exactly, they must be solved numerically, using computers.  Standard methods developed for equations of similar type (so-called hyperbolic conservation laws), however, fail to accurately compute solutions of these small-scale dependent shock problems.  For this reason, the project has developed a class of numerical methods which, we are able to show, accurately compute these solutions.  We can prove that these numerical methods satisfy discrete versions of the desirable properties alluded to above.  We have performed extensive numerical tests on models of interest demonstrating the robustness and accuracy of these methods.  At the time of this writing, additional work has been done which is as yet unpublished.  As this is done, addenda will be added to this report to reflect this.  Besides the technical points noted, the project had broader impacts, particularly in the area of undergraduate research.  The project provided training for two undergraduate students (one of these participated in an NSF REU while working on the project), thereby helping to increase the size of the pool of workers with advanced scientific, mathematical, and computational training.       Last Modified: 12/15/2019       Submitted by: Allen Tesdall]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
