<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Sequence Similarity Networks for the Protein "Universe"</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2015</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2016</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>3172.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>3172</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>05090000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>CSE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>OAC</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Office of Advanced Cyberinfrastructure (OAC)</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Edward Walker</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>edwalker@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924863</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The focus of the Enzyme Function Initiative (EFI, enzymefunction.org) is to devise bioinformatic tools and bioinformatic databases that facilitate the assignment of functions to uncharacterized enzymes discovered in genome projects. To assist in achieving that goal, this project will use the Blue Waters petascale computing facility to precompute libraries of sequence similarity networks (SSNs) for the protein universe and to make these available to the community. The SSNs will be used to 1) analyze sequence-function relationships in large protein families and 2) generate strategies to assign functions to uncharacterized members of those families. The libraries of SSNs will be updated regularly and be disseminated to the scientific community via website maintained&lt;br/&gt;by the EFI (http://efi.igb.illinois.edu/est-precompute/). &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project will use the Blue Waters petascale computing facility to enable large-scale generation of complete libraries of sequence similarity networks (SSNs) for the complete set of protein families and superfamilies (the 14,831 homologous sequence-based families described by Pfam (http://pfam.xfam.org/) and the 2,738 homologous structure based superfamilies described by Gene3D/CATH (http://gene3d.biochem.ucl.ac.uk/Gene3D/), thereby providing the community with easy access to sequence-function space. The conservative estimate is that no more than 50% of the proteins that have been discovered in genome projects have reliable functional annotations that can be accessed by the community using the UniProtKB database (http://www.uniprot.org/). In the absence of reliable functional annotations for all proteins, the biomedical, pharmaceutical, and commercial potential provided by genome sequences cannot be realized. The EFIs goal is to provide tools and strategies that will allow the community to efficiently determine the functions of uncharacterized enzymes. The library of sequence similarity networks (SSNs) to be generated and regularly updated using Blue Waters will be an invaluable bioinformatics database/resource for focusing and guiding those experimental efforts.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/17/2015</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/17/2015</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.070</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1516327</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>John</FirstName>
<LastName>Gerlt</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>John Gerlt</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>j-gerlt@illinois.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2173332187</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000681204</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/17/2015</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign</Name>
<CityName>Champaign</CityName>
<ZipCode>618207406</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2173332187</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1901 South First Street</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[Suite A]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Illinois</StateName>
<StateCode>IL</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>13</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>IL13</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>041544081</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF ILLINOIS</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>041544081</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign]]></Name>
<CityName>Champaign</CityName>
<StateCode>IL</StateCode>
<ZipCode>618207473</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[1901 South First Street, Suite A]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Illinois</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>13</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>IL13</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7781</Code>
<Text>Leadership-Class Computing</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0115</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2015~3172</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><strong>Project goal</strong></p> <p>This project enabled large-scale visualization and analysis of the relationship between sequence and function in the &ldquo;protein universe&rdquo;. We computed protein sequence similarity networks (SSNs) for all proteins with known sequences. This will facilitate assignment of function to those proteins whose role in cellular physiology has been so far unknown. Our goal is to provide the community with a library of precomputed SSNs that is regularly updated: every eight weeks, six times per year. That is the rate at which the protein families (the &ldquo;protein universe&rdquo;; <a href="http://pfam.xfam.org/">http://pfam.xfam.org/</a>) are updated in the UniProt &ndash; currently the &ldquo;gold standard&rdquo; protein sequence database. Frequent updates of the library of SSNs are essential so that the community can access the most current sequence and annotation information to enable their science.&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p><strong>Why it matters</strong></p> <p>Knowledge of the protein function impacts a large number of disciplines, such as the fundamental research into structure, function and mechanism of action of biomolecules, as well as molecular evolution, systems biology and modeling of cellular networks. The outcomes from these research studies enable applications in many economically important areas. For example, in personalized medicine this information is indispensable for drug target discovery, drug design, patient drug responsiveness and metabolism. In biocatalysis and bioengineering it is used for water treatment and soil decontamination. Similarly, it enables adaption of microbial species and communities for oil processing and biofuels.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p><strong>Problem statement</strong></p> <p>It is estimated that the functions of at least half of all the known proteins are unknown, uncertain, or incorrect. To realize the considerable biological and commercial potential contained in genomic sequences of proteins, strategies must be developed for the reliable functional assignment of uncharacterized proteins. Our project succeeded to design just that: a robust, user-friendly tool to facilitate prediction and subsequent experimental assignment of the <em>in vitro</em> activities and <em>in vivo</em> metabolic functions to uncharacterized enzymes discovered in genome projects.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p><strong>Big data problem and the need for Blue Waters</strong></p> <p>The number of proteins in the sequence databases continues to increase exponentially, primarily as the result of microbial genome projects. The current release of the UniProt database (Release 2016_08; <a href="http://www.uniprot.org/">http://www.uniprot.org/</a>) contains as many as 67,457,740 non-redundant protein sequences. The construction of a sequence similarity network requires an all-by-all pairwise sequence comparison to provide pairwise relationships for all members of a protein family, leading to combinatorial explosion of the computational time required to build such a network. This is especially the case for some protein families that are extremely large, such as the ABC transporter superfamily PF00005 containing more than 800,000 sequences. Solving this problem in a reasonable time requires data-level parallelization: breaking up the sequence database in smaller subsets and computing similarities on those, in parallel on many thousands of compute nodes. The Blue Waters petascale facility uniquely provides the infrastructure for this project, enabling us to stay apace with the database updates, due to the sheer number of its compute nodes.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p><strong>Outcomes and products </strong></p> <p>We have designed a computational pipeline that allows the complete library of 16,306 SSNs to be computed every eight weeks. This pipeline includes predictive algorithms to allow dynamic adjustment of the computational resources, so that each update can be calculated with a minimum of manual intervention. This allows us to keep up with the rapid increase in the number of sequences in the UniProt database at the rate of ~2% per month. Such increase requires changes in the allocation of computational resources, such as the number of nodes, RAM, and computational time used for each round of calculations. By using our predictive algorithms, we avoid human error and waste of resources during the updates.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>The magnitude and importance of the functional assignment problem require that the tools and strategies be readily accessible to diverse audiences in the community, with the tools applicable to a wide range of functional assignment problems. The SSNs will be disseminated via a web tool at UIUC (<a href="http://efi.igb.illinois.edu/est-precompute/">http://efi.igb.illinois.edu/est-precompute/</a>), as well as the Enzyme Portal (<a href="http://www.ebi.ac.uk/enzymeportal/">http://www.ebi.ac.uk/enzymeportal/</a>) at the European Molecular Biology Laboratory-European Bioinformatics Institute (EMBL-EBI).</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 10/17/2016<br>      Modified by: John&nbsp;Gerlt</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Project goal  This project enabled large-scale visualization and analysis of the relationship between sequence and function in the "protein universe". We computed protein sequence similarity networks (SSNs) for all proteins with known sequences. This will facilitate assignment of function to those proteins whose role in cellular physiology has been so far unknown. Our goal is to provide the community with a library of precomputed SSNs that is regularly updated: every eight weeks, six times per year. That is the rate at which the protein families (the "protein universe"; http://pfam.xfam.org/) are updated in the UniProt &ndash; currently the "gold standard" protein sequence database. Frequent updates of the library of SSNs are essential so that the community can access the most current sequence and annotation information to enable their science.      Why it matters  Knowledge of the protein function impacts a large number of disciplines, such as the fundamental research into structure, function and mechanism of action of biomolecules, as well as molecular evolution, systems biology and modeling of cellular networks. The outcomes from these research studies enable applications in many economically important areas. For example, in personalized medicine this information is indispensable for drug target discovery, drug design, patient drug responsiveness and metabolism. In biocatalysis and bioengineering it is used for water treatment and soil decontamination. Similarly, it enables adaption of microbial species and communities for oil processing and biofuels.     Problem statement  It is estimated that the functions of at least half of all the known proteins are unknown, uncertain, or incorrect. To realize the considerable biological and commercial potential contained in genomic sequences of proteins, strategies must be developed for the reliable functional assignment of uncharacterized proteins. Our project succeeded to design just that: a robust, user-friendly tool to facilitate prediction and subsequent experimental assignment of the in vitro activities and in vivo metabolic functions to uncharacterized enzymes discovered in genome projects.     Big data problem and the need for Blue Waters  The number of proteins in the sequence databases continues to increase exponentially, primarily as the result of microbial genome projects. The current release of the UniProt database (Release 2016_08; http://www.uniprot.org/) contains as many as 67,457,740 non-redundant protein sequences. The construction of a sequence similarity network requires an all-by-all pairwise sequence comparison to provide pairwise relationships for all members of a protein family, leading to combinatorial explosion of the computational time required to build such a network. This is especially the case for some protein families that are extremely large, such as the ABC transporter superfamily PF00005 containing more than 800,000 sequences. Solving this problem in a reasonable time requires data-level parallelization: breaking up the sequence database in smaller subsets and computing similarities on those, in parallel on many thousands of compute nodes. The Blue Waters petascale facility uniquely provides the infrastructure for this project, enabling us to stay apace with the database updates, due to the sheer number of its compute nodes.     Outcomes and products   We have designed a computational pipeline that allows the complete library of 16,306 SSNs to be computed every eight weeks. This pipeline includes predictive algorithms to allow dynamic adjustment of the computational resources, so that each update can be calculated with a minimum of manual intervention. This allows us to keep up with the rapid increase in the number of sequences in the UniProt database at the rate of ~2% per month. Such increase requires changes in the allocation of computational resources, such as the number of nodes, RAM, and computational time used for each round of calculations. By using our predictive algorithms, we avoid human error and waste of resources during the updates.     The magnitude and importance of the functional assignment problem require that the tools and strategies be readily accessible to diverse audiences in the community, with the tools applicable to a wide range of functional assignment problems. The SSNs will be disseminated via a web tool at UIUC (http://efi.igb.illinois.edu/est-precompute/), as well as the Enzyme Portal (http://www.ebi.ac.uk/enzymeportal/) at the European Molecular Biology Laboratory-European Bioinformatics Institute (EMBL-EBI).       Last Modified: 10/17/2016       Submitted by: John Gerlt]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
