<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Collaborative Research: Cortical Spreading Depression and Ionic Electrodiffusion in the Brain</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2015</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>165000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>165000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DMS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Junping Wang</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>jwang@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924488</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>A major goal of this project is to gain a better understanding of cortical spreading depression. This is a disorder of the brain that is the basis of migraine aura and many other diseases of the brain including stroke and epilepsy. In this disorder the ionic environment of the brain is completely disrupted and the nerve cells turn silent, with a  disturbance that spreads at speeds of two to five millimeters per minute across the brain. When this happens in the visual cortex, the brain area that processes visual information, the patient will perceive an aura, a temporary visual defect that slowly travels over the field of view. Migraine sufferers often perceive an aura (migraine aura) prior to a migraine attack. Better understanding the mechanisms of cortical spreading depression  will thus help in management of migraine headache and many other pathological brain conditions. This research collaboration will train graduate students who will work on various aspects of the project. Summer schools will be held at Florida International University, which is a minority serving institution. Thus this project, accompanied with existing institutional efforts, has the potential to  further the goal of increasing minority representation in the sciences. Further, this collaborative effort brings together experimentalists and theorists of diverse interests and strength, and  therefore provides students with an ideal opportunity for professional growth.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Cortical spreading depression is a massive redistribution of ionic concentrations in the brain that results in a localized temporary loss of neuronal function. This disturbance spreads through the brain at speeds of two to five millimeters per minute and is the physiological substrate of migraine aura. Although cortical spreading depression was first described over seventy years ago, the physiological mechanisms leading to the disturbance remains elusive, most likely due to the fact that it involves many biophysical processes. In this project, a comprehensive mathematical model and computational apparatus to simulate the phenomena will be constructed and validated with experimental data obtained at high spatial resolution. An important aspect of the mathematical model is that it takes into account ionic electro-diffusion, an effect that has not been properly considered in previous studies, and may also be relevant for illucidating mechanisms in many other neurophysiological settings. In particular, the effects of electro-diffusion on extracellular recordings, electroencephalography and magneto-encephalography signals will be studied, thereby improving analysis of these measurement modalities. Overall this research may have an impact in many other brain pathologies which are linked to these underlying biophysical processes.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/24/2015</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/24/2015</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1516176</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Jorge</FirstName>
<LastName>Riera Diaz</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Jorge Riera Diaz</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>jrieradi@fiu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>3053482494</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000628488</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/24/2015</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Florida International University</Name>
<CityName>Miami</CityName>
<ZipCode>331990001</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>3053482494</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>11200 SW 8TH ST</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[MARC 430]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Florida</StateName>
<StateCode>FL</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>26</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>FL26</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>071298814</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>FLORIDA INTERNATIONAL UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>159621697</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Florida International University]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>FL</StateCode>
<ZipCode>331990001</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Florida</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>26</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>FL26</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1253</Code>
<Text>OFFICE OF MULTIDISCIPLINARY AC</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1443</Code>
<Text>FD-Fluid Dynamics</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7334</Code>
<Text>MATHEMATICAL BIOLOGY</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7454</Code>
<Text>MSPA-INTERDISCIPLINARY</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>058E</Code>
<Text>Newtonian fluids</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8007</Code>
<Text>BioMaPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8091</Code>
<Text>BRAIN Initiative Res Support</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0115</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2015~165000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><span>Cortical spreading depression (CSD) is widely considered to be a major physiological substrate of migraine aura, a disabling illness affecting ~11.3% of Americans. CSD triggers the headache attacks by recurrent activation/sensitization of the trigeminovascular system. The CSD events are characterized by a loss of ionic homeostasis and transient changes in neuronal excitability which propagate in contiguous gray matter at 2-6 mm/min. An understanding of this multi-cellular/multi-mechanistic propagating phenomenon is still incomplete, and further advancement requires methods aiming at spatially resolving populations of cells dynamically interacting. The primary goal of this proposal is to study mechanisms underlying the CSD. To that end, we will develop a multidomain electrodiffusion model that accounts for the homeostatic control of the brain ionic environment and link it to experimental CSD data obtained from rats using invasive electrophysiological recording techniques with microelectrodes arrays (MEA) (Figure 1, B&amp;C).</span><span> </span><span>Results obtained from this research will help neurologists to formulate new therapeutic interventions to treat migraines and to define macroscopic EEG biomarkers of this diseases for non-invasive monitoring. We had three aims that covered: 1) model development/validation, 2) experimental CSD data recording, 3) parameter identification via statistical inference. This research was a collaborative effort by Yoichiro Mori (University of Minnesota, UMN) and Jorge Riera-Diaz (Florida International University, FIU). Dr. Mori developed the multidomain electrodiffusion model and computational methods to solve it. Dr. Riera-Diaz created the experimental protocol to obtain two types of electrophysiological data from rats undergoing CSD events: 1) the local field potential (LFP) and the multiunit activity (MUA), both across all cortical layers. We were able to successfully stablish an experimental technique to observe CSD induced by KCH<sub>3</sub>CO<sub>2</sub> using both laminar (Figure 1, A) and planar (Figure 2) MEA probes inserted along the cortical layers. We were able to stablish a biphasic relationship between LFP and intrinsic MUA during CSD, with a first-time reported increase in inhibitory neuronal activity after the event. We also reported a specific laminar profile of transversal propagation using a novel method for current source density analysis.</span><span> As part of this project, three undergraduate students performed high-quality research in my lab, two of them ending in an ARCH thesis work (</span><span>Darlene Ramos and Daniel Rivera), and two of them leading to the Ronald E McNair Post-Baccalaureate Scholarship Achievement Program (Daniel Rivera and Diana Borrego). A substantial part of a PhD thesis dissertation by Arash Moshkforoush was also related to this research project. The results were published in three peer-reviewed journals (Frontiers Cellular Neurosci, J Neurosci Methods and PLoS Computational Biology). These students presented their results in 10 prestigious conferences/workshops. As part of the research, we organized at FIU our first summer mini-school (Picture 1) on August 8<sup>th</sup>-12<sup>th</sup>, 2016, with a total of 10 pre-selected students from three different universities; and a faculty composed of Drs. Mori and Riera and two professors with strong expertise in CSD (KC Brennan, University of Utah; RD Andrew, Queen`s University). Also, as part of the IMA Program: Multiscale Mathematics and Computing in Science and Engineering, we organized an international workshop on ?Mathematical Modeling of Cortical Spreading Depression (SD) and Related Phenomena? at the University of Minnesota (February 12<sup>th</sup> ? 16<sup>th</sup>, 2018). The workshop brought together mathematical and computational scientists with experimental researchers studying CSD and related phenomena (Picture 2). CSD data obtained from this research were used to develop a new course ?Biophysics of Neuronal Computation? at FIU Honor College (Picture 3), which has had an impact on about 107 students with strong interest in biomedical research, mostly underrepresented minorities. As part of this course, two students joined an intensive seven-day workshop offered in early January 2018 by the MIT Center for Brain, Minds and Machines (CBMM) on Quantitative Methods: Introduction to computational tools used in neuroscience research. In collaboration with NSF staffs, we prepared a featured video, which was shown at the NSF booth in the annual meeting of the Society for Neuroscience (Chicago, 17<sup>th</sup> - 21<sup>st</sup> October 2015).</span><span> </span><span>Several areas of the mathematical sciences have benefited of the methodologies and theories developed in this project.</span><strong></strong><em></em></p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 10/30/2019<br>      Modified by: Jorge&nbsp;Riera Diaz</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Images (<span id="selectedPhoto0">1</span> of <span class="totalNumber"></span>)           </div> <div class="galControls" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1516176/1516176_10379806_1572452558668_Slide1--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1516176/1516176_10379806_1572452558668_Slide1--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Figure 1: Data - Laminar MEA"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1516176/1516176_10379806_1572452558668_Slide1--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Figure 1: Data - Laminar MEA"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Figure 1. A. Raw Data from channel 7 of the electrophysiological probe depicting the drop in potential characteristic of the CSD event. B. Graphic representation of the cortex with the electrophysiological probe to the left, demonstrating its approximate position once inserted. C. Coronal section of</div> <div class="imageCredit">FIU</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Jorge&nbsp;Riera Diaz</div> <div class="imageTitle">Figure 1: Data - Laminar MEA</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1516176/1516176_10379806_1572452618399_Slide2--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1516176/1516176_10379806_1572452618399_Slide2--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Figure 2: Data - Planar MEA"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1516176/1516176_10379806_1572452618399_Slide2--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Figure 2: Data - Planar MEA"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Figure 2 shows the position of the craniotomies used to generate (posterior) and observe (anterior) the CSD event (top-left). CSD events were generated with potassium acetate (CH3CO2K). A dental cement barrier was used to avoid leakage. A planar probe was inserted into the neocortex perpendicular to</div> <div class="imageCredit">FIU</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Jorge&nbsp;Riera Diaz</div> <div class="imageTitle">Figure 2: Data - Planar MEA</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1516176/1516176_10379806_1572452674560_Slide3--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1516176/1516176_10379806_1572452674560_Slide3--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Picture 1"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1516176/1516176_10379806_1572452674560_Slide3--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Picture 1"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Picture 1: Lab tours during the first Summer Mini-School on ?Cortical Spreading Depression? at Florida International University (August 8th-12th, 2016)</div> <div class="imageCredit">FIU</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Jorge&nbsp;Riera Diaz</div> <div class="imageTitle">Picture 1</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1516176/1516176_10379806_1572452825793_Slide4--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1516176/1516176_10379806_1572452825793_Slide4--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Picture 2"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1516176/1516176_10379806_1572452825793_Slide4--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Picture 2"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Picture 2: Workshop on ?Mathematical Modeling of Cortical Spreading Depression (SD) and Related Phenomena? at the University of Minnesota (February 12th ? 16th, 2018).</div> <div class="imageCredit">FIU</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Jorge&nbsp;Riera Diaz</div> <div class="imageTitle">Picture 2</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1516176/1516176_10379806_1572452889593_Slide5--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1516176/1516176_10379806_1572452889593_Slide5--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Picture 3"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1516176/1516176_10379806_1572452889593_Slide5--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Picture 3"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Picture 3: New course flier ?Biophysics of Neuronal Computation? at FIU Honor College.</div> <div class="imageCredit">FIU</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Jorge&nbsp;Riera Diaz</div> <div class="imageTitle">Picture 3</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Cortical spreading depression (CSD) is widely considered to be a major physiological substrate of migraine aura, a disabling illness affecting ~11.3% of Americans. CSD triggers the headache attacks by recurrent activation/sensitization of the trigeminovascular system. The CSD events are characterized by a loss of ionic homeostasis and transient changes in neuronal excitability which propagate in contiguous gray matter at 2-6 mm/min. An understanding of this multi-cellular/multi-mechanistic propagating phenomenon is still incomplete, and further advancement requires methods aiming at spatially resolving populations of cells dynamically interacting. The primary goal of this proposal is to study mechanisms underlying the CSD. To that end, we will develop a multidomain electrodiffusion model that accounts for the homeostatic control of the brain ionic environment and link it to experimental CSD data obtained from rats using invasive electrophysiological recording techniques with microelectrodes arrays (MEA) (Figure 1, B&amp;C). Results obtained from this research will help neurologists to formulate new therapeutic interventions to treat migraines and to define macroscopic EEG biomarkers of this diseases for non-invasive monitoring. We had three aims that covered: 1) model development/validation, 2) experimental CSD data recording, 3) parameter identification via statistical inference. This research was a collaborative effort by Yoichiro Mori (University of Minnesota, UMN) and Jorge Riera-Diaz (Florida International University, FIU). Dr. Mori developed the multidomain electrodiffusion model and computational methods to solve it. Dr. Riera-Diaz created the experimental protocol to obtain two types of electrophysiological data from rats undergoing CSD events: 1) the local field potential (LFP) and the multiunit activity (MUA), both across all cortical layers. We were able to successfully stablish an experimental technique to observe CSD induced by KCH3CO2 using both laminar (Figure 1, A) and planar (Figure 2) MEA probes inserted along the cortical layers. We were able to stablish a biphasic relationship between LFP and intrinsic MUA during CSD, with a first-time reported increase in inhibitory neuronal activity after the event. We also reported a specific laminar profile of transversal propagation using a novel method for current source density analysis. As part of this project, three undergraduate students performed high-quality research in my lab, two of them ending in an ARCH thesis work (Darlene Ramos and Daniel Rivera), and two of them leading to the Ronald E McNair Post-Baccalaureate Scholarship Achievement Program (Daniel Rivera and Diana Borrego). A substantial part of a PhD thesis dissertation by Arash Moshkforoush was also related to this research project. The results were published in three peer-reviewed journals (Frontiers Cellular Neurosci, J Neurosci Methods and PLoS Computational Biology). These students presented their results in 10 prestigious conferences/workshops. As part of the research, we organized at FIU our first summer mini-school (Picture 1) on August 8th-12th, 2016, with a total of 10 pre-selected students from three different universities; and a faculty composed of Drs. Mori and Riera and two professors with strong expertise in CSD (KC Brennan, University of Utah; RD Andrew, Queen`s University). Also, as part of the IMA Program: Multiscale Mathematics and Computing in Science and Engineering, we organized an international workshop on ?Mathematical Modeling of Cortical Spreading Depression (SD) and Related Phenomena? at the University of Minnesota (February 12th ? 16th, 2018). The workshop brought together mathematical and computational scientists with experimental researchers studying CSD and related phenomena (Picture 2). CSD data obtained from this research were used to develop a new course ?Biophysics of Neuronal Computation? at FIU Honor College (Picture 3), which has had an impact on about 107 students with strong interest in biomedical research, mostly underrepresented minorities. As part of this course, two students joined an intensive seven-day workshop offered in early January 2018 by the MIT Center for Brain, Minds and Machines (CBMM) on Quantitative Methods: Introduction to computational tools used in neuroscience research. In collaboration with NSF staffs, we prepared a featured video, which was shown at the NSF booth in the annual meeting of the Society for Neuroscience (Chicago, 17th - 21st October 2015). Several areas of the mathematical sciences have benefited of the methodologies and theories developed in this project.       Last Modified: 10/30/2019       Submitted by: Jorge Riera Diaz]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
