<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Vortices and Bound States</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2015</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>208182.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>208182</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DMS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Pedro Embid</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>pembid@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924859</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This research project is concerned with the mathematical modeling and analysis of certain types of behaviors in superconductivity and nonlinear optics.  Many problems arising in physics can be modeled by nonlinear partial differential equations, and some of these differential equations generate solutions with interesting structures, such as pulse-like solutions that model light traveling through fiber optics or vortex solutions that arise in fluids and condensed matter physics.  This research aims to understand some of these structures.  In the first case, the behavior of large numbers of vortices in superconducting materials (a typical feature of certain classes of superconductors) will be studied.  In the second case, how vortices are generated in superconductors will be examined.  The third project will consider numerical algorithms that are used to compute pulse-like solutions that arise in nonlinear optics.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This research will focus on three problems arising in applied mathematics.  The first project will study the mean-field behavior of asymptotically large numbers of vortices arising in superconductivity.  The analysis requires handling asymptotically large numbers of vortices, each of which has asymptotically large energy.  To do so, refined estimates will be developed for tracking concentrations of energy.  The project on the understanding of vortex nucleation in the time-dependent setting should help to understand the transition to the mixed-vortex state in Type-II superconductors.  Finally, the project on iterative methods for computing bound states will study why certain methods are unconditionally convergent, which should lead to better algorithm design.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/24/2015</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/24/2015</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1516565</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Daniel</FirstName>
<LastName>Spirn</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>P</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Daniel P Spirn</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>spirn@math.umn.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6126251349</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000394628</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/24/2015</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Minnesota-Twin Cities</Name>
<CityName>Minneapolis</CityName>
<ZipCode>554552070</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6126245599</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>200 OAK ST SE</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Minnesota</StateName>
<StateCode>MN</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MN05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>555917996</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>REGENTS OF THE UNIVERSITY OF MINNESOTA</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>117178941</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Minnesota-School of Mathematics]]></Name>
<CityName>Minneapolis</CityName>
<StateCode>MN</StateCode>
<ZipCode>554552070</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[206 Church St. SE]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Minnesota</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MN05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1266</Code>
<Text>APPLIED MATHEMATICS</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7237</Code>
<Text>NANO NON-SOLIC SCI &amp; ENG AWD</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8990</Code>
<Text>Optics and Photonics</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9251</Code>
<Text>REU SUPP-Res Exp for Ugrd Supp</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0115</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2015~208182</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><span id="docs-internal-guid-70d44613-7fff-0b71-915f-59dfc1b68347"> </span></p> <p><span id="docs-internal-guid-b16766e1-7fff-e3d6-cfd2-b2075695b8a2"> </span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>Many physical systems, such as superconductors, fluids, and nonlinear optical systems are effectively described by nonlinear partial differential equations. An important feature of many of these equations are solutions with interesting stable structures, such as pulse-like solutions that model light traveling through fiber optics or vortex solutions that arise in fluids and condensed matter physics. This grant supported several projects that examined these structures in many physically relevant situations.</span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>Intellectual Impact:&nbsp;</span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>Vortices are localized eddies of supercurrent in a superconductor, and a clear understanding of the location of vortices provides a deep understanding of the superconductor itself.&nbsp; In one line of research the PI worked on projects that aimed to better understand when and how vortices appear, and how superconductors behave when there are very large numbers of vortices.&nbsp; The results provide intuition into the qualitative behavior of physical systems and methods for accurate numerical simulations these systems.&nbsp;</span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>In a second direction the research, the PI studied thin elastic filaments in two and three dimensional viscous fluids.&nbsp; These problems arise widely in models for microscopic swimmers and microfluidic devices.  The results from this grant help provide a rigorous framework for understanding widely used methods for simulating such filaments.&nbsp;</span></p> <p dir="ltr">Beyond these two primary directions, the PI worked on addition projects that developed techniques for computing optical pulses, schemes for generating specialized meshes for arbitrary shapes, and novel methods for detecting imperfections in linear accelerator cavities.&nbsp;</p> <p dir="ltr"><span>Broader Impact:</span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>Superconductors are used in a wide number of applications, including MRIs, particle accelerators and ultrasensitive detectors.&nbsp; Qualitative understanding of these materials can lead to improved designs. Part of the research funded by this grant helped develop rigorous understanding of superconductors.</span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>Thin elastic filaments are </span><span>ubiquitous</span><span> in microscopic fluid scales, and accurate numerical simulations of these filaments are challenging. A second main part of the research funded by this grant helped provide a rigorous foundation for simpler methods of simulating these filaments.&nbsp;</span></p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 10/30/2019<br>      Modified by: Daniel&nbsp;P&nbsp;Spirn</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[      Many physical systems, such as superconductors, fluids, and nonlinear optical systems are effectively described by nonlinear partial differential equations. An important feature of many of these equations are solutions with interesting stable structures, such as pulse-like solutions that model light traveling through fiber optics or vortex solutions that arise in fluids and condensed matter physics. This grant supported several projects that examined these structures in many physically relevant situations. Intellectual Impact:  Vortices are localized eddies of supercurrent in a superconductor, and a clear understanding of the location of vortices provides a deep understanding of the superconductor itself.  In one line of research the PI worked on projects that aimed to better understand when and how vortices appear, and how superconductors behave when there are very large numbers of vortices.  The results provide intuition into the qualitative behavior of physical systems and methods for accurate numerical simulations these systems.  In a second direction the research, the PI studied thin elastic filaments in two and three dimensional viscous fluids.  These problems arise widely in models for microscopic swimmers and microfluidic devices.  The results from this grant help provide a rigorous framework for understanding widely used methods for simulating such filaments.  Beyond these two primary directions, the PI worked on addition projects that developed techniques for computing optical pulses, schemes for generating specialized meshes for arbitrary shapes, and novel methods for detecting imperfections in linear accelerator cavities.  Broader Impact: Superconductors are used in a wide number of applications, including MRIs, particle accelerators and ultrasensitive detectors.  Qualitative understanding of these materials can lead to improved designs. Part of the research funded by this grant helped develop rigorous understanding of superconductors. Thin elastic filaments are ubiquitous in microscopic fluid scales, and accurate numerical simulations of these filaments are challenging. A second main part of the research funded by this grant helped provide a rigorous foundation for simpler methods of simulating these filaments.        Last Modified: 10/30/2019       Submitted by: Daniel P Spirn]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
