<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>RUI: Collaborative Research: The Role of Microscopic Molecular Structure in Confined Bose-Einstein Condensates of Diatomic Molecules</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2015</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>132000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>132000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03010000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>PHY</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Physics</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Robert Forrey</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>rforrey@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032925199</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Diatomic molecules, consisting of only two atoms, are the simplest molecules that can exist. Yet, although the structure of diatomic molecules is comparatively simple, the molecule, with the two atoms bound together through the overlapping structure of the electrons surrounding the atoms, demonstrates a rich internal structure that can influence the behavior of a system in which the diatomic molecule interacts with other molecules surrounding it. This collaborative theoretical research program is aimed at understanding how the microscopic structure of diatomic molecules influences the bulk behavior of ultracold molecular gases. The goals of the program are to understand how the details of the molecular interactions and internal molecular structure play a role in emergent bulk phenomena in molecular Bose-Einstein condensates, and to provide guidance and motivation for ongoing experiments. Additionally, this research is designed to foster collaborations between scientists with specializations in few-body and many-body quantum physics, and integrate undergraduate student researchers in the entirety of the research process. In particular, students are involved in developing theoretical tools and implementing numerical calculations, and are presenting at scientific meetings and preparing manuscripts for submission to peer reviewed journals. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The focus of this project is quantum degenerate gases of bosonic molecules in which the spatial and microscopic degrees of freedom of the molecules influence the bulk system behavior.  Unlike many conventional condensed matter or solid state systems, quantum degenerate gases of ultracold molecule provide us with a great deal of control over both their microscopic and bulk properties, and they permit the investigation of collective, emergent quantum phenomena in unique contexts. Recent experimental progress towards the realization of quantum degeneracy in samples of diatomic molecules promises to significantly enhance the utility of ultracold quantum systems.  This research is motivated by the idea that the interplay of spatial and microscopic degrees of freedom can lead to a variety of rich behaviors in quantum many-body systems, such as an interaction driven spin-orbit coupling at the two-body level and state-dependent dipolar interactions that exhibit strong dependence on confinement geometry.  Using mean-field and perturbative quantum field theory methods, this research (1) generalizes a two-state model of a molecular Bose gas to account for realistic experimental scenarios, including finite trapping geometries, arbitrary polarization fields, and short-range interactions; (2) extends the model to incorporate more microscopic states and apply it to describe Bose gases of rigid rotor molecules with large effective spin degrees of freedom; and (3) incorporates beyond-dipolar interactions, such as quadrupolar interactions and lossy collisions, into the model. The long term goals of this work are to develop a rigorous theoretical understanding of how the microscopic structure of diatomic molecules influence intermolecular interactions, and thereby play a role in emergent quantum many-body phenomena, and to provide guidance and motivation for experiments with quantum degenerate molecules that will be available in the near future.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/18/2015</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/17/2017</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1516337</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Seth</FirstName>
<LastName>Rittenhouse</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>T</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Seth T Rittenhouse</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>rittenho@usna.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>4102936672</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000678067</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/18/2015</StartDate>
<EndDate>08/31/2015</EndDate>
<RoleCode>Former Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Brandon</FirstName>
<LastName>Peden</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>M</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Brandon M Peden</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>Brandon.peden@wwu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>3606503853</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000678068</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/31/2015</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Brandon</FirstName>
<LastName>Peden</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>M</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Brandon M Peden</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>Brandon.peden@wwu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>3606503853</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000678068</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/18/2015</StartDate>
<EndDate>08/31/2015</EndDate>
<RoleCode>Former Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Western Washington University</Name>
<CityName>Bellingham</CityName>
<ZipCode>982259038</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>3606502884</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>516 High Street</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Washington</StateName>
<StateCode>WA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>WA02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>079253134</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>WESTERN WASHINGTON UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>079253134</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Western Washington University]]></Name>
<CityName>Bellingham</CityName>
<StateCode>WA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>982255996</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[516 High Street]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Washington</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>WA02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1284</Code>
<Text>AMO Theory/Atomic, Molecular &amp;</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7241</Code>
<Text>Physics Instrumentation</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9229</Code>
<Text>RES IN UNDERGRAD INST-RESEARCH</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0115</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0116</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0117</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2015~62000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2016~39000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2017~31000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>When a gas of atoms is cooled to extremely low temperatures, the individual atoms that make up that gas stop behaving like classical billiard balls, and the strange world of quantum mechanics takes over.&nbsp; The atoms move slower as the temperature decreases, and the wavelike character of the quantum particles begins to dominate over the particle-like behavior. For certain kinds of particles (called bosons) when their wavelength is about equal to the inter-particle spacing, a large fraction of the atoms all snap into the same state.&nbsp; This macroscopic collection of particles is a new state of matter called a Bose-Einstein condensate (or BEC), named for Satyendra Nath Bose and Albert Einstein who first predicted its existence.</p> <p><br />The first BECs were created experimentally in the 1990's some 70 years after they were predicted to exist.&nbsp; These strange, purely quantum mechanical systems were made by cooling down gases of alkali atoms to fractions of a millionth of a Kelvin above absolute zero.&nbsp; While these experiments presented amazing opportunities for studying the behavior of this new state, they were also limited because the interactions between the atoms are isotropic (the same independent of how two interacting atoms are oriented) and short range (two atoms only interact when they are very close to each other).&nbsp; In contrast, diatomic molecules interact via their electric dipole moments.&nbsp; The dipole-dipole interaction is both long-range (it falls off as the cube of the inter-molecular separation distance), and anisotropic (it depends on the relative orientation of the molecules). This opens up the possibility for conducting fundamental scientific investigations of chemical reactions, for realizing novels phases of matter, and for engineering new quantum computing platforms.</p> <p><br />The goal of this project was to examine how the microscopic structure of the constituent molecules affects the behavior of the condensate as a whole, with the broader aim of developing a robust model for the description of molecular BECs that can be applied to many current and future experimental studies.</p> <p><br />Previously, we investigated the behavior of a molecular BEC trapped by external electric and magnetic fields into a pancake-like shape and experiencing an electric field aligning dipole moments of the molecules perpendicular to the pancake.&nbsp; Using a two-state model in which the molecular dipole moment was either aligned or anti-aligned with the external field, we examined the behavior resulting from the competition between inter-molecular interactions---which tend to cause nearby dipole moments to anti-align---and the effects of the external field. Under suitable conditions, domains form in which neighboring domains have anti-aligned dipole moments. These regions alternate creating a wave-like structure in the polarization of the gas.&nbsp; The attraction between these neighboring regions destabilizes the BEC towards imploding. We set out to both build a more robust model of the system and to fully characterize its stable phases.</p> <p><br />In this project, we generalized the two-state model in several ways. We predicted that if the trap is not too large in the radial direction (looking like a thicker rather than thinner pancake), there is a parameter regime in which the density profile of the gas is smooth and featureless while the polarization of the molecules takes on a wave-like structure that is partially stabilized in the presence of the trap.</p> <p>We also extended the two-state model to include multiple rotational states, effectively modeling each molecule as a tiny barbell that can freely rotate but still tends to align with an external electric field. If the molecules are free to rotate, under strong enough interactions, they can tilt away from the external field and into the plane of the 'pancake'.&nbsp; By lying almost on their sides, the molecular dipole moments align tip-to-tail. This configuration is strongly attractive, and so the gas destabilizes toward an implosion.</p> <p><br />Finally, to further align the model with real systems which include more complicated inter-molecular interactions, we included beyond-dipole high-order interactions.&nbsp; These so-called 'quadrupolar' interactions lead to ground state behaviors in which the molecular BEC acts like a liquid crystal, a state of matter whose applications include LCD displays such as computer and TV screens. Fitting these phases into the overall picture of the molecular BEC helps to both drive and support experimental studies in the future.</p> <p><br />To date this project has produced fourteen peer reviewed journal publications with several others still in development.&nbsp; We have produced new models of molecular Bose-Einstein condensates that more accurately reflect likely future experimental efforts.&nbsp; Approximately eleven undergraduate students have participated in this research presenting their work in thirteen contributed conference and workshop posters and talks.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 03/24/2021<br>      Modified by: Brandon&nbsp;M&nbsp;Peden</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ When a gas of atoms is cooled to extremely low temperatures, the individual atoms that make up that gas stop behaving like classical billiard balls, and the strange world of quantum mechanics takes over.  The atoms move slower as the temperature decreases, and the wavelike character of the quantum particles begins to dominate over the particle-like behavior. For certain kinds of particles (called bosons) when their wavelength is about equal to the inter-particle spacing, a large fraction of the atoms all snap into the same state.  This macroscopic collection of particles is a new state of matter called a Bose-Einstein condensate (or BEC), named for Satyendra Nath Bose and Albert Einstein who first predicted its existence.   The first BECs were created experimentally in the 1990's some 70 years after they were predicted to exist.  These strange, purely quantum mechanical systems were made by cooling down gases of alkali atoms to fractions of a millionth of a Kelvin above absolute zero.  While these experiments presented amazing opportunities for studying the behavior of this new state, they were also limited because the interactions between the atoms are isotropic (the same independent of how two interacting atoms are oriented) and short range (two atoms only interact when they are very close to each other).  In contrast, diatomic molecules interact via their electric dipole moments.  The dipole-dipole interaction is both long-range (it falls off as the cube of the inter-molecular separation distance), and anisotropic (it depends on the relative orientation of the molecules). This opens up the possibility for conducting fundamental scientific investigations of chemical reactions, for realizing novels phases of matter, and for engineering new quantum computing platforms.   The goal of this project was to examine how the microscopic structure of the constituent molecules affects the behavior of the condensate as a whole, with the broader aim of developing a robust model for the description of molecular BECs that can be applied to many current and future experimental studies.   Previously, we investigated the behavior of a molecular BEC trapped by external electric and magnetic fields into a pancake-like shape and experiencing an electric field aligning dipole moments of the molecules perpendicular to the pancake.  Using a two-state model in which the molecular dipole moment was either aligned or anti-aligned with the external field, we examined the behavior resulting from the competition between inter-molecular interactions---which tend to cause nearby dipole moments to anti-align---and the effects of the external field. Under suitable conditions, domains form in which neighboring domains have anti-aligned dipole moments. These regions alternate creating a wave-like structure in the polarization of the gas.  The attraction between these neighboring regions destabilizes the BEC towards imploding. We set out to both build a more robust model of the system and to fully characterize its stable phases.   In this project, we generalized the two-state model in several ways. We predicted that if the trap is not too large in the radial direction (looking like a thicker rather than thinner pancake), there is a parameter regime in which the density profile of the gas is smooth and featureless while the polarization of the molecules takes on a wave-like structure that is partially stabilized in the presence of the trap.  We also extended the two-state model to include multiple rotational states, effectively modeling each molecule as a tiny barbell that can freely rotate but still tends to align with an external electric field. If the molecules are free to rotate, under strong enough interactions, they can tilt away from the external field and into the plane of the 'pancake'.  By lying almost on their sides, the molecular dipole moments align tip-to-tail. This configuration is strongly attractive, and so the gas destabilizes toward an implosion.   Finally, to further align the model with real systems which include more complicated inter-molecular interactions, we included beyond-dipole high-order interactions.  These so-called 'quadrupolar' interactions lead to ground state behaviors in which the molecular BEC acts like a liquid crystal, a state of matter whose applications include LCD displays such as computer and TV screens. Fitting these phases into the overall picture of the molecular BEC helps to both drive and support experimental studies in the future.   To date this project has produced fourteen peer reviewed journal publications with several others still in development.  We have produced new models of molecular Bose-Einstein condensates that more accurately reflect likely future experimental efforts.  Approximately eleven undergraduate students have participated in this research presenting their work in thirteen contributed conference and workshop posters and talks.       Last Modified: 03/24/2021       Submitted by: Brandon M Peden]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
