<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>RAPID: Hierarchical Carbon Adsorbent for Cytokines Removal from Blood  of the Ebola Virus Disease Patients</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>01/15/2015</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2015</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>100000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>100000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07020000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CBET</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Chem, Bioeng, Env, &amp; Transp Sys</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Athanassios Sambanis</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>PI:  Mochalin, Vadym&lt;br/&gt;Proposal Number:  1518999&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The devastating effects of the Ebola virus in humans are largely related to overproduction of pro-inflammatory proteins, called cytokines, which are responsible for fatal clinical symptoms of the Ebola disease: inflammation, fever, massive internal hemorrhage, and catastrophic thrombosis around the body. Quick removal of pro-inflammatory cytokines from blood by adsorption is essential to mitigate these severe clinical symptoms while the immune system prepares to eliminate the virus. The adsorption of cytokines is complicated by their large variations in molecular size and shape, some being small and elongated, others large and more globular, so when a mix of these molecules is present, larger molecules quickly stick to the outer surface of the adsorbent blocking access to the smaller pores for smaller molecules, significantly reducing available surface. The solution is to create adsorbents with hierarchical pore structure, containing large and small pores which fit all possible sizes and shapes of cytokines. These hierarchical carbon adsorbents will be synthesized from polymer precursors and optimized for specific, quick, and complete removal of cytokines from blood of the Ebola virus disease patients. The proposed research will allow the development of a range of carbon materials featuring precisely controlled pore size, pore volume, pore shape, surface area, and surface chemistry. The developed materials will find broader applications in biotechnology, bioengineering, medicine, water purification, and cosmetics. Medical applications of selective protein adsorption, including removal of wastes or toxins from blood of patients with kidney disease or liver failure, may particularly benefit from this research.  This award is being made jointly by two Programs:  (1) Chemical and Biological Separations, (2) Biomedical Engineering, both in the Chemical, Bioengineering, Environmental and Transport Systems Division in the Engineering Directorate.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The proposed research is focused on investigation of the effects of pore size, shape, and surface termination in hierarchical mesoporous carbons on adsorption and intraporous diffusion of cytokines. Based on this knowledge, hierarchical porous carbon adsorbents will be synthesized and tailored for quick removal of a mix of cytokines specific for the Ebola virus disease. The performance of the developed hierarchical carbon adsorbents will be demonstrated on blood plasma samples spiked with cytokine cocktails in compositions and concentrations typical for those in patients with the Ebola virus disease. The adsorbents will be synthesized from silicon containing polymer-derived ceramics with subsequent removal of silicon by high temperature chlorination. This process allows for full control of pore size and shape through variations of precursor composition, chlorination temperature and time, and has been demonstrated to produce hierarchical porosity with subnanometer control of the pore size. Adsorption of cytokines from blood plasma will then be measured by the enzyme-linked immunosorbent assay. To increase their affinity to cytokines, surface chemistry of the synthesized adsorbents will be modified by oxidation in air or carbon dioxide, reduction in hydrogen, and treatment in ammonia gas. At the end of the experimental program, mesoporous carbon adsorbents with a hierarchical pore structure and large particle size will be developed for quick and complete removal of cytokines from blood of the Ebola virus disease patients by extracorporeal perfusion. The proposed treatments will reduce mortality, accelerate recovery and, when used in conjunction with emerging methods and supporting care, will minimize long-term damage to the patient.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>01/16/2015</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>01/16/2015</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1518999</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Yury</FirstName>
<LastName>Gogotsi</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Yury Gogotsi</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>gogotsi@drexel.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2158956446</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000311096</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>01/16/2015</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Vadym</FirstName>
<LastName>Mochalin</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Vadym Mochalin</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>mochalinv@mst.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5733416043</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000526340</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>01/16/2015</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Drexel University</Name>
<CityName>Philadelphia</CityName>
<ZipCode>191021119</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2158956342</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1505 Race St, 10th Floor</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Pennsylvania</StateName>
<StateCode>PA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>PA03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>002604817</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>DREXEL UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>002604817</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Drexel University]]></Name>
<CityName>Philadelphia</CityName>
<StateCode>PA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>191042875</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[3201 Arch St]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Pennsylvania</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>PA03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1417</Code>
<Text>Interfacial Engineering Progra</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>5345</Code>
<Text>Engineering of Biomed Systems</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>001Z</Code>
<Text>Ebola</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>004E</Code>
<Text>BIOMEDICAL ENG AND DIAGNOSTICS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7914</Code>
<Text>RAPID</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0115</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2015~100000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p class="StyleBodyTextComplexArialComplex10pt">Drexel University completed a RAPID project titled, &ldquo;Development of Hierarchical Carbon Adsorbent with Tuned Porosity and Surface Chemistry for Removal of Cytokines from Blood&rdquo; in June 2015. The motivation of this 6 month research project was to develop carbon-based adsorbents for quick removal of cytokines from blood of the Ebola virus disease patients. Quick removal of the cytokines will mitigate the severe clinical symptoms of the Ebola virus disease and buy the patient time to fully develop natural protecting mechanisms &ndash; the only mechanisms of cure, which the patients can currently rely upon. With latest outbreak of Ebola in Africa in 2014-2015 and new cases reported by WHO in June 2015 in Guinea, the Ebola virus continues to pose a major threat to our society. There is currently no antiviral therapy or vaccine that is effective against Ebola virus infection in humans. Therefore, it is critically important to search for the ways that will ease the clinical course of the Ebola virus disease until other therapies eradicating the virus have been found.</p> <p class="StyleBodyTextComplexArialComplex10pt">When inside the body, the virus triggers production of inflammatory cytokines in large amounts, which result in vascular instability and are largely responsible for fatal clinical symptoms: inflammation, fever, shock from massive hemorrhage, and catastrophic thrombosis around the body. Increases in the levels of inflammatory cytokines were associated with fatality from Ebola hemorrhagic fever in literature. Adsorption of cytokines by porous carbons is one the most effective ways for their selective, quick, and complete removal from blood circulation. The problem with adsorption of cytokines is that they have large variations in molecular size and shape, some being small and elongated (as interleukins, which can be adsorbed in pores of &gt; 5 nanometers in diameter), others large and globular (as TNF-&alpha;, which can be adsorbed in pores ~10 nanometers and larger in diameter). When a mix of these molecules is present, larger molecules quickly stick to the outer surface of the adsorbent particles blocking access to the smaller pores for smaller molecules, significantly reducing available surface. Thus, it is difficult to effectively adsorb all cytokines with one adsorbent having pores of uniform size and shape.</p> <p class="StyleBodyTextComplexArialComplex10pt">To accomplish the goal of the project, we have synthesized 25 different carbon adsorbents of 3 major types: carbide derived carbons, polymer ceramics derived carbons, and thermally expanded graphite. Porosity and surface area of these adsorbents have been measured. Adsorption of two pro-inflammatory cytokines (IL-8 and IL-6), whose levels are known to be elevated at the Ebola virus disease, has been measured for these adsorbents. We have found that polymer ceramics derived mesoporous carbons reduce the levels of IL-8 8-10 fold (from 2000 pg/mL down to 300-200 pg/mL) and the levels of IL-6 decrease 2-3 fold (from 1000 pg/mL down to 500-300 pg/mL) within an hour. These polymer derived mesoporous carbons can be produced in form of millimeter-sized particles or even porous monoliths for subsequent incorporation in blood perfusion cartridges to quickly block those cytokine mediated processes which result in devastating symptoms, triggered by the Ebola virus.</p> <p class="StyleBodyTextComplexArialComplex10pt">The results obtained in this study will be important in the development of inexpensive blood perfusion techniques and devices aimed at fighting the Ebola virus disease, as well as other biological and chemical threats, including sepsis, exposure to ecotoxicants, as well as to various exo- and endotoxins, which are of concern for the general public .</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 07/06/2015<br>      Modified by: Vadym&nbsp;Mochalin</p> <...]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[Drexel University completed a RAPID project titled, "Development of Hierarchical Carbon Adsorbent with Tuned Porosity and Surface Chemistry for Removal of Cytokines from Blood" in June 2015. The motivation of this 6 month research project was to develop carbon-based adsorbents for quick removal of cytokines from blood of the Ebola virus disease patients. Quick removal of the cytokines will mitigate the severe clinical symptoms of the Ebola virus disease and buy the patient time to fully develop natural protecting mechanisms &ndash; the only mechanisms of cure, which the patients can currently rely upon. With latest outbreak of Ebola in Africa in 2014-2015 and new cases reported by WHO in June 2015 in Guinea, the Ebola virus continues to pose a major threat to our society. There is currently no antiviral therapy or vaccine that is effective against Ebola virus infection in humans. Therefore, it is critically important to search for the ways that will ease the clinical course of the Ebola virus disease until other therapies eradicating the virus have been found. When inside the body, the virus triggers production of inflammatory cytokines in large amounts, which result in vascular instability and are largely responsible for fatal clinical symptoms: inflammation, fever, shock from massive hemorrhage, and catastrophic thrombosis around the body. Increases in the levels of inflammatory cytokines were associated with fatality from Ebola hemorrhagic fever in literature. Adsorption of cytokines by porous carbons is one the most effective ways for their selective, quick, and complete removal from blood circulation. The problem with adsorption of cytokines is that they have large variations in molecular size and shape, some being small and elongated (as interleukins, which can be adsorbed in pores of &gt; 5 nanometers in diameter), others large and globular (as TNF-&alpha;, which can be adsorbed in pores ~10 nanometers and larger in diameter). When a mix of these molecules is present, larger molecules quickly stick to the outer surface of the adsorbent particles blocking access to the smaller pores for smaller molecules, significantly reducing available surface. Thus, it is difficult to effectively adsorb all cytokines with one adsorbent having pores of uniform size and shape. To accomplish the goal of the project, we have synthesized 25 different carbon adsorbents of 3 major types: carbide derived carbons, polymer ceramics derived carbons, and thermally expanded graphite. Porosity and surface area of these adsorbents have been measured. Adsorption of two pro-inflammatory cytokines (IL-8 and IL-6), whose levels are known to be elevated at the Ebola virus disease, has been measured for these adsorbents. We have found that polymer ceramics derived mesoporous carbons reduce the levels of IL-8 8-10 fold (from 2000 pg/mL down to 300-200 pg/mL) and the levels of IL-6 decrease 2-3 fold (from 1000 pg/mL down to 500-300 pg/mL) within an hour. These polymer derived mesoporous carbons can be produced in form of millimeter-sized particles or even porous monoliths for subsequent incorporation in blood perfusion cartridges to quickly block those cytokine mediated processes which result in devastating symptoms, triggered by the Ebola virus. The results obtained in this study will be important in the development of inexpensive blood perfusion techniques and devices aimed at fighting the Ebola virus disease, as well as other biological and chemical threats, including sepsis, exposure to ecotoxicants, as well as to various exo- and endotoxins, which are of concern for the general public .       Last Modified: 07/06/2015       Submitted by: Vadym Mochalin]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
