<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>I-Corps:  Feasibility Study for Commercializing a Domain-Specific Big Data Analytics Cloud Software Stack</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>12/15/2014</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2016</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>50000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>50000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07070000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>IIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Industrial Innovation &amp; Partnersh</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Steven Konsek</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>skonsek@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927021</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>In the so-called big data era, the data in many companies are becoming too big to be processed and stored by traditional computing platforms. There are urgent needs to address the challenge from ever-increasing big data facing these industries, especially for small companies and contractors who do not have large scale computing infrastructure. Those big companies that have the large scale computing infrastructure, are currently using the traditional High Performance Computing (HPC) techniques to handle the big data requirements. However, the traditional HPC techniques were designed to process computation intensive works, instead of data-intensive jobs. Moreover, the traditional HPC requires deep knowledge and expertise in HPC architectures and uses low-level parallel programming models, which typically create an obstacle for the regular users and domain experts to utilize HPC infrastructure directly. This I-Corps team proposes the cloud computing technique that provides a cost-effective solution to address the computation and storage requirements, which is especially useful to small companies and startups.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project is to explore the commercialization opportunities for a software stack that stores, processes and analyzes big volume of data in a variety of domains, including petroleum seismic data, medical images, retails, energy and more. Besides the scalable performance and fault-tolerance features provided by the software stack, it also provides high-level programming templates, workflow and a domain specific language to simplify the usage of large scale computing platforms. The proposed cloud-based software stack will deliver a customized computing platform service via a user-friendly web interface that is designed to fill the gap between the big data analytics platforms and the customer?s requirements in a variety of domains. The targeted users are data scientists, analysts, researchers and developers in the petroleum, medical and other industrial domains dealing with big volume of data.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>12/12/2014</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>12/12/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1518140</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Lei</FirstName>
<LastName>Huang</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Lei Huang</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>lhuang@pvamu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>9362619878</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000548424</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>12/12/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Prairie View A &amp; M University</Name>
<CityName>Prairie View</CityName>
<ZipCode>774460519</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>9362611689</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>P.O. Box 519</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[MS 1230]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Texas</StateName>
<StateCode>TX</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>10</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>TX10</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>138170220</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>PRAIRIE VIEW A&amp;M UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>138170220</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Prairie View A & M University]]></Name>
<CityName>Prairie View</CityName>
<StateCode>TX</StateCode>
<ZipCode>774460667</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[SR Collins, Room 111]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Texas</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>10</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>TX10</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>8023</Code>
<Text>I-Corps</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0115</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2015~50000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The NSF I-Corps project supports the Cloud Computing Research Lab at Prairie View A&amp;M University (PVAMU) to explore the feasibility of commercializing the cloud computing and big data analytics research conduct in the lab to the industry since the end of 2014. The project provided vital training to the faculty and students of the research lab for entrepreneurship knowledge and significantly transformed the research methodology in the lab. The most valuable outcomes of the project are the entrepreneurship training to the team and the unique marketing experience the team received from conducting 102 interviews with industry professionals. The team collected valuable user's requirements from these interviews&nbsp;and established networks/collaborations with multiple companies, which dramatically enhanced the research lab's capacity. The project provides invaluable training and experience to the PVAMU graduate and undergraduate students who involve into the project and encourages them to explore entrepreneurship in their careers.&nbsp;</p> <p>As a result, the lab was awarded by the successive NSF AIR (Accelerate Innovative Research) program to develop a prototype of petroleum data analytics platform with commercialization goal in 2015. The lab has collaborated with experts in Geophysics and industry to develop the seismic data analytics software prototype, which is a pioneer in the field. Moreover, the lab also works with Texas A&amp;M Commercialization Office, and a group of MBA students at the University of Texas-Austin to work on the business plan and commercialization feasibility study for the software package. The software package is currently still under active development, and the lab has demonstrated its functionality in the SEG conference in late 2016. While the team is continuously performing research to address the critical challenges in the industry, the research has been recognized by industry and research community with numerous invited&nbsp;research talks to a variety of communities and companies. &nbsp;The team will pursue to set up a startup in 2017 to make the research out of the research lab and create a big data analytics software product to the oil &amp; gas industry.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 03/31/2017<br>      Modified by: Lei&nbsp;Huang</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The NSF I-Corps project supports the Cloud Computing Research Lab at Prairie View A&amp;M University (PVAMU) to explore the feasibility of commercializing the cloud computing and big data analytics research conduct in the lab to the industry since the end of 2014. The project provided vital training to the faculty and students of the research lab for entrepreneurship knowledge and significantly transformed the research methodology in the lab. The most valuable outcomes of the project are the entrepreneurship training to the team and the unique marketing experience the team received from conducting 102 interviews with industry professionals. The team collected valuable user's requirements from these interviews and established networks/collaborations with multiple companies, which dramatically enhanced the research lab's capacity. The project provides invaluable training and experience to the PVAMU graduate and undergraduate students who involve into the project and encourages them to explore entrepreneurship in their careers.   As a result, the lab was awarded by the successive NSF AIR (Accelerate Innovative Research) program to develop a prototype of petroleum data analytics platform with commercialization goal in 2015. The lab has collaborated with experts in Geophysics and industry to develop the seismic data analytics software prototype, which is a pioneer in the field. Moreover, the lab also works with Texas A&amp;M Commercialization Office, and a group of MBA students at the University of Texas-Austin to work on the business plan and commercialization feasibility study for the software package. The software package is currently still under active development, and the lab has demonstrated its functionality in the SEG conference in late 2016. While the team is continuously performing research to address the critical challenges in the industry, the research has been recognized by industry and research community with numerous invited research talks to a variety of communities and companies.  The team will pursue to set up a startup in 2017 to make the research out of the research lab and create a big data analytics software product to the oil &amp; gas industry.          Last Modified: 03/31/2017       Submitted by: Lei Huang]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
