<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Collaborative Research: Investigations on Fluids, Gauge Fields, Matrix Models and Gravity</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/15/2015</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>135000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>135000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03010000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>PHY</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Physics</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Keith Dienes</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>kdienes@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032925314</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This Collaborative award funds the research activities of Professors V.P. Nair and A.P. Polychronakos at the City College of the City University of New York, and Professor Daniel Kabat at Lehman College of the City University of New York.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Physics made tremendous strides during the 20th century, with the landmark achievements of general relativity, relevant to the universe at large, and quantum theory, relevant to the microscopic structure of matter. Further progress calls for studying situations in which our understanding of these theories is incomplete. The interior of a black hole and the binding of quarks to form atomic nuclei are two examples of poorly understood situations. This research program brings powerful mathematical tools to bear on these and related problems.  As a result, research in this area advances the national interest by promoting the progress of science in one of its most fundamental directions:   the discovery and understanding of new physical laws.  Moreover, this research will involve graduate and undergraduate students, providing ideal training for the next generation of scientists and science educators. By running a joint program between City College and Lehman College we achieve a critical mass and can draw on a large pool of students, especially from minority and under-represented groups which are a large part of the student body at both colleges.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;More technically, this project furthers an investigation into a new formulation of fluid dynamics focusing on symmetry structures. It elaborates on previously initiated techniques to study gauge theories in 2+1 dimensions and their extension to the realistic case of four dimensions. New calculational techniques, developed by Professors Kabat, Nair and others, will be used to explore the effects of spin and novel boundary conditions on the Casimir force. Various aspects of field theory on "fuzzy" (noncommutative) spaces will be explored using recently developed techniques, the eventual goal being an effective action which captures nonperturbative effects in the large-N (continuum) limit.  Finally the AdS/CFT correspondence will be used as a precise formulation of quantum gravity to investigate how local bulk physics emerges from the CFT.  Previous work by Kabat and collaborators, relying on 1/N perturbation theory to represent local bulk observables in the CFT, will be extended to higher orders in 1/N and used to constrain CFT four-point functions.  The entanglement structure of the CFT will be used to study the black hole interior, and the failure of bulk locality at finite N for black holes and cosmology will be investigated.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>09/11/2015</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/03/2017</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1519705</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Daniel</FirstName>
<LastName>Kabat</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Daniel Kabat</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>daniel.kabat@lehman.cuny.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>7189607832</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000451946</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/11/2015</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Research Foundation Of The City University Of New York (Lehman)</Name>
<CityName>Bronx</CityName>
<ZipCode>104681589</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>7189608107</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>250 Bedford Park Blvd West</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>13</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NY13</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>620128301</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>RESEARCH FOUNDATION OF THE CITY UNIVERSITY OF NEW YORK</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>073268849</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[CUNY Herbert H Lehman College]]></Name>
<CityName>Bronx</CityName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<ZipCode>104681589</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[250 Bedford Park Blvd West]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>13</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NY13</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1286</Code>
<Text>Elem. Particle Physics/Theory</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0115</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0116</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0117</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2015~45000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2016~45000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2017~45000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Gravity is one of the most familiar forces in everyday life, and at first glance it also appears to be one of the simplest: ever since Galileo it's been known that all objects fall toward the earth with the same constant acceleration. &nbsp;But this simple behavior is only an approximation, and more refined studies have found that gravity is in fact much more complicated. &nbsp;Over large distances gravity can be understood in terms of a bending of space and time, and in this way gravity is the force that is responsible for shaping the universe as a whole. &nbsp;But at short distances the correct description of gravity remains unknown.<br />The research funded by this award seeks to develop a better understanding of gravity, using a mathematical framework that grew out of string theory. &nbsp;The goal of the research is to apply the framework (known as AdS/CFT) to concrete situations and extract lessons about the behavior of gravity. &nbsp;For example the AdS/CFT framework was used to study what happens inside a black hole. &nbsp;We found that the description of gravity in terms of space-time geometry breaks down, but in a way that is not apparent to someone who falls into the black hole. &nbsp;We also considered tiny effects that are expected to arise "non-perturbatively" from AdS/CFT and showed that, in addition to causing the space-time geometry to break down, these effects may also violate some of the basic assumptions of quantum mechanics.<br />This award had significant broader impacts, in particular in education and training. &nbsp;For example a simple and intuitive way of thinking about curved space-time is to view space itself as a type of moving fluid. &nbsp;One of the projects supported by this award developed the fluid description for spinning black holes. &nbsp;This work was carried out in collaboration with a graduate student and a local high school student, who both received valuable training and experience as a result. &nbsp;By providing students with an opportunity to engage in advanced scientific research, especially at a minority-serving institution like Lehman College, this award helped develop a broad and deep interest in science that will pay dividends for years to come.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 10/11/2018<br>      Modified by: Daniel&nbsp;Kabat</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Gravity is one of the most familiar forces in everyday life, and at first glance it also appears to be one of the simplest: ever since Galileo it's been known that all objects fall toward the earth with the same constant acceleration.  But this simple behavior is only an approximation, and more refined studies have found that gravity is in fact much more complicated.  Over large distances gravity can be understood in terms of a bending of space and time, and in this way gravity is the force that is responsible for shaping the universe as a whole.  But at short distances the correct description of gravity remains unknown. The research funded by this award seeks to develop a better understanding of gravity, using a mathematical framework that grew out of string theory.  The goal of the research is to apply the framework (known as AdS/CFT) to concrete situations and extract lessons about the behavior of gravity.  For example the AdS/CFT framework was used to study what happens inside a black hole.  We found that the description of gravity in terms of space-time geometry breaks down, but in a way that is not apparent to someone who falls into the black hole.  We also considered tiny effects that are expected to arise "non-perturbatively" from AdS/CFT and showed that, in addition to causing the space-time geometry to break down, these effects may also violate some of the basic assumptions of quantum mechanics. This award had significant broader impacts, in particular in education and training.  For example a simple and intuitive way of thinking about curved space-time is to view space itself as a type of moving fluid.  One of the projects supported by this award developed the fluid description for spinning black holes.  This work was carried out in collaboration with a graduate student and a local high school student, who both received valuable training and experience as a result.  By providing students with an opportunity to engage in advanced scientific research, especially at a minority-serving institution like Lehman College, this award helped develop a broad and deep interest in science that will pay dividends for years to come.             Last Modified: 10/11/2018       Submitted by: Daniel Kabat]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
