<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>RAPID: Capturing the physics of mountain uplift near the South Alpine Fault New Zealand</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>01/15/2015</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2015</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>31500.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>31500</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>06030204</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>GEO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>EAR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Earth Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Eva Zanzerkia</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>ezanzerk@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924734</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Although mountains are commonly considered fixtures in the landscape, at geological time-scales they are transient phenomena that exist only where the competing processes of rock uplift and erosion are almost exactly balanced.  Where uplift exceeds erosion the height of mountains increase.  Without uplift a mountain range will eventually be eroded to gentle hills, and eventually to a flat plain.  Three types of processes can account for the rise of rocks within a mountain range.  The first is caused by squeezing a rock, akin to squeezing a rubber eraser horizontally whose surface will rise in proportion to the amount of horizontal contraction. The second is caused by horizontal slip toward a subsurface ramp, a thrust fault, which is similar to rock rising on an elevator powered by plate tectonics.  The third process causes rocks to rise in response to the incision of valleys and the removal of rock by rivers.  This rise (known as isostasy) is similar to the rise of an iceberg from the sea as its exposed surface is melted by warm air.  Each of these processes results in the rise of rocks, but the mass lost in each case is different.  By measuring the rise of the rocks and the associated mass change in a mountain range one can distinguish between these three mechanisms.  The rise of a mountain summit can easily be measured using GPS methods. The reduction of mass in a mountain range can be measured with a gravity meter.  The PI measured both in the southern Alps of New Zealand in January 2000 but to determine the answer a second measurement is need. GPS measurements indicate the height has increased by about 80 mm in the past 15 years.  In January 2015 the PI shall for the first time measure the reduction of gravity using the NSF absolute gravimeter.  Unless an earthquake intervenes, the mechanisms that cause the high elevations of mountains in the southern Alps of New Zealand will be revealed.  Should an earthquake occur before the measurements are undertaken, however, the answer may be rendered ambiguous by mass movements accompanying the landslides triggered by severe shaking. For this reason it is urgent to have this NSF RAPID award and make a timely measurement in the southern Alps of New Zealand.  &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;In 2000, NSF funded 16 measurements of absolute value of gravity in New Zealand, mostly near the Southern Alps to investigate the physics of interseismic mountain uplift using a combination of gravity (which is sensitive to local density variations) and GPS (which is not).  The FG5 gravimeter is uniquely drift-free since it measures the acceleration of a freely falling mirror in a vacuum to an accuracy of 10^-11 using an atomic clock and a stabilized laser. Proposed mountain building mechanisms (Poissons-ratio uplift, listric fault slip, or erosion-induced isostatic uplift) are associated with different ratios of uplift to gravity decrease. Now, 15 years later, 8 cm of uplift has occurred and the PI plans to take the same gravimeter to the same summit points to determine the associated lowering in gravity. The accuracy of the gravimeter is 1 µGal, and the decrease in gravity should be about 27 µGal- a significant signal-to-noise ratio. Urgency is associated with the measurements in that should a local earthquake occur, as it did near the Christchurch measurements, landslides may render the gravity signal ambiguous. The Alpine fault is in fact many decades past its median recurrence interval and the probability of rupture in a Mw&gt;8 earthquake is sufficiently high that a device to capture its slip velocity operated in the next few years has a significant chance of doing so. Although the propagation velocity of a rupture can easily be quantified from seismometers (2.5-3.5 km/s) the sliding velocity of the surface fault (0.1-10m/s) has hitherto never been measured. During the gravity measurements suitable locations to install two rupture meters will be identified. Each consists of a graphite rod anchored obliquely across the fault, that pulls a wire from a rotating drum during fault slip. Its measurement range is 13 m, its resolution is 0.1 mm, its sampling rate is 1 s and the systems can run indefinitely on solar panels.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>01/13/2015</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>01/13/2015</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.050</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1519035</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Roger</FirstName>
<LastName>Bilham</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>G</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Roger G Bilham</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>bilham@colorado.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>3034926189</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000157673</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>01/13/2015</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Colorado at Boulder</Name>
<CityName>Boulder</CityName>
<ZipCode>803031058</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>3034926221</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>3100 Marine Street, Room 481</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[572 UCB]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Colorado</StateName>
<StateCode>CO</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CO02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>007431505</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>REGENTS OF THE UNIVERSITY OF COLORADO, THE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>007431505</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Colorado at Boulder]]></Name>
<CityName>Boulder</CityName>
<StateCode>CO</StateCode>
<ZipCode>803031058</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[3100 Marine Street]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Colorado</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CO02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1574</Code>
<Text>Geophysics</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1580</Code>
<Text>Instrumentation &amp; Facilities</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7914</Code>
<Text>RAPID</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0115</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2015~31500</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>We are surrounded by mountains, yet rivers and glaciers are continuously at work eroding summits and deepening valleys. &nbsp;The rivers remove rocks and pebbles and transport their finely pulverized or dissolved remnants to the sea. These erosional processes would seem to be too slow to have much effect on the mountains we see, but because they act for millions of years, they are able to reduce any mountain, first to hills and eventually to a featureless plain. We conclude, then, that for mountains to exist at all they must be driven to their current positions by forces beneath them and that these forces are at work today.</p> <p>The project we undertook was designed to use gravity to resolve between different mechanisms that have been proposed for raising the rocks of mountain ranges to elevations that are often miles above sea level. &nbsp;We chose to undertake this study in the New Zealand Alps, where elevations are not particularly large (&asymp;1 mile) but uplift rates are fast. &nbsp;We completed our first measurements in the year 2000 and our second measurements in 2015, by which time some of the mountains and ridges had risen by 4 inches, and points near the Christchurch earthquake had risen by almost 10 inches.</p> <p>We measured the height increase of 16 points with GPS methods (see map) and &nbsp;the reduction of the Earth's gravity of &nbsp;these same points using a gravimeter. The gravimeter we deployed &nbsp;(see picture) measures the acceleration of a mass falling towards the center of the earth directly in terms of atomic units of length and time to an accuracy of 1 part in 1000 million. &nbsp;The instrument has none of the drift associated with conventional gravity meters, permitting measurements to be conducted 100 years apart with no loss in accuracy. &nbsp;Its disadvantage is that it is heavy, and must &nbsp;be moved in the mountains by helicopter.</p> <p>We discovered &nbsp;that gravity reduces in proportion to increasing height at a rate consistent with the rise of rocks with the approximate density of the Earth's continents. &nbsp;The presence of spurious movements of ice and water added noise to the data, and did not permit us to exclude the possibility that denser rocks of the Earth's mantle (rich in dense crystals like olivene) are also rising beneath the southern Alps. &nbsp;The Christchurch earthquake occurred in 2010 between our two measurements and this provided additional insights into gravity changes in New Zealand. An abrupt decrease occurred locally at the time of the earthquake in the region of uplift south of Christchurch, and an increase occurred in the region subsidense near the center of Christchurch (see graphs of gravity change). &nbsp;A scientific article describing the intellectual consequences of our results will shortly be published.</p> <p>While undertaking the gravity research we discovered evidence that ancient forests on the west coast of the New Zealand alps had been destroyed by tsunami resulting from earthquakes 4-5 times in the past 7000 years. &nbsp;The trunks of these trees had been rent and splintered and in some cases their roots drowned by faulting associated with slip on the faults that are active during some phases of mountain growth. &nbsp;An article describing the fragmentary record of these rare but apparently violent tsunami will shortly be published with New Zealand and Australian collaborators.</p> <p>The broader applications of our studies are related to the interaction between mountains, earthquakes, glaciers and people, and how gravimeters can be used to monitor subsurface water resources. &nbsp;Our gravimeter is particularly sensitive to the presence of local bodies of water or ice and we identified methods to quantify its subtle loss or gain on a regional scale in cases where we have good control on height changes. &nbsp;In principle we can measure subsurface water level changes (without a wate...]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ We are surrounded by mountains, yet rivers and glaciers are continuously at work eroding summits and deepening valleys.  The rivers remove rocks and pebbles and transport their finely pulverized or dissolved remnants to the sea. These erosional processes would seem to be too slow to have much effect on the mountains we see, but because they act for millions of years, they are able to reduce any mountain, first to hills and eventually to a featureless plain. We conclude, then, that for mountains to exist at all they must be driven to their current positions by forces beneath them and that these forces are at work today.  The project we undertook was designed to use gravity to resolve between different mechanisms that have been proposed for raising the rocks of mountain ranges to elevations that are often miles above sea level.  We chose to undertake this study in the New Zealand Alps, where elevations are not particularly large (&asymp;1 mile) but uplift rates are fast.  We completed our first measurements in the year 2000 and our second measurements in 2015, by which time some of the mountains and ridges had risen by 4 inches, and points near the Christchurch earthquake had risen by almost 10 inches.  We measured the height increase of 16 points with GPS methods (see map) and  the reduction of the Earth's gravity of  these same points using a gravimeter. The gravimeter we deployed  (see picture) measures the acceleration of a mass falling towards the center of the earth directly in terms of atomic units of length and time to an accuracy of 1 part in 1000 million.  The instrument has none of the drift associated with conventional gravity meters, permitting measurements to be conducted 100 years apart with no loss in accuracy.  Its disadvantage is that it is heavy, and must  be moved in the mountains by helicopter.  We discovered  that gravity reduces in proportion to increasing height at a rate consistent with the rise of rocks with the approximate density of the Earth's continents.  The presence of spurious movements of ice and water added noise to the data, and did not permit us to exclude the possibility that denser rocks of the Earth's mantle (rich in dense crystals like olivene) are also rising beneath the southern Alps.  The Christchurch earthquake occurred in 2010 between our two measurements and this provided additional insights into gravity changes in New Zealand. An abrupt decrease occurred locally at the time of the earthquake in the region of uplift south of Christchurch, and an increase occurred in the region subsidense near the center of Christchurch (see graphs of gravity change).  A scientific article describing the intellectual consequences of our results will shortly be published.  While undertaking the gravity research we discovered evidence that ancient forests on the west coast of the New Zealand alps had been destroyed by tsunami resulting from earthquakes 4-5 times in the past 7000 years.  The trunks of these trees had been rent and splintered and in some cases their roots drowned by faulting associated with slip on the faults that are active during some phases of mountain growth.  An article describing the fragmentary record of these rare but apparently violent tsunami will shortly be published with New Zealand and Australian collaborators.  The broader applications of our studies are related to the interaction between mountains, earthquakes, glaciers and people, and how gravimeters can be used to monitor subsurface water resources.  Our gravimeter is particularly sensitive to the presence of local bodies of water or ice and we identified methods to quantify its subtle loss or gain on a regional scale in cases where we have good control on height changes.  In principle we can measure subsurface water level changes (without a water well) in desert acquifers to an accuracy of 1 inch, no matter at what depth these occur. Conversely, these same local distributions of ice and water effectively mask the much ...]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
