<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Doctoral Dissertation Research: Factors Affecting the Economic Integration of Refugees</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>06/01/2015</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2016</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>11641.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>11641</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>04050000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>SBE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>SES</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Divn Of Social and Economic Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Patricia White</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Each year the U.S. receives approximately 70,000 refugees for permanent resettlement. The principle goals of resettlement are integration and self-sufficiency, and refugee adaptation has been a persistent subject of inquiry for immigration research. Existing literature examines how diverse skills and life experiences have contributed to divergent trajectories of social and economic integration. Despite extensive research into the effects of skills and life experiences on the economic integration of refugees there is a great deal of variation in economic outcomes that are not understood. Moreover, measuring the degree to which a refugee is capable of deploying their skills and training has been quite difficult and has rarely been done. The purpose of this study is to understand the factors contributing to the successful economic integration of refugees. It builds on the existing literature by examining skills, life experiences, and contexts with attention to the potential barriers that restrict the individual's capability of using their assets to promote integration and self-sufficiency.  &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The researchers will use a mixed methods approach to analyze several forms of economic integration including labor market participation, the acquisition of a livable wage, and occupational mobility. Quantitative data for the study comes from the individual case files of refugees seeking employment assistance at the Refugee and Immigrant Center of Utah. Sets of characteristics that comprise individual capabilities will be identified using Qualitative Comparative Analysis. This analysis will determine the necessary and sufficient factors that generate several different recipes for successful economic integration. These individual factors and "recipes for success" will then be analyzed for their affect on the duration between arrival in the U.S., labor market participation and the acquisition of a livable wage using Event History Analysis. Qualitative data will be collected in a series of focus groups with local service providers and with refugees. Insights from focus groups will be triangulated with quantitative data to enhance our understanding of refugee capabilities and their relationship to economic outcomes. By better understanding the factors that shape the early economic integration experiences of refugees, we will be better equipped to promote sustainable self-sufficiency after resettlement.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>05/15/2015</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/15/2015</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.075</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1519313</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Kim</FirstName>
<LastName>Korinek</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>M</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Kim M Korinek</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>kim.korinek@soc.utah.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>8015816903</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000333872</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/15/2015</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Yvette</FirstName>
<LastName>Young</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>M</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Yvette M Young</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>yvette.young@soc.utah.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>8015816153</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000666997</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/15/2015</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Utah</Name>
<CityName>SALT LAKE CITY</CityName>
<ZipCode>841128930</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>8015816903</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>75 S 2000 E</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[Second Floor]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Utah</StateName>
<StateCode>UT</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>UT02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>009095365</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF UTAH, THE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>009095365</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Utah]]></Name>
<CityName>Salt Lake City</CityName>
<StateCode>UT</StateCode>
<ZipCode>841128930</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[75 South 2000 East]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Utah</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>UT02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1331</Code>
<Text>Sociology</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1331</Code>
<Text>SOCIOLOGY</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9179</Code>
<Text>GRADUATE INVOLVEMENT</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0115</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2015~11641</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>In the United States finding adequate employment is partially contingent upon the education, skills, and previous work experience of the applicant. However, during the recent economic recession many highly skilled workers failed to find employment. The prospects for job seekers with low skill levels and limited experience are dismal. And, the disadvantage is compounded for non-native job seekers like refugees. Each year the United States receives between sixty and seventy thousand refugees from around the world for permanent resettlement, and the state of Utah resettles approximately 1,000 of these individuals annually. The principal goals of resettlement are social integration and self-sufficiency, especially economic self-sufficiency. Existing research emphasizes how the diverse skills and life experiences, have contributed to divergent trajectories of social and economic integration. The refugees resettled in Utah come from nearly 60 different nations, and they arrive in Utah with greatly varying skills and life experiences. Some speak English; others do not. Some are educated and have held good jobs in their country of origin; others have had little or no education and minimal job experience in their former homes. Some come from relatively modern regions of the world. Others have never seen a microwave and never had electricity in their homes. The combined lack of skills and limited cultural knowledge possessed by many refugees can make self-sufficiency especially difficult to achieve.</p> <p>This project explored the question: <em>What individual characteristics and societal factors affect the amount of time it takes for refugees to become economically self-sufficient?</em> I specifically examined how long it takes to get the first job after resettlement, advance in the workplace, and acquire a livable wage? I wanted to understand, first, the extent to which individual skills and training prepare refugees for success in the Utah labor market, second, how individual barriers limit the effectiveness of individual skills in the labor market, and third, how societal opportunity structures enhance or limit employment prospects.</p> <p>To investigate these issues I employed two research methods. First, I analyzed data extracted from the case files of refugees who sought employment assistance from local refugee service agencies. After analyzing this data, I conducted focus group interviews with Utah refugee groups.</p> <p>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; Analysis of the case file data indicated that refugee skills, education, and training are severely undervalued in the Utah labor market. Also, using social connections to find a job was only beneficial for women. Men who used social connections took longer to find their first job and longer to obtain a livable wage than men who did not use their social connections. As expected, high rates of poverty and unemployment reduced the likelihood of finding adequate employment. And, in years when the Salt Lake community expressed more negative attitudes toward immigrants, this manifested poor refugee employment outcomes.</p> <p>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; Finally, the focus groups helped explain some of these surprising findings. First, informants noted that lower levels of education might have no effect because employers ask refugees to provide documentation of their education, while they do not ask the same of native-born applicants. Second, some employment specific cultural behaviors create difficulties for refugees seeking jobs and reduce job retention. Despite training in American employment norms simple differences in communication styles and different understandings of the importance of timeliness, communication with employers in the event of illness or tardiness, and gender norms in the workplace, among other things, create difficulties for refugees. Third, Somali women face religious discrimination due to their practice of wearing hijabs and dresses. Employers cite OSHA regulations for their discriminatory practices even when no such regulation is in place for the particular job. However, women who are educated enough and speak English well enough to obtain a professional job do not experience the same discrimination. Fourth, the Somali Muslim women do not perceive any discrimination based on race, only their Muslim identity, which is visible only do to the fact that they are women. This offers support for the theory that "conspicuous foreignness" matters more than race in the job market. It also speaks to the intersectionality of refugee identities.</p> <p>The findings from this project necessitate a more comprehensive theory of refugee economic integration than has previously been offered. The factors that affect a refugee&rsquo;s prospects for economic self-sufficiency are determined by a complex system of interactions between a refugee&rsquo;s individual characteristics and the attributes of the resettlement context, specifically features of the social, cultural and economic environment in Utah. Also, individual characteristics and the characteristics of the social context coevolve and two-way integration is required for sustained self-sufficiency to occur. Economic integration is interactive, and a refugee&rsquo;s economic prospects stem from an intersection of characteristics, opportunities, and social context. In other words, a refugee's <em>capabilities</em> in the labor market are based not only on their functional abilities but on the "freedom" they have to use their abilities.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 08/01/2016<br>      Modified by: Yvette&nbsp;M&nbsp;Young</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ In the United States finding adequate employment is partially contingent upon the education, skills, and previous work experience of the applicant. However, during the recent economic recession many highly skilled workers failed to find employment. The prospects for job seekers with low skill levels and limited experience are dismal. And, the disadvantage is compounded for non-native job seekers like refugees. Each year the United States receives between sixty and seventy thousand refugees from around the world for permanent resettlement, and the state of Utah resettles approximately 1,000 of these individuals annually. The principal goals of resettlement are social integration and self-sufficiency, especially economic self-sufficiency. Existing research emphasizes how the diverse skills and life experiences, have contributed to divergent trajectories of social and economic integration. The refugees resettled in Utah come from nearly 60 different nations, and they arrive in Utah with greatly varying skills and life experiences. Some speak English; others do not. Some are educated and have held good jobs in their country of origin; others have had little or no education and minimal job experience in their former homes. Some come from relatively modern regions of the world. Others have never seen a microwave and never had electricity in their homes. The combined lack of skills and limited cultural knowledge possessed by many refugees can make self-sufficiency especially difficult to achieve.  This project explored the question: What individual characteristics and societal factors affect the amount of time it takes for refugees to become economically self-sufficient? I specifically examined how long it takes to get the first job after resettlement, advance in the workplace, and acquire a livable wage? I wanted to understand, first, the extent to which individual skills and training prepare refugees for success in the Utah labor market, second, how individual barriers limit the effectiveness of individual skills in the labor market, and third, how societal opportunity structures enhance or limit employment prospects.  To investigate these issues I employed two research methods. First, I analyzed data extracted from the case files of refugees who sought employment assistance from local refugee service agencies. After analyzing this data, I conducted focus group interviews with Utah refugee groups.      Analysis of the case file data indicated that refugee skills, education, and training are severely undervalued in the Utah labor market. Also, using social connections to find a job was only beneficial for women. Men who used social connections took longer to find their first job and longer to obtain a livable wage than men who did not use their social connections. As expected, high rates of poverty and unemployment reduced the likelihood of finding adequate employment. And, in years when the Salt Lake community expressed more negative attitudes toward immigrants, this manifested poor refugee employment outcomes.       Finally, the focus groups helped explain some of these surprising findings. First, informants noted that lower levels of education might have no effect because employers ask refugees to provide documentation of their education, while they do not ask the same of native-born applicants. Second, some employment specific cultural behaviors create difficulties for refugees seeking jobs and reduce job retention. Despite training in American employment norms simple differences in communication styles and different understandings of the importance of timeliness, communication with employers in the event of illness or tardiness, and gender norms in the workplace, among other things, create difficulties for refugees. Third, Somali women face religious discrimination due to their practice of wearing hijabs and dresses. Employers cite OSHA regulations for their discriminatory practices even when no such regulation is in place for the particular job. However, women who are educated enough and speak English well enough to obtain a professional job do not experience the same discrimination. Fourth, the Somali Muslim women do not perceive any discrimination based on race, only their Muslim identity, which is visible only do to the fact that they are women. This offers support for the theory that "conspicuous foreignness" matters more than race in the job market. It also speaks to the intersectionality of refugee identities.  The findings from this project necessitate a more comprehensive theory of refugee economic integration than has previously been offered. The factors that affect a refugee?s prospects for economic self-sufficiency are determined by a complex system of interactions between a refugee?s individual characteristics and the attributes of the resettlement context, specifically features of the social, cultural and economic environment in Utah. Also, individual characteristics and the characteristics of the social context coevolve and two-way integration is required for sustained self-sufficiency to occur. Economic integration is interactive, and a refugee?s economic prospects stem from an intersection of characteristics, opportunities, and social context. In other words, a refugee's capabilities in the labor market are based not only on their functional abilities but on the "freedom" they have to use their abilities.          Last Modified: 08/01/2016       Submitted by: Yvette M Young]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
