<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>SBIR Phase I:  Magnetoreception Sensors for Field Enabled Navigation</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2015</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2016</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>150000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>179999</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07070000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>IIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Industrial Innovation &amp; Partnersh</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Muralidharan Nair</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>mnair@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927059</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The broader impact/commercial potential of this project is the superiority of the accuracy of magnetoreception sensor technology, compared to the state-of-the-art for the aviation industry. In February 2012, Congress passed the FAA Modernization and Reform Act, requiring the Secretary of Transportation to develop a plan to (1) accelerate safely the integration of civil UASs into the national airspace system, and, before completion of the plan, (2) determine if certain drones can operate safely in the national airspace system, with particular emphasis on the need to examine the vulnerability of UASs to GPS spoofing. In 2010, the Federal Aviation Administration?s (FAA), in CFR §92.225 and §91.227 on Next Generation Air Transportation System (NextGen), mandated that, by 2020, all aircraft be equipped with Automatic Dependant Surveillance-Broadcast (ADS-B Out), which provides minute-by-minute transmission of location and altitude to air traffic control. To comply with the ADS-B Out mandate, more than 250,000 civilian general aviation aircraft will require the installation of new navigation capabilities. Unfortunately, much of the equipment needed to comply with the ADS-B Out mandate is still in development, and airline operators are working with industry to achieve compliance. The global civilian aerospace avionics market is estimated to be at $8.3 billion. The North American Military Avionics market is $13.5 billion.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This Small Business Innovation Research (SBIR) Phase I project seeks to develop a high-sensitivity wireless magnetoreception sensor technology with fifth order accuracy, for detecting the Earth?s magnetic field. The targeted sensitivity is more than an order of magnitude greater than the state-of-the-art, and the technology has the potential to be widely adopted in civilian and military aviation for proper real time definition of spatial orientation; guidance and control of unmanned airline systems (UASs); and the biomedical industry. This proposal will determine the feasibility of measuring the spin resonance from the interaction of the magnetic field with radical pair ions ? that is, magnetoreception ? as a means to the development of an accurate sensor of the Earth?s field. This innovative technology is based on scientific knowledge of avian magnetoreception. The resulting accuracy will enable altitude to be determined within a few feet, compared to within a few hundred meters in the state-of-the-art. The magnetoreception sensors will be disruptive to the avionics industry. The Phase I work will also determine the feasibility of (1) construction and testing of a zero field resonance spectrometer, and (2) construction and testing of ultra low-frequency electron spin resonance (ESR) spectrometer for studying spin resonance as selected radical pair ions interact with the Earth?s magnetic field.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/15/2015</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>12/15/2015</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1519795</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Bamidele</FirstName>
<LastName>Omotowa</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>A</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Bamidele A Omotowa</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>bomotowa@yahoo.com</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2083461253</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000076522</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/15/2015</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Pearlhill Technologies, LLC</Name>
<CityName>Idaho Falls</CityName>
<ZipCode>834014629</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2085232266</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>616 S Adam Ln</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Idaho</StateName>
<StateCode>ID</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>ID02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>800333002</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>PEARLHILL TECHNOLOGIES, LLC</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Pearlhill Technologies LLC]]></Name>
<CityName>Idaho Falls</CityName>
<StateCode>ID</StateCode>
<ZipCode>834014629</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[101 Technology Dr]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Idaho</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>ID02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>5371</Code>
<Text>SBIR Phase I</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1185</Code>
<Text>SENSORY SYSTEMS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>163E</Code>
<Text>SBIR Phase IB</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>5371</Code>
<Text>SMALL BUSINESS PHASE I</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>6840</Code>
<Text>ROBOTICS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8035</Code>
<Text>Hardware Devices</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>HPCC</Code>
<Text>HIGH PERFORMANCE COMPUTING &amp; COMM</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0115</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0116</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2015~150000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2016~29999</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Two separate developments informed the impetus for the Phase I project - (1) the International Geophysics Reference Field (IGRF) was produced as an internationally agreed-upon model of the earth&rsquo;s isotonic magnetic field, with field intensities ranging from 30,000 - 65,000 nT. The IGRF is a very reliable, sophisticated, and accurate predictor of the field pattern for aerial locations on the earth; and (2) scientists determined that several types of animals, especially birds, use magnetic sensory systems for seasonal migration, traveling thousands of miles in sophisticated navigation patterns.&nbsp;Based on these developments, Pearlhill developed a concept for magnetoreception sensors that are related to the animal systems and use simple-to-assemble, yet quite sophisticated, spectrometric techniques. The sensors measure the resonance frequency of the Earth&rsquo;s magnetic field, based on chemo-magnetic interactions between (1) photo-induced radical pairs in certain chemical molecules; and (2) the Earth&rsquo;s low magnetic field. The idea is that when the radical pairs interact with the magnetic field, their electron spin resonance can be calibrated to that field. Then, a novel mathematical model was used to convert the field information to position and altitude on the earth, thereby providing pilots with an important tool for guidance and navigation control. The overarching objective of the Phase I work was to obtain proof of feasibility that zero field resonance (ZFR) and electron spin resonance (ESR) spectrometers could be designed to make these measurements over the range of 25,000 to 75,000 nT, which covers the range of the earth&rsquo;s magnetic field. Specifically, the Phase I work involved the assembly of ZFR and ESR spectrometers, along with associated testing, to prove that either or both spectrometers will measure spin resonance from photo-induced radical pairs generated from potassium peroxylamine disulfonate (compound <strong>1</strong>), photolyase (<strong>2</strong>), cryptochromes (<strong>3</strong>), and pyrene + dicyanobenzene (<strong>4</strong>). All of these risks were overcome in Phase I.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>A number of technical risks were associated with this technology: (1) whether randomly selected radical pairs would actually produce chemo-magnetic interactions with the low fields, leading to spin resonance; (2) whether the observed magnetic field effects would be the result of secondary interactions with interference, leading to hyperfine splitting (resulting in a broad spectral shoulder) rather than a Zeeman interaction (resulting in a sharp peak); and (3) whether the spectral resolution, as indicated by the signal-to-noise ratio and line width, would be good enough to calibrate the spectrometer for magnetic field determination. In Phase I, the magnetoreception sensor technology evaluated: (a) photo induced radical pairs for chemically induced dynamic nuclear polarization (CIDNP); (b) magnetic field effects; (c) photochemical stability; (d) temperature suitability; (e) ZFR spectrometer assembly and measurement; (f) ESR spectrometer assembly and measurement; (g) accuracy of field dependent frequency measurement; and (h) the target Size, Weight, Power and Computation (SWAP-C) specifications.&nbsp;The Phase I results showed that the magnetoreception sensor technology can open up a completely new, transformative approach to field-enabled navigation by demonstrating the capacity to determine the Earth&rsquo;s magnetic field to an accuracy of 0.1 nT. The potential benefits include a capability to determine altitude up to 70,000 ft, with and accuracy of 1 m, at temperatures down to -60 <sup>o</sup> C. This represents a significant improvement over state-of-the-art magnetoresistive sensors produced by Honeywell, which have an accuracy of 1.6 x10<sup>-4</sup> and reads changes of 11 nT in the 30,000 - 65,000 nT range of the Earth's fiel...]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Two separate developments informed the impetus for the Phase I project - (1) the International Geophysics Reference Field (IGRF) was produced as an internationally agreed-upon model of the earthÆs isotonic magnetic field, with field intensities ranging from 30,000 - 65,000 nT. The IGRF is a very reliable, sophisticated, and accurate predictor of the field pattern for aerial locations on the earth; and (2) scientists determined that several types of animals, especially birds, use magnetic sensory systems for seasonal migration, traveling thousands of miles in sophisticated navigation patterns. Based on these developments, Pearlhill developed a concept for magnetoreception sensors that are related to the animal systems and use simple-to-assemble, yet quite sophisticated, spectrometric techniques. The sensors measure the resonance frequency of the EarthÆs magnetic field, based on chemo-magnetic interactions between (1) photo-induced radical pairs in certain chemical molecules; and (2) the EarthÆs low magnetic field. The idea is that when the radical pairs interact with the magnetic field, their electron spin resonance can be calibrated to that field. Then, a novel mathematical model was used to convert the field information to position and altitude on the earth, thereby providing pilots with an important tool for guidance and navigation control. The overarching objective of the Phase I work was to obtain proof of feasibility that zero field resonance (ZFR) and electron spin resonance (ESR) spectrometers could be designed to make these measurements over the range of 25,000 to 75,000 nT, which covers the range of the earthÆs magnetic field. Specifically, the Phase I work involved the assembly of ZFR and ESR spectrometers, along with associated testing, to prove that either or both spectrometers will measure spin resonance from photo-induced radical pairs generated from potassium peroxylamine disulfonate (compound 1), photolyase (2), cryptochromes (3), and pyrene + dicyanobenzene (4). All of these risks were overcome in Phase I.     A number of technical risks were associated with this technology: (1) whether randomly selected radical pairs would actually produce chemo-magnetic interactions with the low fields, leading to spin resonance; (2) whether the observed magnetic field effects would be the result of secondary interactions with interference, leading to hyperfine splitting (resulting in a broad spectral shoulder) rather than a Zeeman interaction (resulting in a sharp peak); and (3) whether the spectral resolution, as indicated by the signal-to-noise ratio and line width, would be good enough to calibrate the spectrometer for magnetic field determination. In Phase I, the magnetoreception sensor technology evaluated: (a) photo induced radical pairs for chemically induced dynamic nuclear polarization (CIDNP); (b) magnetic field effects; (c) photochemical stability; (d) temperature suitability; (e) ZFR spectrometer assembly and measurement; (f) ESR spectrometer assembly and measurement; (g) accuracy of field dependent frequency measurement; and (h) the target Size, Weight, Power and Computation (SWAP-C) specifications. The Phase I results showed that the magnetoreception sensor technology can open up a completely new, transformative approach to field-enabled navigation by demonstrating the capacity to determine the EarthÆs magnetic field to an accuracy of 0.1 nT. The potential benefits include a capability to determine altitude up to 70,000 ft, with and accuracy of 1 m, at temperatures down to -60 o C. This represents a significant improvement over state-of-the-art magnetoresistive sensors produced by Honeywell, which have an accuracy of 1.6 x10-4 and reads changes of 11 nT in the 30,000 - 65,000 nT range of the Earth's field. The Phase I effort also provided a basis for developing a mathematical model and associated software for the spatial orientation of pilots, which could eliminate the cause of 32 % of aircraft accidents glob...]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
