<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Workshop and Conference: K-theory: Future Directions</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>03/01/2015</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>02/28/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>34000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>34000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DMS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Joanna Kania-Bartoszynska</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>jkaniaba@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924881</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The "K-theory: Future Directions" workshop/conference will be held at the Ohio State University, Columbus, Ohio, May 11-16, 2015. K-theory is the study of vector bundles on spaces and provides very important invariants of the space. Depending on the space considered and the variant of K-theory used, these invariants are of importance to different parts of mathematics ranging from algebraic topology to number theory. As a result, the program theme lies in the intersection of very active areas in algebraic topology, algebraic geometry and arithmetic geometry,with major advances made in the area during the last decade. In view of these, the workshop and conference should be of great interest to junior faculty and graduate students who may be starting their research careers. The program will feature several key-note talks which will survey the historical background, current state of development and prospects for future progress in the focused areas. These talks will provide an opportunity to take a longer view than is customary at many research conferences and should be particularly valuable for young researchers.&lt;br/&gt; &lt;br/&gt; &lt;br/&gt;In recent years, there have been several major advances in the field of Algebraic K-theory, leading up to the solution of the Milnor, Bloch-Kato and Lichtenbaum-Quillen conjectures. The powerful techniques introduced for the solution of the above conjectures have stimulated work on several outstanding remaining problems in the area. The workshop and conference will focus on the Koszulity conjecture and the Carlsson conjecture, which are among the main remaining open problems after the solution of the Milnor and Bloch-Kato conjectures. The two conjectures have been around for nearly 20 years and special cases of both have been verified. In view of the solution of the Milnor and Bloch-Kato conjectures,  this shows the importance and relevance of the above workshop and conference. &lt;br/&gt; &lt;br/&gt; &lt;br/&gt;For the conference web-site, please visit https://people.math.osu.edu/joshua.1/Ktheory_conf.html</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>01/16/2015</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>01/16/2015</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1519043</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Roy</FirstName>
<LastName>Joshua</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Roy Joshua</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>joshua@math.ohio-state.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6142924014</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000387220</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>01/16/2015</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Ohio State University</Name>
<CityName>Columbus</CityName>
<ZipCode>432101016</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6146888735</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>Office of Sponsored Programs</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[1960 Kenny Road]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Ohio</StateName>
<StateCode>OH</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>OH03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>832127323</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>OHIO STATE UNIVERSITY, THE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>001964634</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Ohio State University]]></Name>
<CityName>Columbus</CityName>
<StateCode>OH</StateCode>
<ZipCode>432101016</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Ohio</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>OH03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1267</Code>
<Text>TOPOLOGY</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7556</Code>
<Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0115</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2015~34000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Since 2008, the PI and Gunnar Carlsson (Stanford) have been involved in an ambitious research program exploring what is often called the Carlsson conjecture.</p> <p>Briefly stated, it is a conjectural, but explicit expression for the Algebraic K-theory of fields that contain an algebraically closed subfield, making use of information of the absolute Galois group of the bigger field. This is an extension of a well-known theorem due to Suslin when the second field is also algebraically closed.&nbsp;</p> <p>The work on this problem by Carlsson and Carlsson and the PI have also yeilded several important results in Algebaric K-theory, for example derived completion theorems extending classical Atiyah-Segal type theorems without the usual finiteness hypotheses.</p> <p>The goal of the conference and workshop was to bring together the leading researchers in the field of K-theory together with several beginning researchers in the field, so as to survey the progress made on key problems in the field of Algebraic K-theory in recent years and facilitate further progress and prospects in the field, with special attention paid to the Carlsson conjecture.</p> <p>We had a very succesful program with 18 speakers (20 one hour talks) and with well over 40 particpants. In fact, the website of the conference and workshop is till available at&nbsp;</p> <p>https://people.math.osu.edu/joshua.1/Ktheory_conf.html</p> <p>As one may see, we had several speakers from overseas and a mixture of expository and research level talks. We supported a significant number of junior participants, who also gave talks: in fact nearly half the funds from the NSF grant went to supporting such junior participants.</p> <p>The progress made during the conference has already yeilded substantial progress on the Carlsson conjecture and related topics in Algebraic K-theory.</p> <p>The program was also funded in part by funds from the Mathematics Research Institute at the the Ohio State University. &nbsp;We expended most of the funds received from the NSF for participant support at the conference and workshop. The remaining little amount (of about $3,000) was used to support speakers in the K-theory seminar at the Ohio State University for February, 2106- February, 2017, after obtaining a no-cost extension of the grant for one more year.&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 03/28/2017<br>      Modified by: Roy&nbsp;Joshua</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Since 2008, the PI and Gunnar Carlsson (Stanford) have been involved in an ambitious research program exploring what is often called the Carlsson conjecture.  Briefly stated, it is a conjectural, but explicit expression for the Algebraic K-theory of fields that contain an algebraically closed subfield, making use of information of the absolute Galois group of the bigger field. This is an extension of a well-known theorem due to Suslin when the second field is also algebraically closed.   The work on this problem by Carlsson and Carlsson and the PI have also yeilded several important results in Algebaric K-theory, for example derived completion theorems extending classical Atiyah-Segal type theorems without the usual finiteness hypotheses.  The goal of the conference and workshop was to bring together the leading researchers in the field of K-theory together with several beginning researchers in the field, so as to survey the progress made on key problems in the field of Algebraic K-theory in recent years and facilitate further progress and prospects in the field, with special attention paid to the Carlsson conjecture.  We had a very succesful program with 18 speakers (20 one hour talks) and with well over 40 particpants. In fact, the website of the conference and workshop is till available at   https://people.math.osu.edu/joshua.1/Ktheory_conf.html  As one may see, we had several speakers from overseas and a mixture of expository and research level talks. We supported a significant number of junior participants, who also gave talks: in fact nearly half the funds from the NSF grant went to supporting such junior participants.  The progress made during the conference has already yeilded substantial progress on the Carlsson conjecture and related topics in Algebraic K-theory.  The program was also funded in part by funds from the Mathematics Research Institute at the the Ohio State University.  We expended most of the funds received from the NSF for participant support at the conference and workshop. The remaining little amount (of about $3,000) was used to support speakers in the K-theory seminar at the Ohio State University for February, 2106- February, 2017, after obtaining a no-cost extension of the grant for one more year.                 Last Modified: 03/28/2017       Submitted by: Roy Joshua]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
