<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>SBIR Phase I:  Making Web Applications Accessible</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2015</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2015</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>150000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>150000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07070000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>IIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Industrial Innovation &amp; Partnersh</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Muralidharan Nair</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>mnair@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927059</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The broader impact/commercial potential of this project include the development of a novel assistive technology that will make dynamic web applications accessible for people with vision impairments. The proposed technology will empower blind people to utilize the immensely popular web applications for social networking, email, online banking, and travel with the same ease-of-use as is experienced by sighted people. The resulting higher productivity of screen-reader users will lead to improved access to education and employment. The proposed technology will be commercialized as part of a screen-reader application for people with vision impairments, a population of up to 25 Million people in the U.S. and a quarter of a million worldwide. The proposed innovation can also be utilized in mainstream technologies that enable web automation and web crawling.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This Small Business Innovation Research (SBIR) Phase I project will investigate the feasibility of making widgets in dynamic web application accessible for blind people. The dynamic nature of modern day web applications has become a serious barrier for blind people who use screen readers to access the Web. Unfortunately, while screen readers can usually narrate all the individual HTML elements in a webpage, they do not recognize widgets, which are a collection of HTML elements forming discrete user interface objects with which the user can interact, e.g., HTML windows, dropdown menus, calendars, suggestion boxes, etc. Inaccessibility of widgets in a web application can make the entire web applications unusable. This project will develop the Widget Accessibility Model that will employ machine learning techniques to identify and classify dynamic widgets in web pages and supply them with generic accessible interfaces. The Model will succinctly represent an assortment of widgets, of varying degrees of complexity, as objects associated with (inheritable) properties and interaction behaviors. WAM will drive the automatic detection of widgets used in a web application and stitch together their composite behavior from their components at runtime. The resulting Model will be incorporated into a commercial screen reader.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/22/2015</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/22/2015</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1520278</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Yury</FirstName>
<LastName>Puzis</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Yury Puzis</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>yury.puzis@charmtechlabs.com</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>3053018718</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000686720</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/22/2015</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Charmtech Labs LLC</Name>
<CityName>Stony Brook</CityName>
<ZipCode>117944600</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>8885337884</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1500 Stony Brook Road</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[CEWIT SBU R&D Park]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NY01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>807799924</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>CHARMTECH LABS LLC</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Charmtech Labs LLC]]></Name>
<CityName>Stony Brook</CityName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<ZipCode>117944000</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[CEWIT 1500 Stony Brook Road]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NY01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>5371</Code>
<Text>SBIR Phase I</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>5371</Code>
<Text>SMALL BUSINESS PHASE I</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>6840</Code>
<Text>ROBOTICS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8035</Code>
<Text>Hardware Devices</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9139</Code>
<Text>INFORMATION INFRASTRUCTURE &amp; TECH APPL</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>HPCC</Code>
<Text>HIGH PERFORMANCE COMPUTING &amp; COMM</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0115</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2015~150000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><span id="docs-internal-guid-10388923-cfe9-9822-afa1-69b5adb165a2"> </span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>We use the Web to obtain and exchange information, shop, pay bills, make travel arrangements, apply for college or employment, connect with others, participate in civic activities, etc. In its evolution from plain-text web sites into rich interactive web applications, the Web has grown less accessible for people who are blind or have low vision (over 20 million people in the U.S. and 285 Million people worldwide). </span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span><span> </span></span><span><span> </span></span><span><span> </span></span><span><span> </span></span><span><span> </span></span><span><span> </span></span><span><span> </span></span><span><span> </span></span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>For web browsing, blind people employ screen readers which convert the webpage content to speech. People with low vision use magnifiers which enlarge a small portion of the screen and require a lot of panning to interact with the rest of it; magnifiers often have screen-reading functionality as well. Currently, only rich internet applications that were designed according to ARIA (Accessible Rich Internet Applications) specification can be accessed with screen readers. In practice, specifying the behavior of complex widgets with ARIA is a very challenging and, most importantly, very expensive task resulting in a situation where most rich internet applications are inaccessible or very difficult to use with a screen reader. As a result, people with vision loss spend a considerable amount of time to complete seemingly simple browsing tasks. There is, therefore, a clear and urgent need to make web widgets, pervasive in modern web applications, accessible.</span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>This Project aims to solve a problem of widget accessibility for screen-reader users and make rich interactive web applications more usable and accessible for people with vision loss. In this project, we developed a prototype of Capti Web Screen Reader (CWSR), which provides an efficient framework for developing highly accessible rich internet applications. The framework is based on the foundation of the object-oriented paradigm, which is commonly used in software development. CWSR makes it much easier for screen-reader developers to make web applications accessible, and for web developers - to customize the behavior of the screen-reader.</span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>In this project we successfully demonstrated feasibility of the technology and gained important insights as to future direction of research and development. Specifically:</span></p> <ol> <li dir="ltr"> <p dir="ltr"><span>We showed that our approach to making web pages accessible is feasible by developing a working prototype and evaluating it in a user study.</span></p> </li> <li dir="ltr"> <p dir="ltr"><span>We identified the need for a graphical interface for CWSR web accessibility development (Web Accessibility Builder) and developed its first prototype.</span></p> </li> <li dir="ltr"> <p dir="ltr"><span>The Phase I user study results showed that developers considered our approach much easier to learn and use than ARIA for making web pages accessible.</span></p> </li> </ol> <p dir="ltr"><span><span> </span></span><span><span> </span></span><span><span> </span></span><span><span> </span></span></p> <p><span>The Project will advance the state of the art in web accessibility beyond what is possible with modern assistive technology. By focusing on reduction of the development costs of </span><span>high quality</span><span> accessible rich internet applications, the project has the potential to improve the quality of lives of millions of people with vision loss and make it easier for web developers to comply with the 21st Century Communications and Video Accessibility Act.</span></p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 03/31/2016<br>      Modified by...]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[   We use the Web to obtain and exchange information, shop, pay bills, make travel arrangements, apply for college or employment, connect with others, participate in civic activities, etc. In its evolution from plain-text web sites into rich interactive web applications, the Web has grown less accessible for people who are blind or have low vision (over 20 million people in the U.S. and 285 Million people worldwide).           For web browsing, blind people employ screen readers which convert the webpage content to speech. People with low vision use magnifiers which enlarge a small portion of the screen and require a lot of panning to interact with the rest of it; magnifiers often have screen-reading functionality as well. Currently, only rich internet applications that were designed according to ARIA (Accessible Rich Internet Applications) specification can be accessed with screen readers. In practice, specifying the behavior of complex widgets with ARIA is a very challenging and, most importantly, very expensive task resulting in a situation where most rich internet applications are inaccessible or very difficult to use with a screen reader. As a result, people with vision loss spend a considerable amount of time to complete seemingly simple browsing tasks. There is, therefore, a clear and urgent need to make web widgets, pervasive in modern web applications, accessible. This Project aims to solve a problem of widget accessibility for screen-reader users and make rich interactive web applications more usable and accessible for people with vision loss. In this project, we developed a prototype of Capti Web Screen Reader (CWSR), which provides an efficient framework for developing highly accessible rich internet applications. The framework is based on the foundation of the object-oriented paradigm, which is commonly used in software development. CWSR makes it much easier for screen-reader developers to make web applications accessible, and for web developers - to customize the behavior of the screen-reader. In this project we successfully demonstrated feasibility of the technology and gained important insights as to future direction of research and development. Specifically:   We showed that our approach to making web pages accessible is feasible by developing a working prototype and evaluating it in a user study.   We identified the need for a graphical interface for CWSR web accessibility development (Web Accessibility Builder) and developed its first prototype.   The Phase I user study results showed that developers considered our approach much easier to learn and use than ARIA for making web pages accessible.         The Project will advance the state of the art in web accessibility beyond what is possible with modern assistive technology. By focusing on reduction of the development costs of high quality accessible rich internet applications, the project has the potential to improve the quality of lives of millions of people with vision loss and make it easier for web developers to comply with the 21st Century Communications and Video Accessibility Act.          Last Modified: 03/31/2016       Submitted by: Yury Puzis]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
