<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>SBIR Phase I:  Chris Cross Cylinder Head Validation</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2015</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2016</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>150000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>150000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07070000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>IIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Industrial Innovation &amp; Partnersh</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Rajesh Mehta</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>rmehta@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922174</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The broader impact/commercial potential of this Small Business Innovation Research (SBIR) Phase I project is in terms of the reduction of emissions and the fuel savings on any motorcycle with this cylinder head design, and possibly also any internal combustion engine with this cylinder head design.   A vast majority of the world's internal combustion engine-driven fleet today are operated without requiring any emission-improving devices such as catalytic converters or fuel injection.  The proposed technology reduces emissions and increases gas mileage without requiring any emission-improving equipment. The proposed cylinder head design could also increase the engine performance as an added benefit. This project has the potential for producing progressively local, national, and even global impact.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The intellectual merit of this project is in the whole new way of thinking about how fuel burns inside the internal combustion engine.  Additionally, there are new ideas about the flow of air and the combustion process of the cylinder head.  This project is a newly designed, divided combustion chamber cylinder head, in which more of the fuel is burned inside the chamber, resulting in significantly lower output of emissions gases; namely hydrocarbons, carbon monoxide, nitrogen oxides, and carbon dioxide greenhouse gases. The objective of this research is to prove these results on a 500cc motorcycle with the newly designed cylinder head installed.  The motorcycle will be taken to an emissions lab to be tested for emissions as well as for gas mileage. It will be tested with catalytic converters installed, and again without catalytic converters, to show results using emission-improving devices as well as results of its stand-alone merit.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/26/2015</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/26/2015</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1520546</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Shawn</FirstName>
<LastName>Chriswell</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Shawn Chriswell</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>shawn@dcmachining.com</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>3037721160</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000694511</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/26/2015</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>DC's Machining, Inc.</Name>
<CityName>Longmont</CityName>
<ZipCode>805016162</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>3037721160</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1121 Delaware Avenue Suite 2</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Colorado</StateName>
<StateCode>CO</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CO04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>151779527</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>DC'S MACHINING</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[DC's Machining]]></Name>
<CityName>Longmont</CityName>
<StateCode>CO</StateCode>
<ZipCode>805016162</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[1121 Delaware Ave]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Colorado</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CO04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>5371</Code>
<Text>SBIR Phase I</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>5371</Code>
<Text>SMALL BUSINESS PHASE I</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8029</Code>
<Text>Manufacturing</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0115</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2015~150000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The Chris Cross cylinder head is a newly designed cylinder head and valve train that was prototyped for a 2014 air cooled, fuel injected&nbsp; 535cc Royal Enfield Continental GT motorcycle.&nbsp; DC's Machining machined this cylinder head from billet aluminum.&nbsp; It was installed on the motorcycle, then on-road testing was conducted, and continued tuning to improve rideability.&nbsp;</p> <p>Next, testing was conducted on an in-house dynamometer.&nbsp; The method used for measuring the fuel mileage is to weigh the gas tank before, during, and after the test to ensure accurate readings.&nbsp; The weight is measured and converted to gallons.&nbsp;</p> <p>As can be seen in the accompanying graph, the stock 2014 motorcycle averages 71.3 mpg.&nbsp; With the Chris Cross cylinder head, stock fuel injection, fuel injection tuner, and stock exhaust, the same motorcycle averages 97.05 mpg.&nbsp; This is a 36% increase over the stock 2014 motorcycle. The motorcycle also has increased top-end speed from 68 mph up to 78+ mph.&nbsp;</p> <p>The broader impact that the Chris Cross technology has on the United States and on the world is significant.&nbsp; A large percentage of the world's population uses small&nbsp; &lt;500cc motorcycles as its primary form of transportation. The impact of the fuel savings and pollution reduction on this small motorcycle fleet worldwide is staggering in its own right.</p> <p>This patented cylinder head technology can be applied not only to on-road vehicles but also to off-road vehicles, DOD applications, small stand-alone engines, and agricultural needs.&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 08/30/2016<br>      Modified by: Shawn&nbsp;Chriswell</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Images (<span id="selectedPhoto0">1</span> of <span class="totalNumber"></span>)           </div> <div class="galControls" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2016/1520546/1520546_10372539_1472587235786_ccteam89(1)--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2016/1520546/1520546_10372539_1472587235786_ccteam89(1)--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Royal Enfield on test Dyno"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2016/1520546/1520546_10372539_1472587235786_ccteam89(1)--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Royal Enfield on test Dyno"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">This is the Royal Enfield Continental GT equipped with the Chris Cross cylinder head being tested for fuel mileage on the in-house dyno.</div> <div class="imageCredit">sc</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyright owner is an institution with an existing agreement allowing use by NSF</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Shawn&nbsp;Chriswell</div> <div class="imageTitle">Royal Enfield on test Dyno</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2016/1520546/1520546_10372539_1472587392101_chriscrossdrawing--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2016/1520546/1520546_10372539_1472587392101_chriscrossdrawing--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Chris Cross"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2016/1520546/1520546_10372539_1472587392101_chriscrossdrawing--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Chris Cross"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Chris Cross logo and trademark</div> <div class="imageCredit">sc</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyright owner is an institution with an existing agreement allowing use by NSF</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Shawn&nbsp;Chriswell</div> <div class="imageTitle">Chris Cross</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2016/1520546/1520546_10372539_1472587837067_graph--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2016/1520546/1520546_10372539_1472587837067_graph--rgov-800width.jpg" title="fuel mileage graph"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2016/1520546/1520546_10372539_1472587837067_graph--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="fuel mileage graph"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">This graph shows the results of the fuel mileage tests performed on the in-house dyno on the Royal Enfield equipped with the Chris Cross cylinder head.</div> <div class="imageCredit">sc</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyright owner is an institution with an existing agreement allowing use by NSF</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Shawn&nbsp;Chriswell</div> <div class="imageTitle">fuel mileage graph</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2016/1520546/1520546_10372539_1472588158386_Atwtr2--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2016/1520546/1520546_10372539_1472588158386_Atwtr2--rgov-800width.jpg" title="2014 Royal Enfield Continental GT with Chris Cross cylinder head"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2016/1520546/1520546_10372539_1472588158386_Atwtr2--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="2014 Royal Enfield Continental GT with Chris Cross cylinder head"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">2014 Royal Enfield Continental GT with Chris Cross cylinder head</div> <div class="imageCredit">sc</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyright owner is an institution with an existing agreement allowing use by NSF</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Shawn&nbsp;Chriswell</div> <div class="imageTitle">2014 Royal Enfield Continental GT with Chris Cross cylinder head</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The Chris Cross cylinder head is a newly designed cylinder head and valve train that was prototyped for a 2014 air cooled, fuel injected  535cc Royal Enfield Continental GT motorcycle.  DC's Machining machined this cylinder head from billet aluminum.  It was installed on the motorcycle, then on-road testing was conducted, and continued tuning to improve rideability.   Next, testing was conducted on an in-house dynamometer.  The method used for measuring the fuel mileage is to weigh the gas tank before, during, and after the test to ensure accurate readings.  The weight is measured and converted to gallons.   As can be seen in the accompanying graph, the stock 2014 motorcycle averages 71.3 mpg.  With the Chris Cross cylinder head, stock fuel injection, fuel injection tuner, and stock exhaust, the same motorcycle averages 97.05 mpg.  This is a 36% increase over the stock 2014 motorcycle. The motorcycle also has increased top-end speed from 68 mph up to 78+ mph.   The broader impact that the Chris Cross technology has on the United States and on the world is significant.  A large percentage of the world's population uses small  &lt;500cc motorcycles as its primary form of transportation. The impact of the fuel savings and pollution reduction on this small motorcycle fleet worldwide is staggering in its own right.  This patented cylinder head technology can be applied not only to on-road vehicles but also to off-road vehicles, DOD applications, small stand-alone engines, and agricultural needs.           Last Modified: 08/30/2016       Submitted by: Shawn Chriswell]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
