<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>SBIR Phase I:  Sustainable Rare Earth Element Recycling from Neodymium Magnets</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2015</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2015</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>150000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>150000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07070000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>IIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Industrial Innovation &amp; Partnersh</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Benaiah Schrag</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>bschrag@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032928323</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This Small Business Innovation Research Phase I project has the potential to bring to commercial scale a process that can create a secondary source of neodymium (Nd) and dysprosium (Dy). This will help reduce U.S. dependence on an unstable and limited supply of rare earth elements (REEs) from China by recycling materials readily available in waste streams. This effort will impact industrial and clean energy manufacturing by supporting the production of neodymium-iron-boron (NdFeB) magnets, which are fundamental for high efficiency electric motors and wind turbines. The increased availability of these resources would also improve the vertical integration of manufacturing for national security technologies, such as guided missile actuators, that depend on these rare earth elements. The company will be able to create a new and reliable revenue stream for electronics recycling companies in exchange for a steady supply of magnets, the primary feedstock for the rare earth reclamation process. The total rare earth market is increasing at a 13% compound annual growth rate. In 2013, the North American market for Nd and Dy was valued at approximately $795 million.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The intellectual merit of this project is the development of a commercially viable rare earth element reclamation process that minimizes the environmental and economic issues that have hindered NdFeB magnet recycling. Conventional methods for rare earth extractions are limited to high energy consumption routes and/or methods which require the use of strong acids. The company will use a proprietary solvent mixture to dissolve the magnets and to selectively extract the REEs. The research will lead to an understanding of the reaction chemistry for recovering REEs from NdFeB and will create a knowledge base for novel rare earth recovery routes. The research objectives are to 1) increase process testing toward commercial batch size and reduce iron contamination to produce rare earths that meet customer specifications, 2) efficiently utilize all materials in the process to produce higher yields by finding the optimal timing, temperature, particle size, and solvent amounts in order to extract at least 95% of all rare earths in each batch, 3) minimize waste materials, and 4) optimize NdFeB magnet pre-processing techniques.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/01/2015</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/01/2015</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1520410</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Pradeep</FirstName>
<LastName>Samarasekere</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Pradeep Samarasekere</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>pradeep@reecycleinc.com</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>8323391793</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000679625</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/01/2015</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Rare Resource Recycling</Name>
<CityName>Houston</CityName>
<ZipCode>772046021</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>8322601072</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>334 Melcher Hall UCBB Ste 528</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Texas</StateName>
<StateCode>TX</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>18</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>TX18</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>079410617</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>RARE RESOURCE RECYCLING INC.</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Rare Resource Recycling]]></Name>
<CityName>Houston</CityName>
<StateCode>TX</StateCode>
<ZipCode>770045667</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[5000 Gulf Freeway Bldg 4 Rm 230]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Texas</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>18</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>TX18</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>5371</Code>
<Text>SBIR Phase I</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>123E</Code>
<Text>CENTERS: ADVANCED MATERIALS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>5371</Code>
<Text>SMALL BUSINESS PHASE I</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8025</Code>
<Text>Advanced Materials Processing</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8029</Code>
<Text>Manufacturing</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0115</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2015~150000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The objective of this SBIR Phase I project was to develop a commercially viable, environmentally-less-hazardous, economical process to extract rare earth elements (REEs) from disposed-of neodymium-iron-boron (NdFeB) magnets.</p> <p>Rare earth elements are critical to the production of advanced electronics, clean energy technologies, and numerous defense applications. Unfortunately, the global supply of rare earths is not increasing at a necessary pace to fulfill the escalating demand for these materials, creating volatility within the supply chain. The rare earth supply risk is largely instigated by Chinese dominance of the rare earth market. With China controlling approximately 90% of global rare earth production, a near monopoly has been created, providing a strategic advantage in the control of technologies that rely upon these unique materials. China&rsquo;s control and dominance over rare earths continues to limit the use of rare earth elements by rest of world manufacturers.</p> <p>Recycling of rare earth elements from end-user products is a key strategy for mitigating the current rare earth supply problem. With a consortium of efforts, efficient, sustainable, and economical rare earth recycling technologies could help to create a secondary source of rare earth elements, providing supply chain security for manufacturers outside of China.</p> <p>Rare Resource Recycling Inc. (REEcycle) has developed a disruptive technology for recycling rare earth elements, creating a reliable and sustainable supply of critical rare earths. REEcycle&rsquo;s process is simple, less environmentally-destructive and more economical when compared to conventional rare earth element reclamation processes. REEcycle&rsquo;s process consists of harvesting magnets from end-of-use products, demagnetizing and crushing the magnets to a fine powder, reacting the powders with REEcycle&rsquo;s proprietary solution, separating and purifying the extracted rare earth products and converting them to rare earth oxides (REOs) through calcination. The tailing water from the reaction is chemically treated and purified before being discarded. REEcycle&rsquo;s process has achieved all set proof-of-feasibility benchmarks for the reclamation of rare earth elements from hard disk drive and production scrap magnets, known as swarf.</p> <p>During the SBIR-Phase I research period, REEcycle successfully studied the feasibility of scaling the process from laboratory to pilot scale. During that period, many developments were made to overcome pre-determined technical hurdles related to transitioning the &ldquo;proof of principle&rdquo; study to larger-scale, commercial production.</p> <p>The Phase I project has allowed REEcycle to a) achieve 90+% rare earth recoveries; b) achieve 99% purity by &nbsp;lowering the non-rare earth impurities to the ranges acceptable by rare earth separation and purification facilities (iron impurity ~0.5%, other impurities &lt;1000 ppm); c) reduce the reaction time to &lt;12 hours; d) significantly scale-up the process batch size; e) generate enough material for early customer testing; and e) improve key magnet pre-processing and waste management techniques. Phase I R&amp;D was performed in a three-pronged approach; 1) core-process developments; 2) scale-up; and 3) auxiliary-process developments. The results of each identified area of research are as follows:</p> <p style="padding-left: 30px;">01.&nbsp; Several process parameters were optimized to improve the product yields, purities, and reaction efficiencies. The effects of demagnetization, particle size, solvent mixing ratios, solvent-to-solid ratios, and reaction temperatures were optimized through systematic variations. Improvements were made to the rare earth product filtration techniques to minimize the product loss and contaminations. An optimum process protocol was thus developed, successfully tested, and confirmed on kilogra...]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The objective of this SBIR Phase I project was to develop a commercially viable, environmentally-less-hazardous, economical process to extract rare earth elements (REEs) from disposed-of neodymium-iron-boron (NdFeB) magnets.  Rare earth elements are critical to the production of advanced electronics, clean energy technologies, and numerous defense applications. Unfortunately, the global supply of rare earths is not increasing at a necessary pace to fulfill the escalating demand for these materials, creating volatility within the supply chain. The rare earth supply risk is largely instigated by Chinese dominance of the rare earth market. With China controlling approximately 90% of global rare earth production, a near monopoly has been created, providing a strategic advantage in the control of technologies that rely upon these unique materials. ChinaÆs control and dominance over rare earths continues to limit the use of rare earth elements by rest of world manufacturers.  Recycling of rare earth elements from end-user products is a key strategy for mitigating the current rare earth supply problem. With a consortium of efforts, efficient, sustainable, and economical rare earth recycling technologies could help to create a secondary source of rare earth elements, providing supply chain security for manufacturers outside of China.  Rare Resource Recycling Inc. (REEcycle) has developed a disruptive technology for recycling rare earth elements, creating a reliable and sustainable supply of critical rare earths. REEcycleÆs process is simple, less environmentally-destructive and more economical when compared to conventional rare earth element reclamation processes. REEcycleÆs process consists of harvesting magnets from end-of-use products, demagnetizing and crushing the magnets to a fine powder, reacting the powders with REEcycleÆs proprietary solution, separating and purifying the extracted rare earth products and converting them to rare earth oxides (REOs) through calcination. The tailing water from the reaction is chemically treated and purified before being discarded. REEcycleÆs process has achieved all set proof-of-feasibility benchmarks for the reclamation of rare earth elements from hard disk drive and production scrap magnets, known as swarf.  During the SBIR-Phase I research period, REEcycle successfully studied the feasibility of scaling the process from laboratory to pilot scale. During that period, many developments were made to overcome pre-determined technical hurdles related to transitioning the "proof of principle" study to larger-scale, commercial production.  The Phase I project has allowed REEcycle to a) achieve 90+% rare earth recoveries; b) achieve 99% purity by  lowering the non-rare earth impurities to the ranges acceptable by rare earth separation and purification facilities (iron impurity ~0.5%, other impurities &lt;1000 ppm); c) reduce the reaction time to &lt;12 hours; d) significantly scale-up the process batch size; e) generate enough material for early customer testing; and e) improve key magnet pre-processing and waste management techniques. Phase I R&amp;D was performed in a three-pronged approach; 1) core-process developments; 2) scale-up; and 3) auxiliary-process developments. The results of each identified area of research are as follows: 01.  Several process parameters were optimized to improve the product yields, purities, and reaction efficiencies. The effects of demagnetization, particle size, solvent mixing ratios, solvent-to-solid ratios, and reaction temperatures were optimized through systematic variations. Improvements were made to the rare earth product filtration techniques to minimize the product loss and contaminations. An optimum process protocol was thus developed, successfully tested, and confirmed on kilogram scale feed batches. 02.  The process scale-up was attempted using a small-scale mock pilot plant. Several kilograms of scrap magnets were successfully processed and sufficient a...]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
