<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>STTR Phase I:  Ultrasonic Nanocoining for Creating Large, Low-Cost Arrays of Sub-Wavelength Features</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2015</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2016</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>224939.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>244933</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07070000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>IIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Industrial Innovation &amp; Partnersh</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Rajesh Mehta</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>rmehta@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922174</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The broader impact/commercial potential of this Small Business Technology Transfer (STTR) Phase 1 project is to drastically reduce the cost of creating large surfaces coated with functional nano-scale features.  One example is the moth-eye structure, consisting of a continuous pattern of 200 nm wide by 200 nm tall features, that gives surface anti-reflective properties.  An anti-reflective surface can increase efficiency of solar cells, conceal aircraft or ships, or prevent glare on windshield glass or computer screens.  Nano-features can also be used to create surfaces with superior durability and cleanliness through self-wetting and anti-fouling characteristics, as well as anti-fogging or de-icing properties.  The low-cost scale-up is done through "roll-to-roll" processing, where a drum-shaped metal cylinder coated with nano-features is used as the mold for rolling miles of thin film, replicating the functional coating.     &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The intellectual merit of this project is focused on accurately and inexpensively creating nano-scale features on the metal drum mold that is used in the roll-to-roll replication process.  This is done using the recently-developed nanocoining process, whereby nano-features are indented into a metal surface using a diamond die indent features into the surface 40,000 times per second.  Current machining methods rely on scraping material away with a sharp tool and cannot create features on nano-scale.  This is because any tool sharp enough to create such a small feature will be prohibitively fragile and susceptible to rapid wear.  Indenting is fundamentally different, and has been used for millennia to create coins.  No material is removed; it is simply pushed aside, leaving behind the pattern on the die.  The reduction of rubbing drastically reduces wear and the absence of a chip of removed material enables the process to work on the nano-scale.  The objective of the initial phase of research is to indent a small test drum and replicate a plastic film coated with the features from the diamond die.  The film will then be tested for anti-reflective and wetting properties, and scale-up will follow in later phases.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/26/2015</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/15/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1521227</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Thomas</FirstName>
<LastName>Dow</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>A</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Thomas A Dow</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>thomas_dow@ncsu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>9195153976</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000230987</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/26/2015</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Stephen</FirstName>
<LastName>Furst</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>J</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Stephen J Furst</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>furst@smartmaterialsolutions.com</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>8456490189</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000652746</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/26/2015</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Smart Material Solutions, Inc.</Name>
<CityName>Raleigh</CityName>
<ZipCode>276070000</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>9195214440</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>984 Trinity Rd.</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>North Carolina</StateName>
<StateCode>NC</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NC04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>078752723</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>SMART MATERIAL SOLUTIONS, INC.</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[North Carolina State University]]></Name>
<CityName>Raleigh</CityName>
<StateCode>NC</StateCode>
<ZipCode>276957918</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[1001 Capability Dr., Research Bu]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>North Carolina</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NC02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1505</Code>
<Text>STTR Phase I</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1084</Code>
<Text>NANOTECHNOLOGY INITIATIVE</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1505</Code>
<Text>STTR PHASE I</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>163E</Code>
<Text>SBIR Phase IB</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8029</Code>
<Text>Manufacturing</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0115</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0116</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2015~224939</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2016~19994</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>As time moves forward, people expect their technology to work better, do more, and cost less. While this demand may seem sensible, the reality is that the world has limited space and energy. However, nano-technology is able to reconcile these conflicting expectations and realities by packing new functionalities into negligibly small spaces. For example, a three-dimensional surface texture comprised of a repeating pattern of nano-scale features occupies virtually no space, but it can manipulate the way light interacts with a surface. This allows light to pass through an interface smoothly, eliminating glare and increasing the amount of light that passes through to the other side. The same transparent surface structure can repel water and contaminants to make a glass or plastic panel that is self-cleaning.</p> <p>These structures offer the potential to save energy through efficient management of light in solar panels, OLED displays or lighting fixtures, and polarizing films. However, the individual features that comprise such structured surfaces are only 300 nm across &ndash; about 1/500<sup>th</sup> the width of a hair &ndash; so about a trillion of them are required to cover a surface the size of a laptop screen. Making these trillion features at a rate of 1 per second would take 30,000 years.</p> <p>The work done during this award made massive improvements in the manufacturing speed for nano-structured surfaces. By adapting technology patented at NC State University called nanocoining, Smart Material Solutions was able to create these nano-features at a rate of 50 million per second. This allows an area the size of a laptop screen to be coated in under an hour &ndash; more than 100x faster than competing mastering methods. Nanocoining has an additional advantage: it uses a diamond to indent the features the same way a die indents coins. As a result, these nanostructures can be pressed into the outer surface of a metal cylinder that can then be used to roll the structure into plastic sheets using a roll-to-roll process that can texture that same laptop screen in a matter of seconds. This multi-step process will make nano-structured surfaces economically viable in large-area applications where several square meters of continuous structured surface is needed.</p> <p>Demonstrating this technology required Smart Material Solutions and NC State University to make innovations on multiple fronts. The diamond die used for indenting (1) is patterned with a focused ion beam; however, prior to this work, large, uniform arrays of sub-wavelength structures had never been ion-milled onto a diamond die. In the next step (2) the die is attached to a vibrating metal beam that moves the die in an elliptical path and indents the mold 47,000 time per second (3). Control of this &ldquo;ultrasonic resonant actuator&rdquo; ensured that each stroke created an indent precisely aligned with previous indents (4) and required new techniques and unprecedented levels of precision.</p> <p>Funding from the NSF allowed the research team to solve these problems that relate not only to nanocoining &ndash; a platform technology itself &ndash; but also to a wide array of other precision manufacturing fields. What&rsquo;s more, unlike many nano-technology processes, nanocoining does not rely on dangerous chemicals or particles and it can be done entirely at room temperature. This ensures that the energy savings provided by nano-structured surfaces are complimented by an efficient, low-energy manufacturing process.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 03/22/2017<br>      Modified by: Stephen&nbsp;J&nbsp;Furst</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Images (<span id="selectedPhoto0">1</span> of <span class="totalNumber"></span>)           </div> <div class="galControls" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1521227/1521227_10372617_1490190911777_Image1a--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1521227/1521227_10372617_1490190911777_Image1a--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Project Products"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1521227/1521227_10372617_1490190911777_Image1a--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Project Products"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Photographs of the diamond die (left), indented Nickel cylinder (center), and an anti-glare plastic film replicated from the cylinder (right).</div> <div class="imageCredit">Smart Material Solutions</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Public Domain</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Stephen&nbsp;J&nbsp;Furst</div> <div class="imageTitle">Project Products</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1521227/1521227_10372617_1490190766929_Image2a--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1521227/1521227_10372617_1490190766929_Image2a--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Nanocoining Process Overview"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1521227/1521227_10372617_1490190766929_Image2a--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Nanocoining Process Overview"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Diagram of how a nano-structured diamond die (1) is attached to a actuator (2) that indents a cylinder (3) to create a nano-structured surface (4).</div> <div class="imageCredit">Smart Material Solutions</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Stephen&nbsp;J&nbsp;Furst</div> <div class="imageTitle">Nanocoining Process Overview</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ As time moves forward, people expect their technology to work better, do more, and cost less. While this demand may seem sensible, the reality is that the world has limited space and energy. However, nano-technology is able to reconcile these conflicting expectations and realities by packing new functionalities into negligibly small spaces. For example, a three-dimensional surface texture comprised of a repeating pattern of nano-scale features occupies virtually no space, but it can manipulate the way light interacts with a surface. This allows light to pass through an interface smoothly, eliminating glare and increasing the amount of light that passes through to the other side. The same transparent surface structure can repel water and contaminants to make a glass or plastic panel that is self-cleaning.  These structures offer the potential to save energy through efficient management of light in solar panels, OLED displays or lighting fixtures, and polarizing films. However, the individual features that comprise such structured surfaces are only 300 nm across &ndash; about 1/500th the width of a hair &ndash; so about a trillion of them are required to cover a surface the size of a laptop screen. Making these trillion features at a rate of 1 per second would take 30,000 years.  The work done during this award made massive improvements in the manufacturing speed for nano-structured surfaces. By adapting technology patented at NC State University called nanocoining, Smart Material Solutions was able to create these nano-features at a rate of 50 million per second. This allows an area the size of a laptop screen to be coated in under an hour &ndash; more than 100x faster than competing mastering methods. Nanocoining has an additional advantage: it uses a diamond to indent the features the same way a die indents coins. As a result, these nanostructures can be pressed into the outer surface of a metal cylinder that can then be used to roll the structure into plastic sheets using a roll-to-roll process that can texture that same laptop screen in a matter of seconds. This multi-step process will make nano-structured surfaces economically viable in large-area applications where several square meters of continuous structured surface is needed.  Demonstrating this technology required Smart Material Solutions and NC State University to make innovations on multiple fronts. The diamond die used for indenting (1) is patterned with a focused ion beam; however, prior to this work, large, uniform arrays of sub-wavelength structures had never been ion-milled onto a diamond die. In the next step (2) the die is attached to a vibrating metal beam that moves the die in an elliptical path and indents the mold 47,000 time per second (3). Control of this "ultrasonic resonant actuator" ensured that each stroke created an indent precisely aligned with previous indents (4) and required new techniques and unprecedented levels of precision.  Funding from the NSF allowed the research team to solve these problems that relate not only to nanocoining &ndash; a platform technology itself &ndash; but also to a wide array of other precision manufacturing fields. What?s more, unlike many nano-technology processes, nanocoining does not rely on dangerous chemicals or particles and it can be done entirely at room temperature. This ensures that the energy savings provided by nano-structured surfaces are complimented by an efficient, low-energy manufacturing process.       Last Modified: 03/22/2017       Submitted by: Stephen J Furst]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
