<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Collaborative Research:  Computational methods for ultra-high sensitivity magnetometry of geological samples</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2015</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>197014.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>197014</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DMS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Christopher Stark</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>cstark@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924869</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This project will develop new techniques and algorithms for analyzing high-resolution high-sensitivity magnetic field maps of geological samples. Such maps are built from scanning magnetic microscopy (SMM) data. This research, which involves a collaboration of mathematicians and geoscientists, will help advance scientific knowledge in several significant ways, such as unlocking the earliest records of the Earth's magnetic field by analyzing ancient zircons; accessing high temporal resolution records of variations in the geomagnetic field that may be preserved in cave formations; and improving our understanding of the evolution of the solar system and planet formation processes by analyzing magnetization records preserved in primitive meteorites. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This investigation will allow paleomagnetic studies to be conducted on geological samples that are currently inaccessible due to lack of sensitivity and spatial resolution of conventional instrumentation and techniques. The computation of magnetic moments from field maps is generally an ill-posed inverse problem. The multi-pronged approach to such problems under study in this project will use different analytical and numerical strategies (e.g., new sparsity and regularization methods) that will ensure the development of tools applicable to a variety of specimens. Given the similar mathematical framework, it is expected that the associated analysis will prove useful for the analysis of data from aeromagnetic surveys and satellite magnetic observations.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/09/2015</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/09/2015</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1521765</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Benjamin</FirstName>
<LastName>Weiss</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>P</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Benjamin P Weiss</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>bpweiss@mit.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6173240224</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000149353</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/09/2015</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Eduardo</FirstName>
<LastName>Andrade Lima</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Eduardo Andrade Lima</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>limaea@mit.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6173242829</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000659789</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/09/2015</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Massachusetts Institute of Technology</Name>
<CityName>Cambridge</CityName>
<ZipCode>021394301</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6172531000</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>77 MASSACHUSETTS AVE</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[NE18-901]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
<StateCode>MA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MA07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>001425594</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>MASSACHUSETTS INSTITUTE OF TECHNOLOGY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>001425594</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Massachusetts Institute of Technology]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>MA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>021394307</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MA07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>8069</Code>
<Text>CDS&amp;E-MSS</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7433</Code>
<Text>CyberInfra Frmwrk 21st (CIF21)</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8084</Code>
<Text>CDS&amp;E</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9263</Code>
<Text>COMPUTATIONAL SCIENCE &amp; ENGING</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0115</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2015~197014</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>In this project, we developed mathematical tools to recover information about ancient planetary magnetic fields that may be preserved in rock samples based on indirect measurements of their magnetization obtained with high-resolution magnetic microscopy. As rocks cooled during their formation, ferromagnetic minerals may have acquired a magnetization in the direction of the ambient magnetic field and with intensity proportional to the field strength. Similarly, sedimentary rocks and mineral deposits, such as stalagmites in caves and iron and manganese oxide precipitates found on the deep ocean floor, may have recorded magnetic fields throughout their formation period by virtue of the magnetization produced by the steady incorporation of small ferromagnetic particles aligned with the ambient field. Given that magnetization in geological samples cannot be directly measured by instruments except on a very thin layer of polished surfaces, mathematical methods are therefore needed to infer the magnetization distribution within the specimen from measurements of the external magnetic field it produces. Often, such external fields are not only extremely faint (up to 1,000,000 times weaker than Earth&prime;s magnetic field) but are also not sufficient to uniquely determine the magnetization that produced them. This poses additional challenges for both instrumentation and mathematical techniques to successfully recover information about paleomagnetic fields preserved in some rocks.</p> <p>We have developed techniques for recovering net magnetic moment (i.e., average magnetization) and also spatial distribution of magnetization within rock samples satisfying certain properties. This has allowed us to conduct paleomagnetic studies on rocks that are inaccessible to standard instrumentation and analytical techniques. In particular, some of the techniques developed in this project were used to successfully analyze magnetization in single zircon crystals from the Jack Hills in Western Australia, which may have preserved the earliest records of Earth&prime;s magnetic field more than 3.5 billion years ago. In combination with a suite of other analytical techniques, they revealed that such possible records of magnetic fields in the early history of our planet are not robust and most likely were altered at a later time after zircon formation.&nbsp; We are now applying the developed tools to recover high temporal resolution records of the geomagnetic field that may be preserved in stalagmites, enabling us to better understand the evolution of Earth&prime;s field over the past thousands of years and to investigate its correlation with paleoclimate events.</p> <p>A female undergraduate student in Mathematics and a Latino PhD student in Planetary Science participated in this project. They closely interacted with both our French and American collaborators, providing an enriching experience and a hands-on opportunity to work in a dynamic, diverse and collaborative research project combining people with different academic and cultural backgrounds.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 09/28/2019<br>      Modified by: Eduardo&nbsp;Andrade Lima</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ In this project, we developed mathematical tools to recover information about ancient planetary magnetic fields that may be preserved in rock samples based on indirect measurements of their magnetization obtained with high-resolution magnetic microscopy. As rocks cooled during their formation, ferromagnetic minerals may have acquired a magnetization in the direction of the ambient magnetic field and with intensity proportional to the field strength. Similarly, sedimentary rocks and mineral deposits, such as stalagmites in caves and iron and manganese oxide precipitates found on the deep ocean floor, may have recorded magnetic fields throughout their formation period by virtue of the magnetization produced by the steady incorporation of small ferromagnetic particles aligned with the ambient field. Given that magnetization in geological samples cannot be directly measured by instruments except on a very thin layer of polished surfaces, mathematical methods are therefore needed to infer the magnetization distribution within the specimen from measurements of the external magnetic field it produces. Often, such external fields are not only extremely faint (up to 1,000,000 times weaker than Earth&prime;s magnetic field) but are also not sufficient to uniquely determine the magnetization that produced them. This poses additional challenges for both instrumentation and mathematical techniques to successfully recover information about paleomagnetic fields preserved in some rocks.  We have developed techniques for recovering net magnetic moment (i.e., average magnetization) and also spatial distribution of magnetization within rock samples satisfying certain properties. This has allowed us to conduct paleomagnetic studies on rocks that are inaccessible to standard instrumentation and analytical techniques. In particular, some of the techniques developed in this project were used to successfully analyze magnetization in single zircon crystals from the Jack Hills in Western Australia, which may have preserved the earliest records of Earth&prime;s magnetic field more than 3.5 billion years ago. In combination with a suite of other analytical techniques, they revealed that such possible records of magnetic fields in the early history of our planet are not robust and most likely were altered at a later time after zircon formation.  We are now applying the developed tools to recover high temporal resolution records of the geomagnetic field that may be preserved in stalagmites, enabling us to better understand the evolution of Earth&prime;s field over the past thousands of years and to investigate its correlation with paleoclimate events.  A female undergraduate student in Mathematics and a Latino PhD student in Planetary Science participated in this project. They closely interacted with both our French and American collaborators, providing an enriching experience and a hands-on opportunity to work in a dynamic, diverse and collaborative research project combining people with different academic and cultural backgrounds.          Last Modified: 09/28/2019       Submitted by: Eduardo Andrade Lima]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
