<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Summer School in Land-atmosphere Interactions</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>03/01/2015</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>02/29/2016</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>49770.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>49770</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>06020105</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>GEO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>AGS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Atmospheric &amp; Geospace Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Chungu Lu</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>clu@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927110</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The PIs are organizing a summer school in the summer of 2015 on land-atmosphere interactions. The objective of the summer school is to cover a large range of topics pertinent to the study of land-atmosphere interactions from soil physics, plant ecophysiology, and boundary layer turbulence and convection. This objective is to train the next generation of scientists in this area and hope that such training will generate rapid research development in the field.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Intellectual merit &lt;br/&gt;An NSF-sponsored workshop was held in September of 2014 to facilitate progress in hydrometeorological, hydroclimatic, and ecohydrological (HHE) research. The study and funding of land-atmosphere interaction research came up as the number one priority of the workshop. One of the main gaps towards research and operational advances in this area is the lack of core training in land-atmosphere interactions. This summer school is targeted at addressing this need.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Broader impacts &lt;br/&gt;One of the objectives is to reach out to a diverse pool of students and young scientists in the U.S. so that the scientists attending the summer school reflect the diversity of the population.  Historically Black Colleges and Universities will be specifically targeted.  Several lectures will be available online through the Consortium of Universities for the Advancement of Hydrologic Sciences, Inc. (CUAHSI).</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>02/05/2015</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>02/05/2015</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.050</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1522174</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Pierre</FirstName>
<LastName>Gentine</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Pierre Gentine</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>pg2328@columbia.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2128546851</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000560401</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>02/05/2015</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Paul</FirstName>
<LastName>Dirmeyer</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>A</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Paul A Dirmeyer</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>pdirmeye@gmu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>7039932295</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000652809</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>02/05/2015</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Columbia University</Name>
<CityName>NEW YORK</CityName>
<ZipCode>100276902</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2128546851</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>2960 Broadway</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>10</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NY10</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>049179401</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>TRUSTEES OF COLUMBIA UNIVERSITY IN THE CITY OF NEW YORK, THE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>049179401</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Columbia University]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<ZipCode>100276900</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>10</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NY10</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1525</Code>
<Text>Physical &amp; Dynamic Meteorology</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1579</Code>
<Text>Hydrologic Sciences</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>0000</Code>
<Text>UNASSIGNED</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>4444</Code>
<Text>INTERDISCIPLINARY PROPOSALS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>OTHR</Code>
<Text>OTHER RESEARCH OR EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0115</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2015~49770</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><strong>NSF-sponsored Summer school on land-atmosphere interactions</strong></p> <p><strong>Valsavarenche, Valle d'Aosta (Italy), Italy 22 June - 1 July, 2015</strong></p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p><strong>Directors of the course: </strong></p> <p><strong>Pierre Gentine<sup>1</sup>&nbsp;and Albert A.M. Holtslag<sup>2</sup> </strong></p> <p><sup>1</sup>Columbia University, New York, NY USA;<sup> 2</sup>Wageningen University, Wageningen, the Netherlands</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>The Italian-French summer school on "Fundamental processes in geophysical fluid dynamics and the climate system" is organized each year by the Institute of Atmospheric Sciences and Climate (ISAC) - CNR (Turin, Italy) and by the Centre national de la recherche scientifique (France). This 23<sup>rd</sup> edition was dedicated to land-atmosphere interactions. This school aimed at providing to young researchers - Ph.D. students in particular - an up-to-date training program presenting a quantitative approach outlining physical principles, and the mathematical basis of land-atmosphere interactions. Some of the most well regarded researchers in the field of land-atmosphere interactions were present at the summer school, both teaching and interacting with the students. We had a total of 50 students and received more than 180 applications, a record for the summer school. More than 50% of the students were from minority (women, underrepresented groups). US students were coming from the following institutions: Princeton Univerity, Columbia University, Texas A&amp;M, University of Washington, University of California Irvine, University of California Berkeley, Duke University, University of Arizona, Boston University, The university of Texas at Austin, West Virginia University, University of Utah , State university of New York: Albany as well as Department of Energy labs The school was sponsored by NSF, GEWEX, EGU and CNRS, which allowed supporting many of the students of the class. Conference room was provided by the region of Valsavarenche. Slides of the summer school have been made widely available to the broader community at http://www.to.isac.cnr.it/aosta/index.html.</p> <p class="formattext">Land-atmosphere interactions describe the coupled exchanges of momentum, heat, moisture and carbon between the land surface and the overlying atmosphere. These feedbacks are regulated through the interface: the planetary boundary layer in which intense turbulence occurs. Land-atmosphere interactions are important sources of seasonal climate predictability in several parts of the world. Soil moisture and vegetation are key parameters influencing land-atmosphere interactions in the climate system by modifying the surface energy, moisture and carbon fluxes, and boundary conditions for the boundary layer. Because soil moisture, vegetation, turbulence (boundary layer and moist convection) organize on many different temporal and spatial scales, the study of land-atmosphere interactions has been notoriously difficult. The study of land-atmosphere interactions encompasses a wide range of disciplines from soil science, surface hydrology, hydrometeorology, plant physiology, turbulence, convection and atmosphere circulation. As such there is no single type of land-atmosphere interactions but a wide variety of cases embedded within the larger-scale general circulation.</p> <p class="formattext">The topic has become one of the leading topics in meteorology, climate and hydrologic sciences. Indeed correctly modeling and measuring the feedbacks between the lad surface and the atmosphere is key for improved hydrological, weather (weekly) and climate forecast (ecpecially on subseasonal-seasonal and interannual time scales). In particular extreme hydrological events over continents (floods and droughts) are strongly modulated by land-atmosphere interactions. Nonetheless the field of land-atmosphere interactions encompasses many fields such as...]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ NSF-sponsored Summer school on land-atmosphere interactions  Valsavarenche, Valle d'Aosta (Italy), Italy 22 June - 1 July, 2015     Directors of the course:   Pierre Gentine1 and Albert A.M. Holtslag2   1Columbia University, New York, NY USA; 2Wageningen University, Wageningen, the Netherlands     The Italian-French summer school on "Fundamental processes in geophysical fluid dynamics and the climate system" is organized each year by the Institute of Atmospheric Sciences and Climate (ISAC) - CNR (Turin, Italy) and by the Centre national de la recherche scientifique (France). This 23rd edition was dedicated to land-atmosphere interactions. This school aimed at providing to young researchers - Ph.D. students in particular - an up-to-date training program presenting a quantitative approach outlining physical principles, and the mathematical basis of land-atmosphere interactions. Some of the most well regarded researchers in the field of land-atmosphere interactions were present at the summer school, both teaching and interacting with the students. We had a total of 50 students and received more than 180 applications, a record for the summer school. More than 50% of the students were from minority (women, underrepresented groups). US students were coming from the following institutions: Princeton Univerity, Columbia University, Texas A&amp;M, University of Washington, University of California Irvine, University of California Berkeley, Duke University, University of Arizona, Boston University, The university of Texas at Austin, West Virginia University, University of Utah , State university of New York: Albany as well as Department of Energy labs The school was sponsored by NSF, GEWEX, EGU and CNRS, which allowed supporting many of the students of the class. Conference room was provided by the region of Valsavarenche. Slides of the summer school have been made widely available to the broader community at http://www.to.isac.cnr.it/aosta/index.html. Land-atmosphere interactions describe the coupled exchanges of momentum, heat, moisture and carbon between the land surface and the overlying atmosphere. These feedbacks are regulated through the interface: the planetary boundary layer in which intense turbulence occurs. Land-atmosphere interactions are important sources of seasonal climate predictability in several parts of the world. Soil moisture and vegetation are key parameters influencing land-atmosphere interactions in the climate system by modifying the surface energy, moisture and carbon fluxes, and boundary conditions for the boundary layer. Because soil moisture, vegetation, turbulence (boundary layer and moist convection) organize on many different temporal and spatial scales, the study of land-atmosphere interactions has been notoriously difficult. The study of land-atmosphere interactions encompasses a wide range of disciplines from soil science, surface hydrology, hydrometeorology, plant physiology, turbulence, convection and atmosphere circulation. As such there is no single type of land-atmosphere interactions but a wide variety of cases embedded within the larger-scale general circulation. The topic has become one of the leading topics in meteorology, climate and hydrologic sciences. Indeed correctly modeling and measuring the feedbacks between the lad surface and the atmosphere is key for improved hydrological, weather (weekly) and climate forecast (ecpecially on subseasonal-seasonal and interannual time scales). In particular extreme hydrological events over continents (floods and droughts) are strongly modulated by land-atmosphere interactions. Nonetheless the field of land-atmosphere interactions encompasses many fields such as boundary layer turbulence, convection, surface fluxes, ecophysiology and most students do not have the background necessary to address their science question. The objective of the summer school was thus to cover a wide rand of topics &ndash; within a coherent and understandable framework &nda...]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
