<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>NSF Postdoctoral Fellowship in Biology FY 2015</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>10/01/2015</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>09/30/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>216000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>216000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Fellowship Award</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>08090000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>BIO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>IOS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Integrative Organismal Systems</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Diane Jofuku Okamuro</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>dokamuro@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924508</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This action funds an NSF National Plant Genome Initiative Postdoctoral Research Fellowship in Biology for FY 2015. The fellowship supports a research and training plan in a host laboratory for the Fellow who also presents a plan to broaden participation in biology. The title of the research and training plan for this fellowship to Brook Moyers is "Using genotype and environment to predict water use physiology in rice."  The host institution for the fellowship is the Colorado State University and the sponsoring scientist is Dr. John McKay.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Rice is a water-intensive crop and the primary calorie source for many developing countries. As global demand for water increases, so will the need for rice varieties that require less water to grow. This project will model the interaction of genotype and environment to predict water use in rice, providing vital information to breeders and potentially contributing to the development of new drought-tolerant rice varieties. The project is in collaboration with researchers at the International Rice Research Institute and includes training in applied agricultural research. A diverse group of undergraduate researchers will participate in the project and will be trained as the next generation of plant breeders. Together, the proposed activities will provide the basis for an independent research program that uses fundamental research to address global needs.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project will tackle the "grand challenge" of predicting phenotype from genotype in specific environments by building and validating a physiological model that incorporates genotype effects. The two major objectives are (1) to use high-throughput phenotyping data from a new, highly recombinant rice population (Global MAGIC) to identify quantitative trait loci (QTL) underlying water use physiology in two soil moisture environments, and (2) to use these QTL as parameters in a model of water use physiology. The model will be validated by predicting phenotypes that are produced by the novel genotypes grown in specific environments. Evaluating the model will provide insight into the interactions among alleles and environmental factors affecting water use physiology in plants. All of the project data will be available to the public via the Dryad Digital Data Repository, and the Global MAGIC population is freely available to rice breeding programs through the International Rice Research Institute.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/22/2015</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/22/2015</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.074</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1523752</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Brooke</FirstName>
<LastName>Moyers</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>T</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Brooke T Moyers</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress/>
<PI_PHON>6172876623</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000679623</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/22/2015</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Moyers                  Brooke         T</Name>
<CityName>Vancouver, BC, V6H 2L4</CityName>
<ZipCode/>
<PhoneNumber/>
<StreetAddress/>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>Canada</CountryName>
<StateName/>
<StateCode/>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT/>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG/>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM/>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME/>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Colorado State University]]></Name>
<CityName>Fort Collins</CityName>
<StateCode>CO</StateCode>
<ZipCode>805231177</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Colorado</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF/>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>8105</Code>
<Text>NPGI PostDoc Rsrch Fellowship</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1329</Code>
<Text>PLANT GENOME RESEARCH PROJECT</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7137</Code>
<Text>POSTDOCTORAL FELLOWSHIPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7174</Code>
<Text>POSTDOC FELLOW IN SCI, MATH EN</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7577</Code>
<Text>PLANT GENOME RESEARCH RESOURCE</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9109</Code>
<Text>AGRICULTURAL BIOTECHNOLOGY</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9178</Code>
<Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>BIOT</Code>
<Text>BIOTECHNOLOGY</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0115</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2015~216000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><!--   @page { margin: 0.79in }   p { margin-bottom: 0.1in; line-height: 115% }   a:link { so-language: zxx }   --> <p><span style="font-family: &quot;Times New Roman&quot;, serif;"><span style="font-size: small;">Rice </span></span><span style="font-family: &quot;Times New Roman&quot;, serif;"><span style="font-size: small;">takes a lot of water to grow </span></span><span style="font-family: &quot;Times New Roman&quot;, serif;"><span style="font-size: small;">and </span></span><span style="font-family: &quot;Times New Roman&quot;, serif;"><span style="font-size: small;">is </span></span><span style="font-family: &quot;Times New Roman&quot;, serif;"><span style="font-size: small;">the primary calorie source for many developing countries. As global demand for water </span></span><span style="font-family: &quot;Times New Roman&quot;, serif;"><span style="font-size: small;">has</span></span><span style="font-family: &quot;Times New Roman&quot;, serif;"><span style="font-size: small;"> increase</span></span><span style="font-family: &quot;Times New Roman&quot;, serif;"><span style="font-size: small;">d</span></span><span style="font-family: &quot;Times New Roman&quot;, serif;"><span style="font-size: small;">, so </span></span><span style="font-family: &quot;Times New Roman&quot;, serif;"><span style="font-size: small;">has</span></span><span style="font-family: &quot;Times New Roman&quot;, serif;"><span style="font-size: small;"> the need for rice varieties that require less water to grow. </span></span><span style="font-family: &quot;Times New Roman&quot;, serif;"><span style="font-size: small;">This project aimed to </span></span><span style="font-family: &quot;Times New Roman&quot;, serif;"><span style="font-size: small;">discover genetic variants that control and interact with the environment to determine </span></span><span style="font-family: &quot;Times New Roman&quot;, serif;"><span style="font-size: small;">how rice responds to limited water</span></span><span style="font-family: &quot;Times New Roman&quot;, serif;"><span style="font-size: small;">. This </span></span><span style="font-family: &quot;Times New Roman&quot;, serif;"><span style="font-size: small;">is</span></span><span style="font-family: &quot;Times New Roman&quot;, serif;"><span style="font-size: small;"> vital information </span></span><span style="font-family: &quot;Times New Roman&quot;, serif;"><span style="font-size: small;">for</span></span><span style="font-family: &quot;Times New Roman&quot;, serif;"><span style="font-size: small;"> breeders and </span></span><span style="font-family: &quot;Times New Roman&quot;, serif;"><span style="font-size: small;">could</span></span><span style="font-family: &quot;Times New Roman&quot;, serif;"><span style="font-size: small;"> contribute to the development of new drought-tolerant rice varieties. In this </span></span><span style="font-family: &quot;Times New Roman&quot;, serif;"><span style="font-size: small;">work</span></span><span style="font-family: &quot;Times New Roman&quot;, serif;"><span style="font-size: small;"> </span></span><span style="font-family: &quot;Times New Roman&quot;, serif;"><span style="font-size: small;">the postdoctoral fellow </span></span><span style="font-family: &quot;Times New Roman&quot;, serif;"><span style="font-size: small;">collaborate</span></span><span style="font-family: &quot;Times New Roman&quot;, serif;"><span style="font-size: small;">d</span></span><span style="font-family: &quot;Times New Roman&quot;, serif;"><span style="font-size: small;"> with researchers at the International Rice Research Institute. </span></span><span style="font-family: &quot;Times New Roman&quot;, serif;"><span style="font-size: small;">An additional aim of this project was the professional development of the postdoctoral fellow and additional training for students and researchers by the postdoctoral fellow.</span></span></p> <p><span style="font-family: &quot;Times New Roman&quot;, serif;"><span style="font-size: small;"><strong>Intellectual Merit: </strong></span></span></p> <p><span style="font-family: &quot;Times New Roman&quot;, serif;"><span style="font-size: small;">This project has three primary research discoveries:</span></span></p> <p><span style="font-family: &quot;Times New Roman&quot;, serif;"><span style="font-size: small;">(1) When rice plants experience drought early in their growth (&lsquo;seedling stage drought&rsquo;), differences in how the plants respond is largely determined by environmental factors and the combined small effects of many genes. This means that rice breeders face a major challenge when trying to create new varieties that consistently grow well under seedling stage drought, because they cannot simply target a few genes with large effects.</span></span></p> <p><span style="font-family: &quot;Times New Roman&quot;, serif;"><span style="font-size: small;">(2) High-throughput phenotyping platforms are new automated technologies for measuring the traits of a lot of plants much faster than unassisted humans can. These platforms, used in real agricultural field environments (&lsquo;field-based&rsquo;), take the form of sensors and cameras mounted on tracks, tractors, or drones. This project helped to establish that field-based high-throughput phenotyping can successfully identify the genetic basis of important traits in rice. This means that these technologies can be used by public and private breeding programs to speed up their own research.</span></span></p> <p><span style="font-family: &quot;Times New Roman&quot;, serif;"><span style="font-size: small;"><span>(3) In a review of the literature, </span><span>this project found evidence for a consistent and </span>general 'genetic cost' imposed by the process of domestication. What this means is that during domestication, because of decreases in population size and strong selection, many species have inadvertently gained &lsquo;bad&rsquo; or negative effect mutations. Breeders should be aware of and address this pattern in their breeding programs.</span></span></p> <p><span style="font-family: &quot;Times New Roman&quot;, serif;"><span style="font-size: small;"><strong>Broad</strong><strong>er Impacts:</strong></span></span></p> <p><span style="font-family: &quot;Times New Roman&quot;, serif;"><span style="font-size: small;">The project&rsquo;s research on the genetic costs of domestication, the use of field-based high-throughput phenotyping platforms, and the genetic basis of early drought tolerance in rice are likely to impact agricultural breeding programs, and could help breeders create more stress tolerant and higher yielding varieties more quickly. These impacts may improve food security globally, particularly in rice. Rice provides a major portion of calories consumed by humans, particularly among the world&rsquo;s poorest people, so this could improve human health and well-being broadly.</span></span></p> <p><span style="font-family: &quot;Times New Roman&quot;, serif;"><span style="font-size: small;">As instructor of short workshops and longer courses, research mentor, and director of a summer-long undergraduate professional development program, the postdoctoral fellow provided training and professional development opportunities to at least 40 undergraduate students, 75 graduate students, 35 governmental researchers and managers, and 10 employees of an NGO. The majority of these opportunities were training in data management, programming, and computing literacy, as well as professional development to prepare students for diverse careers in biological research.</span></span></p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 12/29/2018<br>      Modified by: Brooke&nbsp;T&nbsp;Moyers</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[  Rice takes a lot of water to grow and is the primary calorie source for many developing countries. As global demand for water has increased, so has the need for rice varieties that require less water to grow. This project aimed to discover genetic variants that control and interact with the environment to determine how rice responds to limited water. This is vital information for breeders and could contribute to the development of new drought-tolerant rice varieties. In this work the postdoctoral fellow collaborated with researchers at the International Rice Research Institute. An additional aim of this project was the professional development of the postdoctoral fellow and additional training for students and researchers by the postdoctoral fellow.  Intellectual Merit:   This project has three primary research discoveries:  (1) When rice plants experience drought early in their growth (?seedling stage drought?), differences in how the plants respond is largely determined by environmental factors and the combined small effects of many genes. This means that rice breeders face a major challenge when trying to create new varieties that consistently grow well under seedling stage drought, because they cannot simply target a few genes with large effects.  (2) High-throughput phenotyping platforms are new automated technologies for measuring the traits of a lot of plants much faster than unassisted humans can. These platforms, used in real agricultural field environments (?field-based?), take the form of sensors and cameras mounted on tracks, tractors, or drones. This project helped to establish that field-based high-throughput phenotyping can successfully identify the genetic basis of important traits in rice. This means that these technologies can be used by public and private breeding programs to speed up their own research.  (3) In a review of the literature, this project found evidence for a consistent and general 'genetic cost' imposed by the process of domestication. What this means is that during domestication, because of decreases in population size and strong selection, many species have inadvertently gained ?bad? or negative effect mutations. Breeders should be aware of and address this pattern in their breeding programs.  Broader Impacts:  The project?s research on the genetic costs of domestication, the use of field-based high-throughput phenotyping platforms, and the genetic basis of early drought tolerance in rice are likely to impact agricultural breeding programs, and could help breeders create more stress tolerant and higher yielding varieties more quickly. These impacts may improve food security globally, particularly in rice. Rice provides a major portion of calories consumed by humans, particularly among the world?s poorest people, so this could improve human health and well-being broadly.  As instructor of short workshops and longer courses, research mentor, and director of a summer-long undergraduate professional development program, the postdoctoral fellow provided training and professional development opportunities to at least 40 undergraduate students, 75 graduate students, 35 governmental researchers and managers, and 10 employees of an NGO. The majority of these opportunities were training in data management, programming, and computing literacy, as well as professional development to prepare students for diverse careers in biological research.       Last Modified: 12/29/2018       Submitted by: Brooke T Moyers]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
