<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Doctoral Dissertation Improvement Grant: Insight Into Community Identity Development In Southeast Asia</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2015</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2016</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>16730.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>16730</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>04040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>SBE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>BCS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Behavioral and Cognitive Sci</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>John Yellen</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>jyellen@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032928759</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Southeast Asian countries, such as Vietnam, Indonesia, and the Philippines, are renowned for their culinary diversity. Yet little is known about the early development and variation of these cuisines, which potentially have their origins more than 2000 years ago. An understanding of culinary practice is relevant not only to understanding subsistence practices but also to gaining insight into the formation of stable and unified social and political groups. Shared practices provide an important "glue" which bind societies together and archaeology provides a means to set such interactions within an extended chronological context. Findings of this research will be incorporated into exhibits at Long An Provincial Museum (Vietnam), Siwalima Museum (Eastern Indonesia), and the Burke Museum (University of Washington).&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Under the guidance of Dr. John Krigbaum and in collaboration with colleagues from Australian National University, University of Washington, Southern Institute for Sustainable Development (Vietnam), and Long An Provincial Museum (Vietnam), Michelle S. Eusebio will conduct organic residue analysis on sampled pottery vessels from two Neolithic and two Metal Age sites situated along the tributaries of the Mekong River in southern Vietnam. Data collected will facilitate identification of different types of food (plant, terrestrial animal and aquatic food resources) that were prepared and/or served on recovered pottery. In combination with technofunctional analysis to infer form and function of this pottery, the results will provide complementary evidence of plant and animal resources exploited as food, and inform understanding of the variation, change, and continuity between cuisines. This research will address the questions: Do culinary practices reflect the available food resources and/or culturally conditioned practices in prehistoric Southeast Asia? What are the community identities of these people who occupied these sites based on their shared culinary practices? To aid in the interpretation of the Vietnamese prehistoric data, she will analyze pottery samples from a Neolithic coastal site in eastern Indonesia to provide an outgroup comparison. Ms. Eusebio will also construct a modern Southeast Asian reference collection of organic residues based on experimental and ethnographic pottery samples with known cooking histories and she will isotopically quantify oils and fats from economically important and endemic species of flora and fauna. This project is the first microregional and diachronic survey of food residues from Vietnam, focused on the preparation and presentation of food rather than simply its acquisition. Research findings will demonstrate that prehistoric Southeast Asia provides an ideal spatial and temporal benchmark for comparison to other regions with respect to diversity of cuisines and correlations with social identity. The recovery of food residues in prehistoric pottery used by different communities of people in southern Vietnam will contribute to our detailed knowledge of the history and development of regional cuisines.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>05/27/2015</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/27/2015</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.075</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1523112</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>John</FirstName>
<LastName>Krigbaum</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>S</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>John S Krigbaum</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>krigbaum@ufl.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>3522947540</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000114104</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/27/2015</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Michelle</FirstName>
<LastName>Eusebio</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>S</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Michelle S Eusebio</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>meusebio@ufl.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>3522223571</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000669658</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/27/2015</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Florida</Name>
<CityName>GAINESVILLE</CityName>
<ZipCode>326112002</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>3523923516</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1 UNIVERSITY OF FLORIDA</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Florida</StateName>
<StateCode>FL</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>FL03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>969663814</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF FLORIDA</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>159621697</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Florida]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>FL</StateCode>
<ZipCode>326117305</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Florida</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>FL03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7606</Code>
<Text>Archaeology DDRI</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1391</Code>
<Text>ARCHAEOLOGY</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9179</Code>
<Text>GRADUATE INVOLVEMENT</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0115</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2015~16730</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Doctoral Dissertation Improvement Grant: Insight Into Community Identity Development In Southeast Asia&nbsp;<br /> Project Outcomes Report for Award Number: 1523112<br /> <br /></p> <p>Vietnamese cuisine is considered as one of the healthiest and most enduring ethnic cuisines in the world. However, almost nothing is known about its early development, which potentially has its origin more than 2000 years ago. This is despite the ubiquity of material culture of foodways identified in the archaeological record of prehistoric Vietnam, that includes fragments of clay cooking pots and stoves. My dissertation research investigated the culinary practices in southern Vietnam during the Neolithic and Metal Age (3000 BC-AD 500) by analysis of food residues recovered from earthenware pottery.</p> <p>Specifically, I addressed how the preparation and/or consumption of food varied between four different sites - R?ch N&uacute;i, An S?n (Neolithic), L&ograve; G?ch, and G&ograve; &Ocirc; Ch&ugrave;a (Metal Age), and I also explored change and continuity of cuisine between succeeding time periods in the same region and inferred community identities based on shared cuisine. To address these research problems, I conducted organic residue analysis on sampled pottery vessels to identify former food contents (terrestrial animals and plants, aquatic resources). Data assayed include lipid biomarker compound distributions, compound-specific carbon isotopes of palmitic and stearic acids, as well as bulk carbon and nitrogen stable isotope ratios. To facilitate regional comparison and interpretation of the biochemical prehistoric pottery results, I developed a modern reference collection for Southeast Asia. This reference collection is composed of experimental and ethnographic pottery samples with known cooking histories, as well as oils and fats collected from economically important species of flora and fauna from Southeast Asia.</p> <p>Biochemical results from the prehistoric pottery suggest different vessels had different functions but were principally used for the preparation and consumption of plants and aquatic foodstuffs. The results of organic residue analysis of these pottery vessels suggest usage in the preparation and service of plant foods, and are less indicative of their usage for aquatic sources. The results indicate distinct patterns between sites that suggest that the people who inhabited these sites in prehistory may have distinct community identities based on their culinary practices. Despite this distinctiveness, there does seem to be continuity of culinary practices involving the usage of earthenware pottery vessels to prepare and serve plant and aquatic food sources from Neolithic to Metal Age in all samples with positive results. This continuity is demonstrated by the usage of pottery for preparing and serving a common local plant food source available within the vicinities of the three inland sites. My results highlight the importance of plant food sources and vessel-plant-aquatic source combination in maintaining and promoting identity in the Mekong Delta during prehistory. My results will substantively contribute to the construction of long-term culinary heritage of Vietnam and, more generally, across Southeast Asia. It seems that prehistoric culinary practices are remarkably similar to the present-day Vietnamese cuisine. Plants, probably vegetables, were likely prominent in Vietnamese cuisine prior to being colonized by the Chinese and the French.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 05/05/2017<br>      Modified by: John&nbsp;S&nbsp;Krigbaum</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Doctoral Dissertation Improvement Grant: Insight Into Community Identity Development In Southeast Asia   Project Outcomes Report for Award Number: 1523112     Vietnamese cuisine is considered as one of the healthiest and most enduring ethnic cuisines in the world. However, almost nothing is known about its early development, which potentially has its origin more than 2000 years ago. This is despite the ubiquity of material culture of foodways identified in the archaeological record of prehistoric Vietnam, that includes fragments of clay cooking pots and stoves. My dissertation research investigated the culinary practices in southern Vietnam during the Neolithic and Metal Age (3000 BC-AD 500) by analysis of food residues recovered from earthenware pottery.  Specifically, I addressed how the preparation and/or consumption of food varied between four different sites - R?ch N&uacute;i, An S?n (Neolithic), L&ograve; G?ch, and G&ograve; &Ocirc; Ch&ugrave;a (Metal Age), and I also explored change and continuity of cuisine between succeeding time periods in the same region and inferred community identities based on shared cuisine. To address these research problems, I conducted organic residue analysis on sampled pottery vessels to identify former food contents (terrestrial animals and plants, aquatic resources). Data assayed include lipid biomarker compound distributions, compound-specific carbon isotopes of palmitic and stearic acids, as well as bulk carbon and nitrogen stable isotope ratios. To facilitate regional comparison and interpretation of the biochemical prehistoric pottery results, I developed a modern reference collection for Southeast Asia. This reference collection is composed of experimental and ethnographic pottery samples with known cooking histories, as well as oils and fats collected from economically important species of flora and fauna from Southeast Asia.  Biochemical results from the prehistoric pottery suggest different vessels had different functions but were principally used for the preparation and consumption of plants and aquatic foodstuffs. The results of organic residue analysis of these pottery vessels suggest usage in the preparation and service of plant foods, and are less indicative of their usage for aquatic sources. The results indicate distinct patterns between sites that suggest that the people who inhabited these sites in prehistory may have distinct community identities based on their culinary practices. Despite this distinctiveness, there does seem to be continuity of culinary practices involving the usage of earthenware pottery vessels to prepare and serve plant and aquatic food sources from Neolithic to Metal Age in all samples with positive results. This continuity is demonstrated by the usage of pottery for preparing and serving a common local plant food source available within the vicinities of the three inland sites. My results highlight the importance of plant food sources and vessel-plant-aquatic source combination in maintaining and promoting identity in the Mekong Delta during prehistory. My results will substantively contribute to the construction of long-term culinary heritage of Vietnam and, more generally, across Southeast Asia. It seems that prehistoric culinary practices are remarkably similar to the present-day Vietnamese cuisine. Plants, probably vegetables, were likely prominent in Vietnamese cuisine prior to being colonized by the Chinese and the French.       Last Modified: 05/05/2017       Submitted by: John S Krigbaum]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
