<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>TWC: TTP Option: Small: Collaborative: SRN: On Establishing Secure and Resilient Networking Services</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2015</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>237000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>237000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>05050000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>CSE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CNS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Computer and Network Systems</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Kevin Thompson</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>kthompso@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924220</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Almost every organization depends on cloud-based services. The backend of cloud-based services are designed for multiple tenants and reside in data centers spread across multiple physical locations. Network security and security management are major hurdles in such a complex, shared environment. This research investigates mitigating the security challenges by taking a moving target defense (MTD) approach. Continually adjusting the system resources such as the topology of the data center, bandwidth allocation and traffic flow policies makes it difficult for attackers to compromise the system. New evaluations methods will be developed to ensure that these MTD mechanisms work properly in practice. The outcome of this research is to have cloud services that are more secure and resilient to attacks. This research is a collaborative effort conducted by researchers from three different universities, Arizona State University, Duke University, and the University of Missouri-Kansas City. Graduate students will be trained to serve the growing need for educating professionals in cyber security. The results of the proposed research will be incorporated into several courses taught at the respective institutions. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The MTD approach in a multi-location, multi-tenant data center environment requires a complex level of coordination. This research investigates defense mechanisms in the data center's virtual networking environment based on programmable networking solutions so that proactive attack countermeasures can be deployed with considerations of the system resource consumption, software bugs/vulnerabilities, effectiveness of countermeasures, and impact on consumers running applications. The research outcomes can be employed for applications that require security situation-awareness variables accurately predicted at a very fine grain resolution, from a few milliseconds to a few seconds. This introduces additional challenges, namely, developing new performance models for networking, data collection, big data-enabled security processing, and control. To address these challenges, this project has two interdependent fundamental research thrusts: (a) investigate a dynamic and adaptive defensive framework at both networking and software levels; and (b) deploy an adaptive security-enabled traffic engineering approach to select optimal countermeasures by considering the effectiveness of countermeasures and network bandwidth allocations while minimizing the intrusiveness to the applications and the cost of deploying the countermeasures. The outcomes of this project will include a set of software APIs and tools to integrate the measurement system and analytical models in a transition to practice effort.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>09/11/2015</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>09/11/2015</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.070</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1523994</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Kishor</FirstName>
<LastName>Trivedi</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>S</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Kishor S Trivedi</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>kst@ee.duke.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>9196605269</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000313610</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/11/2015</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Duke University</Name>
<CityName>Durham</CityName>
<ZipCode>277054010</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>9196843030</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>2200 W. Main St, Suite 710</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[Erwin Square]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>North Carolina</StateName>
<StateCode>NC</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NC01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>044387793</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>DUKE UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>044387793</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Duke University]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>NC</StateCode>
<ZipCode>277054010</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>North Carolina</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NC04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>8060</Code>
<Text>Secure &amp;Trustworthy Cyberspace</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7434</Code>
<Text>CNCI</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7923</Code>
<Text>SMALL PROJECT</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0115</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2015~237000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The SRN project is about developing new metrics, analytic models, and evaluation methods to dynamically adjust the networking system based on the security events and vulnerabilities detected in the system. To this end, this research focused on modeling attack scenarios by using a systematic approaches considering how to incorporate theoretical attack analysis models such as attack graphs into a real-time security decision procedure. In particular, software defined networking (SDN), network function virtualization (NFV), distributed firewall (DFW) approaches are used as the fundamental building blocks to provide a more agile and intelligent network security monitoring and management system. &nbsp;Moreover, this research investigates game theory based defense strategies considering sophisticated attack scenarios such as Advanced Persistent Threats (APTs) and appropriate Moving Target Defense (MTD) approach to mitigate APTs. Reliability of systems (both hardware and software) is also investigated.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>To disseminate the research outcomes, at Duke, the research team has produced more than 20 peer-reviewed high-quality research publications and a major textbook titled, Reliability and Availability Engineering, published by Cambridge University Press in 2017. A monograph on software aging and rejuvenation, co-edited by PI Trivedi, is currently with the printers. In addition to the conference presentations, PI Trivedi has delivered many invited talks including research seminars, panels, keynotes, and tutorials.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>Through this project, at Duke, one postdoc, two PhD students, and two MS students have devoted their efforts to build their research agenda, PhD dissertations, and MS thesis, respectively. A PhD student at the Technical University of Munich was co-advised by PI Trivedi and another is being co-advised at the University of Uberlandia in Brazil. PI Trivedi has also prepared a new course on software reliability that includes a module on software safety, security and survivability. This course was piloted at Hiroshima University in Spring 2019 and will be taught again in Spring 2020.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 12/06/2019<br>      Modified by: Kishor&nbsp;S&nbsp;Trivedi</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The SRN project is about developing new metrics, analytic models, and evaluation methods to dynamically adjust the networking system based on the security events and vulnerabilities detected in the system. To this end, this research focused on modeling attack scenarios by using a systematic approaches considering how to incorporate theoretical attack analysis models such as attack graphs into a real-time security decision procedure. In particular, software defined networking (SDN), network function virtualization (NFV), distributed firewall (DFW) approaches are used as the fundamental building blocks to provide a more agile and intelligent network security monitoring and management system.  Moreover, this research investigates game theory based defense strategies considering sophisticated attack scenarios such as Advanced Persistent Threats (APTs) and appropriate Moving Target Defense (MTD) approach to mitigate APTs. Reliability of systems (both hardware and software) is also investigated.     To disseminate the research outcomes, at Duke, the research team has produced more than 20 peer-reviewed high-quality research publications and a major textbook titled, Reliability and Availability Engineering, published by Cambridge University Press in 2017. A monograph on software aging and rejuvenation, co-edited by PI Trivedi, is currently with the printers. In addition to the conference presentations, PI Trivedi has delivered many invited talks including research seminars, panels, keynotes, and tutorials.        Through this project, at Duke, one postdoc, two PhD students, and two MS students have devoted their efforts to build their research agenda, PhD dissertations, and MS thesis, respectively. A PhD student at the Technical University of Munich was co-advised by PI Trivedi and another is being co-advised at the University of Uberlandia in Brazil. PI Trivedi has also prepared a new course on software reliability that includes a module on software safety, security and survivability. This course was piloted at Hiroshima University in Spring 2019 and will be taught again in Spring 2020.          Last Modified: 12/06/2019       Submitted by: Kishor S Trivedi]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
