<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Conference:  Grant Proposal to Support Participation of US Researchers at the Intensification of Resource Recovery Forum 2015</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>03/01/2015</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>02/29/2016</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>30000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>30000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07020000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CBET</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Chem, Bioeng, Env, &amp; Transp Sys</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>William Cooper</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>wjcooper@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032920000</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>1523702&lt;br/&gt;Sharp&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Grant Proposal to Support Participation of US Researchers at the Intensification of Resource Recovery Forum 2015&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;There are numerous challenges associated with the sustainable production of safe water, energy and food and to address these challenges the water industry has identified wastewater as a viable and sustainable source for not only quality water, but recoverable energy and nutrient resources. Recently, it has been understood that wastewater contains valuable resources such as carbon, nitrogen and phosphorus. Carbon in wastewater can be recovered to generate energy, while nitrogen and phosphorus recovery can supplement nutrient demand for agriculture. This conference will establish actionable roadmaps for the further development, demonstration, and implementation of technologies that intensify resource recovery at wastewater treatment plants.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This Conference includes realizing the full potential of resource recovery at wastewater treatment plants through active participation of all stakeholders in the development, testing, and implementation of intensifying technologies. The original paradigm of wastewater treatment to protect public health and improve environmental quality has begun to shift, and now includes sustainable energy production and resource recovery. To support this paradigm shift, the water industry must actively develop, demonstrate and implement new resource recovery technologies to maximize benefit, and reduce the cost and unintended environmental consequences of traditional wastewater treatment technologies. This conference program includes both a "technology pull" and a "technology push" strategy. Drivers for resource recovery and energy neutrality include decreased energy demand and carbon emissions, marketable commodities, and improved efficiency at reduced cost. This conference will actively engage researchers in the development and demonstration of technologies aimed at intensifying resource recovery, allowing them to lead the paradigm shift and create new opportunities for sustainable resource recovery.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>02/11/2015</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>02/11/2015</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1523702</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Robert</FirstName>
<LastName>Sharp</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>R</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Robert R Sharp</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>robert.sharp@manhattan.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>7188627169</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000480923</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>02/11/2015</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Manhattan College</Name>
<CityName>Riverdale</CityName>
<ZipCode>104714004</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>7188627160</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>4513 Manhattan College Parkway</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>16</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NY16</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>071040810</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>MANHATTAN COLLEGE CORP</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>071040810</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Manhattan College]]></Name>
<CityName>Bronx</CityName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<ZipCode>104714004</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[4513 Manhattan College Parkway]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>16</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NY16</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1440</Code>
<Text>EnvE-Environmental Engineering</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>016E</Code>
<Text>POLLUTION AVOIDANCE</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>021E</Code>
<Text>Water management</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7556</Code>
<Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0115</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2015~30000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Through the Leaders Innovation Forum for Technology (LIFT) program and support from the National Science Foundation, the Water Environment Federation (WEF) and the Water Environment Research Federation (WERF) hosted the Intensification and Resource Recovery (IR<sup>2</sup>) Forum on August 9-11, 2015, at Manhattan College in New York.&nbsp; The Forum was held in cooperation with Manhattan College, BlueTech Research, and with conference grant support from the National Science Foundation. &nbsp;The Forum attracted over 140 participants from academia, environmental engineering consulting firms, government agencies, municipalities/utilities, and technology developers/vendors.</p> <p>The primary goal of the IR<sup>2</sup> Forum was to provide an opportunity for technology developers/vendors, researchers, academics, facility owners and industry practitioners to collaborate in the development, assessment and implementation of the most promising resource recovery technologies currently under development.&nbsp;&nbsp; The Forum focused on technologies that had the potential to intensify resource recovery at wastewater treatment plants by achieving at least a 30% reduction in capital costs and a significant reduction in operational costs.&nbsp;</p> <p>The long-term objectives of the Forum was to develop long-lasting collaborations aimed at developing emerging resource recovery technologies. Reconvene to allow groups to discuss their plans, their funding needs, their concerns, etc. &nbsp;More information on the IR<sup>2</sup> Forum, including the Forum program, presentations, detailed notes, as well as continued posts related to Forum discussions and blogging, can be found at <a href="http://www.werf.org/lift/news/2015/IR2_Recap.aspx">www.werf.org/lift/news/2015/IR2_Recap.aspx</a>.&nbsp;&nbsp; Finally, a formal WERF report on the Forum has been submitted to the WERF Steering Committee for review and will be published by WERF in the near future.</p> <p>The Forum focused on five specific technology groups, covering over 30 new technologies aimed at reducing the capital and operational costs of wastewater treatment and resource recovery.&nbsp; These technology groups included:</p> <p><strong>1 - Dewaterability impacts of biological phosphorus removal</strong>: technologies that reduce the negative dewaterability impacts</p> <p><strong>2 - Biosolids to fuel</strong>:<strong> </strong>using pyrolysis or hydrothermal processes to directly produce fuels,</p> <p><strong>3 - Intensification of mainstream BNR:</strong> technologies that reduce aeration costs for nutrient removal or provide a higher biomass inventory in a smaller footprint,</p> <p><strong>4 - Carbon diversion:</strong> using enhanced primary treatment,&nbsp; filtration or high rate systems to increase carbon resource recovery, and</p> <p><strong>5 - Digestion enhancements</strong>:<strong> </strong>technologies that increase digestion biogas yields, including thermal hydrolysis pretreatment and co-digestion.</p> <p>After the technology area presentations, participants formed working groups to discuss the specific needs associated with each technology.&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; Each working session addressed four primary questions aimed at advancing the specific technology area:</p> <p>1. What are the research needs and gaps?</p> <p>2. What are the technology pilot and demonstration needs?</p> <p>3. What else is needed to advance this technology topic?</p> <p>4. Who are the potential partners?</p> <p><strong>Outcomes</strong></p> <p>The Key Outcome of the Forum was the identification of specific gaps and critical needs for advancing and establishing the different resource recovery technologies.&nbsp; Momentum from the Forum and continued initiatives from WEF and WERF have results in the development of collaborations and partnerships that will result in moving some of these technologies into full-scale demonstration and implementa...]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Through the Leaders Innovation Forum for Technology (LIFT) program and support from the National Science Foundation, the Water Environment Federation (WEF) and the Water Environment Research Federation (WERF) hosted the Intensification and Resource Recovery (IR2) Forum on August 9-11, 2015, at Manhattan College in New York.  The Forum was held in cooperation with Manhattan College, BlueTech Research, and with conference grant support from the National Science Foundation.  The Forum attracted over 140 participants from academia, environmental engineering consulting firms, government agencies, municipalities/utilities, and technology developers/vendors.  The primary goal of the IR2 Forum was to provide an opportunity for technology developers/vendors, researchers, academics, facility owners and industry practitioners to collaborate in the development, assessment and implementation of the most promising resource recovery technologies currently under development.   The Forum focused on technologies that had the potential to intensify resource recovery at wastewater treatment plants by achieving at least a 30% reduction in capital costs and a significant reduction in operational costs.   The long-term objectives of the Forum was to develop long-lasting collaborations aimed at developing emerging resource recovery technologies. Reconvene to allow groups to discuss their plans, their funding needs, their concerns, etc.  More information on the IR2 Forum, including the Forum program, presentations, detailed notes, as well as continued posts related to Forum discussions and blogging, can be found at www.werf.org/lift/news/2015/IR2_Recap.aspx.   Finally, a formal WERF report on the Forum has been submitted to the WERF Steering Committee for review and will be published by WERF in the near future.  The Forum focused on five specific technology groups, covering over 30 new technologies aimed at reducing the capital and operational costs of wastewater treatment and resource recovery.  These technology groups included:  1 - Dewaterability impacts of biological phosphorus removal: technologies that reduce the negative dewaterability impacts  2 - Biosolids to fuel: using pyrolysis or hydrothermal processes to directly produce fuels,  3 - Intensification of mainstream BNR: technologies that reduce aeration costs for nutrient removal or provide a higher biomass inventory in a smaller footprint,  4 - Carbon diversion: using enhanced primary treatment,  filtration or high rate systems to increase carbon resource recovery, and  5 - Digestion enhancements: technologies that increase digestion biogas yields, including thermal hydrolysis pretreatment and co-digestion.  After the technology area presentations, participants formed working groups to discuss the specific needs associated with each technology.    Each working session addressed four primary questions aimed at advancing the specific technology area:  1. What are the research needs and gaps?  2. What are the technology pilot and demonstration needs?  3. What else is needed to advance this technology topic?  4. Who are the potential partners?  Outcomes  The Key Outcome of the Forum was the identification of specific gaps and critical needs for advancing and establishing the different resource recovery technologies.  Momentum from the Forum and continued initiatives from WEF and WERF have results in the development of collaborations and partnerships that will result in moving some of these technologies into full-scale demonstration and implementation.   Other technologies are benefiting from increased interest from the industry in the form of additional funding and the identification of test-bed facilities where the technologies can be further tested and demonstrated.  The key outcomes from the Forum include:  1 - The identification of research and development gaps and needs as described in the Summary Notes from Technology Area Breakout Working Session section and with follow up in the upcom...]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
