<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>NSF Postdoctoral Fellowship in Biology FY 2015</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2015</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>138000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>138000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Fellowship Award</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>08080000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>BIO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DBI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Biological Infrastructure</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Amanda Simcox</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This action funds an NSF Postdoctoral Research Fellowship in Biology for FY 2015, Broadening Participation. The fellowship supports a research and training plan in a host laboratory for the Fellow and a plan to broaden participation of groups under-represented in science.  The title of the research plan for this fellowship to Margaret Byron is "How comb jellyfish swim and navigate in ocean turbulence." The host institution for this fellowship is the University of California Irvine, with secondary support to be provided by Stanford University; the sponsoring scientists are Matthew J. McHenry (UCI) and John O. Dabiri (Stanford).&lt;br/&gt; &lt;br/&gt;Ctenophores, commonly called comb jellyfish, are widespread in the earth's oceans and play an important role in the marine food chain.  They are also the largest organisms that swim using cilia, a type of locomotion which is normally reserved for much smaller organisms and animals, in both fresh and salt water.  Only a few centimeters in size, ctenophores live in a complex and turbulent environment, full of gusts and eddies that dwarf them in size.  Despite their relatively simple propulsion system, ctenophores are very agile and maneuverable, retaining impressive control over their orientation and position in the midst of these chaotic surroundings.  This research uses high-speed cameras and flow visualization techniques to study how ctenophores move in response to turbulent gusts, showing how they adapt their behavior to the surrounding flow.  This will provide clues to their preferred habitats, population dynamics, and ecological roles.  In addition to the basic knowledge of locomotion being gained, a better understanding of the principles of ciliated locomotion promises to aid improvements in locomotion and navigation in small underwater robots, important platforms for exploration and discovery in the aquatic environment.  &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This research at the interface of biology and engineering affords the Fellow the opportunity to enhance her background in engineering with training in biology and career advancement opportunties in both fields.  The joint sponsorship and interdisciplinary setting provide a foundation for an eventual independent research program at the intersection of fluid dynamics and aquatic animal locomotion.  Educational outreach includes supervising and mentoring undergraduate research assistants recruited from programs serving underrepresented minorities.  The students are deeply involved in the project, including experiments, analysis, and the presentation and publication of results.  The results are being made available to the Monterey Bay Aquarium, which provides animals and experimental facilities for the research, and are being incorporated into programs and educational displays for the general public and school groups.  As a further effort to engage the public with biology, ocean science, fluid dynamics, and biomechanics research in general, the Fellow is curating an online repository of research results and other relevant work as well as engaging the public via social media and other web-based tools.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/14/2015</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/14/2015</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.074</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1523879</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Margaret</FirstName>
<LastName>Byron</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>L</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Margaret L Byron</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress/>
<PI_PHON>8148630736</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000688884</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/14/2015</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Byron                   Margaret       L</Name>
<CityName>Oakland</CityName>
<ZipCode>946181569</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber/>
<StreetAddress/>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>13</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CA13</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM/>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME/>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of California Irvine]]></Name>
<CityName>Irvine</CityName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>926970001</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>45</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CA45</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1157</Code>
<Text>Broadening Participation of Gr</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7137</Code>
<Text>POSTDOCTORAL FELLOWSHIPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0115</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2015~138000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>As a recipient of the NSF Postdoctoral Research Fellowship in Biology, Dr. Margaret Byron investigated the biomechanics of swimming in comb jellies (ctenophores).&nbsp; Ctenophores occupy a unique position as the oldest known animals on the planet.&nbsp; However, they are also unique from a physical/engineering perspective: they are the largest animals on earth who use cilia to propel themselves through the water.&nbsp; Since ctenophores are several orders of magnitude larger than the microorganisms typically associated with cilia, Dr. Byron and her collaborators wanted to investigate the swimming strategies of these animals to uncover potential applications for engineered devices, such as micro-scale underwater vehicles. Furthermore, this research contributed to our overall understanding of an enigmatic, ancient citizen of the deep.</p> <p>Ctenophores, despite their small size of 1-15cm, have flourished throughout the world's oceans in a variety of flow environments, from the turbulent surface ocean near the coasts to the calmer deep waters hundreds of miles offshore.&nbsp; Dr. Byron subjected the ctenophore species <em>Pleurobrachia bachei</em> to a variety of complex flows, and investigated the animals' ability to maneuver and remain in control of their swimming behavior despite the turbulence surrounding them.&nbsp; She used 3D tracking methods to measure the animals' position and orientation within the flow.&nbsp; These data will be analyzed to help shed light on the strategies used by ctenophores to survive and thrive in turbulence.&nbsp; The physical insights gained by this study will be shared with the robotics community in the hope of developing new and more efficient underwater vehicles.&nbsp;&nbsp;</p> <p>Over the course of this project, Dr. Byron has:</p> <ul> <li>Developed and refined a new tank design for the study of fragile gelatinous marine zooplankton and their swimming behavior in turbulence;</li> <li>Collected a large amount of data on ctenophore swimming behavior, which will be analyzed over the next several months;</li> <li>Participated in other projects in the host lab at UC Irvine, which focused on the hydrodynamic sensing abilities of zebrafish, a key model species;</li> <li>Worked with aquarists at the Monterey Bay Aquarium (MBA) to increase their knowledge of laboratory generation of specialized fluid flows;</li> <li>Established a protocol for tracking ctenophores via visible implant elastomer tags.</li> </ul> <p>Though the full scope of the research results is still pending analysis, preliminary work from this project has already been presented at three scientific conferences (including an international meeting in Eilat, Israel).&nbsp; This includes an invited meeting organized by the National Academies Keck Futures Initiative (NAKFI), after which Dr. Byron and her collaborators received additional seed grant funding to further investigate the biomechanics of ctenophore swimming.&nbsp; Dr. Byron has also established a lasting research collaboration with aquarists and scientists at the Monterey Bay Aquarium, allowing her to disseminate her research results to the general public.&nbsp; In keeping with the fellowship's focus on Broader Impacts, Dr. Byron also served as a project mentor for the UCI Bridges to Baccalaureate program, a program for underrepresented minority students who are transitioning from community college to a four-year institution in the UC system.&nbsp; She also served on UCI's Advisory Council for Campus Climate, Culture, Diversity and Inclusion.&nbsp; Lastly, the fellowship helped Dr. Byron to secure a tenure-track faculty position.&nbsp; She is currently an Assistant Professor of Mechanical Engineering at Penn State University, and plans to continue her work on ctenophore swimming as well as other topics in both animal locomotion and particle transport in environmental turbulence, her PhD topic.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 10/31/2017<br>      Modified by: Margaret&nbsp;L&nbsp;Byron</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Images (<span id="selectedPhoto0">1</span> of <span class="totalNumber"></span>)           </div> <div class="galControls" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1523879/1523879_10376536_1509454211555_tank--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1523879/1523879_10376536_1509454211555_tank--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Custom-built tank for studying ctenophore swimming"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1523879/1523879_10376536_1509454211555_tank--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Custom-built tank for studying ctenophore swimming"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">This custom-built tank allows researchers to precisely control the flow environment experienced by gelatinous marine invertebrates like the comb jelly pictured here.  The animal is injected with fluorescent tags which glow under blue light, which helps to track the swimming behavior.</div> <div class="imageCredit">M. Byron</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Creative Commons</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Margaret&nbsp;L&nbsp;Byron</div> <div class="imageTitle">Custom-built tank for studying ctenophore swimming</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1523879/1523879_10376536_1509454317029_IMG_20170521_094313912(2)--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1523879/1523879_10376536_1509454317029_IMG_20170521_094313912(2)--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Ctenophore close-up"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1523879/1523879_10376536_1509454317029_IMG_20170521_094313912(2)--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Ctenophore close-up"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">A ctenophore (comb jelly) swims in the turbulence tank.  Here you can clearly see the embedded fluorescent tags which help us track the animal's motion.  The swimming behavior of comb jellies in turbulence may help us to design better control and propulsion systems for underwater vehicles.</div> <div class="imageCredit">M. Byron</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Creative Commons</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Margaret&nbsp;L&nbsp;Byron</div> <div class="imageTitle">Ctenophore close-up</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1523879/1523879_10376536_1509454421837_IMG_20170520_170253595--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1523879/1523879_10376536_1509454421837_IMG_20170520_170253595--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Measuring a comb jelly"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1523879/1523879_10376536_1509454421837_IMG_20170520_170253595--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Measuring a comb jelly"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Before being placed in the turbulence tank, individual jellies were measured and tagged with fluorescent elastomer.  The animal has two marks so that we can distinguish between top and bottom and therefore track the animal's orientation with respect to gravity.</div> <div class="imageCredit">M. Byron</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Creative Commons</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Margaret&nbsp;L&nbsp;Byron</div> <div class="imageTitle">Measuring a comb jelly</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ As a recipient of the NSF Postdoctoral Research Fellowship in Biology, Dr. Margaret Byron investigated the biomechanics of swimming in comb jellies (ctenophores).  Ctenophores occupy a unique position as the oldest known animals on the planet.  However, they are also unique from a physical/engineering perspective: they are the largest animals on earth who use cilia to propel themselves through the water.  Since ctenophores are several orders of magnitude larger than the microorganisms typically associated with cilia, Dr. Byron and her collaborators wanted to investigate the swimming strategies of these animals to uncover potential applications for engineered devices, such as micro-scale underwater vehicles. Furthermore, this research contributed to our overall understanding of an enigmatic, ancient citizen of the deep.  Ctenophores, despite their small size of 1-15cm, have flourished throughout the world's oceans in a variety of flow environments, from the turbulent surface ocean near the coasts to the calmer deep waters hundreds of miles offshore.  Dr. Byron subjected the ctenophore species Pleurobrachia bachei to a variety of complex flows, and investigated the animals' ability to maneuver and remain in control of their swimming behavior despite the turbulence surrounding them.  She used 3D tracking methods to measure the animals' position and orientation within the flow.  These data will be analyzed to help shed light on the strategies used by ctenophores to survive and thrive in turbulence.  The physical insights gained by this study will be shared with the robotics community in the hope of developing new and more efficient underwater vehicles.    Over the course of this project, Dr. Byron has:  Developed and refined a new tank design for the study of fragile gelatinous marine zooplankton and their swimming behavior in turbulence; Collected a large amount of data on ctenophore swimming behavior, which will be analyzed over the next several months; Participated in other projects in the host lab at UC Irvine, which focused on the hydrodynamic sensing abilities of zebrafish, a key model species; Worked with aquarists at the Monterey Bay Aquarium (MBA) to increase their knowledge of laboratory generation of specialized fluid flows; Established a protocol for tracking ctenophores via visible implant elastomer tags.   Though the full scope of the research results is still pending analysis, preliminary work from this project has already been presented at three scientific conferences (including an international meeting in Eilat, Israel).  This includes an invited meeting organized by the National Academies Keck Futures Initiative (NAKFI), after which Dr. Byron and her collaborators received additional seed grant funding to further investigate the biomechanics of ctenophore swimming.  Dr. Byron has also established a lasting research collaboration with aquarists and scientists at the Monterey Bay Aquarium, allowing her to disseminate her research results to the general public.  In keeping with the fellowship's focus on Broader Impacts, Dr. Byron also served as a project mentor for the UCI Bridges to Baccalaureate program, a program for underrepresented minority students who are transitioning from community college to a four-year institution in the UC system.  She also served on UCI's Advisory Council for Campus Climate, Culture, Diversity and Inclusion.  Lastly, the fellowship helped Dr. Byron to secure a tenure-track faculty position.  She is currently an Assistant Professor of Mechanical Engineering at Penn State University, and plans to continue her work on ctenophore swimming as well as other topics in both animal locomotion and particle transport in environmental turbulence, her PhD topic.       Last Modified: 10/31/2017       Submitted by: Margaret L Byron]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
