<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>"Science Live!" Workshop on the Acquisition of Recursion across Languages; Holland - July, 2015</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>05/01/2015</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>10/31/2016</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>29681.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>29681</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>04040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>SBE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>BCS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Behavioral and Cognitive Sci</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Joan Maling</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>jmaling@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032928046</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This project will organize a series of workshops that will culminate in a museum exhibit on children's acquisition of recursion in grammar. The exhibit will be presented as part of the Science Live! program at the NEMO Science Museum in Amsterdam in summer 2015, and later will be shared with other museums and schools in the U.S. and abroad. The goal is to educate museum-goers about research by having them participate in on-going data collection as well as demonstrations and learning experiences on the topic of the research. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Recursion is the process of "putting something inside itself," much like Russian dolls within dolls within dolls. Recursive routines are commonly found in computer programs and are the basis for learning the number system--creating the series of n, (n+1), ((n+1) +1), etc. In a generative grammar, it is the mechanism by which small meaningful units are recombined into an unlimited variety of larger structures. All languages have the basic form of recursion, while other forms vary from language to language.  For example, few languages allow recursive possessive phrases the way English does, illustrated by a 3-year-old who said: "You are my Mom's Mom." The recursive process of putting a possessive inside a possessive could, in principle, continue indefinitely.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Despite its importance, surprisingly little is understood about how and when the specific recursive structures found in various languages are acquired. The goal of the proposed exhibit is to use the principles of hands-on, informal learning to translate the abstract concept of recursion into concrete experiences for people of many different ages and backgrounds. The experiments which are the heart of this project provide engaging activities using hands-on apps on an iPad through which subtle aspects of children's understanding of the meanings and limits of recursive structures can be explored. The simplicity and flexibility of the iPad protocol permit the researcher to test a variety of structures across a wide range of ages, and ask further, at what level of abstraction learners generalize. Through the exhibit, the investigators will gather experimental evidence from museum-goers to test their hypotheses; the demonstrations that follow the actual experiments will engage children and their caregivers in challenges similar to those given to children around the world by colleagues in Japan, Canada, the Netherlands, Germany, and among indigenous peoples in Brazil, and will help them understand this fundamental dimension of what makes us human. By emphasizing the abstractness of representations required for all human languages, the project will work to counteract negative stereotypes about so-called 'primitive' languages, sometimes claimed to lack the fundamental property of recursion.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>04/24/2015</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>04/24/2015</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.075</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1523459</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Thomas</FirstName>
<LastName>Roeper</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Thomas Roeper</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>roeper@linguist.umass.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>4135456834</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000328224</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/24/2015</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Massachusetts Amherst</Name>
<CityName>Hadley</CityName>
<ZipCode>010359450</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>4135450698</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>Research Administration Building</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[100 Venture Way, Suite 201]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
<StateCode>MA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MA02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>153926712</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF MASSACHUSETTS</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>079520631</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Massachusetts Amherst]]></Name>
<CityName>Amherst</CityName>
<StateCode>MA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>010039242</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[70 Butterfield Terrace]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MA02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1311</Code>
<Text>Linguistics</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1311</Code>
<Text>LINGUISTICS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>SMET</Code>
<Text>SCIENCE, MATH, ENG &amp; TECH EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0115</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2015~29681</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>SCIENCE LIVE! -- Authentic research on recursion in language carried out in a museum setting</p> <p>The Science Live project allowed us to bring the deepest property of human grammar---a central property of mind---to life in a simple way for parents and children.&nbsp; That capacity, called &ldquo;recursion,&rdquo; is the ability to put a complex structure inside itself in language.&nbsp; Children carried out a game using iPads, that involves building a sequence like: &ldquo;put the car next to the butterfly under the monkey next to the squirrel over the lion&hellip;&rdquo; &nbsp;We sense that it can go on forever--and so do children between 4 and 8 years of age.&nbsp;&nbsp; It is the same property that allows us to put sentences inside each other and talk about other people&rsquo;s ideas and their beliefs, true and false [John thinks that Bill thinks that we all know the earth is round, but some people think it is flat.] &nbsp;It enables people&nbsp; to consciously articulate the intricacy of ideas embedded in other ideas.&nbsp;</p> <p>An important dimension of this project is scientific---an experiment buried in the game. &nbsp;The game explores how and where in language this ability first emerges and how it grows across a range of structures. Many young children understand the sentence "Put the car next to the butterfly under the monkey" as: &ldquo;the car next to the butterfly&nbsp;<span style="text-decoration: underline;">and</span> under the monkey.&rdquo;&nbsp; Or they <span style="text-decoration: underline;">mis</span>understand: &ldquo;John&rsquo;s friend&rsquo;s bike&rdquo; as &ldquo;John&rsquo;s <span style="text-decoration: underline;">and</span> friend&rsquo;s bike.&rdquo; Such misunderstandings can complicate their early reading and also the experience of bilinguals.&nbsp; The misunderstanding also obeys a principle and creates a simpler&mdash;conjoined structure, as if every phrase is linked by <em>and</em>. &nbsp;It can come out radically wrong: &ldquo;the cat chased the rat that ate the cheese&rdquo; becomes &ldquo;the cat chased the rat AND ate the cheese.&rdquo; &nbsp;(Who ate the cheese?)</p> <p>More than 500 children have been involved in the project so far.&nbsp; We have found that acquisition is quite variable.&nbsp; Some children understand at 5 years what others seem to master only at 8 years, but in general, children move from a conjunctive to a recursive preference between ages 5 and 8 years.&nbsp; The museum settings where the experiments were carried out allowed informal interactions with children and easy-going discussions with parents, who often have concerns about their children&rsquo;s language.</p> <p>The project engaged the Dutch National NEMO museum and now the Boston Museum of Science, Holyoke Children&rsquo;s Museum and potentially museums in Barcelona and Washington DC.&nbsp; It will lead, we hope, to a better understanding of both the kinds of rules found throughout the mind and the kinds of skills needed for understanding computer programming.&nbsp; It should lead to an enrichment of children&rsquo;s literature--expanding the intuitive insight that nursery rhymes help children&rsquo;s language, like: &ldquo;this is the cat that chased the rat that ate the cheese that was in the corner.&rdquo;</p> <p>What is on the frontier of this research?&nbsp; An exciting new question: &nbsp;since the chosen forms vary across languages, they must be learned and there is an acquisition sequence to explore.&nbsp; Does one form of recursion enable another?&nbsp; English has endless compounds: <em>coffee-maker-lover</em> while French puts this form of recursion on the other side [<em>&lsquo;a lover of makers of coffee&rsquo;]</em>. &nbsp;In this project, we showed that several forms of &ldquo;right-branching&rdquo; recursive expressions, prepositional phrases and relative clauses, arise in children&rsquo;s language together.&nbsp; Does the left-branching structure, &ldquo;John&rsquo;s friend&rsquo;s sister&rsquo;s dog,&rdquo; arise at the same time as an analogous right-branching structure, &ldquo;a box of packages of oranges&rdquo;? &nbsp;</p> <p>The museum project builds upon 25 years of research into recursion in compounds, adjectives, sentences, possessives, relative clauses, serial verbs, and morphology. &nbsp;Parallel work in Spanish, Japanese, Portuguese, Romanian, Hungarian, Hindi, Piraha, Dutch, and German has begun to allow us to see how other intricacies of grammar interact with the child&rsquo;s grasp of the deeper recursive structures that he/she encounters.&nbsp; Languages like Romanian--where recursion is clearly marked, as we mark relative clauses with <em>that</em>--may facilitate the realization of recursion. The project also engages modern technology in innovative ways, including ipads, a program to build apps, and the resources of software like <em>Explain Everything.</em>&nbsp; Research colleagues at Groningen are extending our first game into new ones.&nbsp; &nbsp;&nbsp;Our connection to the Museum of Science is intersecting with their program in schools to teach elementary computer skills. Thus, across a broad spectrum the project advances science, public awareness, and pedagogical opportunities.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 03/27/2017<br>      Modified by: Thomas&nbsp;Roeper</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Images (<span id="selectedPhoto0">1</span> of <span class="totalNumber"></span>)           </div> <div class="galControls" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1523459/1523459_10360345_1490548554862_Childbeingtested2--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1523459/1523459_10360345_1490548554862_Childbeingtested2--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Childbeing test2.jpg"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1523459/1523459_10360345_1490548554862_Childbeingtested2--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Childbeing test2.jpg"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Child at Science Live! with iPad app</div> <div class="imageCredit">BHollebrandse</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Royalty-free (unrestricted use)</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Thomas&nbsp;Roeper</div> <div class="imageTitle">Childbeing test2.jpg</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1523459/1523459_10360345_1490587759352_IMG_0567Nemo_group--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1523459/1523459_10360345_1490587759352_IMG_0567Nemo_group--rgov-800width.jpg" title="NEMO Museum Science Live!"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1523459/1523459_10360345_1490587759352_IMG_0567Nemo_group--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="NEMO Museum Science Live!"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Language research space at the NEMO Museum, summer 2016</div> <div class="imageCredit">B. Hollebrandse</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Royalty-free (unrestricted use)</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Thomas&nbsp;Roeper</div> <div class="imageTitle">NEMO Museum Science Live!</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1523459/1523459_10360345_1490588572266_NEMO_Researchersandassistants--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1523459/1523459_10360345_1490588572266_NEMO_Researchersandassistants--rgov-800width.jpg" title="NEMO Museum Language researchers"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1523459/1523459_10360345_1490588572266_NEMO_Researchersandassistants--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="NEMO Museum Language researchers"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">B. Hollebrandse (left); T. Roeper (center); A. van Hout (right), with research assistants</div> <div class="imageCredit">B. Hollebrandse</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Royalty-free (unrestricted use)</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Thomas&nbsp;Roeper</div> <div class="imageTitle">NEMO Museum Language researchers</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1523459/1523459_10360345_1490663946504_DollinDoll_crop--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1523459/1523459_10360345_1490663946504_DollinDoll_crop--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Doll_in_Doll.jpg"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1523459/1523459_10360345_1490663946504_DollinDoll_crop--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Doll_in_Doll.jpg"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Infinite sentences with recursion</div> <div class="imageCredit">B. Pearson</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Royalty-free (unrestricted use)</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Thomas&nbsp;Roeper</div> <div class="imageTitle">Doll_in_Doll.jpg</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1523459/1523459_10360345_1490664388834_Capture_car_lion_crop--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1523459/1523459_10360345_1490664388834_Capture_car_lion_crop--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Car_to_Lion.jpg"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1523459/1523459_10360345_1490664388834_Capture_car_lion_crop--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Car_to_Lion.jpg"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">A has implicit "and" (conjunctive) versus B with no "and" (recursive)</div> <div class="imageCredit">S. Amiri</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Royalty-free (unrestricted use)</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Thomas&nbsp;Roeper</div> <div class="imageTitle">Car_to_Lion.jpg</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1523459/1523459_10360345_1490664609357_Genitives_v4_wProtocol_slide7--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1523459/1523459_10360345_1490664609357_Genitives_v4_wProtocol_slide7--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Possessive_slide7.jpg"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1523459/1523459_10360345_1490664609357_Genitives_v4_wProtocol_slide7--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Possessive_slide7.jpg"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Recursive possessive (no implicit 'and")</div> <div class="imageCredit">M.Wilson</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Royalty-free (restricted use - cannot be shared)</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Thomas&nbsp;Roeper</div> <div class="imageTitle">Possessive_slide7.jpg</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ SCIENCE LIVE! -- Authentic research on recursion in language carried out in a museum setting  The Science Live project allowed us to bring the deepest property of human grammar---a central property of mind---to life in a simple way for parents and children.  That capacity, called "recursion," is the ability to put a complex structure inside itself in language.  Children carried out a game using iPads, that involves building a sequence like: "put the car next to the butterfly under the monkey next to the squirrel over the lion&hellip;"  We sense that it can go on forever--and so do children between 4 and 8 years of age.   It is the same property that allows us to put sentences inside each other and talk about other people?s ideas and their beliefs, true and false [John thinks that Bill thinks that we all know the earth is round, but some people think it is flat.]  It enables people  to consciously articulate the intricacy of ideas embedded in other ideas.   An important dimension of this project is scientific---an experiment buried in the game.  The game explores how and where in language this ability first emerges and how it grows across a range of structures. Many young children understand the sentence "Put the car next to the butterfly under the monkey" as: "the car next to the butterfly and under the monkey."  Or they misunderstand: "John?s friend?s bike" as "John?s and friend?s bike." Such misunderstandings can complicate their early reading and also the experience of bilinguals.  The misunderstanding also obeys a principle and creates a simpler&mdash;conjoined structure, as if every phrase is linked by and.  It can come out radically wrong: "the cat chased the rat that ate the cheese" becomes "the cat chased the rat AND ate the cheese."  (Who ate the cheese?)  More than 500 children have been involved in the project so far.  We have found that acquisition is quite variable.  Some children understand at 5 years what others seem to master only at 8 years, but in general, children move from a conjunctive to a recursive preference between ages 5 and 8 years.  The museum settings where the experiments were carried out allowed informal interactions with children and easy-going discussions with parents, who often have concerns about their children?s language.  The project engaged the Dutch National NEMO museum and now the Boston Museum of Science, Holyoke Children?s Museum and potentially museums in Barcelona and Washington DC.  It will lead, we hope, to a better understanding of both the kinds of rules found throughout the mind and the kinds of skills needed for understanding computer programming.  It should lead to an enrichment of children?s literature--expanding the intuitive insight that nursery rhymes help children?s language, like: "this is the cat that chased the rat that ate the cheese that was in the corner."  What is on the frontier of this research?  An exciting new question:  since the chosen forms vary across languages, they must be learned and there is an acquisition sequence to explore.  Does one form of recursion enable another?  English has endless compounds: coffee-maker-lover while French puts this form of recursion on the other side [?a lover of makers of coffee?].  In this project, we showed that several forms of "right-branching" recursive expressions, prepositional phrases and relative clauses, arise in children?s language together.  Does the left-branching structure, "John?s friend?s sister?s dog," arise at the same time as an analogous right-branching structure, "a box of packages of oranges"?    The museum project builds upon 25 years of research into recursion in compounds, adjectives, sentences, possessives, relative clauses, serial verbs, and morphology.  Parallel work in Spanish, Japanese, Portuguese, Romanian, Hungarian, Hindi, Piraha, Dutch, and German has begun to allow us to see how other intricacies of grammar interact with the child?s grasp of the deeper recursive structures that he/she encounters.  Languages like Romanian--where recursion is clearly marked, as we mark relative clauses with that--may facilitate the realization of recursion. The project also engages modern technology in innovative ways, including ipads, a program to build apps, and the resources of software like Explain Everything.  Research colleagues at Groningen are extending our first game into new ones.    Our connection to the Museum of Science is intersecting with their program in schools to teach elementary computer skills. Thus, across a broad spectrum the project advances science, public awareness, and pedagogical opportunities.             Last Modified: 03/27/2017       Submitted by: Thomas Roeper]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
