<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>NSF Postdoctoral Fellowship in Biology FY 2015</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>01/01/2016</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>138000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>138000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Fellowship Award</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>08080000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>BIO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DBI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Biological Infrastructure</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Amanda Simcox</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This action funds an NSF Postdoctoral Research Fellowship in Biology for FY 2015, Research Using Biological Collections. The fellowship supports a research and training plan for the Fellow to take transformative approaches to grand challenges in biology that employ biological collections in highly innovative ways. The title of the research plan for this fellowship to Kristin E. Brzeski is "How range expansion influences genetic change and disease susceptibility in coyotes." The host institution is Princeton University, and the sponsoring scientist is Dr. Bridgett vonHoldt.&lt;br/&gt; &lt;br/&gt;Understanding how animals adapt during range expansion is critical to predict how they may respond to a changing environment and how to assess and manage their interactions with native species. Assessing how animals, i.e., hosts, and pathogens interact during range expansion is especially important because an animal's basic biology can be shaped by efforts to detect and defeat disease. Coyotes (Canis latrans) are an ideal species to evaluate issues of range expansion because they recently expanded their range eastward in the U.S. and are interacting with native species, such as endangered red wolves, and information is needed on coyote pathogens, which may affect other species. The fellowship research evaluates the genetic and immunological consequences of range expansion. Few studies have evaluated adaptive evolution or host-pathogen dynamics in expanding populations, thus the research promises to provide novel insights into important evolutionary and ecological processes.  Specifically, the effects of range expansion are being studied by evaluating 1) coyote genetic variation in their historic and expanded range and 2) host-pathogen dynamics at the coyote expansion front. Genetic and serum samples are provided by the following museums and collections:  Denver Museum of Natural Science; Oklahoma Museum of Natural History; Louisiana State University Museum of Natural Science; New York State Museum; and the Red Wolf Recovery Programs Archival Data.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Training goals include gaining expertise in genomic and bioinformatics techniques.  The fellowship research has value for conservation efforts and wildlife management as coyotes have become highly visible animals and are often considered pests. Thus factors influencing their biology, such as population structure and adaption, are of general interest and can be used to educate the public and inform management actions. This is especially true regarding pathogen data because coyotes and domestic dogs can interact and share diseases, putting pets at risk. Public outreach includes partnerships with conservation organizations and publishing in nontechnical magazines to enhance the public's knowledge of current science discoveries. Educational outreach involves mentoring undergraduate students.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/27/2015</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/27/2015</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.074</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1523859</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Kristin</FirstName>
<LastName>Brzeski</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>E</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Kristin E Brzeski</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress/>
<PI_PHON>2628445956</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000688689</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/27/2015</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Brzeski                 Kristin        E</Name>
<CityName>Baton Rouge</CityName>
<ZipCode>708030001</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber/>
<StreetAddress/>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Louisiana</StateName>
<StateCode>LA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>06</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>LA06</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM/>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME/>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Princeton University, Ecology & Evolutionary Biology]]></Name>
<CityName>Princeton</CityName>
<StateCode>NJ</StateCode>
<ZipCode>085442016</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New Jersey</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>12</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NJ12</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>8049</Code>
<Text>Biology Postdoctoral Research</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7137</Code>
<Text>POSTDOCTORAL FELLOWSHIPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0115</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2015~138000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>My name is Kristin Brzeski, a National Science Foundation (NSF) postdoctoral fellow that worked with Bridgett vonHoldt at Princeton University as a project leader for the Canine Ancestry Project. The Canine Ancestry Project is an on-going endeavor that studies North American canine ecology, demography, and population dynamics using genomic information collected from over 1000 individual canids, including samples from wolves, coyotes, and dogs. NSF support enabled me to collect additional samples for the Canine Ancestry Project from natural history museums throughout the United States and build the dataset necessary to achieve my research objectives. Specific research outcomes included how inbreeding influenced disease susceptibility in wild wolves, identified genes regions that facilitated coyote range expansion eastward, and assessed hybridization among coyote and wolves in the northeastern USA. For instance, we examined relationships between the presence of diseases and genes important for immune response in endangered red wolves. We found few differences between the susceptibility of endangered red wolves and coyotes to disease, even though red wolves had less immune gene variation due to inbreeding. These results have significant conservation value given we demonstrated that rapid population collapse in red wolves reduced immune gene variation but did not affect disease susceptibly. Despite this, decreased genetic variation in red wolves raises the likelihood of their inability to rapidly adapt to future environmental change and new diseases. We also found that gene regions associated with dispersal and spatial learning were under selection in eastern coyote populations and were likely important in coyotes&rsquo; successful and rapid eastward expansion. Our results broadly benefit society in several ways. First, coyotes are often viewed as pests and factors influencing their basic biology, such as population structure and adaption, are of general importance to the public. Second, assessing disease in wild canids is especially important to a wide section of society because wild canids and domestic dogs interact and share diseases, putting both pets and native wildlife health at risk. We communicated results of the Canine Ancestry project to the public in several ways, such as participating in community science outreach events, having a booth at coyote hunting events, and presenting at scientific meetings and discussion nights at local social clubs. My NSF fellowship supported several important training objectives, including advanced genomic and bioinformatics experience, increased capacity to effectively communicate science, and the development of strong mentorship skills.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 04/01/2018<br>      Modified by: Kristin&nbsp;E&nbsp;Brzeski</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Images (<span id="selectedPhoto0">1</span> of <span class="totalNumber"></span>)           </div> <div class="galControls" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1523859/1523859_10392832_1522538718527_ancestry_screenshot--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1523859/1523859_10392832_1522538718527_ancestry_screenshot--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Canine Ancestry Project homepage"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1523859/1523859_10392832_1522538718527_ancestry_screenshot--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Canine Ancestry Project homepage"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">As a NSF postdoctoral fellow, Kristin Brzeski was a leading researcher for Bridgett vonHoldt's Canine Ancestry project at Princeton University. Outreach through social media and public presentation are a continuous part of the project.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Bridgett vonHoldt</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Kristin&nbsp;E&nbsp;Brzeski</div> <div class="imageTitle">Canine Ancestry Project homepage</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1523859/1523859_10392832_1522537797296_marchforscience--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1523859/1523859_10392832_1522537797296_marchforscience--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Teaching youth about canid evolution."><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1523859/1523859_10392832_1522537797296_marchforscience--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Teaching youth about canid evolution."></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">NSF postdoctoral fellow, Kristin Brzeski, teaching youth about coyote and wolf ecology and evolution at a science outreach event in Princeton, NJ.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Bridgett vonHoldt</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Kristin&nbsp;E&nbsp;Brzeski</div> <div class="imageTitle">Teaching youth about canid evolution.</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1523859/1523859_10392832_1522539053839_coyote_hunt1--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1523859/1523859_10392832_1522539053839_coyote_hunt1--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Outreach to hunting community"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1523859/1523859_10392832_1522539053839_coyote_hunt1--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Outreach to hunting community"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Postdoctoral fellow, Kristin Brzeski, participated in outreach and sample collection at a coyote hunting event in Pennsylvania. Kristin and collaborators were able to discuss management concerns and research objectives with the hunting community.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Kristin Brzeski</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Kristin&nbsp;E&nbsp;Brzeski</div> <div class="imageTitle">Outreach to hunting community</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ My name is Kristin Brzeski, a National Science Foundation (NSF) postdoctoral fellow that worked with Bridgett vonHoldt at Princeton University as a project leader for the Canine Ancestry Project. The Canine Ancestry Project is an on-going endeavor that studies North American canine ecology, demography, and population dynamics using genomic information collected from over 1000 individual canids, including samples from wolves, coyotes, and dogs. NSF support enabled me to collect additional samples for the Canine Ancestry Project from natural history museums throughout the United States and build the dataset necessary to achieve my research objectives. Specific research outcomes included how inbreeding influenced disease susceptibility in wild wolves, identified genes regions that facilitated coyote range expansion eastward, and assessed hybridization among coyote and wolves in the northeastern USA. For instance, we examined relationships between the presence of diseases and genes important for immune response in endangered red wolves. We found few differences between the susceptibility of endangered red wolves and coyotes to disease, even though red wolves had less immune gene variation due to inbreeding. These results have significant conservation value given we demonstrated that rapid population collapse in red wolves reduced immune gene variation but did not affect disease susceptibly. Despite this, decreased genetic variation in red wolves raises the likelihood of their inability to rapidly adapt to future environmental change and new diseases. We also found that gene regions associated with dispersal and spatial learning were under selection in eastern coyote populations and were likely important in coyotes? successful and rapid eastward expansion. Our results broadly benefit society in several ways. First, coyotes are often viewed as pests and factors influencing their basic biology, such as population structure and adaption, are of general importance to the public. Second, assessing disease in wild canids is especially important to a wide section of society because wild canids and domestic dogs interact and share diseases, putting both pets and native wildlife health at risk. We communicated results of the Canine Ancestry project to the public in several ways, such as participating in community science outreach events, having a booth at coyote hunting events, and presenting at scientific meetings and discussion nights at local social clubs. My NSF fellowship supported several important training objectives, including advanced genomic and bioinformatics experience, increased capacity to effectively communicate science, and the development of strong mentorship skills.          Last Modified: 04/01/2018       Submitted by: Kristin E Brzeski]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
