<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Education and Health Consequences of Parental Migration on Children</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2015</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2020</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>330836.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>330836</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>04050000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>SBE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>SES</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Divn Of Social and Economic Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Joseph Whitmeyer</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>jwhitmey@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927808</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Over 50% of the world population resides in urban areas and migration (both internal and international) continues to be on the rise and increasingly affects more children in the household. By some estimates, between 15 to 30% of children in Africa, Asia, and Latin America live in households with at least one migrant parent. The long-term separation of children from their parents may have long term negative education and health consequences for children.  Education is the engine of modern society and an important resource and investment for today's children to upward career mobility. To enhance our understanding of this critical issue the investigator will study the education and health outcomes of migrant the large population of children left behind in China.   For the past three decades, China has seen the largest internal migration in human history. This massive wave of migration has also resulted in a major vulnerable population, i.e. roughly 61 million of left behind children whose parents went to work in Chinese cities. The researcher will conduct a major data collection on 4th grade left behind children in rural China. The data collection includes 4th grade student transcripts during grades 1-4, homeroom teachers? written evaluations of student education and behavior outcomes, assessment of student mental health, and a household survey of sampled students.  The study also consists of analyses of variety of education outcomes and student mental health.  Using both newly collected data and existing longitudinal data the investigator will examine health and behavior outcomes.  Taking advantage of rich information on migration, the research examines how a variety of migration related variables (duration of migration, remittance, and distance of migration) affect education, health, and behavior outcomes for left behind children.  &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The project builds major data and research infrastructure for the study of left behind children in rural China and allows U.S. based researchers to carry out a variety of research topics related to migration and the well-being of children.  As both internal and international migration continues to increase in the 21st century, a comprehensive understanding of migration and outcomes for children is not only important for China but also holds implications for left behind children (either due to internal migration or international migration of parents) in other countries as well.  The project collects data on 1,000 current 4th grade students (both left behind children and children whose parents did not migrate) in the migrant-sending province of Sichuan province.  These data include: (a) retrospective 4th grade student transcripts from grade 1 to grade 4; (b) Math and Chinese language tests of 4th graders; (c) homeroom teachers? evaluation of education performance and behavior issues of each student, and (d) a survey of student emotional development.  The research team will also conduct a survey of 1,000 student households, collecting data on basic socioeconomic conditions of each household, migration and labor history of parents, and information on parental home visits along with other household level information.  These data will be used to estimate statistical models of education outcomes, behavior outcomes, and emotional development and test a variety of hypotheses linking these outcomes to migration, remittances, school and community contexts, and peer group influences.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>09/09/2015</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>09/09/2015</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.075</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1524282</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Zai</FirstName>
<LastName>Liang</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Zai Liang</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>zliang@albany.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5184424676</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000306793</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/09/2015</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>SUNY at Albany</Name>
<CityName>Albany</CityName>
<ZipCode>122220100</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5184374974</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1400 WASHINGTON AVE MSC 100A</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>20</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NY20</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>152652822</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>RESEARCH FOUNDATION FOR THE STATE UNIVERSITY OF NEW YORK, THE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>020657151</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[SUNY at Albany]]></Name>
<CityName>Albany</CityName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<ZipCode>122220100</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[1400 Washington Ave]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>20</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NY20</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1331</Code>
<Text>Sociology</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0115</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2015~330836</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Globally, more and more children are separated from their parents due to parental migration.&nbsp; China has the largest number of internal migrants in human history which has led to a huge number of children left behind in the countryside.&nbsp; The project aims to examine health, education, and behavioral impact of parental migration on children.&nbsp;&nbsp; The project carried out a major survey of children in migrant-sending areas in rural China. &nbsp;It collected data from students/children, parents/guardians, homeroom teachers along with student transcripts for various years and spatial locations of households.&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>We analyzed the data along many dimensions of interest and reached significant findings.&nbsp; Several negative consequences are linked to parental migration. For example, we found that children whose parents are migrated are more likely to suffer mental health issue as compared to children whose parents are at home. &nbsp;Similarly, left behind children are more likely to be victims of bully.&nbsp; Beyond mental health, left behind children are also more likely to suffer anemia, which has implications for educational attainment and health in the long run. &nbsp;We provide new evidence that left behind status has been stigmatized and become a salient attribute in affecting adolescents&rsquo;&rsquo; friendship networks.&nbsp; Specifically, current left behind status has independent and negative effects on adolescents&rsquo;&rsquo; popularity (in-degree) among their classmates. Moreover, we find that the discrepancy in network size between left behind children and children with non-left behind experience is mostly the result of avoidance encountered among the subgroup of left behind children.&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>Beyond using cross-sectional data, we also examined the long-term consequences of parental migration on children when they grow up.&nbsp;&nbsp; Our findings reveal that being left behind in early stages of life has long-lasting negative consequences on educational attainment, physical and mental health, and behavioral outcomes.&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>The project has broad impact in the field.&nbsp;&nbsp; First, the project has built a major data infrastructure for researchers who study children during process of migration. Second, the project provides a very systematical study that includes a variety of measures, from traditional health and education measures to social networks, bully, and spatial dimension of children&rsquo;s households.&nbsp; Third, it has trained a group of graduate students in international research.&nbsp; Finally, the project has broad implications for the well-being of children for many other developing countries during the process of urbanization in the 21<sup>st</sup> century. &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 11/27/2020<br>      Modified by: Zai&nbsp;Liang</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Globally, more and more children are separated from their parents due to parental migration.  China has the largest number of internal migrants in human history which has led to a huge number of children left behind in the countryside.  The project aims to examine health, education, and behavioral impact of parental migration on children.   The project carried out a major survey of children in migrant-sending areas in rural China.  It collected data from students/children, parents/guardians, homeroom teachers along with student transcripts for various years and spatial locations of households.      We analyzed the data along many dimensions of interest and reached significant findings.  Several negative consequences are linked to parental migration. For example, we found that children whose parents are migrated are more likely to suffer mental health issue as compared to children whose parents are at home.  Similarly, left behind children are more likely to be victims of bully.  Beyond mental health, left behind children are also more likely to suffer anemia, which has implications for educational attainment and health in the long run.  We provide new evidence that left behind status has been stigmatized and become a salient attribute in affecting adolescents’’ friendship networks.  Specifically, current left behind status has independent and negative effects on adolescents’’ popularity (in-degree) among their classmates. Moreover, we find that the discrepancy in network size between left behind children and children with non-left behind experience is mostly the result of avoidance encountered among the subgroup of left behind children.      Beyond using cross-sectional data, we also examined the long-term consequences of parental migration on children when they grow up.   Our findings reveal that being left behind in early stages of life has long-lasting negative consequences on educational attainment, physical and mental health, and behavioral outcomes.      The project has broad impact in the field.   First, the project has built a major data infrastructure for researchers who study children during process of migration. Second, the project provides a very systematical study that includes a variety of measures, from traditional health and education measures to social networks, bully, and spatial dimension of children’s households.  Third, it has trained a group of graduate students in international research.  Finally, the project has broad implications for the well-being of children for many other developing countries during the process of urbanization in the 21st century.              Last Modified: 11/27/2020       Submitted by: Zai Liang]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
