<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Development and Validation of Assessments for Industry-Valued Professional and Technical Learning Outcomes in Engineering Education</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>01/01/2016</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>560208.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>560208</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>11040200</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>EHR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DUE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Undergraduate Education</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Heather Watson</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>To educate engineering graduates of higher value to industry upon graduation, curriculum reform requires effective assessment of knowledge, skills and abilities (KSA) such as project management, performance on multidisciplinary teams, critical thinking, addressing open-ended problems, thinking entrepreneurially, communicating with diverse audiences, taking calculated risks, and evaluating business and technical trade-offs. This project focuses on KSA assessment in senior capstone design courses where students gain technical and professional skills in realistic project experiences. The project team is defining and prioritizing required professional skills; developing, testing, and validating assessments that measure individual student achievement in diverse settings; and disseminating proven assessments through workshops, conference presentations, and focused communication vehicles including the Capstone Design Conference and an Internet-based Capstone Design Hub. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Validated assessment tools will apply to engineering capstone design courses of all disciplines, project types, team configurations, and student backgrounds. Instruments are being developed with input from and testing with diverse student populations, giving specific attention to female and minority populations. Psychometric analysis of the instruments will involve the use of Classical Test Theory (CTT) and Item Response Theory (IRT) psychometric analysis. Specifically, the Classical Test Theory will be used to analyze item properties (item difficulty and discrimination indices) as well as test properties (test reliability and discrimination indices). Results from the CTT analysis will allow the team to verify (a) whether items can collectively function well in testing what they are purported to test; and (b) if not, which items may warrant further inspection. A diverse community of practitioners is contributing to the ongoing refinement and implementation of the assessments in order for them to gain broad adoption, guide curriculum change, and benefit society through better educated engineers entering the global workforce.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/31/2015</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/31/2015</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.076</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1524518</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Lin</FirstName>
<LastName>Ding</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Lin Ding</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>lding@mps.ohio-state.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6146888377</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000505214</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/31/2015</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Peter</FirstName>
<LastName>Rogers</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Peter Rogers</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>rogers.693@osu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6145793462</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000684119</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/31/2015</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Denny</FirstName>
<LastName>Davis</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Denny Davis</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>davis.4878@osu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6142923805</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000685047</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/31/2015</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Ohio State University</Name>
<CityName>Columbus</CityName>
<ZipCode>432101016</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6146888735</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>Office of Sponsored Programs</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[1960 Kenny Road]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Ohio</StateName>
<StateCode>OH</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>OH03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>832127323</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>OHIO STATE UNIVERSITY, THE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>001964634</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Ohio State University]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>OH</StateCode>
<ZipCode>432101168</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Ohio</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>OH03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1536</Code>
<Text>S-STEM-Schlr Sci Tech Eng&amp;Math</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1998</Code>
<Text>IUSE</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8209</Code>
<Text>Improv Undergrad STEM Ed(IUSE)</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9178</Code>
<Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0415</Code>
<Name>NSF Education &amp; Human Resource</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040106</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>13XX</Code>
<Name>H-1B FUND, EHR, NSF</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>045176</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2015~560208</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Project Outcomes</p> <p>Work under NSF project number 1524518, <strong><em>Development and Validation of Assessments for Industry-Valued Professional and Technical Learning Outcomes in Engineering Education</em></strong>, focused on creation and validation of practical assessments for student motivation in capstone engineering design projects. Because motivation is very important to employers (and to engineering capstone design faculty) and yet not commonly assessed in engineering students, the project team created assessments to measure motivation of students in capstone design courses where they do work similar to engineering practice.</p> <p>Two types of assessments were developed: a 20-item motivational attitudes assessment and a 20-item motivational behaviors assessment. These assessments were designed for use at the beginning, mid-point, and end of capstone projects to measure motivation-related thoughts and actions that developed and were potentially affected by the students&rsquo; capstone design experience. Capstone design faculty at seven diverse institutions tested the instruments and provided feedback for refinements of draft instruments in two different years. Annual meetings with these collaborators provided practical guidance for making instruments more suitable for the engineering capstone design environment.</p> <p>The assessment instruments were evaluated in numerous ways throughout the development and testing period. Instruments under development were presented to capstone design faculty at two Capstone Design Conferences in 2016 and 2018. With over 25 faculty participating in a motivation assessment workshop each of these years, the project teams obtained practical feedback on the length of the instruments, their relevance to capstone design courses, their value to instructors and students, reporting desired for students and for faculty, and strategies for best administering assessments in capstone courses. Some of these participants also volunteered to help test the motivation assessment instruments.</p> <p>Instruments were also tested in capstone design courses for several engineering disciplines at the host institution and at institutions of collaborators, including large and small, private and public, all-female and HCBU institutions. Assessment results were analyzed to identify questions (assessment items) that gave the greatest discrimination between highly-motivated and weakly-motivated students. In addition, student responses were analyzed to determine how consistently questions on similar motivational factors yielded similar scores from students, to determine how well the instrument measured that type of motivational factor. Consistency of assessment results showed that the motivation instruments enable users to discriminate between different motivation levels when using composite scores for a class, but not for discriminating between individual students. This suggests that the instruments can help an instructor measure impacts of capstone course or project changes on student motivation. The instruments at this stage of development cannot definitively measure an individual student&rsquo;s motivation.</p> <p>The project team maximized the impacts of their work by engaging faculty from engineering and education disciplines and graduate and undergraduate students as researchers in the work and by engaging diverse students in the testing of the motivation instruments. Students participating in assessments were exposed to the concept of assessing motivation and saw how their motivation affected their own attitudes and behaviors. Faculty using the instruments and analyzing results from the assessments gained understanding about the motivation of their students and had the opportunity to change their capstone project practices to address factors that negatively affected students&rsquo; motivation. The broader capstone design community learned about the importance of motivation and its assessment to better prepare students for the engineering workplace.</p> <p>The project team also presented posters and oral papers and published articles that reported on the development and testing of assessments for motivation in engineering capstone design projects. These dissemination efforts helped the broader engineering education community learn about the value of engaging industry employers of graduates in the definition of outcomes vital to engineering practice. This realization of the important employer stakeholder should help the engineering education community value the input of employers when refining curriculum and in assessing outcomes in their graduates.</p> <p>The project team also benefitted from the project in developing strengthened collaboration among educators at the host institution and across the nation. Their work stimulated discussions that heightened the importance of assessment of outcomes important to students, faculty, and employers but not currently required for accreditation. They also learned the value of rapid analysis and reporting of assessment results to gain maximum benefit. This suggests that broader implementation of the motivation assessments requires automated analysis of assessment results and reporting of results to students and faculty. Other researchers who continue this work are encouraged to automate these processes and use results to improve student learning and motivation that better prepares them for the engineering workplace.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 09/27/2019<br>      Modified by: Peter&nbsp;Rogers</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Project Outcomes  Work under NSF project number 1524518, Development and Validation of Assessments for Industry-Valued Professional and Technical Learning Outcomes in Engineering Education, focused on creation and validation of practical assessments for student motivation in capstone engineering design projects. Because motivation is very important to employers (and to engineering capstone design faculty) and yet not commonly assessed in engineering students, the project team created assessments to measure motivation of students in capstone design courses where they do work similar to engineering practice.  Two types of assessments were developed: a 20-item motivational attitudes assessment and a 20-item motivational behaviors assessment. These assessments were designed for use at the beginning, mid-point, and end of capstone projects to measure motivation-related thoughts and actions that developed and were potentially affected by the students? capstone design experience. Capstone design faculty at seven diverse institutions tested the instruments and provided feedback for refinements of draft instruments in two different years. Annual meetings with these collaborators provided practical guidance for making instruments more suitable for the engineering capstone design environment.  The assessment instruments were evaluated in numerous ways throughout the development and testing period. Instruments under development were presented to capstone design faculty at two Capstone Design Conferences in 2016 and 2018. With over 25 faculty participating in a motivation assessment workshop each of these years, the project teams obtained practical feedback on the length of the instruments, their relevance to capstone design courses, their value to instructors and students, reporting desired for students and for faculty, and strategies for best administering assessments in capstone courses. Some of these participants also volunteered to help test the motivation assessment instruments.  Instruments were also tested in capstone design courses for several engineering disciplines at the host institution and at institutions of collaborators, including large and small, private and public, all-female and HCBU institutions. Assessment results were analyzed to identify questions (assessment items) that gave the greatest discrimination between highly-motivated and weakly-motivated students. In addition, student responses were analyzed to determine how consistently questions on similar motivational factors yielded similar scores from students, to determine how well the instrument measured that type of motivational factor. Consistency of assessment results showed that the motivation instruments enable users to discriminate between different motivation levels when using composite scores for a class, but not for discriminating between individual students. This suggests that the instruments can help an instructor measure impacts of capstone course or project changes on student motivation. The instruments at this stage of development cannot definitively measure an individual student?s motivation.  The project team maximized the impacts of their work by engaging faculty from engineering and education disciplines and graduate and undergraduate students as researchers in the work and by engaging diverse students in the testing of the motivation instruments. Students participating in assessments were exposed to the concept of assessing motivation and saw how their motivation affected their own attitudes and behaviors. Faculty using the instruments and analyzing results from the assessments gained understanding about the motivation of their students and had the opportunity to change their capstone project practices to address factors that negatively affected students? motivation. The broader capstone design community learned about the importance of motivation and its assessment to better prepare students for the engineering workplace.  The project team also presented posters and oral papers and published articles that reported on the development and testing of assessments for motivation in engineering capstone design projects. These dissemination efforts helped the broader engineering education community learn about the value of engaging industry employers of graduates in the definition of outcomes vital to engineering practice. This realization of the important employer stakeholder should help the engineering education community value the input of employers when refining curriculum and in assessing outcomes in their graduates.  The project team also benefitted from the project in developing strengthened collaboration among educators at the host institution and across the nation. Their work stimulated discussions that heightened the importance of assessment of outcomes important to students, faculty, and employers but not currently required for accreditation. They also learned the value of rapid analysis and reporting of assessment results to gain maximum benefit. This suggests that broader implementation of the motivation assessments requires automated analysis of assessment results and reporting of results to students and faculty. Other researchers who continue this work are encouraged to automate these processes and use results to improve student learning and motivation that better prepares them for the engineering workplace.          Last Modified: 09/27/2019       Submitted by: Peter Rogers]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
