<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Petrogenesis of Hawaiian Tholeiites: Constraints from Non-Traditional Stable Isotopes</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2015</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>249780.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>249780</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>06030107</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>GEO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>EAR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Earth Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Sonia Esperanca</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This award will support an early career investigator to study the application of non-traditional stable isotopes, a novel tool, in the fields of high-temperature geochemistry and petrology. The ultimate goal of the project is to better understand the origin of Hawaiian volcanism. The proposed research involves educating and training graduate and undergraduate students in state-of-the-art analytical techniques and their applications to geosciences. The project will also help this early-career scientist build a state-of-the art laboratory that will support the research of a number of researchers and students not only at his own institution but also in other institutions allied to the Nevada System of Higher Education. The analytical geochemistry laboratory overseen by this investigator will serve a broad area of earth and environmental sciences, as well as to serve as regional infrastructure in an EPSCoR state. Finally, the proposed research will leverage previous NSF investments by using samples recovered from previous NSF funded programs, such as Hawaii Scientific Drilling Project.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The Earth's mantle is thought to be composed of olivine-rich peridotite. However, the major element characteristics of some ocean island basalts (OIB), such as some Hawaiian lavas, cannot be produced by partial melting of peridotite. A variety of models have been suggested to explain the SiO2 variation in Hawaiian lavas, including melt-mantle reaction model, dacite magma model, and secondary pyroxenite model. On a global scale, Hawaiian lavas define the high-SiO2 endmember of the OIB compositional-isotopic spectrum. Consequently, understanding the origin of SiO2 variation within Hawaiian lavas is important in understanding the petrogenesis of global OIBs. Lavas from Mauna Kea, Koolau and Kahoolawe define two endmembers of the compositional-isotopic spectrum of Hawaiian lavas. The investigator proposes a detailed and systematic Mg and Fe isotopic study of Mauna Kea and Kahoolawe lavas to resolve this question.  Koolau lavas have been extensively studied for Mg, Fe and Ca isotopic compositions. This effort expands on an ongoing study of the Ca isotopic compositions of these samples. It is suggested that non-traditional stable isotopic studies based on major elements such as Ca, Mg, and Fe may provide clues as to the nature of the compositional and isotopic variations shown in Hawaiian lavas. In the future, such approach can be applied to global OIBs to constrain their petrogenesis.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/15/2015</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/07/2017</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.050</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1524387</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Shichun</FirstName>
<LastName>Huang</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Shichun Huang</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>shichun.huang@unlv.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>7028952635</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000518608</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/15/2015</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Nevada Las Vegas</Name>
<CityName>Las Vegas</CityName>
<ZipCode>891549900</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>7028951357</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>4505 MARYLAND PARKWAY</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[OFFICE OF SPONSORED PROGRAMS]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Nevada</StateName>
<StateCode>NV</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NV01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>098377336</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>BOARD OF REGENTS NEVADA SYSTEM OF HIGHER EDUCATION</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>067808063</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Nevada Las Vegas]]></Name>
<CityName>Las Vegas</CityName>
<StateCode>NV</StateCode>
<ZipCode>891541055</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[4505 S. Maryland PKWY]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Nevada</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NV01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1573</Code>
<Text>Petrology and Geochemistry</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EPSCoR Co-Funding</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0115</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0117</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2015~166751</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2017~83029</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>With the NSF support, the PI has finished three tasks:</p> <ol> </ol> <p>(1) systematic measurements of metal stable isotope compositions (Mg, Ca, Ti, Cr, and Fe) of igneous rocks, with a focus on Hawaiian lavas.</p> <p>(2) constrain the inter-mineral isotope fractionation factors among major rock-forming minerals for Ca, Ti and K using ab initio calculations.</p> <p>(3) geochemical study of Hawaiian lavas.</p> <ol> </ol> <p>The important findings that have been published include:</p> <ol> </ol> <p>(1) Crystal fractionation of basaltic magmas involving only pyroxenes and plagioclase has negligible effect on Ca isotopes. Partial melts of spinel peridotites have Ca isotope compositions similar to their source value. In contrast, garnet tends to have heavier Ca isotope compositions; hence, partial melts with garnet as a residual phase are expected to have lighter Ca isotope compositions.</p> <p>(2) Our ab initio calculations find sizable inter-mineral Ca and K isotope fractionation factors among some major rock-forming minerals, and their isotope fractionation factors are sensitive to the mineral compositions.</p> <p>(3) At Hawaii, Mauna Kea shield stage high-CaO tholeiitic lavas sampled the depleted rejuvenated stage source component by melting it to a larger degree. The isotope signatures of this depleted rejuvenated stage component are different from the Pacific upper mantle; consequently, it is inferred to be a lower mantle component intrinsic to the Hawaiian plume.&nbsp;</p> <p>This support also trained two PhD students and a master student, as well as six undergraduate students, including five female students and two from underrepresented groups. Two undergraduates, both female, entered/will enter into the graduate programs. It allowed the PI to maintain his long-term national and international collaboration with Teng at the University of Washington, Frey at MIT, Jacobsen at Harvard, Saal at the Brown University, Huang and Wu at the University of Science and Technology of China, and Zhang and Zhao at the China Academy of Science. The important results have been presented at AGU fall meetings and Goldschmidt conferences. The PI also used this support to start a new graduate course on metal stable isotope geochemistry at the University of Nevada Las Vegas. Finally, the PI and his students also participated the Las Vegas Science Expo 2018 and 2019 (scifest.vegas) to show his scientific results to general public. This is the largest science festival in Las Vegas, with ~28,000 participants every year.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 07/29/2019<br>      Modified by: Shichun&nbsp;Huang</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ With the NSF support, the PI has finished three tasks:    (1) systematic measurements of metal stable isotope compositions (Mg, Ca, Ti, Cr, and Fe) of igneous rocks, with a focus on Hawaiian lavas.  (2) constrain the inter-mineral isotope fractionation factors among major rock-forming minerals for Ca, Ti and K using ab initio calculations.  (3) geochemical study of Hawaiian lavas.    The important findings that have been published include:    (1) Crystal fractionation of basaltic magmas involving only pyroxenes and plagioclase has negligible effect on Ca isotopes. Partial melts of spinel peridotites have Ca isotope compositions similar to their source value. In contrast, garnet tends to have heavier Ca isotope compositions; hence, partial melts with garnet as a residual phase are expected to have lighter Ca isotope compositions.  (2) Our ab initio calculations find sizable inter-mineral Ca and K isotope fractionation factors among some major rock-forming minerals, and their isotope fractionation factors are sensitive to the mineral compositions.  (3) At Hawaii, Mauna Kea shield stage high-CaO tholeiitic lavas sampled the depleted rejuvenated stage source component by melting it to a larger degree. The isotope signatures of this depleted rejuvenated stage component are different from the Pacific upper mantle; consequently, it is inferred to be a lower mantle component intrinsic to the Hawaiian plume.   This support also trained two PhD students and a master student, as well as six undergraduate students, including five female students and two from underrepresented groups. Two undergraduates, both female, entered/will enter into the graduate programs. It allowed the PI to maintain his long-term national and international collaboration with Teng at the University of Washington, Frey at MIT, Jacobsen at Harvard, Saal at the Brown University, Huang and Wu at the University of Science and Technology of China, and Zhang and Zhao at the China Academy of Science. The important results have been presented at AGU fall meetings and Goldschmidt conferences. The PI also used this support to start a new graduate course on metal stable isotope geochemistry at the University of Nevada Las Vegas. Finally, the PI and his students also participated the Las Vegas Science Expo 2018 and 2019 (scifest.vegas) to show his scientific results to general public. This is the largest science festival in Las Vegas, with ~28,000 participants every year.       Last Modified: 07/29/2019       Submitted by: Shichun Huang]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
