<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Threat Vigilance in Visual Attention Biases Legal Decision Making</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2015</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>399047.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>429047</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>04040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>SBE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>BCS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Behavioral and Cognitive Sci</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Steven J. Breckler</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>sbreckle@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927369</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Society imbues trained police officers with special authority to wield force when necessary against individuals who may be breaking the law. In the course of duty, police may enter high-conflict, possibly life-threatening situations, and yet officers must uphold the constitutional rights of citizens they encounter. It is a pervasive assumption that video footage depicting encounters between police and civilians, or members of any two different groups, will provide objective insight into the events that occur prior to and during altercations. This project, however, will test the hypothesis that mere provision of video evidence might not ensure a unified, impartial, or accurate understanding of the facts in a given case because visual experience may be inherently subjective. The project aims to deepen scientific understanding of what factors guide attention, and how attention guides subsequent information processing and decision-making, particularly in legal contexts.  &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;A preliminary study by the researcher Emily Balcetis, New York University, suggested that video evidence can be divisive. People watched videotaped legal evidence in ways that increased the punitive nature of their punishment decisions when acting as arbiters of justice regarding individuals from social out-groups relative to in-groups. From these findings, the researcher developed her Blinding Justice Model of legal punishment, a model that challenges one basic assumption of the legal system that all "reasonable jurors" see the evidence the same way. The researcher will test this model in four studies that use eye tracking technology to measure where people direct their visual attention when watching video evidence, how attention changes understanding of case facts, and document the consequences of biased jury decision-making. An additional experiment tests whether an attention-based intervention can improve the accuracy of people's understanding of the events depicted in video footage, and reduce bias in punishment decisions. Understanding the potential pitfalls as well as benefits of videotape evidence is crucial in anticipating and solving the potential limitations of video, improving its ability to serve as an objective source of information, and attenuating its role in exaggerating the "us versus them" divide in America.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/14/2015</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/04/2015</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.075</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1525539</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Emily</FirstName>
<LastName>Balcetis</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Emily Balcetis</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>eb107@nyu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2129883998</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000405555</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/14/2015</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>New York University</Name>
<CityName>NEW YORK</CityName>
<ZipCode>100121019</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2129982121</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>70 WASHINGTON SQUARE S</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>10</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NY10</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>041968306</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>NEW YORK UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>041968306</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[New York University]]></Name>
<CityName>New York</CityName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<ZipCode>100122331</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[665 Broadway]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>12</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NY12</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1332</Code>
<Text>Social Psychology</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1332</Code>
<Text>SOCIAL PSYCHOLOGY</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9251</Code>
<Text>REU SUPP-Res Exp for Ugrd Supp</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0115</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2015~429047</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><em>Model</em>&nbsp;of legal-decision-making (see Figure 1 for a conceptual depiction of the model). It integrated social psychology, psychobiology, and vision science to inform understanding of legal punishment decisions made with regard to video evidence among people from different social groups. The&nbsp;<em>Blinding Justice Model</em>&nbsp;aimed to transform thinking by undermining one basic assumption of the legal system?that all ?reasonable jurors? see the evidence the same way. This work found that they do not. I discovered factors that predict biased visual attention that arises outside of awareness, and explored the consequences of nonconscious visual attention patterns on the accuracy of understanding case facts and bias in judgments of culpability and punishment. In so doing, I offered an explanation for the polarization in legal decisions that society sees among people from different social groups and explains why individuals have no awareness of the source of their discrepant beliefs.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>This research identified a unique individual difference in the ways that people allocate visual attention when viewing video evidence. Visual flitting is a manner of disengaging visual attention quickly and frequently fixating on unique locations. Visual staring indexes sustained visual engagement and less frequent fixations on fewer unique locations. People naturally differ in their style of engaging visual attention when viewing video evidence (see Figure 2 for an example of one participants' eye gaze trajectory juxtaposed against a single selected still frame from the video evidence). Moreover, they have no ability to accurately introspect on their natural viewing patterns, and as a result cannot articulate their visual experience as a source of their biased judgments.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>However, and importantly, these differences in visual attention predict bias in interpretations potential jurors reach about the evidence at hand. In particular, this model explained differences in accuracy and interpretation of objective and ambiguous evidence in addition the mental image individuals formed of defendants which could affect the accuracy of eye-witness identification. Moreover, visual attention flittering increased the likelihood participants interpreted the case facts in a manner that incriminated the defendant when he was a member of a social outgroup, which increased the severity of punishment directed at that defendant. These effects generalized across members of varied social groups, including those based on politics, Muslim and Jewish religions, police officers, individuals from racial minority groups (e.g. Black, Hispanic, Asian), and people associated with social stigma (e.g. participating in sex work). &nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>Affiliation with social groups proved to be a major precursor to biased visual attention, understanding of case facts, and punishment. It also identified predictors of affiliation, and found that people living in high crime areas experienced less frequent positive police encounters and more frequent negative police encounters. As a result, those in higher crime areas were more weakly identified with police and formed biased assessments of the culpability of officer's actions leading to more severe punishment decisions rendered against the officer.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>This evidence accumulated in this work converged to suggest that visual attention is an unknown contributor to bias in legal decisions. Evidence also suggested visual attention could be a solution. This research tested the effectiveness of an intervention based on visual attention that changed how individuals oriented eye gaze. The intervention reduced biased punishment decisions even among people who are most prone to bias (e.g. White-identified participants) when evaluating evidence from cross-race altercations.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>In a dynamically visual age, modern legal systems must consider new ways to ensure that justice remains "blind." The ways people watch video evidence fuels antagonism in a nation angered by case decisions where it seems the evidence of what happened lays before the eyes.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>This research provided extensive research training and professional development for underrepresented women, including 1 post-baccalaureate student, 17 Research Experiences for Undergraduate students, and 2 PhD students. Of these students, 18 were racial minorities, and 10 came from institutions that did not provide extensive opportunities for research training. They all received training in the nonconscious eye tracking, psychological instrument development, statistical modeling, manuscript preparation, and public presenting at professional conferences.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>Results from this project were published in multiple professional journals and edited scientific volumes and presented at numerous professional conferences. These results served as the basis for multiple pedagogical lessons in undergraduate and graduate courses at New York University?courses which drew students also from Columbia University, John Jay College of Criminal Justice, and the City University of New York. Moreover, results were disseminated to the public by way of a public presentation at Cooper Hewitt Smithsonian Museum, on the Invisibilia NPR podcast, and through a collaborative art instillation at the Cooper Hewitt.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 12/04/2019<br>      Modified by: Emily&nbsp;Balcetis</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Images (<span id="selectedPhoto0">1</span> of <span class="totalNumber"></span>)           </div> <div class="galControls" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1525539/1525539_10376391_1575514279896_Figure1--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1525539/1525539_10376391_1575514279896_Figure1--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Figure 1"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1525539/1525539_10376391_1575514279896_Figure1--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Figure 1"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Conceptual depiction of the model detailing the effect of social group identification on visual biases, accuracy and bias in information processing, and consequential social judgments.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Emily Balcetis</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Public Domain</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Emily&nbsp;Balcetis</div> <div class="imageTitle">Figure 1</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1525539/1525539_10376391_1575514364271_Figure2--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1525539/1525539_10376391_1575514364271_Figure2--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Figure 2"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1525539/1525539_10376391_1575514364271_Figure2--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Figure 2"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Pattern of visual attention fixations for one example participant, overlaid a still image selected from the video evidence presenting a police officer engaged in an altercation with a civilian.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Emily Balcetis</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Emily&nbsp;Balcetis</div> <div class="imageTitle">Figure 2</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Model of legal-decision-making (see Figure 1 for a conceptual depiction of the model). It integrated social psychology, psychobiology, and vision science to inform understanding of legal punishment decisions made with regard to video evidence among people from different social groups. The Blinding Justice Model aimed to transform thinking by undermining one basic assumption of the legal system?that all ?reasonable jurors? see the evidence the same way. This work found that they do not. I discovered factors that predict biased visual attention that arises outside of awareness, and explored the consequences of nonconscious visual attention patterns on the accuracy of understanding case facts and bias in judgments of culpability and punishment. In so doing, I offered an explanation for the polarization in legal decisions that society sees among people from different social groups and explains why individuals have no awareness of the source of their discrepant beliefs.     This research identified a unique individual difference in the ways that people allocate visual attention when viewing video evidence. Visual flitting is a manner of disengaging visual attention quickly and frequently fixating on unique locations. Visual staring indexes sustained visual engagement and less frequent fixations on fewer unique locations. People naturally differ in their style of engaging visual attention when viewing video evidence (see Figure 2 for an example of one participants' eye gaze trajectory juxtaposed against a single selected still frame from the video evidence). Moreover, they have no ability to accurately introspect on their natural viewing patterns, and as a result cannot articulate their visual experience as a source of their biased judgments.     However, and importantly, these differences in visual attention predict bias in interpretations potential jurors reach about the evidence at hand. In particular, this model explained differences in accuracy and interpretation of objective and ambiguous evidence in addition the mental image individuals formed of defendants which could affect the accuracy of eye-witness identification. Moreover, visual attention flittering increased the likelihood participants interpreted the case facts in a manner that incriminated the defendant when he was a member of a social outgroup, which increased the severity of punishment directed at that defendant. These effects generalized across members of varied social groups, including those based on politics, Muslim and Jewish religions, police officers, individuals from racial minority groups (e.g. Black, Hispanic, Asian), and people associated with social stigma (e.g. participating in sex work).       Affiliation with social groups proved to be a major precursor to biased visual attention, understanding of case facts, and punishment. It also identified predictors of affiliation, and found that people living in high crime areas experienced less frequent positive police encounters and more frequent negative police encounters. As a result, those in higher crime areas were more weakly identified with police and formed biased assessments of the culpability of officer's actions leading to more severe punishment decisions rendered against the officer.     This evidence accumulated in this work converged to suggest that visual attention is an unknown contributor to bias in legal decisions. Evidence also suggested visual attention could be a solution. This research tested the effectiveness of an intervention based on visual attention that changed how individuals oriented eye gaze. The intervention reduced biased punishment decisions even among people who are most prone to bias (e.g. White-identified participants) when evaluating evidence from cross-race altercations.     In a dynamically visual age, modern legal systems must consider new ways to ensure that justice remains "blind." The ways people watch video evidence fuels antagonism in a nation angered by case decisions where it seems the evidence of what happened lays before the eyes.     This research provided extensive research training and professional development for underrepresented women, including 1 post-baccalaureate student, 17 Research Experiences for Undergraduate students, and 2 PhD students. Of these students, 18 were racial minorities, and 10 came from institutions that did not provide extensive opportunities for research training. They all received training in the nonconscious eye tracking, psychological instrument development, statistical modeling, manuscript preparation, and public presenting at professional conferences.     Results from this project were published in multiple professional journals and edited scientific volumes and presented at numerous professional conferences. These results served as the basis for multiple pedagogical lessons in undergraduate and graduate courses at New York University?courses which drew students also from Columbia University, John Jay College of Criminal Justice, and the City University of New York. Moreover, results were disseminated to the public by way of a public presentation at Cooper Hewitt Smithsonian Museum, on the Invisibilia NPR podcast, and through a collaborative art instillation at the Cooper Hewitt.          Last Modified: 12/04/2019       Submitted by: Emily Balcetis]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
