<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Collaborative research: Sea-level responses to sediment erosion and deposition over the past 3 million years</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2015</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>259443.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>259443</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>06030206</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>GEO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>EAR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Earth Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Richard Yuretich</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>ryuretic@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924744</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>A non-technical description of the project, which explains the project's significance and importance&lt;br/&gt;Rising sea level is a concern for coastal communities, regardless of its ultimate cause. This project will more accurately investigate the height of sea level as it was during the mid-Pliocene climatic optimum, approximately three million years ago. This time period is important because atmospheric carbon dioxide had levels of 350 to 450 parts per million and global temperatures were two to three degrees warmer than today. Accordingly, conditions during this episode are analogous to projections of the Earth's future during the next century. Current models of sea level for this time are controversial because of the lack of knowledge about the extent of polar ice that existed. This project will examine three locations where shorelines that formed during the mid-Pliocene climatic optimum are exposed and have wide differences in elevation above present sea level. The main goal is to incorporate the mass of sediment that has subsequently been eroded and redeposited from these uplifted shorelines into numerical models in order to more accurately reconstruct the actual height of sea level during this era and estimate the extent of polar ice. This will provide a tool to better predict the magnitude of future sea-level rise under warming conditions.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;A technical description of the project&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Sea-level changes provide an important constraint on ice volumes and polar ice-sheet stability during periods of relative ice-age warmth, including the mid-Pliocene Climatic Optimum (MPCO), the interglacial periods represented by Marine Isotope Stages 5e and 11 (~120 thousand years  and ~400 thousand years ago, respectively), and the present. In this regard, the MPCO remains a period of significant interest and contention. Climate models of the MPCO often adopt a eustatic sea level of 25 meters higher than the present-day as a boundary condition, but individual published estimates range from 10-40 meters. Any eustatic value above 10 meters implies major collapse of ice sheets at both poles. Model-based corrections of sea-level markers for glacial isostatic adjustment and mantle flow-induced dynamic topography are available, but the most recent application of these models yields residual elevations for sea-level of MPCO age along the U.S. east coast with large and systematic geographic variability. This proposal focuses on improving existing estimates of eustatic sea level and ice volumes during the MPCO by accounting for sediment redistribution along the US east coast and the southern coastal margins of Australia and South Africa. This research is a novel study at the interface between coastal margin processes and paleoclimate.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/17/2015</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/17/2015</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.050</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1525922</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Ken</FirstName>
<LastName>Ferrier</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Ken Ferrier</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>ken.ferrier@wisc.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5108839026</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000671281</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/17/2015</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Georgia Tech Research Corporation</Name>
<CityName>Atlanta</CityName>
<ZipCode>303320420</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>4048944819</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>Office of Sponsored Programs</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Georgia</StateName>
<StateCode>GA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>GA05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>097394084</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>GEORGIA TECH RESEARCH CORPORATION</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>097394084</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Georgia Institute of Technology]]></Name>
<CityName>Atlanta</CityName>
<StateCode>GA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>303320420</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[225 North Avenue]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Georgia</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>GA05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7458</Code>
<Text>Geomorphology &amp; Land-use Dynam</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0115</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2015~259443</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>During this project, we developed a new theoretical and numerical framework for quantifying the effects of sediment compaction on sea-level change, and we used it to address a range of research questions.&nbsp; This represents a significant advance for understanding past sea-level change, since compaction affects the elevation many geological markers of ancient sea level, which are commonly used to infer the history of sea-level change.&nbsp; This provides a means of fully accounting for this process in sea-level models for the first time.&nbsp;</p> <p>Several studies were published with the support from this project.&nbsp; Our first study showed how to incorporate these effects into the leading theory for sea-level change and quantified how significant these effects are on a global scale.&nbsp; These concepts were then put to use in two additional studies that showed how these effects can affect our understanding of past sea-level change along the US Atlantic coast.&nbsp; A fourth study revealed that incorporating compaction is important for understanding the past history of ocean water volume.&nbsp; This study showed that neglecting it could lead to ~30% errors in estimates of ocean water volume (and hence global ice volume) during the Last Interglacial ~120,000 years ago.&nbsp; A fifth study will be published shortly, which will show that the effects of sediment erosion and deposition was likely one of the largest drivers of local sea-level change along the US Atlantic margin since the so-called mid-Pliocene Warm Period about three million years ago, which is the previous time atmospheric carbon dioxide concentrations were as high as they are now.</p> <p>Overall, this research has led to a better understanding of the drivers of sea-level change, which in turn has contributed to our understanding of how ice sheets will respond to climate change.&nbsp; As a result, the central outcome of this project is an improved ability to project sea-level change and its associated hazards over the next century.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 03/01/2019<br>      Modified by: Ken&nbsp;Ferrier</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ During this project, we developed a new theoretical and numerical framework for quantifying the effects of sediment compaction on sea-level change, and we used it to address a range of research questions.  This represents a significant advance for understanding past sea-level change, since compaction affects the elevation many geological markers of ancient sea level, which are commonly used to infer the history of sea-level change.  This provides a means of fully accounting for this process in sea-level models for the first time.   Several studies were published with the support from this project.  Our first study showed how to incorporate these effects into the leading theory for sea-level change and quantified how significant these effects are on a global scale.  These concepts were then put to use in two additional studies that showed how these effects can affect our understanding of past sea-level change along the US Atlantic coast.  A fourth study revealed that incorporating compaction is important for understanding the past history of ocean water volume.  This study showed that neglecting it could lead to ~30% errors in estimates of ocean water volume (and hence global ice volume) during the Last Interglacial ~120,000 years ago.  A fifth study will be published shortly, which will show that the effects of sediment erosion and deposition was likely one of the largest drivers of local sea-level change along the US Atlantic margin since the so-called mid-Pliocene Warm Period about three million years ago, which is the previous time atmospheric carbon dioxide concentrations were as high as they are now.  Overall, this research has led to a better understanding of the drivers of sea-level change, which in turn has contributed to our understanding of how ice sheets will respond to climate change.  As a result, the central outcome of this project is an improved ability to project sea-level change and its associated hazards over the next century.       Last Modified: 03/01/2019       Submitted by: Ken Ferrier]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
