<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>First-Year Students as Scholars</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/15/2015</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>593251.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>593251</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>11040200</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>EHR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DUE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Undergraduate Education</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Ellen Carpenter</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>elcarpen@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032925104</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Pepperdine University has received an NSF Improving Undergraduate STEM Education: Education and Human Resources Design and Development tier award to integrate high impact teaching practices that have been demonstrated to promote student success into a set of first-year seminars.  In collaboration with colleagues at Whittier College, an Hispanic Serving Institution, the PI team proposes to integrate authentic scholarly research in biology into conventional first-year seminars, thereby invigorating and transforming introductory coursework into a First-Year Students as Scholars Program (SAS-Program). Through this novel approach, biology majors will be engaged in authentic research during their first college term.  At Pepperdine, a subset of those students will apply for and receive an apprenticeship in an active research laboratory.  This will prepare those students for total immersion in research the following summer, after which they will serve as student mentors to the next cohort of first-year biology majors.  &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Both engagement in undergraduate research and participation in first-year seminars have been identified as high impact practices and established as one of the most effective approaches to improving the retention and performance of underrepresented or at-risk populations of STEM students. Thus, the program will benefit all students involved, including first-generation, low-income students and those belonging to underrepresented groups. The first-year seminars will welcome students into a scholarly identity group, engaged in authentic research that applies the scientific method to real world problems. This experience not only will serve to orient high school graduates to successful college life, reducing anxiety during a pivotal transition, but also will invigorate the basic principles being learned in concurrent introductory courses, such as chemistry, biology, statistics, and physics. The project will use a mixed-methods approach both to investigate how well students learned and to elicit student perspectives of the course design and implementation and how these perspectives change over time. In addition faculty-mentors will assess learning objectives of the first-year seminars using an Erbes' survey instrument (Erbes 2008; Carr et al. 2013). This will allow longitudinal comparisons with previous outcomes and focus on skills required to implement the scientific method in "co-creating knowledge with faculty" (Chopp 2014). Examples of student behaviors to be observed include the ability to: complete a primary literature review, identify gaps in knowledge, design appropriate experiments to test hypotheses, employ appropriate statistical methods, solve unanticipated problems, interpret empirical results, etc. The results of the project's evaluation will enhance the general knowledge within the undergraduate STEM education enterprise of the most effective practices for the integration of authentic research in a first-year seminar.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project is funded jointly by the Directorate for Biological Sciences, Division of Biological Infrastructure and the Directorate for Education and Human Resources, Division of Undergraduate Education in support of efforts to address the challenges posed in Vision and Change in Undergraduate Education: A Call to Action http://visionandchange.org/finalreport/.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/25/2015</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/25/2015</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.076</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1525878</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Stephen</FirstName>
<LastName>Davis</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>D</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Stephen D Davis</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>stephen.davis@pepperdine.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>3105064324</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000463472</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/25/2015</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Pepperdine University</Name>
<CityName>Malibu</CityName>
<ZipCode>902634819</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>3105064819</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>24255 Pacific Coast Hwy</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>33</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CA33</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>072280175</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>PEPPERDINE UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>072280175</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[PEPPERDINE UNIVERSITY]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>902634819</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>33</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CA33</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1664</Code>
<Text>Research Coordination Networks</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1998</Code>
<Text>IUSE</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8209</Code>
<Text>Improv Undergrad STEM Ed(IUSE)</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8238</Code>
<Text>DCLS-Hispanic Serving Inst</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9178</Code>
<Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>SMET</Code>
<Text>SCIENCE, MATH, ENG &amp; TECH EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0115</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0415</Code>
<Name>NSF Education &amp; Human Resource</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040106</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2015~593251</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Overall, we have been very pleased with the assessment outcome of our SAS Program.&nbsp; The program appears to be effective in realizing most of its original goals. &nbsp;We have been especially pleased that SAS seminar courses significantly influenced students to retain their STEM majors; generated a desire in students to pursue additional research experiences; gave students enough confidence to present their work at both regional and national conferences; broadened their perspectives on career paths in STEM; improved students? research abilities; complemented other concurrent courses taken by students; enhanced students? ability to read and understand the primary literature; and prepared students to communicate their original research findings among specialists as well as a general audience. We have greatly benefited from the partnership between faculty and peer mentors at Pepperdine University and Whittier College.&nbsp; Annual assessment meetings and workshops on improving the SAS Program were extremely valuable through the sharing of faculty, peer mentor, and institutional knowledge of effective pedagogy.&nbsp; Also, the annual attendance of faculty, peer mentors, and first-year students at a regional undergraduate research conference (SCCUR) was illuminating, rewarding, and rejuvenating. Students blossomed and thrived especially as first-year students saw their peer mentors present scholarly findings in the setting of a cross-disciplinary conference. &nbsp;WestEd assessment reports based on focus groups and student surveys were especially valuable in analyzing strengths and weaknesses of the SAS Program and formulating adjustments in strategic areas of pedagogy. The entire culture among biology majors at Pepperdine has improved as evidenced by increased retention in the major, oversubscribed enrollment in upper division classes with significant waitlists, accelerated completions of honors theses by the end of a student?s junior year, and enhanced student applications for Fulbright, DOD, and NSF GRFP awards.&nbsp; Many of our biology majors are now presenting papers at national conferences in their sophomore year and a few are attending national conferences at the end of their freshman year.&nbsp; Peer mentors in first-year seminars have especially blossomed and contributed significantly to a community of learners, who excitedly volunteer their time to help first-year students.&nbsp; Alumni of our SAS-Program inform new cadres of freshman students about their personal engagement in scholarly research, presentations at scientific conferences, and submission of proposals for Fulbright and NSF awards.&nbsp; First-year students reciprocate by critiquing upper classman presentations in preparation for upcoming scientific conferences. &nbsp;Typically, a new class of first-year seminar students will be joined by a good number of alumni of the SAS-Program on service projects, such as Step Forward Days (Fig. 1). Also, many alumni of the SAS-Program comprise the audience for the final poster session by first-year students, with over 120 in attendance (Fig. 2).</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 08/16/2019<br>      Modified by: Stephen&nbsp;D&nbsp;Davis</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Images (<span id="selectedPhoto0">1</span> of <span class="totalNumber"></span>)           </div> <div class="galControls" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1525878/1525878_10380287_1565979179568_SASFigure2--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1525878/1525878_10380287_1565979179568_SASFigure2--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Final Poster Session"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1525878/1525878_10380287_1565979179568_SASFigure2--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Final Poster Session"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">First-year Seminar students presenting their final projects at a poster session.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Dr. Stephen Davis</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Public Domain</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Stephen&nbsp;D&nbsp;Davis</div> <div class="imageTitle">Final Poster Session</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1525878/1525878_10380287_1565979346935_SASFigure1--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1525878/1525878_10380287_1565979346935_SASFigure1--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Step Forward Day"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1525878/1525878_10380287_1565979346935_SASFigure1--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Step Forward Day"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">First-year Seminar students participating in Pepperdine's annual day of service.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Dr. Stephen Davis</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Public Domain</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Stephen&nbsp;D&nbsp;Davis</div> <div class="imageTitle">Step Forward Day</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Overall, we have been very pleased with the assessment outcome of our SAS Program.  The program appears to be effective in realizing most of its original goals.  We have been especially pleased that SAS seminar courses significantly influenced students to retain their STEM majors; generated a desire in students to pursue additional research experiences; gave students enough confidence to present their work at both regional and national conferences; broadened their perspectives on career paths in STEM; improved students? research abilities; complemented other concurrent courses taken by students; enhanced students? ability to read and understand the primary literature; and prepared students to communicate their original research findings among specialists as well as a general audience. We have greatly benefited from the partnership between faculty and peer mentors at Pepperdine University and Whittier College.  Annual assessment meetings and workshops on improving the SAS Program were extremely valuable through the sharing of faculty, peer mentor, and institutional knowledge of effective pedagogy.  Also, the annual attendance of faculty, peer mentors, and first-year students at a regional undergraduate research conference (SCCUR) was illuminating, rewarding, and rejuvenating. Students blossomed and thrived especially as first-year students saw their peer mentors present scholarly findings in the setting of a cross-disciplinary conference.  WestEd assessment reports based on focus groups and student surveys were especially valuable in analyzing strengths and weaknesses of the SAS Program and formulating adjustments in strategic areas of pedagogy. The entire culture among biology majors at Pepperdine has improved as evidenced by increased retention in the major, oversubscribed enrollment in upper division classes with significant waitlists, accelerated completions of honors theses by the end of a student?s junior year, and enhanced student applications for Fulbright, DOD, and NSF GRFP awards.  Many of our biology majors are now presenting papers at national conferences in their sophomore year and a few are attending national conferences at the end of their freshman year.  Peer mentors in first-year seminars have especially blossomed and contributed significantly to a community of learners, who excitedly volunteer their time to help first-year students.  Alumni of our SAS-Program inform new cadres of freshman students about their personal engagement in scholarly research, presentations at scientific conferences, and submission of proposals for Fulbright and NSF awards.  First-year students reciprocate by critiquing upper classman presentations in preparation for upcoming scientific conferences.  Typically, a new class of first-year seminar students will be joined by a good number of alumni of the SAS-Program on service projects, such as Step Forward Days (Fig. 1). Also, many alumni of the SAS-Program comprise the audience for the final poster session by first-year students, with over 120 in attendance (Fig. 2).       Last Modified: 08/16/2019       Submitted by: Stephen D Davis]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
