<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>TWC: Small: Communication under Adversarial Attacks in Complex Networks - Fundamental Limits and Secure Coding Strategies</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2015</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2020</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>338193.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>338193</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>05050000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>CSE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CNS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Computer and Network Systems</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Phillip Regalia</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>pregalia@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922981</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Today's world is highly dependent on the integrity of communication systems as the Internet, WiFi, or cellular networks. As networks become more pervasive, they are increasingly being used for communication and storage of critical as well as sensitive data and therefore impose more stringent demands on reliability and security, which must be maintained even under extreme settings such as partial power failures, natural disasters, or, most importantly, adversarial attacks. This research seeks to understand fundamental limits of protecting complex practical networks against adversarial attacks, and how these limits can be achieved by optimal secure strategies, thus bridging the gap between advanced theoretical research and the development of realistic solutions. Further, the project is able to provide a significant transformative impact on many other critical applications employing reliable networked communications, for example in the fields of healthcare, environmental monitoring, finance, etc. It also provides a platform for creating broader technological, societal, research, and educational impact as advancing information technology and its benefits to society through newly established theory and practice, an ambitious education plan, and actively engaging students from underrepresented demographics.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Specifically, the project focuses on aspects (e.g., distributed users, heterogeneity, delay requirements, actions of adversaries described by probability distributions) important in real network systems but poorly understood in current literature, and seeks to elucidate the impact of each such aspect on capacity and code design. This research aims both to characterize features of the problems and solutions (e.g., hardness of computing the rate of communication under adversarial attacks, interaction between redundancy in different network flows, and non-uniform adversarial sets) that are new to the literature, as well as to identify commonalities between the solutions required in each new scenario. These commonalities are then applied to characterize the fundamental tradeoff between security and performance in general adversarial networks. The technique employed here is via reductions, which demonstrate the relationship between two problems by showing that any solution for one can be employed to build a solution for the other. In particular, reductions are derived between noisy networks with a state chosen by the adversary and their corresponding noiseless and stateless versions, for which capacity is much easier to characterize. Further, these results lead to analytical performance guarantees for the designed secure coding strategies, thus providing guidance on specific design approaches and for those cases where capacity bounds are still open.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/17/2015</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>03/20/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.070</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1526547</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Joerg</FirstName>
<LastName>Kliewer</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Joerg Kliewer</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>jkliewer@njit.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>9735963512</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000501242</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/17/2015</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>New Jersey Institute of Technology</Name>
<CityName>Newark</CityName>
<ZipCode>071021982</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>9735965275</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>University Heights</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New Jersey</StateName>
<StateCode>NJ</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>10</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NJ10</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>075162990</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>NEW JERSEY INSTITUTE OF TECHNOLOGY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>075162990</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[New Jersey Institute of Technology]]></Name>
<CityName>Newark</CityName>
<StateCode>NJ</StateCode>
<ZipCode>071021982</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New Jersey</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>10</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NJ10</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7797</Code>
<Text>Comm &amp; Information Foundations</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>8060</Code>
<Text>Secure &amp;Trustworthy Cyberspace</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7434</Code>
<Text>CNCI</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7923</Code>
<Text>SMALL PROJECT</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7935</Code>
<Text>COMM &amp; INFORMATION THEORY</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0115</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2015~338193</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>This project has contributed to improving the trade-off between security and performance in adversarial networks. Specifically, the project has focused on networks characterized by a distributed cloud operation, i.e., a single server or user node and several honest, but curious, potentially colluding workers in the cloud. The workers are employed to compute a function in a distributed way, offloaded to the cloud, where in particular distributed matrix multiplication and polynomial computation are considered as operations. Such computations occur in many signal processing and machine learning applications with practical sized data sets. In such a setting, performance is typically characterized by the required rate to upload and download data to the workers, and security requires that the data at the workers should be kept secure from eavesdropping and adversarial actions.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>One of the main results of the project with respect to secure matrix multiplication is the introduction of a novel class of secure codes, referred to as secure generalized PolyDot codes, that generalizes previously published non-secure versions of these codes for matrix multiplication. These code constructions extend the state-of-the-art by allowing a flexible trade-off between recovery threshold and upload/download rate to and from the workers for a fixed maximum number of colluding workers. We have characterized this tradeoff in the project and proposed constructions for two important scenarios: (i) Both data matrices are conveyed to the workers in the cloud. (ii) One of the data matrices is taken from a public set known to all the workers.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>The second major result of this project addresses a distributed storage system with a large number of storage nodes, each node representing a single database. A single user queries a function computation over data stored in these databases in such a way that the specific function is kept private from each database. The goal is to design a query scheme which minimizes the download rate while ensuring privacy. The project has studied both the case of linear and general polynomial computation over coded databases, which are able to provide efficient data storage while providing enough redundancy to repair a corrupted database. For linear computation we have fully characterized the capacity of that scheme, i.e., the achievable download rate and the corresponding converse result. For polynomial computation, we have constructed two novel achievable schemes based on Reed-Solomon coded databases with Lagrange encoding. Both schemes yield improved rates compared to the best known schemes from the literature.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>The third major result focuses on the classical private information retrieval problem, a special case of the above function computation problem, where only a single file is queried by the user from a single database.&nbsp; The user is required to reconstruct the requested file with a prescribed distortion. In addition, the identity of the requested file is required to be kept private from the server with a prescribed privacy level. The project has characterized the complete tradeoff between download rate, distortion, and user privacy leakage. To overcome the practical limitation of unknown statistical properties of real-world datasets, we have also proposed a novel deep learning-based data-driven approach leveraging recent advancements in generative adversarial networks, which allows a user to learn efficient schemes (in terms of download rate) from the data itself. The performance of the scheme matches or even exceeds traditional rate-distortion compression methods for which the data statistics is assumed to be known.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>Further, this project helped to provide training and professional development to two female Ph.D. students at the New Jersey Institute of Technology. Hence, the project has enabled exposing students to state-of-the-art research questions. The results of this project have been disseminated via publications in journals and presentations at international conferences within the information theory and coding community.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 03/24/2021<br>      Modified by: Joerg&nbsp;Kliewer</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ This project has contributed to improving the trade-off between security and performance in adversarial networks. Specifically, the project has focused on networks characterized by a distributed cloud operation, i.e., a single server or user node and several honest, but curious, potentially colluding workers in the cloud. The workers are employed to compute a function in a distributed way, offloaded to the cloud, where in particular distributed matrix multiplication and polynomial computation are considered as operations. Such computations occur in many signal processing and machine learning applications with practical sized data sets. In such a setting, performance is typically characterized by the required rate to upload and download data to the workers, and security requires that the data at the workers should be kept secure from eavesdropping and adversarial actions.     One of the main results of the project with respect to secure matrix multiplication is the introduction of a novel class of secure codes, referred to as secure generalized PolyDot codes, that generalizes previously published non-secure versions of these codes for matrix multiplication. These code constructions extend the state-of-the-art by allowing a flexible trade-off between recovery threshold and upload/download rate to and from the workers for a fixed maximum number of colluding workers. We have characterized this tradeoff in the project and proposed constructions for two important scenarios: (i) Both data matrices are conveyed to the workers in the cloud. (ii) One of the data matrices is taken from a public set known to all the workers.     The second major result of this project addresses a distributed storage system with a large number of storage nodes, each node representing a single database. A single user queries a function computation over data stored in these databases in such a way that the specific function is kept private from each database. The goal is to design a query scheme which minimizes the download rate while ensuring privacy. The project has studied both the case of linear and general polynomial computation over coded databases, which are able to provide efficient data storage while providing enough redundancy to repair a corrupted database. For linear computation we have fully characterized the capacity of that scheme, i.e., the achievable download rate and the corresponding converse result. For polynomial computation, we have constructed two novel achievable schemes based on Reed-Solomon coded databases with Lagrange encoding. Both schemes yield improved rates compared to the best known schemes from the literature.     The third major result focuses on the classical private information retrieval problem, a special case of the above function computation problem, where only a single file is queried by the user from a single database.  The user is required to reconstruct the requested file with a prescribed distortion. In addition, the identity of the requested file is required to be kept private from the server with a prescribed privacy level. The project has characterized the complete tradeoff between download rate, distortion, and user privacy leakage. To overcome the practical limitation of unknown statistical properties of real-world datasets, we have also proposed a novel deep learning-based data-driven approach leveraging recent advancements in generative adversarial networks, which allows a user to learn efficient schemes (in terms of download rate) from the data itself. The performance of the scheme matches or even exceeds traditional rate-distortion compression methods for which the data statistics is assumed to be known.     Further, this project helped to provide training and professional development to two female Ph.D. students at the New Jersey Institute of Technology. Hence, the project has enabled exposing students to state-of-the-art research questions. The results of this project have been disseminated via publications in journals and presentations at international conferences within the information theory and coding community.       Last Modified: 03/24/2021       Submitted by: Joerg Kliewer]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
