<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>III: Small: Algorithms for Genome Assembly of Ultra-Deep Sequencing Data</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2015</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>499000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>499000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>05020000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>CSE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>IIS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Information &amp; Intelligent Systems</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Sylvia Spengler</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>sspengle@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032928930</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This project will  investigate the computational challenges that will brought upon by the analysis of ultra-deep sequencing data (i.e., coverage 1000x or higher), specifically in the context of de novo genome assembly. As sequencing cost continues to decrease, ultra-deep sequencing data will become more common, but the problem of de novo genome assembly remains computationally challenging, in particular for large, repetitive genomes.  Since the sequencing of H. influenzae in 1995, the assembly problem has been characterized by limited depth of sequencing coverage mostly due to the high cost of generating the data.  This project will investigate for the first time the opposite problem, that is, the challenge of dealing with excessive depth of sequencing.  Deliverables will include novel software tools for genome assembly which will benefit researchers and the public worldwide, and potentially lead to new international and industrial collaborations. This project will directly support two graduate students in a highly interdisciplinary environment, building on UCR's strengths in Computer Science and Agricultural Sciences. Undergraduates will have opportunities to participate in research through a Research Experiences for Undergraduates (REU) site at UCR, a collaboration with a nearby community college, and a new US Department of Education Title V Hispanic Serving Institution grant (UCR is an accredited HSI).&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The research plan is aimed at de novo assembly problem under the assumption that the input sequencing data is ultra-deep. The study will demonstrate that when the depth of sequencing increases over a certain threshold, sequencing errors make the genome assembly problem harder and harder, and as a consequence the quality of the solution degrades with more and more data. The project will show that modern de novo assemblers like SPAdes, IDBA-ud, and Velvet are unable take advantage of ultra-deep sequencing data. The research plan will deal with ultra-deep sequencing data using a divide-and-conquer approach. In this proposed meta-assembler, the input data will be partitioned into optimal-sized "slices" and a standard assembly tool (e.g., Velvet, SPAdes, IDBA, Ray) will be used to assemble each slice individually. For the de novo assembler, a set of de Bruijn graphs will be created, each one built form the sequencing data of a slice.  In both cases, a majority voting strategy among the individual assemblies/graphs will be used to generate a high-quality consensus assembly.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Updates and additional information about this project will be made available at http://www.cs.ucr.edu/~stelo/iis15.htm</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/11/2015</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/11/2015</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.070</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1526742</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Stefano</FirstName>
<LastName>Lonardi</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Stefano Lonardi</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>stelo@cs.ucr.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>9518272203</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000286925</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/11/2015</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of California-Riverside</Name>
<CityName>RIVERSIDE</CityName>
<ZipCode>925210217</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>9518275535</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>Research &amp; Economic Development</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[245 University Office Building]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>44</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CA44</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>627797426</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>REGENTS OF THE UNIVERSITY OF CALIFORNIA AT RIVERSIDE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>071549000</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of California-Riverside]]></Name>
<CityName>Riverside</CityName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>925210001</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[900 University Ave]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>41</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CA41</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7364</Code>
<Text>Info Integration &amp; Informatics</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7364</Code>
<Text>INFO INTEGRATION &amp; INFORMATICS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7923</Code>
<Text>SMALL PROJECT</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0115</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2015~499000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Of the estimated ten million eukaryotic species on our planet, less than two thousand had their genome sequenced and assembled. While DNA sequencing cost continues to decrease exponentially fast, the problem of de novo genome assembly is still computationally challenging, in particular for large, repetitive genomes.&nbsp; In this project, we investigated for the first time the computational and analytical challenge of dealing with very large amount of DNA sequencing data when dealing with the assembly of eukaryotic genomes.<br /><br />The algorithmic methods and innovations developed for this research project were used to create the first drafts of the genomes of barley and cowpea.&nbsp; Barley is among the world's earliest domesticated and most important crop plants (ranked fourth among grains in quantity produced behind maize, rice and wheat). Cowpea (black-eyed pea) is a major crop for worldwide food and nutritional security, especially in sub-Saharan Africa, that is resilient to hot and drought-prone environments.<br /><br />All the methods and the genomic resources produced in the context of this project were widely disseminated through peer-reviewed publications, oral presentations at professional symposia, and distribution of open-source software and data sets.<br /><br />Five graduate students were partially supported by this grant and were trainined as computational biologists. Three students graduated during the grant period. The first one became the CTO of a start-up company in NY which focuses on metagenomics analysis in clinical settings. The second obtained a position as a bioinformatician in a leading biotech company in the Bay Area. The third one won the prestiguous Lane Fellowship to be post-doc at Carnegie Mellon University.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 08/09/2019<br>      Modified by: Stefano&nbsp;Lonardi</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Of the estimated ten million eukaryotic species on our planet, less than two thousand had their genome sequenced and assembled. While DNA sequencing cost continues to decrease exponentially fast, the problem of de novo genome assembly is still computationally challenging, in particular for large, repetitive genomes.  In this project, we investigated for the first time the computational and analytical challenge of dealing with very large amount of DNA sequencing data when dealing with the assembly of eukaryotic genomes.  The algorithmic methods and innovations developed for this research project were used to create the first drafts of the genomes of barley and cowpea.  Barley is among the world's earliest domesticated and most important crop plants (ranked fourth among grains in quantity produced behind maize, rice and wheat). Cowpea (black-eyed pea) is a major crop for worldwide food and nutritional security, especially in sub-Saharan Africa, that is resilient to hot and drought-prone environments.  All the methods and the genomic resources produced in the context of this project were widely disseminated through peer-reviewed publications, oral presentations at professional symposia, and distribution of open-source software and data sets.  Five graduate students were partially supported by this grant and were trainined as computational biologists. Three students graduated during the grant period. The first one became the CTO of a start-up company in NY which focuses on metagenomics analysis in clinical settings. The second obtained a position as a bioinformatician in a leading biotech company in the Bay Area. The third one won the prestiguous Lane Fellowship to be post-doc at Carnegie Mellon University.       Last Modified: 08/09/2019       Submitted by: Stefano Lonardi]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
