<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>SHF: Small: An Asynchronous Network-on-Chip Methodology for Cost-Effective and Fault-Tolerant Heterogeneous SoC Architectures</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2015</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>420000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>420000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>05010000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>CSE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CCF</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division of Computing and Communication Foundations</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Sankar Basu</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>sabasu@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927843</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>One of the grand challenges of the next decade is to provide cost-effective and systematic approaches to build large-scale computing systems to meet the country's future technological needs.  Such systems will involve 100s or 1000s of processors, or more, on a single computer chip, which perform massively parallel computation tasks, and can be housed in either large data centers or even in desktop or hand-held consumer products.  Such parallel computing is the key to supporting the continued growth of social networks (texting, Facebook) and rapid Web queries, as well as solving massive scientific computation problems, such as for weather, oceanography, air traffic control, military, and security.  However, there are currently severe cost overheads in designing such systems:  huge energy usage, thermal overheating, poor delivered performance, and complexity in assembling such complex and varied components into a single chip.  Many of these bottlenecks have been exacerbated by the traditional use of a fixed-rate clock, which centrally controls all components on a chip.  The goal of this research is to explore and significantly advance one highly promising alternative solution:  to build ?plug-and-play? easy-to-assemble computer systems without any global clock, but instead through asynchronous (i.e. clock-less) assembly.  Such a solution promises much lower energy consumption, and ease of assembly, of such systems. The project will also train students in asynchronous circuit design and the general area of information and computing technologies.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The particular focus of this research is to develop structured digital interconnection networks for a chip, called "networks-on-chip", which form the "backbone" of recent commercial parallel computer systems.  While initial solutions with asynchronous design have been promising, they have lacked fundamental features needed to make them viable for industry.  In this proposal, several key features are developed for asynchronous networks-on-chip:  error detection and correction, performance enhancement, and automated design flow.   The approach will also be applied to a realistic cell phone application, to demonstrate the ease-of-design and cost benefits.  Taken together, this new approach promises a significant advance forward in providing the capability to assemble complex parallel computer systems needed in the future.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/21/2015</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/21/2015</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.070</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1527796</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Steven</FirstName>
<LastName>Nowick</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>M</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Steven M Nowick</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>nowick@cs.columbia.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2129397000</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000164955</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/21/2015</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Columbia University</Name>
<CityName>NEW YORK</CityName>
<ZipCode>100276902</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2128546851</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>2960 Broadway</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>10</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NY10</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>049179401</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>TRUSTEES OF COLUMBIA UNIVERSITY IN THE CITY OF NEW YORK, THE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>049179401</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Columbia University]]></Name>
<CityName>New York</CityName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<ZipCode>100276902</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[2960 Broadway]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>10</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NY10</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7798</Code>
<Text>Software &amp; Hardware Foundation</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7923</Code>
<Text>SMALL PROJECT</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7944</Code>
<Text>SOFTWARE ENG &amp; FORMAL METHODS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0115</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2015~420000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><div class="page" title="Page 1"> <div class="section"> <div class="layoutArea"> <div class="column"> <p><span>One of the key research challenges of the next decade, and beyond, is the cost-effective design of large-scale computing systems.&nbsp; The computing infrastructure is the foundation of a huge range of critical applications -- for society, the military, commerce and science -- ranging from data centers to handle web search, applications to finance, weather and climate forecasting, astrophysics, vision systems, social media, and gaming.&nbsp; These systems range from hundreds to millions of processors and storage units (memory, caches), all of which are interconnected and must be able to interact easily with each other, to support complex operations, with low energy, high performance and high reliability.</span></p> <p><span>A critical issue has been the "communication bottleneck:"&nbsp; how to assemble and easily integrate diverse components into a working and efficient parallel system? A promising direction has been the use of structured on-chip communication, using "networks-on-chip" (NoCs). These communication networks have been employed both in the consumer electronics domain for systems-on-chip, and for high-end parallel processors.&nbsp; They borrow inspiration from large-scale networks (Ethernet, LANs, etc.), but with wholly different design requirements and scale, to allow flexible and low-cost communication between large numbers of processors and memories within a single chip, and similar approaches are used to connect multiple chips into a larger computing system.</span></p> <div class="page" title="Page 1"> <div class="section"> <div class="layoutArea"> <div class="column"> <p><span style="text-decoration: underline;">The main outcome of the proposed research is to significantly advance the state-of-art of NoC design, through use of clockless (i.e. asynchronous) digital design</span><span><span style="text-decoration: underline;">.</span>&nbsp;&nbsp;Both fully-asynchronous systems, as well as hybrid globally-asynchronous locally-synchronous (GALS) systems using synchronous components connected by an asynchronous network, can be supported, to enable the construction of complex systems in a cost-effective and highly-reliable manner.&nbsp; While traditional systems are built using synchronous design, where a fixed-rate clock controls the operation of all components (or more recently, allowing varying rate clocks), synchronous designs are exhibiting poor ability to scale to organizing large-scale systems, which are built out of diverse components operating at different rates, and where the clock burns power continually -- even where not needed.&nbsp;&nbsp;</span></p> <p>This research advances the state of the art of asynchronous design, for application to large-scale interconnection networks, allowing extremely efficient organization, design and communication.&nbsp; The aim is to achieve much improved costs:&nbsp; lower energy, higher performance, smaller area "footprint", and greater ease of assembly.</p> <p>To this end, the project's outcome includes several major contributions:</p> <p><strong>(i) develop a low-cost and efficient asynchronous switch design, </strong>to be used as a building block in designing asynchronous on-chip networks.&nbsp; The switch is constructed almost entirely of standard hardware components (i.e. gates), with only a few specialized components needed.&nbsp; &nbsp;Capabilities have been developed to enable higher efficiency and wider usability, including:&nbsp; support for multi-way communication (i.e. multicast), new fair and high-speed arbitration units, and improved protocols for avoiding congestion (i.e. "virtual channel" support).</p> <p><strong>(ii) experimental switch and network evaluation:&nbsp; comparing asynchronous to synchronous.&nbsp;</strong>&nbsp;The asynchronous switch has been carefully compared to a leading efficient synchronous switch, called "xpipes", and demonstrates significant benefits in energy consumption (both active and idle) and performance (latency and throughput) for most scenarios.&nbsp; It also exhibits substantially smaller area "footprint."&nbsp; Experiments at the full network-on-chip level confirm these benefits.</p> <p><strong>(iii) develop two efficient asynchronous computer-aided design (CAD) tool flows, leveraging existing synchronous CAD tools.&nbsp; </strong>The first tool flow targets standard-cell design, aimed at fabricating chips (using Synopsys tools), while the second tool flow targets reconfigurable programmable designs (i.e. for FPGAs, using Xilinx tools).&nbsp; The tool flows, unlike most previous approaches, ensure both reliable designs, as well as highly-optimized designs.&nbsp; The tool flows are shown to have efficient run times.&nbsp; Most importantly, these tools facilitate the widespread development and design of asynchronous chips, both in academia and industry, by automating the design flow.</p> <p><strong>(iv) collaborate with a major computer company (AMD), to migrate the asynchronous switch experimentally into their technology, and compare to a commercial synchronous switch.&nbsp; </strong><span style="text-decoration: underline;">This is the first reported comparison ever made in advanced industrial technology (14nm FinFET) of a recent commercial synchronous switch against an asynchronous switch, and thus provides an "apples-to-apples" evaluation.&nbsp;</span> The asynchronous switch is shown to have significantly lower area, latency and energy, for most scenarios, than AMD's commercial synchronous switch.&nbsp; This contribution has generated significant interest, and is a convincing demonstration of the capability of asynchronous networks-on-chip to compete effectively against leading industrial synchronous designs.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> </div> </div> </div> </div> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> </div> </div> </div> </div><br> <p>            Last Modified: 10/20/2019<br>      Modified by: Steven&nbsp;M&nbsp;Nowick</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Images (<span id="selectedPhoto0">1</span> of <span class="totalNumber"></span>)           </div> <div class="galControls" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1527796/1527796_10378557_1571524698814_fig1--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1527796/1527796_10378557_1571524698814_fig1--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Fig. 1."><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1527796/1527796_10378557_1571524698814_fig1--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Fig. 1."></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Asynchronous Network-on-Chip Switch:  architecture and details</div> <div class="imageCredit">Steven Nowick/Davide Bertozzi</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Public Domain</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Steven&nbsp;M&nbsp;Nowick</div> <div class="imageTitle">Fig. 1.</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1527796/1527796_10378557_1571525035618_fig4--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1527796/1527796_10378557_1571525035618_fig4--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Fig. 4."><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1527796/1527796_10378557_1571525035618_fig4--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Fig. 4."></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Performance and Power Comparison:  Asynchronous vs. Synchronous Networks-on-Chip.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Steven Nowick/Davide Bertozzi</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Public Domain</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Steven&nbsp;M&nbsp;Nowick</div> <div class="imageTitle">Fig. 4.</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1527796/1527796_10378557_1571525227075_fig5--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1527796/1527796_10378557_1571525227075_fig5--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Fig. 5."><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1527796/1527796_10378557_1571525227075_fig5--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Fig. 5."></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Comparison with AMD Commercial Synchronous Switch (14nm FinFET Technology).</div> <div class="imageCredit">Steven Nowick/Davide Bertozzi</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Public Domain</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Steven&nbsp;M&nbsp;Nowick</div> <div class="imageTitle">Fig. 5.</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1527796/1527796_10378557_1571525309241_fig6--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1527796/1527796_10378557_1571525309241_fig6--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Fig. 6."><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1527796/1527796_10378557_1571525309241_fig6--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Fig. 6."></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Chip Layout of Asynchronous Switch (Using AMD's 14nm FinFET Technology).</div> <div class="imageCredit">Steven Nowick/Davide Bertozzi</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Public Domain</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Steven&nbsp;M&nbsp;Nowick</div> <div class="imageTitle">Fig. 6.</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1527796/1527796_10378557_1571525554473_fig2-rev--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1527796/1527796_10378557_1571525554473_fig2-rev--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Fig. 2."><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1527796/1527796_10378557_1571525554473_fig2-rev--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Fig. 2."></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Proposed Computer-Aided Design (CAD) Tool Flow:  for asynchronous networks-on-chip.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Steven Nowick/Davide Bertozzi</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Public Domain</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Steven&nbsp;M&nbsp;Nowick</div> <div class="imageTitle">Fig. 2.</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1527796/1527796_10378557_1571525941010_fig3--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1527796/1527796_10378557_1571525941010_fig3--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Fig. 3."><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1527796/1527796_10378557_1571525941010_fig3--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Fig. 3."></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Performance and Area Comparison: Asynchronous vs. Synchronous Switches.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Steven Nowick/Davide Bertozzi</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Steven&nbsp;M&nbsp;Nowick</div> <div class="imageTitle">Fig. 3.</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[     One of the key research challenges of the next decade, and beyond, is the cost-effective design of large-scale computing systems.  The computing infrastructure is the foundation of a huge range of critical applications -- for society, the military, commerce and science -- ranging from data centers to handle web search, applications to finance, weather and climate forecasting, astrophysics, vision systems, social media, and gaming.  These systems range from hundreds to millions of processors and storage units (memory, caches), all of which are interconnected and must be able to interact easily with each other, to support complex operations, with low energy, high performance and high reliability.  A critical issue has been the "communication bottleneck:"  how to assemble and easily integrate diverse components into a working and efficient parallel system? A promising direction has been the use of structured on-chip communication, using "networks-on-chip" (NoCs). These communication networks have been employed both in the consumer electronics domain for systems-on-chip, and for high-end parallel processors.  They borrow inspiration from large-scale networks (Ethernet, LANs, etc.), but with wholly different design requirements and scale, to allow flexible and low-cost communication between large numbers of processors and memories within a single chip, and similar approaches are used to connect multiple chips into a larger computing system.      The main outcome of the proposed research is to significantly advance the state-of-art of NoC design, through use of clockless (i.e. asynchronous) digital design.  Both fully-asynchronous systems, as well as hybrid globally-asynchronous locally-synchronous (GALS) systems using synchronous components connected by an asynchronous network, can be supported, to enable the construction of complex systems in a cost-effective and highly-reliable manner.  While traditional systems are built using synchronous design, where a fixed-rate clock controls the operation of all components (or more recently, allowing varying rate clocks), synchronous designs are exhibiting poor ability to scale to organizing large-scale systems, which are built out of diverse components operating at different rates, and where the clock burns power continually -- even where not needed.    This research advances the state of the art of asynchronous design, for application to large-scale interconnection networks, allowing extremely efficient organization, design and communication.  The aim is to achieve much improved costs:  lower energy, higher performance, smaller area "footprint", and greater ease of assembly.  To this end, the project's outcome includes several major contributions:  (i) develop a low-cost and efficient asynchronous switch design, to be used as a building block in designing asynchronous on-chip networks.  The switch is constructed almost entirely of standard hardware components (i.e. gates), with only a few specialized components needed.   Capabilities have been developed to enable higher efficiency and wider usability, including:  support for multi-way communication (i.e. multicast), new fair and high-speed arbitration units, and improved protocols for avoiding congestion (i.e. "virtual channel" support).  (ii) experimental switch and network evaluation:  comparing asynchronous to synchronous.  The asynchronous switch has been carefully compared to a leading efficient synchronous switch, called "xpipes", and demonstrates significant benefits in energy consumption (both active and idle) and performance (latency and throughput) for most scenarios.  It also exhibits substantially smaller area "footprint."  Experiments at the full network-on-chip level confirm these benefits.  (iii) develop two efficient asynchronous computer-aided design (CAD) tool flows, leveraging existing synchronous CAD tools.  The first tool flow targets standard-cell design, aimed at fabricating chips (using Synopsys tools), while the second tool flow targets reconfigurable programmable designs (i.e. for FPGAs, using Xilinx tools).  The tool flows, unlike most previous approaches, ensure both reliable designs, as well as highly-optimized designs.  The tool flows are shown to have efficient run times.  Most importantly, these tools facilitate the widespread development and design of asynchronous chips, both in academia and industry, by automating the design flow.  (iv) collaborate with a major computer company (AMD), to migrate the asynchronous switch experimentally into their technology, and compare to a commercial synchronous switch.  This is the first reported comparison ever made in advanced industrial technology (14nm FinFET) of a recent commercial synchronous switch against an asynchronous switch, and thus provides an "apples-to-apples" evaluation.  The asynchronous switch is shown to have significantly lower area, latency and energy, for most scenarios, than AMD's commercial synchronous switch.  This contribution has generated significant interest, and is a convincing demonstration of the capability of asynchronous networks-on-chip to compete effectively against leading industrial synchronous designs.                                 Last Modified: 10/20/2019       Submitted by: Steven M Nowick]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
