<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>NRI: Balance Recovery Control for Amputees Using Powered Leg Prostheses</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2015</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>900000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>908000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CMMI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Civil, Mechanical, &amp; Manufact Inn</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Irina Dolinskaya</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>idolinsk@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927078</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Falls among amputees are frequent, costly and negatively impact quality of life. In 2005, there were one million people in the United States with lower limb amputation. About 10 percent of these people experience at least one fall that results in serious injury, resulting in estimated costs to the United States health care system of about $1.1 billion annually. This number is expected to quadruple by the year 2050 due to increasing rates of obesity and diabetes. People with amputation are conscious of their increased fall risk, leading to reduced mobility and social activity. About half of the amputee population reports a fear of falling. Similarly large numbers list as major limitations to their quality of life the inability to walk on uneven terrain or without a stabilizing gait aid. These facts highlight the challenge imposed by imbalance, and suggest that improving balance recovery in amputee locomotion would significantly improve the quality of life of lower-limb amputees as well as reduce related health care costs. The emerging field of robotic prosthetics provides the opportunity to attack this problem with novel prosthesis designs and control strategies. The project seeks to take advantage of this opportunity. It combines computational models of the human neuromuscular control system with novel designs of powered knee-and-ankle prostheses and biomechanical gait analysis to establish new control paradigms for powered prostheses that substantially improve the ability of amputees to recover from large disturbances. Implemented in commercial devices, these control techniques could reduce fall rates and fear of falling, thereby improving the mobility and quality of life for millions of people. Other benefits of the project include the support of education. Graduate and undergraduate students will be trained and mentored, and research tools and outcomes will be integrated into coursework, including the  software and hardware tools developed in this project for studying prosthesis control and disturbance recovery in human locomotion. In addition, the project supports the dissemination of research results by publishing and freely providing simulation code, control implementation code, and hardware designs online.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The overarching goal of this project is to test the hypothesis that a reflex-like prosthesis control strategy inspired by human motor control substantially improves the balance recovery for above-knee amputees during walking. Balance recovery has evolved into a major research area as fall-connected injuries are one of the main causes of impairment, disability and death in aging societies. Lower limb amputees are especially at risk of falling as current prosthetic limbs provide only limited functionality for recovering from unexpected disturbances. The project combines methods from computational neuromechanics, robotic prosthetics, and biomechanical gait analysis to identify prosthesis control strategies that help above-knee amputees recover balance after large disturbances such as trips, slips and pushes. An existing reflex control model of human locomotion is adapted to amputee gait, involving theoretical research on feedback control algorithms for powered prosthetic limbs and predictions of amputee recovery behavior in simulated experiments. Prototypes of powered knee-ankle prostheses are developed, including a tethered prosthesis emulator for rapid human-in-the-loop control design and evaluation on a treadmill, and a mobile prosthesis allowing evaluation outside the laboratory. Control algorithms identified in the reflex control model are embedded in these prototypes and systematically evaluated in balance recovery experiments with above-knee amputees. An outcome confirming the hypothesis could establish new control paradigms for powered prostheses and enable practical controllers for improved balance recovery in amputee gait. In addition, the project will advance theoretical models of human balance recovery as well as control algorithms and hardware designs for robotic knee-ankle prostheses.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/12/2015</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>04/27/2018</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1527140</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Hartmut</FirstName>
<LastName>Geyer</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Hartmut Geyer</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>hgeyer@cs.cmu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>4122681724</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000567740</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/12/2015</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Steve</FirstName>
<LastName>Collins</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Steve Collins</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>stevecollins@stanford.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6504971917</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000572862</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/12/2015</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Carnegie-Mellon University</Name>
<CityName>PITTSBURGH</CityName>
<ZipCode>152133815</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>4122688746</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>5000 Forbes Avenue</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[WQED Building]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Pennsylvania</StateName>
<StateCode>PA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>18</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>PA18</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>052184116</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>CARNEGIE MELLON UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>052184116</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Carnegie-Mellon University]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>PA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>152133890</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Pennsylvania</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>18</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>PA18</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>8013</Code>
<Text>NRI-National Robotics Initiati</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>116E</Code>
<Text>RESEARCH EXP FOR UNDERGRADS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8086</Code>
<Text>Natl Robotics Initiative (NRI)</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9178</Code>
<Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9231</Code>
<Text>SUPPL FOR UNDERGRAD RES ASSIST</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9251</Code>
<Text>REU SUPP-Res Exp for Ugrd Supp</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0115</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0118</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2015~900000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2018~8000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Fall-related injuries are a main cause of impairment, disability and death in aging societies. Lower limb amputees are especially at risk of falling, as commercial prosthetic legs provide only limited functionality for recovering from unexpected disturbances. The field of rehabilitation robotics provides the opportunity to address these problems with novel robotic systems and control strategies. Within this scope, the project has (a) generated new knowledge about the control and parameter tuning of lower limb prostheses for preventing falls in amputee locomotion, (b) enabled the development of novel robotic systems including powered prostheses and automatic balance disturbers to test new prosthesis control and tuning strategies, and (c) promoted the teaching, training and learning of 15 researchers involved in the project. &nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>(a) With advances in rehabilitation robotics, powered limb prostheses and exoskeletons will become more prevalent in our societies. However, the controllers of these complex wearable robots are difficult to tune, especially in clinical settings, as they involve many control parameters, their human users have different preferences, and human objective functions are hard to define. We identified new algorithms for optimizing complex controllers of lower limb prostheses and exoskeletons based on qualitative preference feedback of the human users. These algorithms may help engineers tune wearable robots more accurately, efficiently and consistently.</p> <p>The tuning algorithms further helped us to objectively compare in human locomotion experiments the capabilities of new and more established prosthesis control strategies to prevent falls in the presence of gait disturbances. The results of these experiments suggest that a human-like reflex control in stance combined with a minimum jerk control in swing improves the capability of robotic prostheses to prevent falls (Figure 1). The finding may help improve the mobility of amputees and may generalize to exoskeleton applications as well.</p> <p>The experiments also highlighted shortcomings of all compared prosthesis control strategies, which inspired new ideas for improving amputee mobility. For instance, within this project, we explored and demonstrated a combination of sensor fusion and machine learning techniques to achieve more robust and adaptive prosthesis control in the presence not only of environment disturbances but also of changes in locomotion behavior desired by the human user.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>(b) The project led to the development of powered leg prototypes whose high torque and speed characteristics were critical to implementing and testing fall recovery strategies (Figure 1).</p> <p>Complementary to this outcome, the project led to the development of laboratory-based perturbation systems that have the capability of simulating various modes of fall-inducing perturbations in a repeatable way. These systems enable fundamental research on human gait and balance and facilitate the development of devices to assist human balance. We developed a robotic system capable of rendering bumps and force-fields at a person's pelvis in any direction with forces of up to 50 pounds force that could fully reverse in as little as 0.044 seconds, which is faster than a human's ability to sense and respond to the force (Figure 2). These capabilities enable experiments that require stabilizing or destabilizing subjects as they stand or walk on a treadmill. To facilitate use by researchers from all backgrounds, we designed both a configuration with simpler open-loop force control, and another with higher-performance, closed-loop force control. Both configurations are modular, and the open-loop system is made entirely from 3D-printed and catalog components. The design files and assembly instructions for both are freely available in an online repository: https://biomechatronics.stanford.edu/bump-em.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>(c) The project enabled the involvement of three faculties, one postdoctoral researcher, nine graduate students, and two undergraduate students in research in rehabilitation robotics. The project has advanced the technical and professional skills of all involved researchers through activities such as direct mentoring, participation and presentation at scientific conferences, and writing and publishing research results in journal and conference publications. The students and the postdoctoral researcher will enter the workforce with the ability to meaningfully contribute to the growing sectors of medical devices, wearable robotics, bionics, and biomechatronics.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 11/06/2019<br>      Modified by: Hartmut&nbsp;Geyer</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Images (<span id="selectedPhoto0">1</span> of <span class="totalNumber"></span>)           </div> <div class="galControls" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1527140/1527140_10386658_1573070070403_figure1--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1527140/1527140_10386658_1573070070403_figure1--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Figure 1. CMU prosthesis and disturbance experiments."><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1527140/1527140_10386658_1573070070403_figure1--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Figure 1. CMU prosthesis and disturbance experiments."></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">CMU powered knee-ankle prosthesis and experiments exploring fall recovery of novel and established prosthesis controllers.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Nitish Thatte</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Royalty-free (restricted use - cannot be shared)</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Hartmut&nbsp;Geyer</div> <div class="imageTitle">Figure 1. CMU prosthesis and disturbance experiments.</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1527140/1527140_10386658_1573078685760_Bump-em--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1527140/1527140_10386658_1573078685760_Bump-em--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Figure 2: Disturbance emulation system"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1527140/1527140_10386658_1573078685760_Bump-em--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Figure 2: Disturbance emulation system"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Schematic of the system used to apply controlled disturbances to people while walking. This system allows researchers to identify better ways of recovering balance once pushed.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Stanford University</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Steve&nbsp;Collins</div> <div class="imageTitle">Figure 2: Disturbance emulation system</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Fall-related injuries are a main cause of impairment, disability and death in aging societies. Lower limb amputees are especially at risk of falling, as commercial prosthetic legs provide only limited functionality for recovering from unexpected disturbances. The field of rehabilitation robotics provides the opportunity to address these problems with novel robotic systems and control strategies. Within this scope, the project has (a) generated new knowledge about the control and parameter tuning of lower limb prostheses for preventing falls in amputee locomotion, (b) enabled the development of novel robotic systems including powered prostheses and automatic balance disturbers to test new prosthesis control and tuning strategies, and (c) promoted the teaching, training and learning of 15 researchers involved in the project.       (a) With advances in rehabilitation robotics, powered limb prostheses and exoskeletons will become more prevalent in our societies. However, the controllers of these complex wearable robots are difficult to tune, especially in clinical settings, as they involve many control parameters, their human users have different preferences, and human objective functions are hard to define. We identified new algorithms for optimizing complex controllers of lower limb prostheses and exoskeletons based on qualitative preference feedback of the human users. These algorithms may help engineers tune wearable robots more accurately, efficiently and consistently.  The tuning algorithms further helped us to objectively compare in human locomotion experiments the capabilities of new and more established prosthesis control strategies to prevent falls in the presence of gait disturbances. The results of these experiments suggest that a human-like reflex control in stance combined with a minimum jerk control in swing improves the capability of robotic prostheses to prevent falls (Figure 1). The finding may help improve the mobility of amputees and may generalize to exoskeleton applications as well.  The experiments also highlighted shortcomings of all compared prosthesis control strategies, which inspired new ideas for improving amputee mobility. For instance, within this project, we explored and demonstrated a combination of sensor fusion and machine learning techniques to achieve more robust and adaptive prosthesis control in the presence not only of environment disturbances but also of changes in locomotion behavior desired by the human user.     (b) The project led to the development of powered leg prototypes whose high torque and speed characteristics were critical to implementing and testing fall recovery strategies (Figure 1).  Complementary to this outcome, the project led to the development of laboratory-based perturbation systems that have the capability of simulating various modes of fall-inducing perturbations in a repeatable way. These systems enable fundamental research on human gait and balance and facilitate the development of devices to assist human balance. We developed a robotic system capable of rendering bumps and force-fields at a person's pelvis in any direction with forces of up to 50 pounds force that could fully reverse in as little as 0.044 seconds, which is faster than a human's ability to sense and respond to the force (Figure 2). These capabilities enable experiments that require stabilizing or destabilizing subjects as they stand or walk on a treadmill. To facilitate use by researchers from all backgrounds, we designed both a configuration with simpler open-loop force control, and another with higher-performance, closed-loop force control. Both configurations are modular, and the open-loop system is made entirely from 3D-printed and catalog components. The design files and assembly instructions for both are freely available in an online repository: https://biomechatronics.stanford.edu/bump-em.     (c) The project enabled the involvement of three faculties, one postdoctoral researcher, nine graduate students, and two undergraduate students in research in rehabilitation robotics. The project has advanced the technical and professional skills of all involved researchers through activities such as direct mentoring, participation and presentation at scientific conferences, and writing and publishing research results in journal and conference publications. The students and the postdoctoral researcher will enter the workforce with the ability to meaningfully contribute to the growing sectors of medical devices, wearable robotics, bionics, and biomechatronics.          Last Modified: 11/06/2019       Submitted by: Hartmut Geyer]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
