<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>SHF: Small: Design/Automation for Synthesizable and Scaling Friendly Analog/Mixed-Signal Circuits</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>06/15/2015</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>450000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>450000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>05010000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>CSE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CCF</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division of Computing and Communication Foundations</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Sankar Basu</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>sabasu@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927843</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The goal of the proposed research is to tackle two critical challenges for conventional analog and mixed-signal circuits to address scaling incompatibility and low design productivity. The proposed time-domain analog mixed signal circuits are scaling compatible, and can achieve higher performance with substantially reduced chip area, power, and cost. They address the critical real-world challenge of cost effectively integrating analog-mixed-signal circuits with digital functions. They can enable emerging applications that demand ultra-low-power and ultra-low voltage solutions. The proposed research design for synthesizability and new synthesis tools also has significant impacts on enhancing design productivity, leading to reduced cost, enhanced capability, shortened time-to-market, and improved reliability. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The proposed novel time domain analog-mixed-signal circuits process analog information in the time or phase domain. Thus, they naturally benefit from CMOS scaling with increased transistor speed and reduced delay. Moreover, this proposal opens up a new research direction of analog-mixed-signal design for synthesizability, the objective of which is to alleviate the difficulty in analog synthesis by intentionally creating new topologies that are synthesis friendly. New analog synthesis tools will be developed, with focus on developing compact and high-fidelity models to reduce runtime and tackle process variation. Several previously untouched issues will be addressed, such as sensitive node protection, current flow constraints, and substrate noise coupling. A new machine-learning based framework will also be developed to further increase automation level.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/15/2015</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/15/2015</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.070</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1527320</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>David</FirstName>
<LastName>Pan</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>Z</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>David Z Pan</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>dpan@ece.utexas.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5124711436</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000490997</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/15/2015</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Nan</FirstName>
<LastName>Sun</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Nan Sun</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>nansun@mail.utexas.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5122322051</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000623613</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/15/2015</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Texas at Austin</Name>
<CityName>Austin</CityName>
<ZipCode>787595316</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5124716424</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>3925 W Braker Lane, Ste 3.340</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Texas</StateName>
<StateCode>TX</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>10</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>TX10</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>170230239</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF TEXAS AT AUSTIN</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>042000273</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Texas at Austin]]></Name>
<CityName>Austin</CityName>
<StateCode>TX</StateCode>
<ZipCode>787121532</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[101 East 27th St., Suite 5.300]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Texas</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>25</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>TX25</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7798</Code>
<Text>Software &amp; Hardware Foundation</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7923</Code>
<Text>SMALL PROJECT</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7945</Code>
<Text>DES AUTO FOR MICRO &amp; NANO SYST</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0115</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2015~450000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Conventional analog and mixed-signal (AMS) circuit design methodology relies heavily on the use of operational amplifiers to process signals in the voltage domain (VD). However, it encounters significant challenges in advanced nanometer scale CMOS processes due to the reduction of power supply voltage and transistor intrinsic gain.</p> <p>During this project, we have systematically investigated a promising alternative approach, which is timed-domain (TD) analog signal processing. Our proposed new design methodology benefits from technology scaling due to increasing transistor speed, which leads to higher timing resolution and wider TD dynamic range. We have studied several fundamental topics on TD AMS circuits, including noise, linearity, speed, power, and time variance. To address the challenges in TD analog circuits and maximize their advantages, we have proposed new transistor-level topologies as well as circuit architectures. We have applied our proposed novel design techniques to a wide range of circuits, including analog-to-digital converters (ADC), filters, amplifiers, and capacitive sensor front-end. To verify the proposed techniques thoroughly, we have also taped out and tested prototype circuits in nanometer CMOS processes (e.g., 40 nm CMOS). The measurements show that the proposed circuits outperform the state-of-the-art in key performance merits (e.g., dynamic range, linearity, signal-to-noise ratio, and energy efficiency). Our work has pushed the envelope of TD AMS circuits. It clearly shows that TD AMS circuits are scaling friendly and can achieve higher performance than classic VD AMS circuits in advanced processes. They address the real-world challenge of cost effectively integrating AMS circuits with digital functions on an SoC. They can enable emerging applications that demand ultra-low-power and ultra-low-voltage AMS solutions.</p> <p>In addition to circuit innovation, we have also invented new computer-aided design (CAD) algorithms that can enhance the design automation level of TD AMS circuits. By taking advantage of the fact that TD AMS circuits consist of mostly digital circuits, we have demonstrated, for the first time, the complete automated synthesis of a TD oversampling ADC. We have also proposed novel automated analog layout techniques that can protect sensitive circuit nodes.</p> <p>Over a short period of three years, we have published 6 papers at top journals, including 3 <em>IEEE Journal of Solid-State Circuits</em> papers. We have also published 9 papers at premier conferences, such as <em>IEEE Symposium on VLSI Circuits</em>, <em>Design Automation Conference</em>, etc. We have already graduated three PhD students, one of which becomes assistant professor at SUNY Buffalo.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 07/03/2018<br>      Modified by: Nan&nbsp;Sun</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Conventional analog and mixed-signal (AMS) circuit design methodology relies heavily on the use of operational amplifiers to process signals in the voltage domain (VD). However, it encounters significant challenges in advanced nanometer scale CMOS processes due to the reduction of power supply voltage and transistor intrinsic gain.  During this project, we have systematically investigated a promising alternative approach, which is timed-domain (TD) analog signal processing. Our proposed new design methodology benefits from technology scaling due to increasing transistor speed, which leads to higher timing resolution and wider TD dynamic range. We have studied several fundamental topics on TD AMS circuits, including noise, linearity, speed, power, and time variance. To address the challenges in TD analog circuits and maximize their advantages, we have proposed new transistor-level topologies as well as circuit architectures. We have applied our proposed novel design techniques to a wide range of circuits, including analog-to-digital converters (ADC), filters, amplifiers, and capacitive sensor front-end. To verify the proposed techniques thoroughly, we have also taped out and tested prototype circuits in nanometer CMOS processes (e.g., 40 nm CMOS). The measurements show that the proposed circuits outperform the state-of-the-art in key performance merits (e.g., dynamic range, linearity, signal-to-noise ratio, and energy efficiency). Our work has pushed the envelope of TD AMS circuits. It clearly shows that TD AMS circuits are scaling friendly and can achieve higher performance than classic VD AMS circuits in advanced processes. They address the real-world challenge of cost effectively integrating AMS circuits with digital functions on an SoC. They can enable emerging applications that demand ultra-low-power and ultra-low-voltage AMS solutions.  In addition to circuit innovation, we have also invented new computer-aided design (CAD) algorithms that can enhance the design automation level of TD AMS circuits. By taking advantage of the fact that TD AMS circuits consist of mostly digital circuits, we have demonstrated, for the first time, the complete automated synthesis of a TD oversampling ADC. We have also proposed novel automated analog layout techniques that can protect sensitive circuit nodes.  Over a short period of three years, we have published 6 papers at top journals, including 3 IEEE Journal of Solid-State Circuits papers. We have also published 9 papers at premier conferences, such as IEEE Symposium on VLSI Circuits, Design Automation Conference, etc. We have already graduated three PhD students, one of which becomes assistant professor at SUNY Buffalo.       Last Modified: 07/03/2018       Submitted by: Nan Sun]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
