<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>INSPIRE: A CUAHSI-NCAR Collaboration to Improve Hydrologic Process Representation in Weather, Climate and Earth System Models</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2015</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2020</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>999775.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>999775</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>06030109</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>GEO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>EAR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Earth Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Laura Lautz</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>llautz@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927775</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This INSPIRE project is jointly funded by the (a) Office of Integrative Activities, (b) Hydrologic Sciences Program in the Earth Sciences Division and the (c) Physical and Dynamical Meteorology and (d) Climate and Large Scale Dynamics Programs in Atmospheric and Geospace Sciences Division of the Geosciences Directorate. The project will advance our knowledge of the hydrologic cycle (i.e., how water is stored in  and moves across the land, in the soils and plants, in rivers, lakes and wetlands, and in underground aquifers) on a continental scale. Although hydrologists have quantified  local watersheds for a century, this process  data/knowledge has not been fully integrated into continental scale water cycle models and Earth system models. This project will bring together the hydrologists (who quantify hydrologic processes and theories), and modelers (who develop predictive models for large-scale water cycle research), to assess  the most critical physics, and how to best describe them mathematically in large-scale models. The improved model capability will allow us to explore questions such as: Will there be an adequate quantity and distribution of freshwater to meet the growing demands of food, energy and water security? How will a changing world (land use change, climate variability, sea-level, population change) affect, and be affected by, the volumes and flows of water between the atmosphere and  soils, streams, lakes, wetlands, and aquifers?  Knowing how much water is available where and when, and how that will change in the future, constitutes one of society's most basic scientific quests.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project will (1) create a Hydrology Process Team (HPT) bringing together field hydrologists, theoreticians, process-scale (e.g., hillslope, channel reach) modelers, and global-scale model developers. The team will integrate across  communities, disciplines, and scales  to advance water cycle science of common interest. The project will convene representatives of the hydrologic  and the atmospheric sciences communities to  develop state-of-science process syntheses and a framework for scaling from columns to large model grids and meshes, with recommendations for best ways to represent them in large-scale models. (2) These concepts will be implemented into the Community Land Model (CLM) to compare these new CLM water cycle capabilities with observations from the networks of research sites across the country supported by e.g. USDA, USGS, USFS, NOAA, NASA and NSF.  The comparisons will especially focus on below-ground water stores and fluxes neglected in earlier model tests. The new process implementation and model evaluation tasks will be guided by the synthesis team of scientists and implemented  by a postdoctoral research associate and a software engineer. (3) The project will also conduct a series of model simulations over North America to evaluate new model capabilities derived from this project, to address the water cycle and its controls at various resolutions and to define knowledge gaps for future improvement. Key evaluation criteria will include: how does the new model represent multi-scale stores and fluxes on the continent, and can it better predict droughts and floods at large river basin and national levels?  How do  the new formulations for  water stores and fluxes on land improve the simulation of ecosystem response to environmental stress and the associated carbon fluxes?  How do they improve the simulation of latent and sensible heat fluxes and hence advance  understanding of land-atmosphere interactions at weather and climate scales?  How do they improve the simulations of snowpack and permafrost dynamics and advance our capabilities to predict their responses to a warming climate?  How do they improve the simulations of riverine fluxes from the continents to the ocean basins influencing thermohaline circulation and coastal ecosystem dynamics?  A comprehensive model evaluation framework will be developed to gage model performance in the Earth System context and document model advances, the latter slated to be included in the release of CLM version 6 for participation of the next IPCC projections.  (4) A final synthesis  meeting will analyze model deficiencies and causes, and make recommendations for future modeling and observation priorities. A series of synthesis documents will be produced which will serve as historic benchmarks of land model development. This project is expected to achieve significant breakthroughs in large-scale water cycle research and capacity building, and will establish a mechanism for cross-community collaboration to advance our knowledge of the water cycle.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/22/2015</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/30/2019</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.050</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1528298</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Richard</FirstName>
<LastName>Hooper</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>P</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Richard P Hooper</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>richard.hooper@tufts.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6176273211</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000212728</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/22/2015</StartDate>
<EndDate>03/03/2017</EndDate>
<RoleCode>Former Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Ying Fan</FirstName>
<LastName>Reinfelder</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Ying Fan Reinfelder</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>yingfan@eps.rutgers.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>8484453437</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000424184</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/22/2015</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>David</FirstName>
<LastName>Lawrence</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>David Lawrence</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>dlawren@ucar.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>3034971384</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000513883</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/22/2015</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Martyn</FirstName>
<LastName>Clark</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Martyn Clark</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>mclark@ucar.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>3034972732</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000565944</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/22/2015</StartDate>
<EndDate>05/30/2019</EndDate>
<RoleCode>Former Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>David</FirstName>
<LastName>Gochis</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>David Gochis</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>gochis@ucar.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>3034971000</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000566098</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/22/2015</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Jerad</FirstName>
<LastName>Bales</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>D</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Jerad D Bales</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>jdbales@cuahsi.org</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>3399334660</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000743823</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>03/03/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Rutgers University New Brunswick</Name>
<CityName>Piscataway</CityName>
<ZipCode>088543925</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>8489320150</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>33 Knightsbridge Road</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[2nd Floor East Wing]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New Jersey</StateName>
<StateCode>NJ</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>06</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NJ06</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>001912864</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>RUTGERS, THE STATE UNIVERSITY OF NEW JERSEY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>001912864</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Rutgers University New Brunswick]]></Name>
<CityName>Piscataway</CityName>
<StateCode>NJ</StateCode>
<ZipCode>088548066</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[610 Taylor Road]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New Jersey</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>06</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NJ06</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1525</Code>
<Text>Physical &amp; Dynamic Meteorology</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1579</Code>
<Text>Hydrologic Sciences</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>5740</Code>
<Text>Climate &amp; Large-Scale Dynamics</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7570</Code>
<Text>SURFACE EARTH PROCESS SECTION</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>8078</Code>
<Text>INSPIRE</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>4444</Code>
<Text>INTERDISCIPLINARY PROPOSALS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8653</Code>
<Text>INSPIRE Track-1 Creative</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0115</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2015~999775</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Through this collaborative project between Rutgers University, CUAHSI (<a href="https://www.cuahsi.org/">https://www.cuahsi.org/</a>) and NCAR (<a href="https://ncar.ucar.edu/">https://ncar.ucar.edu/</a>), we brought together hydrologists, who customarily study the movement of water on land at local scales, and global climate modelers, who build complex computer models to simulate the physics, chemistry and biology of the whole earth including the atmosphere, the oceans, the land and the ice, and the life that inhabits these domains. Our goal was to figure out whether our knowledge of water on land, gained by observing and understanding what happens on the ground at local scales, matters to our global climate predictions. Climate models are powerful tools to peek into the future of our planet.&nbsp; The Inter-government Panel on Climate Change (IPCC) uses these computer models to simulate the future climate and issue policy advises. Our goal is to improve how land hydrology is described in these models, so that the models can do a better job predicting water resources for human societies (e.g., how much water do we have in the streams and aquifers?) and for natural ecosystems (e.g., will forests experience more droughts, and crops need more irrigation?).</p> <p>We held workshops and webinars in which the scientific community participated to discuss what we know to be important, and how we can write simple equations to describe the physics of water movement on land at local scales. We conclude that hillslopes, from the ridge top to the valley bottom, hundreds of meters to kilometers long, are fundamental units of land hydrology. Hillslopes organize water movement across the land and water available to plants. Through down-valley flow of the rain water, hills are drained valleys watered, so the valleys have more water for plants to use, so that they can stay green even during droughts (Figure 1). In addition, slopes facing the sun are warmer and often driers than the shaded slopes. In dry and hot climates and parts of the year, plants on shady slopes can stay greener (Figure 2). These are some of the examples of what we know about hydrology on land, at local scales, that may influence global model simulations. Without the inclusion of such features (hills vs. valleys, and sunny vs. shady slopes), global models would simulate little or no vegetation activity in dry periods. These conclusions, and remining questions, are discussed in this paper: <a href="https://agupubs.onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/full/10.1029/2018WR023903">https://agupubs.onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/full/10.1029/2018WR023903</a>.</p> <p>Following the community suggestions, we implemented the down-valley flow in the subsurface lateral flow (Figure 3) in the community terrestrial system model (CTSM) by dividing a hillslope into columns from the valley to the ridge. Allowing hill-valley water flow in the model enabled a wetter valley, so that the vegetation activities continued into and peaked in the driest late summer (red line), compared to the lower and earlier vegetation peak without this lateral flow (blue). These results have been published in this paper: <a href="https://doi.org/10.1029/2019MS001833">https://doi.org/10.1029/2019MS001833</a>.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 08/28/2020<br>      Modified by: Ying Fan&nbsp;Reinfelder</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Images (<span id="selectedPhoto0">1</span> of <span class="totalNumber"></span>)           </div> <div class="galControls" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2020/1528298/1528298_10378830_1598619609335_Figure-3--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2020/1528298/1528298_10378830_1598619609335_Figure-3--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Figure-3"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2020/1528298/1528298_10378830_1598619609335_Figure-3--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Figure-3"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Figure 3. (a) Implementing hill-valley flow among 4 columns, and (b) the increased vegetation transpiration in the valley (C1) as a result (red), compared to no lateral flow (blue). Note higher and later peak in red, suggesting active vegetation in the driest late summer.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Sean Swenson</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Ying Fan&nbsp;Reinfelder</div> <div class="imageTitle">Figure-3</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2020/1528298/1528298_10378830_1598619525960_Figure-2--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2020/1528298/1528298_10378830_1598619525960_Figure-2--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Figure-2"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2020/1528298/1528298_10378830_1598619525960_Figure-2--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Figure-2"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Figure 2. Guadalupe Mountains National Park, with the hotter/dryer south-facing slope dominated by desert shrub/grassland, and the cooler/moister north-facing slope dominated by mixed conifer forest Photo from: http://thecommonmilkweed.blogspot.com/2009/10/guadalupe&#8208;peak&#820</div> <div class="imageCredit">The Common Milkweed</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Public Domain</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Ying Fan&nbsp;Reinfelder</div> <div class="imageTitle">Figure-2</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2020/1528298/1528298_10378830_1598619329745_Figure-1--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2020/1528298/1528298_10378830_1598619329745_Figure-1--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Figure-1"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2020/1528298/1528298_10378830_1598619329745_Figure-1--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Figure-1"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Figure 1. The Sonoita Creek riparian forest in southern Arizona, surrounded by rugged high desert terrain. Photo by The Old Pueblo - Own work, CC BY-SA 4.0, https://commons.wikimedia.org/w/index.php?curid=37519512</div> <div class="imageCredit">The Old Pueblo</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Creative Commons</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Ying Fan&nbsp;Reinfelder</div> <div class="imageTitle">Figure-1</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Through this collaborative project between Rutgers University, CUAHSI (https://www.cuahsi.org/) and NCAR (https://ncar.ucar.edu/), we brought together hydrologists, who customarily study the movement of water on land at local scales, and global climate modelers, who build complex computer models to simulate the physics, chemistry and biology of the whole earth including the atmosphere, the oceans, the land and the ice, and the life that inhabits these domains. Our goal was to figure out whether our knowledge of water on land, gained by observing and understanding what happens on the ground at local scales, matters to our global climate predictions. Climate models are powerful tools to peek into the future of our planet.  The Inter-government Panel on Climate Change (IPCC) uses these computer models to simulate the future climate and issue policy advises. Our goal is to improve how land hydrology is described in these models, so that the models can do a better job predicting water resources for human societies (e.g., how much water do we have in the streams and aquifers?) and for natural ecosystems (e.g., will forests experience more droughts, and crops need more irrigation?).  We held workshops and webinars in which the scientific community participated to discuss what we know to be important, and how we can write simple equations to describe the physics of water movement on land at local scales. We conclude that hillslopes, from the ridge top to the valley bottom, hundreds of meters to kilometers long, are fundamental units of land hydrology. Hillslopes organize water movement across the land and water available to plants. Through down-valley flow of the rain water, hills are drained valleys watered, so the valleys have more water for plants to use, so that they can stay green even during droughts (Figure 1). In addition, slopes facing the sun are warmer and often driers than the shaded slopes. In dry and hot climates and parts of the year, plants on shady slopes can stay greener (Figure 2). These are some of the examples of what we know about hydrology on land, at local scales, that may influence global model simulations. Without the inclusion of such features (hills vs. valleys, and sunny vs. shady slopes), global models would simulate little or no vegetation activity in dry periods. These conclusions, and remining questions, are discussed in this paper: https://agupubs.onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/full/10.1029/2018WR023903.  Following the community suggestions, we implemented the down-valley flow in the subsurface lateral flow (Figure 3) in the community terrestrial system model (CTSM) by dividing a hillslope into columns from the valley to the ridge. Allowing hill-valley water flow in the model enabled a wetter valley, so that the vegetation activities continued into and peaked in the driest late summer (red line), compared to the lower and earlier vegetation peak without this lateral flow (blue). These results have been published in this paper: https://doi.org/10.1029/2019MS001833.             Last Modified: 08/28/2020       Submitted by: Ying Fan Reinfelder]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
