<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Doctoral Dissertation Research: Population Shifts and Suburban Governance</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2015</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>10/31/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>19997.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>19997</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>04040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>SBE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>BCS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Behavioral and Cognitive Sci</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Deborah Winslow</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Contemporary American suburbs are home to the largest and fastest growing poor populations in the country. In the first decade of the 21st century, suburbs saw their poverty populations growing twice as fast as those of central cities because of both internal population movement and immigration.  One result is that suburban communities across the country face the challenge of building an adequate social safety net to serve their rapidly diversifying populations. Two factors have emerged as particularly important in this effort: the presence of a suburban network of nonprofits and philanthropic donors, and the strengthening of regional institutional coalitions that can help implement social policies at a metropolitan scale. However, there are also counter currents, such as the decisions by residents of some suburbs to seek community incorporation and thereby separate themselves from the new arrivals. It is still unclear how these dynamics will play out and what the characteristics of the new American suburb will be. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;To investigate these developments, Northwestern University doctoral student Elisa Lanari, supervised by Dr. Micaela di Leonardo, will undertake 16 months of research in one such community in the American south. The community is an example of a historically white and affluent suburb that has adopted separatist policies and initiatives in response to the growth of low-income and immigrant populations around them. At the same time, the community also has a strong nonprofit sector committed to helping low-income residents. Therefore, the community constitutes an apt site for investigating the many interacting and dynamic factors that are currently remaking American suburbs. The researcher will use a mix of social science methods to gather data, including: participant observation in nonprofits and at community events and organizational meetings; semi-structured interviews with local homeowners, public officials, business leaders, nonprofit activists, and low-income residents; and analysis of printed and online material produced by media, governmental and non-governmental sources on issues of poverty, socioeconomic polarization, and community organizing in the local area. In the last research phase, she will gather archival and statistical data to provide an overall context. Findings from this research will help policy makers to understand how and why communities that have the infrastructural resources needed to build an adequate suburban safety net do not necessarily deploy them to that end. The research will also contribute to social scientific understanding of the changing dynamics and geography of American suburbs.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/10/2015</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/10/2015</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.075</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1528569</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Micaela</FirstName>
<LastName>di Leonardo</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Micaela di Leonardo</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>l-di@northwestern.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>8474914821</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000462608</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/10/2015</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Elisa</FirstName>
<LastName>Lanari</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Elisa Lanari</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>ElisaLanari2017@u.northwestern.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON/>
<NSF_ID>000688880</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/10/2015</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Northwestern University</Name>
<CityName>Chicago</CityName>
<ZipCode>606114579</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>3125037955</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>750 N. Lake Shore Drive</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[Rubloff 7th Floor]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Illinois</StateName>
<StateCode>IL</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>IL07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>160079455</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>NORTHWESTERN UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>005436803</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Northwestern University - Department of Anthropology]]></Name>
<CityName>Evanston</CityName>
<StateCode>IL</StateCode>
<ZipCode>602080809</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[1810 Hinman]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Illinois</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>09</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>IL09</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7605</Code>
<Text>Cult Anthro DDRI</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1390</Code>
<Text>CULTURAL ANTHROPOLOGY</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9179</Code>
<Text>GRADUATE INVOLVEMENT</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>SMET</Code>
<Text>SCIENCE, MATH, ENG &amp; TECH EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0115</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2015~19997</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Contemporary American suburbs are home to the largest and fastest growing poor populations in the country. In the first decade of the 21st century, suburbs saw their poverty populations growing twice as fast as those of central cities because of both internal population movement and immigration. One result is that suburban communities across the country face the challenge of building an adequate social safety net to serve their rapidly diversifying populations. Two factors have emerged as particularly important in this effort: the presence of a suburban network of nonprofits and philanthropic donors, and the strengthening of regional institutional coalitions that can help implement social policies at a metropolitan scale. However, there are also counter currents, such as the decisions by residents of some suburbs to seek municipal incorporation to separate themselves from increasingly diverse metropolitan areas. It is still unclear how these dynamics will play out and what the characteristics of the new American suburb will be.</p> <p>To investigate these issues, Northwestern University doctoral student Elisa Lanari, supervised by Dr. Micaela di Leonardo, undertook 16 months of research in a suburban community in the American south. The community is an example of a historically white and affluent suburb that has adopted separatist policies and initiatives in response to the growth of low-income and immigrant populations around them. At the same time, the community also has a strong nonprofit and philanthropic sector committed to addressing the need of growing immigrant and low-income populations. Therefore, the community constitutes an apt site for investigating the many interacting and dynamic factors that are currently remaking American suburbs. The researcher employed a mix of social science methods to gather data, including: participant observation with local nonprofits, at community events and organizational meetings; semi-structured interviews with local homeowners, public officials, business leaders, nonprofit activists, and low-income residents; and content analysis of printed and online material produced by media, governmental and non-governmental sources on issues of poverty, socioeconomic polarization, and community organizing in the local area. To place this material in a broader historical and comparative framework, she also gathered archival and statistical data, and consulted results from studies conducted in similar communities.&nbsp; &nbsp;</p> <p>The research found that the community in question, like many nearby suburban areas, has abundant economic, social, and infrastructural resources that could, and often were, employed to build a suburban safety net. The community had in fact recently undertaken several private- and public-run initiatives to address the needs of growing low-income and immigrant populations in realms as diverse as housing, social services, public transportation, and education. These initiatives however were often hindered by the lack of broader local and metropolitan support. At the time the research was conducted, in fact, the community was still characterized by debates on how to best invest local resources and design future policy so as to transform the ongoing trends of local economic, real estate, and demographic growth into an opportunity for all residents, regardless of their socioeconomic standing. By highlighting these intersecting trends, thia research advanced social scientific understanding of the changing dynamics and geography of American suburbs. The researcher also disseminated her findings, in aggregated form, among local organizations and policymakers operating in the sectors of housing, education, and social services, thereby contributing to local debates and decisions over these issues.&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 01/26/2018<br>      Modified by: Elisa&nbsp;Lanari</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Contemporary American suburbs are home to the largest and fastest growing poor populations in the country. In the first decade of the 21st century, suburbs saw their poverty populations growing twice as fast as those of central cities because of both internal population movement and immigration. One result is that suburban communities across the country face the challenge of building an adequate social safety net to serve their rapidly diversifying populations. Two factors have emerged as particularly important in this effort: the presence of a suburban network of nonprofits and philanthropic donors, and the strengthening of regional institutional coalitions that can help implement social policies at a metropolitan scale. However, there are also counter currents, such as the decisions by residents of some suburbs to seek municipal incorporation to separate themselves from increasingly diverse metropolitan areas. It is still unclear how these dynamics will play out and what the characteristics of the new American suburb will be.  To investigate these issues, Northwestern University doctoral student Elisa Lanari, supervised by Dr. Micaela di Leonardo, undertook 16 months of research in a suburban community in the American south. The community is an example of a historically white and affluent suburb that has adopted separatist policies and initiatives in response to the growth of low-income and immigrant populations around them. At the same time, the community also has a strong nonprofit and philanthropic sector committed to addressing the need of growing immigrant and low-income populations. Therefore, the community constitutes an apt site for investigating the many interacting and dynamic factors that are currently remaking American suburbs. The researcher employed a mix of social science methods to gather data, including: participant observation with local nonprofits, at community events and organizational meetings; semi-structured interviews with local homeowners, public officials, business leaders, nonprofit activists, and low-income residents; and content analysis of printed and online material produced by media, governmental and non-governmental sources on issues of poverty, socioeconomic polarization, and community organizing in the local area. To place this material in a broader historical and comparative framework, she also gathered archival and statistical data, and consulted results from studies conducted in similar communities.     The research found that the community in question, like many nearby suburban areas, has abundant economic, social, and infrastructural resources that could, and often were, employed to build a suburban safety net. The community had in fact recently undertaken several private- and public-run initiatives to address the needs of growing low-income and immigrant populations in realms as diverse as housing, social services, public transportation, and education. These initiatives however were often hindered by the lack of broader local and metropolitan support. At the time the research was conducted, in fact, the community was still characterized by debates on how to best invest local resources and design future policy so as to transform the ongoing trends of local economic, real estate, and demographic growth into an opportunity for all residents, regardless of their socioeconomic standing. By highlighting these intersecting trends, thia research advanced social scientific understanding of the changing dynamics and geography of American suburbs. The researcher also disseminated her findings, in aggregated form, among local organizations and policymakers operating in the sectors of housing, education, and social services, thereby contributing to local debates and decisions over these issues.        Last Modified: 01/26/2018       Submitted by: Elisa Lanari]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
