<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Doctoral dissertation research: The interpretation of perspectival expressions in Bulu</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2015</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>14973.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>14973</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>04040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>SBE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>BCS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Behavioral and Cognitive Sci</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Joan Maling</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>jmaling@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032928046</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Language allows speakers to represent their own perspective or some other perspective. In spatial language, for example, in one context an expression like "to the left of" can be understood to refer to the left of the speaker, or, in another context, to the left of the addressee or some other individual whose perspective is adopted. Recent research has shown that expressions with perspective-dependent meanings are pervasive in natural language. However, there is no consensus on what the full range of such expressions is, or how participants in a conversation use contextual information to determine which perspective is being adopted. Furthermore, there is very little research on how perspective-dependent expressions work in languages other than English. However, these are important topics due to the pervasiveness of perspective-dependent expressions and because the ability to represent multiple perspectives is a feature of human language not shared by animal communication systems. Thus, understanding perspective-dependent expressions across multiple languages is a key part of understanding what human language itself is and what makes it unique among communication systems. It is also crucial for developing artificial language systems that interact more naturally with humans and incorporate contextual information with greater success.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This research investigates the meanings of perspective-dependent expressions in Bulu, a Bantu language spoken in Cameroon. The researchers will study classes of perspective-dependent expressions that they have investigated previously in English. Specifically, they will investigate the meaning of motion verbs such as 'come' and perspective-dependent spatial expressions, such as 'to the left of'. Because these expressions are used differently in Bulu than in well-studied languages like English, investigating their use in Bulu will improve understanding of the range of variation in the meanings of perspective-dependent expressions. This, in turn, will facilitate the discovery of general principles involved in perspective taking across languages. This research also contributes to the documentation of Bulu and, indirectly, to the development of Bulu pedagogical materials, due to planned collaboration with researchers in Cameroon.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/02/2015</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/02/2015</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.075</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1528394</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Craige</FirstName>
<LastName>Roberts</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Craige Roberts</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>roberts.21@osu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6142928302</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000290546</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/02/2015</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Judith</FirstName>
<LastName>Tonhauser</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Judith Tonhauser</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>judith@ling.osu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6142927849</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000084563</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/02/2015</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Jefferson</FirstName>
<LastName>Barlew</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Jefferson Barlew</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>yakteacher@yahoo.com</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6142923805</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000673926</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/02/2015</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Ohio State University</Name>
<CityName>Columbus</CityName>
<ZipCode>432101016</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6146888735</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>Office of Sponsored Programs</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[1960 Kenny Road]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Ohio</StateName>
<StateCode>OH</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>OH03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>832127323</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>OHIO STATE UNIVERSITY, THE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>001964634</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Ohio State University]]></Name>
<CityName>Columbus</CityName>
<StateCode>OH</StateCode>
<ZipCode>432101298</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[1712 Neil Ave]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Ohio</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>OH03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>8374</Code>
<Text>DDRI Linguistics</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1311</Code>
<Text>LINGUISTICS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7719</Code>
<Text>DEL</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9179</Code>
<Text>GRADUATE INVOLVEMENT</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>SMET</Code>
<Text>SCIENCE, MATH, ENG &amp; TECH EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0115</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2015~14973</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>This project had two major goals:&nbsp; to gather data on perspectival expressions in the Bantu language Bulu, spoken in Cameroon, and to understand the implications of these data for linguistic theory.&nbsp; Both goals were accomplished.&nbsp; NSF funds were used to gather data from Bulu native speakers in Cameroon and the United States.&nbsp; These data and their theoretical implications were reported in Jefferson Barlew&rsquo;s (2017) dissertation and in a presentation at the international linguistics conference Sinn und Bedeutung in 2016.</p> <p>Briefly, perspectival expressions are expressions with meanings that depend on someone&rsquo;s perspective.&nbsp; For example, &ldquo;to the left of&rdquo; is a perspectival expression.&nbsp; If you ask me to bring you &ldquo;the chair to the left of the tree&rdquo;, to comply I have to know whether you mean to the left from your perspective or to the left from my perspective.&nbsp;</p> <p>The Bulu perspectival expressions investigated in this study, specifically deictic motion verbs similar to English "come", were found to have similar meanings to their English counterparts.&nbsp; However, they differ in one crucial respect.&nbsp; In Bulu, the set of people whose perspectives can be adopted is more limited than in English.&nbsp; A Bulu speaker can use perspectival deictic motion verb to represent her own perspective or the perspective of someone she is talking to, but not the perspective of some third party.</p> <p>Gathering data on perspectival expressions and determining their theoretical implications had intellectual merit and broader impact.&nbsp; The intellectual merit is twofold.&nbsp; First, perspectival expressions have not been documented in Bulu, and have only rarely been documented in any Bantu language.&nbsp; As a result, documenting these expressions adds to our knowledge about an understudied language and language family.&nbsp; Second, linguistic theories about perspectival expressions are based largely on data from English and other European languages.&nbsp; The Bulu data confirm certain aspects of those theories and challenge others.&nbsp; Thus, accounting for the Bulu data led to an advance in linguistic theory.&nbsp;</p> <p>With respect to broader impacts, at the level of the field of linguistics, the project made additional data accessible, as mentioned above.&nbsp; It also demonstrates the importance of using data from a broad range of languages.&nbsp; This demonstration is important, as it has the potential to convince researchers working in semantics, the study of meaning, to gather data from a wide range of languages.&nbsp; Finally, at a broader level, perspectival expressions have meanings that depend on the context in which they are used.&nbsp; Many other expressions have similar meanings, and we call these expressions &ldquo;context-sensitive&rdquo;.&nbsp; One example is the word &ldquo;it&rdquo;.&nbsp; To know what someone means when they say &ldquo;it&rdquo;, we have to know what they have been talking about or focused on previously.&nbsp; Although context-sensitive expressions are widespread and common, they are not well-understood.&nbsp; This lack of understanding has practical implications.&nbsp; Cell phone applications and other artificial language applications often have a difficult time interpreting and using context-sensitive expressions because they cannot keep track of contextual information in the same way that humans do.&nbsp; By improving our understanding of how humans use contextual information across different languages, this project helps lay the groundwork for future generations of artificial language systems.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 10/08/2017<br>      Modified by: Jefferson&nbsp;Barlew</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ This project had two major goals:  to gather data on perspectival expressions in the Bantu language Bulu, spoken in Cameroon, and to understand the implications of these data for linguistic theory.  Both goals were accomplished.  NSF funds were used to gather data from Bulu native speakers in Cameroon and the United States.  These data and their theoretical implications were reported in Jefferson Barlew?s (2017) dissertation and in a presentation at the international linguistics conference Sinn und Bedeutung in 2016.  Briefly, perspectival expressions are expressions with meanings that depend on someone?s perspective.  For example, "to the left of" is a perspectival expression.  If you ask me to bring you "the chair to the left of the tree", to comply I have to know whether you mean to the left from your perspective or to the left from my perspective.   The Bulu perspectival expressions investigated in this study, specifically deictic motion verbs similar to English "come", were found to have similar meanings to their English counterparts.  However, they differ in one crucial respect.  In Bulu, the set of people whose perspectives can be adopted is more limited than in English.  A Bulu speaker can use perspectival deictic motion verb to represent her own perspective or the perspective of someone she is talking to, but not the perspective of some third party.  Gathering data on perspectival expressions and determining their theoretical implications had intellectual merit and broader impact.  The intellectual merit is twofold.  First, perspectival expressions have not been documented in Bulu, and have only rarely been documented in any Bantu language.  As a result, documenting these expressions adds to our knowledge about an understudied language and language family.  Second, linguistic theories about perspectival expressions are based largely on data from English and other European languages.  The Bulu data confirm certain aspects of those theories and challenge others.  Thus, accounting for the Bulu data led to an advance in linguistic theory.   With respect to broader impacts, at the level of the field of linguistics, the project made additional data accessible, as mentioned above.  It also demonstrates the importance of using data from a broad range of languages.  This demonstration is important, as it has the potential to convince researchers working in semantics, the study of meaning, to gather data from a wide range of languages.  Finally, at a broader level, perspectival expressions have meanings that depend on the context in which they are used.  Many other expressions have similar meanings, and we call these expressions "context-sensitive".  One example is the word "it".  To know what someone means when they say "it", we have to know what they have been talking about or focused on previously.  Although context-sensitive expressions are widespread and common, they are not well-understood.  This lack of understanding has practical implications.  Cell phone applications and other artificial language applications often have a difficult time interpreting and using context-sensitive expressions because they cannot keep track of contextual information in the same way that humans do.  By improving our understanding of how humans use contextual information across different languages, this project helps lay the groundwork for future generations of artificial language systems.       Last Modified: 10/08/2017       Submitted by: Jefferson Barlew]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
