<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>GOALI/Collaborative Research: Self-powered Dual-mode Piezoelectric Resonant Pressure/Temperature Sensors for Oil and Gas Field Explorations</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>12/30/2014</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>190000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>190000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CMMI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Civil, Mechanical, &amp; Manufact Inn</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Irina Dolinskaya</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>idolinsk@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927078</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The objective of this Grant Opportunity for Academic Liaison with Industry (GOALI) Collaborative Research project is to investigate a novel self-powered dual-mode piezoelectric resonant pressure/temperature sensor that can operate in the harsh downhole environments without requiring external electricity as a step to resolve the critical challenges for downhole sensing and power supply posed by high temperature, high pressure, large shock environment of oil/gas field explorations. The material properties of the new high temperature piezoelectric material will be characterized, and theoretical analysis will be performed to predict the specific cut angle for dual-mode sensing. A novel torsional vibration energy harvester and thermoelectric generator will be designed to harness electricity from downhole drilling with dual function of suppressing the self-excited torsional vibration of the drill string. The complete self-powered sensing system will be validated through laboratory and in-field test. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;If successful, the results will create new knowledge on high temperature and high pressure sensing and energy harvesting. The data of material properties and theoretical modeling will not only enable predictable design of the piezoelectric resonant sensor operating in harsh environments but also will lay a solid foundation for future piezoelectric resonator design. The proposed multi-source thermoelectric and electromagnetic energy harvesting mechanism not only generates useful energy from the intrinsic downhole heat and drillstring vibrations, but also creates new knowledge of energy harvesting in harsh environments with broader applications. The self-powered sensing system will lead the way to drilling deeper and more productive oil &amp; gas wells to meet the urgent national energy need. Integrated with the research is a carefully orchestrated educational and outreach plan at the both participating universities, particularly for minorities, women, undergraduate, and K12 students.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/24/2015</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/24/2015</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1529842</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Lei</FirstName>
<LastName>Zuo</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Lei Zuo</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>leizuo@vt.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5402317270</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000526519</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/24/2015</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University</Name>
<CityName>BLACKSBURG</CityName>
<ZipCode>240610001</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5402315281</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>Sponsored Programs 0170</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[300 Turner Street NW, Suite 4200]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Virginia</StateName>
<StateCode>VA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>09</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>VA09</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>003137015</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>VIRGINIA POLYTECHNIC INSTITUTE AND STATE UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>003137015</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University]]></Name>
<CityName>Blacksburg</CityName>
<StateCode>VA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>240610001</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Virginia</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>09</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>VA09</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1504</Code>
<Text>GOALI-Grnt Opp Acad Lia wIndus</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1639</Code>
<Text>SENSORS AND SENSING SYSTEMS</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>032E</Code>
<Text>SENSORS AND ACTUATORS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>033E</Code>
<Text>Smart and responsive structures</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>036E</Code>
<Text>CIVIL INFRASTRUCTURE</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>099E</Code>
<Text>High voltage switching &amp; conversion</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1057</Code>
<Text>CIS BASE RESEARCH</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1059</Code>
<Text>SENSORS AND SENSOR SYSTEMS FOR CIS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1504</Code>
<Text>GRANT OPP FOR ACAD LIA W/INDUS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1639</Code>
<Text>SENSORS AND SENSING SYSTEMS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7234</Code>
<Text>SENSORS NON-SOLICITATION RESEA</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>CVIS</Code>
<Text>CIVIL INFRASTRUCTURE</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0113</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2013~190000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Oil, natural gas and other similar natural resources are becoming harder and harder to access. Oil/gas field exploration requires reliable sensors since the Schlumberger brothers started downhole drilling in the 1930s. Modern oil wells are 30,000ft or longer, which posts significant challenges in downhole sensing in terms of pressure, temperature, shock, and power supply.&nbsp; The objectives of this collaborative research was (1) to investigate a novel self-powered dual-mode LGX piezoelectric resonant pressure/temperature sensor that could operate in the harsh downhole environment; and (2) harvest the energy from downhole drilling environment so as to power the sensors without requiring external electricity. In collaboration with oilfield services company Schlumberger, University of North Taxes lead the efforts to achieve the first objective, and Virginia Tech took the efforts for achieving the second objective.</p> <p>Three approaches are taking for the energy harvesting. The first one is the stochastic resonance energy harvesting by take advantage of the random whirling (lateral) vibration and periodic stick-slip torsional vibration in the drilling string. We created a bistable electromagnetic energy harvesting and demonstrated up to 7 times more power output than the traditional energy harvesting. The second approach is the piezoelectric energy harvester attached on the torsional tubing. We found that the electrical-mechanical coupling greatly depends on the piezoelectric location and orientation. Optimal angle can be found which allows the transducer synchronously works in 1-5, 3-1, and 3-3 mode. We also investigated the energy harvesting from the coolant temperature difference inside and outside the drilling pipe.</p> <p>This project provide training for several graduate and undergraduate students in the multiple disciplinary areas including vibration, linear and nonlinear dynamics, smart materials, and heat transfer. We published 6 journal papers on this project and presented the results in several conference. &nbsp;We also mentored a high-school student on the piezoelectric sensing, who subsequently was named as a Semifinalist in the Regeneron Science Talent Search, the nation's oldest and most prestigious science competition. The research findings of energy harvesting from rotating systems will have broader applications beyond the oil drilling, for example, the geothermal energy, wind turbines, helicopter rotators, steam and gas turbines, internal combustion engines, manufacturing machines, and many more.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 02/10/2019<br>      Modified by: Lei&nbsp;Zuo</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Images (<span id="selectedPhoto0">1</span> of <span class="totalNumber"></span>)           </div> <div class="galControls" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1529842/1529842_10262400_1549843305579_Figure1,StochasticResonanceEnergyHarvestingfromDrillingString--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1529842/1529842_10262400_1549843305579_Figure1,StochasticResonanceEnergyHarvestingfromDrillingString--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Stochastic Resonance Energy Harvesting from Drilling String"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1529842/1529842_10262400_1549843305579_Figure1,StochasticResonanceEnergyHarvestingfromDrillingString--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Stochastic Resonance Energy Harvesting from Drilling String"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Stochastic Resonance Energy Harvesting from Drilling String</div> <div class="imageCredit">Lei Zuo</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Lei&nbsp;Zuo</div> <div class="imageTitle">Stochastic Resonance Energy Harvesting from Drilling String</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1529842/1529842_10262400_1549845032830_Figure2,PiezoelectricEnergyHarvestingfromTorsionalVibration--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1529842/1529842_10262400_1549845032830_Figure2,PiezoelectricEnergyHarvestingfromTorsionalVibration--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Piezoelectric Energy Harvesting from Torsional Vibration"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1529842/1529842_10262400_1549845032830_Figure2,PiezoelectricEnergyHarvestingfromTorsionalVibration--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Piezoelectric Energy Harvesting from Torsional Vibration"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Piezoelectric Energy Harvesting from Torsional Vibration</div> <div class="imageCredit">Lei Zuo</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Lei&nbsp;Zuo</div> <div class="imageTitle">Piezoelectric Energy Harvesting from Torsional Vibration</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Oil, natural gas and other similar natural resources are becoming harder and harder to access. Oil/gas field exploration requires reliable sensors since the Schlumberger brothers started downhole drilling in the 1930s. Modern oil wells are 30,000ft or longer, which posts significant challenges in downhole sensing in terms of pressure, temperature, shock, and power supply.  The objectives of this collaborative research was (1) to investigate a novel self-powered dual-mode LGX piezoelectric resonant pressure/temperature sensor that could operate in the harsh downhole environment; and (2) harvest the energy from downhole drilling environment so as to power the sensors without requiring external electricity. In collaboration with oilfield services company Schlumberger, University of North Taxes lead the efforts to achieve the first objective, and Virginia Tech took the efforts for achieving the second objective.  Three approaches are taking for the energy harvesting. The first one is the stochastic resonance energy harvesting by take advantage of the random whirling (lateral) vibration and periodic stick-slip torsional vibration in the drilling string. We created a bistable electromagnetic energy harvesting and demonstrated up to 7 times more power output than the traditional energy harvesting. The second approach is the piezoelectric energy harvester attached on the torsional tubing. We found that the electrical-mechanical coupling greatly depends on the piezoelectric location and orientation. Optimal angle can be found which allows the transducer synchronously works in 1-5, 3-1, and 3-3 mode. We also investigated the energy harvesting from the coolant temperature difference inside and outside the drilling pipe.  This project provide training for several graduate and undergraduate students in the multiple disciplinary areas including vibration, linear and nonlinear dynamics, smart materials, and heat transfer. We published 6 journal papers on this project and presented the results in several conference.  We also mentored a high-school student on the piezoelectric sensing, who subsequently was named as a Semifinalist in the Regeneron Science Talent Search, the nation's oldest and most prestigious science competition. The research findings of energy harvesting from rotating systems will have broader applications beyond the oil drilling, for example, the geothermal energy, wind turbines, helicopter rotators, steam and gas turbines, internal combustion engines, manufacturing machines, and many more.          Last Modified: 02/10/2019       Submitted by: Lei Zuo]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
