<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>MRI: Acquisition of a 400 MHz NMR Spectrometer to Support Undergraduate Research and Chemical Education at Florida Gulf Coast University</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2015</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>274466.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>274466</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03090000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CHE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Chemistry</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Carlos Murillo</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>cmurillo@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924970</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>With this award from the Major Research Instrumentation Program (MRI) and support from the Chemistry Research Instrumentation Program (CRIF), Florida Gulf Coast University will acquire a 400 MHz NMR spectrometer. The instrument will allow research in different areas including organic synthesis and materials, peptide, forensic and inorganic chemistry and enhance the  teaching program at the University. The research will impact areas of biological and environmental interest including DNA stability, anti-viral peptides, precursors to novel drugs and gas adsorption materials. In general, Nuclear Magnetic Resonance (NMR) spectroscopy is one of the most powerful tools available to chemists for the elucidation of the structure of molecules. It is used to identify unknown substances, to characterize specific arrangements of atoms within molecules, and to study the dynamics of interactions between molecules in solution.  Access to state-of-the-art NMR spectrometers is essential to chemists who are carrying out frontier research. This instrument will be an integral part of teaching as well as research performed by undergraduate students at Florida Gulf Coast University.  The NMR will also increase the chemistry department's capability to collaborate with local law enforcement institutions on drug identification as well as with local bio-tech companies.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The proposal is aimed at enhancing research and education at all levels, especially in areas such as synthesizing (a) bio-inspired ionic liquids; (b) medicinally relevant natural products; (c) bioactive molecules; (d) studying structure and function of membrane disruptive anti-viral peptides; (e) studying forensic applications of NMR with concentration in long-term structural and chemical stability of DNA; and (f) studying metal-organic materials from pillared discrete structures.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/23/2015</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/23/2015</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1530959</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Scott</FirstName>
<LastName>Michael</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>F</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Scott F Michael</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>smichael@fgcu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2395097439</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000300514</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/23/2015</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Sulekha</FirstName>
<LastName>Coticone</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Sulekha Coticone</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>scoticon@fgcu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2395907029</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000639599</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/23/2015</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Arsalan</FirstName>
<LastName>Mirjafari</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Arsalan Mirjafari</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>amirjafari@fgcu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2395901270</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000691001</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/23/2015</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Gregory</FirstName>
<LastName>Boyce</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>R</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Gregory R Boyce</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>gboyce@fgcu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2395901471</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000691454</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/23/2015</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Daniel</FirstName>
<LastName>Paull</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>H</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Daniel H Paull</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>dpaull@fgcu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2367454335</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000691455</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/23/2015</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Florida Gulf Coast University</Name>
<CityName>Fort Myers</CityName>
<ZipCode>339656565</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2395907582</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>10501 FGCU Blvd South</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[Florida Gulf Coast University Bo]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Florida</StateName>
<StateCode>FL</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>19</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>FL19</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>834477051</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>FLORIDA GULF COAST UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>159621697</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Florida Gulf Coast University]]></Name>
<CityName>Fort Myers</CityName>
<StateCode>FL</StateCode>
<ZipCode>339656565</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[10501 FGCU Blvd, South]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Florida</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>19</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>FL19</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1189</Code>
<Text>Major Research Instrumentation</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1938</Code>
<Text>Chemical Instrumentation</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1189</Code>
<Text>MAJOR RESEARCH INSTRUMENTATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1938</Code>
<Text>CHEMICAL INSTRUMENTATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8819</Code>
<Text>Forensic Science</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0115</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2015~274466</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p style="text-align: left;">In 2015, Florida Gulf Coast University (FGCU) &ndash; a primary undergraduate institution &shy;&ndash;<em> </em>was funded through the NSF Major Research Instrumentation Program (Award # CHE-1530959) to acquire a 400 MHz Nuclear Magnetic Resonance (NMR) to support the research needs of faculty and undergraduate students. The NMR instrument had a profound transformative impact on the quality of the various areas of research at FGCU, i.e., organic synthesis and materials chemistry (ionic liquids and metal-organic frameworks). Since 2015, the PI, four co-PIs and one senior personnel along with their undergraduate research students were required ~2500 NMR spectra for reaction analysis and structural determination. The opportunity to access research-scale NMR instrument resulted in a significant increase in faculty productivity and the dissemination of research results through research funding, high-quality publications and conferences presentations. Over the past three years, 12 publications and 54 conference presentations &nbsp;with undergraduate coauthors were produced directly from the data generated from NMR studies</p> <ul style="text-align: left;"> <li>T. Hmissa, X. Zhang, N. R. Dhumal, G. J. McManus, X. Zhou, H. N. Nulwala, A. Mirjafari, <em>Angew. Chem. Int. Ed.</em> <strong>2018</strong>, DOI: 10.1002/anie.201808304.</li> <li>K. L. Weeks, K. R. Rutkowski, A. A. Morales Loyola,* G. R. Boyce, <em>New J. Chem.</em> <strong>2018</strong>,<strong> </strong>DOI: 10.1039/C8NJ03229G</li> <li>Mirjafari, <em>Chem. Commun. </em><strong>2018</strong>,<em> 54</em>, 2944.</li> <li>S. T. Nestor,* A. N Hawkins, X. Xhani, R. E. Sykora, J. X. Mao, K. Nam, G. J. McManus, A. Mirjafari, <em>J. Mol. Liq. </em><strong>2018</strong>, <em>265, </em>463.</li> <li>J. C. Gaitor, L. M. Paul, M. M. Reardon, T. Hmissa, S. Minkowicz, M. Regner, Y. Sheng, S. F. Michael, S. Isern, A. Mirjafari.<strong> </strong><em>Chem. Commun. </em><strong>2017</strong>,<em> 53</em>, 8328.</li> <li>J. A. Yazarians, B. L. Jim&eacute;nez, G. R. Boyce, <em>Tetrahedron Lett.</em>, <strong>2017</strong>, <em>58</em>, 2258.</li> <li>J. T. Reilly, M. A. Coats, M. M. Reardon, A. Mirjafari, <em>J. Mol. Liq. </em><strong>2017</strong>,<em> 248</em>, 830.</li> <li>S.&nbsp; T. Nestor, B. Heinrich, R. A. Sykora, X. Zhang, G. J. McManus, L. Douce, A. Mirjafari, <em>Tetrahedron</em><strong> 2017</strong>, <em>73</em>, 5456.</li> <li>S. Thigpen, S.&nbsp; T. Nestor, R. A. O&rsquo;Brien, S. Minkowicz, Y. Sheng, J. H. Davis, Jr., K. N. West, A. Mirjafari, <em>New J. Chem.</em><strong> 2017</strong>, <em>41</em>, 1625.</li> <li>R. A. O&rsquo;Brien, M. Sanchez Zayas, S.&nbsp; T. Nestor, J. C. Gaitor, R. E. Sykora, L. M. Paul, F. A. Edhegard, S. Minkowicz, Y. Sheng, S. F. Michael, S. Isern, A. Mirjafari, <em>New J. Chem.</em><strong> 2016</strong>,<em> </em><strong><em>40</em></strong>, 7795.</li> <li>M. Sanchez Zayas, S. T. Nestor, J. C. Gaitor, M. M. Reardon, A. Mirjafari, <em>ECS Trans.</em> <strong>2016</strong>, <em>75</em>, 191.</li> <li>J. D. Williams, J A. Yazarians, C. C. Almeyda, K. A. Anderson, G. R. Boyce, <em>J. Agric. Food Chem.,</em> <strong>2016</strong>, <em>64</em>, 4319.</li> </ul> <p style="text-align: left;">Indeed, having an on-site research-grade NMR significantly increased undergraduate participation and retention. Many undergraduate research students (who are most of them were women, first-generation and underrepresented minorities) have been fully trained to work with the NMR spectrometer for data acquisition and interpretation. The training and usage of the NMR by our undergraduates made them more competitive for graduate programs. The undergraduate students who have received training from the research groups of PI/coPI have been accepted in the chemistry graduate programs of top-tier institutions including: the University of California, Santa Barbara, Yale University, University of California, Davis, University of Texas, Austin, University of Michigan, University of Florida, Carnegie Mellon University, and etc.</p> <p style="text-align: left;">The NMR was exploited extensively in our teaching curriculum. That is, the instrument was integrated into the Practical NMR Spectroscopy, Instrumental Analysis, Forensic Chemistry and Advanced Organic Chemistry courses. An elective upper-level course, Practical NMR Spectroscopy was designed and offered by the PI in Fall 2016. Indeed, access to a modern NMR spectrometer had a dramatic impact on curriculum in general and this course in particular because this course supports the three programs of Chemistry Dept. <em>i.e.,</em> Chemistry, Biochemistry and Forensic Science.</p> <p style="text-align: left;">The Chemistry Department at FGCU has developed a new B.S. degree in Forensic Science. One area that has ignited student attention has been the area of Forensic Chemistry, which provides an excellent setting for illustrating several fundamental scientific concepts and introducing aspects of chemistry to students interested in science. We developed a Forensic Chemistry course that integrate NMR spectroscopy techniques to identify unknown compounds. Students initially performed presumptive tests followed by confirmatory tests including <sup>1</sup>H and <sup>13</sup>C NMR spectroscopy to characterize unknown over-the-counter drugs. A pedagogical paper was published from the results of this course (K. Sinclair,* A. Mirjafari, S. Coticone, <em>Chem. Educator</em> <strong>2018</strong>, <em>23</em>, 143-144).</p> <p style="text-align: left;">The 400 MHz NMR significantly aided in departmental outreach initiatives. The Department of Chemistry and Physics currently does outreach to the community by mentoring high school research students and inviting a local high schools per year to our &ldquo;Chemist for a Day&rdquo; program. We brought local high school AP chemistry students from five local counties to FGCU for a day of activities that include a tour of research and NMR labs and performing an organic chemistry laboratory experiment.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 09/14/2018<br>      Modified by: Arsalan&nbsp;Mirjafari</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[In 2015, Florida Gulf Coast University (FGCU) &ndash; a primary undergraduate institution &shy;&ndash; was funded through the NSF Major Research Instrumentation Program (Award # CHE-1530959) to acquire a 400 MHz Nuclear Magnetic Resonance (NMR) to support the research needs of faculty and undergraduate students. The NMR instrument had a profound transformative impact on the quality of the various areas of research at FGCU, i.e., organic synthesis and materials chemistry (ionic liquids and metal-organic frameworks). Since 2015, the PI, four co-PIs and one senior personnel along with their undergraduate research students were required ~2500 NMR spectra for reaction analysis and structural determination. The opportunity to access research-scale NMR instrument resulted in a significant increase in faculty productivity and the dissemination of research results through research funding, high-quality publications and conferences presentations. Over the past three years, 12 publications and 54 conference presentations  with undergraduate coauthors were produced directly from the data generated from NMR studies  T. Hmissa, X. Zhang, N. R. Dhumal, G. J. McManus, X. Zhou, H. N. Nulwala, A. Mirjafari, Angew. Chem. Int. Ed. 2018, DOI: 10.1002/anie.201808304. K. L. Weeks, K. R. Rutkowski, A. A. Morales Loyola,* G. R. Boyce, New J. Chem. 2018, DOI: 10.1039/C8NJ03229G Mirjafari, Chem. Commun. 2018, 54, 2944. S. T. Nestor,* A. N Hawkins, X. Xhani, R. E. Sykora, J. X. Mao, K. Nam, G. J. McManus, A. Mirjafari, J. Mol. Liq. 2018, 265, 463. J. C. Gaitor, L. M. Paul, M. M. Reardon, T. Hmissa, S. Minkowicz, M. Regner, Y. Sheng, S. F. Michael, S. Isern, A. Mirjafari. Chem. Commun. 2017, 53, 8328. J. A. Yazarians, B. L. Jim&eacute;nez, G. R. Boyce, Tetrahedron Lett., 2017, 58, 2258. J. T. Reilly, M. A. Coats, M. M. Reardon, A. Mirjafari, J. Mol. Liq. 2017, 248, 830. S.  T. Nestor, B. Heinrich, R. A. Sykora, X. Zhang, G. J. McManus, L. Douce, A. Mirjafari, Tetrahedron 2017, 73, 5456. S. Thigpen, S.  T. Nestor, R. A. O?Brien, S. Minkowicz, Y. Sheng, J. H. Davis, Jr., K. N. West, A. Mirjafari, New J. Chem. 2017, 41, 1625. R. A. O?Brien, M. Sanchez Zayas, S.  T. Nestor, J. C. Gaitor, R. E. Sykora, L. M. Paul, F. A. Edhegard, S. Minkowicz, Y. Sheng, S. F. Michael, S. Isern, A. Mirjafari, New J. Chem. 2016, 40, 7795. M. Sanchez Zayas, S. T. Nestor, J. C. Gaitor, M. M. Reardon, A. Mirjafari, ECS Trans. 2016, 75, 191. J. D. Williams, J A. Yazarians, C. C. Almeyda, K. A. Anderson, G. R. Boyce, J. Agric. Food Chem., 2016, 64, 4319.  Indeed, having an on-site research-grade NMR significantly increased undergraduate participation and retention. Many undergraduate research students (who are most of them were women, first-generation and underrepresented minorities) have been fully trained to work with the NMR spectrometer for data acquisition and interpretation. The training and usage of the NMR by our undergraduates made them more competitive for graduate programs. The undergraduate students who have received training from the research groups of PI/coPI have been accepted in the chemistry graduate programs of top-tier institutions including: the University of California, Santa Barbara, Yale University, University of California, Davis, University of Texas, Austin, University of Michigan, University of Florida, Carnegie Mellon University, and etc. The NMR was exploited extensively in our teaching curriculum. That is, the instrument was integrated into the Practical NMR Spectroscopy, Instrumental Analysis, Forensic Chemistry and Advanced Organic Chemistry courses. An elective upper-level course, Practical NMR Spectroscopy was designed and offered by the PI in Fall 2016. Indeed, access to a modern NMR spectrometer had a dramatic impact on curriculum in general and this course in particular because this course supports the three programs of Chemistry Dept. i.e., Chemistry, Biochemistry and Forensic Science. The Chemistry Department at FGCU has developed a new B.S. degree in Forensic Science. One area that has ignited student attention has been the area of Forensic Chemistry, which provides an excellent setting for illustrating several fundamental scientific concepts and introducing aspects of chemistry to students interested in science. We developed a Forensic Chemistry course that integrate NMR spectroscopy techniques to identify unknown compounds. Students initially performed presumptive tests followed by confirmatory tests including 1H and 13C NMR spectroscopy to characterize unknown over-the-counter drugs. A pedagogical paper was published from the results of this course (K. Sinclair,* A. Mirjafari, S. Coticone, Chem. Educator 2018, 23, 143-144). The 400 MHz NMR significantly aided in departmental outreach initiatives. The Department of Chemistry and Physics currently does outreach to the community by mentoring high school research students and inviting a local high schools per year to our "Chemist for a Day" program. We brought local high school AP chemistry students from five local counties to FGCU for a day of activities that include a tour of research and NMR labs and performing an organic chemistry laboratory experiment.             Last Modified: 09/14/2018       Submitted by: Arsalan Mirjafari]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
