<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>NSF 15-022 Fate of aerosolized Nanoparticles: The influence of surface active substances on lung deposition and respiratory effects (NANOaers)</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/15/2016</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>01/31/2020</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>289274.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>289274</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07020000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CBET</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Chem, Bioeng, Env, &amp; Transp Sys</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Nora Savage</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>nosavage@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927949</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Brain, Joseph&lt;br/&gt;1530767&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Nanotechnology has expanded dramatically during the past decades. While maximizing benefits, there is also a need to minimize risks of nanotechnology. One of the current major research areas in nanotechnology is to optimize novel properties of nanomaterials to improve quality of life.  The PIs will study examples of public and workplace exposures to nanoparticles specifically those containing either silver (Ag) or cerium (Ce). Both are inexpensive and produced in large quantities. Silver-containing nanoparticles are used in medical supplies, cosmetics and textiles for their ability to kill microorganisms. Nanoparticles containing cerium oxide are used to polish glass mirrors, computer chips, and ophthalmic lenses. The PIs seek to develop techniques to explain nanoparticle behavior and control human exposures during production, use, and disposal of these products. An important feature of this proposal is that it involves researchers from the United States in an international consortium that includes Germany, Romania, Austria, and Spain. As a result the PIs will better understand how that affects the phospholipids and proteins that bind to particle surfaces and how that influences their ultimate fate and biological effects.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The PIs will characterize human exposures to novel nanoparticles. The research project will use models and exposure scenarios to elucidate the mechanisms underlying inhalation of nanoparticles. The project will involve exploration of where inhaled nanoparticles deposit, how fast they migrate from lungs, and to what extent they cross the air-blood barrier and thus have access to other organs. A key issue is particle interactions since mixtures are commonplace. Nanoparticle exposures are is often combined with particles that are larger and with a variety of chemicals and vapors. This project will explore what happens to particles after they deposit deep in the lungs. The PIs will measure how the size, morphology, and surface composition of nanoparticles determine the specific proteins and phospholipids that bind to their surface. In turn, this binding activity will determine the fate of and biologic responses to nanoparticles. The research objective is to integrate these data to better predict risks from nanomaterials for humans or the environment.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/09/2016</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/09/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1530767</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Joseph</FirstName>
<LastName>Brain</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Joseph Brain</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>brain@hsph.harvard.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6174321272</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000643556</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/09/2016</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Harvard University</Name>
<CityName>Cambridge</CityName>
<ZipCode>021385369</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6174955501</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1033 MASSACHUSETTS AVE</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[5th Floor]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
<StateCode>MA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MA05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>082359691</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>PRESIDENT AND FELLOWS OF HARVARD COLLEGE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>001963263</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Harvard School of Public Health]]></Name>
<CityName>Boston</CityName>
<StateCode>MA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>021156208</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[677 Huntington Ave]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MA07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1179</Code>
<Text>Nanoscale Interactions Program</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7237</Code>
<Text>NANO NON-SOLIC SCI &amp; ENG AWD</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0116</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2016~289274</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>This NSF Grant was part of a consortium from five countries which studied the potential toxicity of consumer products which generated aerosols containing nanomaterials [NMs]. We seek to optimize the positive uses of nanotechnology while minimizing possible harm to humans or the environment. The use of manufactured NMs (MNMs) in common consumer applications is steadily increasing. Two prominent MNMs often used and relevant for potential inhalation exposure are Ag and CeO<sub>2</sub>&nbsp;nanoparticles (NPs). They are relatively inexpensive and produced in large quantities.&nbsp;<strong>Ag&nbsp;</strong>NPs are often used in materials like medical supplies, cosmetics, and textiles for its bacterial inhibiting properties.&nbsp;<strong>CeO<sub>2</sub></strong>&nbsp;NPs are used as polishing agents for glass mirrors, television screens, ophthalmic lenses, and silicon wafers. They are often added to lacquers and wood preservative coatings to improve their UV stability. The specific applications for the two NPs emphasized in this project are aerosols intended to improve the performance of textiles, leather, and some surfaces.</p> <p>Inhalation is the most relevant route of exposure to MNMs. Aerosolized MNMs rarely enter the body in their pristine form. They are usually part of complex mixtures. When deposited in the lungs, MNMs land on airways and the alveolar lining layer containing phospholipids (PLs) and proteins. This results in the formation of a PL-protein corona that changes surface characteristics before it contacts lung cells. Moreover, the aging processes of airborne MNMs during aerosolization or by their reactions in the atmosphere can also alter MNM characteristics. It is important to understand the interplay of the chemical ingredients and physical parameters of liquid aerosol clouds to assess their risks for humans or the environment.</p> <p>The formulation we studied was complex with multiple constituents (Fig. 1). It was essential to evaluate the toxicity of all components in addition to the nanoparticles (Fig. 2). We used a logical progression from [1] simple&nbsp;<em>in vitro&nbsp;</em>assays to [2]&nbsp;<em>ex vivo</em>&nbsp;responses of the entire lung especially Precision Cut Lung Slices (Fig. 3), then we turned to [3] whole animal exposures. As we progress from simple to complex, the throughput decreases but relevance increases.</p> <p>Between over-simplified cellular assays, and the complexity and expense of studying intact animals, there is an important gap. To "mind the gap" and to fill it, an effective preparation is the PCLS.&nbsp;In the PCLS, the morphological organization of cells, matrix, airways, and vessels is nearly identical to that in the&nbsp;<em>in vivo</em>&nbsp;lung. Additional practical advantages of the PCLS include its ease of storage via cryopreservation, suitability for high-resolution microscopy imaging, and inclusion of many species, including human.</p> <p>This project demonstrates that PCLS is a powerful technology in toxicology. When deployed in a 96-well format, different conditions [e.g. chemicals or particles at a range of concentrations] can be studied. It can be a high throughput assay in which thousands of experimental conditions can be studied in a week. PCLS has also&nbsp;evolved&nbsp;into a high content assay. In a single slice, we can measure cell viability, mitochondrial metabolism, DNA damage and&nbsp;repair, or apoptosis. From the fluid above each lung slice, dozens of cytokines and proteins can be quantified.&nbsp;&nbsp;The number of animals sacrificed is greatly reduced since 70-80 slices can be obtained from a mouse. In this project we examined individually the toxicity of multiple components of complex mixtures containing NPs.</p> <p>During the project period, NSF support has resulted in multiple papers, abstracts and presentations at international meetings. A number of important questions have been asked and answered:</p> <p>1. When nanoparticles are present in product formulations, non-nano materials in the mixture have varying but sometimes dominant toxicities. Excipients/additives may be more toxic than the nanoparticles that the mixtures contain.</p> <p>2. Particle size of nanoparticles is critical. Smaller particles are more toxic than larger particles at the same mass (Particle mass vs. area vs. number).</p> <p>3. Silver nanoparticles are more toxic than CeO<sub>2</sub>&nbsp;nanoparticles per unit weight.</p> <p>4. PCLS data from chemicals and particles correlate with responses from&nbsp;<em>in vivo</em>&nbsp;as well as simple&nbsp;<em>in vitro</em>&nbsp;cell based assays.</p> <p>5. In our 5-country consortium there was&nbsp;&nbsp;synergy as we integrated the disciplines, expertise, and technologies of multiple countries.</p> <p>6. Aerosols containing particles and liquids are dynamic. Volatile constituents evaporate; aerosol size decreases. At high particle concentrations, there may be collisions and agglomeration of particles. This dynamic and variable character is common for other common aerosol exposures, such as both normal and e-cigarettes.</p> <ol> </ol> <p>We conclude that support by NSF and other governments was highly leveraged. The consortium utilized the personnel and infrastructure of partners. Future projects should also include the movement of faculty, postdocs, and/or technicians among participants. Each of us has approaches not shared by others; this synergy was valuable.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 05/08/2020<br>      Modified by: Joseph&nbsp;Brain</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Images (<span id="selectedPhoto0">1</span> of <span class="totalNumber"></span>)           </div> <div class="galControls" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2020/1530767/1530767_10448484_1588952623414_Figure1--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2020/1530767/1530767_10448484_1588952623414_Figure1--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Components of a nano-enabled product"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2020/1530767/1530767_10448484_1588952623414_Figure1--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Components of a nano-enabled product"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">An example of nano-enabled product for aerosol application.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Ramon Molina</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Royalty-free (unrestricted use)</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Joseph&nbsp;Brain</div> <div class="imageTitle">Components of a nano-enabled product</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2020/1530767/1530767_10448484_1588952741808_Figure2--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2020/1530767/1530767_10448484_1588952741808_Figure2--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Particles used in the study"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2020/1530767/1530767_10448484_1588952741808_Figure2--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Particles used in the study"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Different particles of variable sizes were studied.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Ramon Molina</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Royalty-free (unrestricted use)</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Joseph&nbsp;Brain</div> <div class="imageTitle">Particles used in the study</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2020/1530767/1530767_10448484_1588952900371_Figure3--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2020/1530767/1530767_10448484_1588952900371_Figure3--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Experimental design - Precision Cut Lung Slices"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2020/1530767/1530767_10448484_1588952900371_Figure3--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Experimental design - Precision Cut Lung Slices"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Outline of experiments using mouse precision-cut lung slices to assess toxicologic potential of chemicals and particles.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Marcelo Sanches</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Royalty-free (unrestricted use)</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Joseph&nbsp;Brain</div> <div class="imageTitle">Experimental design - Precision Cut Lung Slices</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ This NSF Grant was part of a consortium from five countries which studied the potential toxicity of consumer products which generated aerosols containing nanomaterials [NMs]. We seek to optimize the positive uses of nanotechnology while minimizing possible harm to humans or the environment. The use of manufactured NMs (MNMs) in common consumer applications is steadily increasing. Two prominent MNMs often used and relevant for potential inhalation exposure are Ag and CeO2 nanoparticles (NPs). They are relatively inexpensive and produced in large quantities. Ag NPs are often used in materials like medical supplies, cosmetics, and textiles for its bacterial inhibiting properties. CeO2 NPs are used as polishing agents for glass mirrors, television screens, ophthalmic lenses, and silicon wafers. They are often added to lacquers and wood preservative coatings to improve their UV stability. The specific applications for the two NPs emphasized in this project are aerosols intended to improve the performance of textiles, leather, and some surfaces.  Inhalation is the most relevant route of exposure to MNMs. Aerosolized MNMs rarely enter the body in their pristine form. They are usually part of complex mixtures. When deposited in the lungs, MNMs land on airways and the alveolar lining layer containing phospholipids (PLs) and proteins. This results in the formation of a PL-protein corona that changes surface characteristics before it contacts lung cells. Moreover, the aging processes of airborne MNMs during aerosolization or by their reactions in the atmosphere can also alter MNM characteristics. It is important to understand the interplay of the chemical ingredients and physical parameters of liquid aerosol clouds to assess their risks for humans or the environment.  The formulation we studied was complex with multiple constituents (Fig. 1). It was essential to evaluate the toxicity of all components in addition to the nanoparticles (Fig. 2). We used a logical progression from [1] simple in vitro assays to [2] ex vivo responses of the entire lung especially Precision Cut Lung Slices (Fig. 3), then we turned to [3] whole animal exposures. As we progress from simple to complex, the throughput decreases but relevance increases.  Between over-simplified cellular assays, and the complexity and expense of studying intact animals, there is an important gap. To "mind the gap" and to fill it, an effective preparation is the PCLS. In the PCLS, the morphological organization of cells, matrix, airways, and vessels is nearly identical to that in the in vivo lung. Additional practical advantages of the PCLS include its ease of storage via cryopreservation, suitability for high-resolution microscopy imaging, and inclusion of many species, including human.  This project demonstrates that PCLS is a powerful technology in toxicology. When deployed in a 96-well format, different conditions [e.g. chemicals or particles at a range of concentrations] can be studied. It can be a high throughput assay in which thousands of experimental conditions can be studied in a week. PCLS has also evolved into a high content assay. In a single slice, we can measure cell viability, mitochondrial metabolism, DNA damage and repair, or apoptosis. From the fluid above each lung slice, dozens of cytokines and proteins can be quantified.  The number of animals sacrificed is greatly reduced since 70-80 slices can be obtained from a mouse. In this project we examined individually the toxicity of multiple components of complex mixtures containing NPs.  During the project period, NSF support has resulted in multiple papers, abstracts and presentations at international meetings. A number of important questions have been asked and answered:  1. When nanoparticles are present in product formulations, non-nano materials in the mixture have varying but sometimes dominant toxicities. Excipients/additives may be more toxic than the nanoparticles that the mixtures contain.  2. Particle size of nanoparticles is critical. Smaller particles are more toxic than larger particles at the same mass (Particle mass vs. area vs. number).  3. Silver nanoparticles are more toxic than CeO2 nanoparticles per unit weight.  4. PCLS data from chemicals and particles correlate with responses from in vivo as well as simple in vitro cell based assays.  5. In our 5-country consortium there was  synergy as we integrated the disciplines, expertise, and technologies of multiple countries.  6. Aerosols containing particles and liquids are dynamic. Volatile constituents evaporate; aerosol size decreases. At high particle concentrations, there may be collisions and agglomeration of particles. This dynamic and variable character is common for other common aerosol exposures, such as both normal and e-cigarettes.    We conclude that support by NSF and other governments was highly leveraged. The consortium utilized the personnel and infrastructure of partners. Future projects should also include the movement of faculty, postdocs, and/or technicians among participants. Each of us has approaches not shared by others; this synergy was valuable.       Last Modified: 05/08/2020       Submitted by: Joseph Brain]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
