<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>MRI: Development of a High-Resolution Charge Detection Mass Spectrometer with MS/MS Capabilities</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2015</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>696964.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>696964</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03090000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CHE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Chemistry</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Carlos Murillo</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>cmurillo@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924970</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>With this award from the Major Research Instrumentation (MRI), the Chemistry Research Instrumentation and Facilities (CRIF) and the Chemical Measurement and Imaging (CMI) programs, Professor Martin Jarrold from Indiana University will develop a high resolution charge detection mass spectrometer (MS) with tandem capabilties (MS/MS).   Mass spectrometry is a powerful analytical tool used to identify the composition of a mixture or material. It determines the mass of the components by measuring the mass to charge ratio (m/z) of ions produced from the components. It is broadly used to analyze chemical, biological and environmental samples.  A second generation charge detection mass spectrometer (CD/MS) will be built which will incorporate performance upgrades and add new capabilities. The mass resolution will be improved by at least an order of magnitude and the ability to perform MS/MS (where selected ions are broken up and analyzed by CD/MS) will be added.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Upon development, the spectrometer will be used in research including projects that study (a) kinetically trapped intermediates in the assembly of hepatitis B virus, (b) scaffolding protein in bacteriophage P22 procapsids, (c) DNA packaging in adeno-associated virus, and (d) non-icosahedral polymorphs in the self-assembly of Woodchuck hepatitis virus (WHV) capsids.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/17/2015</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/17/2015</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1531823</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Martin</FirstName>
<LastName>Jarrold</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>F</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Martin F Jarrold</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>mfj@indiana.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>8128561182</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000440779</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/17/2015</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Indiana University</Name>
<CityName>Bloomington</CityName>
<ZipCode>474013654</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>3172783473</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>509 E 3RD ST</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Indiana</StateName>
<StateCode>IN</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>09</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>IN09</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>006046700</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>TRUSTEES OF INDIANA UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>006046700</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Indiana University]]></Name>
<CityName>Bloomington</CityName>
<StateCode>IN</StateCode>
<ZipCode>474057102</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[800 E Kirkwood Ave]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Indiana</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>09</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>IN09</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1189</Code>
<Text>Major Research Instrumentation</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1938</Code>
<Text>Chemical Instrumentation</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>6880</Code>
<Text>Chemical Measurement &amp; Imaging</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1189</Code>
<Text>MAJOR RESEARCH INSTRUMENTATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1938</Code>
<Text>CHEMICAL INSTRUMENTATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>6880</Code>
<Text>CHEMICAL MEASUREMENT &amp; IMAGING</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0115</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2015~696964</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Higher Resolution Charge Detection Mass Spectrometry</p> <p>Mass spectrometry is one of the most powerful analytical techniques, providing molecular weight information for a wide range of samples. However, conventional mass spectrometry methods are generally limited to molecular weights less than 1 MDa (around 1,000,000 times the mass of a hydrogen atom). There are many species that have much larger molecular weights, such as viruses and vaccines, where accurate molecular weight information would be valuable. Many new pharmaceutical products are biologics with high molecular weights. Examples include the emerging gene therapies that are revolutionizing treatment of genetic disorders.</p> <p>Charge detection mass spectrometry (CDMS) overcomes the limitations of conventional mass spectrometry and allows accurate mass measurements to be performed for objects with masses up to and beyond 1000 MDa. CDMS is a single particle technique where the mass of individual ions is determined from simultaneous measurement of the ions mass to charge ratio (m/z) and charge. The resolution depends on the uncertainties in both measurements. Accurately measuring the charge on a single ion is challenging and historically the uncertainty in the charge measurement has limited the mass resolution. In this project we have developed methods which overcome this limitation, allowing the charge to be accurately measured for large ions. This allowed a ten-fold improvement in the mass resolution. The graphic shows an example, that illustrates the improvement. The graphic shows mass spectra measured by CDMS for assembly of the hepatitis B virus (HBV) capsid. The capsid is the protein shell that surrounds the genetic material of a virus. For HBV there are two different capsids. Both are icosahedra. The smaller one (<em>T</em>=3) contains 180 capsid proteins and has a molecular weight of around 3 MDa. The larger one (<em>T</em>=4) contains 240 capsid proteins and has a molecular weight of around 4 MDa. The blue line in the graphic shows the spectrum measured with the prototype CDMS instrument. The red line shows the higher resolution spectrum measured with the new instrument built during this project. In the red spectrum, trapped intermediates with specific numbers of capsid protein are resolved.&nbsp; The higher resolution is enabling because it will allow measurements of ligand binding, including for example, drug and antibody binding to viruses (including coronaviruses).&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 04/21/2020<br>      Modified by: Martin&nbsp;F&nbsp;Jarrold</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Image         </div> <div class="galControls onePhoto" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation onePhoto" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2020/1531823/1531823_10377625_1587498063555_Picture1--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2020/1531823/1531823_10377625_1587498063555_Picture1--rgov-800width.jpg" title="CDMS Spectrum of HBV Assembly"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2020/1531823/1531823_10377625_1587498063555_Picture1--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="CDMS Spectrum of HBV Assembly"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">CDMS spectrum of hepatitis B virus (HBV) capsids. The blue line shows the spectrum measured on the prototype CDMS instrument and the red line shows the spectrum measured on the new instrument. The peak at around 3 MDa is due to the T=3 capsid and the peak at around  4 MDa is due to the T=4.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Martin Jarrold</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Public Domain</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Martin&nbsp;F&nbsp;Jarrold</div> <div class="imageTitle">CDMS Spectrum of HBV Assembly</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Higher Resolution Charge Detection Mass Spectrometry  Mass spectrometry is one of the most powerful analytical techniques, providing molecular weight information for a wide range of samples. However, conventional mass spectrometry methods are generally limited to molecular weights less than 1 MDa (around 1,000,000 times the mass of a hydrogen atom). There are many species that have much larger molecular weights, such as viruses and vaccines, where accurate molecular weight information would be valuable. Many new pharmaceutical products are biologics with high molecular weights. Examples include the emerging gene therapies that are revolutionizing treatment of genetic disorders.  Charge detection mass spectrometry (CDMS) overcomes the limitations of conventional mass spectrometry and allows accurate mass measurements to be performed for objects with masses up to and beyond 1000 MDa. CDMS is a single particle technique where the mass of individual ions is determined from simultaneous measurement of the ions mass to charge ratio (m/z) and charge. The resolution depends on the uncertainties in both measurements. Accurately measuring the charge on a single ion is challenging and historically the uncertainty in the charge measurement has limited the mass resolution. In this project we have developed methods which overcome this limitation, allowing the charge to be accurately measured for large ions. This allowed a ten-fold improvement in the mass resolution. The graphic shows an example, that illustrates the improvement. The graphic shows mass spectra measured by CDMS for assembly of the hepatitis B virus (HBV) capsid. The capsid is the protein shell that surrounds the genetic material of a virus. For HBV there are two different capsids. Both are icosahedra. The smaller one (T=3) contains 180 capsid proteins and has a molecular weight of around 3 MDa. The larger one (T=4) contains 240 capsid proteins and has a molecular weight of around 4 MDa. The blue line in the graphic shows the spectrum measured with the prototype CDMS instrument. The red line shows the higher resolution spectrum measured with the new instrument built during this project. In the red spectrum, trapped intermediates with specific numbers of capsid protein are resolved.  The higher resolution is enabling because it will allow measurements of ligand binding, including for example, drug and antibody binding to viruses (including coronaviruses).           Last Modified: 04/21/2020       Submitted by: Martin F Jarrold]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
