<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>MRI: Acquisition of a shared mobile EEG for research and undergraduate training at Occidental College</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2015</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>126567.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>126567</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>04040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>SBE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>BCS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Behavioral and Cognitive Sci</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>John Yellen</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>jyellen@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032928759</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Scientists are increasingly using neural recording techniques to study how and when perceptual, cognitive, and emotional processes unfold in the brain over time. Electroencephalography (EEG) is a non-invasive technique for measuring electrical activity of the brain, with extraordinary temporal precision. With the support from the Major Research Instrumentation Program, the investigators will purchase a state-of-the-art high-density, mobile EEG system for shared use by the faculty and students at Occidental College. The mobility of the EEG system provides an exciting opportunity to investigate perception and cognition both within a laboratory and in naturalistic settings outside of the laboratory. The acquisition of this system will also allow the investigators to foster unique research opportunities for a diverse group of students at the undergraduate level. Faculty and students will be involved in a dynamic, interdisciplinary research program, with investigations of topics such as multisensory perception, time perception, art perception, attention, emotional processing, language processing, and music cognition. The system will also serve as a key instrument for establishing undergraduate training in the cognitive neurosciences at Occidental College and will be integrated into coursework. Participating students will develop a broad range of skills relevant for both graduate study and participation in the STEM workforce, including strong data analytic and computational skills. As the student population at Occidental College is very diverse, the investigators aim to broaden participation of underrepresented groups in the sciences.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The investigators involved will launch several research programs in a broad range of areas within the cognitive sciences, with the goal of expanding opportunities for student research and for multi-disciplinary collaboration across the College. Research project 1 aims to understand how sound can be used to synchronize neural activity across a pair of individuals and whether and how neural synchronization causally influences behavioral coordination. Research project 2 will investigate art perception to understand a) how internal states such as current mood may systematically drive attention toward specific features of an artwork, b) what type of neural response is associated with profound aesthetic experiences from viewing art compared to viewing non-art, and c) the extent to which the neural response associated with aesthetic experience is similar across art modality (e.g. visual art, music, literature). Research project 3 will explore mechanisms underlying temporal perception and how information is transferred across sensory modalities, to address fundamental questions about the multisensory organization of the brain, and will help provide a better understanding of how the brain represents time. Research project 4 will compare the time course of language processing and syllabic stress encoding in English and Spanish speakers to examine processing differences between heritage speakers and monolingual speakers of Spanish. Research project 5 aims to understand the role of consciousness in emotional processing by simultaneously measuring skin conductance response, cortical event-related potentials, and conscious expectancy of an unconditioned stimulus in a backward masking paradigm.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/23/2015</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/23/2015</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.075</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1531456</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Carmel</FirstName>
<LastName>Levitan</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Carmel Levitan</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>levitan@oxy.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>3236390309</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000676239</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/23/2015</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Aleksandra</FirstName>
<LastName>Sherman</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Aleksandra Sherman</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>asherman@oxy.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>3232591414</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000689951</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/23/2015</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Michael</FirstName>
<LastName>Shelton</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>F</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Michael F Shelton</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>mshelton@oxy.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>3232591414</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000690073</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/23/2015</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Anne</FirstName>
<LastName>Schell</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>M</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Anne M Schell</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>schell@oxy.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>3232591414</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000690230</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/23/2015</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Occidental College</Name>
<CityName>Los Angeles</CityName>
<ZipCode>900413314</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>3232591414</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1600 Campus Road</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>34</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CA34</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>046436051</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>OCCIDENTAL COLLEGE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>046436051</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Occidental College]]></Name>
<CityName>Los Angeles</CityName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>900413314</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[1600 Campus Road]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>34</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CA34</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1189</Code>
<Text>Major Research Instrumentation</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1189</Code>
<Text>MAJOR RESEARCH INSTRUMENTATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0115</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2015~126567</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Electroencephalography (EEG) is a temporally precise, non-invasive method for monitoring electrical activity in the brain.&nbsp;Use of EEG brings together aspects of neurobiology, human behavior, and computational methods.&nbsp;This award allowed faculty at Occidental College to purchase a high-density 128-channel electroencephalogram for research and classroom use. Throughout the award period, over 50 undergraduates (enrolled in either Directed Research with Professor Aleksandra Sherman or in the Cognitive Science Department's Cognitive Neuroscience course) have been trained to conduct hands-on research with EEG. In the classroom, students have conducted semester-long group-based research projects investigating topics such as visual and auditory attention, action perception, and multisensory integration. Several students have also presented their indepedent research at national undergraduate and professional conferences. Beyond learning about the specific strengths and weaknesses of the EEG methodology, conducting research using EEG has provided students with extensive computational skills, has increased their capacity to critically analyze the primary literature within the cognitive neurosciences and within STEM disciplines more broadly, and has generally made students more reflective and thoughtful data consumers. Incorporating EEG-based projects into the classroom has crucially increased accessibility to research opportunities for many more students. We expect that this equipment will continue to have long-term impact on the quality and future of research and education in the neurosciences at Occidental College.&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 12/16/2019<br>      Modified by: Carmel&nbsp;Levitan</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Images (<span id="selectedPhoto0">1</span> of <span class="totalNumber"></span>)           </div> <div class="galControls" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1531456/1531456_10379340_1574463253870_IMG_4461--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1531456/1531456_10379340_1574463253870_IMG_4461--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Undergraduate Research Conference Presentation"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1531456/1531456_10379340_1574463253870_IMG_4461--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Undergraduate Research Conference Presentation"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Occidental College undergraduate student, Cassia Harrison, presents her research at Occidental's 2019 Undergraduate Summer Research Conference accompanied by mentors Aleksandra Sherman and Carmel Levitan.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Aleksandra Sherman</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Royalty-free (restricted use - cannot be shared)</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Aleksandra&nbsp;Sherman</div> <div class="imageTitle">Undergraduate Research Conference Presentation</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1531456/1531456_10379340_1574463321370_ScreenShot2019-11-22at2.52.24PM--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1531456/1531456_10379340_1574463321370_ScreenShot2019-11-22at2.52.24PM--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Covert simulation of others' actions in real time"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1531456/1531456_10379340_1574463321370_ScreenShot2019-11-22at2.52.24PM--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Covert simulation of others' actions in real time"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Former Occidental College undergraduate, Julia Hamilton's poster presented at the 2017 Cognitive Neuroscience Society Conference.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Aleksandra Sherman</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Public Domain</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Aleksandra&nbsp;Sherman</div> <div class="imageTitle">Covert simulation of others' actions in real time</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Electroencephalography (EEG) is a temporally precise, non-invasive method for monitoring electrical activity in the brain. Use of EEG brings together aspects of neurobiology, human behavior, and computational methods. This award allowed faculty at Occidental College to purchase a high-density 128-channel electroencephalogram for research and classroom use. Throughout the award period, over 50 undergraduates (enrolled in either Directed Research with Professor Aleksandra Sherman or in the Cognitive Science Department's Cognitive Neuroscience course) have been trained to conduct hands-on research with EEG. In the classroom, students have conducted semester-long group-based research projects investigating topics such as visual and auditory attention, action perception, and multisensory integration. Several students have also presented their indepedent research at national undergraduate and professional conferences. Beyond learning about the specific strengths and weaknesses of the EEG methodology, conducting research using EEG has provided students with extensive computational skills, has increased their capacity to critically analyze the primary literature within the cognitive neurosciences and within STEM disciplines more broadly, and has generally made students more reflective and thoughtful data consumers. Incorporating EEG-based projects into the classroom has crucially increased accessibility to research opportunities for many more students. We expect that this equipment will continue to have long-term impact on the quality and future of research and education in the neurosciences at Occidental College.        Last Modified: 12/16/2019       Submitted by: Carmel Levitan]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
