<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>MRI:  Acquisition of a Laser-diode-heated Floating Zone Furnace for Education and Research</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2015</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>339990.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>339990</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03070000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DMR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Materials Research</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Leonard Spinu</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>lspinu@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922665</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This Major Research Instrumentation (MRI) award will be used by Rutgers University New Brunswick to acquire a Laser-diode-heated Floating Zone furnace (L-FZ), which will be used to grow high quality bulk single crystals of a variety of complex quantum materials including multiferroics, ferroelectrics and low-symmetry magnets. The instrument will support research and education at Rutgers Center for Emergent Materials (RCEM), Rutgers, and the State University of New Jersey. L-FZ is a crystal growth furnace that is newly developed in Japan, and the successful acquisition of L-FZ through this grant will result in the first installation of L-FZ in the United States, serving the national interest by ensuring world-leading research on crystalline quantum materials in the US. Compared with, for example, the conventional infrared-lamp-heated Floating Zone furnace, L-FZ has unique functionalities such as the extreme temperature gradients, high growth temperatures and fast growth rates. These functionalities will enable the growth of high-quality single crystals of an entirely new set of crystalline materials and result in transformative discoveries of new materials. The Principal Investigators and nation-wide collaborators from, for example, New Jersey Institute of Technology (NJIT), Brookhaven National Lab, U. of Tennessee, and Johns Hopkins, will benefit significantly from the previously-unavailable crystals for large-range and high-resolution imaging techniques such as scanning probe microscopy and transmission electron microscopy as well as neutron scattering. L-FZ will support research and education activities involving undergraduate, graduate students and postdocs at RCEM, as well as K-12 students in the New Jersey region and beyond through the Partners in Science Program organized by the Liberty Science Center, New Jersey. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The functionalities of the Laser-diode-heated Floating Zone furnace enable the growth of [1] metastable phases, [2] incongruent melting compounds, [3] materials with high vapor pressure, [4] compositional complex materials, and [5] materials with low viscosity melt. It will be the first machine of its kind installed in the United States, and has potential to be a game changer for education and research in the field of the synthesis of functional quantum materials. Homogeneous single crystals grown with L-FZ will be utilized for transformative investigations of local/global topology, emergent functionalities and manipulation of mesoscopic domains, domain walls, and textures in a wide range of crystalline materials such as multiferroics, low-symmetry magnets, thermodynamically metastable phases and improper ferroelectrics. Using a wide-range of high-resolution imaging techniques such as scanning probe microscopy and transmission electron microscopy as well as neutron scattering, investigation will lead to scientific understanding and technological exploitation of domains, domain walls, and mesoscopic textures such as skyrmions.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/04/2015</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/04/2015</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1532006</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Martha</FirstName>
<LastName>Greenblatt</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Martha Greenblatt</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>greenbla@chem.rutgers.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>8484453277</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000168195</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/04/2015</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Sang-Wook</FirstName>
<LastName>Cheong</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Sang-Wook Cheong</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>sangc@physics.rutgers.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>8484459023</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000468564</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/04/2015</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Valery</FirstName>
<LastName>Kiryukhin</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Valery Kiryukhin</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>vkir@physics.rutgers.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>8484458752</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000202500</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/04/2015</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Weida</FirstName>
<LastName>Wu</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Weida Wu</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>wdwu@physics.rutgers.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>8484458751</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000313787</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/04/2015</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Rutgers University New Brunswick</Name>
<CityName>Piscataway</CityName>
<ZipCode>088543925</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>8489320150</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>33 Knightsbridge Road</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[2nd Floor East Wing]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New Jersey</StateName>
<StateCode>NJ</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>06</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NJ06</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>001912864</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>RUTGERS, THE STATE UNIVERSITY OF NEW JERSEY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>001912864</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Rutgers University New Brunswick]]></Name>
<CityName>Piscataway</CityName>
<StateCode>NJ</StateCode>
<ZipCode>088548019</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[136 Frelinghuysen Road]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New Jersey</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>06</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NJ06</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1189</Code>
<Text>Major Research Instrumentation</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0115</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2015~339990</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><span>The objective of this project is to use the acquired Laser-diode-heated Floating Zone furnace (L-FZ) to grow high quality bulk single crystals of a variety of complex quantum materials including multiferroics, ferroelectrics and low-symmetry magnets. The unique functionalities of L-FZ such as&nbsp;very narrow heating regions&nbsp;and&nbsp;giant temperature gradients,&nbsp;enable the growth of [1] metastable phases, [2] incongruent melting compounds, [3] materials with high vapor pressure, [4] compositional complex materials, and [5] materials with low viscosity melt. Homogeneous single crystals grown with L-FZ will be utilized for transformative investigations of local/global topology, emergent functionalities and manipulation of mesoscopic domains, domain walls, and textures in a wide range of crystalline materials such as multiferroics, low-symmetry magnets, thermodynamically metastable phases and improper ferroelectrics. Our activity up to this reporting period include ordering, installation, operation of the L-FZ and a large number of single crystal growth attempts for various materials. Single crystals of several material systems have been successfully grown for the first time using L-FZ. One paper has been accepted by Physical Review Letters and many other samples grown by L-FZ are under investigation.</span></p> <p><span>Some highlights are summarized as follows. 1) HfO2, has been studied as the high-k substitute material for the traditional silicon oxide extensively and recently has been reported to show ferroelectricity in doped thin ?lms. The robust polarization and high TC make it possible to be applied in room-temperature memory devices. However, all previous studies have focused on thin ?lms. We have successfully grown single crystals of doped HfO2 and been investigating the stabilization the ferroelectric orthorhombic phase in bulk samples and phase relationship among the cubic, tetragonal, orthorhombic and monoclinic phases. The metastable orthorhombic phase has been stablized in L-FZ grown crystals. Only the L-FZ method made it possible to grow bulk single crysta samples of doped HfO2 free from the stress/strain of substrates and grain boundaries to allow clean and microscopic characterizations. 2) (Sr,Ba)3Sn2O7,the first room temperature ferroelectric Sn insulator with switchable electric polarization. We have successfully grown for the first time single crystals of the Sn compound. The ferroelastic twin domains are observed using a polarized optical microscope. The polarization hysteresis loop clearly demonstrates the ferroelectric property. Intriguing polarization switching kinetics are observed through an in situ poling process using a dark-field transmission electron microscopy technique 3) Hexagonal RInO3 (R = Eu, Gd, Tb), we have successfully grown for the first time single crystals of these compounds and performed thorough characterization of their magnetic and structural properties by neutron scattering, TEM, x-ray etc and identified very intriguing ground states, which might categorize some of them to a promising new class of spin-liquid systems. Moreover, interesting vortex domain structures were observed similar to the isostructural RMnO3. 4) Hybrid improper ferroelectric (Ca, Sr)3Ti2O7, a new class of polar instability by mixing two octahedral-distortion modes and features the coexistence of abundant head-to-head and tail-to-tail polar charged domains. We have grown high quality single crystals of the material and uncovered&nbsp;a hidden antipolar order parameter in the model HIF. This work could stimulate further studies of structurally mediated screening in pursuit of new discoveries by thorough group-theoretical explorations in all plausible order-parameter spaces.</span></p> <p><span>Our outreach and education efforts have involved training students and crystal growers from other institutions and making samples available to the community who is interested. Two visiting Ph.D. students from China through a joint Ph.D. research program sponsored by Department of Education in China have joined our group. They were trained and intensively used L-FZ for a variety of single crystals growth. Meixia Wu, from South China University of Technology, 11/2015-05/2017 and Yanbin Li, from Shandong University, 10/2015-10/2017. Dr. Andrey Malyuk from IFW, Institute for Solid State Research, Dresden have scheduled a visit to our lab to learn and use L-FZ for a series interesting but difficult to grow materials in 10/2017. We proposed to the Gordon and Betty Moore foundation to launch a Center for Quantum Materials Synthesis at Rutgers, in an effort to explore transformative &ldquo;active wafer&rdquo; projects by combining the single crystal growth of novel materials and heterostructured film fabrication using PLD/MBE techniques. L-FZ will be one of the central facilities in the center, by providing unique crystal growth technique for various difficult to synthesize materials. The center will&nbsp;have a vibrant visitor program and accommodate two postdoctoral fellows and also visitors to work on the active wafer projects. It will drastically accelerate the pace of quantum materials discoveries/innovations.</span></p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 10/09/2017<br>      Modified by: Sang-Wook&nbsp;Cheong</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The objective of this project is to use the acquired Laser-diode-heated Floating Zone furnace (L-FZ) to grow high quality bulk single crystals of a variety of complex quantum materials including multiferroics, ferroelectrics and low-symmetry magnets. The unique functionalities of L-FZ such as very narrow heating regions and giant temperature gradients, enable the growth of [1] metastable phases, [2] incongruent melting compounds, [3] materials with high vapor pressure, [4] compositional complex materials, and [5] materials with low viscosity melt. Homogeneous single crystals grown with L-FZ will be utilized for transformative investigations of local/global topology, emergent functionalities and manipulation of mesoscopic domains, domain walls, and textures in a wide range of crystalline materials such as multiferroics, low-symmetry magnets, thermodynamically metastable phases and improper ferroelectrics. Our activity up to this reporting period include ordering, installation, operation of the L-FZ and a large number of single crystal growth attempts for various materials. Single crystals of several material systems have been successfully grown for the first time using L-FZ. One paper has been accepted by Physical Review Letters and many other samples grown by L-FZ are under investigation.  Some highlights are summarized as follows. 1) HfO2, has been studied as the high-k substitute material for the traditional silicon oxide extensively and recently has been reported to show ferroelectricity in doped thin ?lms. The robust polarization and high TC make it possible to be applied in room-temperature memory devices. However, all previous studies have focused on thin ?lms. We have successfully grown single crystals of doped HfO2 and been investigating the stabilization the ferroelectric orthorhombic phase in bulk samples and phase relationship among the cubic, tetragonal, orthorhombic and monoclinic phases. The metastable orthorhombic phase has been stablized in L-FZ grown crystals. Only the L-FZ method made it possible to grow bulk single crysta samples of doped HfO2 free from the stress/strain of substrates and grain boundaries to allow clean and microscopic characterizations. 2) (Sr,Ba)3Sn2O7,the first room temperature ferroelectric Sn insulator with switchable electric polarization. We have successfully grown for the first time single crystals of the Sn compound. The ferroelastic twin domains are observed using a polarized optical microscope. The polarization hysteresis loop clearly demonstrates the ferroelectric property. Intriguing polarization switching kinetics are observed through an in situ poling process using a dark-field transmission electron microscopy technique 3) Hexagonal RInO3 (R = Eu, Gd, Tb), we have successfully grown for the first time single crystals of these compounds and performed thorough characterization of their magnetic and structural properties by neutron scattering, TEM, x-ray etc and identified very intriguing ground states, which might categorize some of them to a promising new class of spin-liquid systems. Moreover, interesting vortex domain structures were observed similar to the isostructural RMnO3. 4) Hybrid improper ferroelectric (Ca, Sr)3Ti2O7, a new class of polar instability by mixing two octahedral-distortion modes and features the coexistence of abundant head-to-head and tail-to-tail polar charged domains. We have grown high quality single crystals of the material and uncovered a hidden antipolar order parameter in the model HIF. This work could stimulate further studies of structurally mediated screening in pursuit of new discoveries by thorough group-theoretical explorations in all plausible order-parameter spaces.  Our outreach and education efforts have involved training students and crystal growers from other institutions and making samples available to the community who is interested. Two visiting Ph.D. students from China through a joint Ph.D. research program sponsored by Department of Education in China have joined our group. They were trained and intensively used L-FZ for a variety of single crystals growth. Meixia Wu, from South China University of Technology, 11/2015-05/2017 and Yanbin Li, from Shandong University, 10/2015-10/2017. Dr. Andrey Malyuk from IFW, Institute for Solid State Research, Dresden have scheduled a visit to our lab to learn and use L-FZ for a series interesting but difficult to grow materials in 10/2017. We proposed to the Gordon and Betty Moore foundation to launch a Center for Quantum Materials Synthesis at Rutgers, in an effort to explore transformative "active wafer" projects by combining the single crystal growth of novel materials and heterostructured film fabrication using PLD/MBE techniques. L-FZ will be one of the central facilities in the center, by providing unique crystal growth technique for various difficult to synthesize materials. The center will have a vibrant visitor program and accommodate two postdoctoral fellows and also visitors to work on the active wafer projects. It will drastically accelerate the pace of quantum materials discoveries/innovations.       Last Modified: 10/09/2017       Submitted by: Sang-Wook Cheong]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
