<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>MRI: Acquisition of Thermal Ionization Mass-Spectrometer for UCSC W.M. Keck Facility</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/15/2015</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>540000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>540000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>06030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>GEO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>EAR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Earth Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>David Lambert</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>dlambert@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924736</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This award funds the acquisition of a new Thermal Ionization Mass Spectrometer (TIMS) to be integrated into the W.M. Keck Isotope Laboratory at the University of California, Santa Cruz. The TIMS will be co-located within the recently renovated climate-controlled laboratory and wet chemistry clean labs needed for the preparation of geologic samples for isotopic analysis. The reopening of this open-user facility will catalyze new research and provide the tools needed to train undergraduate, graduate and postdoctoral researchers in the use of high precision isotopic methodologies. The Earth and Planetary Science department, which is one of the largest Earth Science department?s in the country with over a 150 majors, has a population representative of the student body which includes over 40% from underrepresented ethnic backgrounds and a first year class made up of 41% of first generation college students. Outreach from this award includes a mini-grants program, available to internal and external users, to support exploratory and developmental research.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This facility will allow high precision U-Pb and U-series geochronologic dating with research applied to the origin and evolution of the continental and oceanic crust, the dynamics of volcanic systems and the timing and rate of glaciations and climatic change. Additional capabilities include measurements of the Sr, Ca, Nd, and Pb isotope systems, which are applied by UCSC Earth and Marine scientists to reconstruct variations in paleo-seawater in response to changes in tectonic uplift, climate, biogeochemical cycling and ocean circulation. UCSC paleontologists and ecologists use these same tools to study food web dynamics and foraging ranges of organisms in the present and past. &lt;br/&gt;</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/10/2015</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/31/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.050</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1532276</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Paul</FirstName>
<LastName>Koch</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>L</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Paul L Koch</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>plkoch@ucsc.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>8314592931</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000213990</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/10/2015</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Adina</FirstName>
<LastName>Paytan</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Adina Paytan</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>apaytan@ucsc.EDU</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>8314591437</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000486939</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/10/2015</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Jeremy</FirstName>
<LastName>Hourigan</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>K</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Jeremy K Hourigan</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>hourigan@ucsc.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6502696259</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000086626</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/10/2015</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Brian</FirstName>
<LastName>Dreyer</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Brian Dreyer</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>bdreyer@ucsc.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>8314595228</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000558847</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/10/2015</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Terrence</FirstName>
<LastName>Blackburn</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Terrence Blackburn</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>terryb@ucsc.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>8312012313</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000650898</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/10/2015</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of California-Santa Cruz</Name>
<CityName>Santa Cruz</CityName>
<ZipCode>950641077</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>8314595278</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1156 High Street</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>20</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CA20</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>125084723</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF CALIFORNIA, SANTA CRUZ</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>071549000</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of California-Santa Cruz]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>950641077</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>20</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CA20</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1189</Code>
<Text>Major Research Instrumentation</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1580</Code>
<Text>Instrumentation &amp; Facilities</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0115</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0116</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2015~400000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2016~140000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><!-- p.p1 {margin: 0.0px 0.0px 14.0px 0.0px; line-height: 17.0px; font: 14.0px Verdana; color: #333333; -webkit-text-stroke: #333333} span.s1 {font-kerning: none} --> <!-- p.p1 {margin: 0.0px 0.0px 14.0px 0.0px; line-height: 17.0px; font: 14.0px Verdana; color: #333333; -webkit-text-stroke: #333333} span.s1 {font-kerning: none} --> <!-- p.p1 {margin: 0.0px 0.0px 14.0px 0.0px; line-height: 17.0px; font: 14.0px Verdana; color: #333333; -webkit-text-stroke: #333333} span.s1 {font-kerning: none} --> <p class="p1"><span class="s1">Geologic, planetary and ocean sciences provide information on Earth processes both past and present, knowledge that can aid projections of Earth&rsquo;s future. These fields rely on the extraction of information from our natural surroundings that includes the chemical and isotopic makeup of Earth materials. This area of study, isotope geochemistry,<span>&nbsp; </span>utilizes the natural isotopic variation of different elements to discover, for example, the origins and age of Earth materials, the history and current mechanisms operating within our oceans and ice caps, or how and when planetary bodies first formed. This NSF funded project supported the purchase and installation of a new Thermal Ionization Mass Spectrometer at the University of California, Santa Cruz (UCSC). This instrument is designed to produce high-precision isotopic measurements on trace metals extracted from naturally occurring materials. The UCSC lab specializes in applications using U-Pb and U-series geochronology. U-Pb geochronologic investigations include applications to meteorites in effort to reconstruct the timing, structure and size of our solar systems&rsquo; earliest forming planetary bodies. Other applications include dating volcanic events to access volcanic hazards as well as the climatic impact of large-scale eruptions in Earth&rsquo;s past. U-series geochronologic investigations are used to probe the processes operating at the base of glaciers. This instrument is also used for applications in ocean and environmental science, anthropology and forensics by using Sr, Pb or Nd isotopic variations as tracers that, for example, track the composition of Earth&rsquo;s oceans in response to tectonic, climatic and biologic changes. The installation of this equipment has supported the research of a number of faculty, post-doctoral and visiting researchers at UCSC. It is also supports the education and training of graduate student researchers and undergraduate assistants.</span></p> <p class="p1">&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 08/08/2018<br>      Modified by: Terrence&nbsp;Blackburn</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[   Geologic, planetary and ocean sciences provide information on Earth processes both past and present, knowledge that can aid projections of Earth?s future. These fields rely on the extraction of information from our natural surroundings that includes the chemical and isotopic makeup of Earth materials. This area of study, isotope geochemistry,  utilizes the natural isotopic variation of different elements to discover, for example, the origins and age of Earth materials, the history and current mechanisms operating within our oceans and ice caps, or how and when planetary bodies first formed. This NSF funded project supported the purchase and installation of a new Thermal Ionization Mass Spectrometer at the University of California, Santa Cruz (UCSC). This instrument is designed to produce high-precision isotopic measurements on trace metals extracted from naturally occurring materials. The UCSC lab specializes in applications using U-Pb and U-series geochronology. U-Pb geochronologic investigations include applications to meteorites in effort to reconstruct the timing, structure and size of our solar systems? earliest forming planetary bodies. Other applications include dating volcanic events to access volcanic hazards as well as the climatic impact of large-scale eruptions in Earth?s past. U-series geochronologic investigations are used to probe the processes operating at the base of glaciers. This instrument is also used for applications in ocean and environmental science, anthropology and forensics by using Sr, Pb or Nd isotopic variations as tracers that, for example, track the composition of Earth?s oceans in response to tectonic, climatic and biologic changes. The installation of this equipment has supported the research of a number of faculty, post-doctoral and visiting researchers at UCSC. It is also supports the education and training of graduate student researchers and undergraduate assistants.         Last Modified: 08/08/2018       Submitted by: Terrence Blackburn]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
