<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Workshop on Intelligent Systems Research to Support Geosciences and EarthCube Mission</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>03/01/2015</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>02/29/2016</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>99999.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>99999</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>05020000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>CSE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>IIS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Information &amp; Intelligent Systems</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Hector Munoz-Avila</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>hmunoz@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924481</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This workshop will serve as a conduit for jump-starting synergistic research advancing  our understanding of the Earth system through innovative cyber-infrastructure that pushes the envelope on information systems research. The workshop will help synthesize a vision and needs for intelligent systems research that will provide new capabilities envisioned by EarthCube to advance geosciences. The workshop will catalyze a community and research agenda in the emerging area of Discovery Informatics grounded on geoscience requirements. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Participants will discuss how to tackle problems in heterogeneous data integration and visualization (e.g., hand-made sketches, aerial imagery, field-data repositories, stakeholder interviews), ontological reasoning with scientific metadata and mathematical models (e.g., representing uncertainty, simulation predictions, evolving theories). The salient themes arising from discussions at the workshop will be articulated in detail in a final workshop report, which will be made available for the broad research community.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>03/23/2015</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>03/23/2015</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.070</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1533930</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Yolanda</FirstName>
<LastName>Gil</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Yolanda Gil</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>gil@isi.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>3108221511</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000215404</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>03/23/2015</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Southern California</Name>
<CityName>Los Angeles</CityName>
<ZipCode>900890001</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2137407762</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>University Park</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[3720 S. Flower St.]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>37</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CA37</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>072933393</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF SOUTHERN CALIFORNIA</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>072933393</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Southern California]]></Name>
<CityName>Los Angeles</CityName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>902926611</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[4676 Admiralty Way, Suite 1001]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>33</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CA33</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7364</Code>
<Text>Info Integration &amp; Informatics</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7495</Code>
<Text>Robust Intelligence</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>8074</Code>
<Text>EarthCube</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7364</Code>
<Text>INFO INTEGRATION &amp; INFORMATICS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7433</Code>
<Text>CyberInfra Frmwrk 21st (CIF21)</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7495</Code>
<Text>ROBUST INTELLIGENCE</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7556</Code>
<Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0115</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2015~99999</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The goal of the Intelligent Systems for Geosciences workshop was to identify avenues for future research on intelligent systems that will result in fundamental new insights in geosciences. Geosciences representatives brought requirements from Earth, ocean, polar, and geospace sciences. Participants from intelligent systems represented fields such as information integration, machine learning, knowledge representation, semantics and metadata, geospatial computing, robotics, visualization, and augmented reality. The workshop built on the momentum of the NSF EarthCube initiative for geosciences and was informed by ongoing cyberinfrastructure efforts.&nbsp;</p> <p>Many aspects of geosciences research pose novel problems for intelligent systems research. Geoscience data is interesting to computer scientists because it tends to be uncertain, intermittent, sparse, multi-resolution, and multi-scale. Geosciences processes and objects often have amorphous spatio-temporal boundaries. The lack of ground truth makes model evaluation, testing, and comparison difficult.&nbsp; Overcoming these challenges would greatly benefit the geosciences and would require breakthroughs in intelligent systems.</p> <p>Workshop participants agreed that in order to address these challenges new research is required in intelligent and information systems, including:</p> <ul> <li><strong>Knowledge representation</strong>: Capturing scientific knowledge to represent our understanding of geoscience processes will push the limits of the state of the art.</li> <li><strong>Sensing and robotics</strong>: New data collection capabilities that leverage scientific knowledge for optimized data collection and adaptive sampling. </li> <li><strong>Information integration</strong>: Geosciences data and models need to be interconnected and easy to manipulate in an integrated system of systems.&nbsp; </li> <li><strong>Machine learning</strong>: Algorithms need to identify and incorporate appropriate constraints as required by the governing geosciences processes.&nbsp; </li> <li><strong>Intelligent user interfaces</strong>: Interactions must be guided by the geoscience questions that provide context for the content to be conveyed. </li> </ul> <p>All these areas cannot be investigated separately as they are interdependent.&nbsp; For example, improvements in sensing will facilitate learning, deeper representations of data will facilitate information integration, and richer learning algorithms will lead to better interfaces.</p> <p>Recommendations from the workshop include: 1) Interdisciplinary community building through sustained multi-year collaborations; 2) Educating and building awareness of computer scientists and geoscientists in each other&rsquo;s fields, and 3) Establishing direct partnerships between intelligent systems and geoscience researchers. Participants noted that these activities will result in innovations in both intelligent systems and geosciences.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 07/19/2016<br>      Modified by: Yolanda&nbsp;Gil</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The goal of the Intelligent Systems for Geosciences workshop was to identify avenues for future research on intelligent systems that will result in fundamental new insights in geosciences. Geosciences representatives brought requirements from Earth, ocean, polar, and geospace sciences. Participants from intelligent systems represented fields such as information integration, machine learning, knowledge representation, semantics and metadata, geospatial computing, robotics, visualization, and augmented reality. The workshop built on the momentum of the NSF EarthCube initiative for geosciences and was informed by ongoing cyberinfrastructure efforts.   Many aspects of geosciences research pose novel problems for intelligent systems research. Geoscience data is interesting to computer scientists because it tends to be uncertain, intermittent, sparse, multi-resolution, and multi-scale. Geosciences processes and objects often have amorphous spatio-temporal boundaries. The lack of ground truth makes model evaluation, testing, and comparison difficult.  Overcoming these challenges would greatly benefit the geosciences and would require breakthroughs in intelligent systems.  Workshop participants agreed that in order to address these challenges new research is required in intelligent and information systems, including:  Knowledge representation: Capturing scientific knowledge to represent our understanding of geoscience processes will push the limits of the state of the art. Sensing and robotics: New data collection capabilities that leverage scientific knowledge for optimized data collection and adaptive sampling.  Information integration: Geosciences data and models need to be interconnected and easy to manipulate in an integrated system of systems.   Machine learning: Algorithms need to identify and incorporate appropriate constraints as required by the governing geosciences processes.   Intelligent user interfaces: Interactions must be guided by the geoscience questions that provide context for the content to be conveyed.    All these areas cannot be investigated separately as they are interdependent.  For example, improvements in sensing will facilitate learning, deeper representations of data will facilitate information integration, and richer learning algorithms will lead to better interfaces.  Recommendations from the workshop include: 1) Interdisciplinary community building through sustained multi-year collaborations; 2) Educating and building awareness of computer scientists and geoscientists in each otherÆs fields, and 3) Establishing direct partnerships between intelligent systems and geoscience researchers. Participants noted that these activities will result in innovations in both intelligent systems and geosciences.          Last Modified: 07/19/2016       Submitted by: Yolanda Gil]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
