<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Exploring Joint Modeling Approaches for Longitudinal Data: Parsimonious Correlation Modeling and Discrete Observations</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2015</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>38101.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>38101</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>04050000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>SBE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>SES</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Divn Of Social and Economic Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Cheryl Eavey</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>ceavey@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927269</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This research project will develop statistical methods and models for regression analysis for longitudinal data with discrete variables.  Longitudinal studies increasingly are conducted in the social and economic sciences, and these studies often include data with discrete (for example, yes or no) variables.  However, methods for incorporating the correlations between repeated measurements for discrete data are more challenging and remain less explored.  This project will develop more effective and convenient ways for incorporating data information about correlations between the repeated measurements in longitudinal studies.  The project will advance the current state of knowledge regarding statistical methods for longitudinal data modeling and their applications in multiple social and economic sciences areas.  Software will be developed and made publicly available.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project will develop a statistical framework that effectively incorporates correlations between repeated measurements for analyzing a broad class of discrete longitudinal data.  The first major focus of the project will be on a new unconstrained parametrization for the correlation matrices of general correlated and/or clustered data.  This unconstrained parametrization for regression analysis will be parsimonious, flexible, and scientifically and practically interpretable.  The second focus of the project will target the joint distributions of the discrete longitudinal variable.  A regression analysis framework will be constructed by using an innovative copula model whose correlation parameters are represented by the unconstrained parametrization.  This new framework for analyzing discrete categorical longitudinal data generally will be applicable for a broad class of discrete variables.  Theoretical and empirical studies will be carried out for justifying the validity and merits of the new framework.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/25/2015</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/25/2015</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.075</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1533956</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Cheng Yong</FirstName>
<LastName>Tang</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Cheng Yong Tang</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>yongtang@temple.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2152043191</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000632548</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/25/2015</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Temple University</Name>
<CityName>Philadelphia</CityName>
<ZipCode>191226003</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2157077547</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1801 N. Broad Street</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Pennsylvania</StateName>
<StateCode>PA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>PA02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>057123192</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>TEMPLE UNIVERSITY-OF THE COMMONWEALTH SYSTEM OF HIGHER EDUCATION</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>057123192</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Temple University]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>PA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>191226083</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Pennsylvania</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>PA02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1333</Code>
<Text>Methodology, Measuremt &amp; Stats</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9179</Code>
<Text>GRADUATE INVOLVEMENT</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0115</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2015~38101</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>&nbsp;</p> <p>Longitudinal data are commonly encountered in numerous areas including biomedical science, social science, economics, and beyond. The signature feature of longitudinal data is the dependence/correlation between the observations from the same subject. Incorporating the dependence is the key for understanding the mechanism governing the scientific scenarios, and assessing treatment effect, predicting future outcomes, and etc. In many longitudinal studies, many discrete variables are observed such as the symptoms, recurrence counts, and etc. &nbsp;How to describe the dependence/correlations between the discrete observations is an equally important problem for investigations associated with longitudinal studies.</p> <p>The PI successfully developed a new framework for adaptively incorporating broad information in modeling the correlation structure of the longitudinal observations. The new framework has broaden the scope of existing modeling approaches by directly targeting at the correlation matrix itself. Direct evaluation of the impacts from explanatory variables can now be conducted for the measures of the same subject. The PI has made substantial progress on scientifically justifying the validity and practically interpretability of the new modeling approaches for the dependence between longitudinal measurements.</p> <p>The new framework developed by the PI has provided practitioners with a new tool for better understanding the dependence between the repeated measurements in their data set. In the publications from the supported research, it has been demonstrated to be informative and useful. During the two years supported by the award, the PI has 2 papers published, 3 papers accepted for publications, 3 papers in the reviewing process. In terms of dissemination activities, the PI presented his research work at 16 domestic and international conferences as invited speakers. The software for implementing the new approaches has been made available to the public via the PI&rsquo;s research webpage.</p> <p>The PI has devoted serious effort in integrating research into education, especially at the graduate teaching and students advising. The topic of the supported research has been introduced in multiple graduate courses. PhD students are involved in the research activities for developing new theory and method in preparing their dissertations. One PhD student is expected to graduate in spring 2018, and another two PhD students are making good progress of their research work, among them one female student is from the under-represented group in the STEM areas.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 11/27/2017<br>      Modified by: Cheng Yong&nbsp;Tang</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[    Longitudinal data are commonly encountered in numerous areas including biomedical science, social science, economics, and beyond. The signature feature of longitudinal data is the dependence/correlation between the observations from the same subject. Incorporating the dependence is the key for understanding the mechanism governing the scientific scenarios, and assessing treatment effect, predicting future outcomes, and etc. In many longitudinal studies, many discrete variables are observed such as the symptoms, recurrence counts, and etc.  How to describe the dependence/correlations between the discrete observations is an equally important problem for investigations associated with longitudinal studies.  The PI successfully developed a new framework for adaptively incorporating broad information in modeling the correlation structure of the longitudinal observations. The new framework has broaden the scope of existing modeling approaches by directly targeting at the correlation matrix itself. Direct evaluation of the impacts from explanatory variables can now be conducted for the measures of the same subject. The PI has made substantial progress on scientifically justifying the validity and practically interpretability of the new modeling approaches for the dependence between longitudinal measurements.  The new framework developed by the PI has provided practitioners with a new tool for better understanding the dependence between the repeated measurements in their data set. In the publications from the supported research, it has been demonstrated to be informative and useful. During the two years supported by the award, the PI has 2 papers published, 3 papers accepted for publications, 3 papers in the reviewing process. In terms of dissemination activities, the PI presented his research work at 16 domestic and international conferences as invited speakers. The software for implementing the new approaches has been made available to the public via the PI?s research webpage.  The PI has devoted serious effort in integrating research into education, especially at the graduate teaching and students advising. The topic of the supported research has been introduced in multiple graduate courses. PhD students are involved in the research activities for developing new theory and method in preparing their dissertations. One PhD student is expected to graduate in spring 2018, and another two PhD students are making good progress of their research work, among them one female student is from the under-represented group in the STEM areas.          Last Modified: 11/27/2017       Submitted by: Cheng Yong Tang]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
