<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Forensic Science Research Evaluation Workshop; AAAS-Washington, D.C.; May 26-27, 2015</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>05/01/2015</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>04/30/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>47537.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>47537</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>04010000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>SBE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>SMA</Abbreviation>
<LongName>SBE Off Of Multidisciplinary Activities</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Mark Fiegener</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Forensics is a burgeoning field of importance to national security and law enforcement. New technology and scientific advancements allow for more sophisticated analysis of forensic data yet there are no standards for evaluating the reliability of new methods and to determine their usefulness as forensic evidence.  Improving the quality of forensic analyses should result in a higher degree of efficiently and appropriately analyzed evidence. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This workshop has the objective to improve capability within the forensic science community for greater scientific rigor in analytical methods. The workshop will bring together twenty highly reputed forensic science practitioners, research scientists, statisticians and policy makers to discuss the current shortcomings and to recommend ways to most effectively evaluate the forensic science literature. The speakers will contribute to a report that will be published and disseminated by the National Institute of Justice (NIJ).</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>04/28/2015</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>04/28/2015</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.075</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1533843</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Edward</FirstName>
<LastName>Bartick</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Edward Bartick</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>ebartick@gwu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON/>
<NSF_ID>000690242</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/28/2015</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>George Washington University</Name>
<CityName>Washington</CityName>
<ZipCode>200520086</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2029940728</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1922 F Street NW</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[4th Floor]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>District of Columbia</StateName>
<StateCode>DC</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>00</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>DC00</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>043990498</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>GEORGE WASHINGTON UNIVERSITY, THE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>043990498</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[The George Washington University]]></Name>
<CityName>Washington</CityName>
<StateCode>DC</StateCode>
<ZipCode>200071150</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[2100 Foxhall Road, NW]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>District of Columbia</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>00</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>DC00</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1392</Code>
<Text>Biological Anthropology</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7626</Code>
<Text>SciSIP-Sci of Sci Innov Policy</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>NX59</Code>
<Text/>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1392</Code>
<Text>Biological Anthropology</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7626</Code>
<Text>SCIENCE OF SCIENCE POLICY</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8819</Code>
<Text>Forensic Science</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9179</Code>
<Text>GRADUATE INVOLVEMENT</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0114</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0115</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2015~47537</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><div style="text-align: center;"> <p><strong>Forensic Science Research Evaluation Workshop</strong>,</p> <p>AAAS Headquarters, Washington, D.C. May 26-27, 2015.</p> <p>NSF Award No. 1533848.</p> <p>Edward G. Bartick, P.I., McKenzie A. Floyd, Rapporteur</p> <p>George Washington University</p> <p>Washington, DC</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p style="text-align: left;">The National Academies of Science published a report in 2009 (1), and as one of the major conclusions, they have indicated the lack of rigorous research within most of the forensic science disciplines. In order to overcome this problem, the workshop was formed with the following goals in mind.</p> <p style="text-align: left;">1. Conduct a one and one half day workshop on the evaluation of forensic science research at the headquarters of the American Association for the Advancement of Science, 2. Schedule seventeen participants from academia, forensic science practice, and the legal profession, to speak for 1/2 hr. sessions in three categories. These categories are: I. Experimental Design and Statistics, II.&nbsp;Interpretation and Assessment and III.&nbsp;Policy Implications. Each section will be followed by a discussion period.</p> <p style="text-align: left;">A. Each participant was to write up a four to five page essay on their topic and a booklet compiling the essays (chapters).</p> <p style="text-align: left;">B. Print and digitize the final booklet?.</p> <p style="text-align: left;">C. Make the booklet available on-line to all who can benefit from its contents.</p> <p style="text-align: left;">All of the goals were accomplished. The PDF is in the form of a 115 page booklet and is available to anyone on-line through the Department of Justice, Office of Justice Programs, National institute of Justice, Washington, DC 2016,&nbsp;<span style="text-decoration: underline;">https://www.ncjrs.gov/pdffiles1/nij/250088.pdf</span><span style="text-decoration: underline;"> </span><span style="text-decoration: underline;">.</span>&nbsp;The booklet is entitled:&nbsp;<strong>Forensic Science Research and Evaluation Workshop: A Discussion on the Fundamentals of Research Design and an Evaluation of Available Literature</strong>. The booklet may be used as a personal guide or a course guide to understand the principles of conducting and evaluating research regarding forensic science or science in general.&nbsp;</p> <p style="text-align: left;">Reference:</p> <p style="text-align: left;">1. Committee on Identifying the Needs of the Forensic Sciences Community, National Research Council.&nbsp;<em>Strengthening Forensic Science in the United States: A Path Forward,</em>&nbsp;Washington, DC: The National Academies Press, 2009.</p> </div> <p style="text-align: left;">&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 07/19/2017<br>      Modified by: Edward&nbsp;Bartick</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[  Forensic Science Research Evaluation Workshop,  AAAS Headquarters, Washington, D.C. May 26-27, 2015.  NSF Award No. 1533848.  Edward G. Bartick, P.I., McKenzie A. Floyd, Rapporteur  George Washington University  Washington, DC    The National Academies of Science published a report in 2009 (1), and as one of the major conclusions, they have indicated the lack of rigorous research within most of the forensic science disciplines. In order to overcome this problem, the workshop was formed with the following goals in mind. 1. Conduct a one and one half day workshop on the evaluation of forensic science research at the headquarters of the American Association for the Advancement of Science, 2. Schedule seventeen participants from academia, forensic science practice, and the legal profession, to speak for 1/2 hr. sessions in three categories. These categories are: I. Experimental Design and Statistics, II. Interpretation and Assessment and III. Policy Implications. Each section will be followed by a discussion period. A. Each participant was to write up a four to five page essay on their topic and a booklet compiling the essays (chapters). B. Print and digitize the final booklet?. C. Make the booklet available on-line to all who can benefit from its contents. All of the goals were accomplished. The PDF is in the form of a 115 page booklet and is available to anyone on-line through the Department of Justice, Office of Justice Programs, National institute of Justice, Washington, DC 2016, https://www.ncjrs.gov/pdffiles1/nij/250088.pdf . The booklet is entitled: Forensic Science Research and Evaluation Workshop: A Discussion on the Fundamentals of Research Design and an Evaluation of Available Literature. The booklet may be used as a personal guide or a course guide to understand the principles of conducting and evaluating research regarding forensic science or science in general.  Reference: 1. Committee on Identifying the Needs of the Forensic Sciences Community, National Research Council. Strengthening Forensic Science in the United States: A Path Forward, Washington, DC: The National Academies Press, 2009.          Last Modified: 07/19/2017       Submitted by: Edward Bartick]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
