<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>SBIR Phase II:  Prospect: A Hardware Security Verification Tool</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/15/2015</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>02/28/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>749846.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>1159815</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07070000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>IIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Industrial Innovation &amp; Partnersh</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Peter Atherton</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>patherto@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032928772</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The broader impact/commercial potential of this Small Business Innovation Research (SBIR) Phase II project is a dramatic increase in the security of modern computer hardware. This project presents a security verification software suite that detects security vulnerabilities in electronic hardware designs. Current state-of-the-art methods for detecting security vulnerabilities in hardware designs are very informal, consisting of security teams searching for these vulnerabilities through manual code review and committee discussion. This has already been shown to be ineffective in obtaining adequate security coverage, with security vulnerabilities remaining undetected and exploitable by malicious entities. With the unprecedented growth in the number of connected devices being developed for the Internet-of-Things (IoT), the number of security vulnerabilities will increase dramatically. The broader societal impact of this SBIR Phase II project is the increased security of computing systems, leading to more effective management of personal information and increased data privacy. The commercial impact is a unique software offering to semiconductor companies to help detect and prevent security vulnerabilities that could be used to compromise an IoT device. This greatly reduces the resources necessary to achieve high security coverage and eliminates long-term liabilities that can debilitate an entire company.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This Small Business Innovation Research (SBIR) Phase II project focuses on the technical development of a software suite for verifying security properties of hardware designs. The technology improves on the current methods in semiconductor companies that use manual audits in attempts to find security vulnerabilities in chip designs. It provides a systematic platform for verifying the security properties specified by the security teams on the actual hardware within these companies. This greatly improves the security coverage while reducing the time spent performing security audits. This SBIR Phase II project will develop the features requested directly by customers and perform the essential R&amp;D efforts of the company's underlying information flow analysis technology in order to adequately solve customers' problems. The end result of this Phase II project will be a commercial grade product fit to detect and resolve security issues in modern electronic hardware designs.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>09/10/2015</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/11/2017</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1534602</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Jason</FirstName>
<LastName>Oberg</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>K</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Jason K Oberg</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>jason@tortugalogic.com</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>8086357604</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000647316</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/10/2015</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Tortuga Logic, Inc.</Name>
<CityName>San Diego</CityName>
<ZipCode>921062412</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>8086357604</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>3231 Hill Street</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>52</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CA52</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>078848932</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>TORTUGA LOGIC, INC.</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Tortuga Logic, Inc.]]></Name>
<CityName>San Diego</CityName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>921018201</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[101 W. Broadway #200]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>52</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CA52</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1591</Code>
<Text>STTR Phase II</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>5373</Code>
<Text>SBIR Phase II</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>165E</Code>
<Text>SBIR Phase IIB</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>169E</Code>
<Text>SBIR Tech Enhan Partner (TECP)</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>5373</Code>
<Text>SMALL BUSINESS PHASE II</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8033</Code>
<Text>Hardware Software Integration</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8240</Code>
<Text>SBIR/STTR CAP</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0115</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0116</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0117</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2015~749846</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2016~159969</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2017~250000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><strong>Summary</strong></p> <p>Microelectronics in both the commercial and aerospace/defense markets have been the focus of attacks. Exploits have successfully taken advantage of hardware bugs, low level software/firmware vulnerabilities, weaknesses in the supply chain, and trust in the microelectronic designs themselves.</p> <p>This project's primary focus was to create the groundwork for a security verification framework to address microelectronics security concerns. Specifically, this project focused on productizing Tortuga Logic's patented technologies to make the security analysis of both commercial and aerospace/defense microelectronics readily accessible.</p> <p><strong>&nbsp;</strong></p> <p><strong>Intellectual Merit</strong></p> <p>Tortuga Logic's technology and approaches stem back to a long legacy of fundamental research performed at the University of California, Santa Barbara and the University of California, San Diego with funding support from the National Science Foundation. Tortuga Logic was formed to commercialize this long legacy of technologies and address the growing hardware security concerns in the commercial and aerospace/defense markets. Throughout this project, Tortuga Logic has created several commercially available products, patents, and conference publications and presentations.</p> <p><strong>&nbsp;</strong></p> <p><strong>Broader Impacts</strong></p> <p>Concerns about the security of United States' microelectronics continue to grow. Hardware exploits and attacks on the microelectronics supply chain continue to successfully compromising the trust in both commercial and government systems. The outcomes of this project have broad impacts that will bolster the security and trust of microelectronics and reduce the likelihood of exploits that cause harm, financial loss, or national security risks. &nbsp;&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 12/19/2018<br>      Modified by: Jason&nbsp;K&nbsp;Oberg</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Summary  Microelectronics in both the commercial and aerospace/defense markets have been the focus of attacks. Exploits have successfully taken advantage of hardware bugs, low level software/firmware vulnerabilities, weaknesses in the supply chain, and trust in the microelectronic designs themselves.  This project's primary focus was to create the groundwork for a security verification framework to address microelectronics security concerns. Specifically, this project focused on productizing Tortuga Logic's patented technologies to make the security analysis of both commercial and aerospace/defense microelectronics readily accessible.     Intellectual Merit  Tortuga Logic's technology and approaches stem back to a long legacy of fundamental research performed at the University of California, Santa Barbara and the University of California, San Diego with funding support from the National Science Foundation. Tortuga Logic was formed to commercialize this long legacy of technologies and address the growing hardware security concerns in the commercial and aerospace/defense markets. Throughout this project, Tortuga Logic has created several commercially available products, patents, and conference publications and presentations.     Broader Impacts  Concerns about the security of United States' microelectronics continue to grow. Hardware exploits and attacks on the microelectronics supply chain continue to successfully compromising the trust in both commercial and government systems. The outcomes of this project have broad impacts that will bolster the security and trust of microelectronics and reduce the likelihood of exploits that cause harm, financial loss, or national security risks.             Last Modified: 12/19/2018       Submitted by: Jason K Oberg]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
