<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Enhancing Learning of Science Categories Through Guidance of Psychological Models of Classification</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/15/2015</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2020</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>946386.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>946386</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>11040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>EHR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DUE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Undergraduate Education</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Gregg Solomon</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>gesolomo@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032928333</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>A ubiquitous component of science education is learning the key categories of each target domain.  This project, a multidisciplinary collaboration of cognitive scientists, geologists, and science education researchers at Indiana University and Washington University, will take basic research findings on human learning and attempt to develop diagnostic tools that can be matched with instructional technique to facilitate the learning of scientific classifications. Rock categorization will be used as the example target domain because it provides challenges that are representative of scientific classification learning more generally, but the training insights that are generated should be applicable across multiple scientific domains.  A critical practical issue in education research concerns how to explore the vast space of possible instructional variations.  A key advantage of the project is that the researchers will delimit that space by testing specific hypotheses, drawn from successful formal models of human classification learning combined with principles from the training literature, about how content should be delivered to optimize learning of scientific classifications. The researchers will derive novice and expert representations of rock classifications, including the dimensions they attend to. This work bridges laboratory-based mathematical modeling research with more applied research: Instruction using real rocks in authentic learning situations will be contrasted with instruction delivered over computers. Principles that the researchers discover in comparisons of experts and novices should be useful in the development of diagnostic tools for future applications in the classroom and the field. The project fits centrally into the EHR Core Research (ECR) program goal of conducted funamental research and building enduring research foundations for STEM learning.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The studies will entail fundamental scaling work to derive psychological similarity representations for the rock stimuli. Derivation of these representations is a prerequisite for rigorous application of the models of classification that will guide the subsequent empirical training studies. These representations will also provide important insights concerning the major psychological dimensions along which the rock stimuli are organized as well as how the rock category distributions are configured in the multidimensional similarity space. These student representations will be contrasted with those derived from expert geologists. It is highly likely that the experts will have learned to focus attention on dimensions that are far mor ediagnostic than those used by the students. Empirical investigations of these different multidimensional solutions should yield important information regarding fundamental parameters for how most efficiently to support students' learning of the rock categories. These include identifying: i) the optimal training instances to support learning and generalization, ii) the optimal sequencing of these training instances, and iii) the preferred training density for particular subtypes of hierarchically organized category distributions.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>09/09/2015</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>09/09/2015</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.076</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1534014</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Robert</FirstName>
<LastName>Nosofsky</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>M</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Robert M Nosofsky</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>nosofsky@indiana.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>8128552534</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000182476</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/09/2015</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Bruce</FirstName>
<LastName>Douglas</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>J</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Bruce J Douglas</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>douglasb@indiana.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>8128553848</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000114633</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/09/2015</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Mark</FirstName>
<LastName>McDaniel</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Mark McDaniel</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>markmcdaniel@wustl.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>3148895100</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000528315</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/09/2015</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Indiana University</Name>
<CityName>Bloomington</CityName>
<ZipCode>474013654</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>3172783473</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>509 E 3RD ST</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Indiana</StateName>
<StateCode>IN</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>09</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>IN09</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>006046700</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>TRUSTEES OF INDIANA UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>006046700</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Indiana University]]></Name>
<CityName>Bloomington</CityName>
<StateCode>IN</StateCode>
<ZipCode>474013654</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[509 E 3rd Street]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Indiana</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>09</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>IN09</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7980</Code>
<Text>ECR-EHR Core Research</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9178</Code>
<Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0415</Code>
<Name>NSF Education &amp; Human Resource</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040106</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2015~946386</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The goal of the project was to use formal models of human classification to guide the search for teaching methods that will enhance the learning and generalization of science categories.&nbsp; The example target domain was rock classification in geology.&nbsp;</p> <p>There is an enormous number of different strategies that might be applied in teaching categories in science classes. &nbsp;&nbsp;A critical practical issue concerns how to organize empirical inquiries to explore the vast space of possible instructional variations. &nbsp;&nbsp;Our proposal was to use successful formal models of human category learning to simulate the outcome of alternative instructional strategies.&nbsp; We would then focus empirical investigations on those instructional policies that the models predicted to be the most promising.&nbsp; &nbsp;</p> <p>Although the idea is a promising one in principle, major steps are needed for its successful implementation.&nbsp; Although there has been sophisticated development of formal models of human category learning in cognitive science, most applications and tests have taken place in simplified domains involving low-dimensional stimuli and artificially-constructed categories.&nbsp; In this project, the goal was to scale up the application of the models to a real-world, natural-category domain involving complex, high-dimensional objects.&nbsp; Thus, extensive work was needed to extend the models and to characterize the high-dimensional spaces in which the category objects are embedded.&nbsp;&nbsp; In the senses described above, the goals of the project were a two-way street:&nbsp;&nbsp; Formal models would be applied in this rocks domain to generate predictions of optimal instructional strategies; the results from laboratory experiments would be used to test the models? predictions; and further model building would take place in light of the experimental results.&nbsp; Once a satisfactory level of predictive precision was achieved in the cognitive-psychology laboratory, then translation could take place to real-world educational settings.</p> <p>The work conducted in this project turned out to be among the most ambitious attempts in the field to scale up the application of formal psychological models of classification to complex, high-dimensional natural categories found in the real world.&nbsp;&nbsp; First, extensive work was conducted to construct the high-dimensional similarity spaces in which the rocks are embedded.&nbsp; This work made use of a variety of complementary methods, including multidimensional scaling approaches, direct dimension ratings, and modern deep-learning technology.&nbsp; The resulting ?rock-feature space? embeds a very large sample of major types of igneous, metamorphic, and sedimentary rocks in a space composed of roughly 20 dimensions, each dimension having a natural psychological interpretation.&nbsp; Second, when used in combination with this derived high-dimensional rock-feature space, a formal exemplar model of classification provided excellent accounts of category learning and generalization in numerous experiments conducted in this domain.&nbsp;&nbsp; According to the model, people learn and represent categories by storing numerous training examples of the categories in memory, and classify novel test items based on their similarity to the stored training examples.&nbsp; The model proved capable of predicting with high accuracy the probability with which learners classified individual rock samples into a variety of alternative categories, and how performance varied with manipulation of fundamental variables related to category structure and instruction policies.</p> <p>Under the guidance of the model, we discovered a variety of instruction policies that significantly improved our participants? ability to learn to identify and classify rock samples into the categories established in the geologic sciences.&nbsp; One such technique involved use of variable training instances that ?covered? the statistical distributions that defined the rock categories in the high-dimensional rock-feature space.&nbsp; This technique contrasts with ones in which the teacher focuses on use of only centrally located training instances that are the prototypes of their categories.&nbsp; A second technique that proved highly beneficial was use of feature highlighting, in which diagnostic features of the rocks were explicitly described and pictorially illustrated during the training sessions.&nbsp; This technique promoted use of selective attention to diagnostic dimensions, a core principle of the exemplar model of classification.&nbsp; Third, in accord with the predictions from the exemplar model, we discovered that students? ability to learn to classify rock samples into high-level superordinate categories was enhanced if they were required to simultaneously learn to classify the samples into more specific subtype categories.</p> <p>Overall, the research provides a good example of how formal theory and practice in education research can proceed in tandem, with each component informing and enhancing the other.&nbsp; It also provides a good example of synergistic advances that can be achieved through collaborative efforts between researchers from cognitive science and discipline-based education research.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 10/12/2020<br>      Modified by: Robert&nbsp;M&nbsp;Nosofsky</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The goal of the project was to use formal models of human classification to guide the search for teaching methods that will enhance the learning and generalization of science categories.  The example target domain was rock classification in geology.   There is an enormous number of different strategies that might be applied in teaching categories in science classes.   A critical practical issue concerns how to organize empirical inquiries to explore the vast space of possible instructional variations.   Our proposal was to use successful formal models of human category learning to simulate the outcome of alternative instructional strategies.  We would then focus empirical investigations on those instructional policies that the models predicted to be the most promising.     Although the idea is a promising one in principle, major steps are needed for its successful implementation.  Although there has been sophisticated development of formal models of human category learning in cognitive science, most applications and tests have taken place in simplified domains involving low-dimensional stimuli and artificially-constructed categories.  In this project, the goal was to scale up the application of the models to a real-world, natural-category domain involving complex, high-dimensional objects.  Thus, extensive work was needed to extend the models and to characterize the high-dimensional spaces in which the category objects are embedded.   In the senses described above, the goals of the project were a two-way street:   Formal models would be applied in this rocks domain to generate predictions of optimal instructional strategies; the results from laboratory experiments would be used to test the models? predictions; and further model building would take place in light of the experimental results.  Once a satisfactory level of predictive precision was achieved in the cognitive-psychology laboratory, then translation could take place to real-world educational settings.  The work conducted in this project turned out to be among the most ambitious attempts in the field to scale up the application of formal psychological models of classification to complex, high-dimensional natural categories found in the real world.   First, extensive work was conducted to construct the high-dimensional similarity spaces in which the rocks are embedded.  This work made use of a variety of complementary methods, including multidimensional scaling approaches, direct dimension ratings, and modern deep-learning technology.  The resulting ?rock-feature space? embeds a very large sample of major types of igneous, metamorphic, and sedimentary rocks in a space composed of roughly 20 dimensions, each dimension having a natural psychological interpretation.  Second, when used in combination with this derived high-dimensional rock-feature space, a formal exemplar model of classification provided excellent accounts of category learning and generalization in numerous experiments conducted in this domain.   According to the model, people learn and represent categories by storing numerous training examples of the categories in memory, and classify novel test items based on their similarity to the stored training examples.  The model proved capable of predicting with high accuracy the probability with which learners classified individual rock samples into a variety of alternative categories, and how performance varied with manipulation of fundamental variables related to category structure and instruction policies.  Under the guidance of the model, we discovered a variety of instruction policies that significantly improved our participants? ability to learn to identify and classify rock samples into the categories established in the geologic sciences.  One such technique involved use of variable training instances that ?covered? the statistical distributions that defined the rock categories in the high-dimensional rock-feature space.  This technique contrasts with ones in which the teacher focuses on use of only centrally located training instances that are the prototypes of their categories.  A second technique that proved highly beneficial was use of feature highlighting, in which diagnostic features of the rocks were explicitly described and pictorially illustrated during the training sessions.  This technique promoted use of selective attention to diagnostic dimensions, a core principle of the exemplar model of classification.  Third, in accord with the predictions from the exemplar model, we discovered that students? ability to learn to classify rock samples into high-level superordinate categories was enhanced if they were required to simultaneously learn to classify the samples into more specific subtype categories.  Overall, the research provides a good example of how formal theory and practice in education research can proceed in tandem, with each component informing and enhancing the other.  It also provides a good example of synergistic advances that can be achieved through collaborative efforts between researchers from cognitive science and discipline-based education research.          Last Modified: 10/12/2020       Submitted by: Robert M Nosofsky]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
