<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>The 2015 John Barrett Memorial Lectures</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>03/15/2015</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>02/29/2016</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>10000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>10000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DMS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Tomek Bartoszynski</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>tbartosz@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924885</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The 2015 Barrett Lectures will be held May 13-16, 2015 at the University of Tennessee in Knoxville, Tennessee. This year's conference, entitled, "Stochastic filtering, Computations and Applications" will focus on exciting developments of stochastic filtering and its computational implementations and applications. Stochastic filtering has experienced a rapid development in recent years due to its flexibility to engage modeling predictions based on pertinent dynamics with experimental data. Moreover, complex physical phenomena and formidable engineering problems related to big data lead to an urgent need for new theoretical establishments of filtering and novel computational implementations. The conference will feature, Dan Crisan, Tom Kurtz and Boris Rozovsky, who will each present three expository lectures within the realm of the thematic topic of the Lectures. Additionally, invited plenary talks by a dynamic group of international researchers at different stages of their career development and a poster session will take place. This project utilizes NSF funding to support travel and other participant costs for approximately 40 participants, giving high priority to graduate students, postdoctoral scholars, and early career faculty members.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The 2015 Barrett Lectures will be the 45th installment of a highly regarded lecture series that began as a tribute to the distinguished scientist John H. Barrett, head of our Mathematics Department at the time of his death in 1969. The Lectures are one of the longest-standing series of mathematical lectures in the country delivered by distinguished speakers. The focus of the 45th Lectures is the interdisciplinary impact of other mathematical methods into traditional topics of probability, and the increasing interdisciplinary penetration of complex physical phenomena and formidable engineering problems related to big data. A dynamic group of auspicious and prominent researchers will deliver talks and engage in discussions to deepen our understanding of the new stochastic filtering methodologies and theories which need to be further developed in order to meet the challenge of new complex scientific and engineering problems of the 21st century. The link of the conference will be available at http://www.math.utk.edu/barrett/</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>03/06/2015</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>03/06/2015</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1534641</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Jan</FirstName>
<LastName>Rosinski</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Jan Rosinski</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>rosinski@math.utk.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>8659744309</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000361352</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>03/06/2015</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Jie</FirstName>
<LastName>Xiong</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Jie Xiong</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>jxiong@math.utk.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>8659744271</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000249905</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>03/06/2015</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Vasileios</FirstName>
<LastName>Maroulas</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Vasileios Maroulas</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>vmaroula@utk.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>8659743466</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000608067</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>03/06/2015</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Tennessee Knoxville</Name>
<CityName>Knoxville</CityName>
<ZipCode>379163801</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>8659743466</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1331 CIR PARK DR</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Tennessee</StateName>
<StateCode>TN</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>TN02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>003387891</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF TENNESSEE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>003387891</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Tennessee Knoxville]]></Name>
<CityName>Knoxville</CityName>
<StateCode>TN</StateCode>
<ZipCode>379960003</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Tennessee</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>TN02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1263</Code>
<Text>PROBABILITY</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7556</Code>
<Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0115</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2015~10000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><div class="page" title="Page 1"> <div class="layoutArea"> <div class="column"> <p><span>This NSF project provided a portion of participant expenses for the 2015 John Barrett Memorial Lectures, sponsored by the Department of Mathematics of the University of Tennessee. The Lectures, entitled "</span>Stochastic filtering, Computations and Applications," focused on exciting research developments of filtering and their applications. This stimulating four-day conference, organized by Vasileios Maroulas (Chair), Jan Rosinski and Jie Xiong, was held May 13-16, 2015 at the University of Tennessee, Knoxville, TN.&nbsp;</p> <p>The meeting featured leading researchers, Dan Crisan (Imperial College) and Tom Kurtz (University of Wisconsin), who each gave a two-talk main lecture series.&nbsp;<span>Plenary lectures were delivered by a diverse group of researchers, from senior researchers to young faculty and postdocs. Additionally, the meeting included a poster session, and time for informal discussions and collaborations.</span></p> <p><span><span>Participants discussed cutting-edge developments of stochastic filtering and investigated the theory&rsquo;s future developments in association with the computational difficulties of high dimensional data and complex physical phenomena or difficult&nbsp;engineering or scientific problems related to big data. All participants shared their diverse perspectives on problems of mutual interest. A tiny sample of key words from the titles illustartes the broad spectrum of these talks: "</span></span>stochastic global optimization", "rare event simulation", "compressed signal dynamics", &nbsp;"exchangeable branching processes and model selection", "Levy information", "dynamic spatiotemporal processes", "financial ultra-high frequency data", "implicit filter", "uncertainties in geosciences, physics, and engineering", and "multi-scale assimilation for oceans".</p> <div class="page" title="Page 1"> <div class="layoutArea"> <div class="column"> <p><span>The conference brought together researchers from a variety of backgrounds, but it also encouraged interactions among researchers who are at a variety of stages in their careers, including <span>2 Hispanic, 6 female, 2 of African descent, 14 graduate students, 8 postdocs and 7 young faculty (Assistant Professor level or equivalent)</span>. Thanks in part to the NSF funding, we were able to support participants from several institutions across the US as well as bringing some international speakers. This provided for the training and professional development of many early-career mathematicians who learned from and interacted with an international slate of highly regarded researchers.&nbsp;</span></p> </div> </div> </div> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p><span><br /></span></p> <p>&nbsp;</p> </div> </div> </div> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 04/05/2016<br>      Modified by: Vasileios&nbsp;Maroulas</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[    This NSF project provided a portion of participant expenses for the 2015 John Barrett Memorial Lectures, sponsored by the Department of Mathematics of the University of Tennessee. The Lectures, entitled "Stochastic filtering, Computations and Applications," focused on exciting research developments of filtering and their applications. This stimulating four-day conference, organized by Vasileios Maroulas (Chair), Jan Rosinski and Jie Xiong, was held May 13-16, 2015 at the University of Tennessee, Knoxville, TN.   The meeting featured leading researchers, Dan Crisan (Imperial College) and Tom Kurtz (University of Wisconsin), who each gave a two-talk main lecture series. Plenary lectures were delivered by a diverse group of researchers, from senior researchers to young faculty and postdocs. Additionally, the meeting included a poster session, and time for informal discussions and collaborations.  Participants discussed cutting-edge developments of stochastic filtering and investigated the theoryÆs future developments in association with the computational difficulties of high dimensional data and complex physical phenomena or difficult engineering or scientific problems related to big data. All participants shared their diverse perspectives on problems of mutual interest. A tiny sample of key words from the titles illustartes the broad spectrum of these talks: "stochastic global optimization", "rare event simulation", "compressed signal dynamics",  "exchangeable branching processes and model selection", "Levy information", "dynamic spatiotemporal processes", "financial ultra-high frequency data", "implicit filter", "uncertainties in geosciences, physics, and engineering", and "multi-scale assimilation for oceans".     The conference brought together researchers from a variety of backgrounds, but it also encouraged interactions among researchers who are at a variety of stages in their careers, including 2 Hispanic, 6 female, 2 of African descent, 14 graduate students, 8 postdocs and 7 young faculty (Assistant Professor level or equivalent). Thanks in part to the NSF funding, we were able to support participants from several institutions across the US as well as bringing some international speakers. This provided for the training and professional development of many early-career mathematicians who learned from and interacted with an international slate of highly regarded researchers.                          Last Modified: 04/05/2016       Submitted by: Vasileios Maroulas]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
