<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Assessing the Impact of Organizational Justice on Academic Entrepreneurship: Qualitative and Quantitative Evidence From University Scientists</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2015</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>263439.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>263439</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>04010000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>SBE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>SMA</Abbreviation>
<LongName>SBE Off Of Multidisciplinary Activities</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Cassidy Sugimoto</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Universities have established technology transfer offices (TTOs) to manage the commercialization of intellectual property arising from federally-funded research. Faculty members who patent, license, or form a new company based on this intellectual property are directed to work through the university TTO, a process of formal technology transfer.  However, some academic scientists choose to circumvent or bypass the university TTO and engage in informal technology transfer. The objective of this project is to obtain new evidence on the determinants of informal technology transfer. It provides useful insights for university administrators and policymakers who govern universities. An understanding of what induces informal technology transfer can help institutions adopt effective policies to support academic entrepreneurship and also develop an organizational climate that is more conducive to formal technology transfer. The project has further important implications for initiatives designed to stimulate startup formation by faculty and student entrepreneurs, such as the NSF I-Corps program.   &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This research addresses key limitations of prior studies of academic. The focus is the individual faculty member, who is the source of innovation and potential entrepreneurship. This research examines key psychological variables that are relevant to individuals and the decision to work with the university TTO.  Specifically, we examine efforts on the part of TTOs to educate faculty regarding academic entrepreneurship, championing behavior by university administrators (e.g., university presidents who are especially enthusiastic about academic entrepreneurship), and faculty perceptions of fairness and equity (i.e., organizational justice).  This is the first study to apply principles of organizational justice to university technology transfer. We use both quantitative and qualitative methods. We conduct several detailed case studies, and more broadly, survey faculty members at 35 universities. The combined use of data on individuals, academic departments, universities, and the surrounding regions of sampled universities, enables a comprehensive perspective on informal technology transfer.  &lt;br/&gt;</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/06/2015</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/06/2015</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.075</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1534324</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>David</FirstName>
<LastName>Waldman</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>A</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>David A Waldman</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>waldman@asu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>4809655690</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000344307</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/06/2015</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Donald</FirstName>
<LastName>Siegel</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>S</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Donald S Siegel</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>donald.siegel.1@asu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6024961101</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000069955</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/06/2015</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Arizona State University</Name>
<CityName>TEMPE</CityName>
<ZipCode>852816011</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>4809655479</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>ORSPA</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[660 South Mill Avenue, Suite 310]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Arizona</StateName>
<StateCode>AZ</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>09</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>AZ09</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>943360412</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>ARIZONA STATE UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>806345658</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Arizona State University]]></Name>
<CityName>Tempe</CityName>
<StateCode>AZ</StateCode>
<ZipCode>852876011</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[P.O. Box 876011]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Arizona</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>09</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>AZ09</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7626</Code>
<Text>SciSIP-Sci of Sci Innov Policy</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7626</Code>
<Text>SCIENCE OF SCIENCE POLICY</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0115</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2015~263439</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>A great deal was accomplished as a result of this grant. Our findings clearly demonstrate that issues of organizaional justice, or perceptions of workplace fairness, matter, in the context of academic entreprenurship. Faculty who are being treated fairly by their universities are more likely to engage in technology transfer and less likely to "bypass" the university. We also find that entrepreneurial identity and prosocial motivation amplify and attenuate, respectively, the relationship between justice perceptions and academic entrepreneurship. As such, we provide insights into justice sensitivity in the context of academic entrepreneurship.</p> <p>Key accomplishments:</p> <p>1)&nbsp; Presentation of our initial qualitative findings at the Academy of Management Meetings in Anaheim, CA in August 2016.. These findings were presented in a showcase session for <em>Academy of Management Perspectives</em> (2016 SSCI Impact Factor of 4.943) on &ldquo;The Commercialization of Science: An Integrative Research Agenda on Managing the Science-Business Interfaces.&rdquo; At the time, the paper we presented was titled &ldquo;Assessing the Antecedents and Consequences of Academic Entrepreneurship: The Role of Micro/OB Factors.&rdquo; We then formally submitted this article to the journal.</p> <p>2) Published article: Balven, R., Fenters, V., Siegel, D., &amp; Waldman, D. A. 2018. Academic entrepreneurship: The roles of organizational justice, championing, education, work-life balance, identity, and motivation. <em>Academy of Management Perspectives</em>, 32: 1&ndash;22.</p> <p>3) Professor Siegel also presented the above article at SUNY-Stony Brook in September 2016, Rochester Institute of Technology in April 2017, and the University of Connecticut in May 2017.&nbsp;</p> <p>4) The first round of our survey of faculty, department chairs, and technology transfer personnel was conducted in the summer of 2016.&nbsp; For our initial survey in the summer of 2016, we contacted about 20,000 academic scientists, physicians and engineers via email. Of those contacted, 1,983 individuals responded, and approximately half of them (i.e., about 1000) indicated that they would be willing to answer a follow-up survey.&nbsp; In this first round, we asked a series of questions on four aspects of organizational justice.&nbsp;&nbsp; First, <em>distributive</em> <em>justice</em> constitutes the extent to which an individual&rsquo;s compensation for a commercialized innovation is perceived to be in line with his or her effort and accomplishment; for instance, through the use of an adequate royalty distribution formula. Second, <em>procedural justice </em>characterizes the extent to which an individual perceives organizational decision-making processes pertaining to UITT to be consistent and free of bias. Third, <em>interpersonal justice</em> describes the perceived relationship between an individual and the TTO. A connection that is characterized by respect and dignity would thus be considered as high on this dimension. Finally, <em>informational justice </em>describes the extent to which individuals feel that decisions and outcomes are explained individually, thoroughly and timely by the TTO. It is important to note that distributive justice constitutes an outcome-oriented dimension of justice, whereas the other dimensions of justice are process-oriented.&nbsp; We also asked questions regarding three different forms of university technology transfer: (1) formal, (2) informal, and (3) consulting. We define formal technology transfer as working with the TTO to commercialize your research; informal technology transfer as bypassing the university and its formal mechanisms of commercialization; and consulting as part-time activities directly with private companies.</p> <p>5) One of the key themes that emerged from the qualitative analysis of the interviews that we conducted in the previous fiscal year, 2015-2016, at the University at Albany, SUNY Polytechnic, and Arizona State University, was the importance of identity (e.g., entrepreneurial identity) in academic entrepreneurship. Thus, we engaged in a new round of interview data collection with an emphasis on identity issues. As compared to our earlier interviews, are target sample of interviewees specifically entailed scientists and engineers. We initially conducted interviews at John Hopkins University in March 2017, and we delved further into identity issues during those interviews (Virgil Fenters and Don Siegel conducted these interviews). Additional interviews with a more specific focus on identity were conducted in late 2017 and early 2018 at Stanford, UC-Davis, Colorado State, and University of Colorado at Boulder. In total, approximately 60 additional interviews were conducted in this phase of our research.</p> <p>6) Waldman, D. A., Balven, R., Vaulont, M., Rupp, D., &amp; Siegel, D. Academic entrepreneurship and organizational justice: A target similarity perspective. Submitted to <em>Administrative Science Quarterly</em>.</p> <p>7) Fenters, V., Balven, R., Ashforth, B., Waldman, D. A., &amp; Siegel, D. Identity hierarchies of academic entrepreneurs&nbsp; (to be submitted to&nbsp;&nbsp;<em>Academy of Management Journal</em>..&nbsp;</p> <p>8)&nbsp; A key outcome of the grant was the NSF workshop on Organizational Issues in Technology Transfer at Federal Labs, which was targeted to academics, editors of leading academic journals, and technology transfer managers at federal labs.&nbsp; &nbsp;&nbsp;</p> <p><strong>&nbsp;</strong></p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 09/01/2018<br>      Modified by: Donald&nbsp;S&nbsp;Siegel</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ A great deal was accomplished as a result of this grant. Our findings clearly demonstrate that issues of organizaional justice, or perceptions of workplace fairness, matter, in the context of academic entreprenurship. Faculty who are being treated fairly by their universities are more likely to engage in technology transfer and less likely to "bypass" the university. We also find that entrepreneurial identity and prosocial motivation amplify and attenuate, respectively, the relationship between justice perceptions and academic entrepreneurship. As such, we provide insights into justice sensitivity in the context of academic entrepreneurship.  Key accomplishments:  1)  Presentation of our initial qualitative findings at the Academy of Management Meetings in Anaheim, CA in August 2016.. These findings were presented in a showcase session for Academy of Management Perspectives (2016 SSCI Impact Factor of 4.943) on "The Commercialization of Science: An Integrative Research Agenda on Managing the Science-Business Interfaces." At the time, the paper we presented was titled "Assessing the Antecedents and Consequences of Academic Entrepreneurship: The Role of Micro/OB Factors." We then formally submitted this article to the journal.  2) Published article: Balven, R., Fenters, V., Siegel, D., &amp; Waldman, D. A. 2018. Academic entrepreneurship: The roles of organizational justice, championing, education, work-life balance, identity, and motivation. Academy of Management Perspectives, 32: 1&ndash;22.  3) Professor Siegel also presented the above article at SUNY-Stony Brook in September 2016, Rochester Institute of Technology in April 2017, and the University of Connecticut in May 2017.   4) The first round of our survey of faculty, department chairs, and technology transfer personnel was conducted in the summer of 2016.  For our initial survey in the summer of 2016, we contacted about 20,000 academic scientists, physicians and engineers via email. Of those contacted, 1,983 individuals responded, and approximately half of them (i.e., about 1000) indicated that they would be willing to answer a follow-up survey.  In this first round, we asked a series of questions on four aspects of organizational justice.   First, distributive justice constitutes the extent to which an individual?s compensation for a commercialized innovation is perceived to be in line with his or her effort and accomplishment; for instance, through the use of an adequate royalty distribution formula. Second, procedural justice characterizes the extent to which an individual perceives organizational decision-making processes pertaining to UITT to be consistent and free of bias. Third, interpersonal justice describes the perceived relationship between an individual and the TTO. A connection that is characterized by respect and dignity would thus be considered as high on this dimension. Finally, informational justice describes the extent to which individuals feel that decisions and outcomes are explained individually, thoroughly and timely by the TTO. It is important to note that distributive justice constitutes an outcome-oriented dimension of justice, whereas the other dimensions of justice are process-oriented.  We also asked questions regarding three different forms of university technology transfer: (1) formal, (2) informal, and (3) consulting. We define formal technology transfer as working with the TTO to commercialize your research; informal technology transfer as bypassing the university and its formal mechanisms of commercialization; and consulting as part-time activities directly with private companies.  5) One of the key themes that emerged from the qualitative analysis of the interviews that we conducted in the previous fiscal year, 2015-2016, at the University at Albany, SUNY Polytechnic, and Arizona State University, was the importance of identity (e.g., entrepreneurial identity) in academic entrepreneurship. Thus, we engaged in a new round of interview data collection with an emphasis on identity issues. As compared to our earlier interviews, are target sample of interviewees specifically entailed scientists and engineers. We initially conducted interviews at John Hopkins University in March 2017, and we delved further into identity issues during those interviews (Virgil Fenters and Don Siegel conducted these interviews). Additional interviews with a more specific focus on identity were conducted in late 2017 and early 2018 at Stanford, UC-Davis, Colorado State, and University of Colorado at Boulder. In total, approximately 60 additional interviews were conducted in this phase of our research.  6) Waldman, D. A., Balven, R., Vaulont, M., Rupp, D., &amp; Siegel, D. Academic entrepreneurship and organizational justice: A target similarity perspective. Submitted to Administrative Science Quarterly.  7) Fenters, V., Balven, R., Ashforth, B., Waldman, D. A., &amp; Siegel, D. Identity hierarchies of academic entrepreneurs  (to be submitted to  Academy of Management Journal..   8)  A key outcome of the grant was the NSF workshop on Organizational Issues in Technology Transfer at Federal Labs, which was targeted to academics, editors of leading academic journals, and technology transfer managers at federal labs.              Last Modified: 09/01/2018       Submitted by: Donald S Siegel]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
