<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>DMREF: Exploring multi-functional molecular electronic materials</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/15/2015</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>1200000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>1200000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03090000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CHE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Chemistry</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Anne-Marie Schmoltner</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>aschmolt@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924716</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>With this award, the Designing Materials to Revolutionize and Engineer our Future (DMREF) Program of the Division of Chemistry and the Division of Materials Research is funding Professors Hai-Ping Cheng, George Christou, and Xiaoguang Zhang at the University of Florida to study how to make magnetic materials with some of the smallest dimensions possible. Magnetic materials are important for the electronics industry and the ongoing trend towards miniaturization of devices, has made the development of ever-smaller magnets essential. The team is studying what are termed single-molecule magnets; these are individual molecules that function as magnets yet are smaller than those of traditional magnetic materials. The team is using advanced computational methods to predict which structures will yield the optimal magnetic properties and they are also studying ways to attach the single-molecule magnets to a surface to introduce certain effects crucial to the potential use of these materials in new technologies. The project is providing multi-disciplinary training to the participating graduate students and postdoctoral researchers, research opportunities for high school students through the University of Florida's Summer Student Training Program, and outreach to the general public through the including "Chemistry Day at the Mall" activity.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The team led by Professor Cheng has demonstrated from first-principles calculations that the quantum capacitance of a small molecule or nanocluster depends upon its magnetic or geometric configuration. In this project they are now focusing on synthesizing high nuclearity manganese carboxylate clusters with various ligands and correlating the structures with the self-capacitance of the clusters and the magnetic field needed for a low-spin state to a high-spin state transition. The group is using first-principles calculations to predict the effects of changing carboxylate ligands on the magnetic states of high nuclearity manganese clusters and the effects of support surfaces (e.g. boron nitride) on the magnetic and electronic properties of these clusters. The systems are being synthesized, and various scanning tunneling microscopy, spectroscopic and electrochemical studies are being used to characterize the "charging" properties of the nanoclusters.  By searching through the three basic "genes," the molecule/cluster, the ligands, and the supporting substrate, the group is quantifying and characterizing how different combinations impact properties, and finding the best combination that produces the largest effect and is most suitable for applications.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>09/05/2015</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>09/05/2015</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1534401</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>George</FirstName>
<LastName>Christou</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>George Christou</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>christou@chem.ufl.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>3523926737</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000291947</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/05/2015</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Hai-Ping</FirstName>
<LastName>Cheng</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Hai-Ping Cheng</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>cheng@qtp.ufl.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>3523926256</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000307254</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/05/2015</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Xiaoguang</FirstName>
<LastName>Zhang</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Xiaoguang Zhang</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>xgz@ufl.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>3523926971</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000667621</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/05/2015</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Florida</Name>
<CityName>GAINESVILLE</CityName>
<ZipCode>326112002</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>3523923516</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1 UNIVERSITY OF FLORIDA</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Florida</StateName>
<StateCode>FL</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>FL03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>969663814</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF FLORIDA</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>159621697</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Florida]]></Name>
<CityName>Gainesville</CityName>
<StateCode>FL</StateCode>
<ZipCode>326110884</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[2001 Museum Street]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Florida</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>FL03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>8292</Code>
<Text>DMREF</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7237</Code>
<Text>NANO NON-SOLIC SCI &amp; ENG AWD</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8037</Code>
<Text>Advanced Manufacturing</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8400</Code>
<Text>DMREF</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9263</Code>
<Text>COMPUTATIONAL SCIENCE &amp; ENGING</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0115</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2015~1200000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The focus of this NSF funded research is to search for and design novel nano-structured, multifunctional molecular electronic materials. Our team consists of computation, theory, and synthesis expertise, and our mission is to understand the functionality of molecules at the fundamental level. Using a state-of-the-art computational approach based on quantum mechanics, we unveiled the path for magnetic interactions between atoms in nano-size building blocks.&nbsp; Guided by computational findings, we synthesized new compounds with desired magnetic properties, thus completing a full cycle of synthesis-computation-understanding-synthesis.</p> <p>When the size of an electronic device decreases to the nanometer scale, an ultimate limit for electronics, classical concepts that we are familiar with are no longer valid. Instead of classical resistors, we must introduce a quantum resistor whose resistance depends up-stream and down-stream current; unlike classical capacitors, a quantum capacitor accounts for extra pieces of energy that do not show in the classical limit. The concept of magnetocapacitance is further introduced to describe the effects of electron spin, which is totally quantum mechanical. Building on fundamental knowledge acquired in our studies, we predicted a spin pump that drives currents with electrons of one type spin.&nbsp; Such a spin current has low dissipation, and a coherent spin current has potential applications in quantum information science.</p> <p>The success of our project illustrates the importance of a combination of high-level quantum mechanical calculation coupled with mesoscale theoretical modeling and synthesis. A computational approaches plays a crucial role in <em>driving</em> the synthesis and characterization, and in identifying which of the large number of possible combinations among nano-cluster molecules and ligands should be targeted and explored as building blocks of functional electronic materials. Our approach is <em>genomic</em>: by searching through the three basic 'genes' - the molecule/cluster, the ligands, and the supporting substrate - we aim to quantify and characterize how different combinations impact properties, and to facilitate finding the best combinations that produces the largest effects and are most suitable for applications. The research is built on a hierarchy of theoretical quantum chemistry approaches, allowing the materials search to start from computationally cheaper methods to cover a broad landscape, with more substantial methods employed to refine physical properties for promising candidates. Our objective and approach fits naturally into the Materials Genome Initiative (MGI).</p> <p>Results from our efforts are of great importance to the development of future electronic applications. Our outcomes also have the potential to impact other important areas such as catalysis and energy storage. The project provides multidisciplinary training to graduate students and postdocs that addresses the modern challenges of a career in science. The PI and co-PI's have actively been involved along a broad front of activities involving education and outreach. We also have organized one NSF-supported workshop as well as DOE-supported focus sessions on magnetic molecules at the Sanibel Symposium for the last three years.</p> <p>&nbsp;<strong>Key words. </strong>Magnetic molecule, cluster, electron-transport, multifunction, ligands.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 12/07/2019<br>      Modified by: Hai-Ping&nbsp;Cheng</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Images (<span id="selectedPhoto0">1</span> of <span class="totalNumber"></span>)           </div> <div class="galControls" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1534401/1534401_10396518_1575411923146_iso_v5--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1534401/1534401_10396518_1575411923146_iso_v5--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Mn8Ce3"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1534401/1534401_10396518_1575411923146_iso_v5--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Mn8Ce3"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Electron orbital (in Wannier representation) responsible for the long-range magnetic interaction in a Mn8Ce3 nano-molecule. Left panel depict an isosurface of the electron density and the right are the contours of a cross section showing a pathway connecting Ce and Mn.</div> <div class="imageCredit">X.-G. Li, Y.-P. Wang, H.-P. Cheng, X.-G. Zhang</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Hai-Ping&nbsp;Cheng</div> <div class="imageTitle">Mn8Ce3</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1534401/1534401_10396518_1575414955623_SpinPump--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1534401/1534401_10396518_1575414955623_SpinPump--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Molecular Spin Pump"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1534401/1534401_10396518_1575414955623_SpinPump--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Molecular Spin Pump"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Adiabatic Spin Pump through a Molecular Antiferromagnet Ce3Mn8III</div> <div class="imageCredit">Jie Gu, Hai-Ping Cheng, Xiaoguang Zhang</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Xiaoguang&nbsp;Zhang</div> <div class="imageTitle">Molecular Spin Pump</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1534401/1534401_10396518_1575756286974_Picture2--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1534401/1534401_10396518_1575756286974_Picture2--rgov-800width.jpg" title="AFM order"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1534401/1534401_10396518_1575756286974_Picture2--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="AFM order"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Diagrammatic representation of the A-type AF and C-type AF spin configurations of an MnIII8 unit. Guided by theory, experimentalists turned the C-type Mn8 to an A-type system.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Thai Son Cao, Hai-Ping Cheng, George Christou</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Hai-Ping&nbsp;Cheng</div> <div class="imageTitle">AFM order</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The focus of this NSF funded research is to search for and design novel nano-structured, multifunctional molecular electronic materials. Our team consists of computation, theory, and synthesis expertise, and our mission is to understand the functionality of molecules at the fundamental level. Using a state-of-the-art computational approach based on quantum mechanics, we unveiled the path for magnetic interactions between atoms in nano-size building blocks.  Guided by computational findings, we synthesized new compounds with desired magnetic properties, thus completing a full cycle of synthesis-computation-understanding-synthesis.  When the size of an electronic device decreases to the nanometer scale, an ultimate limit for electronics, classical concepts that we are familiar with are no longer valid. Instead of classical resistors, we must introduce a quantum resistor whose resistance depends up-stream and down-stream current; unlike classical capacitors, a quantum capacitor accounts for extra pieces of energy that do not show in the classical limit. The concept of magnetocapacitance is further introduced to describe the effects of electron spin, which is totally quantum mechanical. Building on fundamental knowledge acquired in our studies, we predicted a spin pump that drives currents with electrons of one type spin.  Such a spin current has low dissipation, and a coherent spin current has potential applications in quantum information science.  The success of our project illustrates the importance of a combination of high-level quantum mechanical calculation coupled with mesoscale theoretical modeling and synthesis. A computational approaches plays a crucial role in driving the synthesis and characterization, and in identifying which of the large number of possible combinations among nano-cluster molecules and ligands should be targeted and explored as building blocks of functional electronic materials. Our approach is genomic: by searching through the three basic 'genes' - the molecule/cluster, the ligands, and the supporting substrate - we aim to quantify and characterize how different combinations impact properties, and to facilitate finding the best combinations that produces the largest effects and are most suitable for applications. The research is built on a hierarchy of theoretical quantum chemistry approaches, allowing the materials search to start from computationally cheaper methods to cover a broad landscape, with more substantial methods employed to refine physical properties for promising candidates. Our objective and approach fits naturally into the Materials Genome Initiative (MGI).  Results from our efforts are of great importance to the development of future electronic applications. Our outcomes also have the potential to impact other important areas such as catalysis and energy storage. The project provides multidisciplinary training to graduate students and postdocs that addresses the modern challenges of a career in science. The PI and co-PI's have actively been involved along a broad front of activities involving education and outreach. We also have organized one NSF-supported workshop as well as DOE-supported focus sessions on magnetic molecules at the Sanibel Symposium for the last three years.   Key words. Magnetic molecule, cluster, electron-transport, multifunction, ligands.       Last Modified: 12/07/2019       Submitted by: Hai-Ping Cheng]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
