<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>SBIR Phase II:  Novel Compositions for Narrow Bandwidth Light Emitting Diode Phosphors</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2015</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>729689.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>1135625</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07070000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>IIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Industrial Innovation &amp; Partnersh</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Anna Brady-Estevez</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>abrady@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927077</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The broader impact/commercial potential of this Small Business Innovation Research (SBIR) Phase II project is the development of a novel phosphor material system that drives up to a 20% improvement in energy efficiency of phosphor-converted LEDs (pcLEDs) over current state-of-the-art phosphor material systems in nearly all pcLED applications. The market for LED phosphors in 2012 was roughly $500 million and is expected to reach $1.2 billion by 2016. The 20% improvement in the packaged LED efficiency will also trigger a cascade of tangible impacts at the end-product system level such as using fewer LEDs, increasing efficacy (lumens per watt) and mobile device battery life, reducing electronic driver complexity, reducing heat, a thinner form factor, and a far more brilliant color gamut. The anticipated results from this grant will satisfy the 2020 goals for down-converting materials laid out in the U.S. Department of Energy's 2013 Multi-Year Program Plan, bringing these efficacy and efficiency goals and standards to market four years ahead of schedule.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This Small Business Innovation Research Phase II project aims to further develop a novel and proprietary phosphor material system for use in phosphor-converted light-emitting diode (pcLED) applications that will improve pcLED efficacy up to 20%. In display backlighting, 20-40% of the light emitted by the state-of-the-art phosphors miss the sweet spot of the display's color filters resulting in unused light and wasted energy. Similarly, in general lighting approximately 15% of the emitted light falls outside the visible spectrum, again resulting in wasted energy. The technology developed is a phosphor material utilizing a novel chemistry that exhibits a narrow light emission spectrum to increase LED brightness and energy efficiency by 10-20% in display backlighting and up to 15% in general lighting applications. Prototype materials have been synthesized that exhibit a narrow emission peak at target wavelengths, and the next steps include optimization and characterization of the most effective compositions. The anticipated results of this project are narrow-band phosphor materials that exhibit performance and reliability characteristics commensurate with industry standards.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/29/2015</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/30/2017</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1534771</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Jonathan</FirstName>
<LastName>Melman</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Jonathan Melman</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>jonathan@eiematerials.com</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>7328416654</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000646733</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/29/2015</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>EIE Materials, Inc</Name>
<CityName>Lexington</CityName>
<ZipCode>405111209</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>4087990125</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1501 Bull Lea Rd.</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[Suite 105]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Kentucky</StateName>
<StateCode>KY</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>06</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>KY06</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>078818109</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>EIE MATERIALS, INC</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[EIE Materials Inc.]]></Name>
<CityName>Emeryville</CityName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>946082083</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[5980 Horton St.]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>13</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CA13</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>5373</Code>
<Text>SBIR Phase II</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>091E</Code>
<Text>Light generation &amp; detection</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>123E</Code>
<Text>CENTERS: ADVANCED MATERIALS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>165E</Code>
<Text>SBIR Phase IIB</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>169E</Code>
<Text>SBIR Tech Enhan Partner (TECP)</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>5373</Code>
<Text>SMALL BUSINESS PHASE II</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8240</Code>
<Text>SBIR/STTR CAP</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0115</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0116</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0117</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2015~729689</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2016~155937</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2017~249999</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>This Small Business Innovative Research (SBIR) Phase II project aimed to develop novel narrow-bandwidth phosphors for LED applications. The project focused on the development of both narrow-band red and narrow-band green phosphors, the latter being nearly ready for commercial adoption while the former will require further R&amp;D to improve the performance to meet commercial requirements. Consequently, the narrow-band green phosphor (NBG) development was the focus of the SBIR Phase IIB effort. In general lighting, this NBG phosphor gives more vibrant reds and greens, more saturated colors overall, and up to a 10% increase in luminous efficacy of radiation. In displays, this NBG phosphor expands the display gamut coverage by 10-20%.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>By the outset of the Phase IIB project, the NBG phosphor performance had already achieved a significant improvement over current state-of-the-art (SOTA) NBG phosphors. However, the NBG performance lifetime was quite problematic, and therefore the focus of the Phase IIB effort was on improving the stability of the phosphor. The first approach to improving the stability of NBG was to modify the chemical composition. This not only resulted in a dramatic improvement in stability, but also led to a five-fold reduction in NBG green phosphor loading per LED compared to the current SOTA. The second approach to improving the NBG phosphor stability was to apply a barrier coating to the phosphor. This particular class of materials is difficult to achieve a non-porous, thick and uniform coating, but the novel coating chemistry invented during the course of this Phase IIB project resulted in a ten-fold improvement in stability.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>There is still additional coating improvements that need to be made before this NBG phosphor is commercializable. However, this NSF project allowed the Company to advance this game-changing NBG phosphor technology and attract the interest of investors and strategic partners and ultimately result in marketable NBG phosphor product.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 09/15/2018<br>      Modified by: Jonathan&nbsp;Melman</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ This Small Business Innovative Research (SBIR) Phase II project aimed to develop novel narrow-bandwidth phosphors for LED applications. The project focused on the development of both narrow-band red and narrow-band green phosphors, the latter being nearly ready for commercial adoption while the former will require further R&amp;D to improve the performance to meet commercial requirements. Consequently, the narrow-band green phosphor (NBG) development was the focus of the SBIR Phase IIB effort. In general lighting, this NBG phosphor gives more vibrant reds and greens, more saturated colors overall, and up to a 10% increase in luminous efficacy of radiation. In displays, this NBG phosphor expands the display gamut coverage by 10-20%.     By the outset of the Phase IIB project, the NBG phosphor performance had already achieved a significant improvement over current state-of-the-art (SOTA) NBG phosphors. However, the NBG performance lifetime was quite problematic, and therefore the focus of the Phase IIB effort was on improving the stability of the phosphor. The first approach to improving the stability of NBG was to modify the chemical composition. This not only resulted in a dramatic improvement in stability, but also led to a five-fold reduction in NBG green phosphor loading per LED compared to the current SOTA. The second approach to improving the NBG phosphor stability was to apply a barrier coating to the phosphor. This particular class of materials is difficult to achieve a non-porous, thick and uniform coating, but the novel coating chemistry invented during the course of this Phase IIB project resulted in a ten-fold improvement in stability.     There is still additional coating improvements that need to be made before this NBG phosphor is commercializable. However, this NSF project allowed the Company to advance this game-changing NBG phosphor technology and attract the interest of investors and strategic partners and ultimately result in marketable NBG phosphor product.          Last Modified: 09/15/2018       Submitted by: Jonathan Melman]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
