<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Doctoral Dissertation Research: Geographic Dimensions of Local Policy Change Across Different Urban Settings</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2015</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>01/31/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>15579.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>15579</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>04040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>SBE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>BCS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Behavioral and Cognitive Sci</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Thomas Baerwald</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This doctoral dissertation research project will investigate the factors that influence the geographic spread of campaigns for an increased minimum wage across the U.S.  The doctoral student will examine the spatial strategies employed by labor organizations, the variation of these strategies across locations, and the generalized patterns of movement of minimum wage increases as they proliferate throughout the country.  Although focused on the topic of minimum-wage increases, the project will provide new insights and information regarding a broader range of topics by examining the importance of networks, policy context, and the material and discursive power of institutions for the spatial-temporal mobility of policies.  The project will yield new theoretical insights about the strategies of labor organizations as well as an empirical investigation into the practical mechanisms that enable and constrain policy mobility, thereby benefitting both scholars and policy practitioners.   As a Doctoral Dissertation Research Improvement award, this award also will provide support to enable a promising student to establish a strong independent research career.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project will focus three core questions:  (1) How do policy initiatives to increase the minimum wage spread spatially?  (2) What are the spatial strategies employed by labor unions and other labor organizations as they design and implement campaigns to promote increased minimum wage?  (3) How do these campaigns and the wage-related policies vary by location?  The doctoral student will perform a comparative case study of three campaigns for an increase in the minimum-wage rate in the cities of Seattle, Washington; Milwaukee, Wisconsin; and Charlotte, North Carolina.  She will employ participant observation and qualitative interviews to gather relevant data, and she will analyze these data using a grounded theory approach to identify the mechanisms through which policy translation occurs and to trace the spread of recent minimum wage increase efforts throughout the nation.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/14/2015</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/14/2015</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.075</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1535674</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Kim</FirstName>
<LastName>England</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Kim England</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>england@u.washington.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2066852509</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000269614</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/14/2015</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Megan</FirstName>
<LastName>Brown</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>E</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Megan E Brown</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>meb5@uw.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2065434043</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000692176</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/14/2015</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Washington</Name>
<CityName>Seattle</CityName>
<ZipCode>981950001</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2065434043</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>4333 Brooklyn Ave NE</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Washington</StateName>
<StateCode>WA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>WA07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>605799469</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF WASHINGTON</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>042803536</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Field Research]]></Name>
<CityName>Milwaukee</CityName>
<StateCode>WI</StateCode>
<ZipCode>532233215</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[Tower Ave]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Wisconsin</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>WI04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1352</Code>
<Text>Geography and Spatial Sciences</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1352</Code>
<Text>GEOGRAPHY AND SPATIAL SCIENCES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9179</Code>
<Text>GRADUATE INVOLVEMENT</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0115</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2015~15579</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>This project investigated the geographic spread of local campaigns for $15 minimum wages throughout the U.S. In 2012, the idea of a $15 minimum wage was outlandish. By 2017, $15 minimum wages had been passed in multiple municipalities and two of the largest states in the country. Once these and other laws are fully implemented, one fifth of all US workers will be covered by a $15 minimum wage. Notably, the $15 wage movement has been successful in all regions of the country, even breaking a historic firewall that had largely kept pro-worker policies out of the US South. Labor unions, locally-based community groups, local and national policymakers, business owners and organizations, and fast food worker activists have all contributed to the virality of this policy. This project has investigated the explosion of campaigns for $15 minimum wages, tracing the connections that have allowed these campaigns to move and spread throughout the country. In the process, it has contributed to academic debates about the spatial strategies of labor unions and social movements.</p> <p>This project was a three-part case study of campaigns to increase local minimum wages to $15 per hour. Over the course of 9 months of fieldwork, it involved more than 100 interviews, participant observation at more than three-dozen campaign events, and document review of campaign and policy materials. By tracing the connections and disconnections between three disparate sites of $15 wage activism &ndash; Seattle, WA, Chicago, IL, and Greensboro/Durham, NC &ndash; the project analyzed both the processes by which campaigns moved throughout the country and the local conditions that shaped the campaigns in various places. Local campaigns differed in their engagement with broad national conversations about the purpose and functioning of the low-wage labor market, emphasizing critiques of self-improvement embedded in dominant discussions of the labor market, the racialization of the low-wage labor market, or the moral underpinnings of the labor market depending on the locally relevant political and economic environment. Meanwhile, large national labor unions involved in the $15 wage movement utilized various strategies to encourage the spread of these campaigns, including the strategic movement of resources and staff from place to place and the top-down organization of local campaigns, provoking tensions and challenges between different scales of organization. Finally, the importance of the intersections between class-based organizing and gender- or race-centric organizing grew as the campaigns progressed, and took different characteristics depending on location.</p> <p>This project compiled rich qualitative data on local iterations of minimum wage campaigns in three distinct regions of the US, contributing to an understanding of the diversity of strategies and tactics used by policymakers and activists alike when crafting policies. It also contributed to an understanding of the mobility of policies more generally, following one policy as it is translated from place to place, mutating as it travels to account for local specificity. As localities, states, and other political jurisdictions continue to grapple with the decision to increase minimum wage rates, this project increases the understanding of how these decisions reach public agenda, how they are negotiated, and the implications the decisions.&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 04/25/2017<br>      Modified by: Megan&nbsp;E&nbsp;Brown</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ This project investigated the geographic spread of local campaigns for $15 minimum wages throughout the U.S. In 2012, the idea of a $15 minimum wage was outlandish. By 2017, $15 minimum wages had been passed in multiple municipalities and two of the largest states in the country. Once these and other laws are fully implemented, one fifth of all US workers will be covered by a $15 minimum wage. Notably, the $15 wage movement has been successful in all regions of the country, even breaking a historic firewall that had largely kept pro-worker policies out of the US South. Labor unions, locally-based community groups, local and national policymakers, business owners and organizations, and fast food worker activists have all contributed to the virality of this policy. This project has investigated the explosion of campaigns for $15 minimum wages, tracing the connections that have allowed these campaigns to move and spread throughout the country. In the process, it has contributed to academic debates about the spatial strategies of labor unions and social movements.  This project was a three-part case study of campaigns to increase local minimum wages to $15 per hour. Over the course of 9 months of fieldwork, it involved more than 100 interviews, participant observation at more than three-dozen campaign events, and document review of campaign and policy materials. By tracing the connections and disconnections between three disparate sites of $15 wage activism &ndash; Seattle, WA, Chicago, IL, and Greensboro/Durham, NC &ndash; the project analyzed both the processes by which campaigns moved throughout the country and the local conditions that shaped the campaigns in various places. Local campaigns differed in their engagement with broad national conversations about the purpose and functioning of the low-wage labor market, emphasizing critiques of self-improvement embedded in dominant discussions of the labor market, the racialization of the low-wage labor market, or the moral underpinnings of the labor market depending on the locally relevant political and economic environment. Meanwhile, large national labor unions involved in the $15 wage movement utilized various strategies to encourage the spread of these campaigns, including the strategic movement of resources and staff from place to place and the top-down organization of local campaigns, provoking tensions and challenges between different scales of organization. Finally, the importance of the intersections between class-based organizing and gender- or race-centric organizing grew as the campaigns progressed, and took different characteristics depending on location.  This project compiled rich qualitative data on local iterations of minimum wage campaigns in three distinct regions of the US, contributing to an understanding of the diversity of strategies and tactics used by policymakers and activists alike when crafting policies. It also contributed to an understanding of the mobility of policies more generally, following one policy as it is translated from place to place, mutating as it travels to account for local specificity. As localities, states, and other political jurisdictions continue to grapple with the decision to increase minimum wage rates, this project increases the understanding of how these decisions reach public agenda, how they are negotiated, and the implications the decisions.                    Last Modified: 04/25/2017       Submitted by: Megan E Brown]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
