<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Doctoral Dissertation Research: Environmental Governance and the Emergence of Ecosystem-Based Fisheries Management</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/15/2015</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>15750.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>15750</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>04040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>SBE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>BCS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Behavioral and Cognitive Sci</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Antoinette WinklerPrins</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>anwinkle@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927266</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This project analyzes the governance of the New England groundfish fishery through the emergence of Ecosystem-based Fisheries Management (EBFM), focusing on how science and management function together in a network of ecological, social, and economic relationships. Despite the application of the best science available to guide management practices, stock assessments for several species are at record lows and socioeconomic impacts are rippling through the sector. A transition from management based on single stock assessments to EBFM, which takes into account the biophysical dynamics of the marine environment and incorporates socio-ecological dimensions into conceptualization of the ecosystem, is an opportunity to address interrelated and underrepresented fishery processes. Among supporters of EBFM, tensions exist about the best way to move forward because stakeholders analyze the fishery in different ways depending on their roles and their epistemological approaches to understanding the fishery. Scientific uncertainty, rapidly changing environmental conditions, and variable market dynamics require participatory and adaptive management strategies that reconcile disciplinary and epistemological divisions. This project will identify areas where conflicting epistemologies are straining collaboration and action and determine ways to attenuate or resolve these conflicts. It will provide insights into the contradictions that hinder understanding and areas where economic, social, and conservation agendas potentially converge. Although this research aims to capture the complexity of the New England groundfish fishery specifically, it has potential to provide insights for the management of similar fishery crises throughout the world. Further, this work has implications for implementation of ecosystems based management paradigms more generally.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project addresses three overarching research questions: 1) How do ongoing scientific and social processes, based on the emergence of EBFM, construct the ecosystem as a category for governance? 2) How do place-specific ecological, social, and economic relationships mediate and produce outcomes from the processes and practices of fisheries science and management? 3) How can this analysis advance our understanding of natural resource policy and management?  Through ethnography and discourse analysis, this research examines the spaces where actors come together to produce management plans and will utilize observations of management and research lab meetings, interviews with fisheries scientists, and contextualized evaluation of popular media, industry publications, management plans, and legislation. The analysis integrates methods from political ecology and political economy, Socio-ecological Systems (SES) theory and the Global Production Networks approach to analyze the coupling of ecological and social-economic systems within the fisheries sector.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/13/2015</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>12/11/2017</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.075</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1535960</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Cindi</FirstName>
<LastName>Katz</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>R</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Cindi R Katz</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>ckatz@gc.cuny.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2128178728</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000155040</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>12/11/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>James</FirstName>
<LastName>Biles</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>James Biles</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>jbiles@ccny.cuny.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2126505969</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000539504</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/13/2015</StartDate>
<EndDate>12/11/2017</EndDate>
<RoleCode>Former Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Catherine</FirstName>
<LastName>King</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Catherine King</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>cking3@gradcenter.cuny.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2128177523</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000674151</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/13/2015</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>CUNY Graduate School University Center</Name>
<CityName>New York</CityName>
<ZipCode>100164309</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2128177526</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>365 Fifth Avenue</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>12</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NY12</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>620128194</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>RESEARCH FOUNDATION OF THE CITY UNIVERSITY OF NEW YORK</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>073268849</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[CUNY Graduate School University Center]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<ZipCode>100164309</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>12</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NY12</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1352</Code>
<Text>Geography and Spatial Sciences</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1352</Code>
<Text>GEOGRAPHY AND SPATIAL SCIENCES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9179</Code>
<Text>GRADUATE INVOLVEMENT</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0115</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2015~15750</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>This research employed analytical approaches of environmental geography to investigate the emergence of ecosystems-based fisheries management (EBFM) for New England's marine fisheries in the context of the "crisis" that is escalating in its groundfish fishery. It investigates how multi-scalar and interactive processes and relationships constrain or facilitate innovative efforts to improve the functioning of the fishery. Through observing the practices of fisheries scientists in coordination with managers at the New England Fisheries Management Council (NEFMC), I analyzed how knowledge is produced and employed for the production of science-based fisheries regulations. I focused on these spaces of interaction between science and management observing how specific actors and institutions function together as a dynamic network to negotiate environmental governance. Positioning this analysis to emphasize the political ecology and political economy of the fishery contributes a better understanding of environmental management interventions as emergent constructions produced by networks of associations, and not strictly as policy prescriptions by experts on ecology and socio-economics. While fisheries scientists, economists, and managers must understand and engage social scientific analysis in order to participate in this science/management policy space, limitations on time and training do not allow for in-depth assessments of how their own epistemological biases and institutionalized practices affect their contributions to science-based policy.</p> <p>Prior to funding from the NSF DDRI grant, this research project included attendance at fisheries meetings on the early stages of the formation of the Ecosystems-based Fisheries Management (EBFM) Committee in the NEFMC.&nbsp; With this grant award, the outcomes of this research were further developed by the opportunity to closely follow the creation of an example Fisheries Management Plan (eFEP), from its early planning stages through recent work.&nbsp; Using ethnographic methods and document analysis, I observed the processes of making and framing of resource policy as it takes place through scientific and socio-economic research, industry and community input, and political deliberations. Through this research, I argue that efforts and hopes placed in EBFM to resolve the groundfish fishery crisis need to include the probability that ontological complexity requires us to learn how to live with the changing dynamics of socio-ecological networks, rather than trying to control them too rigidly to meet our interpretation of a balanced socio-economic system. Although EBFM is considered a radical shift away from single-species management that is failing the fishery, institutionalized processes and practices may continue to presume that the collapsing groundfish fishery can be saved by exerting more effort to model the complexity to predict future values. Ecosystems-based management theory emphasizes that uncertainty and complexity in linked socioecological systems are poorly addressed by solutions that require controllable and predictable objects for management; EBFM implementation strategies in New England must explicitly address this issue, otherwise problems that this management intervention seeks to resolve may be perpetuated. Explicit pathways need to be forged for integrating relevant qualitative social theory and the myriad of non-economic social and cultural values into management to meet several of other socio-ecological tenets and objectives invoked by EBFM theory.</p> <p>&nbsp;A salient case study of the New England groundfish fishery provides an opportunity to address the current crisis and contribute to knowledge that is needed to build more robust governance with Ecosystem-based Fisheries Management. Moving beyond analysis of the fishery as a set of formal and informal institutions and human interactions to more fully incorporate the contributions of the biophysical entities and processes helps us to understand how the political and cultural matters and practices of power affect the construction of knowledge about the nature of the fishery itself &ndash; and nature, more generally. Although this research captured the specificities of the EBFM science-based management intervention for the New England fishery, the findings bring awareness to the affects of the processes and practices of other fisheries councils seeking to create their own versions of EBFM, and for ocean governance in general. Overexploited and depleted marine fish stocks are concerns across the globe; pollution, ocean acidification, habitat degradation, and climate change add to the issues impacting fisheries worldwide that must be addressed by managing ocean spaces as ecosystems with collaboration of affected industries and communities, concerned citizens, researchers, and policy makers. The scholarly research from this project targets a range of academic disciplines that address fisheries issues, including geography, anthropology, ecology, marine policy, and planning. These research experiences and theoretical insights on fisheries science and management will continue to inform the interdisciplinary courses that I create and teach in geography, earth sciences, and environmental studies.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 04/01/2018<br>      Modified by: Catherine&nbsp;King</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Images (<span id="selectedPhoto0">1</span> of <span class="totalNumber"></span>)           </div> <div class="galControls" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1535960/1535960_10376040_1522628909829_IMG_1671--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1535960/1535960_10376040_1522628909829_IMG_1671--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Port City of New Bedford, MA"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1535960/1535960_10376040_1522628909829_IMG_1671--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Port City of New Bedford, MA"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">New Bedford is the highest grossing port in the nation due primarily to the scallop fishery.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Catherine King</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Catherine&nbsp;King</div> <div class="imageTitle">Port City of New Bedford, MA</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1535960/1535960_10376040_1522628754954_LegalizeFreedom--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1535960/1535960_10376040_1522628754954_LegalizeFreedom--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Seafood processing plant, Point Judith, RI."><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1535960/1535960_10376040_1522628754954_LegalizeFreedom--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Seafood processing plant, Point Judith, RI."></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">The Political Ecology of Fisheries: National political rhetoric and debates affect regional management of fisheries.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Catherine King</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Catherine&nbsp;King</div> <div class="imageTitle">Seafood processing plant, Point Judith, RI.</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1535960/1535960_10376040_1522629029455_IMG_1113--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1535960/1535960_10376040_1522629029455_IMG_1113--rgov-800width.jpg" title="International Seafood Expo, Boston, MA"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1535960/1535960_10376040_1522629029455_IMG_1113--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="International Seafood Expo, Boston, MA"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">New England fisheries as part of a global production network</div> <div class="imageCredit">Catherine King</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Catherine&nbsp;King</div> <div class="imageTitle">International Seafood Expo, Boston, MA</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1535960/1535960_10376040_1522629279807_IMG_1006--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1535960/1535960_10376040_1522629279807_IMG_1006--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Maine Fishermen's Forum, Rockport, ME"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1535960/1535960_10376040_1522629279807_IMG_1006--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Maine Fishermen's Forum, Rockport, ME"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Annual 5-day gathering of New England fishing community members, scientists, managers, and other stakeholders and their families at the Samoset Resort that includes professional, educational, and social events.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Catherine King</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Catherine&nbsp;King</div> <div class="imageTitle">Maine Fishermen's Forum, Rockport, ME</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1535960/1535960_10376040_1522629403987_codplush--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1535960/1535960_10376040_1522629403987_codplush--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Groundfish plushes"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1535960/1535960_10376040_1522629403987_codplush--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Groundfish plushes"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Groundfish including cod, haddock, and yellowtail flounder, are significant to the identity (and tourist industry) of New England</div> <div class="imageCredit">Catherine King</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Catherine&nbsp;King</div> <div class="imageTitle">Groundfish plushes</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ This research employed analytical approaches of environmental geography to investigate the emergence of ecosystems-based fisheries management (EBFM) for New England's marine fisheries in the context of the "crisis" that is escalating in its groundfish fishery. It investigates how multi-scalar and interactive processes and relationships constrain or facilitate innovative efforts to improve the functioning of the fishery. Through observing the practices of fisheries scientists in coordination with managers at the New England Fisheries Management Council (NEFMC), I analyzed how knowledge is produced and employed for the production of science-based fisheries regulations. I focused on these spaces of interaction between science and management observing how specific actors and institutions function together as a dynamic network to negotiate environmental governance. Positioning this analysis to emphasize the political ecology and political economy of the fishery contributes a better understanding of environmental management interventions as emergent constructions produced by networks of associations, and not strictly as policy prescriptions by experts on ecology and socio-economics. While fisheries scientists, economists, and managers must understand and engage social scientific analysis in order to participate in this science/management policy space, limitations on time and training do not allow for in-depth assessments of how their own epistemological biases and institutionalized practices affect their contributions to science-based policy.  Prior to funding from the NSF DDRI grant, this research project included attendance at fisheries meetings on the early stages of the formation of the Ecosystems-based Fisheries Management (EBFM) Committee in the NEFMC.  With this grant award, the outcomes of this research were further developed by the opportunity to closely follow the creation of an example Fisheries Management Plan (eFEP), from its early planning stages through recent work.  Using ethnographic methods and document analysis, I observed the processes of making and framing of resource policy as it takes place through scientific and socio-economic research, industry and community input, and political deliberations. Through this research, I argue that efforts and hopes placed in EBFM to resolve the groundfish fishery crisis need to include the probability that ontological complexity requires us to learn how to live with the changing dynamics of socio-ecological networks, rather than trying to control them too rigidly to meet our interpretation of a balanced socio-economic system. Although EBFM is considered a radical shift away from single-species management that is failing the fishery, institutionalized processes and practices may continue to presume that the collapsing groundfish fishery can be saved by exerting more effort to model the complexity to predict future values. Ecosystems-based management theory emphasizes that uncertainty and complexity in linked socioecological systems are poorly addressed by solutions that require controllable and predictable objects for management; EBFM implementation strategies in New England must explicitly address this issue, otherwise problems that this management intervention seeks to resolve may be perpetuated. Explicit pathways need to be forged for integrating relevant qualitative social theory and the myriad of non-economic social and cultural values into management to meet several of other socio-ecological tenets and objectives invoked by EBFM theory.   A salient case study of the New England groundfish fishery provides an opportunity to address the current crisis and contribute to knowledge that is needed to build more robust governance with Ecosystem-based Fisheries Management. Moving beyond analysis of the fishery as a set of formal and informal institutions and human interactions to more fully incorporate the contributions of the biophysical entities and processes helps us to understand how the political and cultural matters and practices of power affect the construction of knowledge about the nature of the fishery itself &ndash; and nature, more generally. Although this research captured the specificities of the EBFM science-based management intervention for the New England fishery, the findings bring awareness to the affects of the processes and practices of other fisheries councils seeking to create their own versions of EBFM, and for ocean governance in general. Overexploited and depleted marine fish stocks are concerns across the globe; pollution, ocean acidification, habitat degradation, and climate change add to the issues impacting fisheries worldwide that must be addressed by managing ocean spaces as ecosystems with collaboration of affected industries and communities, concerned citizens, researchers, and policy makers. The scholarly research from this project targets a range of academic disciplines that address fisheries issues, including geography, anthropology, ecology, marine policy, and planning. These research experiences and theoretical insights on fisheries science and management will continue to inform the interdisciplinary courses that I create and teach in geography, earth sciences, and environmental studies.          Last Modified: 04/01/2018       Submitted by: Catherine King]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
