<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Collaborative Research: Multi-Perspective Evacuation Performance Measurement</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2015</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2020</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>152352.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>190775</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CMMI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Civil, Mechanical, &amp; Manufact Inn</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Walter Peacock</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>wpeacock@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922634</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>If successful, the research will provide a point of departure from current viewpoints on evacuation planning by representing an evacuation as a network composed of transportation and household perspectives by considering systems, and systems containing processes linked through performance metrics. Given that the information and data of this research will be grounded in household responses and transportation occurrences calibrated in realistic scenarios suggests that the derived performance targets could be more readily incorporated by both transportation agencies and households. Project funding will support a minimum of one University of Delaware School of Public Policy and Administration Summer Scholar. The PIs will develop age appropriate activities for middle to high school students to participate in camps at Virginia Tech sponsored through the Center for Enhancement of Engineering Diversity. In terms of under-represented groups, a PI will seek to fund and recruit a student through the William A. Anderson Fund, a 501c.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The research approach begins with the assertion that "performance" is a socio-technical process that requires both scientific measurement and an understanding of social systems that empower, inform, and constrain views on what makes a good or bad evacuation. The research approach requires unpacking the basic phenomena of evacuation and rethinking how good or bad outcomes of that phenomenon are evaluated and measured. This suggests that it is neither appropriate to use a single performance measure nor to consider only a single point of view. This research adapts and augments dynamic network performance measurement approaches to conceptualize and model the relationships between transportation agencies and households and the performance of these groups as a "system" that co-produces the outcomes of an evacuation. The team defines and computes multiple measures of performance at different points in time. Analytical approaches are used to evaluate transportation strategies.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/25/2015</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/07/2018</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1536477</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Joseph</FirstName>
<LastName>Trainor</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>E</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Joseph E Trainor</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>jtrainor@udel.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>3028312136</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000210654</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/25/2015</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Delaware</Name>
<CityName>Newark</CityName>
<ZipCode>197160099</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>3028312136</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>210 Hullihen Hall</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Delaware</StateName>
<StateCode>DE</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>00</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>DE00</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>059007500</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF DELAWARE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>059007500</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Disaster Researh Center]]></Name>
<CityName>Newark</CityName>
<StateCode>DE</StateCode>
<ZipCode>197162553</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[111 Academy Street]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Delaware</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>00</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>DE00</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1638</Code>
<Text>HDBE-Humans, Disasters, and th</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>041E</Code>
<Text>HAZARD AND DISASTER REDUCTION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>042E</Code>
<Text>HAZARD AND DISASTER RESPONSE</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>116E</Code>
<Text>RESEARCH EXP FOR UNDERGRADS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1576</Code>
<Text>NATIONL EARTHQK HZRD REDCT PRG</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9178</Code>
<Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9231</Code>
<Text>SUPPL FOR UNDERGRAD RES ASSIST</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9251</Code>
<Text>REU SUPP-Res Exp for Ugrd Supp</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0115</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0117</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0118</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2015~152352</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2017~8000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2018~30423</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><strong><span style="text-decoration: underline;">Outcomes Report</span></strong></p> <p><strong>Collaborative Award: Multi-Perspective Evacuation Performance Measurement </strong><strong>(NSF Award Number </strong><strong>1536808)</strong><strong>&nbsp;</strong></p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>K. Triantis (Virginia Tech), P. Murray-Tuite (Clemson University), J. Trainor (University of Delaware), P. Edara (University of Missouri)</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>This research provides a point of departure from current viewpoints on evacuation planning by representing an evacuation as a network composed of transportation and household perspectives by considering systems, and systems containing processes linked through performance metrics. Grounded in household responses and transportation occurrences calibrated in realistic scenarios this research suggests that the derived approaches to performance can be more readily incorporated by both transportation agencies and households.</p> <p>The proposed approach began with the assertion that &ldquo;performance&rdquo; is a socio-technical process that requires both scientific measurement and an understanding of social systems that empower, inform, and constrain views on what makes a good or bad evacuation. The research approach required unpacking the basic phenomena of evacuation and rethinking how good or bad outcomes of that phenomenon are evaluated and measured. This suggested that it is neither appropriate to use a single performance measure nor to consider only a single point of view.</p> <p>The research team achieved a number of technical outcomes. The Virginia Tech researchers led the investigation of fundamental issues associated with performance measurement modeling. These included: a) the appropriate unit of analysis and perspective (household, community, and agency); b) the nature of the evacuation process; c) the use of survey data in performance modeling; d) the consideration that during an evacuation, households are influenced by factors outside their control; e) performance model conceptualizations taking into account the two data sets collected, the protective action decision model that describes how households might behave during an evacuation, the demand modeling, and the transportation simulation. The Delaware researchers focused on developing and delivering the data collection approach. Their intent was to develop data that would meet the individual analyses needs and would allow the modeling approaches to intersect. Further, they focused on integrating social and behavioral theory and empirical results in the formulation and analyses conducted. The Clemson group explored 1) evacuate/stay decisions, 2) the linkage between household accommodation, destination, and departure time choices, 3) number of vehicles to bring during hurricane evacuation based on the survey data, and 4) the influence of delays and arrival at the destination relative to hurricane landfall on evacuation choices. The Clemson researchers extended models (1-3) to the population to generate demand for the transportation simulation. The Missouri group inferred evacuee route selection from survey data and prepared the origin-destination zones for the new travel demand data generated by Clemson researchers. They also tested different variations of contraflow facility designs and ingress/egress alternatives. They conducted multiple simulation runs as part of evaluating different transportation strategies.</p> <p>Another important outcome of the research is the collection of two unique and different datasets. We conducted a survey that was sent to homeowners living in the coastal areas in the Hampton Roads region of Virginia. The goal of this survey was to collect data on how individuals perceive, understand, and make decisions about evacuations from hurricanes. We asked questions about the respondents&rsquo; perception of, past-experience with, and planning for hurricane evacuations. We also presented respondents with a hypothetical hurricane scenario, and we asked what decisions they would make in that scenario. We also asked respondents questions about how they would evaluate the success or failure of an evacuation.</p> <p>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; The second survey was similar to the first, but we focused it on a recent real evacuation event, rather than a hypothetical situation. In September 2017, there were evacuations in the state of Florida in response to the approach of Hurricane Irma. We sent this survey to communities in Florida that participated in those evacuations, to obtain behavioral and perception data about what makes for a successful evacuation. We modified the first survey mentioned above, to ask specifically about the respondents&rsquo; experiences during Hurricane Irma. This allowed us to gather factual, specific data. The data collected from both surveys were of great value for the research project&rsquo;s analysis, models, and simulations that address the central question of our research, i.e., what makes an evacuation "successful" and whether different transportation strategies contribute to that success.</p> <p>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; There were educational, training and outreach outcomes achieved as well. Clemson University developed a new graduate class on Transportation Risk and Evacuation for the Fall 2019 and worked with the mayor of Edisto Beach, who will be generating evacuation plans. This initiative facilitated workforce development. At Virginia Tech, the approaches used in this research were integrated into an advanced course in performance measurement and evaluation. Each of the graduate students and postdoc on this project gained experience with their own disciplines and in working across disciplines. This has better prepared them to address broader societal issues in the future.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 12/18/2020<br>      Modified by: Joseph&nbsp;E&nbsp;Trainor</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Outcomes Report  Collaborative Award: Multi-Perspective Evacuation Performance Measurement (NSF Award Number 1536808)      K. Triantis (Virginia Tech), P. Murray-Tuite (Clemson University), J. Trainor (University of Delaware), P. Edara (University of Missouri)     This research provides a point of departure from current viewpoints on evacuation planning by representing an evacuation as a network composed of transportation and household perspectives by considering systems, and systems containing processes linked through performance metrics. Grounded in household responses and transportation occurrences calibrated in realistic scenarios this research suggests that the derived approaches to performance can be more readily incorporated by both transportation agencies and households.  The proposed approach began with the assertion that "performance" is a socio-technical process that requires both scientific measurement and an understanding of social systems that empower, inform, and constrain views on what makes a good or bad evacuation. The research approach required unpacking the basic phenomena of evacuation and rethinking how good or bad outcomes of that phenomenon are evaluated and measured. This suggested that it is neither appropriate to use a single performance measure nor to consider only a single point of view.  The research team achieved a number of technical outcomes. The Virginia Tech researchers led the investigation of fundamental issues associated with performance measurement modeling. These included: a) the appropriate unit of analysis and perspective (household, community, and agency); b) the nature of the evacuation process; c) the use of survey data in performance modeling; d) the consideration that during an evacuation, households are influenced by factors outside their control; e) performance model conceptualizations taking into account the two data sets collected, the protective action decision model that describes how households might behave during an evacuation, the demand modeling, and the transportation simulation. The Delaware researchers focused on developing and delivering the data collection approach. Their intent was to develop data that would meet the individual analyses needs and would allow the modeling approaches to intersect. Further, they focused on integrating social and behavioral theory and empirical results in the formulation and analyses conducted. The Clemson group explored 1) evacuate/stay decisions, 2) the linkage between household accommodation, destination, and departure time choices, 3) number of vehicles to bring during hurricane evacuation based on the survey data, and 4) the influence of delays and arrival at the destination relative to hurricane landfall on evacuation choices. The Clemson researchers extended models (1-3) to the population to generate demand for the transportation simulation. The Missouri group inferred evacuee route selection from survey data and prepared the origin-destination zones for the new travel demand data generated by Clemson researchers. They also tested different variations of contraflow facility designs and ingress/egress alternatives. They conducted multiple simulation runs as part of evaluating different transportation strategies.  Another important outcome of the research is the collection of two unique and different datasets. We conducted a survey that was sent to homeowners living in the coastal areas in the Hampton Roads region of Virginia. The goal of this survey was to collect data on how individuals perceive, understand, and make decisions about evacuations from hurricanes. We asked questions about the respondents’ perception of, past-experience with, and planning for hurricane evacuations. We also presented respondents with a hypothetical hurricane scenario, and we asked what decisions they would make in that scenario. We also asked respondents questions about how they would evaluate the success or failure of an evacuation.              The second survey was similar to the first, but we focused it on a recent real evacuation event, rather than a hypothetical situation. In September 2017, there were evacuations in the state of Florida in response to the approach of Hurricane Irma. We sent this survey to communities in Florida that participated in those evacuations, to obtain behavioral and perception data about what makes for a successful evacuation. We modified the first survey mentioned above, to ask specifically about the respondents’ experiences during Hurricane Irma. This allowed us to gather factual, specific data. The data collected from both surveys were of great value for the research project’s analysis, models, and simulations that address the central question of our research, i.e., what makes an evacuation "successful" and whether different transportation strategies contribute to that success.                         There were educational, training and outreach outcomes achieved as well. Clemson University developed a new graduate class on Transportation Risk and Evacuation for the Fall 2019 and worked with the mayor of Edisto Beach, who will be generating evacuation plans. This initiative facilitated workforce development. At Virginia Tech, the approaches used in this research were integrated into an advanced course in performance measurement and evaluation. Each of the graduate students and postdoc on this project gained experience with their own disciplines and in working across disciplines. This has better prepared them to address broader societal issues in the future.          Last Modified: 12/18/2020       Submitted by: Joseph E Trainor]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
