<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Collaborative Proposal: Resource Allocation with Learning in Dynamic and Partially Observable Networks</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2015</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>161344.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>161344</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CMMI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Civil, Mechanical, &amp; Manufact Inn</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Georgia-Ann Klutke</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>gaklutke@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922443</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This collaborative project will research restoration of connectivity of interdependent road and service networks under uncertainty and learning. Real-life applications include post-disaster debris clearance to enable disaster response activities and interdependent infrastructure recovery and repair after a disruption. For example, when the road network is (partially) disrupted, edges (roads) need to be restored (e.g., through repair and debris clearance). The goal is to establish connectivity between supply and demand nodes in a timely manner to satisfy demand. Under uncertainty (about network conditions, and supply-demand levels), decision-making can be improved by collecting situational spatial data. However, data collection consumes time and resources. Furthermore, a common set of resources may perform both restoration and learning activities. Hence, under resource and time constraints, decisions on dynamically prioritizing edge recovery and resource allocation between recovery and learning are crucial for operational efficiency and effectiveness. This project considers the trade-off between learning and restoration activities, and decisions on (equitable and timely) resource allocation and frequency of information updates. The project will leverage the outreach network established by the Center for Health and Humanitarian Systems at Georgia Tech to disseminate results and interact with practitioners during project execution.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Previous research on network connectivity in stochastic networks with learning is limited. If successful, this project will introduce network repair models that are characterized by limited resources, uncertainty, ability to reduce uncertainty by deploying resources, and the need to maintain fairness in service access. It will contribute to a deeper understanding of how to solve dynamic multi-stage decision problems in stochastic networks that offer an opportunity to update information and in which learning and recovery actions share the same resources. This research will lead to efficient solution approaches for finding optimal or near-optimal solutions. The research team will perform structural analysis of underlying problems on simple networks, evaluate different information update mechanisms, and use those to derive insights and generate customized solutions.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/22/2015</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/22/2015</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1537824</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Ozlem</FirstName>
<LastName>Ergun</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Ozlem Ergun</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>o.ergun@neu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6173732508</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000692559</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/22/2015</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Northeastern University</Name>
<CityName>BOSTON</CityName>
<ZipCode>021155005</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6173733004</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>360 HUNTINGTON AVE</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[177-500]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
<StateCode>MA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MA07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>001423631</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>NORTHEASTERN UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>001423631</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Northeastern University]]></Name>
<CityName>Boston</CityName>
<StateCode>MA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>021155005</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[360 Huntington Ave]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MA07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>006Y</Code>
<Text>OE Operations Engineering</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>076E</Code>
<Text>SERVICE ENTERPRISE SYSTEMS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>078E</Code>
<Text>ENTERPRISE DESIGN &amp; LOGISTICS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8023</Code>
<Text>Health Care Enterprise Systems</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0115</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2015~161344</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Critical infrastructure systems (CIS) underpin almost every aspect of the modern society by providing the essential functions through overlaying service networks. In the case of a disruption, the functionality of these networks are degraded, which adversely affects the daily lives and economic productivity of communities. Thus, after an extreme event, in order to minimize the negative impact to society, it is crucial to restore the disrupted services provided by CIS as soon as possible and improve resilience of the CIS. In this project, we focused on disruptions created by natural hazards on transportation CIS, and developed mathematical models and methods to efficiently plan the post-disaster response and recovery operations.&nbsp;</p> <p>In the aftermath of a natural disaster, the transportation network is disrupted due to the debris blocking the roads and obstructing the flow of relief aid and search-and-rescue teams between critical facilities and disaster sites. We define the road network recovery problem (RNRP) as finding a schedule to clear the roads with limited resources such that all the service demanding locations are served, in the shortest possible time. In the first work stream, we tackle the deterministic RNRP and propose a novel network science inspired measure, service network edge betweenness centrality (SNEBC), to quantify the criticality of the components within a disrupted service network and develop a restoration heuristic, Cent-Restore.&nbsp;</p> <p>In illustrative computational studies, we use randomly generated and realistic instances settings. For randomly generated instances, we prove that Cent-Restore provides near-optimal results in a comparably short time. For the realistic instances, we evaluate the performance of Cent-Restore with respect to resilience by comparing it with other restoration strategies that are based on different prioritization rules of the disrupted components. We show that Cent-Restore re-establishes the services faster than other considered strategies (including those that are used or recommended in practice). This is because, Cent-Restore incorporates the service and post-disruption related characteristics of the networks while generating a restoration schedule. In realistic settings, disruption intensity varies over the network, hence the distribution of the disruption and demand locations vary. We conclude that using the topological attributes of the underlying infrastructure networks is not sufficient to derive effective restoration strategies. The distribution of the disruption on the overlaying service network and the location and capacity of the service components (such as demand and supply) within the disrupted network is more important. Ultimately, considering the post-disruption and service related components in the restoration strategies improves resilience</p> <p>As in the case of many realistic applications, any problem concerned with post-disruption operations, including the road clearance problem, involves uncertain components. This is mainly due to the information flow impeded as a result of chaos and unpredictable human behavior in the aftermath of a disruption. The uncertainties include but not limited to the amount of available resources for recovery, impact of the disruption, supply locations and demand emerging in the aftermath of a disruption. For instance, during the first several days after the Haiti earthquake the number of disaster victims ranged from 30,000 to 100,000, indicating the difficulty in precise estimations of the disaster impact. Among all the uncertainties that may arise after a disaster, demand uncertainty is very critical since not correctly accounting for demand uncertainty may lead to sub-optimal or infeasible emergency response planning which may eventually lead to deaths. Motivated by the importance of addressing demand uncertainty, in the second work stream we tackle RNRP with stochastic demand and propose an approximate dynamic programming (ADP) approach for identifying an effective policy under uncertainty. We test this approach&nbsp;&nbsp;on&nbsp;&nbsp;a&nbsp;&nbsp;case&nbsp;&nbsp;study&nbsp;&nbsp;based&nbsp;&nbsp;on&nbsp;&nbsp;the&nbsp;&nbsp;Boston&nbsp;&nbsp;road&nbsp;&nbsp;infrastructure network. We observe that, as the urgency of re-establishing the services increases or the resources become more scarce, the information&nbsp;gained&nbsp;&nbsp;from&nbsp;&nbsp;the&nbsp;&nbsp;network&nbsp;&nbsp;characteristics&nbsp;&nbsp;and&nbsp;&nbsp;short-term&nbsp;&nbsp;decisions&nbsp;&nbsp;should&nbsp;&nbsp;be the main driving factors to guide recovery policies. The results of all the experiments strongly evidence the significance of utilizing the inherent network interactions and attributes to generate key components of the ADP models that yield high-quality recovery policies.</p> <p>&nbsp;After the immediate effects of the disaster have passed, the debris accumulated on the road-sides during the response phase are collected and transported to processing sites by multiple contractors. In this context, in the third stream, we define the debris collection problem as finding an assignment of roads for each contractor such that the assigned workload among different subcontractors is balanced, the time to complete all debris collection operations is minimized, and the overlap between the assigned regions to different contractors is minimized creating an operationally practical solution. We develop an interactive optimization scheme and explore the effectiveness of human and computer collaboration through game based experiments in solving hard optimization problems with a spatial objective in the context of post-disaster recovery.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 11/07/2019<br>      Modified by: Ozlem&nbsp;Ergun</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Critical infrastructure systems (CIS) underpin almost every aspect of the modern society by providing the essential functions through overlaying service networks. In the case of a disruption, the functionality of these networks are degraded, which adversely affects the daily lives and economic productivity of communities. Thus, after an extreme event, in order to minimize the negative impact to society, it is crucial to restore the disrupted services provided by CIS as soon as possible and improve resilience of the CIS. In this project, we focused on disruptions created by natural hazards on transportation CIS, and developed mathematical models and methods to efficiently plan the post-disaster response and recovery operations.   In the aftermath of a natural disaster, the transportation network is disrupted due to the debris blocking the roads and obstructing the flow of relief aid and search-and-rescue teams between critical facilities and disaster sites. We define the road network recovery problem (RNRP) as finding a schedule to clear the roads with limited resources such that all the service demanding locations are served, in the shortest possible time. In the first work stream, we tackle the deterministic RNRP and propose a novel network science inspired measure, service network edge betweenness centrality (SNEBC), to quantify the criticality of the components within a disrupted service network and develop a restoration heuristic, Cent-Restore.   In illustrative computational studies, we use randomly generated and realistic instances settings. For randomly generated instances, we prove that Cent-Restore provides near-optimal results in a comparably short time. For the realistic instances, we evaluate the performance of Cent-Restore with respect to resilience by comparing it with other restoration strategies that are based on different prioritization rules of the disrupted components. We show that Cent-Restore re-establishes the services faster than other considered strategies (including those that are used or recommended in practice). This is because, Cent-Restore incorporates the service and post-disruption related characteristics of the networks while generating a restoration schedule. In realistic settings, disruption intensity varies over the network, hence the distribution of the disruption and demand locations vary. We conclude that using the topological attributes of the underlying infrastructure networks is not sufficient to derive effective restoration strategies. The distribution of the disruption on the overlaying service network and the location and capacity of the service components (such as demand and supply) within the disrupted network is more important. Ultimately, considering the post-disruption and service related components in the restoration strategies improves resilience  As in the case of many realistic applications, any problem concerned with post-disruption operations, including the road clearance problem, involves uncertain components. This is mainly due to the information flow impeded as a result of chaos and unpredictable human behavior in the aftermath of a disruption. The uncertainties include but not limited to the amount of available resources for recovery, impact of the disruption, supply locations and demand emerging in the aftermath of a disruption. For instance, during the first several days after the Haiti earthquake the number of disaster victims ranged from 30,000 to 100,000, indicating the difficulty in precise estimations of the disaster impact. Among all the uncertainties that may arise after a disaster, demand uncertainty is very critical since not correctly accounting for demand uncertainty may lead to sub-optimal or infeasible emergency response planning which may eventually lead to deaths. Motivated by the importance of addressing demand uncertainty, in the second work stream we tackle RNRP with stochastic demand and propose an approximate dynamic programming (ADP) approach for identifying an effective policy under uncertainty. We test this approach  on  a  case  study  based  on  the  Boston  road  infrastructure network. We observe that, as the urgency of re-establishing the services increases or the resources become more scarce, the information gained  from  the  network  characteristics  and  short-term  decisions  should  be the main driving factors to guide recovery policies. The results of all the experiments strongly evidence the significance of utilizing the inherent network interactions and attributes to generate key components of the ADP models that yield high-quality recovery policies.   After the immediate effects of the disaster have passed, the debris accumulated on the road-sides during the response phase are collected and transported to processing sites by multiple contractors. In this context, in the third stream, we define the debris collection problem as finding an assignment of roads for each contractor such that the assigned workload among different subcontractors is balanced, the time to complete all debris collection operations is minimized, and the overlap between the assigned regions to different contractors is minimized creating an operationally practical solution. We develop an interactive optimization scheme and explore the effectiveness of human and computer collaboration through game based experiments in solving hard optimization problems with a spatial objective in the context of post-disaster recovery.             Last Modified: 11/07/2019       Submitted by: Ozlem Ergun]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
