<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Collaborative Research: The effect of sand fraction and event evolution on fine-sediment transport and the depositional record in wave-supported mud flows</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2015</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>259648.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>259648</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>06040200</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>GEO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>OCE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Ocean Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Candace Major</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>cmajor@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927597</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Part 1&lt;br/&gt;Offshore delivery of fine sediment on the continental shelf via wave supported gravity currents (WSGC) is a key component of sediment transport fromsource to sink, yet it remains poorly understood. Current models of this process focus on suspension and transport of silt and clay sized particles. However, recent laboratory experiments show that even a small amount of sand in the sediment layer may exert a dominant control on the dynamics of the transport layer. The proposed effort will investigate the effect of sand fraction on sediment transport in WSGC, particularly, the transition between transport modes, the downslope transport and the depositional signatures. The objectives will be addressed using a comprehensive series of laboratory experiments, 3D turbulence-resolving numerical simulations, and re-analysis of existing field data from WSGC on active continental margins. The work is relevant to a broad range of fields, from fluid mechanics and water resource engineering, to studies of biogeochemical cycles. Outreach include introduction of the relevance of sedimentary processes to K-12 students with hand-on experiments in the university labs, and invited presentations to local schools.  Undergraduate  and graduate students will be involved. In addition to journal papers and conference presentations, open-source codes will be disseminated through Community Surface Dynamics Modeling System (CSDMS) framework.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Part 2&lt;br/&gt;Offshore delivery of fine sediment on the continental shelf via wave supported gravity currents (WSGC) is a key component of sediment source to sink, yet it remains poorly understood. Current models of this process focus on suspension and transport of silt and clay sized particles. However, recent laboratory experiments show that even a small amount of sand in the sediment layer may exert a dominant control on the dynamics of the transport layer. The proposed effort investigates the effect of sand fraction on sediment transport in WSGC, particularly, the transition between transport modes, the downslope transport and the depositional signatures. The project is formed around two main objectives: 1) Determine the role of the sand fraction in controlling dynamics and transport within WSGC and the bed deposits associated with them. 2) Evaluate impacts of event evolution (surging and waning of a storm) on the sediment and flow dynamics within a gravity flow and the resulting depositional signatures These will be addressed using a comprehensive series of laboratory experiments, 3D turbulence-resolving numerical simulations, and re-analysis of existing field data from WSGC on active continental margins. The work is relevant to a broad range of fields, from fluid mechanics and water resource engineering, to studies of biogeochemical cycles. Outreach include introduction of the relevance of sedimentary processes to K-12 students with hand-on experiments in the university labs, and invited presentations to local schools.  Undergraduate  and graduate students will be involved. In addition to journal papers and conference presentations, open-source codes will be disseminated through Community Surface Dynamics Modeling System (CSDMS) framework.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/17/2015</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/17/2015</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.050</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1537231</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Tian-Jian (Tom)</FirstName>
<LastName>Hsu</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Tian-Jian (Tom) Hsu</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>thsu@udel.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>3028314172</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000126431</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/17/2015</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Delaware</Name>
<CityName>Newark</CityName>
<ZipCode>197160099</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>3028312136</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>210 Hullihen Hall</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Delaware</StateName>
<StateCode>DE</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>00</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>DE00</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>059007500</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF DELAWARE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>059007500</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Delaware]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>DE</StateCode>
<ZipCode>197161551</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Delaware</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>00</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>DE00</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1610</Code>
<Text>PHYSICAL OCEANOGRAPHY</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1620</Code>
<Text>Marine Geology and Geophysics</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0115</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2015~259648</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Fine sediments delivered by rivers are the main agent to carry terrestrial organic carbon, nutrients and contaminants to the ocean. Therefore, it is important to understand and predict the fate of these fine sediments in the coastal ocean. Field observations have revealed that the thin wave bottom boundary is a main offshore delivery pathway of fine sediment through a unique process called wave-supported sediment-driven gravity flows (WSGFs). However, the physical factors controlling the magnitude of this offshore-directed downslope sediment flux remains unclear. This is particularly important as suspended sediment can attenuate turbulence and there exist a maximum suspended load (sediment carrying capacity) to limit offshore sediment flux due to WSGFs.</p> <p>This study created a new turbulence-resolving numerical model for fine sediment resuspension in the wave bottom boundary layer, TURBID, that is able to simulate event-scale wave-supported gravity flows driven by energetic wave condition observed in active margins. As a first step, we consider flat-bed condition and simulation results reveal that the maximum sediment load can be sustained by the wave bottom boundary layer without laminarization is about 25 g/L, which lead to a maximum downslope gravity current velocity of about 2 cm/s (see Figure 1). This downslope flux intensity is comparable to some field observations with lower intensity but cannot explain some other observations showing maximum sediment load of about 50~100 g/L with downslope gravity current speed reaching 5~10 cm/s.</p> <p>Through collaboration with our U. Washington colleagues, we understand that with only a small amount of fine sand (only 1~10%) in a predominant mud sample, fine sand can armor the surface layer and form anorbital or suborbital ripples. These ripples enhance turbulence level and maximum suspended load in the wave bottom boundary layer. Therefore, we hypothesize that the presence of small bedforms or enhanced roughness due to fine sand fraction at the bed surface may play a key role to enhance WSGF downslope flux and explain those field observed high WSGF fluxes. TURBID was further enhanced with coordinate transformation capability to simulate fine sediment resuspension over ripples. Preliminary simulation results suggest that even at low wave energy condition, the presence of sub-orbital ripple significantly enhances turbulence and is able to suspend about 60 g/L fine sediments (see Figure 2). This result is encouraging and we will complete several energetic wave runs with anorbital ripples to investigate the role of bedforms in WSGF more completely.&nbsp;&nbsp;</p> <p>This project focuses on quantifying the intensity of offshore-directed downslope sediment flux via WSGF using numerical model with different scenarios. We identify the importance of turbulence attenuation by sediments in limiting the WSGF intensity while in the meantime the competing role due to presence of bedforms in mixed sediment condition often encountered in continental shelves. Our finding leads to a much more complete understanding on WSGF and provide new direction for parameterizing offshore fine sediment flux in sediment source to sink. This project supported a PhD student at University of Delaware to develop cutting edge turbulence-resolving numerical models and to work closely with lab and field experimentalists in U. Washington on outstanding issues in sediment source to sink. PI and graduate student presented talks and posters in many international conference, such as AGU meeting, Ocean Science Meeting, and International Conference on Coastal Engineering. PI also delivered invited seminar/lectures on topics related to WSGF in several countries outside US, including Taiwan, Japan, France and South Korea. The numerical model is disseminated as an open-source model to other researchers via Github.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 12/13/2019<br>      Modified by: Tian-Jian (Tom)&nbsp;Hsu</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Images (<span id="selectedPhoto0">1</span> of <span class="totalNumber"></span>)           </div> <div class="galControls" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1537231/1537231_10388821_1576254629987_fig1--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1537231/1537231_10388821_1576254629987_fig1--rgov-800width.jpg" title="WSGF flat bed"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1537231/1537231_10388821_1576254629987_fig1--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="WSGF flat bed"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Wave-period-averaged (a) sediment concentration (b) downslope gravity velocity for flat bed condition in energetic wave condition of active margin for two different wave directions.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Liangyi Yue and Tian-Jian Hsu</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Royalty-free (unrestricted use)</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Tian-Jian (Tom)&nbsp;Hsu</div> <div class="imageTitle">WSGF flat bed</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1537231/1537231_10388821_1576254766978_fig2--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1537231/1537231_10388821_1576254766978_fig2--rgov-800width.jpg" title="sediment concentration over ripple bed"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1537231/1537231_10388821_1576254766978_fig2--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="sediment concentration over ripple bed"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Snapshot taken at under wave crest for (a) Turbulent coherent structures visualized by swirling strength and (b) iso-surface of sediment mass concentration of 55 g/L.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Liangyi Yue and Tian-Jian Hsu</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Royalty-free (unrestricted use)</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Tian-Jian (Tom)&nbsp;Hsu</div> <div class="imageTitle">sediment concentration over ripple bed</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Fine sediments delivered by rivers are the main agent to carry terrestrial organic carbon, nutrients and contaminants to the ocean. Therefore, it is important to understand and predict the fate of these fine sediments in the coastal ocean. Field observations have revealed that the thin wave bottom boundary is a main offshore delivery pathway of fine sediment through a unique process called wave-supported sediment-driven gravity flows (WSGFs). However, the physical factors controlling the magnitude of this offshore-directed downslope sediment flux remains unclear. This is particularly important as suspended sediment can attenuate turbulence and there exist a maximum suspended load (sediment carrying capacity) to limit offshore sediment flux due to WSGFs.  This study created a new turbulence-resolving numerical model for fine sediment resuspension in the wave bottom boundary layer, TURBID, that is able to simulate event-scale wave-supported gravity flows driven by energetic wave condition observed in active margins. As a first step, we consider flat-bed condition and simulation results reveal that the maximum sediment load can be sustained by the wave bottom boundary layer without laminarization is about 25 g/L, which lead to a maximum downslope gravity current velocity of about 2 cm/s (see Figure 1). This downslope flux intensity is comparable to some field observations with lower intensity but cannot explain some other observations showing maximum sediment load of about 50~100 g/L with downslope gravity current speed reaching 5~10 cm/s.  Through collaboration with our U. Washington colleagues, we understand that with only a small amount of fine sand (only 1~10%) in a predominant mud sample, fine sand can armor the surface layer and form anorbital or suborbital ripples. These ripples enhance turbulence level and maximum suspended load in the wave bottom boundary layer. Therefore, we hypothesize that the presence of small bedforms or enhanced roughness due to fine sand fraction at the bed surface may play a key role to enhance WSGF downslope flux and explain those field observed high WSGF fluxes. TURBID was further enhanced with coordinate transformation capability to simulate fine sediment resuspension over ripples. Preliminary simulation results suggest that even at low wave energy condition, the presence of sub-orbital ripple significantly enhances turbulence and is able to suspend about 60 g/L fine sediments (see Figure 2). This result is encouraging and we will complete several energetic wave runs with anorbital ripples to investigate the role of bedforms in WSGF more completely.    This project focuses on quantifying the intensity of offshore-directed downslope sediment flux via WSGF using numerical model with different scenarios. We identify the importance of turbulence attenuation by sediments in limiting the WSGF intensity while in the meantime the competing role due to presence of bedforms in mixed sediment condition often encountered in continental shelves. Our finding leads to a much more complete understanding on WSGF and provide new direction for parameterizing offshore fine sediment flux in sediment source to sink. This project supported a PhD student at University of Delaware to develop cutting edge turbulence-resolving numerical models and to work closely with lab and field experimentalists in U. Washington on outstanding issues in sediment source to sink. PI and graduate student presented talks and posters in many international conference, such as AGU meeting, Ocean Science Meeting, and International Conference on Coastal Engineering. PI also delivered invited seminar/lectures on topics related to WSGF in several countries outside US, including Taiwan, Japan, France and South Korea. The numerical model is disseminated as an open-source model to other researchers via Github.       Last Modified: 12/13/2019       Submitted by: Tian-Jian (Tom) Hsu]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
