<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Collaborative Research: Modeling hydrothermal recharge and outflow in oceanic crust analogs with sharp permeability gradients</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2015</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>68238.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>68238</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>06040200</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>GEO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>OCE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Ocean Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Deborah K. Smith</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>dksmith@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927978</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Fluid circulation through the oceanic crust at the axis of mid-ocean ridges is a primary mechanism through which the Earth loses its internal heat. At the seafloor, this circulation releases hot fluids into the deep ocean. These hydrothermal sites typically host ecosystems and life forms found nowhere else on the planet and are thought to be one of the places on Earth where life may have originated. Hydrothermal fluid venting often occurs at or near major fault or fracture zones, suggesting that these breaks in the ocean crust can act as highly permeable conduits for fluids escape. It is unclear, however, to what extent these breaks in Earth's crust enable fluids to enter and move downward into the seafloor where they get heated. This research uses analog experiments, using a 3-D printer, and modeling to explore how fluid circulation at mid-ocean ridges spontaneously organizes itself and transports heat in highly fractured and faulted crust. By allowing exploration of the relation between venting sites and major tectonic features, the research facilitates our understanding of geothermal processes and the search for new hydrothermal sites on the seafloor.  Broader impacts of the work include integration of research and education and support of three early career investigators, one from an institution in an EPSCoR state (Idaho).  Results have applications ranging from terrestrial groundwater hydrology to geothermal energy, carbon sequestration, and the oil industry.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This research employs numerical and analog experiments to describe and quantitatively explain the effect of heterogeneous permeability on subsurface flow geometry and heat extraction. Using a 3-D printer, we will generate plastic analogs of oceanic crust, containing a series of regularly spaced tubes that will act as fluid pathways of defined permeability. Within this permeable matrix, a planar slot of prescribed width, inclination, and greater permeability (achieved through wider tubes) will be created, representing the damage zone that typically surrounds active faults. The printed volume will be placed in a glass-walled tank containing a mixture of glucose and water. The fluid will be heated from below to initiate porous convection. A combination of particle image velocimetry, thermo-chromic liquid crystals, and temperature sensors at the top and bottom of the volume will allow quantification of the locations of fluid recharge and discharge and the heat output of the convective system as the permeability contrast and geometry of the slot is varied.  Results will be compared to numerical models of porous convection in heterogeneous media and then extrapolated to natural conditions. The research will focus on predicting the conditions under which high-permeability fault zones can trap and focus hydrothermal convection rolls. The combined experimental and theoretical approach will greatly inform the investigation of targeted hydrothermal sites on slow-spreading mid-ocean ridges that sit next to major fault systems or near major crustal heterogeneities.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/06/2015</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/06/2015</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.050</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1537650</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Eric</FirstName>
<LastName>Mittelstaedt</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>L</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Eric L Mittelstaedt</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>emittelstaedt@uidaho.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2088852045</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000623602</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/06/2015</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Regents of the University of Idaho</Name>
<CityName>MOSCOW</CityName>
<ZipCode>838443020</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2088856651</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>Office of Sponsored Programs</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[875 Perimeter Drive MS 3020]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Idaho</StateName>
<StateCode>ID</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>ID01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>075746271</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>REGENTS OF THE UNIVERSITY OF IDAHO</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>075746271</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Idaho]]></Name>
<CityName>Moscow</CityName>
<StateCode>ID</StateCode>
<ZipCode>838443020</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[875 Perimeter Dr. MS3022]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Idaho</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>ID01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1620</Code>
<Text>Marine Geology and Geophysics</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>0000</Code>
<Text>UNASSIGNED</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0115</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2015~68238</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>At numerous sites along mid-ocean ridges, the locations where the tectonic plates spread apart, high-temperature fluids (&le;400?C) discharge into the oceans through localized chimneys or vents on the seafloor; this process is known as hydrothermal venting and is driven by heat sources deep in the crust (e.g., magma chambers). These high temperature fluids modify the long-term chemistry of the oceans, account for a large fraction of the cooling of our planet, and form important mineral deposits. However, it is not well understood what controls the locations of hydrothermal vents and the spacing between them. For instance, some groups of vents appear to be regularly spaced, but others lack a systematic pattern. One likely control on vent location is the physical structure of the oceanic crust. For example, many hydrothermal vents are found near exposed faults on the seafloor. It is possible that faults may alter the route high-temperature fluids take as they rise toward the surface because movement on faults (e.g. during earthquakes) causes rocks around the fault to break, opening gaps and spaces that are easier for fluids to pass through than the small pores in unbroken rock. Faults at mid-ocean ridges are commonly observed to dip downward at an angle of about 60? and to be approximately planar. Thus, fluids rising from beneath a fault encounter the broken-up rocks and sometimes move up along the fault dip, rather than rising vertically through unbroken rock. This study aimed to quantify the extent to which broken-up rocks around faults alter the paths that high-temperature fluids take on their way to the surface. By understanding the role faults play in controlling the location of hydrothermal vents, we can use observations of hydrothermal vent locations to tell us about the structure of the crust.&nbsp;</p> <p>To investigate how faults alter hydrothermal vent locations, we used laboratory experiments and numerical simulations of fluid circulation through the broken rocks around a single fault located above a heat source within an otherwise uniform crust. Results indicate that faults will change the location of hydrothermal venting if two conditions are true. First, the overall rate fluids rise through the unbroken oceanic crust must be relatively slow; if fluids can rise too easily through the crust, they will pass through the broken-up fault zone rocks and rise vertically to the surface. Second, it must be at least several times easier for fluids to pass through broken-up fault zone rocks than to pass through unbroken crust. The balance between how easy it is to pass through fault zone rocks relative to unbroken crust determines how far fluids will rise along the fault dip before entering the overlying unbroken rock.&nbsp; If it takes a long time for fluids to rise through unbroken crust they will remain trapped in the fault zone and discharge from the seafloor at the fault.&nbsp; In contrast, if it is very easy to pass through the unbroken crustal rock, the fluids will rise through the fault zone for a short time, but quickly enter the unbroken rock above the fault, discharging at the seafloor above the heat source that drives fluid circulation.&nbsp;</p> <p>The broken-up rock around faults may also alter the spacing of hydrothermal systems along a mid-ocean ridge.&nbsp; In experiments both with and without a fault, we find the spacing between fluid discharge zones depends on temperature of the heating element at the base of the tank and the ease with which fluids can rise through the system. Similar to previous studies, we found that increasing the heating element temperature and the size of pores within the material (making it easier for fluid to rise) leads to more closely spaced plumes. However, in cases with a fault, the spacing of fluid discharge was ~3 times larger than for a similar case without a fault, suggesting that fault zones may increase the expected plume spacing.</p> <p>The above results allow us to use observations of hydrothermal vent locations and fault characteristics to better understand the properties of the oceanic crust. For example, the ease with which fluids pass through the crust (i.e., the permeability) is one of the most poorly known, yet important properties of the ocean crust for understanding hydrothermal venting; our results can place bounds on this value for some vents.&nbsp; Moreover, by examining the locations of hydrothermal systems relative to faults, we can infer the locations of heat sources, such as magma chambers. Overall, the results of this study provide important information about how faults can control the circulation of high-temperature fluids and how the locations of hydrothermal vents can provide constraints on the structure of the oceanic crust.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 03/30/2019<br>      Modified by: Eric&nbsp;L&nbsp;Mittelstaedt</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Image         </div> <div class="galControls onePhoto" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation onePhoto" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1537650/1537650_10384356_1553957715946_OutcomesModelImages_2019--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1537650/1537650_10384356_1553957715946_OutcomesModelImages_2019--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Numerical simulations of fluid circulation near a fault"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1537650/1537650_10384356_1553957715946_OutcomesModelImages_2019--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Numerical simulations of fluid circulation near a fault"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Fluids rising (red arrows) from a heat source will travel (top) vertically through a fault zone (red dashed lines) if crustal rocks are easy to pass through. Fluids will rise along the fault zone if crustal rocks are relatively difficult and the fault zone several times easier to pass through.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Jean-Arthur Olive, Qinkai Fan, Eric Mittelstaedt, Thibaut Barreyre</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Eric&nbsp;L&nbsp;Mittelstaedt</div> <div class="imageTitle">Numerical simulations of fluid circulation near a fault</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ At numerous sites along mid-ocean ridges, the locations where the tectonic plates spread apart, high-temperature fluids (&le;400?C) discharge into the oceans through localized chimneys or vents on the seafloor; this process is known as hydrothermal venting and is driven by heat sources deep in the crust (e.g., magma chambers). These high temperature fluids modify the long-term chemistry of the oceans, account for a large fraction of the cooling of our planet, and form important mineral deposits. However, it is not well understood what controls the locations of hydrothermal vents and the spacing between them. For instance, some groups of vents appear to be regularly spaced, but others lack a systematic pattern. One likely control on vent location is the physical structure of the oceanic crust. For example, many hydrothermal vents are found near exposed faults on the seafloor. It is possible that faults may alter the route high-temperature fluids take as they rise toward the surface because movement on faults (e.g. during earthquakes) causes rocks around the fault to break, opening gaps and spaces that are easier for fluids to pass through than the small pores in unbroken rock. Faults at mid-ocean ridges are commonly observed to dip downward at an angle of about 60? and to be approximately planar. Thus, fluids rising from beneath a fault encounter the broken-up rocks and sometimes move up along the fault dip, rather than rising vertically through unbroken rock. This study aimed to quantify the extent to which broken-up rocks around faults alter the paths that high-temperature fluids take on their way to the surface. By understanding the role faults play in controlling the location of hydrothermal vents, we can use observations of hydrothermal vent locations to tell us about the structure of the crust.   To investigate how faults alter hydrothermal vent locations, we used laboratory experiments and numerical simulations of fluid circulation through the broken rocks around a single fault located above a heat source within an otherwise uniform crust. Results indicate that faults will change the location of hydrothermal venting if two conditions are true. First, the overall rate fluids rise through the unbroken oceanic crust must be relatively slow; if fluids can rise too easily through the crust, they will pass through the broken-up fault zone rocks and rise vertically to the surface. Second, it must be at least several times easier for fluids to pass through broken-up fault zone rocks than to pass through unbroken crust. The balance between how easy it is to pass through fault zone rocks relative to unbroken crust determines how far fluids will rise along the fault dip before entering the overlying unbroken rock.  If it takes a long time for fluids to rise through unbroken crust they will remain trapped in the fault zone and discharge from the seafloor at the fault.  In contrast, if it is very easy to pass through the unbroken crustal rock, the fluids will rise through the fault zone for a short time, but quickly enter the unbroken rock above the fault, discharging at the seafloor above the heat source that drives fluid circulation.   The broken-up rock around faults may also alter the spacing of hydrothermal systems along a mid-ocean ridge.  In experiments both with and without a fault, we find the spacing between fluid discharge zones depends on temperature of the heating element at the base of the tank and the ease with which fluids can rise through the system. Similar to previous studies, we found that increasing the heating element temperature and the size of pores within the material (making it easier for fluid to rise) leads to more closely spaced plumes. However, in cases with a fault, the spacing of fluid discharge was ~3 times larger than for a similar case without a fault, suggesting that fault zones may increase the expected plume spacing.  The above results allow us to use observations of hydrothermal vent locations and fault characteristics to better understand the properties of the oceanic crust. For example, the ease with which fluids pass through the crust (i.e., the permeability) is one of the most poorly known, yet important properties of the ocean crust for understanding hydrothermal venting; our results can place bounds on this value for some vents.  Moreover, by examining the locations of hydrothermal systems relative to faults, we can infer the locations of heat sources, such as magma chambers. Overall, the results of this study provide important information about how faults can control the circulation of high-temperature fluids and how the locations of hydrothermal vents can provide constraints on the structure of the oceanic crust.       Last Modified: 03/30/2019       Submitted by: Eric L Mittelstaedt]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
