<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Smart Manufacturing of Hybrid Materials with an Exceptional Combination of Strength and Toughness</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2015</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>348684.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>348684</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CMMI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Civil, Mechanical, &amp; Manufact Inn</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Alexis Lewis</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>alewis@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922624</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Traditional engineering materials frequently compromise strength for toughness, limiting the reliability and safety of many materials. A material that could break this paradigm would find applications in critical high loading environments where failure from either mode is not an option. Such a novel material could be used for medical implants with a smaller form factor, smaller and more precise surgical instrumentation, and even strengthen automotive and aircraft structures.  By combining high strength and high toughness properties, this material would fit into many existing applications and enable new engineering advances to across the medical, aerospace, automotive, and many other industries.  This award will support research to develop high strength, high toughness metallic materials, which mimic structures found in nature. This research has the potential to establish a new area of materials engineering and processing devoted to the discovery of similar hybrid materials and foster interest in related fields among university students and industry engineers.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The objective of this research is to investigate smart manufacturing processes that employ shape memory alloys to transcribe the "J-curve" mechanical response and uniform molecular/atomic level deformation of the organic biopolymer in bio-inspired hybrid materials. The research approaches are to: (1) replicate nacre's architecture in engineering composites with shape memory alloy and intermetallic lamellae through eutectic solidification, (2) unveil the deformation mechanisms of individual lamellae by in-situ synchrotron high-energy X-ray diffraction and high resolution transmission electron microscopy mechanical testing, (3) uncover the load transfer mechanisms between shape memory alloy and intermetallic lamellae by mapping local strain fields with digital image correlation, and (4) establish a smart manufacturing strategy for a new class of high-performance, bio-inspired hybrid materials of exceptional mechanical prowess. The anticipated outcome will be the coupling of bio-inspired materials design strategies with smart manufacturing techniques to enable the discovery of material systems with exceptional properties and to enable their rapid insertion into existing manufacturing processes. This transformative research has the potential (1) to generate new paradigms of design, development, and implementation of smart manufacturing processes and (2) to accelerate the development and use of high performance, bio-inspired materials.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/31/2015</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/31/2015</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1537021</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Xiaodong</FirstName>
<LastName>Li</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Xiaodong Li</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>xl3p@virginia.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>4342437762</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000650730</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/31/2015</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Virginia Main Campus</Name>
<CityName>CHARLOTTESVILLE</CityName>
<ZipCode>229044195</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>4349244270</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>P.O.  BOX 400195</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Virginia</StateName>
<StateCode>VA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>VA05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>065391526</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>RECTOR &amp; VISITORS OF THE UNIVERSITY OF VIRGINIA</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>065391526</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Virginia Main Campus]]></Name>
<CityName>Charlottesville</CityName>
<StateCode>VA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>229044195</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[P.O. BOX 400195]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Virginia</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>VA05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>8092</Code>
<Text>Materials Eng. &amp; Processing</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>024E</Code>
<Text>MATERIALS DESIGN</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>080E</Code>
<Text>DEFORMATION PROCESSES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1444</Code>
<Text>SURFACE ENGINEERING</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8021</Code>
<Text>Materials Engineering</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8037</Code>
<Text>Advanced Manufacturing</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0115</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2015~348684</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The project aims at the establishment of materials engineering and processing devoted to the discovery of hybrid materials. The primary goal of this work is to investigate smart manufacturing processes that employ shape memory alloys and other engineering materials to transcribe the "<em>J</em>-curve" mechanical response and uniform molecular/atomic level deformation of the organic biopolymer in bio-inspired hybrid materials. The coupling of bio-inspired materials design strategies with smart manufacturing techniques enabled the discovery of material systems with exceptional properties and their rapid insertion into existing manufacturing processes. This research program has studied the replication of nacre's architecture in engineering composites with shape memory alloy and intermetallic lamellae through eutectic solidification, metal/polymer and graphene/graphene-oxide through shear mixing, freeze drying, and synthesizing; the deformation mechanisms of individual lamellae; the load transfer mechanisms between shape memory alloy and intermetallic lamellae by mapping local strain fields with digital image correlation; and a smart manufacturing strategy for a new class of high-performance, bio-inspired hybrid materials of exceptional mechanical prowess. Graphene and graphene oxide have been used to engineer and tailor the reinforcement/matrix interfaces to form strong load carriers and enhance the load transfer efficiency.</p> <p>The results of this research have contributed to a better understanding of the manufacturing-structure-property-function of bio-inspired hybrid materials. This research has enabled new paradigms of design and development of smart manufacturing processes, and accelerated the development of high performance, bio-inspired materials.</p> <p>This project has enhanced the expertise of faculty in this area, helped recruit qualified students, developed new educational opportunities, and increased the public awareness of NSF- driven research and educational activities in Materials Engineering and Processing.</p> <p>This project supported 5 students (1 female student), resulted in 6 scientific papers in prestigious peer reviewed journals, 7 invited talks and 6 presentations at international conferences/workshops, 1 US patent (pending), and 1 PhD dissertation. The research activities were used as an educational platform for students at all levels to learn about Materials Engineering and Processing. The research advances made through this project have generated new knowledge that has been introduced to undergraduate and graduate students through existing courses and newly developed courses (for instance, "Manufacturing and Process Technology" and "Micro/Nano Manufacturing" offered by the principal investigator). Students in these courses were given lab tours and opportunities to do their final course projects using facilities and techniques that were developed in the research. In addition, the research advances generated through this project were presented to high school students via lab tours and the Center for Diversity in Engineering events. The research activities and findings have been covered by media as news story.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 10/31/2019<br>      Modified by: Xiaodong&nbsp;Li</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The project aims at the establishment of materials engineering and processing devoted to the discovery of hybrid materials. The primary goal of this work is to investigate smart manufacturing processes that employ shape memory alloys and other engineering materials to transcribe the "J-curve" mechanical response and uniform molecular/atomic level deformation of the organic biopolymer in bio-inspired hybrid materials. The coupling of bio-inspired materials design strategies with smart manufacturing techniques enabled the discovery of material systems with exceptional properties and their rapid insertion into existing manufacturing processes. This research program has studied the replication of nacre's architecture in engineering composites with shape memory alloy and intermetallic lamellae through eutectic solidification, metal/polymer and graphene/graphene-oxide through shear mixing, freeze drying, and synthesizing; the deformation mechanisms of individual lamellae; the load transfer mechanisms between shape memory alloy and intermetallic lamellae by mapping local strain fields with digital image correlation; and a smart manufacturing strategy for a new class of high-performance, bio-inspired hybrid materials of exceptional mechanical prowess. Graphene and graphene oxide have been used to engineer and tailor the reinforcement/matrix interfaces to form strong load carriers and enhance the load transfer efficiency.  The results of this research have contributed to a better understanding of the manufacturing-structure-property-function of bio-inspired hybrid materials. This research has enabled new paradigms of design and development of smart manufacturing processes, and accelerated the development of high performance, bio-inspired materials.  This project has enhanced the expertise of faculty in this area, helped recruit qualified students, developed new educational opportunities, and increased the public awareness of NSF- driven research and educational activities in Materials Engineering and Processing.  This project supported 5 students (1 female student), resulted in 6 scientific papers in prestigious peer reviewed journals, 7 invited talks and 6 presentations at international conferences/workshops, 1 US patent (pending), and 1 PhD dissertation. The research activities were used as an educational platform for students at all levels to learn about Materials Engineering and Processing. The research advances made through this project have generated new knowledge that has been introduced to undergraduate and graduate students through existing courses and newly developed courses (for instance, "Manufacturing and Process Technology" and "Micro/Nano Manufacturing" offered by the principal investigator). Students in these courses were given lab tours and opportunities to do their final course projects using facilities and techniques that were developed in the research. In addition, the research advances generated through this project were presented to high school students via lab tours and the Center for Diversity in Engineering events. The research activities and findings have been covered by media as news story.       Last Modified: 10/31/2019       Submitted by: Xiaodong Li]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
