<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Analytical Mode Decomposition of Dynamic Structural Response for The Detection of Damage</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2015</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>269252.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>269252</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CMMI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Civil, Mechanical, &amp; Manufact Inn</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Jordan Berg</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>jberg@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032925365</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Damage detection is the process of identifying the occurrence of changes to the material and/or geometric properties of a structural system that adversely affect performance. The goal is to transform subjective and inconsistent visual inspections into objective and reliable condition screening of degrading structures, in particular during extreme events such as earthquakes and blasts. Most techniques currently available depend on the establishment of a structural model with no damage progression over time, which is often unrealistic during extreme events. This award supports fundamental research for the development of a model-free and adaptive data analysis technique. The new technique will enable an accurate and robust evaluation of time-dependent structural conditions, which has been increasingly sought for applications in civil infrastructure immediately after a disastrous event. Therefore, results from this study will greatly benefit post-event response and recovery, leading to enhanced resiliency and stable economy. The technique will be made available through a Wikipedia page and may be applicable to multiple disciplines in science, engineering, healthcare and finance industries. These multi-disciplinary applications will help broaden the participation of underrepresented groups in research and positively impact engineering education.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Empirical mode decomposition is a non-parametric and adaptive damage detection technique that has since 1996 been demonstrated powerful to deal with nonstationary and nonlinear dynamic responses. However, it has never been mathematically proven for guaranteed success in various applications and thus faced challenges in analyzing noisy data, weak intermittent fluctuations, closely-spaced modes of vibration, and temporal changes in vibration mode. This research is to provide a mathematical foundation to the decomposition of structural dynamic response and explore analytical mode decomposition for damage detection of time-varying structures. The research team will establish a sampling rate and finite data length criterion that guarantees an accurate decomposition of a discrete time sequence, develop a new adaptive wavelet transform for the optimal determination of time-dependent bisecting frequencies, derive a computationally efficient solution to a new system-response characteristics relationship recently discovered for nonlinear structures, and experimentally validate the robustness, accuracy, and efficiency of the analytical decomposition in system identification and damage detection of complex structures with different nonlinearities.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/26/2015</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/26/2015</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1538416</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Genda</FirstName>
<LastName>Chen</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Genda Chen</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>gchen@mst.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5733414462</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000148267</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/26/2015</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Missouri University of Science and Technology</Name>
<CityName>Rolla</CityName>
<ZipCode>654096506</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5733414134</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>300 W 12th Street</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[202 Centennial Hall]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Missouri</StateName>
<StateCode>MO</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>08</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MO08</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>804883767</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF MISSOURI SYSTEM</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>006326904</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Missouri University of Science and Technology]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>MO</StateCode>
<ZipCode>654096506</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Missouri</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>08</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MO08</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7569</Code>
<Text>Dynamics, Control and System D</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>030E</Code>
<Text>CONTROL SYSTEMS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>031E</Code>
<Text>MECHATRONICS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>032E</Code>
<Text>SENSORS AND ACTUATORS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>033E</Code>
<Text>Smart and responsive structures</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>034E</Code>
<Text>Dynamical systems</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>035E</Code>
<Text>NOISE, ACOUSTICS, VIBRATIONS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8024</Code>
<Text>Complex Systems</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0115</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2015~269252</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><strong>Intellectual Merits</strong></p> <p>This project explored and developed three new concepts: (1) adaptive wavelet transform, (2) multiple analytical mode decomposition, and (3) multi-bandwidth wavelength transform.</p> <p><strong><em>Adaptive wavelet transform (AWT)</em></strong> An AWT is defined as an average of overlapped short-time wavelet transforms with optimized time-varying resolution in a time-frequency region of interest. Two optimization algorithms is developed for time and frequency resolution updating and implemented in MATLAB to search for desirable wavelet parameters over time.</p> <p>For an analytical signal with two closely-spaced delta functions and two closely-spaced frequency-modulated sinusoids, the time and frequency resolutions of the AWT are approximately 2.7 times more uniform than those of continuous wavelet transform. When applied to the impact echo responses experimentally recorded from a 60"&times;36"&times;7.25" concrete slab, this improvement leads to 7 more successful detections (from 31 to 38) of deep or shallow delamination out of 40 sets of analyzed test data with a deep delamination localization error of less than 3%. A synchro-squeezing process of the AWT can further improve the delamination detection with 1.5% and 5% estimation errors in deep delamination depth and slab thickness, respectively.</p> <p><strong><em>Multiple analytical mode decompositions (M-AMD)</em></strong> M-AMD is developed to identify the parameters of nonlinear oscillators from dynamic responses, and minimize or eliminate any error that incurs during the discretization of dynamic responses from analog to digital recording.</p> <p>Under free vibration, the time-varying damping (stiffness) coefficient of an oscillator is divided into slow- and fast-varying components by a bisecting frequency in reference to velocity (displacement). The slow component is estimated from the oscillator&rsquo;s responses and their Hilbert transforms, and adaptively filtered with the AMD. Each fast-varying component is estimated from the oscillator&rsquo;s responses and the determined slow-varying components, and corrected with AMD using an approximate bisecting frequency of the two fast-varying components. For Duffing oscillators, the M-AMD yields a less than 1.2% error in estimation of model parameters when the nonlinear term of the restoring force is less than 25 times the linear term. For spherical bearings, the M-AMD gives a less than 1.2% error when the coefficient of friction is less than 0.017. Under harmonic loading, the errors in estimation of all model parameters of a Duffing oscillator are less than 3% from simulated displacement responses.</p> <p>Under earthquake excitations, the M-AMD algorithm is first applied directly to a &frac14;-scale, 3-story building with an installed piezoelectric friction damper to have the damper parameter identified with less than 1% in error. Then, the AWT is used to determine time-varying bisecting frequencies of the acceleration time history of a 1/20-scale cable-stayed bridge model. The bisecting frequencies are applied to decompose modal components of the acceleration by AMD. The optimized AMD can remove signal distortion when transferred from analogue to digital recording, thus decomposing the signal accurately. The combined AWT and M-AMD algorithms enable real-time identification of the progression of damage.</p> <p><strong><em>Multi-bandwidth wavelet transform (MBWT)</em></strong> MBWT is a simplified and computationally-efficient AWT. When two central frequencies are selected over time, the MBWT is one time more accurate than Fourier transform for the identification of resonant frequencies in the concrete slab. When detailed time-varying wavelet parameters are selected from a representative acoustic emission signal, the MBWT can successfully discriminate different characteristics of acoustic signals from a series of cable tests. Prior to wire fracture, acoustic events of inter-wire slippage and fracture initiation are observed from a steel strand of 7 wires. In comparison with the fracture initiation signals, the inter-wire slippage signals have substantially lower frequency components and similar time duration. Acoustic signals of fracture initiation possess unique time-frequency characteristics such as wide frequency bandwidth and short time duration.</p> <p><strong>Broader Impact</strong></p> <p>Accurate identification of structural properties by the synchro-squeezed AWT and the optimized M-AMD allows engineers to develop a maintenance strategy of existing infrastructure more accurately and thus more cost-effectively. Both technologies and associated theories can be applied to detect defects in mechanical and aerospace engineering. The AWT can also be extended to the analysis of images in science and engineering.&nbsp;</p> <p>This project resulted in 1 software copyright, 7 journal papers, 2 conference papers, 1 keynote and 1 invited presentations at international conferences, and one Ph.D. dissertation (Dr. Hongya Qu) completed. It provided interdisciplinary training (civil engineering and computer science) in signal analysis and system identification of nonlinear structures for at least 2 Ph.D. students (Drs. Hongya Qu and Tiantian Li), including one female. Hongya was also trained for the proposal preparation and writing skills. The MATLAB code developed for AWT provides a new tool for general users.</p> <p><strong>Data Management</strong></p> <p>The definitions and mathematical expressions of AWT, synchro-squeezed AWT, and M-AMD are documented in details in the published journal papers. Numerical and experimental examples are also included in the journal articles to illustrate the new concepts and provide a step-by-step application procedure.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 01/16/2020<br>      Modified by: Genda&nbsp;Chen</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Intellectual Merits  This project explored and developed three new concepts: (1) adaptive wavelet transform, (2) multiple analytical mode decomposition, and (3) multi-bandwidth wavelength transform.  Adaptive wavelet transform (AWT) An AWT is defined as an average of overlapped short-time wavelet transforms with optimized time-varying resolution in a time-frequency region of interest. Two optimization algorithms is developed for time and frequency resolution updating and implemented in MATLAB to search for desirable wavelet parameters over time.  For an analytical signal with two closely-spaced delta functions and two closely-spaced frequency-modulated sinusoids, the time and frequency resolutions of the AWT are approximately 2.7 times more uniform than those of continuous wavelet transform. When applied to the impact echo responses experimentally recorded from a 60"&times;36"&times;7.25" concrete slab, this improvement leads to 7 more successful detections (from 31 to 38) of deep or shallow delamination out of 40 sets of analyzed test data with a deep delamination localization error of less than 3%. A synchro-squeezing process of the AWT can further improve the delamination detection with 1.5% and 5% estimation errors in deep delamination depth and slab thickness, respectively.  Multiple analytical mode decompositions (M-AMD) M-AMD is developed to identify the parameters of nonlinear oscillators from dynamic responses, and minimize or eliminate any error that incurs during the discretization of dynamic responses from analog to digital recording.  Under free vibration, the time-varying damping (stiffness) coefficient of an oscillator is divided into slow- and fast-varying components by a bisecting frequency in reference to velocity (displacement). The slow component is estimated from the oscillator’s responses and their Hilbert transforms, and adaptively filtered with the AMD. Each fast-varying component is estimated from the oscillator’s responses and the determined slow-varying components, and corrected with AMD using an approximate bisecting frequency of the two fast-varying components. For Duffing oscillators, the M-AMD yields a less than 1.2% error in estimation of model parameters when the nonlinear term of the restoring force is less than 25 times the linear term. For spherical bearings, the M-AMD gives a less than 1.2% error when the coefficient of friction is less than 0.017. Under harmonic loading, the errors in estimation of all model parameters of a Duffing oscillator are less than 3% from simulated displacement responses.  Under earthquake excitations, the M-AMD algorithm is first applied directly to a &frac14;-scale, 3-story building with an installed piezoelectric friction damper to have the damper parameter identified with less than 1% in error. Then, the AWT is used to determine time-varying bisecting frequencies of the acceleration time history of a 1/20-scale cable-stayed bridge model. The bisecting frequencies are applied to decompose modal components of the acceleration by AMD. The optimized AMD can remove signal distortion when transferred from analogue to digital recording, thus decomposing the signal accurately. The combined AWT and M-AMD algorithms enable real-time identification of the progression of damage.  Multi-bandwidth wavelet transform (MBWT) MBWT is a simplified and computationally-efficient AWT. When two central frequencies are selected over time, the MBWT is one time more accurate than Fourier transform for the identification of resonant frequencies in the concrete slab. When detailed time-varying wavelet parameters are selected from a representative acoustic emission signal, the MBWT can successfully discriminate different characteristics of acoustic signals from a series of cable tests. Prior to wire fracture, acoustic events of inter-wire slippage and fracture initiation are observed from a steel strand of 7 wires. In comparison with the fracture initiation signals, the inter-wire slippage signals have substantially lower frequency components and similar time duration. Acoustic signals of fracture initiation possess unique time-frequency characteristics such as wide frequency bandwidth and short time duration.  Broader Impact  Accurate identification of structural properties by the synchro-squeezed AWT and the optimized M-AMD allows engineers to develop a maintenance strategy of existing infrastructure more accurately and thus more cost-effectively. Both technologies and associated theories can be applied to detect defects in mechanical and aerospace engineering. The AWT can also be extended to the analysis of images in science and engineering.   This project resulted in 1 software copyright, 7 journal papers, 2 conference papers, 1 keynote and 1 invited presentations at international conferences, and one Ph.D. dissertation (Dr. Hongya Qu) completed. It provided interdisciplinary training (civil engineering and computer science) in signal analysis and system identification of nonlinear structures for at least 2 Ph.D. students (Drs. Hongya Qu and Tiantian Li), including one female. Hongya was also trained for the proposal preparation and writing skills. The MATLAB code developed for AWT provides a new tool for general users.  Data Management  The definitions and mathematical expressions of AWT, synchro-squeezed AWT, and M-AMD are documented in details in the published journal papers. Numerical and experimental examples are also included in the journal articles to illustrate the new concepts and provide a step-by-step application procedure.       Last Modified: 01/16/2020       Submitted by: Genda Chen]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
