<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Carbon Sedimentation In the Ocean Watercolumn (C-SNOW): Calibration</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>10/01/2015</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>03/31/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>648906.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>778687</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>06040100</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>GEO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>OCE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Ocean Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Kandace Binkley</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>kbinkley@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927577</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Carbon sedimentation (10 Pg C/year) via the ocean biological carbon pump is important to the regulation of atmospheric CO2, yet is poorly observed in space and time due to limitations of current methodology (moorings/ships), and thus is poorly understood and consequently is poorly represented in carbon cycle simulations. Current estimates of the strength of the ocean biological carbon pump are highly uncertain. The one year project will deploy and calibrate low-cost robotic ocean-profiling current-following Carbon Flux Explorers (CFEs) which is a necessary step paving the way high frequency broad scale monitoring and prediction of carbon sedimentation in the ocean. Project scientists will work with the San Francisco Exploratorium to enhance public knowledge of the ocean carbon cycle, ocean robotics. UC Berkeley undergraduate students will be exposed to this research activity in the class-room, as laboratory assistants, and in hands-on experience at sea. &lt;br/&gt; &lt;br/&gt;The CFEs represent the integration of an ocean profiling float ? similar to those widely deployed in the ocean as part of the ARGO program ? with the UC Berkeley / Lawrence Berkeley National Laboratory - developed Optical Sedimentation Recorder (OSR). The CFEs dive to depth and the OSR uses a camera and three modes of illumination to image particles over time as they accumulate in a sediment trap. Periodically the sample is removed and the imaging resumes. The use of transmitted, transmitted cross-polarized transmitted, and side illumination permits three modes of quantification sample loading as measured sample attenuance, sample cross-polarized photon yield, and sample reflectance. The project specifically aims to relate the three optical metrics of sample load to the amount of particulate organic carbon, particulate inorganic carbon (also known as calcium carbonate), and other biogenic particle phases. Thus, the development will demonstrate the ability of the Carbon Flux Explorer to measure the strength of carbon sedimentation in the ocean. In a one year project. Scientists at University of California, Berkeley and engineers at Lawrence Berkeley National Laboratory and Scripps Institution of Oceanography will build/modify 2 Carbon Flux Explorers to enable the collection of samples for their calibration. These and two other CFEs and a surface tethered OSR will be co-deployed during an oceanographic expedition in California coastal and offshore waters. Collected samples will be analyzed and compared with the optical metrics of sample load, collected at the same time. The project will thus meet its major goal of demonstrating that the CFEs can measure the strength of ocean carbon sedimentation as a function of depth, time, and ocean location, in a way here-to-fore impossible to achieve from ships.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>09/17/2015</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>02/06/2017</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.050</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1538686</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>James</FirstName>
<LastName>Bishop</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>K</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>James K Bishop</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>jkbishop@berkeley.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5106426110</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000149833</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/17/2015</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of California-Berkeley</Name>
<CityName>BERKELEY</CityName>
<ZipCode>947101749</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5106433891</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>Sponsored Projects Office</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[1608 Fourth Street, Suite 220]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>13</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CA13</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>124726725</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>REGENTS OF THE UNIVERSITY OF CALIFORNIA, THE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>071549000</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of California-Berkeley]]></Name>
<CityName>Berkeley</CityName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>947045940</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[2150 Shattuck Avenue, Suite #300]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>13</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CA13</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1680</Code>
<Text>OCEAN TECH &amp; INTERDISC COORDIN</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0115</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0117</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2015~648906</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2017~129781</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Marine phytoplankton account for about half (or 50 Pg C y<sup>-1</sup>) of global primary productivity and live for one week on average before being consumed by zooplankton. Approximately10 Pg C y<sup>-1</sup> settles from the surface layer as sinking aggregates containing both particulate organic and inorganic carbon (POC and PIC). The carbon that reaches the deep ocean remains isolated from the atmosphere for centuries. This process, the &ldquo;biological carbon pump&rdquo; (BCP), is a fundamental player in the global carbon cycle. To date, most observations of the&nbsp; BCP are limited both spatially and seasonally due to the requirement to have attending ships or nearby islands to support such studies.&nbsp;</p> <p>The Carbon Flux Explorer (CFE), a robotic Lagrangian float-deployed imaging sediment trap, has been designed to optically measure the hourly variations of particle flux to kilometer depths for months to seasons while relaying data in near-real time to shore via satellite without attending ships. The main optical proxy of particle load recorded by the CFE, volume-attenuance (VA; units of mATN-cm<sup>2</sup>), while rigorously defined and highly precise, has not been calibrated in terms of particulate organic carbon (POC), nitrogen (PN), and phosphorus (PP). In this project, a novel 3D printed particle sampler using cutting edge additive manufacturing was developed and integrated with the CFE (Fig. 1). Two such modified floats (CFE-Cals) were deployed a total of 15 times for 18-24 hour periods to gain calibration imagery and samples at depths near 150 meters in four contrasting productivity environments during the June 1 to July 2 2017 California Current Ecosystem &ndash; Long Term Ecological Research (LTER) process study (Fig. 2). Regression slopes for VA:POC and VA:PN (units mATN-cm<sup>2</sup>:mmol; R<sup>2</sup> in parentheses) were 10.1x10<sup>3</sup> (0.86), 10.0x10<sup>4</sup> (0.87) respectively and were not sensitive to environment or classes of particles sampled (Fig. 3). The detailed calibration study results are available online (Bourne et al. 2018, Biogeosciences Discuss.,  https://doi.org/10.5194/bg-2018-294, in review).</p> <p>The project succeeded in its goal of calibrating the CFE and thus provides justification for wider deployments of CFEs in remote and biologically dynamic waters. Such deployments will provide badly needed observations of the biological processes that transport and redistribute carbon in the ocean. Such observations are required for improved ocean carbon cycle simulations and prediction, for understanding controls of atmospheric CO<sub>2</sub>, and for the understanding of how energy flows from surface waters through biological food webs to the deep sea. This project supported the STEM PhD dissertation research of one graduate student and research projects for three undergraduates.</p> <p>One note: during our month long expedition, we deployed 2 CFEs and 2 CFE-Cal robots. One CFE was violently attacked and sunk in 4000 m of water by a short-fin Mako shark on June 20th 2017 just as it was about to be recovered. This was a shock to all involved in the study.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 07/25/2018<br>      Modified by: James&nbsp;K&nbsp;Bishop</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Images (<span id="selectedPhoto0">1</span> of <span class="totalNumber"></span>)           </div> <div class="galControls" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1538686/1538686_10400509_1531023677610_Figure2--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1538686/1538686_10400509_1531023677610_Figure2--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Carbon Flux Explorer with Calibration Sampler"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1538686/1538686_10400509_1531023677610_Figure2--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Carbon Flux Explorer with Calibration Sampler"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">(A) CFE-Cal during deployment from R/V Revelle in 2017. The sampling system for particles is interfaced between the Optical Sedimentation Recorder (left) and SOLO float (right). (B) Suction action of a pump draws water and particles through a tube (shown disconnected) into one of 4 sample tubes.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Jim Bishop</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">James&nbsp;K&nbsp;Bishop</div> <div class="imageTitle">Carbon Flux Explorer with Calibration Sampler</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1538686/1538686_10400509_1531024045244_Figure1--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1538686/1538686_10400509_1531024045244_Figure1--rgov-800width.jpg" title="CFE-Cal deployment locations June 2017"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1538686/1538686_10400509_1531024045244_Figure1--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="CFE-Cal deployment locations June 2017"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Map of CFE-Cal deployment and drift locations overlaying map of sea surface temperature (°C) for June 10-17 2017 from NASA Ocean Color Aqua Modis 4km resolution (https://oceancolor.gsfc.nasa.gov/). Blue and red dots denote locations where CFE-Cals were deployed. Cold water was highly productive.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Jim Bishop / Hannah Bourne</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">James&nbsp;K&nbsp;Bishop</div> <div class="imageTitle">CFE-Cal deployment locations June 2017</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1538686/1538686_10400509_1531025469701_Figure3--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1538686/1538686_10400509_1531025469701_Figure3--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Images of Particles from CFE-Cal"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1538686/1538686_10400509_1531025469701_Figure3--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Images of Particles from CFE-Cal"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">CFE-Cal transmitted light images of sinking particles captured at 150 m. four locations - corresponding to those shown in Figure 2. Dash marks are 1 mm long. Our calibration results are insensitive to large variations of particle size distribution. Data in Bourne 2018 (Biogeosciences in review).</div> <div class="imageCredit">Jim Bishop / Hannah Bourne UC Berkeley</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">James&nbsp;K&nbsp;Bishop</div> <div class="imageTitle">Images of Particles from CFE-Cal</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Marine phytoplankton account for about half (or 50 Pg C y-1) of global primary productivity and live for one week on average before being consumed by zooplankton. Approximately10 Pg C y-1 settles from the surface layer as sinking aggregates containing both particulate organic and inorganic carbon (POC and PIC). The carbon that reaches the deep ocean remains isolated from the atmosphere for centuries. This process, the "biological carbon pump" (BCP), is a fundamental player in the global carbon cycle. To date, most observations of the  BCP are limited both spatially and seasonally due to the requirement to have attending ships or nearby islands to support such studies.   The Carbon Flux Explorer (CFE), a robotic Lagrangian float-deployed imaging sediment trap, has been designed to optically measure the hourly variations of particle flux to kilometer depths for months to seasons while relaying data in near-real time to shore via satellite without attending ships. The main optical proxy of particle load recorded by the CFE, volume-attenuance (VA; units of mATN-cm2), while rigorously defined and highly precise, has not been calibrated in terms of particulate organic carbon (POC), nitrogen (PN), and phosphorus (PP). In this project, a novel 3D printed particle sampler using cutting edge additive manufacturing was developed and integrated with the CFE (Fig. 1). Two such modified floats (CFE-Cals) were deployed a total of 15 times for 18-24 hour periods to gain calibration imagery and samples at depths near 150 meters in four contrasting productivity environments during the June 1 to July 2 2017 California Current Ecosystem &ndash; Long Term Ecological Research (LTER) process study (Fig. 2). Regression slopes for VA:POC and VA:PN (units mATN-cm2:mmol; R2 in parentheses) were 10.1x103 (0.86), 10.0x104 (0.87) respectively and were not sensitive to environment or classes of particles sampled (Fig. 3). The detailed calibration study results are available online (Bourne et al. 2018, Biogeosciences Discuss.,  https://doi.org/10.5194/bg-2018-294, in review).  The project succeeded in its goal of calibrating the CFE and thus provides justification for wider deployments of CFEs in remote and biologically dynamic waters. Such deployments will provide badly needed observations of the biological processes that transport and redistribute carbon in the ocean. Such observations are required for improved ocean carbon cycle simulations and prediction, for understanding controls of atmospheric CO2, and for the understanding of how energy flows from surface waters through biological food webs to the deep sea. This project supported the STEM PhD dissertation research of one graduate student and research projects for three undergraduates.  One note: during our month long expedition, we deployed 2 CFEs and 2 CFE-Cal robots. One CFE was violently attacked and sunk in 4000 m of water by a short-fin Mako shark on June 20th 2017 just as it was about to be recovered. This was a shock to all involved in the study.       Last Modified: 07/25/2018       Submitted by: James K Bishop]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
