<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>2015 Conference on Science at the Sanford Underground Research Facility; Rapid City, South Dakota at the South Dakota School of Mines; May 18-20, 2015.</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>06/01/2015</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2016</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>10000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>10000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03010000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>PHY</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Physics</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Jonathan Whitmore</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>jwhitmor@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032928908</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This award will provide partial participant support for US junior scientists and members of under-represented minorities to participate in the 2015 Conference on Science at the Sanford Underground Research Facility (SURF) to be held on May 18-20, 2015 on the campus at the South Dakota School of Mines &amp; Technology in Rapid City, South Dakota. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The conference will address the science that can be carried out at SURF: Neutrino Physics, Proton Decay, Nuclear Astrophysics, Dark Matter, Neutrinoless Double Beta Decay, Materials Science for Nuclear and Particle Physics, Geology, and Astrobiology and Life in Extreme Environments. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;For Broader Impacts, the conference has a particular focus on junior scientists as well as scientists who are members of groups underrepresented in science and engineering (e.g., underrepresented minorities, women, and persons with disabilities). The PI is also working to encourage the participation of Native American students, scientists, and engineers in the conference. This conference is important in the education of young scientists not only because of the presentations they listen to, but also because during the meeting they directly communicate with the more experienced scientists who are in attendance.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>05/14/2015</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/14/2015</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1538923</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Richard</FirstName>
<LastName>Schnee</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>W</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Richard W Schnee</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>richard.schnee@sdsmt.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6053945206</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000105462</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/14/2015</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Luke</FirstName>
<LastName>Corwin</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>A</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Luke A Corwin</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>luke.corwin@sdsmt.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6053942728</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000649242</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/14/2015</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>South Dakota School of Mines and Technology</Name>
<CityName>Rapid City</CityName>
<ZipCode>577013995</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6053941218</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>501 East Saint Joseph Street</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>South Dakota</StateName>
<StateCode>SD</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>00</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>SD00</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>929928018</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>SOUTH DAKOTA SCHOOL OF MINES &amp; TECHNOLOGY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>929538999</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[South Dakota School of Mines and Technology]]></Name>
<CityName>Rapid City</CityName>
<StateCode>SD</StateCode>
<ZipCode>577013995</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[501 East Saint Joseph Street]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>South Dakota</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>00</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>SD00</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1221</Code>
<Text>HEP-High Energy Physics</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1234</Code>
<Text>NUCLEAR PRECISION MEASUREMENTS</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7235</Code>
<Text>Particle Astrophysics/Undergro</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>9134</Code>
<Text>Integrative Activities in Phys</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7483</Code>
<Text>PHYSICS OF THE UNIVERSE</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0115</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2015~10000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The Sanford Underground Research Facility (SURF) in Lead, South Dakota, provides a unique national resource for science that must be done deep underground. This science includes sensitive experiments that explore some of the most challenging questions facing 21st century physics, such as the origin of matter, the nature of dark matter and the properties of neutrinos. The facility also hosts experiments in other disciplines including geology, biology and engineering. This project provided funding support to increase the effectiveness of a conference on SURF science&nbsp; held at the South Dakota School of Mines and Technology, an hour&rsquo;s drive from SURF.</p> <p><br />Intellectual Merit :<br /><br />The intellectual merit of this project consists of support through the conference for the current and future SURF program. The Particle Physics Project Prioritization Panel (P5) recommended strong support for the SURF program in particle physics: significantly increased funding for the second-generation dark matter direct detection program, the hosting of at least one third-generation dark matter direct-detection experiment, and support for the Long Baseline Neutrino Facility, described as the highest-priority large project in its timeframe. The SURF program in nuclear physics -- including neutrinoless double beta decay, and measurements at an underground accelerator to improve understanding of critical astrophysics processes -- also takes high priority, with an underground accelerator facility for nuclear astrophysics among the top three priorities in the Long Range Plan of the 2015 Nuclear Science Advisory Committee (NSAC).<br /><br />Exchange of the most recent results and ideas related to SURF science at the conference improved the effectiveness of these high-priority projects. This conference was unique in its coverage of the full SURF science program, allowing researchers to learn of synergies between fields while also focussing on specifics of SURF, including existing and planned infrastructure. The conference was 2.5 days in length with an attendance of 106 people, with plenary sessions in the mornings and parallel sessions in the afternoon. A satellite workshop, on low-background research common to dark matter and neutrinoless double beta decay experiments, was held the day after this conference.<br /><br />Broader Impacts :<br /><br />One of the goals of the conference was to increase participation in SURF from scientists from neighboring states, most of which are EPSCoR states. Fifty of the participants were from South Dakota or states that border on South Dakota. To strengthen the future of underground science, there was also an emphasis on training young scientists. A poster session with prizes helped increase participation of young scientists. The $10,000 funding under this proposal was all used for partial travel support to increase participation of young scientists, under-represented minorities, and scientists from neighboring states.&nbsp; Travel awards averaging $526 each, with maximum awards $600, were granted to five post-doctoral researchers, nine graduate students, one post-baccalaureate Assistant Specialist, and 4 undergraduates.&nbsp; Maximum travel award to an in-state awardee was $300.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 08/29/2016<br>      Modified by: Richard&nbsp;W&nbsp;Schnee</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The Sanford Underground Research Facility (SURF) in Lead, South Dakota, provides a unique national resource for science that must be done deep underground. This science includes sensitive experiments that explore some of the most challenging questions facing 21st century physics, such as the origin of matter, the nature of dark matter and the properties of neutrinos. The facility also hosts experiments in other disciplines including geology, biology and engineering. This project provided funding support to increase the effectiveness of a conference on SURF science  held at the South Dakota School of Mines and Technology, an hour?s drive from SURF.   Intellectual Merit :  The intellectual merit of this project consists of support through the conference for the current and future SURF program. The Particle Physics Project Prioritization Panel (P5) recommended strong support for the SURF program in particle physics: significantly increased funding for the second-generation dark matter direct detection program, the hosting of at least one third-generation dark matter direct-detection experiment, and support for the Long Baseline Neutrino Facility, described as the highest-priority large project in its timeframe. The SURF program in nuclear physics -- including neutrinoless double beta decay, and measurements at an underground accelerator to improve understanding of critical astrophysics processes -- also takes high priority, with an underground accelerator facility for nuclear astrophysics among the top three priorities in the Long Range Plan of the 2015 Nuclear Science Advisory Committee (NSAC).  Exchange of the most recent results and ideas related to SURF science at the conference improved the effectiveness of these high-priority projects. This conference was unique in its coverage of the full SURF science program, allowing researchers to learn of synergies between fields while also focussing on specifics of SURF, including existing and planned infrastructure. The conference was 2.5 days in length with an attendance of 106 people, with plenary sessions in the mornings and parallel sessions in the afternoon. A satellite workshop, on low-background research common to dark matter and neutrinoless double beta decay experiments, was held the day after this conference.  Broader Impacts :  One of the goals of the conference was to increase participation in SURF from scientists from neighboring states, most of which are EPSCoR states. Fifty of the participants were from South Dakota or states that border on South Dakota. To strengthen the future of underground science, there was also an emphasis on training young scientists. A poster session with prizes helped increase participation of young scientists. The $10,000 funding under this proposal was all used for partial travel support to increase participation of young scientists, under-represented minorities, and scientists from neighboring states.  Travel awards averaging $526 each, with maximum awards $600, were granted to five post-doctoral researchers, nine graduate students, one post-baccalaureate Assistant Specialist, and 4 undergraduates.  Maximum travel award to an in-state awardee was $300.       Last Modified: 08/29/2016       Submitted by: Richard W Schnee]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
