<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Collaborative Research : Nonlinear Long Wave Amplification in the Shadow Zone of Offshore Islands</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2015</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>668815.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>668815</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CMMI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Civil, Mechanical, &amp; Manufact Inn</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Joy Pauschke</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>jpauschk@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927024</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Field survey reports from recent tsunamis suggest that local residents in mainland areas shadowed by nearby islands may be under the impression that these islands protect them from tsunamis.  Recent numerical results using the mathematical procedure known as "active learning" have generated substantial attention in world media (The Economist, Der Spiegel, Science, Korean Herald, Kathimerini), because they suggest that,  in most cases,  islands amplify  tsunamis in the shadow zones behind them.  In this application, the active learning methodology requires about 100,000 times fewer computations than conventional mathematical approaches, and it is unclear if the amplification effect is real.  Through comprehensive laboratory experiments, the physical manifestation of this effect will be studied.  If indeed the physical experiments confirm the numerical idealizations, this research will help save lives by better targeting educational campaigns to at risk populations.  For example, it will be determined if coastlines shadowed by offshore islands along the Pacific Coast of the US are more vulnerable than earlier believed. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The early numerical results from active learning are only applicable for non-breaking waves.  While many existing numerical codes attempt to model mild long-wave breaking, as they sometimes do, it is unclear how well they perform when scattered long waves break and interact.  It is equally unclear if the isthmus between islands scatters the wave energy or focuses further in the mainland behind them, or under what geographical conditions either effect prevails.  Through the laboratory experiments, it will be determined if this vexing phenomenon persists when waves break.  The results will help validate active learning as a mathematical procedure for uncertainty reduction which greatly reduces computational costs.  Also, a substantial laboratory data set will be developed to help benchmark numerical computations for interacting breaking wave fronts, under conditions as yet unstudied.  An outreach campaign is planned to educate populations at risk and improve the awareness of emergency managers on this unusual amplification phenomenon.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/08/2015</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/08/2015</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1538624</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Costas</FirstName>
<LastName>Synolakis</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>E</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Costas E Synolakis</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>costas@usc.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2137400613</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000466810</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/08/2015</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Patrick</FirstName>
<LastName>Lynett</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>J</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Patrick J Lynett</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>plynett@usc.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2137403133</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000606235</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/08/2015</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Southern California</Name>
<CityName>Los Angeles</CityName>
<ZipCode>900890001</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2137407762</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>University Park</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[3720 S. Flower St.]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>37</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CA37</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>072933393</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF SOUTHERN CALIFORNIA</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>072933393</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Southern California]]></Name>
<CityName>Los Angeles</CityName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>900890001</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[3720 S Flower Street]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>37</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CA37</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7396</Code>
<Text>NEES RESEARCH</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>036E</Code>
<Text>CIVIL INFRASTRUCTURE</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>043E</Code>
<Text>EARTHQUAKE ENGINEERING</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1057</Code>
<Text>CIS BASE RESEARCH</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>151E</Code>
<Text>Tsunami Research</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1576</Code>
<Text>NATIONL EARTHQK HZRD REDCT PRG</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>CVIS</Code>
<Text>CIVIL INFRASTRUCTURE</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0115</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2015~668815</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Field survey reports from &nbsp; tsunami impacts in the past decade suggest unusal and counterintuitive nearshroe amplification phenomena which cost lives exactly because they are unexpected. As an example, local residents in mainland areas shadowed by nearby islands maybe under the impression that these islands protect them from tsunamis.&nbsp;</p> <p>This is a study of the runup amplification &nbsp;in the shadow zone of the offshore islands, analytically, in the laboratory and numerically. Runup amplification (RA) is the ratio of the runup along the beach shadowed by the island to the runup that would be observed, if there was no island present. If the island amplifies the wave, then RA&gt;1, Recent numerical results using &nbsp;machine learning and examining only non--breaking waves &nbsp;have generated substantial attention in world media, because they suggest that, in most cases, islands amplify tsunamis in the shadow zones behind them. (https://www.economist.com/science-and-technology/2013/06/15/the-dangers-of-insularity)&nbsp;</p> <p>This study focused on &nbsp;the idealized bathymetry of a circular island fronting a uniformly sloping beach, as in Stefanakis et al (2014)), and laboratory experiments were conducted in a large wave basin. The study used MOST, a NSW solver, while several simulations were run with the Boussinesq--type equation solver COULWAVE. Measurements from the &nbsp;laboratory were used to assess the veracity of both codes at small scales, while exact solutions of the SW to check the veracity of MOST at geophysical scales.&nbsp;</p> <p>Two sets of experiments are presented, with one and two 1:2 slope conical islands &nbsp; fronting a 1:10 uniformly sloping beach. The particle tracking algorithm &nbsp;implemented by Kalligeris (2017) was used to track the particles between successive video frames. &nbsp; For a given inter--particle spacing, the tracking became more difficult as the flow speed increases. In other words, for faster flows, one needs more frames per second. The detection threshold turned out to be 1m/sec.&nbsp;</p> <p>The laboratory measurements were compared with both analytical results and numerical predictions. &nbsp;It was found that the analytical formulation of Kanoglu and Synolakis (1988) &nbsp;proved capable of capturing the maximum runup for the one island configuration, where it is valid; &nbsp;there is no analytical solution for two islands. It appears that both MOST and COULWAVE reproduce the maximum runup very well, both around the island and along the sloping beach. oth models reproduce the flow velocities, &nbsp;but COULWAVE also reproduces flow velocities better for highly nonlinear waves, with 0.4 initial height-to-depth ratios.&nbsp;</p> <p>Surprisingly, for very long waves on very steep beaches, a new asymptotic solution was discovered withe runup amplificaation equalt to two, to complement the classic analytical expression for a solitary wave climbing up a sloping beach known as Synolakis' runup law.</p> <p>The results suggest that both runup ampplification (RA&gt;1) and shadowing (RA&lt;1) occur, depending primarily on whether the initial wave breaks of not on the front face of the island. Shorter solitary--like initial waves break on islands with mild faces, &nbsp;and then islands appear not to shelter the coastlines behind them. Longer waves climbing up islands with steeper front faces evolve in the beginning as predicted by Synolakis (1991), then continue to climb up the sloping beach and produce high runup amplification. This is the case more likely to occur in nature.&nbsp;</p> <p>The counter intuitive phenomena described here suggest public education &nbsp;is urgently needed to help people identify locales at higher risk than others, as is the provision of high--resolution inundation maps which account for such phenomena, for evacuation planning.</p> <p><span style="color: #333333; font-family: Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif;"><span>Kalligeris_2017. N,&nbsp;</span></span><span>Tsunami-induced turbulent coherent structures. Phd Dissertation,</span></p> <div>T. S. Stefanakis,&nbsp; E. Contal,&nbsp;&nbsp;N. Vayatis,&nbsp;F. Dias and&nbsp;&nbsp;C. E. Synolakis,&nbsp;Can small islands protect nearby coasts from tsunamis? An active experimental design approach, am active experimental dean approach. Proc. R. Soc A 470:891-91</div> <div><span><br /></span></div> <div><span style="font-size: x-small;">Utku&nbsp;Kanoglu and&nbsp;</span><span>Costas Emmanuel Synolakis,</span><span>&nbsp;Long wave runup on piecewise linear topographies,&nbsp;</span><span>Journal of Fluid Mechanics</span></div> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 07/02/2020<br>      Modified by: Costas&nbsp;E&nbsp;Synolakis</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Image         </div> <div class="galControls onePhoto" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation onePhoto" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2020/1538624/1538624_10375117_1593705982478_images2--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2020/1538624/1538624_10375117_1593705982478_images2--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Two island configuration"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2020/1538624/1538624_10375117_1593705982478_images2--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Two island configuration"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Two island configuration timestep of the N-wave</div> <div class="imageCredit">Dr. Pedro Lomonaco</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Costas&nbsp;E&nbsp;Synolakis</div> <div class="imageTitle">Two island configuration</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Field survey reports from   tsunami impacts in the past decade suggest unusal and counterintuitive nearshroe amplification phenomena which cost lives exactly because they are unexpected. As an example, local residents in mainland areas shadowed by nearby islands maybe under the impression that these islands protect them from tsunamis.   This is a study of the runup amplification  in the shadow zone of the offshore islands, analytically, in the laboratory and numerically. Runup amplification (RA) is the ratio of the runup along the beach shadowed by the island to the runup that would be observed, if there was no island present. If the island amplifies the wave, then RA&gt;1, Recent numerical results using  machine learning and examining only non--breaking waves  have generated substantial attention in world media, because they suggest that, in most cases, islands amplify tsunamis in the shadow zones behind them. (https://www.economist.com/science-and-technology/2013/06/15/the-dangers-of-insularity)   This study focused on  the idealized bathymetry of a circular island fronting a uniformly sloping beach, as in Stefanakis et al (2014)), and laboratory experiments were conducted in a large wave basin. The study used MOST, a NSW solver, while several simulations were run with the Boussinesq--type equation solver COULWAVE. Measurements from the  laboratory were used to assess the veracity of both codes at small scales, while exact solutions of the SW to check the veracity of MOST at geophysical scales.   Two sets of experiments are presented, with one and two 1:2 slope conical islands   fronting a 1:10 uniformly sloping beach. The particle tracking algorithm  implemented by Kalligeris (2017) was used to track the particles between successive video frames.   For a given inter--particle spacing, the tracking became more difficult as the flow speed increases. In other words, for faster flows, one needs more frames per second. The detection threshold turned out to be 1m/sec.   The laboratory measurements were compared with both analytical results and numerical predictions.  It was found that the analytical formulation of Kanoglu and Synolakis (1988)  proved capable of capturing the maximum runup for the one island configuration, where it is valid;  there is no analytical solution for two islands. It appears that both MOST and COULWAVE reproduce the maximum runup very well, both around the island and along the sloping beach. oth models reproduce the flow velocities,  but COULWAVE also reproduces flow velocities better for highly nonlinear waves, with 0.4 initial height-to-depth ratios.   Surprisingly, for very long waves on very steep beaches, a new asymptotic solution was discovered withe runup amplificaation equalt to two, to complement the classic analytical expression for a solitary wave climbing up a sloping beach known as Synolakis' runup law.  The results suggest that both runup ampplification (RA&gt;1) and shadowing (RA&lt;1) occur, depending primarily on whether the initial wave breaks of not on the front face of the island. Shorter solitary--like initial waves break on islands with mild faces,  and then islands appear not to shelter the coastlines behind them. Longer waves climbing up islands with steeper front faces evolve in the beginning as predicted by Synolakis (1991), then continue to climb up the sloping beach and produce high runup amplification. This is the case more likely to occur in nature.   The counter intuitive phenomena described here suggest public education  is urgently needed to help people identify locales at higher risk than others, as is the provision of high--resolution inundation maps which account for such phenomena, for evacuation planning.  Kalligeris_2017. N, Tsunami-induced turbulent coherent structures. Phd Dissertation, T. S. Stefanakis,  E. Contal,  N. Vayatis, F. Dias and  C. E. Synolakis, Can small islands protect nearby coasts from tsunamis? An active experimental design approach, am active experimental dean approach. Proc. R. Soc A 470:891-91   Utku Kanoglu and Costas Emmanuel Synolakis, Long wave runup on piecewise linear topographies, Journal of Fluid Mechanics          Last Modified: 07/02/2020       Submitted by: Costas E Synolakis]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
