<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Inkjet-Electrospray Hybrid Printing: Understanding the Processing-Structure Relationship</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2015</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>399970.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>399970</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CMMI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Civil, Mechanical, &amp; Manufact Inn</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Andrew Wells</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>awells@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927225</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The ability to create thin films of functional materials addresses vital technological needs for many applications, including: flexible electronics, bio-sensing, optical coatings, energy conversion/harvesting, and data storage. As one of the dominant thin film manufacturing techniques, printing of materials underpins multi-billion dollar industries. However, the current printing methods have reached a fundamental limit that has inhibited innovation in thin film processing. The overarching goal of this research is to provide the much-needed knowledge for creating a high-resolution, scalable technique that can achieve mass production of printed patterns using a variety of functional inks. The new technique will provide manufacturers with a unique tool to print novel materials for industrial applications and consumer products. The success of this research will lay the groundwork for changing the paradigm of thin film processing and will have an impact on accelerating manufacturing innovation in the United States. In addition, the integration of undergraduate and graduate students into this research will provide industry with the highly qualified and experienced personnel they need to expand the commercial use of thin film additive manufacturing.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project aims to combine inkjet technology and electrospray printing to create a hybrid printing technique that provides the advantages of photolithography and traditional printing, namely, high feature resolution, material versatility, material conservation, and control over microstructure. Using electrospray, dry colloidal material is delivered to the surface of inkjet-printed sacrificial rivulets to form colloidal monolayers. The monolayers are subsequently transferred to the substrate upon complete evaporation of the rivulets to create self-assembled, close-packed nanoparticle monolayers. Unique mechanical, electrical, and optical properties can emerge in the monolayers by controlling the deposit structure on the length scale of an individual particle. This research will integrate computational modeling and experimental approaches to discover the fundamental relationships among the process parameters, printing dynamics, and final deposit structure. Advanced imaging techniques will be used to characterize the time evolution of this complex system and the final deposits. A novel two-way coupled Lagrangian particle tracking-lattice Boltzmann model will be developed to provide fundamental insight into the electrospray of nanoparticles, the physico-chemical hydrodynamics of the evaporating rivulet, and the self-organization of particles at the interface and subsequent deposition. With a greater understanding of this hybrid printing process, the research team will design and build an integrated hybrid printhead that encompass an inkjet nozzle and electrospray emitter for scalable processing.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/26/2015</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/26/2015</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1538090</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Timothy</FirstName>
<LastName>Singler</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>J</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Timothy J Singler</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>singler@binghamton.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6077774330</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000201678</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/26/2015</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Paul</FirstName>
<LastName>Chiarot</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Paul Chiarot</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>pchiarot@binghamton.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6077773208</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000616893</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/26/2015</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Xin</FirstName>
<LastName>Yong</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Xin Yong</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>xyong@binghamton.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6077774981</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000679199</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/26/2015</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>SUNY at Binghamton</Name>
<CityName>BINGHAMTON</CityName>
<ZipCode>139026000</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6077776136</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>4400 VESTAL PKWY E</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[PO Box 6000]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>22</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NY22</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>090189965</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>RESEARCH FOUNDATION FOR THE STATE UNIVERSITY OF NEW YORK, THE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>020657151</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[SUNY at Binghamton]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<ZipCode>139026000</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>22</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NY22</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>8092</Code>
<Text>Materials Eng. &amp; Processing</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1444</Code>
<Text>SURFACE ENGINEERING</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8021</Code>
<Text>Materials Engineering</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8025</Code>
<Text>Advanced Materials Processing</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0115</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2015~399970</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p class="Default">The main goal of this project was to create a novel additive manufacturing technique by combining inkjet printing and electrospray atomization. This hybrid printing method enables high-resolution, scalable manufacturing of thin-film materials for electronic, photonic, and biomedical applications. The work supported by this award focused on discovering the fundamental processing-structure relationship of this hybrid printing methodology using both computational and experimental approaches. Specifically, we performed computational modeling to investigate the coupled mass and heat transfer processes involved in inkjet printing and electrospray targeting on various length scales. On the nanoscale, we exploited many-body dissipative particle dynamics to predict the suppressed evaporation of a liquid-vapor interface caused by a nanoparticle monolayer covering the interface. This result provides important insight into the interplay of evaporation and colloidal assembly at fluid interfaces. On the mesoscale, we created a novel lattice Boltzmann-Brownian dynamics model to discover how the assembly and deposition of colloids are governed by contact line dynamics, evaporation-driven flow, and the moving surface of the drying droplet. The simulations revealed the distinct dynamics of particles confined on the interface compared to the ones dispersed in the bulk. The computational work has been extended to surfactant-laden droplets and nonspherical sessile droplets, in which Marangoni flow and long-range interfacial forces play a critical role in determining the deposition patterns. On the microscale, we have developed an axisymmetric lattice Boltzmann method to explore droplet impact on flat and curved substrates with different wettability, focusing on understanding morphology evolution and contact time during impact. These computer simulations have provided consolidated guidelines <span>for the experimental efforts of this research.</span></p> <p class="Default">Experiments were conducted using electrospray to deliver dry colloids to the interface of sessile droplets. The particles adsorbed at the interface and were used as tracers to probe the interfacial flow during evaporation. It was found that the presence and type of surfactant in the spray played a significant role in governing the particle transport and final deposit structure. When no surfactant was present, there was no observable convection of the interfacial particles, and the final deposit was uniformly distributed. When a small surfactant (sodium dodecyl sulfate, SDS) was present in the spray solution (and delivered to the interface), there was a net motion of the interfacial particles towards the apex of the target droplet. This was due to the presence of a strong Marangoni flow. SDS was able to desorb from the interface at a sufficient rate into the bulk of the target droplet. It was then transported to the contact line (due to the ?coffee ring? phenomena), setting up a surface tension gradient along the droplet interface. The use of large surfactants (Tween 80) did not initiate a Marangoni flow, since it was unable to desorb at a sufficient rate over the time scale of the target droplet evaporation. As a result, the final deposit was more uniformly distributed (similar to the no surfactant case). In addition to sessile droplet targets, experiments were also conducted on liquid rivulets to probe the interfacial transport for this non-axisymmetric case. To obtain a more comprehensive understanding of rivulet transport, the bulk flow inside the rivulet was probed using particle tracking velocimetry for varying alcohol content. The presence of alcohol induced strong Marangoni convection in the transverse direction inside the evaporating rivulet. Fluid transport and particle deposition for inkjet printed liquid rivulets has important implications for materials printing in electronics manufacturing.</p> <p class="Default"><span>This project has trained students at both the undergraduate and graduate levels, developed new educational opportunities, and increased public awareness of research in additive manufacturing. Three PhD students and four undergraduate students (two female students) have been supported by this award. These students developed interdisciplinary skills in manufacturing, materials engineering, and high-performance computing while contributing to the major goals of the project. The findings of this research have been disseminated through numerous journal and conference publications and by the media as news stories to the broader community. This project also supported an annual advanced manufacturing lab tour to engage K-12 students and their parents.</span></p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 11/25/2019<br>      Modified by: Xin&nbsp;Yong</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[The main goal of this project was to create a novel additive manufacturing technique by combining inkjet printing and electrospray atomization. This hybrid printing method enables high-resolution, scalable manufacturing of thin-film materials for electronic, photonic, and biomedical applications. The work supported by this award focused on discovering the fundamental processing-structure relationship of this hybrid printing methodology using both computational and experimental approaches. Specifically, we performed computational modeling to investigate the coupled mass and heat transfer processes involved in inkjet printing and electrospray targeting on various length scales. On the nanoscale, we exploited many-body dissipative particle dynamics to predict the suppressed evaporation of a liquid-vapor interface caused by a nanoparticle monolayer covering the interface. This result provides important insight into the interplay of evaporation and colloidal assembly at fluid interfaces. On the mesoscale, we created a novel lattice Boltzmann-Brownian dynamics model to discover how the assembly and deposition of colloids are governed by contact line dynamics, evaporation-driven flow, and the moving surface of the drying droplet. The simulations revealed the distinct dynamics of particles confined on the interface compared to the ones dispersed in the bulk. The computational work has been extended to surfactant-laden droplets and nonspherical sessile droplets, in which Marangoni flow and long-range interfacial forces play a critical role in determining the deposition patterns. On the microscale, we have developed an axisymmetric lattice Boltzmann method to explore droplet impact on flat and curved substrates with different wettability, focusing on understanding morphology evolution and contact time during impact. These computer simulations have provided consolidated guidelines for the experimental efforts of this research. Experiments were conducted using electrospray to deliver dry colloids to the interface of sessile droplets. The particles adsorbed at the interface and were used as tracers to probe the interfacial flow during evaporation. It was found that the presence and type of surfactant in the spray played a significant role in governing the particle transport and final deposit structure. When no surfactant was present, there was no observable convection of the interfacial particles, and the final deposit was uniformly distributed. When a small surfactant (sodium dodecyl sulfate, SDS) was present in the spray solution (and delivered to the interface), there was a net motion of the interfacial particles towards the apex of the target droplet. This was due to the presence of a strong Marangoni flow. SDS was able to desorb from the interface at a sufficient rate into the bulk of the target droplet. It was then transported to the contact line (due to the ?coffee ring? phenomena), setting up a surface tension gradient along the droplet interface. The use of large surfactants (Tween 80) did not initiate a Marangoni flow, since it was unable to desorb at a sufficient rate over the time scale of the target droplet evaporation. As a result, the final deposit was more uniformly distributed (similar to the no surfactant case). In addition to sessile droplet targets, experiments were also conducted on liquid rivulets to probe the interfacial transport for this non-axisymmetric case. To obtain a more comprehensive understanding of rivulet transport, the bulk flow inside the rivulet was probed using particle tracking velocimetry for varying alcohol content. The presence of alcohol induced strong Marangoni convection in the transverse direction inside the evaporating rivulet. Fluid transport and particle deposition for inkjet printed liquid rivulets has important implications for materials printing in electronics manufacturing. This project has trained students at both the undergraduate and graduate levels, developed new educational opportunities, and increased public awareness of research in additive manufacturing. Three PhD students and four undergraduate students (two female students) have been supported by this award. These students developed interdisciplinary skills in manufacturing, materials engineering, and high-performance computing while contributing to the major goals of the project. The findings of this research have been disseminated through numerous journal and conference publications and by the media as news stories to the broader community. This project also supported an annual advanced manufacturing lab tour to engage K-12 students and their parents.       Last Modified: 11/25/2019       Submitted by: Xin Yong]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
