<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>CyberSEES: Type 1: Enabling Sustainable Water Supplies Through Self-Powered Sensor-Based Monitoring</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2015</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>396011.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>396011</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>05010000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>CSE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CCF</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division of Computing and Communication Foundations</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>David Corman</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>dcorman@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032928754</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The worldwide demand for freshwater is increasing rapidly while water resources are becoming increasingly scarce. Exacerbating this imbalance is the deteriorated state of the water distribution infrastructure, which is afflicted with leakages of 15-25% of the total water supply. Consequently, the severe deterioration of this infrastructure poses a serious challenge to water sustainability. Leakage detection is an essential, but challenging, aspect of water supply management. Real-time monitoring schemes based on the changes in the vibration characteristics of the water pipelines have potential to detect leaks in a timely manner. Embedded wireless sensor networks are essential for such monitoring schemes; however, model designs and architectures of currently available wireless sensing networks remain severely constrained by the small energy reserves of environmentally-harmful batteries that last only for a limited period of time. This CyberSEES project is exploring possible hardware and software schemes for embedded wireless sensing systems, powered by locally harvested energy, to detect leakages in water distribution systems.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Leveraging a real-size, experimental pipeline set-up, this project explores (1) the energy harvesting potential in the water distribution system environment for use in sustainable powering of smart embedded sensing networks; (2) the use of vibration sensing-based methods to detect and locate pipeline leaks in water distribution systems; and (3) energy-efficient sensing and communication schemes suitable for use in constrained and variable energy environments. With advancements on several fronts, the research outcomes will make it possible to build smarter and adaptable water supply infrastructures for a more sustainable future.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;By adopting the developed sustainable monitoring set-up, water utilities will be equipped to prevent leakage of treated fresh water, conserve energy, and potentially prevent catastrophic failures in water distribution systems through early-detection of defects. The developed wireless sensing-based monitoring scheme can be easily adapted to other harsh, dynamic and energy-constrained environments for defect detection. The impact of this project on research infrastructure, especially the expansion of the pipeline test bed on the Clemson University campus, is significant as it offers several follow-up research and educational opportunities. This project also offers research opportunities for undergraduates and underrepresented students in addition to graduate student mentoring.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/25/2015</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/25/2015</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.070</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1539536</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Abdul</FirstName>
<LastName>Khan</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>A</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Abdul A Khan</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>abdkhan@clemson.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>8646563327</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000482163</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/25/2015</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Sez</FirstName>
<LastName>Atamturktur Russcher</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Sez Atamturktur Russcher</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>sez@psu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>8646437909</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000574977</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/25/2015</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Jacob</FirstName>
<LastName>Sorber</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Jacob Sorber</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>jsorber@clemson.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>8018855071</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000587927</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/25/2015</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Kalyan</FirstName>
<LastName>Piratla</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Kalyan Piratla</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>kpiratl@clemson.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>8646563324</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000641883</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/25/2015</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Clemson University</Name>
<CityName>CLEMSON</CityName>
<ZipCode>296345701</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>8646562424</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>230 Kappa Street</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[Suite 200]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>South Carolina</StateName>
<StateCode>SC</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>SC03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>042629816</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>CLEMSON UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>042629816</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Clemson University]]></Name>
<CityName>Clemson</CityName>
<StateCode>SC</StateCode>
<ZipCode>296340001</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[300 Brackett Hall]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>South Carolina</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>SC03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>8211</Code>
<Text>CyberSEES</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8207</Code>
<Text>CyberSEES Type 1</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8231</Code>
<Text>CyberSEES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0115</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2015~396011</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>It is estimated that 15-25% of treated freshwater is lost in distribution pipelines through leakages in the United States. Continuous monitoring schemes based on the change in the vibrational characteristics of water pipelines have the potential to detect leaks in a timely manner. Embedded wireless sensor networks are essential for such monitoring schemes; however, model designs and architectures of currently available wireless sensing networks remain severely constrained by the small energy reserves of environmentally harmful batteries that last only for a limited period of time. This CyberSEES project explored the possibility of using non-intrusive vibration monitoring schemes for detecting leakages and assessing their severities. This project also explored the energy harvesting potential in buried water pipelines for powering the leakage monitoring equipment in a sustainable manner. The findings from this project can be classified into three categories based on their intellectual merits:</p> <p>(1)&nbsp;&nbsp; The leak detection index (LDI) technique developed in this project is different from the previous acoustics-based techniques in that it uses a correlation function to increase data-fidelity, while monitoring the variation in the cross-spectral density of the pipeline?s vibrational response under operational conditions for detecting leakage presence. This physics-based technique was found to be promising based on a two-phase controlled experimental evaluation carried out on a buried plastic (PVC) pipeline test bed built on Clemson University campus. Plastic pipelines have been reported to be difficult for leakage detection using conventional techniques. Further development and testing of the LDI technique for practical uses beyond the proof-of-concept testing carried out in this study will likely enable water utilities across the U.S. to more proactively detect significant leakages in their systems to be able to respond in a timely manner.</p> <p>(2)&nbsp;&nbsp; Furthermore, this project evaluated the capability of a deep learning algorithm, namely convolutional neural networks (CNNs), to predict leakage presence and severity based on data from a single monitoring location. Specifically, vibration signal data collected from the experimental test bed were converted to scalogram images which were shown to be different for leakages of various severities using the image classifying CNN algorithm. The CNN algorithm used in this study proved to be effective in leakage detection and localization with an approximate accuracy of 95% on both buried and unburied sections of PVC pipeline testbed. The advantage of using the CNN algorithm is that it does not require extensive data pre-processing and only requires an acceleration signal from a single accelerometer, whereas the LDI technique or other conventional techniques require data from at least a pair of locations to detect leakages.</p> <p>(3)&nbsp;&nbsp; The energy harvesting analyses that was focused on harvesting energy from pipeline surface vibrations have revealed that there might not be sufficient power available at all the locations to power sensing and communication systems; it may, however, be possible to efficiently use the small amounts of power to monitor pipelines for leakage detection. For example, harvested energy over several hours may be stored in a capacitor to power a sensor that can collect and transmit data for a few seconds to minutes every day. The conversion of AC current that is harvested from the ambient pipeline environment to DC current that is required to power monitoring sensors is found to be inefficient for low voltages observed in the experimental work using the current conversion tools. Furthermore, harvesting energy from the flow turbulence inside the pipeline in an intrusive manner may offer adequate amount of power. This is an ongoing research effort that may yield promising results, but the suitability of intrusive harvesters for water pipeline systems is doubtful because of the access and other constraints.</p> <p>The&nbsp;broader impact of this research project includes: (a) development of algorithms for near real-time leakage detection will enable water utilities to be better aware of their pipelines? condition and possibly intervene to save large amount of treated water, preserve the embedded energy that is spent on collecting, treating and distributing the otherwise lost water, and potentially prevent future catastrophic failures; (b) one of the proposed approaches uses a deep learning image classification algorithm to minimize extensive pre-processing and transformation of the raw signal data, to bypass the characterization of the structural system dynamics, to minimize the number of monitoring locations, to minimize human discretion and the associated misinterpretations; (c) development of data collection and hardware schemes for evaluating energy harvesting potential in low power and uncertain energy environments will be broadly impactful beyond this project; (d) dissemination of the research findings in the form of several peer-reviewed technical publications and presentations made at national and international conferences has made the scientific research community and direct beneficiaries such as utility owners and consultants more aware of the techniques evaluated in this study and their applications for addressing the leakage detection issues in the real-world.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 11/28/2019<br>      Modified by: Kalyan&nbsp;Piratla</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ It is estimated that 15-25% of treated freshwater is lost in distribution pipelines through leakages in the United States. Continuous monitoring schemes based on the change in the vibrational characteristics of water pipelines have the potential to detect leaks in a timely manner. Embedded wireless sensor networks are essential for such monitoring schemes; however, model designs and architectures of currently available wireless sensing networks remain severely constrained by the small energy reserves of environmentally harmful batteries that last only for a limited period of time. This CyberSEES project explored the possibility of using non-intrusive vibration monitoring schemes for detecting leakages and assessing their severities. This project also explored the energy harvesting potential in buried water pipelines for powering the leakage monitoring equipment in a sustainable manner. The findings from this project can be classified into three categories based on their intellectual merits:  (1)   The leak detection index (LDI) technique developed in this project is different from the previous acoustics-based techniques in that it uses a correlation function to increase data-fidelity, while monitoring the variation in the cross-spectral density of the pipeline?s vibrational response under operational conditions for detecting leakage presence. This physics-based technique was found to be promising based on a two-phase controlled experimental evaluation carried out on a buried plastic (PVC) pipeline test bed built on Clemson University campus. Plastic pipelines have been reported to be difficult for leakage detection using conventional techniques. Further development and testing of the LDI technique for practical uses beyond the proof-of-concept testing carried out in this study will likely enable water utilities across the U.S. to more proactively detect significant leakages in their systems to be able to respond in a timely manner.  (2)   Furthermore, this project evaluated the capability of a deep learning algorithm, namely convolutional neural networks (CNNs), to predict leakage presence and severity based on data from a single monitoring location. Specifically, vibration signal data collected from the experimental test bed were converted to scalogram images which were shown to be different for leakages of various severities using the image classifying CNN algorithm. The CNN algorithm used in this study proved to be effective in leakage detection and localization with an approximate accuracy of 95% on both buried and unburied sections of PVC pipeline testbed. The advantage of using the CNN algorithm is that it does not require extensive data pre-processing and only requires an acceleration signal from a single accelerometer, whereas the LDI technique or other conventional techniques require data from at least a pair of locations to detect leakages.  (3)   The energy harvesting analyses that was focused on harvesting energy from pipeline surface vibrations have revealed that there might not be sufficient power available at all the locations to power sensing and communication systems; it may, however, be possible to efficiently use the small amounts of power to monitor pipelines for leakage detection. For example, harvested energy over several hours may be stored in a capacitor to power a sensor that can collect and transmit data for a few seconds to minutes every day. The conversion of AC current that is harvested from the ambient pipeline environment to DC current that is required to power monitoring sensors is found to be inefficient for low voltages observed in the experimental work using the current conversion tools. Furthermore, harvesting energy from the flow turbulence inside the pipeline in an intrusive manner may offer adequate amount of power. This is an ongoing research effort that may yield promising results, but the suitability of intrusive harvesters for water pipeline systems is doubtful because of the access and other constraints.  The broader impact of this research project includes: (a) development of algorithms for near real-time leakage detection will enable water utilities to be better aware of their pipelines? condition and possibly intervene to save large amount of treated water, preserve the embedded energy that is spent on collecting, treating and distributing the otherwise lost water, and potentially prevent future catastrophic failures; (b) one of the proposed approaches uses a deep learning image classification algorithm to minimize extensive pre-processing and transformation of the raw signal data, to bypass the characterization of the structural system dynamics, to minimize the number of monitoring locations, to minimize human discretion and the associated misinterpretations; (c) development of data collection and hardware schemes for evaluating energy harvesting potential in low power and uncertain energy environments will be broadly impactful beyond this project; (d) dissemination of the research findings in the form of several peer-reviewed technical publications and presentations made at national and international conferences has made the scientific research community and direct beneficiaries such as utility owners and consultants more aware of the techniques evaluated in this study and their applications for addressing the leakage detection issues in the real-world.       Last Modified: 11/28/2019       Submitted by: Kalyan Piratla]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
