<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>EarthCube IA: Collaborative Proposal: Cross-Domain Observational Metadata Environmental Sensing Network (X-DOMES)</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2015</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>55288.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>55288</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>06010000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>GEO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>ICER</Abbreviation>
<LongName>ICER</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Eva Zanzerkia</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>ezanzerk@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924734</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Across-domains, agencies and political boundaries, our environment is being continuously observed and studied.  The researchers in this project are looking for short-term, near-term and long-term changes while researching new and evolving methods to observe properties and to process the collected observations.  Emerging technologies enable us to provide and discover the data openly and freely.  But, if we do not understand the newly discovered data, with its inherent limitations and biases, it cannot be responsibly utilized for new or collaborative research efforts.  Working with environmental sensor manufacturers and researchers, the X-DOMES project will develop tools and social and technical infrastructure to facilitate the creation of data about data (metadata).   Metadata describes not only who, when and where the observations were made, but also it must document how an observation came to be (provenance).  By taking this knowledge out of manuals and human-readable documents, the X-DOMES model creates metadata that can be treated like data ? discoverable and searchable, making it ready to be incorporated into automated archival and processing for quality assurance and validation methods. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Leveraging existing relationships with large NSF-funded data management programs, EarthCube building blocks and working groups, and environmental sensor manufacturers and consortia, we will establish a community of sensor manufacturers and other stakeholders to provide a unifying approach to describing sensors and observations across geo-science domains.  Built on an existing sensor metadata model that references registered, standards-based vocabularies, the X-DOMES pilot project will provide a suite of tools, built upon community-adopted standards of the Open Geospatial Consortium (OGC) and World Wide Web Consortium (W3C) to demonstrate and facilitate the generation of documents that are discoverable and accessible on-line and/or directly from onboard sensor descriptions.  The project will also demonstrate mechanisms to associate the data with the metadata through standards-based web services.  With vendor-ready tools implemented throughout a broad-based community, the X-DOMES Network will lay the foundation for the development of and adoption of interoperable access to much needed content-rich sensor metadata.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/18/2015</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/18/2015</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.050</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1540849</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Krzysztof</FirstName>
<LastName>Janowicz</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>W</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Krzysztof W Janowicz</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>jano@geog.ucsb.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>8058802572</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000582770</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/18/2015</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of California-Santa Barbara</Name>
<CityName>Santa Barbara</CityName>
<ZipCode>931062050</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>8058934188</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>Office of Research</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[Rm 3227 Cheadle Hall]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>24</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CA24</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>094878394</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF CALIFORNIA, SANTA BARBARA</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>071549000</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Dept. of Geography, UC Santa Barbara]]></Name>
<CityName>Santa Barbara</CityName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>931064060</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[1832 Ellison Hall]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>24</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CA24</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>8074</Code>
<Text>EarthCube</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7433</Code>
<Text>CyberInfra Frmwrk 21st (CIF21)</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0115</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2015~55288</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Sensors are a crucial data source for geo-scientists today. While such sensor readings may be published as mere values, searching, reusing, integrating, and interpreting these data requires more than just the observation results. For a meaningful interpretation of these results, additional information about the studied feature of interest, the observed property, the sampling strategy, and a variety of other information is of equal importance. From the perspective of reusability and reproducibility, such information acts as provenance records that put the observation results into context.<br /><br />The Open Geospatial Consortium (OGC) has published a collection of standards for Sensor Web Enablement to provide a commonly agreed on means to annotate sensors and their observations. While widely used, these standards are not integrated and aligned with recommendations of the World Wide Web Consortium (W3C) on data publishing on the Web, and more specifically with the set of standards describing Semantic Web technologies and Linked Data. These standards provide the basic building blocks for many of today's knowledge graphs and advanced cyber-infrastructures for the publication, retrieval, access, and reuse of data. For Earthcube's sucess it would, be important to have a layer that bridges between OGC and W3C standards.<br /><br />The X-DOMES project aims at providing a suite of tools and best practice guides, built upon the aforementioned standards, to demonstrate and facilitate the generation of metadata records that are discoverable and accessible online and describe the properties of sensors, sensing procedures, and the properties they observe, thereby fostering interoperability and reuse. By involving sensor manufacturers, key repositories, and end users, X-DOMES helps to record contextual observation data without the need to enter this data repeatedly or having to match data such as measurement types across repositories. <br /><br />Within the X-DOMES project, UCSB Geography took on the task to develop a vocabulary (a set of ontologies) to describe sensors, their properties, such as their survival range, the procedures they implement, samples, and sampling activities, observations and their results, the features being sampled and observed, an so forth.&nbsp; The resulting modular collection of ontologies was created during a two-year period as part of the 'Spatial Data on the Web' working group, the first joint working group of the OGC and W3C. The results have been published as a joint standard called SSN and are accessible at https://www.w3.org/TR/vocab-ssn/ .&nbsp; SSN builds upon lessons learned from the initial W3C-XG SSN incubator group, various OGC standards such as Observations and Measurements , as well as end-user and developer feedback.<br /><br />This is a very significant and far-reaching result as SSN is not only the first joint standard (together with OWL-Time) but also because the developed ontologies&nbsp; targets a broader range of use cases and user levels than before. These range from individual domain scientists wanting to annotate their data using a simple and intuitive model to repository holder, knowledge engineers, and sensor manufacturers. For instance, the SOSA ontology (as part of the SSN standard) targets an audience that benefits most from a lightweight vocabulary in the spirit of Schema.org, while sensor manufacturers are more likely to be interested in the sensor capabilities module of SSN. Thus, the X-DOMES project results delivered by UCSB Geography will significantly contribute to publishing and retrieving geo-science data in a style and level of simplicity that was only available for publishing and finding Web pages today. <br /><br />During the second project year, i.e., the reporting period from 2016-17, UCSB took on a leading role in this development. More specifically, the previously conceptualized models were implemented using the Resource Description Framework and the Web Ontology Language, test cases and implementation evidence were collected to show uptake in academia and industry, the modularization of the vertical and horizontal ontologies was developed and implemented, and the specifications were written and published. Each of these steps was carried out with an international team of experts and underwent multiple reviews and rounds of corrections and improvements during each phase. Aside from the final standardization document&nbsp; (https://www.w3.org/TR/vocab-ssn/), project results have been published in:<br /><br />1. Linda van den Brink, Payam Barnaghi, Jeremy Tandy, Ghislain Atemezing, Rob Atkinson, Byron Cochrane, Yasmin Fathy, Ra&uacute;l Garcia Castro, Armin Haller, Andreas Harth, Krzysztof Janowicz, Sefki Kolozali, Bart van Leeuwen, Maxime Lefran&ccedil;ois, Josh Lieberman, Andrea Perego, Danh Le-Phuoc, Bill Roberts, Kerry Taylor, and Raph&auml;el Troncy (2018): "Best Practices for Publishing, Retrieving, and Using Spatial Data on the Web". Semantic Web Journal. IOS Press.<br /><br />2. Krzysztof Janowicz, Armin Haller, Simon J D Cox, Danh Le Phuoc, and Maxime Lefrancois (under review): "SOSA: A Lightweight Ontology for Sensors, Observations, Samples, and Actuators". Journal of Web Semantics. Elsevier.<br /><br />3. Armin Haller, Krzysztof Janowicz, Simon J D Cox, Maxime Lefran&ccedil;ois, Kerry Taylor, Danh Le Phuoc, Joshua Lieberman, Ra&uacute;l Garc&iacute;a-Castro, Rob Atkinson, and Claus Stadler (under review): "The SOSA/SSN Ontology: A Joint W3C and OGC Standard Specifying the Semantics of Sensors, Observations, Actuation, and Sampling". Semantic Web Journal. IOS Press.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 01/18/2018<br>      Modified by: Krzysztof&nbsp;W&nbsp;Janowicz</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Sensors are a crucial data source for geo-scientists today. While such sensor readings may be published as mere values, searching, reusing, integrating, and interpreting these data requires more than just the observation results. For a meaningful interpretation of these results, additional information about the studied feature of interest, the observed property, the sampling strategy, and a variety of other information is of equal importance. From the perspective of reusability and reproducibility, such information acts as provenance records that put the observation results into context.  The Open Geospatial Consortium (OGC) has published a collection of standards for Sensor Web Enablement to provide a commonly agreed on means to annotate sensors and their observations. While widely used, these standards are not integrated and aligned with recommendations of the World Wide Web Consortium (W3C) on data publishing on the Web, and more specifically with the set of standards describing Semantic Web technologies and Linked Data. These standards provide the basic building blocks for many of today's knowledge graphs and advanced cyber-infrastructures for the publication, retrieval, access, and reuse of data. For Earthcube's sucess it would, be important to have a layer that bridges between OGC and W3C standards.  The X-DOMES project aims at providing a suite of tools and best practice guides, built upon the aforementioned standards, to demonstrate and facilitate the generation of metadata records that are discoverable and accessible online and describe the properties of sensors, sensing procedures, and the properties they observe, thereby fostering interoperability and reuse. By involving sensor manufacturers, key repositories, and end users, X-DOMES helps to record contextual observation data without the need to enter this data repeatedly or having to match data such as measurement types across repositories.   Within the X-DOMES project, UCSB Geography took on the task to develop a vocabulary (a set of ontologies) to describe sensors, their properties, such as their survival range, the procedures they implement, samples, and sampling activities, observations and their results, the features being sampled and observed, an so forth.  The resulting modular collection of ontologies was created during a two-year period as part of the 'Spatial Data on the Web' working group, the first joint working group of the OGC and W3C. The results have been published as a joint standard called SSN and are accessible at https://www.w3.org/TR/vocab-ssn/ .  SSN builds upon lessons learned from the initial W3C-XG SSN incubator group, various OGC standards such as Observations and Measurements , as well as end-user and developer feedback.  This is a very significant and far-reaching result as SSN is not only the first joint standard (together with OWL-Time) but also because the developed ontologies  targets a broader range of use cases and user levels than before. These range from individual domain scientists wanting to annotate their data using a simple and intuitive model to repository holder, knowledge engineers, and sensor manufacturers. For instance, the SOSA ontology (as part of the SSN standard) targets an audience that benefits most from a lightweight vocabulary in the spirit of Schema.org, while sensor manufacturers are more likely to be interested in the sensor capabilities module of SSN. Thus, the X-DOMES project results delivered by UCSB Geography will significantly contribute to publishing and retrieving geo-science data in a style and level of simplicity that was only available for publishing and finding Web pages today.   During the second project year, i.e., the reporting period from 2016-17, UCSB took on a leading role in this development. More specifically, the previously conceptualized models were implemented using the Resource Description Framework and the Web Ontology Language, test cases and implementation evidence were collected to show uptake in academia and industry, the modularization of the vertical and horizontal ontologies was developed and implemented, and the specifications were written and published. Each of these steps was carried out with an international team of experts and underwent multiple reviews and rounds of corrections and improvements during each phase. Aside from the final standardization document  (https://www.w3.org/TR/vocab-ssn/), project results have been published in:  1. Linda van den Brink, Payam Barnaghi, Jeremy Tandy, Ghislain Atemezing, Rob Atkinson, Byron Cochrane, Yasmin Fathy, Ra&uacute;l Garcia Castro, Armin Haller, Andreas Harth, Krzysztof Janowicz, Sefki Kolozali, Bart van Leeuwen, Maxime Lefran&ccedil;ois, Josh Lieberman, Andrea Perego, Danh Le-Phuoc, Bill Roberts, Kerry Taylor, and Raph&auml;el Troncy (2018): "Best Practices for Publishing, Retrieving, and Using Spatial Data on the Web". Semantic Web Journal. IOS Press.  2. Krzysztof Janowicz, Armin Haller, Simon J D Cox, Danh Le Phuoc, and Maxime Lefrancois (under review): "SOSA: A Lightweight Ontology for Sensors, Observations, Samples, and Actuators". Journal of Web Semantics. Elsevier.  3. Armin Haller, Krzysztof Janowicz, Simon J D Cox, Maxime Lefran&ccedil;ois, Kerry Taylor, Danh Le Phuoc, Joshua Lieberman, Ra&uacute;l Garc&iacute;a-Castro, Rob Atkinson, and Claus Stadler (under review): "The SOSA/SSN Ontology: A Joint W3C and OGC Standard Specifying the Semantics of Sensors, Observations, Actuation, and Sampling". Semantic Web Journal. IOS Press.       Last Modified: 01/18/2018       Submitted by: Krzysztof W Janowicz]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
