<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Optics and the Brain Topical Meeting</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>06/01/2015</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>11/30/2015</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>15000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>15000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07020000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CBET</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Chem, Bioeng, Env, &amp; Transp Sys</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Leon Esterowitz</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>lesterow@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927942</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>PI: Rogan, Elizabeth &lt;br/&gt;Proposal No.: 1540895 &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The high level of technical development stimulated by the BRAIN initiatives is drawing new researchers into the field from diverse disciplines ranging from chemistry and genetics, to laser optics and neurosurgery. OSA has identified the urgent need for a forum where these researchers can come together and discuss optics in the brain at many levels. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The researchers will participate in discussions of highly technical components of optical design and optical interactions with tissue. They will also consider the motivating factors in developing optical tools for neuroscience research across organisms, from cells and flies to rodents and humans. This meeting will provide a forum for presentation of results from projects related to the BRAIN initiative and Human Brain Project, and will stimulate new ideas and collaborations that will provide visionary direction for future projects. In addition this meeting will provide an opportunity for students, trainees and young investigators to present their work, and to hear and network with internationally-renowned invited speakers who represent the broad diversity of this burgeoning field. This meeting will serve to shape the careers of young trainees embarking on careers in which optics and the brain converge.&lt;br/&gt;The Optics and the Brain meeting will be held at the Pinnacle Vancouver Harbourside Hotel, Vancouver, Canada April 12-15, 2015.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>05/19/2015</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/19/2015</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1540895</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Elizabeth</FirstName>
<LastName>Hillman</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Elizabeth Hillman</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>eh2245@columbia.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2128542788</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000091005</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/19/2015</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Elizabeth</FirstName>
<LastName>Rogan</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Elizabeth Rogan</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>02MR145737ALIAS@SIDDUPLICATE.sid</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2024161925</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000684833</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/19/2015</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Optical Society of America</Name>
<CityName>Washington</CityName>
<ZipCode>200361012</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2024166102</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>2010 Massachusetts Avenue NW</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>District of Columbia</StateName>
<StateCode>DC</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>00</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>DC00</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>074825845</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>OPTICAL SOCIETY OF AMERICA, INCORPORATED THE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Optical Society of America, Inc.]]></Name>
<CityName>Washington</CityName>
<StateCode>DC</StateCode>
<ZipCode>200361012</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[2010 Massachusetts Avenue NW]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>District of Columbia</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>00</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>DC00</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7236</Code>
<Text>BioP-Biophotonics</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>005E</Code>
<Text>Neuro-photonics</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7556</Code>
<Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8089</Code>
<Text>Understanding the Brain/Cognitive Scienc</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8091</Code>
<Text>BRAIN Initiative Res Support</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0115</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2015~15000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><strong>2015 OSA Biomedical Optics &amp; Photonics Congress: Optics in the Life Sciences &ldquo;Optics and the Brain&rdquo;NSF FINAL REPORT <br /></strong></p> <p><strong>Principal Investigator:</strong> Elizabeth Rogan, Executive Director, The Optical Society (OSA)<br />The Optical Society (OSA) is thankful to the National Science Foundation (NSF) for your grant award of $15,000. Critical support was provided by the NSF to assist in reduction of registration fees to increase participation and enhance diversity of speakers, presenters, attendees and students in the important exchange and dissemination of research. This Final Report is a review of the accomplishments and activities of the funded event and is accompanied by an attachment of the OSA Biomedical Optics and Photonics Congress: Optics in the Life Scinces Program Book. The specific &ldquo;Optics and the Brain&rdquo; Conference within the congress was held April 12-15, 2015 and attended by 84 participants. NSF provided registration assistance eight (8) student participants.<br /> <br /> Significant advances in the development of optical techniques have led to an ever increasing role of optics in the study of and treatment of various problems in the life sciences ranging from molecular level investigations to clinical treatment of patients. Optics and the Brain is a new OSA topical meeting to be included in a larger &lsquo;Optics in the Life Sciences Congress&rsquo;.</p> <p>&nbsp;A unique advantage of this co-location of several additional small meetings was encouraging further cross-fertilization between experts in diverse areas of biomedical optics. For example, neuroscientists at the forefront of optical applications were able to attend talks on optical trapping, while experts in the development of molecular probes for cancer diagnosis had the chance to see speakers at the forefront of optogenetics.&nbsp; In terms of similar meetings, while several of the larger optics and biomedical optics meetings (such as SPIE Photonics West (held annually e.g. 7-12<sup>th</sup> February 2015, San Francisco, CA), OSA Biomed (held biennially, e.g. 26-30<sup>th</sup> April 2014, Miami FL),&nbsp; OSA Frontiers in Optics (FIO) (held annually e.g. 18-22<sup>nd</sup> October 2014, Rochester NY) and SPIE/OSA The European Conference on Biomedical Optics (ECBO) (held biennially, e.g. 21-25<sup>th</sup> June 2015, Munich Germany)&nbsp; have incorporated sessions or sub-topics devoted to optics and the brain, <strong>there had not been a dedicated meeting focusing entirely on this topic. </strong></p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>With identification of technologies needed to better probe the working brain, across all levels from single neurons to entire behaving organisms, optical tools and techniques have become central to neuroscience and biomedical research. The high level of technical development stimulated by the BRAIN initiative drew new researchers into the field from diverse disciplines ranging from chemistry and genetics, to laser optics and neurosurgery. OSA identified the urgent need for a forum and organized the 2015 &ldquo;<em>OPTICS AND THE BRAIN&rdquo;</em> conference where these researchers came together and discussed optics in the brain at many levels, from the highly technical components of optical design and optical interactions with tissue, to the motivating factors in developing optical tools for neuroscience research across organisms, from cells and flies to rodents and humans. The event provided a forum for presentations from projects related to the BRAIN initiative and Human Brain Project and stimulated new ideas and collaborations for future projects. Moreover, this meeting provided an opportunity for students, trainees and young investigators to present their work, and to hear and network with internationally-renowned invited speakers who represented the broad diversity of this burgeoning field. This meeting served ...]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ 2015 OSA Biomedical Optics &amp; Photonics Congress: Optics in the Life Sciences "Optics and the Brain"NSF FINAL REPORT    Principal Investigator: Elizabeth Rogan, Executive Director, The Optical Society (OSA) The Optical Society (OSA) is thankful to the National Science Foundation (NSF) for your grant award of $15,000. Critical support was provided by the NSF to assist in reduction of registration fees to increase participation and enhance diversity of speakers, presenters, attendees and students in the important exchange and dissemination of research. This Final Report is a review of the accomplishments and activities of the funded event and is accompanied by an attachment of the OSA Biomedical Optics and Photonics Congress: Optics in the Life Scinces Program Book. The specific "Optics and the Brain" Conference within the congress was held April 12-15, 2015 and attended by 84 participants. NSF provided registration assistance eight (8) student participants.    Significant advances in the development of optical techniques have led to an ever increasing role of optics in the study of and treatment of various problems in the life sciences ranging from molecular level investigations to clinical treatment of patients. Optics and the Brain is a new OSA topical meeting to be included in a larger æOptics in the Life Sciences CongressÆ.   A unique advantage of this co-location of several additional small meetings was encouraging further cross-fertilization between experts in diverse areas of biomedical optics. For example, neuroscientists at the forefront of optical applications were able to attend talks on optical trapping, while experts in the development of molecular probes for cancer diagnosis had the chance to see speakers at the forefront of optogenetics.  In terms of similar meetings, while several of the larger optics and biomedical optics meetings (such as SPIE Photonics West (held annually e.g. 7-12th February 2015, San Francisco, CA), OSA Biomed (held biennially, e.g. 26-30th April 2014, Miami FL),  OSA Frontiers in Optics (FIO) (held annually e.g. 18-22nd October 2014, Rochester NY) and SPIE/OSA The European Conference on Biomedical Optics (ECBO) (held biennially, e.g. 21-25th June 2015, Munich Germany)  have incorporated sessions or sub-topics devoted to optics and the brain, there had not been a dedicated meeting focusing entirely on this topic.      With identification of technologies needed to better probe the working brain, across all levels from single neurons to entire behaving organisms, optical tools and techniques have become central to neuroscience and biomedical research. The high level of technical development stimulated by the BRAIN initiative drew new researchers into the field from diverse disciplines ranging from chemistry and genetics, to laser optics and neurosurgery. OSA identified the urgent need for a forum and organized the 2015 "OPTICS AND THE BRAIN" conference where these researchers came together and discussed optics in the brain at many levels, from the highly technical components of optical design and optical interactions with tissue, to the motivating factors in developing optical tools for neuroscience research across organisms, from cells and flies to rodents and humans. The event provided a forum for presentations from projects related to the BRAIN initiative and Human Brain Project and stimulated new ideas and collaborations for future projects. Moreover, this meeting provided an opportunity for students, trainees and young investigators to present their work, and to hear and network with internationally-renowned invited speakers who represented the broad diversity of this burgeoning field. This meeting served to shape the careers of young trainees embarking on careers in which optics and the brain converge.  Key Topics included the following:  Optics in the Human Brain      Structural and Multiscale Brain Imaging    Functional Brain Microscopy Techniques     Functional Brain Macroscopy a...]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
