<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Workshop: Future Directions for Science of Organizations</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>05/15/2015</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>04/30/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>50000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>50000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>04050000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>SBE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>SES</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Divn Of Social and Economic Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>chu-hsiang chang</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Nontechnical Description of Significance and Importance&lt;br/&gt;The hallmark of the Science of Organizations is its applicability to a variety of disciplines including business, communication, economics, engineering, information technology, psychology, public administration, and sociology.  These disparate disciplines offer varying perspectives about a range of issues associated with organizations of all sizes (e.g., corporations, small non-profit organizations, government agencies, teams) and scopes (e.g., multi-national, local, subsets of larger organizations).  At the same time, however, the breadth of disciplines present challenges in identifying areas to strategically grow the field?s research portfolio, encouraging interdisciplinary and international research activities, and promoting the applications of research results.  Moreover, methodological advances have occurred that make new, more sophisticated approaches to organizational research possible.  A workshop will be held that assembles participants from multiple disciplines to participate in focused discussions about this inherently interdisciplinary field.  The successful completion of this workshop has the potential to fundamentally change organizational science research by highlighting new, innovative opportunities for research and promoting opportunities for longitudinal, complex, interdisciplinary research activities.  The results of such efforts may provide new insights about how to foster more effective organizations.  Significant effort will be made to ensure that underrepresented populations are invited to participate in the workshop.  Students will be involved in the workshop, thereby exposing them to cutting-edge research ideas and providing the opportunity to meet leaders in the field of organization science.  &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Technical Description&lt;br/&gt;The community of Science of Organizations has a strong history of welcoming a broad array of disciplinary perspectives researching organizations of all sizes and scopes, including business, sociology, information/information technology, engineering/operations research, communication, economics, political science, public administration, industrial labor relations, and psychology. The purpose of the proposed workshop is to assemble scholars from these various disciplines to (1) discuss the future of research in science of organizations, (2) identify strategies for encouraging, and rewarding, interdisciplinary and international collaborative research initiatives in the science of organizations community, and (3) brainstorm how to promote the results of research conducted in science of organizations. The one-and-half day workshop will be held on October 1 and 2, 2015 at Purdue University in West Lafayette, IN.  Three half-day sessions will each focus on one of the three elements of the workshop purpose.  The invited participants will bring a variety of perspectives about the research process including previously funded principal investigators for the Science of Organizations (SoO) program at NSF, journal editors, thought leaders, and active researchers.  The complement of participants will engage in rich dialogs about the aforementioned issues that may be instrumental in prioritizing research activities in this field and highlight opportunities for the research community.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>05/06/2015</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/06/2015</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.075</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1540199</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Sara</FirstName>
<LastName>McComb</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>A</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Sara A McComb</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>sara@purdue.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>7654944029</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000328559</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/06/2015</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Purdue University</Name>
<CityName>West Lafayette</CityName>
<ZipCode>479072114</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>7654941055</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>Young Hall</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[155 S Grant Street]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Indiana</StateName>
<StateCode>IN</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>IN04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>072051394</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>PURDUE UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>072051394</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Purdue University]]></Name>
<CityName>West Lafayette</CityName>
<StateCode>IN</StateCode>
<ZipCode>479072114</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[155 South Grant Street]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Indiana</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>IN04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>8031</Code>
<Text>SoO-Science Of Organizations</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0115</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2015~50000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The hallmark of the National Science Foundation (NSF) Science of Organizations (SoO) program is its applicability to a variety of disciplines including business (i.e., organizational behavior, marketing, and strategic management), communication, economics, engineering, information technology, psychology, public administration, and sociology.&nbsp; These disparate disciplines offer varying perspectives about a range of issues associated with organizations of all sizes and scopes.&nbsp; At the same time, the breadth of disciplines present challenges in identifying areas to strategically grow the SoO program&rsquo;s portfolio of funded projects. The purpose of this workshop was three-fold:&nbsp; (1) discuss the future of organizational research, (2) identify strategies for encouraging, and rewarding, interdisciplinary and international collaborative research initiatives in the science of organizations community, and (3) brainstorm how to promote the program and the results of its projects.&nbsp; This purpose was met by bringing together scholars from the various disciplines that study organizations.&nbsp; Additionally, participants with varying perspectives about the research process including SoO principal investigators, journal editors, thought leaders, and active researchers were invited.&nbsp; The complement of participants engaged in rich dialogs about issues to help program officers prioritize activities associated with the SoO program.</p> <p><strong>Intellectual Merit&nbsp;<br /></strong>The focused discussions about an inherently interdisciplinary field resulted in recommendations for multiple areas where focused research may benefit from support from the NSF.&nbsp; Specifically, the workshop participants recommended funded research examine complex organizational problems from a systematic perspective that is grounded in real-world problems.&nbsp; When considering the advances in methodology available to organizational researchers, the workshop participants clearly advised that a mix of rigorously applied methods would provide the most significant advances including traditional approaches (e.g., longitudinal, field experiments), more recent additions to the methodological toolbox (e.g., computational modeling, mining big data), and approaches rarely used in organizational research but routinely used in other fields (e.g., replication, data-driven exploratory studies, implementation science, and randomized control trials).&nbsp; The workshop participants overwhelmingly agreed that interdisciplinary research is critical because it broadens perspectives, but it should not be the sole focus of the SoO program because mono-discipline research can still advance the science of organizations. &nbsp;Opportunities to promote interdisciplinary engagement were suggested including awarding small planning grants, hosting cross-cutting workshops, and collaborating with other NSF-funded initiatives where the addition of organizational researchers may be mutually beneficial.</p> <p><strong>Broader Impacts&nbsp;<br /></strong>The success of this workshop will impact organizational research beyond that conducted by the workshop participants. The workshop report was widely distributed through professional networks, with the intention of motivating scholars to consider the SoO program as a means to facilitate ambitious longitudinal, complex, high-risk, interdisciplinary, and/or international research activities.&nbsp; The results of such efforts may provide new insights about how to foster more effective organizations. Four graduate students, three of which are women and two are minorities, participated in the workshop, which exposed them to cutting-edge research ideas and provided the opportunity to meet leaders in the field of organization science.&nbsp; This experience may broaden their perspectives about their own futures, as well as enhance their professional networks and increase their potential to seek future funding from the NSF. &nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 07/21/2017<br>      Modified by: Sara&nbsp;A&nbsp;Mccomb</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The hallmark of the National Science Foundation (NSF) Science of Organizations (SoO) program is its applicability to a variety of disciplines including business (i.e., organizational behavior, marketing, and strategic management), communication, economics, engineering, information technology, psychology, public administration, and sociology.  These disparate disciplines offer varying perspectives about a range of issues associated with organizations of all sizes and scopes.  At the same time, the breadth of disciplines present challenges in identifying areas to strategically grow the SoO program?s portfolio of funded projects. The purpose of this workshop was three-fold:  (1) discuss the future of organizational research, (2) identify strategies for encouraging, and rewarding, interdisciplinary and international collaborative research initiatives in the science of organizations community, and (3) brainstorm how to promote the program and the results of its projects.  This purpose was met by bringing together scholars from the various disciplines that study organizations.  Additionally, participants with varying perspectives about the research process including SoO principal investigators, journal editors, thought leaders, and active researchers were invited.  The complement of participants engaged in rich dialogs about issues to help program officers prioritize activities associated with the SoO program.  Intellectual Merit  The focused discussions about an inherently interdisciplinary field resulted in recommendations for multiple areas where focused research may benefit from support from the NSF.  Specifically, the workshop participants recommended funded research examine complex organizational problems from a systematic perspective that is grounded in real-world problems.  When considering the advances in methodology available to organizational researchers, the workshop participants clearly advised that a mix of rigorously applied methods would provide the most significant advances including traditional approaches (e.g., longitudinal, field experiments), more recent additions to the methodological toolbox (e.g., computational modeling, mining big data), and approaches rarely used in organizational research but routinely used in other fields (e.g., replication, data-driven exploratory studies, implementation science, and randomized control trials).  The workshop participants overwhelmingly agreed that interdisciplinary research is critical because it broadens perspectives, but it should not be the sole focus of the SoO program because mono-discipline research can still advance the science of organizations.  Opportunities to promote interdisciplinary engagement were suggested including awarding small planning grants, hosting cross-cutting workshops, and collaborating with other NSF-funded initiatives where the addition of organizational researchers may be mutually beneficial.  Broader Impacts  The success of this workshop will impact organizational research beyond that conducted by the workshop participants. The workshop report was widely distributed through professional networks, with the intention of motivating scholars to consider the SoO program as a means to facilitate ambitious longitudinal, complex, high-risk, interdisciplinary, and/or international research activities.  The results of such efforts may provide new insights about how to foster more effective organizations. Four graduate students, three of which are women and two are minorities, participated in the workshop, which exposed them to cutting-edge research ideas and provided the opportunity to meet leaders in the field of organization science.  This experience may broaden their perspectives about their own futures, as well as enhance their professional networks and increase their potential to seek future funding from the NSF.            Last Modified: 07/21/2017       Submitted by: Sara A Mccomb]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
