<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>SL-CN: Contributions of Executive Function Subdomains to Math and Reading Cognition in the Classroom</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/15/2015</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>750000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>750000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>04010000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>SBE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>SMA</Abbreviation>
<LongName>SBE Off Of Multidisciplinary Activities</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Soo-Siang Lim</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>slim@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927878</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Understanding how the brain of a student learns new information and flexibly applies that information in real-world settings is critical for guiding efforts to improve the U.S. education system. How a student learns is fundamentally related to core aspects of cognition, termed executive functions (EFs). EFs are known predictors of academic achievement across multiple content areas (e.g., math and reading); however, there remain many unanswered questions regarding exactly how EFs contribute to academic performance and whether weak EFs can be enhanced with cognitive training. It is important to build a precise understanding of how these abilities develop over childhood and how they can be improved in order to supply educators with precise tools and insights about whether, when, and how to intervene when a student is struggling.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The study of how EFs contribute to academic achievement has advanced rapidly in recent years, but has not typically included the investigation of EFs in middle childhood. Because middle childhood is a period of high neural plasticity, it promises great opportunity to intervene when EFs are weak. This research program develops an innovative approach that improves both diagnostic and intervention methodology for detecting and remediating EF weaknesses in educational settings. The program leverages a novel, precision EF assessment tool in order to rapidly assess and longitudinally track the multidimensional profile of EFs in children over time. The critical advancement is the adaptive nature of the assessment tool, which increases in difficulty as the learner improves. This adaptivity allows multiple, precise assessments over time and thus enables unprecedented understanding of how different EF profiles develop across middle childhood and, critically, how these profiles contribute to math and reading achievement. Additionally, by utilizing a novel intervention that uses each student's multidimensional EF profile to selectively challenge subdomains of EF during physical fitness training, the research will inform us if personalized, multi-factor EF training can improve math and reading outcomes. Specifically, the research will: (1) fill gaps in existing knowledge about the relationship between EF profiles and academic skills beyond early childhood, (2) characterize how these relationships evolve across age, (3) determine whether EFs are more critical to certain content areas (subdomains of math and reading), and (4) advance the field's understanding of the feasibility and timeline of personalized EF interventions. Importantly, this research will serve to lay a definitive foundation for future science of learning research to build upon. In particular, the proposed investigations of the typically developing mind will inform efforts to understand disorders of development such as ADHD and autism. Finally, the EFs assessment tool will be made publicly available, to promote widescale investigations of EFs across the diverse range of student learners. A precise understanding of how the multidimensional profile of EFs contributes to academic achievement promises tremendous societal impact by guiding efforts to intervene when students are struggling academically.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/18/2015</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/18/2015</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.075</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1540854</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Silvia</FirstName>
<LastName>Bunge</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>A</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Silvia A Bunge</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>sbunge@berkeley.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5102198147</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000252781</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/18/2015</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Adam</FirstName>
<LastName>Gazzaley</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Adam Gazzaley</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>adam.gazzaley@ucsf.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>4154762164</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000120683</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/18/2015</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Melina</FirstName>
<LastName>Uncapher</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Melina Uncapher</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>melina.uncapher@ucsf.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>4154762977</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000693881</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/18/2015</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Bruce</FirstName>
<LastName>McCandliss</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>D</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Bruce D McCandliss</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>brucemc@stanford.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6152900820</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000693882</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/18/2015</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Fumiko</FirstName>
<LastName>Hoeft</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Fumiko Hoeft</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>fumiko.hoeft@uconn.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6502457016</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000693984</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/18/2015</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of California-San Francisco</Name>
<CityName>San Francisco</CityName>
<ZipCode>941034249</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>4154762977</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1855 Folsom St Ste 425</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>12</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CA12</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>094878337</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>REGENTS OF THE UNIVERSITY OF CALIFORNIA, SAN FRANCISCO, THE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of California-San Francisco]]></Name>
<CityName>San Francisco</CityName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>941034249</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[1855 Folsom St Ste 425]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>12</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CA12</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>004Y</Code>
<Text>Science of Learning</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7645</Code>
<Text>Discovery Research K-12</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7298</Code>
<Text>COLLABORATIVE RESEARCH</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7956</Code>
<Text>SBE Interdisciplinary Research</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8089</Code>
<Text>Understanding the Brain/Cognitive Scienc</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0115</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0415</Code>
<Name>NSF Education &amp; Human Resource</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040106</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2015~750000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><strong><em>Executive functioning</em></strong>&mdash;the cognitive skills that allow us to control our attention, thoughts, actions, and emotions in service of our goals&mdash;is a core foundation for learning. Executive function is shown to be important for all kinds of academic and life outcomes, and seems to tell us something about human behavior above and beyond factors such as IQ and socio-economic status. The major aims of this NSF Science of Learning Collaborative Networks grant were to (1) use novel technology to begin to understand how executive functions develop in real-world environments, (2) understand how the multiple aspects of executive function relate to real-world outcomes such as math and reading learning, and (3) use precision technology to determine how those relationships develop over elementary and middle school years. Understanding the precise relationships between executive function and math/reading promises to advance our ability to improve executive function in all students, with particular impact on those students who may not have had as many opportunities to practice building executive function.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>This NSF Science of Learning Collaborative Networks grant funded the genesis of <strong><a href="https://sites.google.com/view/projectileadnsf/home">Project iLEAD</a></strong>, a consortium of 62 researchers across seven universities (UC San Francisco, Stanford, UC Berkeley, U Connecticut/Yale, UC San Diego, UC Davis, Rutgers University). Project iLEAD produced a large-scale, longitudinal, in-school database designed to reveal relationships between executive function domains (working memory, cognitive flexibility, attentional and inhibitory control) and academic achievement (math and reading) in middle childhood (grades 3 through 8). The project engaged with over 1,000 students and over 100 teachers in nine schools (public, private, and parochial) in the San Francisco Bay Area. Over the course of the 2-yr longitudinal study, Project iLEAD researchers collected ~100,000 tasks, providing unprecedented data on how students learn, and how executive function skills contribute to such learning. Lead Principal Investigator Prof Melina Uncapher and the UCSF team made 516 site visits across the nine participating schools in those two years, building a strong Research-Practice Partnership (RPP) that has been highlighted as a model for RPPs throughout the country.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>The foundation of this novel research program is the innovative mobile measurement technology developed by Prof Adam Gazzaley and Prof Joaquin Anguera at UCSF&rsquo;s <a href="https://neuroscape.ucsf.edu/">Neuroscape</a> Center. These mobile tools allow research to be moved from the lab to the real-world, to ensure that research is grounded in authentic educational experiences. Their novelty lies in their adaptivity: they use adaptive algorithms that enable the &lsquo;game&rsquo; to get harder as the student gets better, and for it to get easier as they reach their current limit of skill. This is a critical functionality, as it allows the same tasks to be used across students, demographics, and time. This will reveal unprecedented understanding of how executive functioning develops over the course of childhood and the lifespan, and will be critical information for educators and researchers as they develop training programs that are intended to build the core executive function training skills critical for academic success. &nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>The large-scale database and mobile technologies that have been produced by Project iLEAD are intended for open access for use by the research and educational communities. We have made the outputs of the project accessible for inquiry on the <a href="https://sites.google.com/view/projectileadnsf/home">Project iLEAD website</a> and the <a href="https://sites.google.com/view/aceexplorer/home">Adaptive Cognitive Evaluation (ACE) website</a>.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 12/02/2018<br>      Modified by: Melina&nbsp;Uncapher</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Executive functioning&mdash;the cognitive skills that allow us to control our attention, thoughts, actions, and emotions in service of our goals&mdash;is a core foundation for learning. Executive function is shown to be important for all kinds of academic and life outcomes, and seems to tell us something about human behavior above and beyond factors such as IQ and socio-economic status. The major aims of this NSF Science of Learning Collaborative Networks grant were to (1) use novel technology to begin to understand how executive functions develop in real-world environments, (2) understand how the multiple aspects of executive function relate to real-world outcomes such as math and reading learning, and (3) use precision technology to determine how those relationships develop over elementary and middle school years. Understanding the precise relationships between executive function and math/reading promises to advance our ability to improve executive function in all students, with particular impact on those students who may not have had as many opportunities to practice building executive function.     This NSF Science of Learning Collaborative Networks grant funded the genesis of Project iLEAD, a consortium of 62 researchers across seven universities (UC San Francisco, Stanford, UC Berkeley, U Connecticut/Yale, UC San Diego, UC Davis, Rutgers University). Project iLEAD produced a large-scale, longitudinal, in-school database designed to reveal relationships between executive function domains (working memory, cognitive flexibility, attentional and inhibitory control) and academic achievement (math and reading) in middle childhood (grades 3 through 8). The project engaged with over 1,000 students and over 100 teachers in nine schools (public, private, and parochial) in the San Francisco Bay Area. Over the course of the 2-yr longitudinal study, Project iLEAD researchers collected ~100,000 tasks, providing unprecedented data on how students learn, and how executive function skills contribute to such learning. Lead Principal Investigator Prof Melina Uncapher and the UCSF team made 516 site visits across the nine participating schools in those two years, building a strong Research-Practice Partnership (RPP) that has been highlighted as a model for RPPs throughout the country.     The foundation of this novel research program is the innovative mobile measurement technology developed by Prof Adam Gazzaley and Prof Joaquin Anguera at UCSF?s Neuroscape Center. These mobile tools allow research to be moved from the lab to the real-world, to ensure that research is grounded in authentic educational experiences. Their novelty lies in their adaptivity: they use adaptive algorithms that enable the ?game? to get harder as the student gets better, and for it to get easier as they reach their current limit of skill. This is a critical functionality, as it allows the same tasks to be used across students, demographics, and time. This will reveal unprecedented understanding of how executive functioning develops over the course of childhood and the lifespan, and will be critical information for educators and researchers as they develop training programs that are intended to build the core executive function training skills critical for academic success.       The large-scale database and mobile technologies that have been produced by Project iLEAD are intended for open access for use by the research and educational communities. We have made the outputs of the project accessible for inquiry on the Project iLEAD website and the Adaptive Cognitive Evaluation (ACE) website.          Last Modified: 12/02/2018       Submitted by: Melina Uncapher]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
