<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>GP EXTRA: Minorities Striving and Pursuing Higher Degrees of Success in GEO REU (MS PHD'S-GEO REU) Professional Development Program</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2015</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>84815.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>84815</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>06010000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>GEO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>ICER</Abbreviation>
<LongName>ICER</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Brandon Jones</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>mbjones@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924713</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Numerous reports from the President's Council of Advisors on Science and Technology (PCAST) and the National Research Council (NRC) have documented the need to increase diversity within STEM disciplines as being vital to our nation's innovation agenda, economic prosperity, and global competitiveness.  Although slow progress in broadening participation in some STEM disciplines is being made, the geosciences community still has a long way to go before the number of African Americans, Hispanics, Native Americans, and persons with disabilities are earning degrees and pursuing careers in the geosciences at a level that is consistent with their demographic representation.  Both recruitment of new underrepresented minority (URM) students into STEM majors and retention of those students who are already in the education and career pipeline are needed to make progress on this goal.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The University of Texas at Arlington (UTA) and the Institute for Broadening Participation (IBP) are implementing a 3-year program to provide virtual and on-site professional development, networking, community building and mentoring activities to 45 URM students who have participated in geoscience-related Research Experiences for Undergraduate (REU) Site programs. The goals of this program are focused on retention of students who have already demonstrated an interest in the geosciences, but who are at risk of leaving the field because of isolation, lack of role models, and lack of mentors who can help guide them to the next stages of their professional success. The "Minorities Striving and Pursuing Higher Degrees of Success in GEO REU" (MS PHD'S-GEO REU) program builds on a successful pilot effort, leveraging previous NSF investments to build model programs for recruitment, retention, and leadership development of traditionally underrepresented students in STEM disciplines.  The program uses evidence-based mentoring concepts that are rooted in the theories of situated learning and authentic learning.  Career exposure and professional socialization activities are embedded.  A rigorous recruitment, application, and selection process is being used to identify three cohorts (15 each) of students from a national pool of REU Site participants.  The program involves two main phases: 1) on-site mentored professional development in conjunction with the annual Fall meeting of the American Geophysical Union; and 2) virtual and face-to-face mentoring and networking at discipline-specific conferences, supported by on-going virtual professional development webinars. Formative and summative evaluation components are included in the project design.  Impact evaluation studies will investigate whether students participating in the MS PHD'S-GEO REU program show greater persistence in STEM and the geosciences, as well as more informed career decision-making, compared with other REU students who are not selected for the program.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/27/2015</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/27/2015</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.050</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1540731</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Ashanti</FirstName>
<LastName>Johnson</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Ashanti Johnson</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>Dr.ashantijohnson@gmail.com</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2146042797</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000630732</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/27/2015</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Texas at Arlington</Name>
<CityName>Arlington</CityName>
<ZipCode>760190145</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>8172722105</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>701 S Nedderman Dr, Box 19145</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Texas</StateName>
<StateCode>TX</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>06</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>TX06</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>064234610</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF TEXAS AT ARLINGTON</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>042000273</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Texas at Arlington]]></Name>
<CityName>Arlington</CityName>
<StateCode>TX</StateCode>
<ZipCode>760190145</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[1 UNIVERSITY OF TEXAS AT ARLINGT]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Texas</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>06</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>TX06</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1998</Code>
<Text>IUSE</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1697</Code>
<Text>OPPORT FOR ENHANCING DIVERSITY</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0115</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2015~84815</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>This award was on an extended hiatus for the past three years.&nbsp; We are in the process of re-establishing the award at Ft. Valley State University (FVSU).&nbsp; It is anticipated that the award will be re-established by summer 2019 and with the addition of supplemental funds become fully staffed so that we can carry out the proposed activities and achieve the outlined project objectives.</p> <p><strong><span>MS PHD'S Initiative Overview</span></strong></p> <p>Since 2003, the&nbsp;<em>MS PHD&rsquo;S&nbsp;</em>initiative has promoted the advancement of URM students and recent URM doctoral degree recipients committed to achieving outstanding geosciences careers.&nbsp;<em>MS PHD&rsquo;S&nbsp;</em>has been repeatedly recognized as a national model STEM diversity program.&nbsp; To date more than 250&nbsp;<em>MS PHD&rsquo;S</em>&nbsp;participants attending academic institutions from across the US have engaged in a series of activities that have:</p> <p>-&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; Increased STEM exposure and career preparation</p> <p>-&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; Facilitated participation in international scientific conferences,</p> <p>-&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; Established effective mentoring relationships, virtual activities, and fieldtrips;</p> <p>-&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; Enhanced professional skills, grantsmanship, oral and written communication skills;</p> <p>-&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; Provided resources for future funding, education and career opportunities;</p> <p>-&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; Increased networking opportunities with established researchers and educators; and</p> <p>-&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; Provided on-going interaction, communication and support via membership within a virtual community comprised of peers, junior- and senior-level researchers, and educators.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p><strong><em><span>MS PHD&rsquo;S</span></em></strong><strong><span>&nbsp;Initiative Impact</span></strong></p> <p>Since 2004,&nbsp;<em>MS PHD&rsquo;S&nbsp;</em>has cultivated organizational partnerships&nbsp;<em>(MS PHD&rsquo;S OPs)&nbsp;</em>with premier scientific societies and symposia to provide URM geoscience students with opportunities to engage in organization specific programs that offer travel support, research presentation opportunities, mentoring experiences, and broadening participation exposure at organizational meetings and conferences. Some of the&nbsp;<em>MS</em>&nbsp;<em>PHD&rsquo;S OPs&nbsp;</em>include: the National Academies, NSF, NOAA, NASA, EPA, US FWS, American Geophysical Union (AGU), American Geosciences Institute, American Meteorological Society, Association for the Sciences of Limnology and Oceanography, Compact for Faculty Diversity Institute on Teaching and Mentoring, Consortium for Ocean Leadership, Ecological Society of America, Ivy League Symposium, Geological Society of America, National Association of Black Geoscientists, National Association of Geoscience Teachers On The Cutting Edge, Sigma Xi the Scientific Research Society, and the Society for Freshwater Science.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>Of the&nbsp;<em>MS PHD&rsquo;S&nbsp;</em>alumni, +120 participants self-identified as African American; +47 as Puerto</p> <p>Rican; +27 as Hispanic/Mexican American; 14 as American Indian/Alaskan Native; 7 as Native</p> <p>Hawaiian/Pacific Islander; +8 as White/Caucasian, Other Hispanic, African, Asian or Multi-Ethnic; 61% as female and 39% as male. To date, a total of 133 students began participation in&nbsp;<em>MS PHD&rsquo;S&nbsp;</em>as graduate students, +100 as undergraduate students, and the remaining 7 as post-baccalaureate in transition to graduate school. Geographic representation of participants includes 35 states, the District of Columbia, Puerto Rico and two international postdoctoral appointments &ndash; one in Saudi Arabia and the other in France. More than 60 alumni have completed their doctoral degree and another 62 are enrolled in doctoral programs.</p> <p>Several peer-reviewed articles and conference proceedings have been published on the program design and outcomes of&nbsp;<em>MS PHD&rsquo;S</em>.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>Anonymous surveys completed annually by&nbsp;<em>MS PHD&rsquo;S&nbsp;</em>participants show broad agreement (96%) on the need for the&nbsp;<em>MS PHD&rsquo;S&nbsp;</em>as well as willingness to advocate for the program. The most cited beneficial aspects of the program identified by all respondents of the annual surveys fall into categories of Peer and Community Engagement, Networking, and Professional Development. At the conclusion of their&nbsp;<em>MS</em>&nbsp;<em>PHD&rsquo;S&nbsp;</em>experience, student participants report that they are better prepared to achieve their academic and professional goals.&nbsp;</p> <p><strong><em><span>MS PHD&rsquo;S</span></em></strong><strong><span>&nbsp;Programs</span></strong></p> <p>The&nbsp;<em>MS PHD&rsquo;S&nbsp;</em>initiative provides high quality professional development and mentoring experiences for underrepresented minority (URM) students and more recently early career professionals.</p> <p>-&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;<em>MS PHD&rsquo;S&nbsp;</em>pilot - held in conjunction with the 2003 Final Joint Global Ocean Flux Meeting at the National Academies.</p> <p>-&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;<em>MS PHD&rsquo;S in Earth System Science (MS PHD&rsquo;S ESS) PDP</em>&nbsp;- In 2004 findings from the initial pilot project and scientific community support were used to launch the&nbsp;<em>MS PHD&rsquo;S in Earth System Science (MS PHD&rsquo;S ESS) PDP</em>.</p> <p>-&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;<em>MS PHD&rsquo;S Beyond the</em>&nbsp;<em>PhD (MS PHD&rsquo;S B-PhD) PDP</em>&nbsp;- in 2011, in direct response to the expressed needs of the&nbsp;<em>MS PHD&rsquo;S ESS&nbsp;</em>alumni, a second pilot project entitled the&nbsp;<em>MS PHD&rsquo;S Beyond the</em>&nbsp;<em>PhD (MS PHD&rsquo;S B-PhD) PDP&nbsp;</em>was designed to facilitate the advancement of recent URM geosciences doctoral degree recipients in academia, federal government and industry sectors.</p> <p>-&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;<em>MS</em>&nbsp;<em>PHD&rsquo;S-GEO REU PDP</em>&nbsp;- which represents the newest undertaking of the&nbsp;<em>MS PHD&rsquo;S&nbsp;</em>initiative, was piloted with 10 undergraduates at the 2014 American Geophysical Union (AGU) Fall Meeting, via an NSF supplemental award and subsequently received NSF funding as a separate activity.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;<strong><span>Continued National Need and Interest in<em>&nbsp;MS PHD&rsquo;S</em></span></strong></p> <p>-&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; There is a tremendous amount of expressed need/desire in the&nbsp;<span>Earth system science community</span>&nbsp;to re-launch the&nbsp;<em>MS PHD&rsquo;S ESS PDP</em>&nbsp;and&nbsp;<em>MS PHD&rsquo;S B-PhD</em>, as well as to continue the&nbsp;<em>MS PHD&rsquo;S GEO REU</em>&nbsp;activities.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 02/27/2019<br>      Modified by: Ashanti&nbsp;Johnson</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ This award was on an extended hiatus for the past three years.  We are in the process of re-establishing the award at Ft. Valley State University (FVSU).  It is anticipated that the award will be re-established by summer 2019 and with the addition of supplemental funds become fully staffed so that we can carry out the proposed activities and achieve the outlined project objectives.  MS PHD'S Initiative Overview  Since 2003, the MS PHD?S initiative has promoted the advancement of URM students and recent URM doctoral degree recipients committed to achieving outstanding geosciences careers. MS PHD?S has been repeatedly recognized as a national model STEM diversity program.  To date more than 250 MS PHD?S participants attending academic institutions from across the US have engaged in a series of activities that have:  -          Increased STEM exposure and career preparation  -          Facilitated participation in international scientific conferences,  -          Established effective mentoring relationships, virtual activities, and fieldtrips;  -          Enhanced professional skills, grantsmanship, oral and written communication skills;  -          Provided resources for future funding, education and career opportunities;  -          Increased networking opportunities with established researchers and educators; and  -          Provided on-going interaction, communication and support via membership within a virtual community comprised of peers, junior- and senior-level researchers, and educators.     MS PHD?S Initiative Impact  Since 2004, MS PHD?S has cultivated organizational partnerships (MS PHD?S OPs) with premier scientific societies and symposia to provide URM geoscience students with opportunities to engage in organization specific programs that offer travel support, research presentation opportunities, mentoring experiences, and broadening participation exposure at organizational meetings and conferences. Some of the MS PHD?S OPs include: the National Academies, NSF, NOAA, NASA, EPA, US FWS, American Geophysical Union (AGU), American Geosciences Institute, American Meteorological Society, Association for the Sciences of Limnology and Oceanography, Compact for Faculty Diversity Institute on Teaching and Mentoring, Consortium for Ocean Leadership, Ecological Society of America, Ivy League Symposium, Geological Society of America, National Association of Black Geoscientists, National Association of Geoscience Teachers On The Cutting Edge, Sigma Xi the Scientific Research Society, and the Society for Freshwater Science.     Of the MS PHD?S alumni, +120 participants self-identified as African American; +47 as Puerto  Rican; +27 as Hispanic/Mexican American; 14 as American Indian/Alaskan Native; 7 as Native  Hawaiian/Pacific Islander; +8 as White/Caucasian, Other Hispanic, African, Asian or Multi-Ethnic; 61% as female and 39% as male. To date, a total of 133 students began participation in MS PHD?S as graduate students, +100 as undergraduate students, and the remaining 7 as post-baccalaureate in transition to graduate school. Geographic representation of participants includes 35 states, the District of Columbia, Puerto Rico and two international postdoctoral appointments &ndash; one in Saudi Arabia and the other in France. More than 60 alumni have completed their doctoral degree and another 62 are enrolled in doctoral programs.  Several peer-reviewed articles and conference proceedings have been published on the program design and outcomes of MS PHD?S.     Anonymous surveys completed annually by MS PHD?S participants show broad agreement (96%) on the need for the MS PHD?S as well as willingness to advocate for the program. The most cited beneficial aspects of the program identified by all respondents of the annual surveys fall into categories of Peer and Community Engagement, Networking, and Professional Development. At the conclusion of their MS PHD?S experience, student participants report that they are better prepared to achieve their academic and professional goals.   MS PHD?S Programs  The MS PHD?S initiative provides high quality professional development and mentoring experiences for underrepresented minority (URM) students and more recently early career professionals.  -          MS PHD?S pilot - held in conjunction with the 2003 Final Joint Global Ocean Flux Meeting at the National Academies.  -          MS PHD?S in Earth System Science (MS PHD?S ESS) PDP - In 2004 findings from the initial pilot project and scientific community support were used to launch the MS PHD?S in Earth System Science (MS PHD?S ESS) PDP.  -          MS PHD?S Beyond the PhD (MS PHD?S B-PhD) PDP - in 2011, in direct response to the expressed needs of the MS PHD?S ESS alumni, a second pilot project entitled the MS PHD?S Beyond the PhD (MS PHD?S B-PhD) PDP was designed to facilitate the advancement of recent URM geosciences doctoral degree recipients in academia, federal government and industry sectors.  -          MS PHD?S-GEO REU PDP - which represents the newest undertaking of the MS PHD?S initiative, was piloted with 10 undergraduates at the 2014 American Geophysical Union (AGU) Fall Meeting, via an NSF supplemental award and subsequently received NSF funding as a separate activity.      Continued National Need and Interest in MS PHD?S  -          There is a tremendous amount of expressed need/desire in the Earth system science community to re-launch the MS PHD?S ESS PDP and MS PHD?S B-PhD, as well as to continue the MS PHD?S GEO REU activities.          Last Modified: 02/27/2019       Submitted by: Ashanti Johnson]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
