<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Doctoral Dissertation Research: Insect Consumption in Sympatric Primate Species</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/15/2015</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>02/28/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>24615.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>24615</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>04040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>SBE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>BCS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Behavioral and Cognitive Sci</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Rebecca Ferrell</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>rferrell@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927850</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Insects are found in the diet of many primates, and in humans they are an underappreciated but significant component of many non-Western diets. Insects are particularly important for hunter-gatherer societies and groups living in tropical regions. However, despite their dietary importance, the role that insects have played over the course of primate and human evolution and in living primates is understudied. Gaining a complete understanding of entomophagy (insect eating) has been challenging historically because primate insect consumption is difficult to observe, and because insects themselves are often cryptic. However, recent advances in genetic methods have made insect prey identification more practical, allowing for the evaluation of explicit hypotheses related to entomophagy that were previously untestable. This project incorporates methodologies from anthropology, ecology, entomology, and molecular biology to examine insect consumption in closely related monkey species. The project will provide training of a woman (Co-PI) in a broad range of cross-disciplinary scientific methods, thus increasing the participation of women in science. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project will examine variation in insect consumption by sympatric, omnivorous primates to test the hypothesis that differential use of insects as a food resource facilitates coexistence of omnivorous species. This will be accomplished by integrating advanced molecular methods and noninvasive field data collection to identify insect prey consumed by redtail monkeys (Cercopithecus ascanius) and blue monkeys (C. mitis): two omnivorous cercopithecine primate species. These data will be used to investigate variation in entomophagy between species, sex-class, and seasons. Results of this research will add to our understanding of the influences of ecological and life history variables on primate insect consumption, and will have implications for interpreting the role of entomophagy in feeding niche differentiation and coexistence among closely related primate species.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/10/2015</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>09/17/2015</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.075</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1540337</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Joanna</FirstName>
<LastName>Lambert</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>E</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Joanna E Lambert</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>joanna.lambert@utsa.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2104584075</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000310313</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/10/2015</StartDate>
<EndDate>09/17/2015</EndDate>
<RoleCode>Former Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Thad</FirstName>
<LastName>Bartlett</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>Q</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Thad Q Bartlett</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>THAD.BARTLETT@UTSA.EDU</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2104584340</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000558563</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/17/2015</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Martha</FirstName>
<LastName>Lyke</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Martha Lyke</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>marthalyke@gmail.com</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2104584340</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000673536</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/10/2015</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Texas at San Antonio</Name>
<CityName>San Antonio</CityName>
<ZipCode>782491644</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2104584340</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>One UTSA Circle</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[Grants, Contracts & Ind. Agr.]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Texas</StateName>
<StateCode>TX</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>20</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>TX20</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>800189185</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF TEXAS AT SAN ANTONIO, THE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>042000273</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Texas at Austin,Dept of Anthropology]]></Name>
<CityName>Austin</CityName>
<StateCode>TX</StateCode>
<ZipCode>787121086</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[1 University Station]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Texas</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>25</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>TX25</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7608</Code>
<Text>Bio Anthro DDRI</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1392</Code>
<Text>Biological Anthropology</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9179</Code>
<Text>GRADUATE INVOLVEMENT</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>SMET</Code>
<Text>SCIENCE, MATH, ENG &amp; TECH EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0115</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2015~24615</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>In this project, we examined variation in insect consumption by sympatric, omnivorous primates to test the hypothesis that differential use of insects as a food resource facilitates coexistence of omnivorous species. As such, the primary research goal was to investigate the role of entomophagy as a mechanism of coexistence through dietary resource partitioning. Secondary goals included the analysis of intra-specific and inter-seasonal variation in primate entomophagy to gain a more holistic understanding of each study species&rsquo; feeding ecology. To achieve these goals, we integrated advanced molecular methods and noninvasive field data collection to identify insect prey consumed by redtail monkeys (<em>Cercopithecus ascanius</em>) and blue monkeys (<em>C. mitis</em>): two omnivorous cercopithecine primate species inhabiting Kibale National Park (KNP), Uganda.</p> <p>Field work for this project was completed in December, 2015 and laboratory analyses were completed in August, 2016. Since that time, the co-PI has been analyzing data and starting to write up results. While results are still preliminary, we have successfully identified arthropod prey taxa consumed by both primate species and identified considerable and significant variation in the specific taxa consumed. Arthropod DNA was detected in 223 of 225 samples, and a total of 68 arthropod families (15 orders, 122 genera) were identified. Redtails consumed insects from 54 families, of which 12 (21.8%) were absent from blue monkey samples. Blue monkeys consumed insects from 56 families, of which 14 (24.6%) were absent from redtail samples. These results indicate that while overlap exists in the insect portion of their diets, 20-25% of taxa consumed are unique to each group. Our findings reveal numerous arthropod prey not previously reported and suggest that variation in entomophagy can be an important mechanism in decreasing niche overlap and facilitating coexistence among closely related species that occupy the same feeding guild. Further data analysis of seasonal variation will help elucidate associations between food resource availability and intraspecific dietary variability, and has further implications for understanding how primate dietary strategies are developed and maintained. By providing a direct means for identifying insect prey, as well as analyzing ecological associations of insect consumption, once completed, this research will also provide a novel contribution to developing theories regarding the evolutionary importance of insect use by primates, including humans.&nbsp;</p> <p>While this research is still in progress, it has already provided training and professional opportunities for a female student (co-PI), while integrating methods and theories from the fields of anthropology, biology, genetics, and ecology. The field portion of this research provided training and employment of local Ugandans and strengthened the relationship between the University of Texas at San Antonio and Makerere University in Uganda. Preliminary results have been presented at the annual meeting of the American Association of Physical Anthropologists, and final results will be submitted for peer review in a number of scholarly journals.&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 05/13/2017<br>      Modified by: Martha&nbsp;Lyke</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ In this project, we examined variation in insect consumption by sympatric, omnivorous primates to test the hypothesis that differential use of insects as a food resource facilitates coexistence of omnivorous species. As such, the primary research goal was to investigate the role of entomophagy as a mechanism of coexistence through dietary resource partitioning. Secondary goals included the analysis of intra-specific and inter-seasonal variation in primate entomophagy to gain a more holistic understanding of each study species? feeding ecology. To achieve these goals, we integrated advanced molecular methods and noninvasive field data collection to identify insect prey consumed by redtail monkeys (Cercopithecus ascanius) and blue monkeys (C. mitis): two omnivorous cercopithecine primate species inhabiting Kibale National Park (KNP), Uganda.  Field work for this project was completed in December, 2015 and laboratory analyses were completed in August, 2016. Since that time, the co-PI has been analyzing data and starting to write up results. While results are still preliminary, we have successfully identified arthropod prey taxa consumed by both primate species and identified considerable and significant variation in the specific taxa consumed. Arthropod DNA was detected in 223 of 225 samples, and a total of 68 arthropod families (15 orders, 122 genera) were identified. Redtails consumed insects from 54 families, of which 12 (21.8%) were absent from blue monkey samples. Blue monkeys consumed insects from 56 families, of which 14 (24.6%) were absent from redtail samples. These results indicate that while overlap exists in the insect portion of their diets, 20-25% of taxa consumed are unique to each group. Our findings reveal numerous arthropod prey not previously reported and suggest that variation in entomophagy can be an important mechanism in decreasing niche overlap and facilitating coexistence among closely related species that occupy the same feeding guild. Further data analysis of seasonal variation will help elucidate associations between food resource availability and intraspecific dietary variability, and has further implications for understanding how primate dietary strategies are developed and maintained. By providing a direct means for identifying insect prey, as well as analyzing ecological associations of insect consumption, once completed, this research will also provide a novel contribution to developing theories regarding the evolutionary importance of insect use by primates, including humans.   While this research is still in progress, it has already provided training and professional opportunities for a female student (co-PI), while integrating methods and theories from the fields of anthropology, biology, genetics, and ecology. The field portion of this research provided training and employment of local Ugandans and strengthened the relationship between the University of Texas at San Antonio and Makerere University in Uganda. Preliminary results have been presented at the annual meeting of the American Association of Physical Anthropologists, and final results will be submitted for peer review in a number of scholarly journals.           Last Modified: 05/13/2017       Submitted by: Martha Lyke]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
