<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Understanding Essential Dynamics and Predictability of Madden-Julian Oscillation (MJO)</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>12/15/2015</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>11/30/2020</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>500000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>500000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>06020106</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>GEO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>AGS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Atmospheric &amp; Geospace Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Varavut Limpasuvan</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>vlimpasu@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922746</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The overall goal of the research is to advance understanding of fundamental mechanisms governing the propagation and development of Madden-Julian Oscillation (MJO) and to improve the ability of dynamical models to simulate and predict intraseasonal variability. Fundamental causes for slow eastward propagation and initiation/intensification of the MJO will be investigated through multi-model diagnostic analysis,  and numerical experiments using coupled climate models. Processes through which the MJO teleconnection may feedback to its own eastward propagation will also be examined. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The first hypothesis that will be tested focuses on mechanisms determining eastward propagation of the MJO. The coupled Kelvin-Rossby wave structure and the phase difference between the MJO convection and the low pressure anomaly suggest that slow eastward propagation of MJO may be essentially driven by convective interaction with dynamical processes associated with low-frequency equatorial waves. Thus, the coupling low frequency waves and the large scale convective complex (envelope) by frictional moisture convergence may serve as a basic driver for the MJO moving eastward. The local change of moisture, moisture advection, mean state moist static energy (thus SST) distribution, surface entropy flux exchange, upscale eddy transport of momentum, heat and moisture, environmental vertical shear and advection, the extratropical eddy activity flux, and atmosphere-ocean mixed layer interaction can all further modify propagation speed to various degrees. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The second hypothesis deals with mechanisms responsible for intensification and maintenance of the MJO. The convective interaction with wave dynamics alone does not generate instability. However, the additional frictional moisture convergence interacting with the latent heat released in shallow and congestus clouds can generate planetary scale instability for MJO intensification through conversion of mean state available moist static energy to MJO available potential and kinetic energy. The moisture advection, the surface evaporation-wind feedback, the interaction between MJO and upscale eddy transport of heat, moisture and momentum, the energy propagation from outside of the tropics may also important for initiation and amplification of the MJO.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>12/07/2015</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>12/07/2015</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.050</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1540783</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Bin</FirstName>
<LastName>Wang</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Bin Wang</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>wangbin@hawaii.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>8089562563</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000483023</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>12/07/2015</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Hawaii</Name>
<CityName>Honolulu</CityName>
<ZipCode>968222234</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>8089567800</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>2440 Campus Road, Box 368</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Hawaii</StateName>
<StateCode>HI</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>HI01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>965088057</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF HAWAII SYSTEMS</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>009438664</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Hawaii]]></Name>
<CityName>Honolulu</CityName>
<StateCode>HI</StateCode>
<ZipCode>968222234</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[1680 east-west Rd.]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Hawaii</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>HI01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>5740</Code>
<Text>Climate &amp; Large-Scale Dynamics</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>OTHR</Code>
<Text>OTHER RESEARCH OR EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0116</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2016~500000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Madden-Julian Oscillation (MJO) is a dominant form of tropical climate variability on an intraseasonal time scale (20-70 days). The MJO studies lay a cornerstone for sub-seasonal prediction.&nbsp;The overall goal of this project is to improve our understanding of the fundamental dynamics of MJO.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>Significant achievements are highlighted below.</p> <p>1) Observational findings:&nbsp;</p> <ul> <li>A pilot classification of the MJO diversity (Wang et al. 2019). Climate modeling and prediction of MJO remain a big challenge, partially due to a lack of understanding the MJO diversity. Our pilot cluster analysis of propagation patterns of MJO events reveals four archetypes of MJO: Standing, Jumping, Slow eastward, and Fast eastward propagation. Each type exhibits distinctive east-west asymmetric circulation and thermodynamic structures. The Pacific sea surface temperature anomalies can affect MJO diversity by modifying the Kelvin-wave response and its coupling to MJO convection.</li> <li>Revealed the MJO&rsquo;s Front Walker Cell plays an essential role to drive MJO&rsquo;s eastward propagation (Chen and Wang 2017)&nbsp;</li> <li>Established a pair of tropical cyclone genesis potential indices to diagnose MJO modulation of TC genesis during boreal winter (Wang and Moon 2017) and boreal summer (Moon et al. 2018)&nbsp;</li> <li>Revealed the main factors determining the MJO propagation speed (Chen and Wang 2020)&nbsp;</li> </ul> <p>2) Theoretical understandings<strong>:</strong></p> <ul> <li>Advanced a novel trio-interaction theory for MJO (Wang et al. 2016). The MJO dynamics are rooted in a trio-interaction among convection, moisture, and wave-boundary layer (BL) dynamics. The theory addressed why the MJO has a preferred planetary scale; why it propagates eastward; what control the MJO&rsquo;s slow eastward speed that results in the 30&ndash;60-day period; why the MJO possesses a mixed Kelvin&ndash;Rossby wave structure; and why MJO amplifies over the warm pool ocean and decays rapidly in the eastern Pacific.&nbsp;For the first time, the theory reveals an intrinsic relationship between MJO propagation and MJO zonal structural asymmetry and the dependence of the MJO structure on model&rsquo;s convective parameterization.</li> <li>Established on a general theoretical framework for understanding the essential dynamics of Madden-Julian Oscillation (Wang and Chen 2017). The model extends the Matsuno-Gill theory by incorporating (a) interaction among circulation and convective heating (simplified Betts-Miller (B-M) cumulus parameterization) and (b) moisture feedback to precipitation. The cumulus parameterization scheme may affect propagation speed through changing MJO horizontal structure. The SST or basic-state moist static energy has a control on MJO propagation speed and intensification/decay.&nbsp;</li> <li>Proposed dynamic moisture mode theory and elaborated the critical roles of the wave and boundary layer convergence feedback in the MJO dynamics (Chen and Wang 2018)&nbsp;</li> <li>Elaborated the effects of moisture feedback in the MJO dynamics&nbsp;(Liu and Wang 2016a)<strong>&nbsp;</strong></li> <li>Illuminated the impact of horizontal advection of seasonal mean moisture on MJO dynamics (Liu and Wang 2016b)<strong></strong></li> </ul> <p>3) Numerical modeling<strong>:&nbsp;</strong></p> <ul> <li>Revealed, with multi-model simulation, the intrinsic relationship between MJO structure and propagation&nbsp;(Wang and Lee 2017).</li> <li>Advanced new dynamics-oriented diagnostics for the MJO (Wang et al. 2018). A suite of dynamics-oriented diagnostics is developed to evaluate whether a model produces eastward-propagating MJOs for the right reasons. The metrics are based on the finding that MJO propagation is intrinsically linked to the MJO structural asymmetry and the trio-interaction theory. The diagnostics include six critical circulation and thermodynamic fields, quantifying the boundary layer moisture convergence structure, zonal asymmetry in 850-hPa zonal winds, equivalent potential temperature and convective instability, diabatic heating, the upper-level divergence, and MJO available potential energy generation.&nbsp;&nbsp;</li> <li>Improved MJO simulation by modification of the&nbsp;Tidtke&nbsp;(TDK) and&nbsp;Relaxed Arakawa-Schubert&nbsp;(RAS) convective schemes&nbsp;in a coupled climate model while keeping global energy and water balance unaffected (Yang and Wang 2018). The modifications include a) a&nbsp;BL depth-dependent convective&nbsp;inhibition (INH) and b) a&nbsp;bottom-heavy&nbsp;diffusivity&nbsp;in the shallow convection scheme (SHC).&nbsp;<strong></strong></li> <li>Demonstrated a significant mechanism driving MJO northward propagation during northern summer.</li> </ul> <p><strong>&nbsp;</strong></p> <p>The scientific results have significant impacts on the improvement of modeling MJO and sub-seasonal prediction: 1) The trio-interaction theory of MJO advances a comprehensive theoretical perception for understanding the essential characteristics of the MJO. The theory guides for improving GCM&rsquo;s MJO simulation.&nbsp;2) The taxonomy of MJOdiversity provides potential precursors for foreseeing MJO propagation.&nbsp;3) The established dynamic-oriented metrics for MJO diagnosis is a powerful tool for assessment and improvement of the climate models&rsquo; simulation and future projection of MJO.&nbsp;&nbsp;4) The established intraseasonal tropical cyclone genesis potential indices provide&nbsp;a large potential to improve dynamical sub-seasonal prediction of TC genesis. 5) Our modeling work indicates an effective way of improving he numerical model&rsquo;s performance in simulating realistic MJO.&nbsp;</p> <p>The project has provided funds to train three postdoc fellows, two graduate students, and one undergraduate student. Two of them are female.&nbsp;&nbsp;The observational, theoretical, and modeling results generated in this project significantly enriched the PI&rsquo;s teaching of a graduate course on tropical climate dynamics at the University of Hawaii.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 12/06/2020<br>      Modified by: Bin&nbsp;Wang</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Madden-Julian Oscillation (MJO) is a dominant form of tropical climate variability on an intraseasonal time scale (20-70 days). The MJO studies lay a cornerstone for sub-seasonal prediction. The overall goal of this project is to improve our understanding of the fundamental dynamics of MJO.     Significant achievements are highlighted below.  1) Observational findings:   A pilot classification of the MJO diversity (Wang et al. 2019). Climate modeling and prediction of MJO remain a big challenge, partially due to a lack of understanding the MJO diversity. Our pilot cluster analysis of propagation patterns of MJO events reveals four archetypes of MJO: Standing, Jumping, Slow eastward, and Fast eastward propagation. Each type exhibits distinctive east-west asymmetric circulation and thermodynamic structures. The Pacific sea surface temperature anomalies can affect MJO diversity by modifying the Kelvin-wave response and its coupling to MJO convection. Revealed the MJO’s Front Walker Cell plays an essential role to drive MJO’s eastward propagation (Chen and Wang 2017)  Established a pair of tropical cyclone genesis potential indices to diagnose MJO modulation of TC genesis during boreal winter (Wang and Moon 2017) and boreal summer (Moon et al. 2018)  Revealed the main factors determining the MJO propagation speed (Chen and Wang 2020)    2) Theoretical understandings:  Advanced a novel trio-interaction theory for MJO (Wang et al. 2016). The MJO dynamics are rooted in a trio-interaction among convection, moisture, and wave-boundary layer (BL) dynamics. The theory addressed why the MJO has a preferred planetary scale; why it propagates eastward; what control the MJO’s slow eastward speed that results in the 30&ndash;60-day period; why the MJO possesses a mixed Kelvin&ndash;Rossby wave structure; and why MJO amplifies over the warm pool ocean and decays rapidly in the eastern Pacific. For the first time, the theory reveals an intrinsic relationship between MJO propagation and MJO zonal structural asymmetry and the dependence of the MJO structure on model’s convective parameterization. Established on a general theoretical framework for understanding the essential dynamics of Madden-Julian Oscillation (Wang and Chen 2017). The model extends the Matsuno-Gill theory by incorporating (a) interaction among circulation and convective heating (simplified Betts-Miller (B-M) cumulus parameterization) and (b) moisture feedback to precipitation. The cumulus parameterization scheme may affect propagation speed through changing MJO horizontal structure. The SST or basic-state moist static energy has a control on MJO propagation speed and intensification/decay.  Proposed dynamic moisture mode theory and elaborated the critical roles of the wave and boundary layer convergence feedback in the MJO dynamics (Chen and Wang 2018)  Elaborated the effects of moisture feedback in the MJO dynamics (Liu and Wang 2016a)  Illuminated the impact of horizontal advection of seasonal mean moisture on MJO dynamics (Liu and Wang 2016b)   3) Numerical modeling:   Revealed, with multi-model simulation, the intrinsic relationship between MJO structure and propagation (Wang and Lee 2017). Advanced new dynamics-oriented diagnostics for the MJO (Wang et al. 2018). A suite of dynamics-oriented diagnostics is developed to evaluate whether a model produces eastward-propagating MJOs for the right reasons. The metrics are based on the finding that MJO propagation is intrinsically linked to the MJO structural asymmetry and the trio-interaction theory. The diagnostics include six critical circulation and thermodynamic fields, quantifying the boundary layer moisture convergence structure, zonal asymmetry in 850-hPa zonal winds, equivalent potential temperature and convective instability, diabatic heating, the upper-level divergence, and MJO available potential energy generation.   Improved MJO simulation by modification of the Tidtke (TDK) and Relaxed Arakawa-Schubert (RAS) convective schemes in a coupled climate model while keeping global energy and water balance unaffected (Yang and Wang 2018). The modifications include a) a BL depth-dependent convective inhibition (INH) and b) a bottom-heavy diffusivity in the shallow convection scheme (SHC).  Demonstrated a significant mechanism driving MJO northward propagation during northern summer.      The scientific results have significant impacts on the improvement of modeling MJO and sub-seasonal prediction: 1) The trio-interaction theory of MJO advances a comprehensive theoretical perception for understanding the essential characteristics of the MJO. The theory guides for improving GCM’s MJO simulation. 2) The taxonomy of MJOdiversity provides potential precursors for foreseeing MJO propagation. 3) The established dynamic-oriented metrics for MJO diagnosis is a powerful tool for assessment and improvement of the climate models’ simulation and future projection of MJO.  4) The established intraseasonal tropical cyclone genesis potential indices provide a large potential to improve dynamical sub-seasonal prediction of TC genesis. 5) Our modeling work indicates an effective way of improving he numerical model’s performance in simulating realistic MJO.   The project has provided funds to train three postdoc fellows, two graduate students, and one undergraduate student. Two of them are female.  The observational, theoretical, and modeling results generated in this project significantly enriched the PI’s teaching of a graduate course on tropical climate dynamics at the University of Hawaii.             Last Modified: 12/06/2020       Submitted by: Bin Wang]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
