<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>BSF:2014359:Invariance in error correcting codes and computational complexity</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2015</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2020</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>40000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>40000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>05010000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>CSE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CCF</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division of Computing and Communication Foundations</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>A. Funda Ergun</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>fergun@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922216</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Information can be digitally encoded (as 0s and 1s) so that even if some of these bits are lost or modified, the information can be recovered.  This foundational idea, which is the basis for such commonplace technologies as DVDs and digital broadcast, is explored in theoretical computer science, where it plays a key role in probabilistically checkable proofs and property testing.  Exploring the limits of this idea in these abstract settings can lead to new understanding, which enables technological innovation. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;It has been long known in mathematics that studying the invariances (symmetries) of an object has an important role in understanding the object. In recent years, the study of invariances has led to some significant  advances in various topics in theoretical computer science, such as property testing, error-correcting codes and complexity theory.  For example, codes with affine invariance and codes with a transitive invariance group  have been shown to have important applications in complexity theory, such as constructing PCPs.  This project will support the travel of the PIs and their students for research collaborations on these topics with collaborators in Israel. This research will deepen our understanding of objects with invariances, and develop new applications of this theory in complexity theory.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/07/2015</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/07/2015</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.070</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1540634</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Shubhangi</FirstName>
<LastName>Saraf</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Shubhangi Saraf</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>shubhangi.saraf@gmail.com</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>8484457949</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000618097</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/07/2015</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Swastik</FirstName>
<LastName>Kopparty</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Swastik Kopparty</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>swastik.kopparty@rutgers.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>8484457953</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000597426</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/07/2015</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Rutgers University New Brunswick</Name>
<CityName>Piscataway</CityName>
<ZipCode>088543925</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>8489320150</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>33 Knightsbridge Road</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[2nd Floor East Wing]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New Jersey</StateName>
<StateCode>NJ</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>06</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NJ06</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>001912864</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>RUTGERS, THE STATE UNIVERSITY OF NEW JERSEY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>001912864</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Rutgers, The State University of New Jersey]]></Name>
<CityName>Piscataway</CityName>
<StateCode>NJ</StateCode>
<ZipCode>088548019</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[110 Frelinghuysen Rd Hill Center]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New Jersey</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>06</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NJ06</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>2878</Code>
<Text>Special Projects - CCF</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>2878</Code>
<Text>SPECIAL PROJECTS - CCF</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0115</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2015~40000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>This project explored the role invariances and invariance groups play in coding theory and complexity theory. The results of this research are new understandings and new applications of these notions, resulting in better soundness for interactive and probabilistic proof systems, which have applications to blockchains and cryptography.</p> <p>At the technical level, the main new advances are strong new invariance properties of the error-correcting behaviour of polynomial codes. These properties imply that random linear combinations of functions that are far from polynomials are themselves far from polynomials with high probability. This enables the compression of many algebraic claims (such as those that appear in algebraic versions of Probabilistically Checkable Proofs and Interactive Proofs) into a single algebraic claim. Such compression plays an important part of popular proof systems such as STARKs, and the main advances of this research project enables better soundness guarantees for these proof systems.&nbsp;</p> <p>This project supported the research of the PIs and their PhD students, as well as their collaboration with researchers in Israel. These PhD students have graduated and are now in various jobs in academia and industry. Results of this research were published in conference proceedings and journals, and talks about the results of this research were given at various workshops and seminars.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 05/05/2021<br>      Modified by: Swastik&nbsp;Kopparty</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ This project explored the role invariances and invariance groups play in coding theory and complexity theory. The results of this research are new understandings and new applications of these notions, resulting in better soundness for interactive and probabilistic proof systems, which have applications to blockchains and cryptography.  At the technical level, the main new advances are strong new invariance properties of the error-correcting behaviour of polynomial codes. These properties imply that random linear combinations of functions that are far from polynomials are themselves far from polynomials with high probability. This enables the compression of many algebraic claims (such as those that appear in algebraic versions of Probabilistically Checkable Proofs and Interactive Proofs) into a single algebraic claim. Such compression plays an important part of popular proof systems such as STARKs, and the main advances of this research project enables better soundness guarantees for these proof systems.   This project supported the research of the PIs and their PhD students, as well as their collaboration with researchers in Israel. These PhD students have graduated and are now in various jobs in academia and industry. Results of this research were published in conference proceedings and journals, and talks about the results of this research were given at various workshops and seminars.          Last Modified: 05/05/2021       Submitted by: Swastik Kopparty]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
