<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Evolution of magnetoelasticity from a single-atom bridge to bulk</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2014</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2020</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>398046.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>398046</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03070000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DMR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Materials Research</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Tomasz Durakiewicz</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>tdurakie@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924892</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>****Technical Abstract****&lt;br/&gt;This project will experimentally map the evolution of magneto-elasticity in ferromagnets from a single-atom to bulk. This will be accomplished by using a custom built probe that is capable of making stable atomic-sized samples as small as a single-atom bridge, an atomic chain or atomic clusters, and measure their interatomic forces and distortions with pico-level resolution under applied field, mechanical perturbations, and as a function of temperature. The project will focus on iron, cobalt, nickel, terbium and gadolinium, which are key components of all magnetic actuator materials. By pinpointing the length scales where enhanced magnetoelasticity occur will lead to new strategies for "materials by design" and development of new alloys with enhanced actuation. The project will support education of two graduate students. Training of graduate students in thin films and vacuum technology, nano-science and nanofabrication is of direct relevance to wealth generating high-tech companies and opens vast opportunities for students upon graduation. The project will also host 1-2 high school or undergraduate students through university's Louis Stokes Alliance for Minorities Program. The project will also offer outreach to a startup company that seeks to commercialize the probe used to conduct experiments in this project.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;****Non-Technical Abstract****&lt;br/&gt;The ability of magnetic materials to precisely expand or contract in a magnetic field makes them highly useful as sensors and actuators in industries ranging from automobile, aerospace, data storage, to satellites and telecommunication systems. There is urgent need to create new magnetic alloys that can exhibit larger displacements or exert higher forces in a magnetic field. This project will experimentally map the evolution of this actuation ability in magnets, starting with samples as small as a single atom bridge or an atomic chain, to bulk. This will be accomplished by using a custom built probe capable of making atomic sized samples and measure forces and displacements with sub-nanometer accuracy. The project will focus on iron, cobalt, nickel, terbium and gadolinium, which are key components of all magnetic actuators and sensors. Pinpointing the optimum size for highest actuation will lead to new strategies for "materials by design" and development of advanced alloys. The project will support education of two graduate students and 1-2 undergraduate students whose training in thin films and vacuum technology, nano-science and microfabrication is highly sought after by wealth generating high tech companies. The project will also offer help to a startup company that is commercializing the probe used for experiments in this project.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>04/28/2015</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/23/2019</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1541236</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Harsh</FirstName>
<LastName>Chopra</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>D</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Harsh D Chopra</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>chopra@temple.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2152046394</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000200509</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/28/2015</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Temple University</Name>
<CityName>Philadelphia</CityName>
<ZipCode>191226003</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2157077547</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1801 N. Broad Street</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Pennsylvania</StateName>
<StateCode>PA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>PA02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>057123192</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>TEMPLE UNIVERSITY-OF THE COMMONWEALTH SYSTEM OF HIGHER EDUCATION</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>057123192</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Temple University]]></Name>
<CityName>Philadelphia</CityName>
<StateCode>PA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>191226023</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[1947 N. 12th Street]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Pennsylvania</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>PA02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1710</Code>
<Text>CONDENSED MATTER PHYSICS</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7237</Code>
<Text>NANO NON-SOLIC SCI &amp; ENG AWD</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0113</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0114</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0115</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0116</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2013~38046</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~120000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2015~120000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2016~120000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Intellectual Merits:</p> <p>Under the auspices of this grant, research has led to several significant outcomes. These include the discovery of non-Joulian magnetostriction phenomenon that upends a 170-year old paradigm of volume conservation in magnets in magnetic fields set by John Prescott Joule (Joulian magnetostriction). Further investigations of non-Joulian magnetostriction led PI to discover a new class of magnetism called <em>Non-Joulian Magnetism</em>, which provides a new basis to design advanced functional materials. During the course of these investigations, PI established a new field called &lsquo;<em>Magnetic Cybernetics</em>&rsquo;, which is based on correlating the observed digital magnetic properties of non-Joulian magnets. Magnetic Cybernetics provides a practical approach for designing magnets with enhanced magnetic effects, make possible magnetic properties that are otherwise not feasible in conventional magnets like ferro- or ferrimagnets, and leads to the discovery of physical phenomena that can be uniquely attributed to this new field. Indeed, the Magnetic Cybernetics approach pioneered by PI established a <em>new benchmark</em> for the magnitude of room temperature magnetostriction strains (3400 ppm) in inexpensive Fe-Al alloy system, versus magneto-strains of just 1900 ppm reported 40 years ago in brittle, reactive, hard to process, and geo-strategically scarce rare-earth magnets (e.g., Tb-Fe, Tb-Fe-Dy). Cumulatively, the outcomes of this grant have led to 8 publications in premier journals, including 2 in Nature, as well as a USPTO granted in August 22, 2020 on non-Joulian magnetostriction materials.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>Broader Impacts</p> <p>This NSF grant provided training to 14 undergraduate students (including two African-Americans and a woman), several of whom have gone on to pursue graduate degrees (at Stanford, Australia, Temple, etc.). Several of these undergraduate students are co-authors on publications resulting from this grant. In addition, research supported the work of five graduate students. In terms of technological Broader Impacts, the impacts are both <em>functional</em> in terms of enhanced properties, and <em>fundamental</em> in terms of discovery of new phenomena unique to Magnetic Cybernetics and non-Joulian magnetism. The findings will necessitate the development of new theory incorporating discontinuous (digital) magnetic behavior of non-Joulian magnets. Impacts of Magnetic Cybernetics and non-Joulian magnetism are also <em>far-reaching since digital behavior affects all</em> <em>functional properties</em> (magnetoresistive, magneto-optical, magneto-elastics, soft magnetism, etc.), and in bulk, thin films and multilayers.</p> <p>Non-Joulian magnetism has also rendered a sizeable literature over the past two decades moot and unreliable for high-fidelity and/or critical applications. This is because the past literature ignored hallmarks of volume changing non-Joulian magnetism, and instead, characterized a wide variety of magnetic crystals on the basis of Joulian (volume-conserving) framework and phenomenological magnetostriction theory of homogeneous crystals, which <em>a priori</em> assumes volume conservation. These assumptions have been shown to be invalid through the work reported in this grant, past data shown to be unreliable, and applications using past data perilous for critical applications.</p> <p>This NSF work was subjected to attempted undermining by a research group at Beihang University, Beijing (a defense university of China) and their international partners/collaborators. This group attempted to portray non-Joulian volume change as not generalizable to all Fe-Ga alloys. PI called out this group&rsquo;s data to be specious and showed that it hid large volume changes contrary to their claims.</p> <p>To summarize, research supported by this NSF grant has led to the discovery of non-Joulian magnetostriction wherein magnets change their volume in applied magnetic fields, thereby upending a 170-year old paradigm of volume conservation first set by John Prescott Joule called Joulian magnetostriction. PI has discovered a new class of magnets called <em>Non-Joulian Magnetism and functional materials based it</em>. Subsequently, PI founded a new approach called &lsquo;<em>Magnetic Cybernetics</em>&rsquo;, which provides a fundamentally new basis for designing magnets with enhanced magnetic effects, and to design magnetic properties otherwise not possible using conventional magnets. Magnetic Cybernetics approach established a <em>new benchmark</em> for the magnitude of room temperature magnetostriction strains in inexpensive Fe-Al system that are nearly twice the 40-year record in brittle, reactive, hard to process, and geo-strategically scarce rare-earth magnets (e.g., Tb-Fe, Tb-Fe-Dy). Research supported by this grant has also rendered a sizeable literature over the past two decades moot and unreliable for high-fidelity applications because past literature ignored the hallmarks of volume changing non-Joulian magnetism, and instead, characterized a wide variety of magnetic crystals on the basis of Joulian (volume-conserving) framework. Impacts of research stemming from this grant are both <em>functional</em> in terms of enhanced properties, and <em>fundamental</em> in terms of discovery of new phenomena unique to Magnetic Cybernetics. It will necessitate the development of new theory incorporating discontinuous (digital) behavior. Impacts of Magnetic Cybernetics are <em>far-reaching since digital behavior affects <span style="text-decoration: underline;">all</span></em> <em>functional properties</em> (magnetoresistive, magneto-optical, magneto-elastics, soft magnetism, etc.), and in bulk, thin films and multilayers. These activities engaged 14 undergraduate students (including two African-Americans and a woman), several of whom are co-authors on papers published with the help of this grant, 5 graduate students; several undergraduate students went on to pursue graduate degrees.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 09/29/2020<br>      Modified by: Harsh&nbsp;D&nbsp;Chopra</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Intellectual Merits:  Under the auspices of this grant, research has led to several significant outcomes. These include the discovery of non-Joulian magnetostriction phenomenon that upends a 170-year old paradigm of volume conservation in magnets in magnetic fields set by John Prescott Joule (Joulian magnetostriction). Further investigations of non-Joulian magnetostriction led PI to discover a new class of magnetism called Non-Joulian Magnetism, which provides a new basis to design advanced functional materials. During the course of these investigations, PI established a new field called ‘Magnetic Cybernetics’, which is based on correlating the observed digital magnetic properties of non-Joulian magnets. Magnetic Cybernetics provides a practical approach for designing magnets with enhanced magnetic effects, make possible magnetic properties that are otherwise not feasible in conventional magnets like ferro- or ferrimagnets, and leads to the discovery of physical phenomena that can be uniquely attributed to this new field. Indeed, the Magnetic Cybernetics approach pioneered by PI established a new benchmark for the magnitude of room temperature magnetostriction strains (3400 ppm) in inexpensive Fe-Al alloy system, versus magneto-strains of just 1900 ppm reported 40 years ago in brittle, reactive, hard to process, and geo-strategically scarce rare-earth magnets (e.g., Tb-Fe, Tb-Fe-Dy). Cumulatively, the outcomes of this grant have led to 8 publications in premier journals, including 2 in Nature, as well as a USPTO granted in August 22, 2020 on non-Joulian magnetostriction materials.     Broader Impacts  This NSF grant provided training to 14 undergraduate students (including two African-Americans and a woman), several of whom have gone on to pursue graduate degrees (at Stanford, Australia, Temple, etc.). Several of these undergraduate students are co-authors on publications resulting from this grant. In addition, research supported the work of five graduate students. In terms of technological Broader Impacts, the impacts are both functional in terms of enhanced properties, and fundamental in terms of discovery of new phenomena unique to Magnetic Cybernetics and non-Joulian magnetism. The findings will necessitate the development of new theory incorporating discontinuous (digital) magnetic behavior of non-Joulian magnets. Impacts of Magnetic Cybernetics and non-Joulian magnetism are also far-reaching since digital behavior affects all functional properties (magnetoresistive, magneto-optical, magneto-elastics, soft magnetism, etc.), and in bulk, thin films and multilayers.  Non-Joulian magnetism has also rendered a sizeable literature over the past two decades moot and unreliable for high-fidelity and/or critical applications. This is because the past literature ignored hallmarks of volume changing non-Joulian magnetism, and instead, characterized a wide variety of magnetic crystals on the basis of Joulian (volume-conserving) framework and phenomenological magnetostriction theory of homogeneous crystals, which a priori assumes volume conservation. These assumptions have been shown to be invalid through the work reported in this grant, past data shown to be unreliable, and applications using past data perilous for critical applications.  This NSF work was subjected to attempted undermining by a research group at Beihang University, Beijing (a defense university of China) and their international partners/collaborators. This group attempted to portray non-Joulian volume change as not generalizable to all Fe-Ga alloys. PI called out this group’s data to be specious and showed that it hid large volume changes contrary to their claims.  To summarize, research supported by this NSF grant has led to the discovery of non-Joulian magnetostriction wherein magnets change their volume in applied magnetic fields, thereby upending a 170-year old paradigm of volume conservation first set by John Prescott Joule called Joulian magnetostriction. PI has discovered a new class of magnets called Non-Joulian Magnetism and functional materials based it. Subsequently, PI founded a new approach called ‘Magnetic Cybernetics’, which provides a fundamentally new basis for designing magnets with enhanced magnetic effects, and to design magnetic properties otherwise not possible using conventional magnets. Magnetic Cybernetics approach established a new benchmark for the magnitude of room temperature magnetostriction strains in inexpensive Fe-Al system that are nearly twice the 40-year record in brittle, reactive, hard to process, and geo-strategically scarce rare-earth magnets (e.g., Tb-Fe, Tb-Fe-Dy). Research supported by this grant has also rendered a sizeable literature over the past two decades moot and unreliable for high-fidelity applications because past literature ignored the hallmarks of volume changing non-Joulian magnetism, and instead, characterized a wide variety of magnetic crystals on the basis of Joulian (volume-conserving) framework. Impacts of research stemming from this grant are both functional in terms of enhanced properties, and fundamental in terms of discovery of new phenomena unique to Magnetic Cybernetics. It will necessitate the development of new theory incorporating discontinuous (digital) behavior. Impacts of Magnetic Cybernetics are far-reaching since digital behavior affects all functional properties (magnetoresistive, magneto-optical, magneto-elastics, soft magnetism, etc.), and in bulk, thin films and multilayers. These activities engaged 14 undergraduate students (including two African-Americans and a woman), several of whom are co-authors on papers published with the help of this grant, 5 graduate students; several undergraduate students went on to pursue graduate degrees.       Last Modified: 09/29/2020       Submitted by: Harsh D Chopra]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
