<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>CC*DNI Networking Infrastructure: Building a High Performance Network to Support Advanced Instrumentation, Computation-Intensive Analysis and Data-Intensive Science Research</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>01/01/2016</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>394715.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>394715</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>05090000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>CSE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>OAC</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Office of Advanced Cyberinfrastructure (OAC)</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Kevin Thompson</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>kthompso@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924220</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Siena College is a vibrant undergraduate liberal arts college with a strong School of Science. Siena faculty in the sciences conduct cutting-edge research and involve undergraduate students in that research. Students also conduct independent  research with faculty supervision as part of the Center for Undergraduate Research and Creative Activity (CURCA) program.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This two-year project creates a state-of-the-art research oriented network infrastructure to support STEM research at the College.  Research projects in the fields of computational chemistry (using Siena's High Performance Computing Cluster or HPCC), nanoscience, biophysics, astrophysics, and particle physics have been hampered by currently limited network transfer speeds. This project significantly enhances the ability for faculty and students to carry out their work.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The project creates a network infrastructure designed to optimize networking and security for high performance scientific applications. This includes improving data transfer speeds within the School of Science building complex and between the sciences and the College data center where the HPCC is housed by a factor of 10. The proposed upgrades also position Siena to create connections to external high-performance networks such as NYSERnet and Internet2, facilitating collaboration with researchers at other institutions as well as access to instrumentation and research tools at other institutions.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;As a result of this project interdisciplinary research projects are fostered and encouraged. Sophisticated cyberinfrastructure is a critical underpinning to scientific research initiatives and this project creates that foundation at Siena College.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>12/24/2015</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>01/03/2017</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.070</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1541001</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Allan</FirstName>
<LastName>Weatherwax</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>T</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Allan T Weatherwax</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>weatherwaxa@merrimack.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>9788375234</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000150595</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>12/24/2015</StartDate>
<EndDate>01/03/2017</EndDate>
<RoleCode>Former Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>George</FirstName>
<LastName>Barnes</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>L</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>George L Barnes</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>gbarnes@siena.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5187826880</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000656378</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>12/24/2015</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Mark</FirstName>
<LastName>Berman</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Mark Berman</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>mberman@siena.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5187826957</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000668834</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>12/24/2015</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Mary</FirstName>
<LastName>Parlett-Sweeney</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Mary Parlett-Sweeney</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>mparlett-sweeney@siena.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5187832307</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000668835</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>12/24/2015</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>John</FirstName>
<LastName>Moustakas</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>John Moustakas</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>jmoustakas@siena.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5187834274</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000668902</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>12/24/2015</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Angelo</FirstName>
<LastName>Santabarbara</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Angelo Santabarbara</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>asantabarbara@siena.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5187826996</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000668998</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>01/03/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Siena College</Name>
<CityName>LOUDONVILLE</CityName>
<ZipCode>122111462</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5187822322</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>515 LOUDON ROAD</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>20</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NY20</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>080481351</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>SIENA COLLEGE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>080481351</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Siena College]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<ZipCode>122111462</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>20</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NY20</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>8080</Code>
<Text>Campus Cyberinfrastructure</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0116</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2016~394715</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><span id="docs-internal-guid-c52daac8-7204-d30e-a6ac-b1176a3c6a52"> </span></p> <p><span id="docs-internal-guid-c52daac8-720f-a169-4b39-2163368df44e"> </span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>Project Title: CC*IIE Networking Infrastructure: Building a high performance network to support advanced instrumentation, computation-intensive analysis and data-intensive science research</span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>Principal Investigator: Mark Berman</span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>Co-PI(s): John Moustakas, Mary Parlett-Sweeney, George Barnes, Angelo Santabarbara</span></p> <h2 dir="ltr"><span>Project Goals</span></h2> <p dir="ltr"><span>This two year project has created a state-of-the-art research oriented network infrastructure to support STEM research at the College. Research projects in the fields of computational chemistry (using our High Performance Computing Cluster or HPCC), nanoscience, biophysics, astrophysics, and particle physics had been hampered by limited network transfer speeds.</span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>This project significantly enhances the ability for faculty to carry on research and for students to be involved in research projects. A high speed network was created, parallel to the production data network which is used for teaching, study, the business of the College, and for student entertainment. &nbsp;By separating scientific traffic onto its own network, up to 40 times faster than the production network, scientific research of a sort not possible on the production network can become routine.</span></p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p dir="ltr"><span>Siena College also houses a High Performance Computing Cluster (HPCC), used primarily for computational chemistry, but shared with researchers in other fields such as physics and astronomy. The project increased inter-node connection speed in the HPCC from 10 Gb/Sec to 56 Gb/Sec. With direct connection to the Science DMZ, and high-speed connection to an associated high-performance storage system, we have allowed greater collaboration between researchers and for research data to be kept separate between projects using the HPCC.</span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>The upgrades have also positioned us to create connections to external high performance networks such as NYSERnet and Internet2, facilitating collaboration with researchers at other institutions as well as access to instrumentation and research tools at other institutions. We are in the process of preparing to go live with a 10 Gb/sec link to NYSERnet&rsquo;s State research network that will allow researchers at our small residential college to collaborate as peers with researchers at large R1 research institutions.</span></p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p dir="ltr"><span>As a result of this project interdisciplinary research projects are fostered and encouraged. Sophisticated cyberinfrastructure is a critical underpinning to scientific research initiatives and this project creates that foundation at Siena College.</span></p> <h2 dir="ltr"><span>Accomplishments</span></h2> <ul> <li dir="ltr"> <p dir="ltr"><span>Joined NYSERNET, the NY State regional research and education network provider.</span></p> </li> <li dir="ltr"> <p dir="ltr"><span>Upgraded the cable infrastructure to support high-speed (10G and greater) in and to the two buildings of the Science Center, specifically targeting teaching lab spaces and research labs.</span></p> </li> <li dir="ltr"> <p dir="ltr"><span>Upgraded Juniper routers and core switches to support 40G network speeds to and between the science buildings.</span></p> </li> <li dir="ltr"> <p dir="ltr"><span>Installed separate fiber data lines on campus to provide alternate physical paths to the two data centers on campus to provide additional redundancy and reliability to the campus network and Science DMZ.</span></p> </li> <li dir="ltr"> <p dir="ltr"><span>Added two additional Juniper core switches to act as the distribution layer for the new Science DMZ.</span></p> </li> <li dir="ltr"> <p dir="ltr"><span>Upgraded the intra-node networking in the HPCC from 1G to 56 G</span></p> </li> <li dir="ltr"> <p dir="ltr"><span>Installed PerfSonar monitoring of our Science DMZ and added our PerfSonar configuration to the national network of PerfSonar nodes.</span></p> </li> <li dir="ltr"> <p dir="ltr"><span>Taking advantage of our NYSERNET membership to obtain favorable pricing to increase the speed of Siena&rsquo;s connections to the outside world.</span></p> </li> </ul> <h2 dir="ltr"><span>Results</span></h2> <p dir="ltr"><span>Today Siena College faculty researcher are beginning to take advantage of these new capabilities to move existing projects along more quickly and to contemplate new projects that might have been too time consuming, or even impossible before. We have already seen one peer-reviewed research publication, with others in preparation, which took advantage of our new Science DMZ and the improved accessibility and data processing speed of our HPCC</span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span> </span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>Barnes, George L., and Amanda Podczerwinski. &ldquo;Simulating the Effect of Charge State on Reactive Landing of a Cyclic Tetrapeptide on Chemically Modified Alkylthiolate Self-Assembled Monolayer Surfaces.&rdquo; </span><span>The Journal of Physical Chemistry C</span><span> 121, no. 27 (2017): 14628&ndash;14635.</span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span> </span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>Researchers in health studies or quantitative business analysis can now use our HPCC with the confidence that the confidential data with which they are working can be adequately protected within the new high speed storage system. Siena students are also beginning to take advantage of the new science network both as research assistants to faculty and to conduct their own undergraduate research. We believe that the facilities provided by this grant will enhance not only faculty research but also undergraduate student research and STEM teaching and learning.</span></p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p dir="ltr"><span>There is a great deal of excitement about the project among our STEM faculty. The impact on currently ongoing research projects is noticeable, and the opportunities for our undergraduate students to engage with scientific research are growing. Connections between the Science DMZ and our instrumentation lab, the Stewart's Advanced Instrumentation and Technology (SAInT) Center, offer opportunities for student research projects to take advantage of our new science network and for students to collaborate with projects at other institutions.</span></p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 03/29/2018<br>      Modified by: Mark&nbsp;Berman</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[      Project Title: CC*IIE Networking Infrastructure: Building a high performance network to support advanced instrumentation, computation-intensive analysis and data-intensive science research Principal Investigator: Mark Berman Co-PI(s): John Moustakas, Mary Parlett-Sweeney, George Barnes, Angelo Santabarbara Project Goals This two year project has created a state-of-the-art research oriented network infrastructure to support STEM research at the College. Research projects in the fields of computational chemistry (using our High Performance Computing Cluster or HPCC), nanoscience, biophysics, astrophysics, and particle physics had been hampered by limited network transfer speeds. This project significantly enhances the ability for faculty to carry on research and for students to be involved in research projects. A high speed network was created, parallel to the production data network which is used for teaching, study, the business of the College, and for student entertainment.  By separating scientific traffic onto its own network, up to 40 times faster than the production network, scientific research of a sort not possible on the production network can become routine.    Siena College also houses a High Performance Computing Cluster (HPCC), used primarily for computational chemistry, but shared with researchers in other fields such as physics and astronomy. The project increased inter-node connection speed in the HPCC from 10 Gb/Sec to 56 Gb/Sec. With direct connection to the Science DMZ, and high-speed connection to an associated high-performance storage system, we have allowed greater collaboration between researchers and for research data to be kept separate between projects using the HPCC. The upgrades have also positioned us to create connections to external high performance networks such as NYSERnet and Internet2, facilitating collaboration with researchers at other institutions as well as access to instrumentation and research tools at other institutions. We are in the process of preparing to go live with a 10 Gb/sec link to NYSERnet?s State research network that will allow researchers at our small residential college to collaborate as peers with researchers at large R1 research institutions.    As a result of this project interdisciplinary research projects are fostered and encouraged. Sophisticated cyberinfrastructure is a critical underpinning to scientific research initiatives and this project creates that foundation at Siena College. Accomplishments   Joined NYSERNET, the NY State regional research and education network provider.   Upgraded the cable infrastructure to support high-speed (10G and greater) in and to the two buildings of the Science Center, specifically targeting teaching lab spaces and research labs.   Upgraded Juniper routers and core switches to support 40G network speeds to and between the science buildings.   Installed separate fiber data lines on campus to provide alternate physical paths to the two data centers on campus to provide additional redundancy and reliability to the campus network and Science DMZ.   Added two additional Juniper core switches to act as the distribution layer for the new Science DMZ.   Upgraded the intra-node networking in the HPCC from 1G to 56 G   Installed PerfSonar monitoring of our Science DMZ and added our PerfSonar configuration to the national network of PerfSonar nodes.   Taking advantage of our NYSERNET membership to obtain favorable pricing to increase the speed of Siena?s connections to the outside world.   Results Today Siena College faculty researcher are beginning to take advantage of these new capabilities to move existing projects along more quickly and to contemplate new projects that might have been too time consuming, or even impossible before. We have already seen one peer-reviewed research publication, with others in preparation, which took advantage of our new Science DMZ and the improved accessibility and data processing speed of our HPCC   Barnes, George L., and Amanda Podczerwinski. "Simulating the Effect of Charge State on Reactive Landing of a Cyclic Tetrapeptide on Chemically Modified Alkylthiolate Self-Assembled Monolayer Surfaces." The Journal of Physical Chemistry C 121, no. 27 (2017): 14628&ndash;14635.   Researchers in health studies or quantitative business analysis can now use our HPCC with the confidence that the confidential data with which they are working can be adequately protected within the new high speed storage system. Siena students are also beginning to take advantage of the new science network both as research assistants to faculty and to conduct their own undergraduate research. We believe that the facilities provided by this grant will enhance not only faculty research but also undergraduate student research and STEM teaching and learning.    There is a great deal of excitement about the project among our STEM faculty. The impact on currently ongoing research projects is noticeable, and the opportunities for our undergraduate students to engage with scientific research are growing. Connections between the Science DMZ and our instrumentation lab, the Stewart's Advanced Instrumentation and Technology (SAInT) Center, offer opportunities for student research projects to take advantage of our new science network and for students to collaborate with projects at other institutions.                Last Modified: 03/29/2018       Submitted by: Mark Berman]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
