<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>CC*DNI Networking Infrastructure: Custom Science DMZ Per Research Lab with a Secure Invitation to Opt-In</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>01/01/2016</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>499681.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>499681</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>05090000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>CSE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>OAC</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Office of Advanced Cyberinfrastructure (OAC)</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Kevin Thompson</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>kthompso@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924220</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Science data transfers originating from various research labs to other collaborating labs and cloud resources have long been enabled by significant investments in research infrastructure at the university level. However, when a research lab transfers large scientific data sets, many hurdles still exist for research and Information Technology (IT) communities to work together in creating secure topologies for research collaboration.  The University of Houston's vision is to enable the abstraction of circuit setup, traffic steering, and leveraging of network functionality for end-users to opt-in to connect their data with researcher labs in a customized fashion with relevant data sharing policies enforced on the topology. This project: (1) deploys network function instantiation (NFI) within main distribution frame (MDF) components at strategic buildings with research labs on university campuses; (2) implements an interdisciplinary data sharing isolated network customized for an air quality and healthcare research use case; and (3) deploys the NFI capability as a pilot on LEARN (Lonestar Education and Research Network) for future support of science data flows.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This work has a broad impact across many dimensions: isolated networks per research lab creates an environment for accelerated innovation, free of operational constraints. The proposed prototype research topology supports researchers in eliminating the data sharing problems, with concepts that extend to all research collaborations.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>12/24/2015</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/31/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.070</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1541368</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Deniz</FirstName>
<LastName>Gurkan</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Deniz Gurkan</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>dgurkan@uh.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>7137434037</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000486896</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>12/24/2015</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Nicholas</FirstName>
<LastName>Bastin</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Nicholas Bastin</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>nick.bastin@gmail.com</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2026423578</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000686473</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>12/24/2015</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Houston</Name>
<CityName>Houston</CityName>
<ZipCode>772042015</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>7137435773</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>4800 Calhoun Boulevard</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Texas</StateName>
<StateCode>TX</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>18</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>TX18</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>036837920</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF HOUSTON SYSTEM</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>042916627</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Houston]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>TX</StateCode>
<ZipCode>772044020</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Texas</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>18</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>TX18</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>8080</Code>
<Text>Campus Cyberinfrastructure</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0116</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2016~499681</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The project has been on creation of customized connectivity options for various data transfer needs of domain science research laboratories at University of Houston and collaborating institutions in the region. We generalize these connectivity options for research institution's cyberinfrastructure settings cognizant of the domain science research lab connections in an academic department and the hierarchy of work processes within information technology departments. Furthermore, the data sharing principles of particular projects, regulatory expectations, and institutional research data handling processes feed into how data flows may have applicable policy sets within the science DMZ frameworks. The intellectual merit of the project is composed of multiple outcomes: an IT process flow and associated network policy enforcement frameworks for a science DMZ request per custom domain science research lab; the custom data flow connectivity policy enforcement function and a reference implementation. The data exchange scenario has been mapped with domain science collaborators spanning healthcare patient data, environmental air quality data, and associated correlation analysis components. The access permissions and authorizations were used to create policies to be enforced over the network, through trust maps of environments that the data may traverse. To that end, a reference network function has been implemented with policy enforcement for a given access permission set.&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>The network function reference implementation is developed on a topology that is built by the cyberinfrastructure orchestrator of the UH networking research lab. The security policies relating to authorization of access levels and on-demand connectivity are enforced in an end-to-end scenario. The broader impact of the project is the collective contribution to the distributed systems and networking research scientific community with the outcomes of reference implementation along with experimentation framework and the orchestrator. All code is maintained as open source at real time on a professional version control repository.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>The UH experimentation framework and custom policy enforcement methods generated educational broader impacts as well. The PIs developed instructional material for the high school settings as well as undergraduate, and graduate level computer networking, network security, and network programming curricula. Particularly, (1) the orchestration of network models for specific connectivity scenarios; and (2) the experimentation framework for generation of network data exchange scenarios are leveraged to create realistic hands-on labs. Computer networking course has been revamped to assign custom topologies per student to observe network behavior with specific policy enforcements. Furthermore, the content has been redesigned in the graduate level network programming course to offer a design method and process to implement and develop policies, network functions, and associated validation topologies.&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 03/21/2019<br>      Modified by: Deniz&nbsp;Gurkan</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The project has been on creation of customized connectivity options for various data transfer needs of domain science research laboratories at University of Houston and collaborating institutions in the region. We generalize these connectivity options for research institution's cyberinfrastructure settings cognizant of the domain science research lab connections in an academic department and the hierarchy of work processes within information technology departments. Furthermore, the data sharing principles of particular projects, regulatory expectations, and institutional research data handling processes feed into how data flows may have applicable policy sets within the science DMZ frameworks. The intellectual merit of the project is composed of multiple outcomes: an IT process flow and associated network policy enforcement frameworks for a science DMZ request per custom domain science research lab; the custom data flow connectivity policy enforcement function and a reference implementation. The data exchange scenario has been mapped with domain science collaborators spanning healthcare patient data, environmental air quality data, and associated correlation analysis components. The access permissions and authorizations were used to create policies to be enforced over the network, through trust maps of environments that the data may traverse. To that end, a reference network function has been implemented with policy enforcement for a given access permission set.      The network function reference implementation is developed on a topology that is built by the cyberinfrastructure orchestrator of the UH networking research lab. The security policies relating to authorization of access levels and on-demand connectivity are enforced in an end-to-end scenario. The broader impact of the project is the collective contribution to the distributed systems and networking research scientific community with the outcomes of reference implementation along with experimentation framework and the orchestrator. All code is maintained as open source at real time on a professional version control repository.     The UH experimentation framework and custom policy enforcement methods generated educational broader impacts as well. The PIs developed instructional material for the high school settings as well as undergraduate, and graduate level computer networking, network security, and network programming curricula. Particularly, (1) the orchestration of network models for specific connectivity scenarios; and (2) the experimentation framework for generation of network data exchange scenarios are leveraged to create realistic hands-on labs. Computer networking course has been revamped to assign custom topologies per student to observe network behavior with specific policy enforcements. Furthermore, the content has been redesigned in the graduate level network programming course to offer a design method and process to implement and develop policies, network functions, and associated validation topologies.        Last Modified: 03/21/2019       Submitted by: Deniz Gurkan]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
