<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>High Resolution Underway Observations in Drake Passage: Ocean Physics</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2016</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2020</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>530448.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>530448</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>06090300</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>GEO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>OPP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Office of Polar Programs (OPP)</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Peter Milne</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>pmilne@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924714</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The Antarctic Circumpolar Current (ACC) is the strongest ocean current in the world, with a flow rate more than 100 times greater than all the rivers on Earth combined.  This project continues a long-term study of ocean properties and variability in the ACC by repeat transects across the Drake Passage from Punta Arenas to Palmer Station using the USAP supply ship RV/AS LMGould.  This project will provide information about long term trends and variability in Southern Ocean fronts, surface water mass properties, heat, and salinity budgets.  This study will contribute to understanding the response of the ACC to atmospheric forcing on climate relevant time scales, and its role in driving the meridional overturning circulation of the Southern Ocean. These data represent the only year-round shipboard measurements in the Southern Ocean.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project will continue high-resolution, near-repeat XBT/XCTD/ADCP transect sampling in Drake Passage in order to study modes of variability in ocean temperature, salinity, currents and backscatter in the Antarctic Circumpolar Current (ACC).  The data will capture variability on time scales from seasonal to interannual and on spatial scales from current cores to eddies. With almost two decades of data now available, the primary science objectives are to analyze the Drake Passage time series and (1) describe and relate the seasonal and long-term ocean energy distribution to wind, buoyancy and topographic forcing and sinks, and (2) describe and relate seasonal and long-term changes in the ACC fronts, water masses and upwelling to biogeochemical variability. The continued data collection, quality control and dissemination of the Drake Passage data sets to the broader oceanographic community are critical components of the project.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>09/01/2016</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>09/01/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.078</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1542902</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Teresa</FirstName>
<LastName>Chereskin</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>K</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Teresa K Chereskin</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>tchereskin@ucsd.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>8585346368</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000315076</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/01/2016</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Janet</FirstName>
<LastName>Sprintall</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Janet Sprintall</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>jsprintall@ucsd.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>8588220589</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000430579</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/01/2016</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of California-San Diego Scripps Inst of Oceanography</Name>
<CityName>LA JOLLA</CityName>
<ZipCode>920930210</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>8585341293</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>8602 La Jolla Shores Dr</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[Univ of California-San Diego]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>49</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CA49</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>175104595</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF CALIFORNIA SAN DIEGO</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>071549000</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[UCSD Scripps Inst of Oceanography]]></Name>
<CityName>La Jolla</CityName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>920930210</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[9500 Gilman Drive]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>49</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CA49</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>5113</Code>
<Text>ANT Ocean &amp; Atmos Sciences</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>5113</Code>
<Text>ANTARCTIC OCEAN &amp; ATMOSPH SCI</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>02XX</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2016~530448</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>This report gives outcomes from an award that provided 3 years of support for a long-term observational program that continues under renewed funding.&nbsp;</p> <p>The Southern Ocean heat balance is important for global climate, driving downwelling and upwelling across the Antarctic Circumpolar Current (ACC). Although this vertical circulation is small compared to the horizontal transport of the ACC, its effects on climate and the ecosystem are critical: for example, facilitating biological productivity through the vertical transport of nutrients and governing the sequestration and release of CO2 between ocean and atmosphere. Understanding how heat crosses the ACC is crucial to correctly model and predict the ocean's influence on climate and its response to change.&nbsp;</p> <p>To address our goals to better understand the processes of importance to the Southern Ocean heat balance, we continued underway sampling of upper ocean temperature, salinity and ocean currents in conjunction with the collection of atmospheric and oceanic CO2, nutrients, and meteorological parameters from the repeated transits of the principal USAP supply vessel that crosses Drake Passage on average 22 times annually. Many of these time series began almost two decades ago, and together they provide concurrent information of the physical and biogeochemical air-sea variability at high temporal and spatial resolution on a near year-round basis, an unmatched achievement in the Southern Ocean.</p> <p>Our research using the Drake Passage time series addressed two major topics. The first was to describe and quantify the seasonal and long-term distribution of heat and energy in Drake Passage on spatial scales from hundreds to ten kilometers. The second was to describe and relate changes in the ACC fronts, water masses, and upwelling to biogeochemical variability.</p> <p>The ACC comprises multiple deep-reaching velocity jets (also called fronts) that encircle the globe and present significant barriers to across-ACC exchange. Ocean eddies are a mechanism that break these barriers and transport heat across the ACC. Drake Passage is an identified eddy hot spot, one of six or so locations in the Southern Ocean where there is significant heat flux across the ACC. A key result of this project was to quantify eddy heat flux across the ACC in Drake Passage relative to the two largest jets: the Subantarctic Front (SAF) and Polar Front (PF). &nbsp;Satellite altimetry was used to track the meandering front locations. Eddy heat flux was estimated from the unique time series of upper ocean temperature and velocity transects in Drake Passage collected as part of this award. The across-stream eddy heat flux was found to be maximum poleward in the SAF, and was reduced towards the south, becoming statistically insignificant in the PF. The eddy kinetic energy had its largest signal in the Polar Frontal Zone between the SAF and PF and exhibited a seasonal cycle, with maximum amplitude in the austral spring-summer. The across-ACC eddy heat flux was maximum poleward during the austral fall-winter. Seasonality of the eddy heat flux implies that the eddy-driven upwelling of deep waters also varies seasonally.&nbsp;</p> <p>A second focus was on biogeochemical variability. We used a combination of the in situ nutrient samples and temperature data from the Drake Passage time series to better understand physical and biogeochemical co-variability in this dynamical hotspot. Seasonal and interannual variability and change were quantified in key climate variables, such as temperature, salinity, nitrate, and silicic acid over the period 2004-2017. Using front locations derived from subsurface temperature data and remotely sensed altimetry, the relationship between frontal position and the biogeochemistry was investigated in space and time.&nbsp;</p> <p>Our observations and analyses have improved the estimate of the mean and time-varying ACC, the major current system of the Southern Ocean. They have been used to validate satellite retrievals, climatologies and numerical models. The data we collect is assimilated in the Southern Ocean State Estimate. We provide processed data sets that are publicly available and used by scientists within multiple disciplines (physics, biology, chemistry). We provide high-quality in situ data for other researchers interested in variability in upper ocean temperature,currents, acoustic backscatter, carbon, and atmospheric CO2, and for testing ocean and coupled climate models.</p> <p>We provide the official request and clearance reporting for all underway measurements on the LMG. Without such requests and reporting, underway data for scientific use cannot be collected within foreign exclusive economic zones (EEZs), which include half of Drake Passage.</p> <p>The XBT software and probe launcher developed for the project has been widely used by the global Volunteer Observing Ship program. The ADCP software developed for the project is currently in use by the US oceanographic fleet.</p> <p>Publications from the award include 5 peer-reviewed journal articles and 17 conference presentations.</p> <p>The award contributed to education through support and training of 2 graduate students and 1 postdoctoral scholar.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 10/01/2020<br>      Modified by: Teresa&nbsp;K&nbsp;Chereskin</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ This report gives outcomes from an award that provided 3 years of support for a long-term observational program that continues under renewed funding.   The Southern Ocean heat balance is important for global climate, driving downwelling and upwelling across the Antarctic Circumpolar Current (ACC). Although this vertical circulation is small compared to the horizontal transport of the ACC, its effects on climate and the ecosystem are critical: for example, facilitating biological productivity through the vertical transport of nutrients and governing the sequestration and release of CO2 between ocean and atmosphere. Understanding how heat crosses the ACC is crucial to correctly model and predict the ocean's influence on climate and its response to change.   To address our goals to better understand the processes of importance to the Southern Ocean heat balance, we continued underway sampling of upper ocean temperature, salinity and ocean currents in conjunction with the collection of atmospheric and oceanic CO2, nutrients, and meteorological parameters from the repeated transits of the principal USAP supply vessel that crosses Drake Passage on average 22 times annually. Many of these time series began almost two decades ago, and together they provide concurrent information of the physical and biogeochemical air-sea variability at high temporal and spatial resolution on a near year-round basis, an unmatched achievement in the Southern Ocean.  Our research using the Drake Passage time series addressed two major topics. The first was to describe and quantify the seasonal and long-term distribution of heat and energy in Drake Passage on spatial scales from hundreds to ten kilometers. The second was to describe and relate changes in the ACC fronts, water masses, and upwelling to biogeochemical variability.  The ACC comprises multiple deep-reaching velocity jets (also called fronts) that encircle the globe and present significant barriers to across-ACC exchange. Ocean eddies are a mechanism that break these barriers and transport heat across the ACC. Drake Passage is an identified eddy hot spot, one of six or so locations in the Southern Ocean where there is significant heat flux across the ACC. A key result of this project was to quantify eddy heat flux across the ACC in Drake Passage relative to the two largest jets: the Subantarctic Front (SAF) and Polar Front (PF).  Satellite altimetry was used to track the meandering front locations. Eddy heat flux was estimated from the unique time series of upper ocean temperature and velocity transects in Drake Passage collected as part of this award. The across-stream eddy heat flux was found to be maximum poleward in the SAF, and was reduced towards the south, becoming statistically insignificant in the PF. The eddy kinetic energy had its largest signal in the Polar Frontal Zone between the SAF and PF and exhibited a seasonal cycle, with maximum amplitude in the austral spring-summer. The across-ACC eddy heat flux was maximum poleward during the austral fall-winter. Seasonality of the eddy heat flux implies that the eddy-driven upwelling of deep waters also varies seasonally.   A second focus was on biogeochemical variability. We used a combination of the in situ nutrient samples and temperature data from the Drake Passage time series to better understand physical and biogeochemical co-variability in this dynamical hotspot. Seasonal and interannual variability and change were quantified in key climate variables, such as temperature, salinity, nitrate, and silicic acid over the period 2004-2017. Using front locations derived from subsurface temperature data and remotely sensed altimetry, the relationship between frontal position and the biogeochemistry was investigated in space and time.   Our observations and analyses have improved the estimate of the mean and time-varying ACC, the major current system of the Southern Ocean. They have been used to validate satellite retrievals, climatologies and numerical models. The data we collect is assimilated in the Southern Ocean State Estimate. We provide processed data sets that are publicly available and used by scientists within multiple disciplines (physics, biology, chemistry). We provide high-quality in situ data for other researchers interested in variability in upper ocean temperature,currents, acoustic backscatter, carbon, and atmospheric CO2, and for testing ocean and coupled climate models.  We provide the official request and clearance reporting for all underway measurements on the LMG. Without such requests and reporting, underway data for scientific use cannot be collected within foreign exclusive economic zones (EEZs), which include half of Drake Passage.  The XBT software and probe launcher developed for the project has been widely used by the global Volunteer Observing Ship program. The ADCP software developed for the project is currently in use by the US oceanographic fleet.  Publications from the award include 5 peer-reviewed journal articles and 17 conference presentations.  The award contributed to education through support and training of 2 graduate students and 1 postdoctoral scholar.       Last Modified: 10/01/2020       Submitted by: Teresa K Chereskin]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
