<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>International Travel to the Gender Summits for US Women Faculty and Researchers in STEM</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>06/15/2015</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2016</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>110185.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>132186</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>11060000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>EHR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>HRD</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Human Resource Development</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Claudia Rankins</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The project at the American Association for the Advancement of Science builds on the successful outcomes of the Mentoring Women in International Research Collaborations (MWIRC) in STEM initiative.  Women faculty in science, technology, enginnering and mathematics (STEM) fields at Historically Black Colleges and Universities (HBCUs) and other Minority Serving Institutions (MSIs) are supported to create and sustain new research networks at the international level, thus enabling them to learn about developing and establishing critical research collaborations. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Twelve women faculty will travel to one of the three upcoming Gender Summits, to be held in South Korea and Germany in 2015 and in Mexico in 2016.  Attendance at the summits and follow-up activities will allow faculty to expand their networks, perspectives, and collaborations in the STEM disciplines which will enrich their research capacity and that of their institutions.  The participants will be able to benefit from an already existing gender-concerned community. This project will create a strong synergy and engagement from a variety of entities and partners, will help STEM faculty better understand international research priorities, resources for developing international research collaborations, and guidelines for U.S. STEM researchers traveling and conducting research abroad. The project has co-funding support from the Global Venture Fund in the Office of International Science and Engineering.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/12/2015</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>03/04/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.076</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1543108</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Shirley</FirstName>
<LastName>Malcom</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>M</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Shirley M Malcom</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>smalcom@aaas.org</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2023266668</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000428075</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/12/2015</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Yolanda</FirstName>
<LastName>Comedy</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Yolanda Comedy</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>ycomedy@aaas.org</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2023266780</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000618392</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/12/2015</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>American Association for the Advancement of Science</Name>
<CityName>Washington</CityName>
<ZipCode>200053928</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2023266400</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1200 NEW YORK AVENUE, N.W.</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>District of Columbia</StateName>
<StateCode>DC</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>00</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>DC00</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>077795672</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>AMERICAN ASSOCIATION FOR THE ADVANCEMENT OF SCIENCE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>077795672</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[American Association For Advancement Science]]></Name>
<CityName>Washington</CityName>
<StateCode>DC</StateCode>
<ZipCode>200053928</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[1200 New York Avenue, NW]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>District of Columbia</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>00</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>DC00</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>016Y</Code>
<Text>ADVANCE</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1594</Code>
<Text>Hist Black Colleges and Univ</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7298</Code>
<Text>International Research Collab</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>5922</Code>
<Text>MEXICO</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>5924</Code>
<Text>TAIWAN</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>5936</Code>
<Text>GERMANY (F.R.G.)</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>5942</Code>
<Text>KOREA</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7556</Code>
<Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7568</Code>
<Text>ADVANCE-PAID</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9178</Code>
<Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0115</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0116</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0415</Code>
<Name>NSF Education &amp; Human Resource</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040106</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0416</Code>
<Name>NSF Education &amp; Human Resource</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040106</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2015~110185</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2016~22001</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The American Association for the Advancement of Science (AAAS)&nbsp;developed and implemented a project with support from the National Science Foundation (NSF)&nbsp;<em>&ldquo;International Travel to Gender Summits&rdquo;</em>. This project offered ideal opportunities for women at minority serving institutions (MSIs) and Historically Black Colleges (HBCUs) to meet potential research partners.&nbsp; These potential collaborators were either seeked out at local universities, research organizations by the awardees ahead of their travel to the Gender Summit.&nbsp; Potential research partners were also sought at the Gender Summit, whose attendees included researchers who are interested in making gender equality a norm in science and embedding gender as a primary dimension of research and innovation quality.</p> <p>The project responded to the critical need for providing U.S. female  faculty and students in STEM, at MSI's, with  international research opportunities because of the fact that most  problems we are trying to solve as a nation have global implications and  lessons-learned.</p> <p>Over the course of the grant, the project provided 12 U.S. women researchers in STEM to participate in three Gender Summits: GS-6, Seoul, South Korea, Aug. '15; GS-7. Berlin, Germany, Nov. 2015 and GS-8 Mexico City, Mexico, April 2016. Immediate outcomes noted following the participation in the Gender Summits:</p> <p>1. Increased interest in and plans to continue engaging in international collaborations in the future;</p> <p>2. augmented ability to identify, initiate, and develop international contacts and collaborations;</p> <p>3. greatly enhanced understanding of national and international issues facing women in STEM</p> <p>Intellectual Merit</p> <p>The project aimed to build upon the outcomes and insights learned during the evaluation of the MWIRC project. The interviewed MWIRC awardees stressed the need for opportunities to sustain international research collaborations, as well as support to international travel as a mean to establish networks and research exchanges.</p> <p>Through this award, the American Association for the Advancement of Science (AAAS), targeted a new group of qualified participants affiliated with HBCUs and MSIs, who needed an opportunity for networking and gaining knowledge about the possibilities and processes of international research collaborations. In fact, the grant allowed STEM female Faculty to create and sustain new networks, thus enabling them to learn about planning and developing critical international research collaborations. Given their affiliations with HBCUs and MSIs, the knowledge gained during their activities can be transferred directly to their institutions and research environments, and will engage their universities and partners, in supporting international research collaborations for other Faculty and students.</p> <p>Broader Impacts</p> <p>The entire project was aimed at broadening the participation of STEM female researchers that could engage several potential stakeholders, including their institutions, for supporting international research collaborations. Following their participation at the Gender Summit, their impacts would become more visible as they will stimulate and grow interest and engagement by fellow researchers, students, universities, research partners.</p> <p>The Gender Summits have already acquired a solid audience (2000 participants and 300 speakers), that is concerned with the issues of gender equity in STEM and research. The participants were able to benefit from an already existing &ldquo;gender-concerned community&rdquo; to draw interest of relevant stakeholders, in support to International Research Collaborations.&nbsp; Thishas created a strong synergy and engagement from a variety of entities and partners, to tackle more broadly and actively the pressing questions and provide additional support and opportunities for international research collaborations by STEM female researchers.</p> <p>An external evaluation indicated the direct positive impact of international research collaborations on the&nbsp;career advancement of female faculty and their students. It also highlighted the important impact of international research on student&nbsp;commitment to STEM research careers. Further it provided an opportunity to create sustainable international collaborations between institutions in United States and other countries in order to advance research outcomes.</p> <p>The project allowed all participants and collaborators to substantially&nbsp;increase their understanding of the benefits of doing international work. Feedback from the evaluation indicated that the grantees accomplished the following:</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <ol> <li>plans to co-author publications in U.S. and foreign journals</li> <li>additional funding to participate in international panels as collaborators</li> <li>enrichment and creation of curricula and seminars based on collaboration outcomes</li> <li>development of exchange programs</li> <li>creating sustainable collaborations</li> <li>building the skill-set of grantees through providing the opportunity and assistance to solve the unexpected consequences of collaborating internationally</li> <li>creating better faculty</li> <li>providing students with research collaboration opportunities</li> </ol> <p>Overall, the project enhanced international networks for female STEM faculty in a variety of STEM disciplines. It allowed for multidisciplinary exchanges between countries in order to find better solutions to problems and understand the global reach of many of the research challenges. The project allowed researchers from different cultures to better understand each other and become more innovative in their own work. &nbsp;It also enhanced faculty teaching and mentoring abilities to provide students with both research opportunities and career advice. This project overall helped &nbsp;faculty create better research in order to provide solutions to the challenges that face society.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 12/08/2016<br>      Modified by: Yolanda&nbsp;Comedy</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The American Association for the Advancement of Science (AAAS) developed and implemented a project with support from the National Science Foundation (NSF) "International Travel to Gender Summits". This project offered ideal opportunities for women at minority serving institutions (MSIs) and Historically Black Colleges (HBCUs) to meet potential research partners.  These potential collaborators were either seeked out at local universities, research organizations by the awardees ahead of their travel to the Gender Summit.  Potential research partners were also sought at the Gender Summit, whose attendees included researchers who are interested in making gender equality a norm in science and embedding gender as a primary dimension of research and innovation quality.  The project responded to the critical need for providing U.S. female  faculty and students in STEM, at MSI's, with  international research opportunities because of the fact that most  problems we are trying to solve as a nation have global implications and  lessons-learned.  Over the course of the grant, the project provided 12 U.S. women researchers in STEM to participate in three Gender Summits: GS-6, Seoul, South Korea, Aug. '15; GS-7. Berlin, Germany, Nov. 2015 and GS-8 Mexico City, Mexico, April 2016. Immediate outcomes noted following the participation in the Gender Summits:  1. Increased interest in and plans to continue engaging in international collaborations in the future;  2. augmented ability to identify, initiate, and develop international contacts and collaborations;  3. greatly enhanced understanding of national and international issues facing women in STEM  Intellectual Merit  The project aimed to build upon the outcomes and insights learned during the evaluation of the MWIRC project. The interviewed MWIRC awardees stressed the need for opportunities to sustain international research collaborations, as well as support to international travel as a mean to establish networks and research exchanges.  Through this award, the American Association for the Advancement of Science (AAAS), targeted a new group of qualified participants affiliated with HBCUs and MSIs, who needed an opportunity for networking and gaining knowledge about the possibilities and processes of international research collaborations. In fact, the grant allowed STEM female Faculty to create and sustain new networks, thus enabling them to learn about planning and developing critical international research collaborations. Given their affiliations with HBCUs and MSIs, the knowledge gained during their activities can be transferred directly to their institutions and research environments, and will engage their universities and partners, in supporting international research collaborations for other Faculty and students.  Broader Impacts  The entire project was aimed at broadening the participation of STEM female researchers that could engage several potential stakeholders, including their institutions, for supporting international research collaborations. Following their participation at the Gender Summit, their impacts would become more visible as they will stimulate and grow interest and engagement by fellow researchers, students, universities, research partners.  The Gender Summits have already acquired a solid audience (2000 participants and 300 speakers), that is concerned with the issues of gender equity in STEM and research. The participants were able to benefit from an already existing "gender-concerned community" to draw interest of relevant stakeholders, in support to International Research Collaborations.  Thishas created a strong synergy and engagement from a variety of entities and partners, to tackle more broadly and actively the pressing questions and provide additional support and opportunities for international research collaborations by STEM female researchers.  An external evaluation indicated the direct positive impact of international research collaborations on the career advancement of female faculty and their students. It also highlighted the important impact of international research on student commitment to STEM research careers. Further it provided an opportunity to create sustainable international collaborations between institutions in United States and other countries in order to advance research outcomes.  The project allowed all participants and collaborators to substantially increase their understanding of the benefits of doing international work. Feedback from the evaluation indicated that the grantees accomplished the following:     plans to co-author publications in U.S. and foreign journals additional funding to participate in international panels as collaborators enrichment and creation of curricula and seminars based on collaboration outcomes development of exchange programs creating sustainable collaborations building the skill-set of grantees through providing the opportunity and assistance to solve the unexpected consequences of collaborating internationally creating better faculty providing students with research collaboration opportunities   Overall, the project enhanced international networks for female STEM faculty in a variety of STEM disciplines. It allowed for multidisciplinary exchanges between countries in order to find better solutions to problems and understand the global reach of many of the research challenges. The project allowed researchers from different cultures to better understand each other and become more innovative in their own work.  It also enhanced faculty teaching and mentoring abilities to provide students with both research opportunities and career advice. This project overall helped  faculty create better research in order to provide solutions to the challenges that face society.       Last Modified: 12/08/2016       Submitted by: Yolanda Comedy]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
