<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>CS10K: Training Arkansas Computing Teachers (TACT)</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>10/01/2015</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>09/30/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>991664.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>991664</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>05050000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>CSE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CNS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Computer and Network Systems</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Allyson Kennedy</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>aykenned@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032928905</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The University of Arkansas (UA) proposes a multifaceted program - called TACT (Training Arkansas Computing Teachers)- to certify high school teachers to teach computer science (CS).  Arkansas has recently become the first state in the nation to require that all public high schools offer CS courses. This has left schools scrambling to comply as prior to June 2015, only 6.4% of them offered CS. In addition, the state had no process in place to certify CS teachers. While online CS courses will help most Arkansas high schools comply with the new legislation, the literature suggests significant benefits to face-to-face instruction. To meet the immediate and ongoing demand for well-trained and CS certified high school teachers, and to better prepare Arkansas' high school students for computer-related professions, the UA College of Engineering (COE) propose a multifaceted program that will develop both in-service and pre-service high school teachers to be certified to teach Computer Science (CS) Principles.  The in-service component will rapidly address the immediate demand and the pre-service component will prepare an ongoing pipeline of CS teachers. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The project will use a dual track approach. Pre-service professional development will be developed through the Arkansas UTeach program using curricula developed at the University of Texas at Austin's UTeach Institute in Austin, TX. In-service teachers will be prepared through UA's Advanced Placement Summer Institute (APSI). In both cases the curricula will be based on the Thriving in Our Digital World CS Principles course developed at the University of Texas, Austin.  The effort will be evaluated, assessing both teacher and students outcomes, and comparing student outcomes against their peers who worked online. These findings will contribute to the CS education literature, helping to clarify how effective solely online CS instruction in high school populations relative to face-to-face instruction. In addition, TACT experiences refining the components of this multifaceted teacher preparation program will help inform additional scaling efforts specifically based on Thriving in Our Digital World, and it will help inform policymakers more generally considering statewide mandates on CS education.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/24/2015</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/24/2015</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.070</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1543195</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>William</FirstName>
<LastName>Oliver</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>F</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME>III</PI_SUFX_NAME>
<PI_FULL_NAME>William F Oliver</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>woliver@uark.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>4795756571</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000421765</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/24/2015</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Dale</FirstName>
<LastName>Thompson</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>R</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Dale R Thompson</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>drt@uark.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>4795755090</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000357131</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/24/2015</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Bryan</FirstName>
<LastName>Hill</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Bryan Hill</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>bwhill@uark.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>4795757236</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000082472</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/24/2015</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Eric</FirstName>
<LastName>Specking</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>A</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Eric A Specking</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>especki@uark.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>4795753845</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000695066</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/24/2015</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Arkansas</Name>
<CityName>Fayetteville</CityName>
<ZipCode>727013124</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>4795753845</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1125 W. Maple Street</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[316 Administration Building]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Arkansas</StateName>
<StateCode>AR</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>AR03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>191429745</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF ARKANSAS SYSTEM</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>055600001</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Arkansas]]></Name>
<CityName>Fayetteville</CityName>
<StateCode>AR</StateCode>
<ZipCode>727011201</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[227 N Harmon Ave #504]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Arkansas</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>AR03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>005Y</Code>
<Text>STEM + Computing (STEM+C) Part</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EPSCoR Co-Funding</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7578</Code>
<Text>CS 10K</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0115</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2015~991664</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The Training Arkansas Computing Teachers, TACT, project at the Department of Computer Science and Computer Engineering in the University of Arkansas trained a total of 64 in-service teachers and two pre-service teachers from 2016 until 2018. These 66 teachers represent 48 different schools from the Northwest, Central, Southwest, and Northeast areas of the State of Arkansas. In addition, TACT developed curriculum for a week-long workshop designed to cover computer science topics that are typically covered in licensure exams for high school teachers. The in-service part of the program was the largest part of the project. Two of the pre-service teachers from the UAteach program attended the professional development, graduated from the UAteach program, and are now teaching computer science. TACT was a major factor in providing access to excellent computer science instruction for students across the state. This exposure to computer science should enhance secondary students' interest in computing careers, helping to close the computing labor gap experienced both in Arkansas and across the country.<br /><br />TACT influenced the addition of courses based on the Computer Science Principles framework to be added to an Arkansas list of courses that satisfy Act 187, a law based on the Governor?s mandate that all high schools in the State of Arkansas must offer a computer science course. In addition, the Arkansas Department of Education recognizes the CS Principles course as an endorsed AP course. Students taught by TACT-trained teachers scored higher on the AP CS Principles exam than other students taught by other Arkansas teachers. TACT-trained teachers scored higher on the licensure exam used for computer science in the State of Arkansas and had a higher pass rate.<br /><br />The course materials developed by the project are available at the project website, https://tact.uark.edu. The project website documents the accomplished objectives of the project, provides a map of the general locations of TACT-trained teachers, links to the Arkansas CS initiatives website, and provides computer science educational materials arranged based upon the seven big ideas from the AP Computer Science Principles course framework.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 11/05/2019<br>      Modified by: Dale&nbsp;R&nbsp;Thompson</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The Training Arkansas Computing Teachers, TACT, project at the Department of Computer Science and Computer Engineering in the University of Arkansas trained a total of 64 in-service teachers and two pre-service teachers from 2016 until 2018. These 66 teachers represent 48 different schools from the Northwest, Central, Southwest, and Northeast areas of the State of Arkansas. In addition, TACT developed curriculum for a week-long workshop designed to cover computer science topics that are typically covered in licensure exams for high school teachers. The in-service part of the program was the largest part of the project. Two of the pre-service teachers from the UAteach program attended the professional development, graduated from the UAteach program, and are now teaching computer science. TACT was a major factor in providing access to excellent computer science instruction for students across the state. This exposure to computer science should enhance secondary students' interest in computing careers, helping to close the computing labor gap experienced both in Arkansas and across the country.  TACT influenced the addition of courses based on the Computer Science Principles framework to be added to an Arkansas list of courses that satisfy Act 187, a law based on the Governor?s mandate that all high schools in the State of Arkansas must offer a computer science course. In addition, the Arkansas Department of Education recognizes the CS Principles course as an endorsed AP course. Students taught by TACT-trained teachers scored higher on the AP CS Principles exam than other students taught by other Arkansas teachers. TACT-trained teachers scored higher on the licensure exam used for computer science in the State of Arkansas and had a higher pass rate.  The course materials developed by the project are available at the project website, https://tact.uark.edu. The project website documents the accomplished objectives of the project, provides a map of the general locations of TACT-trained teachers, links to the Arkansas CS initiatives website, and provides computer science educational materials arranged based upon the seven big ideas from the AP Computer Science Principles course framework.       Last Modified: 11/05/2019       Submitted by: Dale R Thompson]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
