<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>CAREER: Mind your P's and O's--Theoretical Studies on Phosphoryl Transfer Enzymes: Transition-State Analogues and Catalysis</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2014</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>342876.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>290672</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03090000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CHE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Chemistry</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Catalina Achim</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>cachim@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922048</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Professor Charles E. Webster of the University of Memphis is supported by the Chemistry of Life Processes (CLP) Program in the Division of Chemistry to develop computational methods to address mechanistic and structural details of phosphoryl transfer enzymes and transition state analogues. The project focuses on quantum mechanics/molecular mechanics computational analysis of several potential species on the enzyme's reaction pathway.  Collaborations with experimentalists that are working with the target enzymes allow comparison with experimentally derived data to produce a cyclic synergism between experiments and theory. This research project has potential benefits for applications in biocatalysis, including the rational design of inhibitors for phosphoryl transfer enzymes, which play an important role in metabolic and other biological reactions. The broader impacts involve an educational program to train all 66 high school chemistry teachers in Memphis through a series of workshops, and to assist with curriculum development and refinement. This outreach effort benefits several thousand students, including many minorities.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/18/2015</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>09/23/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1543490</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Charles Edwin</FirstName>
<LastName>Webster</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Charles Edwin Webster</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>ewebster@chemistry.msstate.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6623257224</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000264085</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/18/2015</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Mississippi State University</Name>
<CityName>MISSISSIPPI STATE</CityName>
<ZipCode>397629662</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6623257404</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>PO Box 6156</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Mississippi</StateName>
<StateCode>MS</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MS03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>075461814</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>MISSISSIPPI STATE UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>075461814</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Mississippi State University]]></Name>
<CityName>Starkville</CityName>
<StateCode>MS</StateCode>
<ZipCode>397626156</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[133 Etheredge Hall]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Mississippi</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MS03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>6883</Code>
<Text>Chemistry of Life Processes</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EPSCoR Co-Funding</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>0000</Code>
<Text>UNASSIGNED</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1045</Code>
<Text>CAREER-Faculty Erly Career Dev</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1187</Code>
<Text>PECASE- eligible</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>OTHR</Code>
<Text>OTHER RESEARCH OR EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0110</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0111</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2010~115670</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2011~175000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The transfer of a phosphoryl group (PO<sub>3</sub><sup>&ndash;</sup>) from one molecule to another plays a crucial role in hundreds of metabolic reactions in the bacterial, plant, and animal kingdoms including those involved in metabolism, gene regulation, and signal transduction. Due to a high kinetic barrier, enzymatic catalysis of phosphoryl transfer reactions is essential. Understanding the mechanistic and structural details of phosphoryl transfer enzymes and their transition state analogues has potential benefits for applications in the rational design of inhibitors which, due to the ubiquitous nature of these enzymes, make them attractive targets human therapeutics as well as next generation insecticides and herbicides.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>The broad goal of this project was to develop computational methods focused on quantum mechanical analysis of potential intermediate and transition state species on the reaction pathway catalyzed by enzymes. Metal containing fluoro species such as BeF<sub>3</sub><sup>-</sup>, MgF<sub>3</sub><sup>-</sup>, AlF<sub>4</sub><sup>-</sup>, and AlF<sub>3</sub><sup>0</sup> have been used as transition-state and ground-state analogues for a variety of phosphoryl transfer enzymes. Collaborations with experimentalists have allowed for the comparison of experimentally derived high-resolution X-ray crystal structural data and <sup>19</sup>F nuclear magnetic resonance (NMR) data to quantum mechanical computational analysis leading to new insights in the mechanism of enzyme-catalyzed phosphoryl transfer at the atomic and molecular levels. During this project, we have developed computational strategies for successfully studying these systems.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&beta;-phosphoglucomutase (&beta;-PGM) is a highly studied enzyme that plays a key role in the regulation of energy metabolism by facilitating the interconversion of glucose-1-phosphate (G1P) and glucose-6-phosphate (G6P). By combining high-resolution X-ray crystal structures and <sup>19</sup>F NMR data it was demonstrated that complexes of the ground state analog, trifluoroberyllate (BeF<sub>3</sub><sup>-</sup>) complexes, with &beta;-PGM and glucose phosphate deploy a high degree of stabilization of near attack conformers (NACs), intermediate species that serve as precursors to transition states of reactions. These experimental observations marry well with quantum mechanical predictions of the chemical barrier in this enzyme.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>Human histidine triad nucleotide binding protein 1 (hHint1), a homodimeric protein, is considered as a protein kinase C inhibitor and haploinsufficient tumour suppressor. hHint1 is an enzyme efficient in the hydrolysis of phosphoramidate. In particular, hHint1 has been utilized to activate nucleotide prodrugs (proTides). Understanding the mechanism of hHint1 will aid in the future design of proTides. Density functional theory (DFT) computations on an active-site model were performed to investigate the hydrolysis mechanism of a phosphoramidate substrate. The overall proposed mechanism included the key involvement of the histidine triad as a proton shuttle.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>Cyclic AMP-dependent protein kinase (cAPK) catalyzes the transfer of the &gamma; phosphoryl group of ATP to the serine hydroxyl group of a peptide chain. For cAPK, we present computational studies of the mechanism of phosphoryl transfer and the structure and <sup>19</sup>F NMR spectra of various ground- (BeF<sub>3</sub><sup>&minus;</sup>) and transitionstate (MgF<sub>3</sub><sup>&minus;</sup>, AlF<sub>4</sub><sup>&minus;</sup>, and AlF<sub>3</sub><sup>0</sup>) analogues. With native substrate, the phosphoryl transfer proceeds through a five-coordinate phosphorene transition state, i.e., there is not a five-coordinate phosphorene intermediate. Comparisons of simulated and experimental <sup>19</sup>F NMR spectra show cAPK prefers a monoanionic analogue (MgF<sub>3</sub><sup>&minus;</sup> or AlF<sub>4</sub><sup>&minus;</sup>) over a neutral analogue (AlF<sub>3</sub>), supporting the charge balance hypothesis which states that the active site of an enzyme favors a constant charge.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>Tyrosyl-DNA phosphodiesterase I (Tdp1) is a DNA repair enzyme that catalyzes the hydrolysis of the phosphodiester bond between the tyrosine residue of topoisomerase I and the 3&rsquo;-phosphoate of DNA. Atomic level details of the mechanism of Tdp1 are proposed using a fully quantum mechanical, geometrically constrained model. Transition states and intermediates along the reaction coordinate suggest an associative phosphoryl transfer mechanism with five-coordinate phosphorene intermediates. Similar to both theoretical and experimental results for phopholipase D, the proposed mechanism for hTdp1 also includes the thermodynamically favorable possibility of a four-coordinate phosphohistidine "dead-end" product.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 11/18/2017<br>      Modified by: Charles Edwin&nbsp;Webster</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The transfer of a phosphoryl group (PO3&ndash;) from one molecule to another plays a crucial role in hundreds of metabolic reactions in the bacterial, plant, and animal kingdoms including those involved in metabolism, gene regulation, and signal transduction. Due to a high kinetic barrier, enzymatic catalysis of phosphoryl transfer reactions is essential. Understanding the mechanistic and structural details of phosphoryl transfer enzymes and their transition state analogues has potential benefits for applications in the rational design of inhibitors which, due to the ubiquitous nature of these enzymes, make them attractive targets human therapeutics as well as next generation insecticides and herbicides.     The broad goal of this project was to develop computational methods focused on quantum mechanical analysis of potential intermediate and transition state species on the reaction pathway catalyzed by enzymes. Metal containing fluoro species such as BeF3-, MgF3-, AlF4-, and AlF30 have been used as transition-state and ground-state analogues for a variety of phosphoryl transfer enzymes. Collaborations with experimentalists have allowed for the comparison of experimentally derived high-resolution X-ray crystal structural data and 19F nuclear magnetic resonance (NMR) data to quantum mechanical computational analysis leading to new insights in the mechanism of enzyme-catalyzed phosphoryl transfer at the atomic and molecular levels. During this project, we have developed computational strategies for successfully studying these systems.     &beta;-phosphoglucomutase (&beta;-PGM) is a highly studied enzyme that plays a key role in the regulation of energy metabolism by facilitating the interconversion of glucose-1-phosphate (G1P) and glucose-6-phosphate (G6P). By combining high-resolution X-ray crystal structures and 19F NMR data it was demonstrated that complexes of the ground state analog, trifluoroberyllate (BeF3-) complexes, with &beta;-PGM and glucose phosphate deploy a high degree of stabilization of near attack conformers (NACs), intermediate species that serve as precursors to transition states of reactions. These experimental observations marry well with quantum mechanical predictions of the chemical barrier in this enzyme.     Human histidine triad nucleotide binding protein 1 (hHint1), a homodimeric protein, is considered as a protein kinase C inhibitor and haploinsufficient tumour suppressor. hHint1 is an enzyme efficient in the hydrolysis of phosphoramidate. In particular, hHint1 has been utilized to activate nucleotide prodrugs (proTides). Understanding the mechanism of hHint1 will aid in the future design of proTides. Density functional theory (DFT) computations on an active-site model were performed to investigate the hydrolysis mechanism of a phosphoramidate substrate. The overall proposed mechanism included the key involvement of the histidine triad as a proton shuttle.     Cyclic AMP-dependent protein kinase (cAPK) catalyzes the transfer of the &gamma; phosphoryl group of ATP to the serine hydroxyl group of a peptide chain. For cAPK, we present computational studies of the mechanism of phosphoryl transfer and the structure and 19F NMR spectra of various ground- (BeF3&minus;) and transitionstate (MgF3&minus;, AlF4&minus;, and AlF30) analogues. With native substrate, the phosphoryl transfer proceeds through a five-coordinate phosphorene transition state, i.e., there is not a five-coordinate phosphorene intermediate. Comparisons of simulated and experimental 19F NMR spectra show cAPK prefers a monoanionic analogue (MgF3&minus; or AlF4&minus;) over a neutral analogue (AlF3), supporting the charge balance hypothesis which states that the active site of an enzyme favors a constant charge.     Tyrosyl-DNA phosphodiesterase I (Tdp1) is a DNA repair enzyme that catalyzes the hydrolysis of the phosphodiester bond between the tyrosine residue of topoisomerase I and the 3?-phosphoate of DNA. Atomic level details of the mechanism of Tdp1 are proposed using a fully quantum mechanical, geometrically constrained model. Transition states and intermediates along the reaction coordinate suggest an associative phosphoryl transfer mechanism with five-coordinate phosphorene intermediates. Similar to both theoretical and experimental results for phopholipase D, the proposed mechanism for hTdp1 also includes the thermodynamically favorable possibility of a four-coordinate phosphohistidine "dead-end" product.       Last Modified: 11/18/2017       Submitted by: Charles Edwin Webster]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
