<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Grace Hopper Celebration of Women in Computing (GHC) Scholarship Program</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2015</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2016</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>157860.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>157860</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>05050000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>CSE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CNS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Computer and Network Systems</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Kamau Bobb</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This award provides funding for approximately one hundred undergraduate and graduate students to attend the 2015 Grace Hopper Celebration (GHC), an annual conference focused on the needs of technical women in computing. It brings research and career interests of women in computing to the forefront in order to encourage and support women to pursue, remain, and advance in computing.  NSF scholarship support allows students who could not otherwise attend to participate and to become part of the larger community of computing professionals that is cultivated at the conference.  &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The intellectual merit of this project lies in the access to the many technical presentations and researchers at GHC. The conference exposes students to a wide range of leading edge scientists, researchers, and visionaries from industry and academia who serve as role models and mentors. It showcases participants' technical success and provides a forum for exploration of the frontiers of the discipline and a dialogue between students and leading practitioners and researchers while offering opportunities for professional development.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Past GHC conferences have been shown to break down the barriers to women pursuing careers in computing.  The broader impacts of students participating in this conference include: increased student intention to remain in computing and pursue higher studies; broadening of attendees' knowledge of technical fields; breaking the feelings of isolation common among women in computing disciplines; and instilling confidence to pursue computing careers.  This travel scholarship support provides a unique opportunity to directly affect the careers of future computer scientists and meet the challenge of broadening participation in computing.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/30/2015</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/12/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.070</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1543771</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Telle</FirstName>
<LastName>Whitney</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Telle Whitney</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>tellew@anitaborg.org</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6502364758</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000425798</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/30/2015</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Barbara</FirstName>
<LastName>Gee</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Barbara Gee</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>barbarag@anitaborg.org</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>4153074789</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000618809</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/30/2015</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Roshni</FirstName>
<LastName>Kasad</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Roshni Kasad</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>roshnik@anitaborg.org</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5103568354</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000676062</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/30/2015</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Anita Borg Institute for Women and Technology</Name>
<CityName>Belmont</CityName>
<ZipCode>940024154</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6503527500</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1301 Shoreway Road</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[Ste 425]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>14</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CA14</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>096342444</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>ANITA BORG INSTITUTE FOR WOMEN AND TECHNOLOGY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Anita Borg Institute for Women and Technology]]></Name>
<CityName>Palo Alto</CityName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>943041126</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[1501 Page Mill Road]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>18</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CA18</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1714</Code>
<Text>Special Projects - CNS</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0115</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2015~157860</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>This award provided funding for 113 undergraduate and graduate students to attend the 2015 Grace Hopper Celebration (GHC), an annual conference focused on the needs of technical women in computing. GHC brings research and career interests of women in computing to the forefront in order to encourage and support women to pursue, remain, and advance in computing. The GHC Scholarship program allows students to become part of the larger community of academic, industry, and research computing professionals that is cultivated at the conference.&nbsp; <br /> <br /> The intellectual merit of this project lies in the access to the many technical presentations and researchers at GHC. The conference exposes students to the leading scientists, researchers, and visionaries from industry and academia who serve as role models and mentors. It provides a forum for students to explore the range and depth of the field of computing, opportunities for dialogue between students and leading practitioners and researchers, and access to professional development.<br /> <br /> Evaluation results show that the GHC Scholar program helps break down the barriers to women pursuing careers in computing. Eighty-four percent of scholars reported that their commitment to a career in technology has increased due to participating in GHC.&nbsp; GHC afforded many opportunities to interact with female role models in computing, as 91% of scholars reported being able to get advice from other technical women via the conference.&nbsp; Seventy-nine percent of scholars learned technical or &ldquo;soft&rdquo; skills that will help them in advancing their careers.&nbsp; Fifty-nine percent of scholars gained more knowledge on academic programs in computing through participating in GHC.&nbsp; Finally, 92% of scholars report that participation in the scholarship program made them feel they are now part of a community of technical women, breaking the feelings of isolation common among women in computing disciplines. This travel scholarship provided a unique opportunity to directly affect the careers of future computer scientists and to meet the challenge of broadening participation in computing.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 06/08/2016<br>      Modified by: Roshni&nbsp;Kasad</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ This award provided funding for 113 undergraduate and graduate students to attend the 2015 Grace Hopper Celebration (GHC), an annual conference focused on the needs of technical women in computing. GHC brings research and career interests of women in computing to the forefront in order to encourage and support women to pursue, remain, and advance in computing. The GHC Scholarship program allows students to become part of the larger community of academic, industry, and research computing professionals that is cultivated at the conference.      The intellectual merit of this project lies in the access to the many technical presentations and researchers at GHC. The conference exposes students to the leading scientists, researchers, and visionaries from industry and academia who serve as role models and mentors. It provides a forum for students to explore the range and depth of the field of computing, opportunities for dialogue between students and leading practitioners and researchers, and access to professional development.    Evaluation results show that the GHC Scholar program helps break down the barriers to women pursuing careers in computing. Eighty-four percent of scholars reported that their commitment to a career in technology has increased due to participating in GHC.  GHC afforded many opportunities to interact with female role models in computing, as 91% of scholars reported being able to get advice from other technical women via the conference.  Seventy-nine percent of scholars learned technical or "soft" skills that will help them in advancing their careers.  Fifty-nine percent of scholars gained more knowledge on academic programs in computing through participating in GHC.  Finally, 92% of scholars report that participation in the scholarship program made them feel they are now part of a community of technical women, breaking the feelings of isolation common among women in computing disciplines. This travel scholarship provided a unique opportunity to directly affect the careers of future computer scientists and to meet the challenge of broadening participation in computing.          Last Modified: 06/08/2016       Submitted by: Roshni Kasad]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
