<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>MATH: EAGER: Collaborative Research: Implementing a Peer-Mentorship Model for Mathematics Graduate Student Instructors</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/15/2015</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>166690.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>166690</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>11040200</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>EHR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DUE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Undergraduate Education</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Talitha Washington</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Undergraduate mathematics teachers of the future are the mathematics graduate students of today. A significant number of these graduate students will have careers which will involve a combination of teaching, advising, and research, and/or will be working in business, government, or industry. In fact, evidence suggests that a significant percentage of mathematics Ph.D. students will spend a substantial portion of their professional careers teaching undergraduate students at community colleges, 4-year colleges, and universities. In turn, many teach foundational undergraduate mathematics courses while they are still graduate students. Although these graduate student instructors (GSIs) are positioned to have a significant impact on the quality of instruction and student learning for these courses, they often lack the background and specific training to teach effectively. Moreover, faculty members' teaching practices and beliefs usually are related to the strategies, skills, practices, and knowledge they learned and applied while they were GSIs. This project will affect GSIs' current teaching practices as well as their practices and beliefs as potential future faculty members. Specifically, investigators from Bowling Green State University and the University of South Carolina will collaborate to create and investigate a graduate student mentorship model that will: (1) allow experienced GSIs to mentor protégé GSIs; (2) create an environment where GSIs have a support structure to enhance their teaching and understanding of student learning; and (3) help experienced and novice mathematics GSIs to increase their pedagogical knowledge base, stimulate their appreciation of mathematics education, and improve their teaching skills as future faculty. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;A main goal of the project is to provide professional development (PD) for GSIs that includes training experienced GSIs for mentoring protégé GSIs about teaching and student learning. After participating in PD workshops, mentor GSIs will observe, advise, and collaborate with protégé GSIs to improve foundational mathematics course pedagogy by providing protégés with resources and specific feedback to incorporate more student-centered teaching techniques. The GSI mentor model will allow for a sustainable, pay-it-forward design, bridging education and mathematics departments. Transformative knowledge on how to educate GSIs about effective teaching strategies (e.g. student-centered instruction) will be discovered, researched, analyzed, and disseminated. In particular, investigations will be conducted and results will be disseminated using the Carnegie Foundation methodology of Network Improvement Community Research. Using this methodology, other educational institutions will be able to pinpoint specific techniques for addressing their GSIs' needs without necessarily replicating the entire design. This study will lead to guidelines to develop the next generation of mathematicians proficient at, and appreciative of, mathematics education, and better prepared to enter the workforce, especially in positions where undergraduate teaching is an important component of their responsibilities.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/22/2015</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/22/2015</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.076</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1544342</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Kimberly</FirstName>
<LastName>Rogers</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>C</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Kimberly C Rogers</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>kcroger@bgsu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>4193727450</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000694890</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/22/2015</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Bowling Green State University</Name>
<CityName>Bowling Green</CityName>
<ZipCode>434030230</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>4193722481</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>302 Hayes Hall</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Ohio</StateName>
<StateCode>OH</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>OH05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>617407325</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>BOWLING GREEN STATE UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>041349010</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Bowling Green State University]]></Name>
<CityName>Bowling Green</CityName>
<StateCode>OH</StateCode>
<ZipCode>434030230</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[106 University Hall]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Ohio</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>OH05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1536</Code>
<Text>S-STEM-Schlr Sci Tech Eng&amp;Math</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1998</Code>
<Text>IUSE</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>005Z</Code>
<Text>Math Success in First 2 Years of College</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7916</Code>
<Text>EAGER</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8209</Code>
<Text>Improv Undergrad STEM Ed(IUSE)</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9178</Code>
<Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0415</Code>
<Name>NSF Education &amp; Human Resource</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040106</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>13XX</Code>
<Name>H-1B FUND, EHR, NSF</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>045176</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2015~166690</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><span id="docs-internal-guid-0d39c441-6db0-fd35-2e7a-288435904716"> </span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>This project developed and implemented a peer mentorship process in which specially-trained, experienced graduate student instructors (mentor GSIs) provided mentoring and support to novice graduate student instructors (prot&eacute;g&eacute;s). The intention was to address the needs of prot&eacute;g&eacute;s as they taught undergraduate mathematics courses for the first time as the instructors of record. This Graduate Student Instructor Mentorship Model (GSIMM) helped prot&eacute;g&eacute;s develop their skills as teachers, with positive impacts on their undergraduate students. Each mentor provided three to five prot&eacute;g&eacute;s with training, feedback, and peer support around the classes they were teaching. Specifically, every semester, each mentor conducted (and recorded) three observations for each of their prot&eacute;g&eacute;s and facilitated systematic small-group meetings with all their prot&eacute;g&eacute;s. Observation data indicated that, within their first semester of participation, prot&eacute;g&eacute;s had begun to adopt teaching strategies that were likely to improve their teaching effectiveness. Results indicated that after one year, prot&eacute;g&eacute;s at both universities demonstrated the ability to implement, reflect upon, and improve teaching methods.</span><span><br class="kix-line-break" /><br class="kix-line-break" /></span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>INTELLECTUAL MERIT</span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>The intellectual merit of the project is separated into the three critical stakeholders: mentor GSIs, prot&eacute;g&eacute; GSIs, and undergraduate students of GSIs. The mentor professional development and semester agenda for mentoring was viewed as quite successful, based on interview responses and surveys of mentors. Mentors found great value in the way they were prepared to facilitate constructive conversations with prot&eacute;g&eacute;s and small-group discussions around teaching by focusing on discourse during the professional development. Mentors also learned how to deconstruct the concepts of &ldquo;successful&rdquo; teaching and the critical role instructors play when educating undergraduate mathematics students.</span></p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p dir="ltr"><span>After just one year, prot&eacute;g&eacute;s&rsquo; teaching effectiveness was comparable to other, more experienced GSIs. Results indicated that the small-group meetings helped prot&eacute;g&eacute;s feel comfortable and become proficient in discussing teaching issues with others. Specifically, prot&eacute;g&eacute;s demonstrated they were able to apply curricular problem-solving methods collaboratively to help each other grow as instructors with specific attention to student learning; thereby, generating a desired and sustainable community of practice amongst GSIs. Mentors were also able to identify potentially dangerous teaching situations in prot&eacute;g&eacute;s&rsquo; classrooms early in the semester, which either led to explicit adjustments in prot&eacute;g&eacute;s' teaching strategies and course structures or modifications in teaching assignments. In this way, the GSIMM helped curb the number of undergraduate students&rsquo; formal complaints because faculty members in the departments at each institution proactively addressed potentially problematic teaching instances.</span></p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p dir="ltr"><span>Undergraduate students in mathematics courses at the two institutions were generally positive about their courses and instructors. Undergraduates had a tendency to see these courses as a necessity rather than covering material of intrinsic interest. Analysis of course grades and outcomes suggests that, in their first semester teaching at one of the institutions, prot&eacute;g&eacute;s were at least as effective (or more) than experienced GSIs. At the other institution, this effect of the mentoring program had prot&eacute;g&eacute;s as effective by their second semester.</span></p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p dir="ltr"><span>BROADER IMPACT </span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>This project has successfully completed its major goals and objectives. Eleven experienced GSIs participated in professional development seminars and nine went on to serve as mentors at the two institutions. The cohort of prot&eacute;g&eacute;s who participated in the GSIMM demonstrated that the peer-mentoring process provided them with the information, support, and assistance needed to quickly become successful instructors of students in undergraduate mathematics courses. In many cases, classes taught by prot&eacute;g&eacute;s had outcomes that were comparable to those of more experienced GSIs in grade distributions, formative assessment modeling, and use of student-centered instruction. </span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span><br class="kix-line-break" /></span><span>The evidence developed in this study indicates that the peer-mentoring program is very promising as a method of supporting prot&eacute;g&eacute;s and improving the course outcomes for undergraduates taught by prot&eacute;g&eacute;s. Critical products created and necessary for success of the GSIMM include: (1) GSI Observation Protocol (GSIOP) used when mentors observed prot&eacute;g&eacute;s&rsquo; classroom teaching, (2) mentor professional development seminar series for training mentors, and (3) a structured schedule for mentors to follow to successfully complete all observations, post-observation conversations, and small-group meetings. The longitudinal analysis of the GSIOP data from prot&eacute;g&eacute;s demonstrated progression in categorical scores through the full year of implementation at both universities. Specifically, analysis of these data indicates that prot&eacute;g&eacute;s made substantial progress using student-centered learning techniques through the academic year they were mentored. This result has broader implications to improve mathematics GSIs&rsquo; development as mathematics educators while completing their course work and preparation as future mathematicians. Thus, mentors&rsquo; and prot&eacute;g&eacute;s&rsquo; experiences in the peer-mentoring program helps bridge the fields of mathematics and mathematics education for those GSIs who choose careers in academia. Moreover, the pedagogical products, research results, and collaborative orchestration of implementation between the PI and Co-PI at these two universities opens new doors for the GSIMM to be viable, sustainable, and ideal for future dissemination to other STEM fields.</span></p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 10/30/2017<br>      Modified by: Kimberly&nbsp;Rogers</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Images (<span id="selectedPhoto0">1</span> of <span class="totalNumber"></span>)           </div> <div class="galControls" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1544342/1544342_10378867_1509395421801_CopyofConceptMapofBGSUVariablesforposter2017--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1544342/1544342_10378867_1509395421801_CopyofConceptMapofBGSUVariablesforposter2017--rgov-800width.jpg" title="BGSU Peer-Mentoring Program"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1544342/1544342_10378867_1509395421801_CopyofConceptMapofBGSUVariablesforposter2017--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="BGSU Peer-Mentoring Program"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Major Variables and Components of the Peer-Mentoring Program at Bowling Green State University from 2016-2017 Academic Year</div> <div class="imageCredit">Kimberly Cervello Rogers and Sean P. Yee</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Kimberly&nbsp;Rogers</div> <div class="imageTitle">BGSU Peer-Mentoring Program</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1544342/1544342_10378867_1509395489651_CopyofConceptMapofUSCVariablesforposter2017--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1544342/1544342_10378867_1509395489651_CopyofConceptMapofUSCVariablesforposter2017--rgov-800width.jpg" title="UofSC Peer-Mentoring Program"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1544342/1544342_10378867_1509395489651_CopyofConceptMapofUSCVariablesforposter2017--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="UofSC Peer-Mentoring Program"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Variables and Components of Peer-Mentoring Program at the University of South Carolina during 2016-2017 Academic Year</div> <div class="imageCredit">Kimberly Cervello Rogers and Sean P. Yee</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Kimberly&nbsp;Rogers</div> <div class="imageTitle">UofSC Peer-Mentoring Program</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[   This project developed and implemented a peer mentorship process in which specially-trained, experienced graduate student instructors (mentor GSIs) provided mentoring and support to novice graduate student instructors (prot&eacute;g&eacute;s). The intention was to address the needs of prot&eacute;g&eacute;s as they taught undergraduate mathematics courses for the first time as the instructors of record. This Graduate Student Instructor Mentorship Model (GSIMM) helped prot&eacute;g&eacute;s develop their skills as teachers, with positive impacts on their undergraduate students. Each mentor provided three to five prot&eacute;g&eacute;s with training, feedback, and peer support around the classes they were teaching. Specifically, every semester, each mentor conducted (and recorded) three observations for each of their prot&eacute;g&eacute;s and facilitated systematic small-group meetings with all their prot&eacute;g&eacute;s. Observation data indicated that, within their first semester of participation, prot&eacute;g&eacute;s had begun to adopt teaching strategies that were likely to improve their teaching effectiveness. Results indicated that after one year, prot&eacute;g&eacute;s at both universities demonstrated the ability to implement, reflect upon, and improve teaching methods. INTELLECTUAL MERIT The intellectual merit of the project is separated into the three critical stakeholders: mentor GSIs, prot&eacute;g&eacute; GSIs, and undergraduate students of GSIs. The mentor professional development and semester agenda for mentoring was viewed as quite successful, based on interview responses and surveys of mentors. Mentors found great value in the way they were prepared to facilitate constructive conversations with prot&eacute;g&eacute;s and small-group discussions around teaching by focusing on discourse during the professional development. Mentors also learned how to deconstruct the concepts of "successful" teaching and the critical role instructors play when educating undergraduate mathematics students.    After just one year, prot&eacute;g&eacute;s? teaching effectiveness was comparable to other, more experienced GSIs. Results indicated that the small-group meetings helped prot&eacute;g&eacute;s feel comfortable and become proficient in discussing teaching issues with others. Specifically, prot&eacute;g&eacute;s demonstrated they were able to apply curricular problem-solving methods collaboratively to help each other grow as instructors with specific attention to student learning; thereby, generating a desired and sustainable community of practice amongst GSIs. Mentors were also able to identify potentially dangerous teaching situations in prot&eacute;g&eacute;s? classrooms early in the semester, which either led to explicit adjustments in prot&eacute;g&eacute;s' teaching strategies and course structures or modifications in teaching assignments. In this way, the GSIMM helped curb the number of undergraduate students? formal complaints because faculty members in the departments at each institution proactively addressed potentially problematic teaching instances.    Undergraduate students in mathematics courses at the two institutions were generally positive about their courses and instructors. Undergraduates had a tendency to see these courses as a necessity rather than covering material of intrinsic interest. Analysis of course grades and outcomes suggests that, in their first semester teaching at one of the institutions, prot&eacute;g&eacute;s were at least as effective (or more) than experienced GSIs. At the other institution, this effect of the mentoring program had prot&eacute;g&eacute;s as effective by their second semester.    BROADER IMPACT  This project has successfully completed its major goals and objectives. Eleven experienced GSIs participated in professional development seminars and nine went on to serve as mentors at the two institutions. The cohort of prot&eacute;g&eacute;s who participated in the GSIMM demonstrated that the peer-mentoring process provided them with the information, support, and assistance needed to quickly become successful instructors of students in undergraduate mathematics courses. In many cases, classes taught by prot&eacute;g&eacute;s had outcomes that were comparable to those of more experienced GSIs in grade distributions, formative assessment modeling, and use of student-centered instruction.  The evidence developed in this study indicates that the peer-mentoring program is very promising as a method of supporting prot&eacute;g&eacute;s and improving the course outcomes for undergraduates taught by prot&eacute;g&eacute;s. Critical products created and necessary for success of the GSIMM include: (1) GSI Observation Protocol (GSIOP) used when mentors observed prot&eacute;g&eacute;s? classroom teaching, (2) mentor professional development seminar series for training mentors, and (3) a structured schedule for mentors to follow to successfully complete all observations, post-observation conversations, and small-group meetings. The longitudinal analysis of the GSIOP data from prot&eacute;g&eacute;s demonstrated progression in categorical scores through the full year of implementation at both universities. Specifically, analysis of these data indicates that prot&eacute;g&eacute;s made substantial progress using student-centered learning techniques through the academic year they were mentored. This result has broader implications to improve mathematics GSIs? development as mathematics educators while completing their course work and preparation as future mathematicians. Thus, mentors? and prot&eacute;g&eacute;s? experiences in the peer-mentoring program helps bridge the fields of mathematics and mathematics education for those GSIs who choose careers in academia. Moreover, the pedagogical products, research results, and collaborative orchestration of implementation between the PI and Co-PI at these two universities opens new doors for the GSIMM to be viable, sustainable, and ideal for future dissemination to other STEM fields.          Last Modified: 10/30/2017       Submitted by: Kimberly Rogers]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
