<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>CPS: Breakthrough: Collaborative Research: The Interweaving of Humans and Physical Systems: A Perspective from Power Systems</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>10/01/2015</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>09/30/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>250000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>250000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>05050000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>CSE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CNS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Computer and Network Systems</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>David Corman</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>dcorman@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032928754</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>As information technology has transformed physical systems such as the power grid, the interface between these systems and their human users has become both richer and much more complex. For example, from the perspective of an electricity consumer, a whole host of devices and technologies are transforming how they interact with the grid: demand response programs; electric vehicles; "smart" thermostats and appliances; etc. These novel technologies are also forcing us to rethink how the grid interacts with its users, because critical objectives such as stability and robustness require effective integration among the many diverse users in the grid. This project studies the complex interweaving of humans and physical systems. Traditionally, a separation principle has been used to isolate humans from physical systems. This principle requires users to have preferences that are well-defined, stable, and quickly discoverable. These assumptions are increasingly violated in practice: users' preferences are often not well-defined; unstable over time; and take time to discover. Our project articulates a new framework for interactions between physical systems and their users, where users' preferences must be repeatedly learned over time while the system continually operates with respect to imperfect preference information.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;We focus on the area of power systems. Our project has three main thrusts. First, user models are rethought to reflect the fact this new dynamic view of user preferences, where even the users are learning over time. The second thrust focuses on developing a new system model that learns about users, since we cannot understand users in a "single-shot"; rather, repeated interaction with the user is required. We then focus on the integration of these two new models. How do we control and operate a physical system, in the presence of the interacting "learning loops", while mediating between many competing users? We apply ideas from mean field games and optimal power flow to capture, analyze, and transform the interaction between the system and the ongoing preference discovery process. Our methods will yield guidance for market design in power systems where user preferences are constantly evolving. If successful, our project will usher in a fundamental change in interfacing physical systems and users. For example, in the power grid, our project directly impacts how utilities design demand response programs; how smart devices learn from users; and how the smart grid operates. In support of this goal, the PIs intend to develop avenues for knowledge transfer through interactions with industry. The PIs will also change their education programs to reflect a greater entanglement between physical systems and users.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>09/15/2015</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>09/15/2015</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.070</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1544160</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Baosen</FirstName>
<LastName>Zhang</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Baosen Zhang</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>zhangbao@u.washington.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2066163818</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000694676</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/15/2015</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Washington</Name>
<CityName>Seattle</CityName>
<ZipCode>981950001</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2065434043</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>4333 Brooklyn Ave NE</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Washington</StateName>
<StateCode>WA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>WA07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>605799469</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF WASHINGTON</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>042803536</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Washington]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>WA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>981952500</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Washington</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>WA07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7918</Code>
<Text>CPS-Cyber-Physical Systems</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7918</Code>
<Text>CYBER-PHYSICAL SYSTEMS (CPS)</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8234</Code>
<Text>CPS-Breakthrough</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0115</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2015~250000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><span>Cyberphysical systems are usually integrated with their human users and need to operate under uncertainties about these user's preferences and behaviors. For example,&nbsp; demand response is a program that promotes the interaction between the electrical grid operator and its consumers. It offers a broad range of potential benefits on system operation and expansion and on market efficiency but suffers from the fact that operators typically do not have much information about the users. It is therefore crucial to accurately estimate the effect of certain demand response signals, especially given that consumers' behavior is uncertain and noisy. </span></p> <p>In this project, we study how cyberphysical systems can be operated while learning their human users' behaviors, using the power system as the motivating case study. We first consider that demand response signals are binary and model the consumption behavior by a linear model. We compare several different linear estimators of demand response effect and propose an optimal demand response signal assignment strategy that improves the performance of the linear estimator in terms of optimal reduction in estimation variance. In a more realistic setting where demand response signals from the operator are continuous, i.e., price signals, we assume that the operator does not know the cost function of consumers and cannot have multiple rounds of information exchange with consumers. We formulate an optimization problem for the operator to minimize its operational cost considering time-varying demand response targets and responses of consumers. We develop a joint online learning and pricing algorithm and show that our online algorithm achieves logarithmic regret with respect to the operating horizon. Besides, as a future of urban power system development, the generation of electricity from renewables constitutes a large portion of the total generation in the power grid. The inherent uncertainty of renewables and their wide distribution in the network bring new challenges in planning and operation. We design a decentralized market to engage the participation of small scaled distributed renewable energy resources. It is known that most deterministic capacity games tend to result in very inefficient equilibria, even when there are a large number of similar players. In contrast, we show that due to the inherent uncertainty of renewable resources, the equilibria in our capacity game becomes efficient as the number of players grows and coincides with the centralized decision from the social planner's problem. In addition, we use reactive power compensation as demand response to alleviate the problem of fluctuated voltage resulted from introduction of renewables. We adopt a chance constrained approach that accounts for arbitrary correlations between renewable resources at each of the buses in the system. We show that the problem can be solved efficiently using historical samples via our proposed descent algorithm. We also show that this optimization problem is convex for a wide variety of probabilistic distributions. We use both synthetic generated and real-world energy data, as well as parterner with local utitlties, to validate the claims and the proposed algorithms.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 12/26/2018<br>      Modified by: Baosen&nbsp;Zhang</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Cyberphysical systems are usually integrated with their human users and need to operate under uncertainties about these user's preferences and behaviors. For example,  demand response is a program that promotes the interaction between the electrical grid operator and its consumers. It offers a broad range of potential benefits on system operation and expansion and on market efficiency but suffers from the fact that operators typically do not have much information about the users. It is therefore crucial to accurately estimate the effect of certain demand response signals, especially given that consumers' behavior is uncertain and noisy.   In this project, we study how cyberphysical systems can be operated while learning their human users' behaviors, using the power system as the motivating case study. We first consider that demand response signals are binary and model the consumption behavior by a linear model. We compare several different linear estimators of demand response effect and propose an optimal demand response signal assignment strategy that improves the performance of the linear estimator in terms of optimal reduction in estimation variance. In a more realistic setting where demand response signals from the operator are continuous, i.e., price signals, we assume that the operator does not know the cost function of consumers and cannot have multiple rounds of information exchange with consumers. We formulate an optimization problem for the operator to minimize its operational cost considering time-varying demand response targets and responses of consumers. We develop a joint online learning and pricing algorithm and show that our online algorithm achieves logarithmic regret with respect to the operating horizon. Besides, as a future of urban power system development, the generation of electricity from renewables constitutes a large portion of the total generation in the power grid. The inherent uncertainty of renewables and their wide distribution in the network bring new challenges in planning and operation. We design a decentralized market to engage the participation of small scaled distributed renewable energy resources. It is known that most deterministic capacity games tend to result in very inefficient equilibria, even when there are a large number of similar players. In contrast, we show that due to the inherent uncertainty of renewable resources, the equilibria in our capacity game becomes efficient as the number of players grows and coincides with the centralized decision from the social planner's problem. In addition, we use reactive power compensation as demand response to alleviate the problem of fluctuated voltage resulted from introduction of renewables. We adopt a chance constrained approach that accounts for arbitrary correlations between renewable resources at each of the buses in the system. We show that the problem can be solved efficiently using historical samples via our proposed descent algorithm. We also show that this optimization problem is convex for a wide variety of probabilistic distributions. We use both synthetic generated and real-world energy data, as well as parterner with local utitlties, to validate the claims and the proposed algorithms.       Last Modified: 12/26/2018       Submitted by: Baosen Zhang]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
