<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>CPS: Breakthrough: Collaborative Research: Securing Smart Grid by Understanding</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2015</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>245000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>245000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>05050000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>CSE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CNS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Computer and Network Systems</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Ralph Wachter</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>rwachter@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032928950</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Smart grid includes two interdependent infrastructures: power transmission and distribution network, and the supporting telecommunications network. Complex interactions among these infrastructures lead to new pathways for attack and failure propagation that are currently not well understood. This innovative project takes a holistic multilevel approach to understand and characterize the interdependencies between these two infrastructures, and devise mechanisms to enhance their robustness. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Specifically, the project has four goals.  The first goal is to understand the standardized smart grid communications protocols in depth and examine mechanisms to harden them. This is essential since the current protocols are notoriously easy to attack. The second goal is to ensure robustness in state estimation techniques since they form the basis for much of the analysis of smart grid. In particular, the project shall exploit a steganography-based approach to detect bad data and compromised devices. The third goal is to explore trust-based attack detection strategies that combine the secure state estimation with power flow models and software attestation to detect and isolate compromised components. The final goal is to study reconfiguration strategies that combine light-weight prediction models, stochastic decision processes, intentional islanding, and game theory techniques to mitigate the spreading of failures and the loss of load. A unique aspect of smart grid security that will be studied in this project is the critical importance of timeliness, and thus a tradeoff between effectiveness of the mechanisms and the overhead introduced. The project is expected to provide practical techniques for making the smart grid more robust against failures and attacks, and enable it to recover from large scale failures with less loss of capacity. The project will also train students in the multidisciplinary areas of power systems operation and design, networking protocols, and cyber-physical security.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>09/11/2015</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>09/11/2015</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.070</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1544904</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Krishna</FirstName>
<LastName>Kant</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Krishna Kant</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>kkant@temple.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2152049654</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000656409</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/11/2015</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Avinash</FirstName>
<LastName>Srinivasan</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Avinash Srinivasan</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>avinash@temple.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2152045774</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000677190</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/11/2015</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Temple University</Name>
<CityName>Philadelphia</CityName>
<ZipCode>191226003</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2157077547</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1801 N. Broad Street</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Pennsylvania</StateName>
<StateCode>PA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>PA02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>057123192</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>TEMPLE UNIVERSITY-OF THE COMMONWEALTH SYSTEM OF HIGHER EDUCATION</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>057123192</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Temple University]]></Name>
<CityName>Philadelphia</CityName>
<StateCode>PA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>191226018</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[1925 N. 12th Street]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Pennsylvania</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>PA02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7918</Code>
<Text>CPS-Cyber-Physical Systems</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7918</Code>
<Text>CYBER-PHYSICAL SYSTEMS (CPS)</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8234</Code>
<Text>CPS-Breakthrough</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8235</Code>
<Text>CPS-Synergy</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0115</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2015~245000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Smart electric grid adds sophisticated monitoring, communications and decision-making capability to the electric grid in order to manage it well and quickly and proactively detect problems and take control actions. Some of the events relating to the safe operation of the grid (e.g., short-circuit or voltage surge) need to be communicated to the control center immediately and thus have very strict transfer latency requirements. Since these message cannot tolerate the additional delay added by normal security mechanisms, they are invariably transmitted without any security. &nbsp;This provides an idea opportunity to hackers to disrupt the operation of the grid. In this project, we developed two different light-weight mechanisms to enable protection of these messages. The first mechanism relies on permutation of the message bits and the second on the generation of one-time key between messages. Both mechanisms have much wider applicability and can be used in many other contexts including those that require low latency and those that are severely energy constrained.</p> <p>The comprehensive monitoring of the grid (e.g., voltage, phase, frequency at electrical &ldquo;bus&rdquo;) is used by the control center to estimate the &ldquo;state&rdquo; of the grid by minimizing the impact of real measurement errors and discrepancies that arise since not all measurements can be done at the same time instant. Along the way, the procedure determines which data points are bad (&ldquo;bad data detection&rdquo;) and excludes those data points. An accurate state estimation is crucial since many applications such as those determining the health of the grid or those that control power flows depend on the output of the state estimation. If an adversary can somehow change the input data used by the state estimator such that the altered data is not thrown out as &ldquo;bad data&rdquo;, the state estimator can mislead the applications that depend on it. We show that it is possible to do such perturbation without precisely knowing the parameters of the grid. We also show that by repeated undetected attacks like this, one can perturb the state of the grid sufficiently to cause serious harm. We also show a mechanism to detect such attacks. This work points to the need for comprehensive mechanism for detecting such silent perturbations in cyberphysical systems in general including the smart grid.</p> <p>We expect our mechanisms to be applicable in a number of other scenarios of control of large scale physical systems that involve monitoring, communication, and estimation of the &ldquo;state&rdquo; of the system.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 11/17/2019<br>      Modified by: Krishna&nbsp;Kant</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Smart electric grid adds sophisticated monitoring, communications and decision-making capability to the electric grid in order to manage it well and quickly and proactively detect problems and take control actions. Some of the events relating to the safe operation of the grid (e.g., short-circuit or voltage surge) need to be communicated to the control center immediately and thus have very strict transfer latency requirements. Since these message cannot tolerate the additional delay added by normal security mechanisms, they are invariably transmitted without any security.  This provides an idea opportunity to hackers to disrupt the operation of the grid. In this project, we developed two different light-weight mechanisms to enable protection of these messages. The first mechanism relies on permutation of the message bits and the second on the generation of one-time key between messages. Both mechanisms have much wider applicability and can be used in many other contexts including those that require low latency and those that are severely energy constrained.  The comprehensive monitoring of the grid (e.g., voltage, phase, frequency at electrical "bus") is used by the control center to estimate the "state" of the grid by minimizing the impact of real measurement errors and discrepancies that arise since not all measurements can be done at the same time instant. Along the way, the procedure determines which data points are bad ("bad data detection") and excludes those data points. An accurate state estimation is crucial since many applications such as those determining the health of the grid or those that control power flows depend on the output of the state estimation. If an adversary can somehow change the input data used by the state estimator such that the altered data is not thrown out as "bad data", the state estimator can mislead the applications that depend on it. We show that it is possible to do such perturbation without precisely knowing the parameters of the grid. We also show that by repeated undetected attacks like this, one can perturb the state of the grid sufficiently to cause serious harm. We also show a mechanism to detect such attacks. This work points to the need for comprehensive mechanism for detecting such silent perturbations in cyberphysical systems in general including the smart grid.  We expect our mechanisms to be applicable in a number of other scenarios of control of large scale physical systems that involve monitoring, communication, and estimation of the "state" of the system.          Last Modified: 11/17/2019       Submitted by: Krishna Kant]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
