<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>BRAIN EAGER: Danionella translucida: A New Fish Model for Systems Neuroscience</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/15/2015</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>300000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>300000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>08090200</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>BIO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>IOS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Integrative Organismal Systems</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Edda Thiels</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>ethiels@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032928167</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Neuroscientists face the difficult task of describing the coordinated activities of many single neurons across the brain, and explaining how the cells' firing patterns create behavior. Achieving this goal at the immense scale of the human brain is the ultimate goal of the BRAIN Initiative.  To accomplish this complex goal, it first is necessary to establish appropriate experimental and analytical techniques, as well as a better understanding of basic circuit principles, in simpler systems.  The current project expands the opportunities for gaining insight by developing a new laboratory model organism.  The candidate species is the fish Danionella translucida.  This species is very small (~1 cm body length as an adult) and optically transparent, two characteristics that make the species exquisitely well-suited to molecular and optical techniques for recording from and manipulating large sets of neurons, and enabling researchers to use the most powerful experimental methods to study how each neuron in an adult vertebrate contributes to complex behaviors.  The project will establish this potentially revolutionary model species and demonstrate proof-of-principle by mapping the neural circuits that underlie odor-mediated social alarm behavior in adult Danionella.  The societal benefits of this work include unprecedented insight into the mechanisms of complex behaviors, some of which are affected in human neurological diseases.  Additionally, the integration of multiple levels of analysis, from molecular biology to social behavior, render this project the basis of a particularly powerful neuroscience teaching tool, to be implemented through existing undergraduate and high school research programs that include outreach to students from minority groups. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project draws on Danionella's close phylogenetic similarity to the zebrafish, Danio rerio, to apply existing experimental tools to a new animal model. The first aim is to establish breeding, transgenesis, and gene editing techniques that will allow propagation of these fish in the lab, introduction of fluorescent reporters and optogenetic actuators, and targeted manipulation of specific, endogenous genes. The second aim is to apply multiphoton and light-sheet imaging to adult Danionella, and evaluate the results against benchmarks established in larval zebrafish. The third aim is to develop assays for a pheromone-mediated social alarm behavior, and record pheromone-evoked activity from every neuron in the brain. These experiments collectively demonstrate the experimental power of this new model species and create tools that are essential for its adoption by the research community. The insights will be disseminated through, among others, existing and new websites supporting exchange among scientists.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/10/2015</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/10/2015</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.074</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1545885</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Adam</FirstName>
<LastName>Douglass</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Adam Douglass</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>adam.douglass@neuro.utah.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>8015816903</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000689848</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/10/2015</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Utah</Name>
<CityName>SALT LAKE CITY</CityName>
<ZipCode>841128930</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>8015816903</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>75 S 2000 E</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[Second Floor]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Utah</StateName>
<StateCode>UT</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>UT02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>009095365</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF UTAH, THE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>009095365</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Utah]]></Name>
<CityName>Salt Lake City</CityName>
<StateCode>UT</StateCode>
<ZipCode>841323401</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[20 North 1900 East, 311A]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Utah</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>UT02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7275</Code>
<Text>Cross-BIO Activities</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7714</Code>
<Text>Modulation</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1228</Code>
<Text>MINORITY INVOLVEMENT -- BIO</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7916</Code>
<Text>EAGER</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8091</Code>
<Text>BRAIN Initiative Res Support</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9178</Code>
<Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9179</Code>
<Text>GRADUATE INVOLVEMENT</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0115</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2015~300000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Over the last few decades, the zebrafish <em>Danio rerio</em> has become particularly popular as a model organism in neuroscience research.&nbsp; During early (larval) stages of development, the zebrafish brain comprises just 100,000 neurons and is small and transparent enough that researchers can visualize every cell in a living, unmanipulated animal, a degree of experimental access that is unattainable in mouse, rat, and primate species.&nbsp; Despite this simplicity, the fish brain possesses many of the essential structural and functional features of those more complex vertebrates and has yielded important general insights into the neural mechanisms of behavior.</p> <p>While powerful, zebrafish work is also quite limited in its reliance on young animals, which are behaviorally immature and lack the ability to perform most forms of learning and memory and social behavior. Conversely, while adult fish are agile learners and exhibit a number of interesting social behaviors, such as courtship, fighting, and shoaling, their brains are much larger and are enclosed within an opaque skull and skin that make it impossible to use essential microscopy techniques to observe and manipulate neural activity.&nbsp;</p> <p>An ideal model organism would retain the small size and optical transparency of the larval zebrafish while exhibiting the mature behavioral repertoire of the adults.&nbsp; This project investigated whether another fish species, called <em>Danionella translucida</em>, might meet those criteria.&nbsp; <em>Danionella </em>are unique in remaining quite small - just 1cm in length - and optically transparent throughout life.&nbsp; They are also close evolutionary relatives of zebrafish, giving hope that existing molecular, anatomical, and behavioral techniques might be easily applied to this new species.&nbsp;</p> <p>The specific goals of this work were to (1) Establish methods for breeding, performing transgenesis, and manipulating the genome of <em>Danionella </em>in the lab; (2) Use microscopy to image neural structure and activity in living, adult fish; (3) Investigate the neural basis of social behavior in this species.&nbsp; By doing so, we hoped to create a new experimental model that would enable us and other researchers to ask previously impossible questions about neural circuits and behavior.</p> <p>The project has succeeded in most of its aims.&nbsp; First, we showed that <em>Danionella</em>, which had previously not been studied in a laboratory context, are readily amenable to standard zebrafish husbandry conditions and procedures.&nbsp; Colonies of adult fish breed daily, producing large quantities of fertilized embryos (up to 30 per clutch) that we are able to collect prior to the first cell division for microinjection of DNA and RNA.&nbsp; Fish injected with DNA constructs originally developed for zebrafish work express the transgenes with their intended neuronal specificities, allowing us to label a number of distinct cell populations. These fish can then be imaged as adults using two-photon microscopy, which we have showed enables optical access to even the deepest regions of the brain without surgical manipulation.&nbsp; Our efforts to establish quantitative assays for behaviors that are difficult or impossible to study in larval zebrafish were similarly successful.&nbsp; We demonstrated that adult <em>Danionella </em>readily perform pheromone-driven avoidance behaviors, aversive conditioning, shoaling, and socially-reinforced learning.&nbsp; For the latter, we observed that social interactions with a conspecific reinforced preferences for spatial and arbitrary visual cues that the fish exhibited for up to an hour after conditioning.</p> <p>Together, these data demonstrate the potential power of <em>Danionella </em>as a neuroscience model and create a foundation for my lab's follow-up investigations into the relationship between oxytocin-producing neurons and social behavior.&nbsp; To date we have already sent fish to approximately a dozen labs around the world, a clear indication of the general interest in this new system and of our committment to dissemination.&nbsp; The project has also enabled a number of training activities by supporting one graduate student, three undergrads, and two technicians, all of whom contributed to a manuscript describing our results.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 04/03/2019<br>      Modified by: Adam&nbsp;Douglass</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Over the last few decades, the zebrafish Danio rerio has become particularly popular as a model organism in neuroscience research.  During early (larval) stages of development, the zebrafish brain comprises just 100,000 neurons and is small and transparent enough that researchers can visualize every cell in a living, unmanipulated animal, a degree of experimental access that is unattainable in mouse, rat, and primate species.  Despite this simplicity, the fish brain possesses many of the essential structural and functional features of those more complex vertebrates and has yielded important general insights into the neural mechanisms of behavior.  While powerful, zebrafish work is also quite limited in its reliance on young animals, which are behaviorally immature and lack the ability to perform most forms of learning and memory and social behavior. Conversely, while adult fish are agile learners and exhibit a number of interesting social behaviors, such as courtship, fighting, and shoaling, their brains are much larger and are enclosed within an opaque skull and skin that make it impossible to use essential microscopy techniques to observe and manipulate neural activity.   An ideal model organism would retain the small size and optical transparency of the larval zebrafish while exhibiting the mature behavioral repertoire of the adults.  This project investigated whether another fish species, called Danionella translucida, might meet those criteria.  Danionella are unique in remaining quite small - just 1cm in length - and optically transparent throughout life.  They are also close evolutionary relatives of zebrafish, giving hope that existing molecular, anatomical, and behavioral techniques might be easily applied to this new species.   The specific goals of this work were to (1) Establish methods for breeding, performing transgenesis, and manipulating the genome of Danionella in the lab; (2) Use microscopy to image neural structure and activity in living, adult fish; (3) Investigate the neural basis of social behavior in this species.  By doing so, we hoped to create a new experimental model that would enable us and other researchers to ask previously impossible questions about neural circuits and behavior.  The project has succeeded in most of its aims.  First, we showed that Danionella, which had previously not been studied in a laboratory context, are readily amenable to standard zebrafish husbandry conditions and procedures.  Colonies of adult fish breed daily, producing large quantities of fertilized embryos (up to 30 per clutch) that we are able to collect prior to the first cell division for microinjection of DNA and RNA.  Fish injected with DNA constructs originally developed for zebrafish work express the transgenes with their intended neuronal specificities, allowing us to label a number of distinct cell populations. These fish can then be imaged as adults using two-photon microscopy, which we have showed enables optical access to even the deepest regions of the brain without surgical manipulation.  Our efforts to establish quantitative assays for behaviors that are difficult or impossible to study in larval zebrafish were similarly successful.  We demonstrated that adult Danionella readily perform pheromone-driven avoidance behaviors, aversive conditioning, shoaling, and socially-reinforced learning.  For the latter, we observed that social interactions with a conspecific reinforced preferences for spatial and arbitrary visual cues that the fish exhibited for up to an hour after conditioning.  Together, these data demonstrate the potential power of Danionella as a neuroscience model and create a foundation for my lab's follow-up investigations into the relationship between oxytocin-producing neurons and social behavior.  To date we have already sent fish to approximately a dozen labs around the world, a clear indication of the general interest in this new system and of our committment to dissemination.  The project has also enabled a number of training activities by supporting one graduate student, three undergrads, and two technicians, all of whom contributed to a manuscript describing our results.       Last Modified: 04/03/2019       Submitted by: Adam Douglass]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
