<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>RAPID: Effects of Enhanced Circulation on Vertical Mixing and Algal Blooms In Freshwater Reservoirs</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>06/01/2015</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>48874.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>58487</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07020000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CBET</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Chem, Bioeng, Env, &amp; Transp Sys</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Karl Rockne</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>krockne@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032925356</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>1545624&lt;br/&gt;Obenour&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Jordan Lake, like many similar reservoirs around the world, is impaired due to excessive algal growth and harmful algal blooms are becoming more prevalent. The lake provides drinking water to 300,000 people, and it serves as a recreational attraction for many more. The use of enhanced circulation has been proposed as a means of suppressing the formation of harmful algal blooms in freshwater and coastal waterbodies. This study represents a rare opportunity to directly investigate how large-scale enhanced circulation affects mixing and algal dynamics (i.e. growth) in a large waterbody.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;At present, characterization of artificial mixing and its effect on phytoplankton community structure has been limited to whole-lake mixing (i.e. destratification), which may be impractical for larger waterbodies. The proposed research represents the first comprehensive characterization of how enhanced surface-layer circulation affects vertical diffusion rates and HABs formation potential. The project takes advantage of a uniquely large deployment of surface-layer circulators, to answer scientific and engineering questions at multiple scales. Overall, the project will help provide critical insight into the potential role of geoengineering as a tool for the abatement of HABs. For this research project, the principle investigators will perform a series of field activities to determine how these circulators are affecting physical and biological conditions within the lake. Activities will be conducted in different arms of the lake, representing treatment (circulators present) and control (circulators absent) conditions. Physical measurements will include vertical profiles of temperature micro-structure to infer vertical diffusivity, near-surface current velocities to determine extent of circulation, and wind velocities. Biological measurements will include vertical profiles of chlorophyll (total algae) and phycocyanin (indicating blue-green, cyanobacteria algae). Monitoring will be coordinated with the North Carolina Department of Water Resources, who will be measuring a series of conventional water quality parameters that will also be used in this study. Using the data from these field activities, we will determine how the synergistic impacts of wind speed and artificial circulation affect vertical diffusion within the surface layer, which is expected to be a primary control on algal dynamics. We will further test hypotheses related to how mixing (natural and artificial) affects the abundance and vertical distribution of total chlorophyll and cyanobacteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/02/2015</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>04/10/2017</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1545624</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Tarek</FirstName>
<LastName>Aziz</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>N</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Tarek N Aziz</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>tnaziz@ncsu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>9195152444</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000589426</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/02/2015</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Daniel</FirstName>
<LastName>Obenour</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Daniel Obenour</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>drobenour@ncsu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>9195157702</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000696042</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/02/2015</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>North Carolina State University</Name>
<CityName>Raleigh</CityName>
<ZipCode>276957514</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>9195152444</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>2601 Wolf Village Way</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[Admin. III, STE 240]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>North Carolina</StateName>
<StateCode>NC</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NC04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>042092122</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>NORTH CAROLINA STATE UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>142363428</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[North Carolina State University]]></Name>
<CityName>Raleigh</CityName>
<StateCode>NC</StateCode>
<ZipCode>276957908</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[2701 Sullivan Dr.]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>North Carolina</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NC02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1440</Code>
<Text>EnvE-Environmental Engineering</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>021E</Code>
<Text>Water management</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7914</Code>
<Text>RAPID</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7974</Code>
<Text>GRAD RESEARCH SUPPLEMENT</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0115</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0117</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2015~48874</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2017~9613</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Physical mixing processes have a strong influence on the chemical and biological condition of lakes and reservoirs.&nbsp; Thus, artificial mixing through enhanced water column circulation is often employed by water resources managers to improve water quality.&nbsp; While the benefits of vertical mixing for improving some water quality characteristics, such as increasing dissolved oxygen concentrations, are relatively well understood, the utility of mixing to influence phytoplankton (i.e., algal) dynamics remains unclear, especially for shallow eutrophic waterbodies.&nbsp; In this study, we investigate the efficacy of solar-powered circulators for enhancing vertical mixing rates and reducing algal blooms in Jordan Lake, a major water supply reservoir in North Carolina (NC, USA).&nbsp; These circulators were installed over large areas of the reservoir as part of a multi-year pilot project conducted by the state of NC.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>In this project, we characterized temporal variability in mixing and phytoplankton dynamics in two segments of Jordan Lake with and without artificial circulators. A multi-year field campaign was conducted to assess how the artificial circulators influenced vertical diffusion and water column thermal structure, relative to background conditions.&nbsp; In addition, phytoplankton and other water quality measurements were collected at different times and locations with and without circulators present.&nbsp; A hydrodynamic model, calibrated to field data using a novel optimization approach, was created to simulate vertical diffusion over time.&nbsp; Simulated diffusion, along with other factors thought to influence phytoplankton growth, were then related to observed in-lake phytoplankton metrics (chlorophyll and cyanobacteria dominance) using hierarchical regression modeling.&nbsp; In general, field measurements and hydrodynamic modeling indicate that the artificial (solar-powered) circulators had minimal impact on mixing conditions within Jordan Lake.&nbsp; At the same time, increased natural mixing (due to meteorological drivers) was significantly associated with lower cyanobacteria concentration within the hierarchical multiple linear regression models.&nbsp; Furthermore, coupling the hydrodynamic model with a phytoplankton tracer model indicated that intensive (natural or artificial) mixing can substantially reduce cyanobacteria light exposure and thus growth.&nbsp; Overall, the study provides new insights into the role of artificial mixing for controlling harmful algal blooms, particularly in shallow turbid waterbodies.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>The monitoring and modeling approaches developed in this research are readily transferrable to other waterbodies. Furthermore, our results can help inform lake and reservoir management, particularly for similar waterbodies throughout the southeast United States.&nbsp; Results have been presented at multiple state, national, and international conferences on lake and reservoir management, water resources management, and freshwater science.&nbsp; This project has supported the dissertation research of one PhD student who plans to continue this research in the future.&nbsp; In addition, the project has supported one undergraduate who continued this research as a master&rsquo;s student and will graduate this year.&nbsp; The research has been of particular interest to the NC management community, and additional research has been funded by the NC Urban Water Consortium and Water Resources Research Institute.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 09/24/2018<br>      Modified by: Daniel&nbsp;Obenour</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Image         </div> <div class="galControls onePhoto" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation onePhoto" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1545624/1545624_10366870_1537806506997_IMG_1758--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1545624/1545624_10366870_1537806506997_IMG_1758--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Temperature microstructure profiling"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1545624/1545624_10366870_1537806506997_IMG_1758--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Temperature microstructure profiling"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Temperature microstructure profiling to obtain vertical diffusion estimates on Jordan Lake, NC</div> <div class="imageCredit">Daniel Obenour</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Daniel&nbsp;Obenour</div> <div class="imageTitle">Temperature microstructure profiling</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Physical mixing processes have a strong influence on the chemical and biological condition of lakes and reservoirs.  Thus, artificial mixing through enhanced water column circulation is often employed by water resources managers to improve water quality.  While the benefits of vertical mixing for improving some water quality characteristics, such as increasing dissolved oxygen concentrations, are relatively well understood, the utility of mixing to influence phytoplankton (i.e., algal) dynamics remains unclear, especially for shallow eutrophic waterbodies.  In this study, we investigate the efficacy of solar-powered circulators for enhancing vertical mixing rates and reducing algal blooms in Jordan Lake, a major water supply reservoir in North Carolina (NC, USA).  These circulators were installed over large areas of the reservoir as part of a multi-year pilot project conducted by the state of NC.     In this project, we characterized temporal variability in mixing and phytoplankton dynamics in two segments of Jordan Lake with and without artificial circulators. A multi-year field campaign was conducted to assess how the artificial circulators influenced vertical diffusion and water column thermal structure, relative to background conditions.  In addition, phytoplankton and other water quality measurements were collected at different times and locations with and without circulators present.  A hydrodynamic model, calibrated to field data using a novel optimization approach, was created to simulate vertical diffusion over time.  Simulated diffusion, along with other factors thought to influence phytoplankton growth, were then related to observed in-lake phytoplankton metrics (chlorophyll and cyanobacteria dominance) using hierarchical regression modeling.  In general, field measurements and hydrodynamic modeling indicate that the artificial (solar-powered) circulators had minimal impact on mixing conditions within Jordan Lake.  At the same time, increased natural mixing (due to meteorological drivers) was significantly associated with lower cyanobacteria concentration within the hierarchical multiple linear regression models.  Furthermore, coupling the hydrodynamic model with a phytoplankton tracer model indicated that intensive (natural or artificial) mixing can substantially reduce cyanobacteria light exposure and thus growth.  Overall, the study provides new insights into the role of artificial mixing for controlling harmful algal blooms, particularly in shallow turbid waterbodies.     The monitoring and modeling approaches developed in this research are readily transferrable to other waterbodies. Furthermore, our results can help inform lake and reservoir management, particularly for similar waterbodies throughout the southeast United States.  Results have been presented at multiple state, national, and international conferences on lake and reservoir management, water resources management, and freshwater science.  This project has supported the dissertation research of one PhD student who plans to continue this research in the future.  In addition, the project has supported one undergraduate who continued this research as a master?s student and will graduate this year.  The research has been of particular interest to the NC management community, and additional research has been funded by the NC Urban Water Consortium and Water Resources Research Institute.          Last Modified: 09/24/2018       Submitted by: Daniel Obenour]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
