<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Collaborative Research: Rational Design of Anticancer Drug Combinations using Dynamic Multidimensional Theory</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>06/15/2016</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>791580.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>791580</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03010000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>PHY</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Physics</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Krastan Blagoev</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>kblagoev@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924666</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This award is part of the NSF effort to promote significant advances in the fundamental understanding of cancer biology made possible through multidisciplinary research that involves experts in theoretical physics, applied mathematics, and computer science.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Achieving durable control of metastatic solid tumors will require high-order targeted therapeutic combinations, because single-agent therapeutics eventually become thwarted by the development of tumor drug resistance. However, design of combinatorial regimens cannot be done by empirical trial and error in the clinical setting. The goal of the project is to blend a systems biology network-based theoretical framework with an integrated experimental and analytical program in order to address the combinatorial regimen challenge in oncology. Based on areas of exemplary clinical need, investigator expertise, and the availability of patient-derived tumor tissue, the project will focus on BRAF-mutant melanoma and PIK3CA-mutant, estrogen receptor positive (ER+) breast cancer as initial tumor types in which to pilot the approach. In addition the project will offer interdisciplinary training and research experience to postdoctoral and clinical fellows, graduate students, and indirectly to all members of the groups who participate. Professional development of all trainees will be enhanced by yearly meetings of the whole project team which will include tutorials on modeling and experimental methodologies. A symposium on the quantitative science of cancer will be organized at the Dana Farber Cancer Institute during the third year of this project. Team members are also committed to broadening the participation of women and under-represented minorities in STEM fields by pro-active recruitment and mentoring.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The project will integrate dynamic modeling of signal transduction pathways relevant to cell proliferation and apoptosis, genomic and evolutionary analyses of tumor cells, and systematic cell death and therapeutic resistance studies. The dynamic models will be informed, tested, and iterated using experimental approaches applied to relevant cancer model systems. The experiments leverage emerging technologies such as pooled genome-wide open reading frame screens, dynamic BH3 profiling of cancer cells' closeness to the apoptotic threshold, whole exome sequencing and single cell RNA-seq analysis. The models will recapitulate steady state signaling network activation, acute adaptive effects of treatment (e.g., feedback dysregulation) and the range of drug-resistant states that may emerge following longer-term drug exposure. Tumor cell heterogeneity will be represented by the implementation of different initial configurations or state overrides of network components. Using newly developed systems control methodologies, the models will be used to prioritize drug combinations and dosing/scheduling principles for in vitro and in vivo testing. The final result will be a theoretical and experimentally validated approach that can be generalized across many other cancer types. This project develops a new framework to address cancer as a deregulated complex dynamical system and it will lead to an improved understanding of adaptive and acquired drug resistance mechanisms. The project will make a significant contribution toward a major goal of cancer precision medicine, namely the identification of optimal high-order combinations for individual cancer patients. The project will also establish new connections between evolutionary theory and dynamical systems theory. The theoretical and methodological advances will be applicable or adaptable to other cancers and diseases in general, leading to potentially transformative impacts on human health. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This proposal is cofunded by the Physics of Living Systems Program in the Physics Division and the Systems and Synthetic Biology Program in the Molecular and Cellular Biosciences Division.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/09/2016</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/19/2018</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1545839</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Levi</FirstName>
<LastName>Garraway</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Levi Garraway</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>Levi_Garraway@dfci.harvard.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6176323940</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000695130</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/09/2016</StartDate>
<EndDate>11/08/2016</EndDate>
<RoleCode>Former Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Anthony</FirstName>
<LastName>Letai</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Anthony Letai</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>anthony_letai@dfci.harvard.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6176322348</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000696485</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>03/21/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Anthony</FirstName>
<LastName>Letai</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Anthony Letai</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>anthony_letai@dfci.harvard.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6176322348</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000696485</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/09/2016</StartDate>
<EndDate>11/08/2016</EndDate>
<RoleCode>Former Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Nikhil</FirstName>
<LastName>Wagle</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Nikhil Wagle</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>nikhil_wagle@dfci.harvard.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6176323134</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000746784</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>03/21/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Dana-Farber Cancer Institute</Name>
<CityName>Boston</CityName>
<ZipCode>022155450</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6176323940</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>Office of Grants and Contracts</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[450 Brookline Avenue]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
<StateCode>MA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MA07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>076580745</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>DANA-FARBER CANCER INSTITUTE, INC.</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>076580745</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Dana-Farber Cancer Institute]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>MA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>022155450</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MA07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1253</Code>
<Text>OFFICE OF MULTIDISCIPLINARY AC</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7246</Code>
<Text>PHYSICS OF LIVING SYSTEMS</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>8011</Code>
<Text>Systems and Synthetic Biology</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0116</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0117</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0118</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2016~470000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2017~160790</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2018~160790</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Normal cells have within them mechanisms for making important decisions, such as whether to divide or not, and whether to die or not.&nbsp; The mechanisms depend upoin the interaction of many different proteins in what amounts to a complicated game of "telephone".&nbsp; Protein A tells protein B something, protein B passes it along to protein C and so on, until the final executing protein gets a message that has passed through many hands.&nbsp; Cancer cells distort this communication pathway and&nbsp;alters the transmission of these messages so that they are biased to tell the cell to divide rather than to stay quiescent, and to survive rather than to die.&nbsp;</p> <p>This type of cancer this grant focused on is breast cancer, in particular the relatively common kind of breast cancer that still receives signals from estrogen.&nbsp; In some of these cancers, there are alterations in a pathway, called PI3K, &nbsp;that regulates whether or not the cancer cell will grow and divide.&nbsp; The estrogen and PI3K signals combine to tell the cancer cell to grow and stay alive.&nbsp;</p> <p>There are anti-cancer drugs that target both the estrogen pathway as well as the PI3K pathway.&nbsp; However, they are not universally effective.&nbsp; In this grant we investigated what sort of alterations in the genes of the cancer cell makes cancer cells tolerate these kinds of therapies, when we might expect the cell to die.&nbsp; In one phase of this work, we relied on biologists working mainly on computers to take existing data, and combine it with new data we generated, to create a roadmap with all of the relevant connections that keep the cell alive. This roadmap helped guide us toward new therapies that could force the cancer cell to not only stop growing, but also to choose to die.</p> <p>In another phase of this work, we were able to study the genetic code of actual patients getting these therapies. We were able to use this information to see how cancer cells evolve to becom resistant and survive. Moreover, we can now use this information to design new therapies to overcome resistance.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 10/29/2019<br>      Modified by: Anthony&nbsp;Letai</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Normal cells have within them mechanisms for making important decisions, such as whether to divide or not, and whether to die or not.  The mechanisms depend upoin the interaction of many different proteins in what amounts to a complicated game of "telephone".  Protein A tells protein B something, protein B passes it along to protein C and so on, until the final executing protein gets a message that has passed through many hands.  Cancer cells distort this communication pathway and alters the transmission of these messages so that they are biased to tell the cell to divide rather than to stay quiescent, and to survive rather than to die.   This type of cancer this grant focused on is breast cancer, in particular the relatively common kind of breast cancer that still receives signals from estrogen.  In some of these cancers, there are alterations in a pathway, called PI3K,  that regulates whether or not the cancer cell will grow and divide.  The estrogen and PI3K signals combine to tell the cancer cell to grow and stay alive.   There are anti-cancer drugs that target both the estrogen pathway as well as the PI3K pathway.  However, they are not universally effective.  In this grant we investigated what sort of alterations in the genes of the cancer cell makes cancer cells tolerate these kinds of therapies, when we might expect the cell to die.  In one phase of this work, we relied on biologists working mainly on computers to take existing data, and combine it with new data we generated, to create a roadmap with all of the relevant connections that keep the cell alive. This roadmap helped guide us toward new therapies that could force the cancer cell to not only stop growing, but also to choose to die.  In another phase of this work, we were able to study the genetic code of actual patients getting these therapies. We were able to use this information to see how cancer cells evolve to becom resistant and survive. Moreover, we can now use this information to design new therapies to overcome resistance.       Last Modified: 10/29/2019       Submitted by: Anthony Letai]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
