<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>EAGER: GETBIO-PGR Gateway for Education, Training, Broader Impacts and Outreach in Plant Genome Research</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2016</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>02/28/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>299959.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>299959</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>08090000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>BIO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>IOS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Integrative Organismal Systems</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Kimberly Gallagher</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Most research projects that are engaged in characterizing the whole set of genes crop plants possess are complex in nature and carry out a diverse set of activities in addition to research. These include education and training of students, postdoctoral associates, and other professionals in different settings that range from classrooms and labs to workshops. In addition, many of these programs are also engaged in outreach activities with the community to raise awareness of the role that plant science plays in the quality of everyday life. One of the challenges faced by these scientists is recruitment of the research team, and communication with academic groups and the community at large. This project proposes to develop a web portal that will enable scientists to carry out these activities effectively and efficiently. In addition, this project will also assemble a large collection of highly specialized analytical software in a manner that will allow scientist to search and select the appropriate tool for very specific analytical tasks. The project also plans to request feedback from the community to target development of appropriate resources.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The primary objective of this project is to create an integrated Gateway for Education, Training, Broader Impacts and Outreach in Plant Genome Research (GETBIO-PGR). This resource will provide an infrastructure to access, create, share and exchange information about plant genome research projects and broader impact activities. It will also provide a resource to enable users to discover the most relevant bioinformatics analytic tools. More specifically, GETBIO-PGR will enable investigators to create individual, integrated web pages that will serve the multiple needs of their research program including recruitment of students and postdocs, availability of internships, and scheduling of workshops. The web pages will also be used to communicate research results, and describe resources that are available to the community. These may include availability of sequence information, clones, seeds of genetic stocks, and research software. This project will also create a bioinformatics analytic Tool Discovery System (Bio-TDS) and integrate it into GETBIO-PGR. An ontology annotation system will be added to the Bio-TDS to enable robust searching capabilities. Finally, the PIs will introduce the research and educational communities to GETBIO-PGR through education, presentations, and workshops while gathering usability feedback.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/19/2016</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/19/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.074</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1545596</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Ann</FirstName>
<LastName>Stapleton</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>E</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Ann E Stapleton</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>stapletona@uncw.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>9109627267</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000397270</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/19/2016</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Carol</FirstName>
<LastName>Lushbough</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Carol Lushbough</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>clushbou@usd.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6056776138</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000480530</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/19/2016</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Etienne</FirstName>
<LastName>Gnimpieba</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>Z</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Etienne Z Gnimpieba</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>Etienne.Gnimpieba@usd.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6056776064</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000670356</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/19/2016</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Michael</FirstName>
<LastName>Gonzales</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>D</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Michael D Gonzales</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>m.d.gonzo@gmail.com</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5056993643</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000695692</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/19/2016</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of South Dakota Main Campus</Name>
<CityName>vermillion</CityName>
<ZipCode>570692307</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6056775370</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>414 E CLARK ST</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>South Dakota</StateName>
<StateCode>SD</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>00</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>SD00</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>929930808</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>THE UNIVERSITY OF SOUTH DAKOTA</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>929538999</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of South Dakota]]></Name>
<CityName>Vermillion</CityName>
<StateCode>SD</StateCode>
<ZipCode>570691915</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[414 E. Clark]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>South Dakota</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>00</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>SD00</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1329</Code>
<Text>Plant Genome Research Project</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7577</Code>
<Text>PLANT GENOME RESEARCH RESOURCE</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7916</Code>
<Text>EAGER</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9109</Code>
<Text>AGRICULTURAL BIOTECHNOLOGY</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9178</Code>
<Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9179</Code>
<Text>GRADUATE INVOLVEMENT</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>BIOT</Code>
<Text>BIOTECHNOLOGY</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0116</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2016~299959</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><span>A </span><strong><span>Gateway for Education, Training, Broader Impacts and Outreach in Plant Genome Research</span></strong><span> (GETBIO-PGR,<a title="https://getbiopgr.org" href="https://getbiopgr.org">https://getbiopgr.org</a>) has been created to provide an infrastructure for researchers, educators, students and the general public&nbsp;to access, create, share and exchange information about plant genome research projects&rsquo; broader impact activities, opportunities, and resources. &nbsp;GETBIO-PGR</span>&nbsp;elevates the visibility and importance of broader impact activities -- and their intertwined research activities -- in a scalable, transformative way.</p> <p>Education, training, collaboration, broadening participation as well as raising awareness of the role that plant science plays in the quality of everyday life have remained important goals in the development of the National Plant Genome Initiative (NPGI) 2014-2018 five year plan. All NSF funded grants have the potential to not only advance scientific knowledge through research but also contribute to the achievement of societally relevant outcomes &ndash; what NSF calls Broader Impacts.</p> <p><span>GETBIO-PGR&nbsp;enables researchers to share the full range of their broader impact activities, opportunities, and resources within a centralized, integrated infrastructure.&nbsp;This platform makes it possible to provide more rapid dissemination and more effective use of best practices for mentoring, workshop management, and data analysis along with an increase in peer-to-peer interactions at all levels, from undergraduate students to faculty.&nbsp;Though this systems, users are able to access information such as: 1) Who else is studying &ldquo;soybean root&rdquo;?; 2) Are there any internships relating to CRISPR technology?; 3) Can I get some information about best practices in workshop design?; and 4) What are the best analytic tools for microbiology genome mapping using RNA-Seq?.</span></p> <p><em>&nbsp;</em>The Bioscience Query Tool Discovery Systems<strong> </strong>(<strong>Bio-TDS</strong>) integrated into GETBIO-PGR assists users in retrieving the <em>most relevant analytic tools</em> for their specific research question by allowing them to formulate their query as free text. The Bio-TDS is a flexible retrieval system allowing users to query over 15,000 analytic tool descriptions integrated from well-established, community repositories. Analytic tools are annotated and curated using an ontology and natural language processing workflow. The Bio-TDS offers researchers the capacity to associate their bioscience question with the most relevant computational toolsets required for the data analysis in their knowledge discovery process.&nbsp;</p> <p><span>Consider an example query submitted to Google from a user seeking recommendations for a &ldquo;fast, automated cell phenotype image classification tool&rdquo;. The first two pages of the Google result set contain references to published papers relating to automated image classification whereas Bio-TDS returns a list of recommended analytic tools such <em>CellClassifer </em>which is a tool for classifying single-cell phenotypes in microscope images.</span></p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 03/06/2018<br>      Modified by: Carol&nbsp;Lushbough</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Image         </div> <div class="galControls onePhoto" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation onePhoto" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1545596/1545596_10452496_1519934131251_getbio--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1545596/1545596_10452496_1519934131251_getbio--rgov-800width.jpg" title="GETBIO-PGR Platform"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1545596/1545596_10452496_1519934131251_getbio--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="GETBIO-PGR Platform"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Figure 1: GETBIO-PGR is a Gateway for Education, Training, Broader Impacts and Outreach in Plant Genome Research (GETBIO-PGR) and enables PGRP researchers to share the full range of their broader impact activities within a centralized, integrated infrastructure.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Carol Lushbough</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Public Domain</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Carol&nbsp;Lushbough</div> <div class="imageTitle">GETBIO-PGR Platform</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ A Gateway for Education, Training, Broader Impacts and Outreach in Plant Genome Research (GETBIO-PGR,https://getbiopgr.org) has been created to provide an infrastructure for researchers, educators, students and the general public to access, create, share and exchange information about plant genome research projects? broader impact activities, opportunities, and resources.  GETBIO-PGR elevates the visibility and importance of broader impact activities -- and their intertwined research activities -- in a scalable, transformative way.  Education, training, collaboration, broadening participation as well as raising awareness of the role that plant science plays in the quality of everyday life have remained important goals in the development of the National Plant Genome Initiative (NPGI) 2014-2018 five year plan. All NSF funded grants have the potential to not only advance scientific knowledge through research but also contribute to the achievement of societally relevant outcomes &ndash; what NSF calls Broader Impacts.  GETBIO-PGR enables researchers to share the full range of their broader impact activities, opportunities, and resources within a centralized, integrated infrastructure. This platform makes it possible to provide more rapid dissemination and more effective use of best practices for mentoring, workshop management, and data analysis along with an increase in peer-to-peer interactions at all levels, from undergraduate students to faculty. Though this systems, users are able to access information such as: 1) Who else is studying "soybean root"?; 2) Are there any internships relating to CRISPR technology?; 3) Can I get some information about best practices in workshop design?; and 4) What are the best analytic tools for microbiology genome mapping using RNA-Seq?.   The Bioscience Query Tool Discovery Systems (Bio-TDS) integrated into GETBIO-PGR assists users in retrieving the most relevant analytic tools for their specific research question by allowing them to formulate their query as free text. The Bio-TDS is a flexible retrieval system allowing users to query over 15,000 analytic tool descriptions integrated from well-established, community repositories. Analytic tools are annotated and curated using an ontology and natural language processing workflow. The Bio-TDS offers researchers the capacity to associate their bioscience question with the most relevant computational toolsets required for the data analysis in their knowledge discovery process.   Consider an example query submitted to Google from a user seeking recommendations for a "fast, automated cell phenotype image classification tool". The first two pages of the Google result set contain references to published papers relating to automated image classification whereas Bio-TDS returns a list of recommended analytic tools such CellClassifer which is a tool for classifying single-cell phenotypes in microscope images.          Last Modified: 03/06/2018       Submitted by: Carol Lushbough]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
