<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>RAPID/Collaborative Research: Post-Disaster, Reinforced Concrete Building Performance Data Collection following the April 25, 2015 Nepal Earthquake</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2015</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>24040.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>24040</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CMMI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Civil, Mechanical, &amp; Manufact Inn</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Joy Pauschke</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>jpauschk@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927024</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The magnitude 7.8 Ghorka, Nepal earthquake that occurred on April 25, 2015, and the many aftershocks that followed significantly affected Nepal, causing significant human loss as well as widespread structural damage and ground failure. The building stock in the affected regions predominantly consists of poorly engineered unreinforced masonry buildings. However, approximately 25 per cent of the buildings consist of reinforced concrete (RC) frames infilled with masonry walls.  This structural system was widely used in the 1920s and 1930s in California as well as in the Pacific Northwest; hence, understanding the damage to this structural system from the Nepal earthquake has direct implications for the seismic performance of a large number of buildings in metropolitan areas in the United States. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This rapid response research will focus on post-earthquake assessment of existing RC building frames with masonry infill in Nepal. A team of three researchers and three graduate students will travel to Nepal to collect perishable field data and perform detailed assessments of the seismic performance of 25-30 buildings. The team will acquire, process, and archive architectural and structural data, including building drawings, in residential buildings and critical facilities such as schools and hospitals. The data will be obtained through visual inspections and geo-referenced, three-dimensional (3D), ground-based Lidar scans and Structure from Motion, i.e., 3D reconstructions from two-dimensional photographs, thus providing detailed, quantitative damage measurements.  This collected data will be made publicly available to enable future research to advance computational modeling and structural analysis for understanding the seismic performance of RC frame with masonry infill buildings. This collected data will provide new earthquake reconnaissance case studies of RC frame with infill buildings and will be used to evaluate current U.S. guidelines for assessment of existing structures. Moreover, it will serve to inform local rebuilding and recovery efforts in Nepal though close collaboration with local agencies in Nepal. The research team will collaborate with researchers and practicing engineers from Italy, Nepal, and Portugal.  This project will also provide foreign research experiences for graduate students and further strengthen ties among the engineering research communities in the United States, Nepal, and European Union.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/23/2015</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/23/2015</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1545595</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Andreas</FirstName>
<LastName>Stavridis</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Andreas Stavridis</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>astavrid@buffalo.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>7166457366</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000616228</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/23/2015</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>SUNY at Buffalo</Name>
<CityName>Buffalo</CityName>
<ZipCode>142282567</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>7166452634</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>520 Lee Entrance</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[Suite 211]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>26</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NY26</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>038633251</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>RESEARCH FOUNDATION FOR THE STATE UNIVERSITY OF NEW YORK, THE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>020657151</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[SUNY at Buffalo]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<ZipCode>142601660</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>26</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NY26</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7396</Code>
<Text>NEES RESEARCH</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>036E</Code>
<Text>CIVIL INFRASTRUCTURE</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>039E</Code>
<Text>STRUCTURAL SYSTEMS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>043E</Code>
<Text>EARTHQUAKE ENGINEERING</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1057</Code>
<Text>CIS BASE RESEARCH</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1576</Code>
<Text>NATIONL EARTHQK HZRD REDCT PRG</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7914</Code>
<Text>RAPID</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>CVIS</Code>
<Text>CIVIL INFRASTRUCTURE</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0114</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2015~24040</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The outcomes of this project included (1) the documentation of the seismic performance of concrete and masonry structures during the 2015 Gorkha earthquake, (2) the data obtained through lidar scans and accelerometers installed on selected damaged structures, (3) the validation of a numerical modeling framework for infilled RC frames, (4) formation of lasting international collaboration, and (5) graduate and undergraduate student research and education. The five major outcomes are discussed in more detail in the following sections.&nbsp; <strong></strong></p> <p><strong>1.&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; </strong><strong>Documentation of Seismic Damage</strong></p> <ol> </ol> <p>During the reconnaissance trip to Nepal in June 2015, the researchers from the University at Buffalo, i.e. Dr. Stavridis and doctoral student S. Bose collaborated with researchers from the US (Oregon State University, the University of Nebraska, Lincoln), Nepal, Italy, and Portugal to document and understand the seismic load-transfer mechanisms and failure patterns of concrete and masonry structures. The focus of the team was on URM structures, as well as reinforced concrete frames with masonry infills used to house schools and apartments. This work has shed light into the behavior of these structures which has been documented in two collaborative journal papers (currently are under review).<strong></strong></p> <p><strong>2.&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; </strong><strong>Obtained Data</strong></p> <ol> </ol> <p>During the reconnaissance trip, the team acquired and archived architectural and structural data, including drawings of residential buildings and sensitive facilities such as schools. Ambient vibration data was collected from 5 structures using accelerometers. Damage data were obtained through traditional methods as well as via geo-referenced, 3D, ground-based lidar (GBL) scans and Structure from Motion (SfM), i.e. 3D reconstructions from 2D photographs, thus providing detailed, quantitative damage measurements. In addition, the team collected many pictures on cameras mounted on unmanned aerial vehicles that show promise for disaster reconnaissance efforts. The complete set of collected data, published DesignSafe-CI &nbsp;provides case studies of RC and masonry buildings, ad can be used to evaluate guidelines for the assessment of existing structures, and to update the Nepalese building code.<strong></strong></p> <p><strong>3.&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; </strong><strong>Validation of Nonlinear Numerical Models</strong></p> <ol> </ol> <p>A key outcome of this study is the validation of the newly proposed framework for the simulation of the seismic behavior of infilled RC frames. The models incorporate strut models to simulate the effect of masonry infills. The struts are calibrated with a new approach that is drastically different to the one used in the past, as the calibration depends on the anticipated failure mechanism which is estimated with the proposed methodology. The framework has been applied to two school buildings of five stories, and two apartment complexes of 12 and 16 stories. The comparison with the data obtained in the field indicates that the models can reproduce accurately the damage patterns when subjected to the ground motions recorded nearby.<strong></strong></p> <p><strong>4.&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; Across Disciplines and International Collaboration</strong></p> <ol> </ol> <p>As a result of the activities funded by this project, Dr. Stavridis has collaborated with a number of international research groups. A collaboration with researchers from USGS and the National Society for Earthquake Technology-Nepal, has focused on developing fragility curves for school buildings using infilled RC frames with masonry infills. The vulnerable school buildings in Nepal are the focus of the international research team, led by the University of Bristol, which involves researchers from Asia and Europe, as well as the World Bank and focuses on the improvement of the structural performance of the schools in Nepal. Moreover, discussions with students and faculty in the Department of Architecture in UB about the damage patterns observed in Nepal has enhanced their understanding of the seismic hazard for these structures. This is helping bridge the gap between the two disciplines and it can lead to safer but also more aesthetically pleasing structures both in the US and Nepal, as a number of students in architecture at UB are from Nepal. Dr. Stavridis is also serving on the committee for one MS student in architecture, whose research focuses on the improvement of the seismic performance of traditional Nepali structures without altering their appearance.<strong></strong></p> <p><strong>5.&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; </strong><strong>Graduate and Undergraduate Research and Education</strong></p> <ol> </ol> <p>This project has had a significant impact on the education of four graduate students at the University at Buffalo. Supratik Bose (doctoral student) traveled to Nepal in Summer 2015 and experienced first-hand the destruction and assisted in the reconnaissance efforts. His doctoral thesis, to be defended in few months, is focusing on developing efficient simulation methods for masonry-infilled RC structures, which he has validated with data obtained from the damaged structures in Nepal. Wen Yu Chang traveled to Nepal in Fall 2016 and assisted in the instrumentation of additional buildings. For his MS thesis, he developed a numerical model for one of the school buildings in Nepal. Tim van Oss and Liangchun Huang completed an MS and a BS graduation project focusing on the simulation of the seismic performance of two 16-story structures. <strong></strong></p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 10/24/2017<br>      Modified by: Andreas&nbsp;Stavridis</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Images (<span id="selectedPhoto0">1</span> of <span class="totalNumber"></span>)           </div> <div class="galControls" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1545595/1545595_10371602_1508827965030_2015-06-0913.03.36--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1545595/1545595_10371602_1508827965030_2015-06-0913.03.36--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Damaged School Building in Sankhu"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1545595/1545595_10371602_1508827965030_2015-06-0913.03.36--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Damaged School Building in Sankhu"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">This building was instrumented and the data was used to validate a nonlinear numerical model.</div> <div class="imageCredit">A. Stavridis</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Andreas&nbsp;Stavridis</div> <div class="imageTitle">Damaged School Building in Sankhu</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1545595/1545595_10371602_1508828151042_2015-06-0523.27.08--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1545595/1545595_10371602_1508828151042_2015-06-0523.27.08--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Damaged Apartment Building"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1545595/1545595_10371602_1508828151042_2015-06-0523.27.08--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Damaged Apartment Building"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">This 16-story building consists of infilled RC frames and was severely damaged by the earthquake</div> <div class="imageCredit">A. Stavridis</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Andreas&nbsp;Stavridis</div> <div class="imageTitle">Damaged Apartment Building</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1545595/1545595_10371602_1508828443989_Picture1--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1545595/1545595_10371602_1508828443989_Picture1--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Numerical Model of School Building"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1545595/1545595_10371602_1508828443989_Picture1--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Numerical Model of School Building"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">The three-dimensional model, developed to simulate the seismic performance of the school building, was subjected to the ground motions recorded in close proximity.</div> <div class="imageCredit">A. Stavridis</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Andreas&nbsp;Stavridis</div> <div class="imageTitle">Numerical Model of School Building</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1545595/1545595_10371602_1508828544312_Picture2--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1545595/1545595_10371602_1508828544312_Picture2--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Mode shapes"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1545595/1545595_10371602_1508828544312_Picture2--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Mode shapes"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Comparison of the mode shapes extracted from the recorded data and from the numerical model.</div> <div class="imageCredit">A. Stavridis</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Andreas&nbsp;Stavridis</div> <div class="imageTitle">Mode shapes</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The outcomes of this project included (1) the documentation of the seismic performance of concrete and masonry structures during the 2015 Gorkha earthquake, (2) the data obtained through lidar scans and accelerometers installed on selected damaged structures, (3) the validation of a numerical modeling framework for infilled RC frames, (4) formation of lasting international collaboration, and (5) graduate and undergraduate student research and education. The five major outcomes are discussed in more detail in the following sections.    1.    Documentation of Seismic Damage    During the reconnaissance trip to Nepal in June 2015, the researchers from the University at Buffalo, i.e. Dr. Stavridis and doctoral student S. Bose collaborated with researchers from the US (Oregon State University, the University of Nebraska, Lincoln), Nepal, Italy, and Portugal to document and understand the seismic load-transfer mechanisms and failure patterns of concrete and masonry structures. The focus of the team was on URM structures, as well as reinforced concrete frames with masonry infills used to house schools and apartments. This work has shed light into the behavior of these structures which has been documented in two collaborative journal papers (currently are under review).  2.    Obtained Data    During the reconnaissance trip, the team acquired and archived architectural and structural data, including drawings of residential buildings and sensitive facilities such as schools. Ambient vibration data was collected from 5 structures using accelerometers. Damage data were obtained through traditional methods as well as via geo-referenced, 3D, ground-based lidar (GBL) scans and Structure from Motion (SfM), i.e. 3D reconstructions from 2D photographs, thus providing detailed, quantitative damage measurements. In addition, the team collected many pictures on cameras mounted on unmanned aerial vehicles that show promise for disaster reconnaissance efforts. The complete set of collected data, published DesignSafe-CI  provides case studies of RC and masonry buildings, ad can be used to evaluate guidelines for the assessment of existing structures, and to update the Nepalese building code.  3.    Validation of Nonlinear Numerical Models    A key outcome of this study is the validation of the newly proposed framework for the simulation of the seismic behavior of infilled RC frames. The models incorporate strut models to simulate the effect of masonry infills. The struts are calibrated with a new approach that is drastically different to the one used in the past, as the calibration depends on the anticipated failure mechanism which is estimated with the proposed methodology. The framework has been applied to two school buildings of five stories, and two apartment complexes of 12 and 16 stories. The comparison with the data obtained in the field indicates that the models can reproduce accurately the damage patterns when subjected to the ground motions recorded nearby.  4.    Across Disciplines and International Collaboration    As a result of the activities funded by this project, Dr. Stavridis has collaborated with a number of international research groups. A collaboration with researchers from USGS and the National Society for Earthquake Technology-Nepal, has focused on developing fragility curves for school buildings using infilled RC frames with masonry infills. The vulnerable school buildings in Nepal are the focus of the international research team, led by the University of Bristol, which involves researchers from Asia and Europe, as well as the World Bank and focuses on the improvement of the structural performance of the schools in Nepal. Moreover, discussions with students and faculty in the Department of Architecture in UB about the damage patterns observed in Nepal has enhanced their understanding of the seismic hazard for these structures. This is helping bridge the gap between the two disciplines and it can lead to safer but also more aesthetically pleasing structures both in the US and Nepal, as a number of students in architecture at UB are from Nepal. Dr. Stavridis is also serving on the committee for one MS student in architecture, whose research focuses on the improvement of the seismic performance of traditional Nepali structures without altering their appearance.  5.    Graduate and Undergraduate Research and Education    This project has had a significant impact on the education of four graduate students at the University at Buffalo. Supratik Bose (doctoral student) traveled to Nepal in Summer 2015 and experienced first-hand the destruction and assisted in the reconnaissance efforts. His doctoral thesis, to be defended in few months, is focusing on developing efficient simulation methods for masonry-infilled RC structures, which he has validated with data obtained from the damaged structures in Nepal. Wen Yu Chang traveled to Nepal in Fall 2016 and assisted in the instrumentation of additional buildings. For his MS thesis, he developed a numerical model for one of the school buildings in Nepal. Tim van Oss and Liangchun Huang completed an MS and a BS graduation project focusing on the simulation of the seismic performance of two 16-story structures.        Last Modified: 10/24/2017       Submitted by: Andreas Stavridis]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
