<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>EAGER: Cybermanufacturing: Enabling Production as a Service (PaaS)</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>10/01/2015</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>09/30/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>250000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>250000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>05050000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>CSE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CNS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Computer and Network Systems</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>David Corman</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>dcorman@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032928754</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Production as a service (PaaS) defines a new paradigm in manufacturing that will allow designers of new products to query existing manufacturing facilities and receive information about fabrication capabilities and production availability. The access to information such as part cost, part quality, and production time will help new products to be prototyped and scaled-up quickly, while also allowing existing manufacturing facilities to benefit from underutilized equipment and labor. The PaaS framework will include both a front-end query interface for the users and a back-end analysis component. The interface will be designed to connect users with small-, mid-, and large-sized manufacturing facilities, while the scheduling and routing algorithms will provide the flexibility and security protocols needed to guarantee operational and production safety across the range of facilities. Manufacturers that utilize the PaaS framework will reap the potential of meeting customer needs in terms of cost, quality, on-time delivery, while being reactive to changing market forces. With 12 percent of the GDP represented by the manufacturing industry, the manufacturing operational improvements that will result from this EArly-concept Grant for Exploratory Research (EAGER) project have the potential to make a significant impact in the national bottom line. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The aim of the PaaS platform is to enable distributed manufacturing plant locations to efficiently coordinate both within one plant location as well as across plant locations to realize a flexible service interface for supporting production management. The intellectual merit of this research lies in the extensions that will be created to the existing science and technology in service-oriented architectures to enable distributed production, while preserving proprietary information of the manufacturing systems. The key software abstraction that enables this innovation comes from the extension to the well-known APIs to capture the sophisticated query logic and diverse production requirements to meet user needs. Routing and scheduling decisions will be optimized by leveraging a global view of the current state of all of the components in the manufacturing facilities. To demonstrate scalability and ensure privacy guarantees across multiple facilities, hierarchical abstraction will be used to hide low-level details and proprietary information. The PaaS framework will transform the way manufacturing companies interact with the emerging high-value market; providing the architecture to drive innovation and enable small-, mid-, and large-scale manufacturing companies across the U.S. to compete for new product business on an even playing field.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/28/2015</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/14/2017</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.070</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1546036</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Dawn</FirstName>
<LastName>Tilbury</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Dawn Tilbury</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>tilbury@umich.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>7349362129</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000387238</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/28/2015</StartDate>
<EndDate>06/14/2017</EndDate>
<RoleCode>Former Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Zhuoqing</FirstName>
<LastName>Mao</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>M</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Zhuoqing M Mao</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>zmao@umich.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>7347635407</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000490161</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/28/2015</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Kira</FirstName>
<LastName>Barton</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Kira Barton</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>bartonkl@umich.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>7347647293</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000614093</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/28/2015</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Regents of the University of Michigan - Ann Arbor</Name>
<CityName>Ann Arbor</CityName>
<ZipCode>481091274</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>7347636438</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>3003 South State St. Room 1062</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Michigan</StateName>
<StateCode>MI</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>12</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MI12</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>073133571</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>REGENTS OF THE UNIVERSITY OF MICHIGAN</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>073133571</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Michigan Ann Arbor]]></Name>
<CityName>Ann Arbor</CityName>
<StateCode>MI</StateCode>
<ZipCode>481092121</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[2260 Hayward]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Michigan</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>12</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MI12</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7918</Code>
<Text>CPS-Cyber-Physical Systems</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7951</Code>
<Text>ENG IDR-Eng Interdisciplin Res</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7916</Code>
<Text>EAGER</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0115</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2015~250000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>In current practice, product developers with customized small batch production needs come across the problem of finding capable and flexible manufacturers, whereas manufac- turers face underutilization due to inconsistent demand. This project presents a Production as a Service (PaaS) framework to connect users (consumers or product developers) who have customized small batch manufacturing needs with manufacturers who have existing underutilized resources. PaaS is a cloud-based, centralized framework based on a service-oriented architecture that abstracts the manufacturing steps of a product as individual (production) service requests. Using PaaS, the user is able to reach many capable manufacturers at once and receive quotations for the production request. On the other end, PaaS reduces the effort required to find new customers and enables the manufacturers to easily submit quotations to increase the utilization of their resources. The functionalities and concepts defined in this work are illustrated through case studies.</p> <p>&nbsp;In order to transition product fabrication from the design phase to manufacturing, there is a need for identifying capable manufacturers with available resources that could be paired with user requirements. We propose Production as a Service (PaaS) in this project and present initial implementations of the front-end and back-end components with a customizable optimization algorithm. Proposed abstractions and data structures make PaaS a unique, efficient, and intellectual property preserving framework. The current implementation of the framework has been tested with new designs. The PaaS framework has the potential to scale over a large network of manufacturers to effectively coordinate geo-distributed manufacturers for custom manufacturing needs.</p> <p>We have implemented a prototype of the PaaS&nbsp;design and evaluated it in the context of several realistic case&nbsp;studies working with local industry demonstrating its usefulness.&nbsp;</p> <p>The PaaS framework enables effective utilization of manufacturing resources for rapid realization of custom manufacturing needs of product developers. This paper can handle precedence and batch splitting constraints to efficiently evaluate optimal manufacturing solutions. Introducing CAPP capabilities for the feature extraction module to automatically assign precedence relationships and extract the most significant manufacturing features of a design is an important future direction. The proposed quality assignment model is a general approach that has limited flexibility for certain manufacturing methods (e.g., AM); future work will incorporate customized quality definitions. Future research will consider supply?demand dynamics in the service matching algorithm to incorporate real-time updates for enhanced user?manufacturer matching.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 12/03/2018<br>      Modified by: Zhuoqing&nbsp;M&nbsp;Mao</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Images (<span id="selectedPhoto0">1</span> of <span class="totalNumber"></span>)           </div> <div class="galControls" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1546036/1546036_10393291_1543865269520_PaaSIllustration--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1546036/1546036_10393291_1543865269520_PaaSIllustration--rgov-800width.jpg" title="PaaS illustration"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1546036/1546036_10393291_1543865269520_PaaSIllustration--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="PaaS illustration"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">1?user submits a new production request to the framework through the customer interface (RFQ interface). 2?manufacturers with adequate capabilities are notified with the MFS. 3?manufacturer responds to the MFS through the mfr interface. 4?user changes the preference on the weight of CTQ of the evalu</div> <div class="imageCredit">Efe Balta</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Zhuoqing&nbsp;M&nbsp;Mao</div> <div class="imageTitle">PaaS illustration</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1546036/1546036_10393291_1543865182502_framework--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1546036/1546036_10393291_1543865182502_framework--rgov-800width.jpg" title="PaaS overview"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1546036/1546036_10393291_1543865182502_framework--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="PaaS overview"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">PaaS overview</div> <div class="imageCredit">Efe Balta</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Zhuoqing&nbsp;M&nbsp;Mao</div> <div class="imageTitle">PaaS overview</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ In current practice, product developers with customized small batch production needs come across the problem of finding capable and flexible manufacturers, whereas manufac- turers face underutilization due to inconsistent demand. This project presents a Production as a Service (PaaS) framework to connect users (consumers or product developers) who have customized small batch manufacturing needs with manufacturers who have existing underutilized resources. PaaS is a cloud-based, centralized framework based on a service-oriented architecture that abstracts the manufacturing steps of a product as individual (production) service requests. Using PaaS, the user is able to reach many capable manufacturers at once and receive quotations for the production request. On the other end, PaaS reduces the effort required to find new customers and enables the manufacturers to easily submit quotations to increase the utilization of their resources. The functionalities and concepts defined in this work are illustrated through case studies.   In order to transition product fabrication from the design phase to manufacturing, there is a need for identifying capable manufacturers with available resources that could be paired with user requirements. We propose Production as a Service (PaaS) in this project and present initial implementations of the front-end and back-end components with a customizable optimization algorithm. Proposed abstractions and data structures make PaaS a unique, efficient, and intellectual property preserving framework. The current implementation of the framework has been tested with new designs. The PaaS framework has the potential to scale over a large network of manufacturers to effectively coordinate geo-distributed manufacturers for custom manufacturing needs.  We have implemented a prototype of the PaaS design and evaluated it in the context of several realistic case studies working with local industry demonstrating its usefulness.   The PaaS framework enables effective utilization of manufacturing resources for rapid realization of custom manufacturing needs of product developers. This paper can handle precedence and batch splitting constraints to efficiently evaluate optimal manufacturing solutions. Introducing CAPP capabilities for the feature extraction module to automatically assign precedence relationships and extract the most significant manufacturing features of a design is an important future direction. The proposed quality assignment model is a general approach that has limited flexibility for certain manufacturing methods (e.g., AM); future work will incorporate customized quality definitions. Future research will consider supply?demand dynamics in the service matching algorithm to incorporate real-time updates for enhanced user?manufacturer matching.       Last Modified: 12/03/2018       Submitted by: Zhuoqing M Mao]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
