<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>BIGDATA: Collaborative Research: IA: Population Reproduction of Poverty at Birth from Surveys, Censuses, and Birth Registrations</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>01/01/2016</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2020</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>358829.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>358829</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>05020000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>CSE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>IIS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Information &amp; Intelligent Systems</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Sara Kiesler</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>skiesler@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032928643</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The potential for upward mobility from one generation to the next is fundamental to the wellbeing of a democratic society, and to that society's long-term economic productivity. Poverty at birth is a condition affecting more than 1 in 4 American children. It is a critical barrier to children's subsequent development and life chances, and therefore to breaking intergenerational cycles of disadvantage. Both mother's and father's characteristics contribute to the chance that a child will be born into poverty. Therefore it is important to incorporate both the mother and father into the scientific modeling of the experience of poverty at birth from one generation to the next. Existing data and methods do not allow for this modeling in representative samples of the U.S. population, especially as it evolves as an increasingly multi-ethnic society. Limited data are collected on the characteristics of every birth in the United States. Limited additional data on all individuals and their households are collected every 10 years in the Census. Larger amounts of data per individual and household are collected every year from random samples that are representative of the U.S. population. These samples include the large-scale American Community Survey and numerous medium- and small-scale sample surveys. This research develops and evaluates statistical estimation and simulation methods to combine data from all these sources to answer questions about intergenerational mobility. The research will answer questions about the degree of persistence of poverty at birth from one generation to the next across different race and ethnic groups, and about the roles of education and family formation in creating upward mobility versus persistence of disadvantage. Open-source, user-friendly software for the statistical methods developed in the project will be made available to researchers. The project also develops graduate students' skills in Big Data methods in statistics and the social sciences. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The project has as its goal the development of a transformative, Big Data approach to exploiting the rich "traditional" data sources to build social-scientific theory in a statistically-rigorous and empirically-comprehensive way. In no single nationally-representative data source is poverty at birth observed for the mother-father-child triad. The triad's poverty statuses at each one's birth are instead linked in a model that simulates four connected processes: (1) educational progress predicted from the birth conditions of household poverty and parents' education, race, ethnicity, and immigrant statuses; (2) couple formation and dissolution; (3) couple fertility and unpartnered women's fertility; and (4) household poverty when their own children are born. The "Big Data" of this project consist of more than 100 million births, combined with census, microcensus, large-scale cross-sectional survey, and medium-scale and smaller-scale longitudinal survey data sources that together include millions of years of exposure to schooling, to partner-matching, and to partnered and (co-residentially) unpartnered births. These multiple sources of data of the study, unlike in many Big Data applications, are all either complete enumerations or probability samples of a well-specified population. The project develops combined-survey and combined population-and-survey estimation methods to estimate with enhanced precision the individual behavioral parameters of the process, and develops a simulation-modeling approach to generating inference about causal associations that emerge from the four connected processes, integrating the multiple sources of uncertainty about each component process. Results and methodological advances will be disseminated to the scholarly community through presentations and peer-reviewed journal articles. Additional, broader dissemination will occur through project investigator contact with the news media and other forums for engagement with the broader policy community about the project results and their significance.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>09/14/2015</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>09/14/2015</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.070</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1546300</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Mark</FirstName>
<LastName>Handcock</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>S</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Mark S Handcock</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>handcock@ucla.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>3108176778</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000315714</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/14/2015</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of California-Los Angeles</Name>
<CityName>LOS ANGELES</CityName>
<ZipCode>900951406</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>3107940102</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>10889 Wilshire Boulevard</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[Suite 700]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>33</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CA33</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>092530369</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF CALIFORNIA, LOS ANGELES</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>071549000</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of California-Los Angeles]]></Name>
<CityName>Los Angeles</CityName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>900951554</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[8125 Mathematical Sciences Bldg.]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>33</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CA33</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>8069</Code>
<Text>CDS&amp;E-MSS</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>8083</Code>
<Text>Big Data Science &amp;Engineering</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7433</Code>
<Text>CyberInfra Frmwrk 21st (CIF21)</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8083</Code>
<Text>Big Data Science &amp;Engineering</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8084</Code>
<Text>CDS&amp;E</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8251</Code>
<Text>Math Sci Innovation Incubator</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0115</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2015~358829</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>A model of intergenerational reproduction of a social phenomenon should account for the roles of partnering, of partnered and unpartnered childbearing, and for parent-child correlations in ("transmission of") the social phenomenon. Our model's key outcome was poverty at birth. We published one article, and have under review a second article, that find that low parental education, scarce availability of resources from another adult or adults, and inconsistent own contraceptive behavior are all associated with higher likelihood of a child's being born poor. The studies we conducted also compared different methods for measuring poverty. We found that taking into account a cohabiting partner's resources, which the official poverty measure does not, was crucial to accurate poverty measurement, and to measurement of race/ethnic disparities, in poverty especially at the time of a child's birth.</p> <p>Our project moved beyond previous work by accounting carefully for the ways that two parents "match" (become partnered with each other). We also examined how the number of children a couple has depends on both the woman's and the man's characteristics, and we found that it depends more on the father's characteristics than on the mother's characteristics. This all emphasizes the importance of understanding the reproduction of characteristics from one generation to the next, including the reproduction of adverse circumstances such as poverty at birth, as a consequence of the social processes involved in partnering, and of childbearing behavior between different partnered combinations of women and men.</p> <p>The major advance of our project was to build and validate a model that would incorporate these gender interactions at a couple level into a model of the entire population across generations. The validation of this model consisted of testing the model&rsquo;s ability to simulate, in our first version of this model, education levels of women and of mothers observed in the US population.</p> <p>In summary, we overcame some of the important limitations of previous intergenerational reproduction models by specifying, estimating, simulating, and validating a "two-sex" model of intergenerational reproduction of education, with childbearing both inside and outside marriage included in the model.</p> <p>The scientific human resource development outcomes included the training of three social science graduate students and two early career investigators in these advanced social modeling methods used and developed, and the successful collaboration between the social science and statistical science disciplines represented in the joint team of domain expertise and methodological expertise.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 04/30/2021<br>      Modified by: Mark&nbsp;S&nbsp;Handcock</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ A model of intergenerational reproduction of a social phenomenon should account for the roles of partnering, of partnered and unpartnered childbearing, and for parent-child correlations in ("transmission of") the social phenomenon. Our model's key outcome was poverty at birth. We published one article, and have under review a second article, that find that low parental education, scarce availability of resources from another adult or adults, and inconsistent own contraceptive behavior are all associated with higher likelihood of a child's being born poor. The studies we conducted also compared different methods for measuring poverty. We found that taking into account a cohabiting partner's resources, which the official poverty measure does not, was crucial to accurate poverty measurement, and to measurement of race/ethnic disparities, in poverty especially at the time of a child's birth.  Our project moved beyond previous work by accounting carefully for the ways that two parents "match" (become partnered with each other). We also examined how the number of children a couple has depends on both the woman's and the man's characteristics, and we found that it depends more on the father's characteristics than on the mother's characteristics. This all emphasizes the importance of understanding the reproduction of characteristics from one generation to the next, including the reproduction of adverse circumstances such as poverty at birth, as a consequence of the social processes involved in partnering, and of childbearing behavior between different partnered combinations of women and men.  The major advance of our project was to build and validate a model that would incorporate these gender interactions at a couple level into a model of the entire population across generations. The validation of this model consisted of testing the model’s ability to simulate, in our first version of this model, education levels of women and of mothers observed in the US population.  In summary, we overcame some of the important limitations of previous intergenerational reproduction models by specifying, estimating, simulating, and validating a "two-sex" model of intergenerational reproduction of education, with childbearing both inside and outside marriage included in the model.  The scientific human resource development outcomes included the training of three social science graduate students and two early career investigators in these advanced social modeling methods used and developed, and the successful collaboration between the social science and statistical science disciplines represented in the joint team of domain expertise and methodological expertise.          Last Modified: 04/30/2021       Submitted by: Mark S Handcock]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
