<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>I-Corps:  Knowledge Access for Design Ideation in Bioinspired Invention</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2015</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2016</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>50000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>50000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07070000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>IIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Industrial Innovation &amp; Partnersh</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Steven Konsek</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>skonsek@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927021</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Over the last generation, bioinspiration has transformed into an important, widespread and growing design movement with applications in fields as varied as building, energy, water, transportation, communication, food systems, health technology, manufacturing, and consumer products. Bioinspiration views nature as a vast library of robust, efficient, multifunctional and sustainable designs, and espouses the use of biological systems as sources of inspiration as well as standards of evaluation for designing technological systems. Over the last generation, bioinspiration has transformed into an important, widespread and growing design movement.Bioinspiration is expected to have a global economic value of $1.6 trillion - $2.1 trillion by 2030. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The adoption and growth of the bioinspiration movement is limited by the fact that most designers are novices in biology. This causes two major 'pains': slow, tedious, frustrating search for biological analogues relevant to a design problem, and slow, inaccurate and imprecise understanding of biological systems. Thus there is a need for information systems that provide access to biological knowledge from a design perspective, and interactive tools that support the process of making biological analogies in conceptual design. In this project, the I-Corps team will investigate the commercial viability of interactive technologies for supporting design ideation in bioinspired invention that has been developed. A successful commercial enterprise in knowledge access for design ideation in bioinspired invention has the potential for a transformative impact on the business of bioinspiration.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/23/2015</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/23/2015</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1546967</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Ashok</FirstName>
<LastName>Goel</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>K</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Ashok K Goel</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>ashok.goel@cc.gatech.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>4048944994</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000284024</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/23/2015</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Georgia Tech Research Corporation</Name>
<CityName>Atlanta</CityName>
<ZipCode>303320420</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>4048944819</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>Office of Sponsored Programs</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Georgia</StateName>
<StateCode>GA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>GA05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>097394084</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>GEORGIA TECH RESEARCH CORPORATION</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>097394084</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Georgia Institute of Technology]]></Name>
<CityName>Atlanta</CityName>
<StateCode>GA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>303320002</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[225 North Ave. NW]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Georgia</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>GA05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>8023</Code>
<Text>I-Corps</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0115</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2015~50000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><!--   @font-face  {font-family:Times;  panose-1:2 0 5 0 0 0 0 0 0 0;  mso-font-charset:0;  mso-generic-font-family:auto;  mso-font-pitch:variable;  mso-font-signature:3 0 0 0 1 0;} @font-face  {font-family:"?? ??";  panose-1:0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0;  mso-font-charset:128;  mso-generic-font-family:roman;  mso-font-format:other;  mso-font-pitch:fixed;  mso-font-signature:1 134676480 16 0 131072 0;} @font-face  {font-family:"?? ??";  panose-1:0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0;  mso-font-charset:128;  mso-generic-font-family:roman;  mso-font-format:other;  mso-font-pitch:fixed;  mso-font-signature:1 134676480 16 0 131072 0;} @font-face  {font-family:Cambria;  panose-1:2 4 5 3 5 4 6 3 2 4;  mso-font-charset:0;  mso-generic-font-family:auto;  mso-font-pitch:variable;  mso-font-signature:-536870145 1073743103 0 0 415 0;}   p.MsoNormal, li.MsoNormal, div.MsoNormal  {mso-style-unhide:no;  mso-style-qformat:yes;  mso-style-parent:";  margin:0in;  margin-bottom:.0001pt;  mso-pagination:widow-orphan;  font-size:12.0pt;  font-family:Cambria;  mso-ascii-font-family:Cambria;  mso-ascii-theme-font:minor-latin;  mso-fareast-font-family:"?? ??";  mso-fareast-theme-font:minor-fareast;  mso-hansi-font-family:Cambria;  mso-hansi-theme-font:minor-latin;  mso-bidi-font-family:"Times New Roman";  mso-bidi-theme-font:minor-bidi;} p  {mso-style-noshow:yes;  mso-style-priority:99;  mso-margin-top-alt:auto;  margin-right:0in;  mso-margin-bottom-alt:auto;  margin-left:0in;  mso-pagination:widow-orphan;  font-size:10.0pt;  font-family:Times;  mso-fareast-font-family:"?? ??";  mso-fareast-theme-font:minor-fareast;  mso-bidi-font-family:"Times New Roman";} .MsoChpDefault  {mso-style-type:export-only;  mso-default-props:yes;  font-family:Cambria;  mso-ascii-font-family:Cambria;  mso-ascii-theme-font:minor-latin;  mso-fareast-font-family:"?? ??";  mso-fareast-theme-font:minor-fareast;  mso-hansi-font-family:Cambria;  mso-hansi-theme-font:minor-latin;  mso-bidi-font-family:"Times New Roman";  mso-bidi-theme-font:minor-bidi;} @page WordSection1  {size:8.5in 11.0in;  margin:1.0in 1.25in 1.0in 1.25in;  mso-header-margin:.5in;  mso-footer-margin:.5in;  mso-paper-source:0;} div.WordSection1  {page:WordSection1;} --> <p>The original goal of this project was to explore the hypothesis that a technology for accessing biology articles on the web relevant to a given problem in engineering design may have commercial value. However, customer discovery in 2015 revealed that while there was significant interest in the technology, there were few companies willing and able to pay for the technology. Therefore, we pivoted to other business sectors.</p> <p>Additional customer discovery indicated significant interest from the financial and legal sectors. We decided to focus on financial banks. We have since cultivated a strong relationship with a specific bank as a potential customer. In 2016, we obtained a small grant from Georgia Research Alliance for developing a software prototype for the said bank. The software prototype is under construction in our research laboratory. We are now negotiating a contract with the said bank. &nbsp;</p> <p>In the meanwhile, in 2016 our research laboratory we developed a related technology for question answering that appears even more relevant to banking and other business sectors. In particular, we have identified customer relation management as generic customer segment for the new question answering technology. We are presently negotiating grants and contracts with potential customers engaged in customer relation management in several business sectors ranging from education to healthcare to human resources.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 04/20/2017<br>      Modified by: Ashok&nbsp;K&nbsp;Goel</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[  The original goal of this project was to explore the hypothesis that a technology for accessing biology articles on the web relevant to a given problem in engineering design may have commercial value. However, customer discovery in 2015 revealed that while there was significant interest in the technology, there were few companies willing and able to pay for the technology. Therefore, we pivoted to other business sectors.  Additional customer discovery indicated significant interest from the financial and legal sectors. We decided to focus on financial banks. We have since cultivated a strong relationship with a specific bank as a potential customer. In 2016, we obtained a small grant from Georgia Research Alliance for developing a software prototype for the said bank. The software prototype is under construction in our research laboratory. We are now negotiating a contract with the said bank.    In the meanwhile, in 2016 our research laboratory we developed a related technology for question answering that appears even more relevant to banking and other business sectors. In particular, we have identified customer relation management as generic customer segment for the new question answering technology. We are presently negotiating grants and contracts with potential customers engaged in customer relation management in several business sectors ranging from education to healthcare to human resources.       Last Modified: 04/20/2017       Submitted by: Ashok K Goel]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
