<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>BIGDATA: IA: Exploring Analysis of Environment and Health Through Multiple Alternative Clustering</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>01/01/2016</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2020</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>860648.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>876648</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>05020000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>CSE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>IIS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Information &amp; Intelligent Systems</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Wendy Nilsen</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>wnilsen@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922568</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>While many disciplines have become increasingly exploratory given that large-scale and multi-source data collection has become prevalent, we find that volumes of data that were carefully collected and studied to answer project-specific questions, are neglected and unstudied, even if they hold key answers to tomorrow's questions. This project addresses this challenge by developing novel data analysis, alternative clustering, data visualization and acceleration solutions to enable exploration and identification of connections hidden in diverse data sets, leading to new discoveries and knowledge. In particular, the data analysis algorithms will be applied to a large dataset taken from an ongoing National Institute of Environmental Health Sciences (NIEHS) project that is assessing the impact of water-borne pollutants on premature birth rates in Puerto Rico.  The exploratory analysis will focus on discovering the unknown underlying environmental factors and processes that may more broadly impact health and the environment.  As such, this study promotes progress in data science, environmental science and health.  Note that this project will address women?s health in an under-served population.  In addition, this project supports education through graduate research support, development of inter-disciplinary tutorials, and creation of a new undergraduate class that addresses the intersection between machine learning approaches and parallel computing.&lt;br/&gt; &lt;br/&gt;The environmental health data comprises of multiple heterogeneous sources with varying temporal and spatial resolutions: mass spectrometer readings to identify targeted and non-targeted compounds in well and tap water, participant surveys detailing personal care and household products use in the home, and analyzed placental, blood and urine samples. Such complex data challenges traditional clustering algorithms in the following ways. The first challenge is in defining the appropriate similarity measure for each type of data source. The second step involves how to integrate information from these multiple sources for clustering. The third challenge is that in exploratory analysis, the solution found may not be what the analyst is looking for. How can one discover alternative solutions given this knowledge? In real world applications, data can often be interpreted in many different ways. However, existing multi-source fusion methods can only find a single solution. This study will develop new alternative clustering approaches, exploring multiple heterogeneous information sources. The project will deliver both visual and scalable solutions to enable sifting through the mountains of data efficiently. Moreover, the project will produce parallel libraries within Spark, and demonstrate the power of these new methods to this environmental health application.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>09/14/2015</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/12/2018</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.070</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1546428</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>David</FirstName>
<LastName>Kaeli</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>R</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>David R Kaeli</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>kaeli@ece.neu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6173735413</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000179508</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/14/2015</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Jennifer</FirstName>
<LastName>Dy</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>G</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Jennifer G Dy</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>jdy@ece.neu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6173733062</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000286912</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/14/2015</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>April</FirstName>
<LastName>Gu</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>Z</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>April Z Gu</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>aprilgu@cornell.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6072558778</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000107344</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/14/2015</StartDate>
<EndDate>06/12/2018</EndDate>
<RoleCode>Former Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Northeastern University</Name>
<CityName>BOSTON</CityName>
<ZipCode>021155005</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6173733004</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>360 HUNTINGTON AVE</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[177-500]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
<StateCode>MA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MA07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>001423631</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>NORTHEASTERN UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>001423631</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Northeastern University]]></Name>
<CityName>Boston</CityName>
<StateCode>MA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>021155005</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[360 Huntington Ave]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MA07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>8083</Code>
<Text>Big Data Science &amp;Engineering</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7433</Code>
<Text>CyberInfra Frmwrk 21st (CIF21)</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8083</Code>
<Text>Big Data Science &amp;Engineering</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9251</Code>
<Text>REU SUPP-Res Exp for Ugrd Supp</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0115</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0116</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2015~860648</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2016~16000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>While many disciplines have become increasingly exploratory given that large-scale and multi-sources data collection has become prevalent, we find that volumes of data that were carefully collected and studied to answer project-specific questions, are neglected and unstudied, even if they hold key answers to tomorrow's questions.&nbsp; This project developed novel alternative clustering methods, combined with visualization and acceleration solutions to enable exploration of diverse data sets.</p> <p>Intellectual Merit:&nbsp;</p> <p>We developed interpretable models for machine learning and also focused on challenges of working with real data associated with the NIEHS P42 project, PROTECT, identifying potential environmental contributors to preterm birth.&nbsp;</p> <p>We introduced Interpretable Kernel Dimensionality Reduction (IKDR) algorithms that can find a low dimensional representation of the original data capable of capturing nonlinear relationships, yet easy to interpret. Unfortunately, the IKDR objective requires a non-convex manifold optimization that is difficult to solve and can no longer be solved by eigendecomposition. We developed an efficient iterative spectral (eigendecomposition) method (ISM) for this objective.&nbsp; We provided theoretical guarantees of ISM to an entire family of kernels. &nbsp;We also establish how a wide range of IKDR applications across different learning paradigms (supervised, semi-supervised, unsupervised) can be solved by ISM.</p> <p>Discovering alternative clustering solutions can be cast as an IKDR problem. We developed ISM for solving alternative clustering.&nbsp; We have also provided a GPU implementation of an interactive kernel dimension alternative clustering, enabling exploration of data.</p> <p>Clustering algorithms group similar samples together based on some predefined notion of similarity. One way of representing this similarity is through kernels. However, the choice for an appropriate kernel is data-dependent; as a result, the kernel design process is frequently an art that requires intimate knowledge of the data. A common alternative is to simply use a general-purpose kernel that performs well under various conditions (e.g., polynomial or Gaussian kernels).&nbsp; We developed KernelNet (KNet) clustering, a methodology for learning a kernel and an induced clustering directly from the observed data. In particular, we train a deep kernel by combining a neural network representation with a Gaussian kernel.&nbsp; Intuitively, incorporating a neural network (NN) parameterization to a Gaussian kernel, we are able to learn a flexible deep kernel for clustering, tailored specifically to a given dataset.</p> <p>On the domain side, we have explored applying decision trees that can deal with imbalance class distributions in PROTECT data.&nbsp; We have found promising linkages between preterm birth and the use of pesticides in the home. In addition to class imbalance in our data set. There is also a significant amount of missing data in the data set due to the nature of the collection and the targeted population.&nbsp; We have developed an undersampling strategy combined with emsemble learning to deal with this imbalance to identify factors contributing to preterm birth.&nbsp;</p> <p>In environmental science and ecology, single-cell technologies such as Raman single-cell spectroscopy (SCRS) are emerging technologies for a deeper understanding of microbial ecology at the single-cell level. A major application challenge is the determination of sufficient sample size under the balance between statistical power and limited time or resources. We proposed, tested and validated a computational sampling size assessment protocol taking advantage of a novel metric, we named kernel divergence.</p> <p>Broader Impacts:</p> <p>This project allowed us to mentor and educate five PhD students from three different disciplines (machine learning, high-performance computing, and environmental engineering). In addition, we have trained several undergraduate REU students through this grant. The undergraduates learned about state-of-the-art programming practices and testing protocols, leveraging github and Google test.&nbsp; Everyone became more knowledgeable in machine learning algorithms, as well as parallel programming practices. Our PhD graduate students learned how to mentor and lead large software development projects.&nbsp; We have published papers in quality conferences on both fundamental advances in algorithms, machine learning, environmental science, and biotechnology. The project has potential to improve health outcomes for residents of northern Puerto Rico through our collaboration with PROTECT.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 05/01/2021<br>      Modified by: Jennifer&nbsp;G&nbsp;Dy</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Images (<span id="selectedPhoto0">1</span> of <span class="totalNumber"></span>)           </div> <div class="galControls" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/1546428/1546428_10399311_1619871158568_results1--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/1546428/1546428_10399311_1619871158568_results1--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Iterative Spectral Method for Alternative Clustering"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/1546428/1546428_10399311_1619871158568_results1--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Iterative Spectral Method for Alternative Clustering"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">The images on the left show the original clustering for each data and the alternative clustering for the same data.  On the right we show the results of our Iterative Spectral Method (ISM) against competing approaches.  High NMI shows good match with true solution and CQ means good cluster quality.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Published in AISTATS 2018</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Jennifer&nbsp;G&nbsp;Dy</div> <div class="imageTitle">Iterative Spectral Method for Alternative Clustering</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/1546428/1546428_10399311_1619871977085_results2--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/1546428/1546428_10399311_1619871977085_results2--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Decision Tree Learned for Predicting Preterm Birth"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/1546428/1546428_10399311_1619871977085_results2--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Decision Tree Learned for Predicting Preterm Birth"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Decision Tree that can deal with class imbalance is applied to the PROTECT data.  This is the tree learned evaluating the first and second visit forms. The factors at the top of the tree are the most important factors tied to preterm birth in these forms.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Shi Dong, Northeastern University</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Jennifer&nbsp;G&nbsp;Dy</div> <div class="imageTitle">Decision Tree Learned for Predicting Preterm Birth</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/1546428/1546428_10399311_1619872781739_results3a--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/1546428/1546428_10399311_1619872781739_results3a--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Machine Learning Kernel Divergence-Based de novo Sampling Size Optimization"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/1546428/1546428_10399311_1619872781739_results3a--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Machine Learning Kernel Divergence-Based de novo Sampling Size Optimization"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Kernel divergence (using most significant kernel eigenvalues preserving 96% total) profiled against sampling depth, simulated independently on 8 single-cell Raman spectroscopic (SCRS) microbial phenotyping datasets. The point of convergence (POC) occur at thresholds indicating sufficient sampling.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Guangyu Li, Northeastern University</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Jennifer&nbsp;G&nbsp;Dy</div> <div class="imageTitle">Machine Learning Kernel Divergence-Based de novo Sampling Size Optimization</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ While many disciplines have become increasingly exploratory given that large-scale and multi-sources data collection has become prevalent, we find that volumes of data that were carefully collected and studied to answer project-specific questions, are neglected and unstudied, even if they hold key answers to tomorrow's questions.  This project developed novel alternative clustering methods, combined with visualization and acceleration solutions to enable exploration of diverse data sets.  Intellectual Merit:   We developed interpretable models for machine learning and also focused on challenges of working with real data associated with the NIEHS P42 project, PROTECT, identifying potential environmental contributors to preterm birth.   We introduced Interpretable Kernel Dimensionality Reduction (IKDR) algorithms that can find a low dimensional representation of the original data capable of capturing nonlinear relationships, yet easy to interpret. Unfortunately, the IKDR objective requires a non-convex manifold optimization that is difficult to solve and can no longer be solved by eigendecomposition. We developed an efficient iterative spectral (eigendecomposition) method (ISM) for this objective.  We provided theoretical guarantees of ISM to an entire family of kernels.  We also establish how a wide range of IKDR applications across different learning paradigms (supervised, semi-supervised, unsupervised) can be solved by ISM.  Discovering alternative clustering solutions can be cast as an IKDR problem. We developed ISM for solving alternative clustering.  We have also provided a GPU implementation of an interactive kernel dimension alternative clustering, enabling exploration of data.  Clustering algorithms group similar samples together based on some predefined notion of similarity. One way of representing this similarity is through kernels. However, the choice for an appropriate kernel is data-dependent; as a result, the kernel design process is frequently an art that requires intimate knowledge of the data. A common alternative is to simply use a general-purpose kernel that performs well under various conditions (e.g., polynomial or Gaussian kernels).  We developed KernelNet (KNet) clustering, a methodology for learning a kernel and an induced clustering directly from the observed data. In particular, we train a deep kernel by combining a neural network representation with a Gaussian kernel.  Intuitively, incorporating a neural network (NN) parameterization to a Gaussian kernel, we are able to learn a flexible deep kernel for clustering, tailored specifically to a given dataset.  On the domain side, we have explored applying decision trees that can deal with imbalance class distributions in PROTECT data.  We have found promising linkages between preterm birth and the use of pesticides in the home. In addition to class imbalance in our data set. There is also a significant amount of missing data in the data set due to the nature of the collection and the targeted population.  We have developed an undersampling strategy combined with emsemble learning to deal with this imbalance to identify factors contributing to preterm birth.   In environmental science and ecology, single-cell technologies such as Raman single-cell spectroscopy (SCRS) are emerging technologies for a deeper understanding of microbial ecology at the single-cell level. A major application challenge is the determination of sufficient sample size under the balance between statistical power and limited time or resources. We proposed, tested and validated a computational sampling size assessment protocol taking advantage of a novel metric, we named kernel divergence.  Broader Impacts:  This project allowed us to mentor and educate five PhD students from three different disciplines (machine learning, high-performance computing, and environmental engineering). In addition, we have trained several undergraduate REU students through this grant. The undergraduates learned about state-of-the-art programming practices and testing protocols, leveraging github and Google test.  Everyone became more knowledgeable in machine learning algorithms, as well as parallel programming practices. Our PhD graduate students learned how to mentor and lead large software development projects.  We have published papers in quality conferences on both fundamental advances in algorithms, machine learning, environmental science, and biotechnology. The project has potential to improve health outcomes for residents of northern Puerto Rico through our collaboration with PROTECT.          Last Modified: 05/01/2021       Submitted by: Jennifer G Dy]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
