<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>EAGER: Energy-efficient Massive MIMO Processing for Millimeter-wave Communications</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2015</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>244614.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>244614</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07010000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>ECCS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Electrical, Commun &amp; Cyber Sys</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>akbar sayeed</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Abstract Title: &lt;br/&gt;Energy-efficient Massive MIMO Processing for Millimeter-wave Wireless Communications&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Abstract: &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;To meet the ever-growing demands for high-speed, large-capacity wireless services, millimeter-wave (mmWave) technology has emerged as a promising option for next-generation wireless networks. The mmWave systems operate around and above 30GHz, where the spectrum is less crowded and the available bandwidth is much wider than that of legacy wireless systems at relatively lower radio frequencies. On the other hand, the use of such high frequencies incurs severe channel path loss, which is the dominant factor limiting the coverage and robustness of mmWave communications. A natural opportunity to cope with this problem is to adopt massive multiple-input multiple-output (MIMO) in mmWave transceivers, where very large antenna arrays with hundreds of antenna elements can be packaged in a miniature size to provide large diversity-multiplexing gains and hence significantly improved coverage, throughput and robustness against channel fading. However, as the number of antenna elements increases, not only the signal acquisition and hardware costs increase drastically, but also the computational complexity of traditional antenna array processing techniques becomes prohibitively high. The objective of this research is to provide key technological innovations in large-scale array processing such that massive MIMO can be utilized for high-speed mmWave wireless communications at affordable computational costs. New signal processing techniques will be developed to perform the key sensing tasks of mmWave massive MIMO transceivers, including direction of arrival estimation and channel estimation, in an energy-efficient and robust manner. Solving such computational bottlenecks of massive MIMO is an essential step toward unleashing the well-appreciated potential of mmWave technology, which will make available abundant spectrum opportunities for wireless connectivity in both cellular data services and Internet of things. Another important goal of this project is to integrate research with education in effort to enhance the learning experiences for students in the field of wireless communications. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project aims to develop an innovative compressive sensing framework to tackle the computational bottleneck in two important sensing tasks of MIMO processing: direction-of-arrival estimation for beamforming and spatial sectorization, and channel estimation for data demodulation. While existing research seeks strenuously to find affordable solutions to high-dimensional signal estimation problems over a very large angle or channel space, this project sets forth an exploratory path that gets around this difficulty by exploiting the inherent structures of the sensing tasks to reduce the problem space itself. At the core of this research is a new framework of compressive covariance sparse sensing (CCSS), which bypasses the intermediate step of recovering the original signals whenever possible and directly extracts the useful statistics to effect strong signal compression and efficient feature extraction at low sampling costs. Based on the CCSS framework, new formulations, algorithms and sensing mechanisms will be developed to efficiently solve the direction-of-arrival and channel estimation problems in resource-constrained mmWave massive MIMO systems, with quantified performance and cost tradeoffs.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/31/2015</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/31/2015</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1546604</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Zhi</FirstName>
<LastName>Tian</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Zhi Tian</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>ztian1@gmu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>7039935295</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000244907</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/31/2015</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>George Mason University</Name>
<CityName>FAIRFAX</CityName>
<ZipCode>220304422</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>7039932295</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>4400 UNIVERSITY DR</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Virginia</StateName>
<StateCode>VA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>11</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>VA11</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>077817450</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>GEORGE MASON UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>077817450</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[George Mason University]]></Name>
<CityName>Fairfax</CityName>
<StateCode>VA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>220304444</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[4400 University Drive]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Virginia</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>11</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>VA11</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7564</Code>
<Text>CCSS-Comms Circuits &amp; Sens Sys</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>153E</Code>
<Text>Wireless comm &amp; sig processing</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7916</Code>
<Text>EAGER</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0115</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2015~244614</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Millimeter-wave technology has emerged as a promising option for next-generation wireless networks. It is often deployed together with massive multiple-input multiple-output (MIMO) systems with a few hundred or thousand antennas to improve the link quality and user capacity. This exploratory project develops an innovative compressive sensing framework to tackle the computational bottleneck in two important sensing tasks of massive MIMO processing: direction-of-arrival estimation for beamforming and spatial sectorization, and channel estimation for data demodulation. Recent research progress on massive MIMO systems mostly stands from the communications viewpoint, which relies on traditional grid-based compressive sensing for channel estimation, but suffers from performance degradation caused by the finite grid size and grid mismatch issue. This project takes the array signal processing viewpoint by exploring the angular properties of millimeter-wave propagation channels for various communication system designs.</p> <p>Intellectual merit:</p> <p>The project outcomes include a set of off-grid compressive sensing techniques that can accurately estimate the channel state information within a short sensing time at affordable computational costs, even for large-size, high-dimensional massive MIMO channels. Several major outcomes are highlighted below.</p> <p>The first major outcome is the development of compressive covariance sensing (CCS) for channel estimation in millimeter-wave massive MIMO systems. Different from traditional compressed sensing schemes for linear deterministic systems, CCS is well suited for efficient extraction of useful statistical features from random processes, such as communication signals in the presence of random noise. &nbsp;The CCS-based approach results in efficient channel statistics estimation for massive MIMO, which directly estimates the useful second-order statistics of the channel while bypassing the intermediate recovery of the instantaneous channel matrix itself. The developed technique has low computational complexity and reduced overhead in training and feedback, owing to its proper utilization of the joint sparsity structure of the channel covariance matrix. It offers competitive estimation accuracy with immunity to gridding issues.</p> <p>Second, an off-grid compress sensing framework based on decoupled atomic norm minimization (D-ANM) has been developed for high-dimensional channel estimation for massive MIMO under limited training resources. The D-ANM technique offers super-resolution angle and channel estimation from few training symbols, and can be applied to a broad range of operating conditions to handle high-speed data transmission under frequency selective channels and Doppler effects. Further, a fast algorithm named iterative Vandermonde-decomposition and shrinkage-thresholding (IVDST) is developed, which offers low computational complexity compared with the existing convex optimization based ANM solutions through semi-definite programming. The D-ANM framework, along with the IVDST implementation, offers computational simplicity that is several orders of magnitude lower than the state of the art, which is quite appealing for massive MIMO. Meanwhile, it offers performance advantages when the sensing time is extremely short and the signal sources might be correlated.</p> <p>Third, a new signal detection scheme for non-coherent communications is developed, which can collect all multipath diversity and array gain for reliable data transmission, without having to estimate the channel state information. This scheme is based on the multi-symbol differential detection (MSDD) framework, which outperforms the traditional differential detection. The technical innovation lies in the design of MSDD in the spatial domain for multiple antenna systems. Because it does not rely on channel knowledge, the MSDD scheme can offer competitive symbol detection accuracy compared with a practical coherent detector subject to channel estimation errors.</p> <p>Finally, it is recognized that massive MIMO processing entails large data size and high dimensionality, which invites a data-driven approach to 5G wireless communications. Advanced machine learning techniques are investigated, which suggest possible research directions for cross-pollination between model-based communication technologies and data-driven machine learning techniques for millimeter-wave massive MIMO systems.</p> <p>Broader impacts:</p> <p>This project has introduced the compressive covariance sparse sensing principle to the angular spectrum estimation problems in massive MIMO. An off-grid optimization based approach is also developed that can effectively handle data-starved applications where the number of samples is severely limited due to the short sensing time and large problem dimension. Solving such computational bottlenecks of massive MIMO is an essential step toward unleashing the well-appreciated potential of millimeter-wave technology, which will make available abundant spectrum opportunities for wireless connectivity in both cellular data services and Internet of things.</p> <p>Further, the angular and frequency estimation problems addressed in this project arise in many other important applications such as radar, astronomy, seismic exploration, biomedical imaging and so on. The outcomes of this project could broadly impact these broad applications by offering fast, low-complexity solutions to sensing and feature extraction.</p> <p>This project provides direct training opportunities for PhD students and postdoctoral researchers, who will enter the workforce with well-developed skills in STEM. The knowledge acquired in this project has been conscientiously incorporated into classroom teaching to enhance students&rsquo; learning experience.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 08/08/2018<br>      Modified by: Zhi&nbsp;Tian</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Millimeter-wave technology has emerged as a promising option for next-generation wireless networks. It is often deployed together with massive multiple-input multiple-output (MIMO) systems with a few hundred or thousand antennas to improve the link quality and user capacity. This exploratory project develops an innovative compressive sensing framework to tackle the computational bottleneck in two important sensing tasks of massive MIMO processing: direction-of-arrival estimation for beamforming and spatial sectorization, and channel estimation for data demodulation. Recent research progress on massive MIMO systems mostly stands from the communications viewpoint, which relies on traditional grid-based compressive sensing for channel estimation, but suffers from performance degradation caused by the finite grid size and grid mismatch issue. This project takes the array signal processing viewpoint by exploring the angular properties of millimeter-wave propagation channels for various communication system designs.  Intellectual merit:  The project outcomes include a set of off-grid compressive sensing techniques that can accurately estimate the channel state information within a short sensing time at affordable computational costs, even for large-size, high-dimensional massive MIMO channels. Several major outcomes are highlighted below.  The first major outcome is the development of compressive covariance sensing (CCS) for channel estimation in millimeter-wave massive MIMO systems. Different from traditional compressed sensing schemes for linear deterministic systems, CCS is well suited for efficient extraction of useful statistical features from random processes, such as communication signals in the presence of random noise.  The CCS-based approach results in efficient channel statistics estimation for massive MIMO, which directly estimates the useful second-order statistics of the channel while bypassing the intermediate recovery of the instantaneous channel matrix itself. The developed technique has low computational complexity and reduced overhead in training and feedback, owing to its proper utilization of the joint sparsity structure of the channel covariance matrix. It offers competitive estimation accuracy with immunity to gridding issues.  Second, an off-grid compress sensing framework based on decoupled atomic norm minimization (D-ANM) has been developed for high-dimensional channel estimation for massive MIMO under limited training resources. The D-ANM technique offers super-resolution angle and channel estimation from few training symbols, and can be applied to a broad range of operating conditions to handle high-speed data transmission under frequency selective channels and Doppler effects. Further, a fast algorithm named iterative Vandermonde-decomposition and shrinkage-thresholding (IVDST) is developed, which offers low computational complexity compared with the existing convex optimization based ANM solutions through semi-definite programming. The D-ANM framework, along with the IVDST implementation, offers computational simplicity that is several orders of magnitude lower than the state of the art, which is quite appealing for massive MIMO. Meanwhile, it offers performance advantages when the sensing time is extremely short and the signal sources might be correlated.  Third, a new signal detection scheme for non-coherent communications is developed, which can collect all multipath diversity and array gain for reliable data transmission, without having to estimate the channel state information. This scheme is based on the multi-symbol differential detection (MSDD) framework, which outperforms the traditional differential detection. The technical innovation lies in the design of MSDD in the spatial domain for multiple antenna systems. Because it does not rely on channel knowledge, the MSDD scheme can offer competitive symbol detection accuracy compared with a practical coherent detector subject to channel estimation errors.  Finally, it is recognized that massive MIMO processing entails large data size and high dimensionality, which invites a data-driven approach to 5G wireless communications. Advanced machine learning techniques are investigated, which suggest possible research directions for cross-pollination between model-based communication technologies and data-driven machine learning techniques for millimeter-wave massive MIMO systems.  Broader impacts:  This project has introduced the compressive covariance sparse sensing principle to the angular spectrum estimation problems in massive MIMO. An off-grid optimization based approach is also developed that can effectively handle data-starved applications where the number of samples is severely limited due to the short sensing time and large problem dimension. Solving such computational bottlenecks of massive MIMO is an essential step toward unleashing the well-appreciated potential of millimeter-wave technology, which will make available abundant spectrum opportunities for wireless connectivity in both cellular data services and Internet of things.  Further, the angular and frequency estimation problems addressed in this project arise in many other important applications such as radar, astronomy, seismic exploration, biomedical imaging and so on. The outcomes of this project could broadly impact these broad applications by offering fast, low-complexity solutions to sensing and feature extraction.  This project provides direct training opportunities for PhD students and postdoctoral researchers, who will enter the workforce with well-developed skills in STEM. The knowledge acquired in this project has been conscientiously incorporated into classroom teaching to enhance students? learning experience.       Last Modified: 08/08/2018       Submitted by: Zhi Tian]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
