<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Core Support for the National Academy of Sciences' Board on Chemical Sciences and Technology (BCST) and Chemical Sciences Roundtable (CSR)</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2015</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>983154.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>983154</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03090000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CHE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Chemistry</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Michelle Bushey</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>mbushey@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924938</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The Divisions of Chemistry (CHE) and Chemical, Bioengineering, Environmental and Transport Systems (CBET) fund this award to the National Academy of Sciences to support the core activities of both the Board on Chemical Sciences and Technology (BCST) and the Chemical Sciences Roundtable (CSR). The results of BCST and CSR discussions and workshops are disseminated through workshop reports made available through professional societies, scientific and trade publications, and on the web.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The BCST has broad representation from academe and industry and uses its collective expertise to identify the needs of the community and to provide peer-reviewed consensus reports, workshops, and symposia, as broad outreach into the chemical community and beyond. The BCST enhances the impacts of the chemistry and chemical engineering communities by engaging in questions of importance to federal decision-makers. BCST members oversee a portfolio of ad hoc studies in three key areas of education, workforce, and research issues.  Specific areas of consideration include: energy and sustainability, safety, and security. By raising issues impacting the conduct of chemistry and chemical engineering research with federal officials, BCST helps assure that the community of practitioners can remain at the forefront of knowledge. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The CSR provides an apolitical forum for leaders in the chemical sciences and engineering, with the objective of enhancing understanding of issues that affect government, academic, national laboratory, and nonprofit sectors. CSR discussions provide a vehicle for interaction among the participants, and for education, exchange of information, and discussion of issues and trends that affect the chemical sciences. CSR engages leading scientists and engineers to identify and explore, through workshops, emerging topics of importance to the community of practitioners and beyond.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/24/2015</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/20/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1546732</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Teresa</FirstName>
<LastName>Fryberger</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Teresa Fryberger</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>tfryberger@nas.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2023342075</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000659893</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/24/2015</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>National Academy of Sciences</Name>
<CityName>Washington</CityName>
<ZipCode>200012721</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2023342254</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>500 FIFTH STREET NW</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>District of Columbia</StateName>
<StateCode>DC</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>00</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>DC00</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>041964057</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>NATIONAL ACADEMY OF SCIENCES</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>041964057</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[National Academy of Sciences]]></Name>
<CityName>washington</CityName>
<StateCode>DC</StateCode>
<ZipCode>200012736</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>District of Columbia</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>00</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>DC00</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1978</Code>
<Text>PROJECTS</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7909</Code>
<Text>BIOSENS-Biosensing</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1978</Code>
<Text>PROJECTS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7556</Code>
<Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7909</Code>
<Text>BIOSENSING</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0115</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0116</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2015~614472</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2016~368682</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The Board on Chemical Sciences and Technology (BCST) is the focal point within the National Academies of Sciences, Engineering, and Medicine for chemical sciences and engineering. The board explores the science, policies, and infrastructure needed to support the health of the chemical and chemical engineering disciplines and their impacts on society. The board exercises leadership within the chemical sciences/engineering communities by helping to identify and communicate the needs for the field, responds to specific requests for advice and information from government agencies and Congress, and oversees a variety of study projects related to the chemical sciences/engineering. Because chemistry is vital to a broad range of issues, the board provides guidance to many different agencies, including a longstanding engagement with the NSF&rsquo;s Division of Chemistry and Division of Chemical, Bioengineering, Environmental and Transport Systems.</p> <p>BCST has three primary mechanisms to accomplish its mission. The first is the board itself; biannual board meetings provide an important venue for high level, strategic dialogues among leading members of the science and engineering communities and also with the federal agencies engaged in the chemical sciences and engineering. The second mechanism is the ad hoc committee process, in which specially appointed groups conduct in-depth analysis of focused topics. Ad hoc studies are separately funded, but cannot take place without board involvement in design, member selection, and oversight. In the last 3 years, BCST completed 9&nbsp;<em>ad hoc</em>&nbsp;studies and activities on topics ranging from access to chemicals used in improvised explosive devices to synthetic biology to communicating chemistry in informal environments. The third mechanism is the<em>&nbsp;Chemical Sciences Roundtable</em>, which is a complementary venue for the science community (the subject of a separate Outcomes Report).</p> <p>BCST&rsquo;s board members are integral to BCST accomplishing its mission. Board members are responsible for identifying emerging and important issues, strategic planning for new initiatives, information gathering, interactions with agencies and other scientists, program oversight, information dissemination, and outreach. Over the period from 2015-2018, the board explored a broad range of topics at its meetings, examples include:</p> <ul> <li>Issues in chemical education/workforce;</li> <li>Marine plastic debris: chemical aspects;</li> <li>Environmental dynamics of subsurface contaminants;</li> <li>Data science for chemistry and chemical engineering;</li> <li>Preprint servers for chemists;</li> <li>Entrepreneurship in chemistry and chemical engineering;</li> <li>Nontraditional careers;</li> <li>Chem/bio defense: advances in chemical sensing;</li> <li>Separations for sustainable manufacturing;</li> <li>Molecules in motion: dynamic measurement using ultrafast X-rays.</li> </ul> <p>Below is a listing of the studies and activities conducted by the BCST from 2015-2018 (these reports are available for free download at&nbsp;<a href="http://www.dels.nas.edu/bcst/Reports-Academies-Findings">http://www.dels.nas.edu/bcst/Reports-Academies-Findings</a>):</p> <ul> <li>Negative Emissions Technologies and Reliable Sequestration: A Research Agenda (2018)</li> <li>Gaseous Carbon Waste Streams Utilization: Status and Research Needs (2018)</li> <li>Biodefense in the Age of Synthetic Biology (2018)</li> <li>Reducing the Threat of Improvised Explosive Device Attacks by Restricting Access to Explosive Precursor Chemicals (2017)</li> <li>A Proposed Framework for Identifying Potential Biodefense Vulnerabilities Posed by Synthetic Biology: Interim Report (2017)</li> <li>Preparing for Future Products of Biotechnology (2017)</li> <li>Communicating Chemistry: A Framework for Sharing Science:&nbsp; A Practical Evidence-Based Guide (2016)</li> <li>Chemical Laboratory Safety and Security: A Guide to Developing Standard Operating Procedures (2016)</li> <li>Effective Chemistry Communication in Informal Environments (2016)</li> <li>Spills of Diluted Bitumen from Pipelines: A Comparative Study of Environmental Fate, Effects, and Response (2015)</li> </ul> <p>The consensus studies that BCST oversees provide answers and recommendations to federal decision makers on topics of national importance related to chemistry and chemical engineering. BCST studies have had wide ranging impacts within the science community: they have provided scientific direction for federal research programs, have communicated information to researchers about research gaps and opportunities, have provided guidelines for the practice of chemistry, and have addressed workforce issues. BCST studies have also had far-reaching influence beyond the field of chemistry, such as education, public policy, regulations, public safety, and defense.</p> <p>The results of BCST studies are disseminated to the chemistry and chemical engineering communities, policy and decision makers, and the broader public, enhancing awareness of issues that impact the conduct of research and improving scientific and technological understanding of issues of national concern. BCST serves as an important and unique bridge between the science and engineering communities and the federal sector. More information about the BCST and its current activities can be found at&nbsp;<a href="http://dels.nas.edu/bcst">http://dels.nas.edu/bcst</a>.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 11/15/2018<br>      Modified by: Teresa&nbsp;Fryberger</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The Board on Chemical Sciences and Technology (BCST) is the focal point within the National Academies of Sciences, Engineering, and Medicine for chemical sciences and engineering. The board explores the science, policies, and infrastructure needed to support the health of the chemical and chemical engineering disciplines and their impacts on society. The board exercises leadership within the chemical sciences/engineering communities by helping to identify and communicate the needs for the field, responds to specific requests for advice and information from government agencies and Congress, and oversees a variety of study projects related to the chemical sciences/engineering. Because chemistry is vital to a broad range of issues, the board provides guidance to many different agencies, including a longstanding engagement with the NSF?s Division of Chemistry and Division of Chemical, Bioengineering, Environmental and Transport Systems.  BCST has three primary mechanisms to accomplish its mission. The first is the board itself; biannual board meetings provide an important venue for high level, strategic dialogues among leading members of the science and engineering communities and also with the federal agencies engaged in the chemical sciences and engineering. The second mechanism is the ad hoc committee process, in which specially appointed groups conduct in-depth analysis of focused topics. Ad hoc studies are separately funded, but cannot take place without board involvement in design, member selection, and oversight. In the last 3 years, BCST completed 9 ad hoc studies and activities on topics ranging from access to chemicals used in improvised explosive devices to synthetic biology to communicating chemistry in informal environments. The third mechanism is the Chemical Sciences Roundtable, which is a complementary venue for the science community (the subject of a separate Outcomes Report).  BCST?s board members are integral to BCST accomplishing its mission. Board members are responsible for identifying emerging and important issues, strategic planning for new initiatives, information gathering, interactions with agencies and other scientists, program oversight, information dissemination, and outreach. Over the period from 2015-2018, the board explored a broad range of topics at its meetings, examples include:  Issues in chemical education/workforce; Marine plastic debris: chemical aspects; Environmental dynamics of subsurface contaminants; Data science for chemistry and chemical engineering; Preprint servers for chemists; Entrepreneurship in chemistry and chemical engineering; Nontraditional careers; Chem/bio defense: advances in chemical sensing; Separations for sustainable manufacturing; Molecules in motion: dynamic measurement using ultrafast X-rays.   Below is a listing of the studies and activities conducted by the BCST from 2015-2018 (these reports are available for free download at http://www.dels.nas.edu/bcst/Reports-Academies-Findings):  Negative Emissions Technologies and Reliable Sequestration: A Research Agenda (2018) Gaseous Carbon Waste Streams Utilization: Status and Research Needs (2018) Biodefense in the Age of Synthetic Biology (2018) Reducing the Threat of Improvised Explosive Device Attacks by Restricting Access to Explosive Precursor Chemicals (2017) A Proposed Framework for Identifying Potential Biodefense Vulnerabilities Posed by Synthetic Biology: Interim Report (2017) Preparing for Future Products of Biotechnology (2017) Communicating Chemistry: A Framework for Sharing Science:  A Practical Evidence-Based Guide (2016) Chemical Laboratory Safety and Security: A Guide to Developing Standard Operating Procedures (2016) Effective Chemistry Communication in Informal Environments (2016) Spills of Diluted Bitumen from Pipelines: A Comparative Study of Environmental Fate, Effects, and Response (2015)   The consensus studies that BCST oversees provide answers and recommendations to federal decision makers on topics of national importance related to chemistry and chemical engineering. BCST studies have had wide ranging impacts within the science community: they have provided scientific direction for federal research programs, have communicated information to researchers about research gaps and opportunities, have provided guidelines for the practice of chemistry, and have addressed workforce issues. BCST studies have also had far-reaching influence beyond the field of chemistry, such as education, public policy, regulations, public safety, and defense.  The results of BCST studies are disseminated to the chemistry and chemical engineering communities, policy and decision makers, and the broader public, enhancing awareness of issues that impact the conduct of research and improving scientific and technological understanding of issues of national concern. BCST serves as an important and unique bridge between the science and engineering communities and the federal sector. More information about the BCST and its current activities can be found at http://dels.nas.edu/bcst.          Last Modified: 11/15/2018       Submitted by: Teresa Fryberger]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
