<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>I-Corps L:  Interactive Stem Cell Demonstration Activity</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/15/2015</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2016</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>50000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>50000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>11040200</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>EHR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DUE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Undergraduate Education</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Karen Crosby</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Through the NSF Innovation Corps for Learning Program (I-Corps L), this project will develop ways to increase the scale and impact of interactive activity to help high school students and the general public understand the foundational principles of stem cell biology.  The project focusing on stem cells is an interactive activity and demonstration developed to educate the public about key principles of stem cell biology and stem cell research. As stem cell research advances, there is a critical need to develop a solid foundational understanding of stem cells in both the next generation of scientists and the general public. Currently, there is a lack of interactive engaging activities and demonstrations available for use in the classroom to engage students on the topic. Most materials are limited to static presentations or non-interactive videos. This stem cell activity is unique in that the students begin to understand key concepts while engaging in an interactive activity. A prototype has been tested in high school biology classrooms and science festivals, with very positive results. Students involved are engaged throughout the interactive demonstration, rather than merely receiving information passively.  The activity improves students' understanding of what stem cells are and the challenges of stem cell research. This I-Corps for Learning project will develop approaches to enable this engaging activity to be easily implemented by other educators throughout the country.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The basic biological principles taught though this activity and apparatus include self-renewal, pluripotency, and differentiation. Additionally, students learn about growth factors and inhibitors through the use of the available tools to guide their pluripotent stem cell down the desired path. The equipment is currently available in two different sizes. A table-top sized unit is available for teachers to use in a classroom setting. A larger board version provides a tool for STEM outreach volunteers and STEM advocates to use when participating in STEM outreach events. Through I-Corps L, implementation in public school systems and STEM outreach organizations will be expanded with the goal of achieving broader impact in a sustainable manner.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/05/2015</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/05/2015</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.076</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1547768</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Robert</FirstName>
<LastName>Nerem</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Robert Nerem</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>robert.nerem@ibb.gatech.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>4048942768</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000303405</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/05/2015</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Georgia Tech Research Corporation</Name>
<CityName>Atlanta</CityName>
<ZipCode>303320420</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>4048944819</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>Office of Sponsored Programs</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Georgia</StateName>
<StateCode>GA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>GA05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>097394084</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>GEORGIA TECH RESEARCH CORPORATION</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>097394084</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Georgia Tech Research Corporation]]></Name>
<CityName>Atlanta</CityName>
<StateCode>GA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>303320420</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[505 10th Street]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Georgia</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>GA05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1998</Code>
<Text>IUSE</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>007Z</Code>
<Text>I-Corps for Learning</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7914</Code>
<Text>RAPID</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0415</Code>
<Name>NSF Education &amp; Human Resource</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040106</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2015~50000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>During the 2015 cohort of NSF <em>I-Corps for Learning</em> program in Washington D.C., a Georgia Tech team explored the scalability of a stem cell demonstration activity, Stem Cell Plinko.&nbsp; The team consisted of the Principal Investigator-Robert Nerem, Business Mentor-Stephen Renda, Entrepreneurial Lead-Katy Lassahn, and team members-Tom Bongiorno, Jessica Butts and Liane Tellier. Over the course of 6 weeks the team interviewed over a hundred potential stakeholders or customers, including K-12 teachers, school administrators, science center directors, museum directors (including the Smithsonian), and parents from across America.</p> <p>One of the major conclusions taken away from the interviews with K-12 teachers and administrators was the lack of need/demand/money in public schools for educational tools on topics not found in the &ldquo;standards.&rdquo; This finding led us to pivot from our original target market of high school biology classrooms and look into creating a stem cell science exhibit for museums. There did appear to be a need here; however, the structure of the museum exhibit industry is not scalable nor sustainable since it is a very individualized process &ndash; with each museum making decisions based on its mission and funding. When we were exposed to the science camp industry through the interview process, we found both a demand and need that is scalable and sustainable for activities like our stem cell demonstration. When the summer with I-Corps ended, the team had concluded that we would pivot again and begin exploring the possibility of creating a BioSTEM curriculum for summer camps.</p> <p>The major goal of the next project was to develop a successful business strategy that exposes middle school aged students to STEM. Middle school students were chosen as the target student range in order to have an early impact on the students&rsquo; STEM interest. In the middle school age group, we also found demand for STEM concepts that lie outside of the school curriculum, with relatively little competition in our topic area. Through investing time in the next generation of students, we hope not only to increase the number of students going into STEM careers, but also to improve students&rsquo; performance in high school classes. By giving students context into why they need to learn physics or chemistry, the students will have greater motivation to do well in these classes in high school.</p> <p>The business strategy we determined to be the most sustainable was a non-profit that conducted week-long camps at a competitive market rate to cover expenses, while also funding work to offer programs in schools or community centers at no cost. The over-arching goal is to immerse middle school students in bioengineering principles and to encourage them to consider related careers. BioIgnite, Inc. was formed in February 2016 and received its 501c3 approval from the IRS in March 2016. During the spring of 2016 the curriculum developers spent over 200 hours developing a novel, interactive, and high quality curriculum about topics including Regenerative Medicine, Biomedical Imaging, NeuroEngineering, Genetic Engineering, and Medical Device Design. The curriculum was tested at camps hosted by Georgia Tech&rsquo;s Center for Education Integrating Science, Math and Computing (CEISMC) and improved before running a total of three week-long camps in the summer of 2016 in the metro Atlanta area.</p> <p>BioIgnite&rsquo;s business model requires the vicinity of a university with a Biomedical Engineering graduate program. BioIgnite forms relationships with graduate student groups to recruit teachers. BioIgnite utilizes PhD students as the expert teachers of the curriculum. This strategy was determined to be scalable for ensuring high quality teachers for the students. There is an additional benefit to the PhD student&rsquo;s university as graduate students gain valuable pedagogical training to improving their teaching and presentation skills while also understanding the importance of community outreach.</p> <p>BioIgnite will double the summer camp offerings in 2017 in addition to hosting multiple Saturday camps for students throughout the school year. In the future, BioIgnite also hopes to use the scalable business model they have formed in Atlanta to re-create similar camp set-ups in other cities that have established biomedical engineering graduate programs. The money awarded by the NSF I-Corps program and the rigorous entrepreneurship program were critical for the establishment and success of BioIgnite.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 02/08/2017<br>      Modified by: Robert&nbsp;Nerem</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ During the 2015 cohort of NSF I-Corps for Learning program in Washington D.C., a Georgia Tech team explored the scalability of a stem cell demonstration activity, Stem Cell Plinko.  The team consisted of the Principal Investigator-Robert Nerem, Business Mentor-Stephen Renda, Entrepreneurial Lead-Katy Lassahn, and team members-Tom Bongiorno, Jessica Butts and Liane Tellier. Over the course of 6 weeks the team interviewed over a hundred potential stakeholders or customers, including K-12 teachers, school administrators, science center directors, museum directors (including the Smithsonian), and parents from across America.  One of the major conclusions taken away from the interviews with K-12 teachers and administrators was the lack of need/demand/money in public schools for educational tools on topics not found in the "standards." This finding led us to pivot from our original target market of high school biology classrooms and look into creating a stem cell science exhibit for museums. There did appear to be a need here; however, the structure of the museum exhibit industry is not scalable nor sustainable since it is a very individualized process &ndash; with each museum making decisions based on its mission and funding. When we were exposed to the science camp industry through the interview process, we found both a demand and need that is scalable and sustainable for activities like our stem cell demonstration. When the summer with I-Corps ended, the team had concluded that we would pivot again and begin exploring the possibility of creating a BioSTEM curriculum for summer camps.  The major goal of the next project was to develop a successful business strategy that exposes middle school aged students to STEM. Middle school students were chosen as the target student range in order to have an early impact on the students? STEM interest. In the middle school age group, we also found demand for STEM concepts that lie outside of the school curriculum, with relatively little competition in our topic area. Through investing time in the next generation of students, we hope not only to increase the number of students going into STEM careers, but also to improve students? performance in high school classes. By giving students context into why they need to learn physics or chemistry, the students will have greater motivation to do well in these classes in high school.  The business strategy we determined to be the most sustainable was a non-profit that conducted week-long camps at a competitive market rate to cover expenses, while also funding work to offer programs in schools or community centers at no cost. The over-arching goal is to immerse middle school students in bioengineering principles and to encourage them to consider related careers. BioIgnite, Inc. was formed in February 2016 and received its 501c3 approval from the IRS in March 2016. During the spring of 2016 the curriculum developers spent over 200 hours developing a novel, interactive, and high quality curriculum about topics including Regenerative Medicine, Biomedical Imaging, NeuroEngineering, Genetic Engineering, and Medical Device Design. The curriculum was tested at camps hosted by Georgia Tech?s Center for Education Integrating Science, Math and Computing (CEISMC) and improved before running a total of three week-long camps in the summer of 2016 in the metro Atlanta area.  BioIgnite?s business model requires the vicinity of a university with a Biomedical Engineering graduate program. BioIgnite forms relationships with graduate student groups to recruit teachers. BioIgnite utilizes PhD students as the expert teachers of the curriculum. This strategy was determined to be scalable for ensuring high quality teachers for the students. There is an additional benefit to the PhD student?s university as graduate students gain valuable pedagogical training to improving their teaching and presentation skills while also understanding the importance of community outreach.  BioIgnite will double the summer camp offerings in 2017 in addition to hosting multiple Saturday camps for students throughout the school year. In the future, BioIgnite also hopes to use the scalable business model they have formed in Atlanta to re-create similar camp set-ups in other cities that have established biomedical engineering graduate programs. The money awarded by the NSF I-Corps program and the rigorous entrepreneurship program were critical for the establishment and success of BioIgnite.       Last Modified: 02/08/2017       Submitted by: Robert Nerem]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
