<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Upgrades to Shock Wave Laboratory for Research in High-Pressure Earth Science</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>04/15/2016</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>136103.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>136103</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>06030202</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>GEO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>EAR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Earth Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>David Lambert</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>dlambert@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924736</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The Caltech shock-wave laboratory is the only US university-based laboratory dedicated to studying deep Earth geophysical problems with shock waves. This proposal is to maintain equipment for safe operation of the shock-wave laboratory at Caltech.  The data are applied to problems across a wide range of disciplines in geophysics, materials science and planetary science.  The laboratory has trained numerous graduate and undergraduate students, and visitors who have gone on to establish experimental geophysics programs around the world. Outreach activities include hosting numerous Earth science and astronomy-related television programs filming in the lab. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The shock-wave facility is used to obtain equation-of-state behavior of model melts at pressures and temperatures of the lower mantle of the Earth. The ultimate goal is development of accurate models of phase equilibria and physical properties of simplified mantle and core compositions that can be compared to geophysical observables or inserted into dynamic models of phenomena like magma evolution, plume ascent, dynamo generation, and inner core growth.&lt;br/&gt;</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>03/22/2016</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/12/2019</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.050</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1547575</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Paul</FirstName>
<LastName>Asimow</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>D</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Paul D Asimow</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>asimow@gps.caltech.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6263956111</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000444327</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>03/22/2016</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>California Institute of Technology</Name>
<CityName>PASADENA</CityName>
<ZipCode>911250600</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6263956219</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1200 E California Blvd</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[Mail Code 273-6]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>27</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CA27</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>009584210</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>CALIFORNIA INSTITUTE OF TECHNOLOGY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>009584210</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[California Institute of Technology]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>911250001</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>27</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CA27</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1580</Code>
<Text>Instrumentation &amp; Facilities</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0116</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2016~136103</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>This award from the NSF Geosciences Instrumentation and Facilities program was used to purchase several items of equipment to maintain and upgrade operations in the Caltech Lindhurst Laboratory for Experimental Geophysics. This lab uses several large gunpowder-driven launchers to create powerful shock waves and then study the results. Our research includes planetary impacts (understanding craters and their consequences on Earth and other planets), shock metamorphism (understanding the record in meteorites of collisions between asteroids), deep planetary interior studies (measuring melting points, densities, wave speeds, and other properties of minerals throughout the mantle and core of the Earth or other terrestrial planets), materials technology (synthesizing or testing new materials and composites using shock processing), and more. Each of the equipment items purchased with this award contributes to one or more of these research areas.</p> <p>Specifically, this award supported the purchase of four equipment items and a laboratory upgrade. The four equipment items and the outcomes associated with them are;</p> <p>(1) A new central breech for our two-stage light gas gun. The two-stage gun achieves projectile velocities up to 7.6 km/s, suifficient to generate pressures of millions of atmospheres upon impact, using compressed hydrogen to store and then relay the energy of the gunpowder detonation. The central breech is the coupling between the two chambers of the gun, where the compressed hydrogen accumulates until it breaks a valve and then expands into the second-stage barrel to launch the projectile. This piece has a lifetime of around 100 experiments, which is about four to six years of operations. So, this item supports all of our high-pressure science for several years to come.</p> <p>(2) A two-color infrared pyrometer. This non-contact device measures temperatures between 475 &deg;C and 1500 *C by looking at the relative brightness of light emitted by the object at two diferent wavelengths (the ratios of different colors in light emiited by hot objects is a well-known function of temperature). This items was needed to enable reliable temperature measurements at lower temperature than our previous pyrometer. We use it for experiments where we preheat glass to just above its glass transition temperature. At this condition, the material becomes a supercooled liquid and can be used to study the high-pressure behavior of liquid without extra complexity associated with glassy starting materials ... but it remains viscous enough that it does not flow out of the sample chamber and so a window is not required to keep it in place. The temperature range where this works is only a few tens of degrees, so an accurate and precise way to measured and control the preheat temperature was needed. We have now done several of these experiments and used them to increase significantly the precision with which we know the density of certain magma compositions at very high pressure, and therefore how the early Earth might have evolved from its very hot, probably fully molten state to the solid mantle we observe today.</p> <p>(3) and (4) A pulsed light source and a calibrated standard lamp. Both of these are related to making the highest quality possible measurements of the temperature of samples undergoing shock compression and heating. Shocked materials radiate light, and collecting that light at various wavelengths can tell us the temperature, which is turns tells us about the thermodynamic properties of a material such as its heat capacity. Making such temperature measurements well requires using the same instrument to observe a standard light source whose brightness at each wavelength is precisely and accurately known. The National Institute of Standards offers such calibrated light sources, so we purchased one and had it calibrated for us. The pulsed light source addresses the problem of characterizing whether the instrument, when calibrated with a steady source of light but applied to measuring a transient light source, still yields the correct temperature. With this combination of calibration tools, we now claim our measured temperatures in the range of several thousand K are accurate to tens of K.</p> <p>Finally, in order to fire our guns and make high-quality measurements, the target chambers must be pumped down to good vacuum. This is a large volume to pump and with our old pump and plumbing system it was quite slow to pump down, introducing several hours delay (sometimes overnight) to our experimental operations. We used the balance of funds in this award to set up a fabrication account that partly offset the cost of rebuilding our vacuum system with larger-bore plumbing, fewer right-angle bends, new large-orifice valves, and a bigger blower. This new system pumps down much faster and reaches a better ultimate vacuum, allowing us to shoot more often and with higher quality data and higher initial preheat temperatures. Again, this expenditure contributes to all our work in the lab.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 01/05/2020<br>      Modified by: Paul&nbsp;D&nbsp;Asimow</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ This award from the NSF Geosciences Instrumentation and Facilities program was used to purchase several items of equipment to maintain and upgrade operations in the Caltech Lindhurst Laboratory for Experimental Geophysics. This lab uses several large gunpowder-driven launchers to create powerful shock waves and then study the results. Our research includes planetary impacts (understanding craters and their consequences on Earth and other planets), shock metamorphism (understanding the record in meteorites of collisions between asteroids), deep planetary interior studies (measuring melting points, densities, wave speeds, and other properties of minerals throughout the mantle and core of the Earth or other terrestrial planets), materials technology (synthesizing or testing new materials and composites using shock processing), and more. Each of the equipment items purchased with this award contributes to one or more of these research areas.  Specifically, this award supported the purchase of four equipment items and a laboratory upgrade. The four equipment items and the outcomes associated with them are;  (1) A new central breech for our two-stage light gas gun. The two-stage gun achieves projectile velocities up to 7.6 km/s, suifficient to generate pressures of millions of atmospheres upon impact, using compressed hydrogen to store and then relay the energy of the gunpowder detonation. The central breech is the coupling between the two chambers of the gun, where the compressed hydrogen accumulates until it breaks a valve and then expands into the second-stage barrel to launch the projectile. This piece has a lifetime of around 100 experiments, which is about four to six years of operations. So, this item supports all of our high-pressure science for several years to come.  (2) A two-color infrared pyrometer. This non-contact device measures temperatures between 475 &deg;C and 1500 *C by looking at the relative brightness of light emitted by the object at two diferent wavelengths (the ratios of different colors in light emiited by hot objects is a well-known function of temperature). This items was needed to enable reliable temperature measurements at lower temperature than our previous pyrometer. We use it for experiments where we preheat glass to just above its glass transition temperature. At this condition, the material becomes a supercooled liquid and can be used to study the high-pressure behavior of liquid without extra complexity associated with glassy starting materials ... but it remains viscous enough that it does not flow out of the sample chamber and so a window is not required to keep it in place. The temperature range where this works is only a few tens of degrees, so an accurate and precise way to measured and control the preheat temperature was needed. We have now done several of these experiments and used them to increase significantly the precision with which we know the density of certain magma compositions at very high pressure, and therefore how the early Earth might have evolved from its very hot, probably fully molten state to the solid mantle we observe today.  (3) and (4) A pulsed light source and a calibrated standard lamp. Both of these are related to making the highest quality possible measurements of the temperature of samples undergoing shock compression and heating. Shocked materials radiate light, and collecting that light at various wavelengths can tell us the temperature, which is turns tells us about the thermodynamic properties of a material such as its heat capacity. Making such temperature measurements well requires using the same instrument to observe a standard light source whose brightness at each wavelength is precisely and accurately known. The National Institute of Standards offers such calibrated light sources, so we purchased one and had it calibrated for us. The pulsed light source addresses the problem of characterizing whether the instrument, when calibrated with a steady source of light but applied to measuring a transient light source, still yields the correct temperature. With this combination of calibration tools, we now claim our measured temperatures in the range of several thousand K are accurate to tens of K.  Finally, in order to fire our guns and make high-quality measurements, the target chambers must be pumped down to good vacuum. This is a large volume to pump and with our old pump and plumbing system it was quite slow to pump down, introducing several hours delay (sometimes overnight) to our experimental operations. We used the balance of funds in this award to set up a fabrication account that partly offset the cost of rebuilding our vacuum system with larger-bore plumbing, fewer right-angle bends, new large-orifice valves, and a bigger blower. This new system pumps down much faster and reaches a better ultimate vacuum, allowing us to shoot more often and with higher quality data and higher initial preheat temperatures. Again, this expenditure contributes to all our work in the lab.       Last Modified: 01/05/2020       Submitted by: Paul D Asimow]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
