<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Constraining lowermost mantle flow through observations and models of seismic anisotropy</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>06/01/2016</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2020</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>269934.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>269934</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>06030204</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>GEO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>EAR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Earth Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Robin Reichlin</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>rreichli@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032928556</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The core-mantle boundary (CMB) is the most dramatic physical boundary within the Earth's interior. The CMB is the interface between the rocky, convecting mantle and the liquid iron outer core, whose motions give rise to the Earth's magnetic field. The major contrasts in composition, density, viscosity, and temperature across the CMB region mean that this interface plays a critical role in controlling the dynamics and evolution of the Earth's interior. Specifically, the CMB represents the bottom boundary layer for mantle convection, the process through which the Earth cools off over geologic time as relatively hot material rises and relatively cool material sinks. A major unsolved problem is what the pattern of mantle convection looks like just above the CMB, and how that pattern interacts with convective motions in the rest of the mantle and their surface expressions in plate tectonic features such as subduction zones. The goal of this project is to use observations of seismic waves that have passed through the lowermost mantle to constrain the pattern of mantle flow just above the CMB.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project involves a three-year effort to study seismic anisotropy and flow patterns at the base of the mantle via observations and modeling. Because of the causative link between deformation and seismic anisotropy, the characterization and interpretation of anisotropy can provide crucial constraints on flow patterns in the mantle. While seismic anisotropy is commonly studied in the upper mantle, it is much more difficult to isolate the signal from lowermost mantle anisotropy; furthermore, major uncertainties remain about the relationships between strain and anisotropy in lowermost mantle minerals. Despite the challenges inherent in studying D" anisotropy, however, it holds exceptional promise as a tool for deciphering patterns of flow at the base of the mantle and understanding the processes that drive these patterns. This project addresses two fundamental unsolved problems related to the structure and dynamics of the lowermost mantle: 1) What is the geometry of seismic anisotropy in the D" layer? and 2) What is the pattern of flow in the lowermost mantle, and what physical processes drive this flow? In order to address these science questions, the investigator proposes to carry out five activities. First, the team will carry out differential shear wave splitting observations of S-ScS and SKS-SKKS phases to constrain splitting due to anisotropy at the base of the mantle in selected regions over a range of ray propagation directions. Second, they will carry out array analysis of phases that have been reflected off the D" discontinuity (PdP and SdS); the polarities of these phases are affected by D" anisotropy and in combination with shear wave splitting measurements can more tightly constrain the anisotropic geometry. Third, they will apply a mineral physics-based forward modeling framework that uses single-crystal elasticity to identify plausible anisotropic geometries that are consistent with seismic observations. Fourth, they will use these observations of anisotropy to test the predictions of global models for flow and elasticity at the base of the mantle. Finally, they will integrate results from all phases of the project to test the predictions made by a set of hypotheses about the driving forces for flow at the base of the mantle. Broader impacts of this work include the training of a graduate student, the cultivation of international collaborations, the creation of a website on deep Earth processes aimed at the general public, and the dissemination of the results in both scientific publications and public education and outreach presentations.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>12/07/2015</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/16/2017</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.050</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1547499</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Maureen</FirstName>
<LastName>Long</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>D</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Maureen D Long</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>maureen.long@yale.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2034325031</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000505563</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>12/07/2015</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Yale University</Name>
<CityName>New Haven</CityName>
<ZipCode>065208327</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2037854689</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>Office of Sponsored Projects</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[P.O. Box 208327]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Connecticut</StateName>
<StateCode>CT</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CT03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>043207562</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>YALE UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>043207562</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Yale University]]></Name>
<CityName>New Haven</CityName>
<StateCode>CT</StateCode>
<ZipCode>065118902</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[210 Whitney Ave.]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Connecticut</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CT03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1574</Code>
<Text>Geophysics</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7222</Code>
<Text>XC-Crosscutting Activities Pro</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1031</Code>
<Text>STUDIES OF THE EARTH'S DEEP INTERIOR</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0116</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0117</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2016~101619</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2017~168315</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><span>The core-mantle boundary (CMB) is the most dramatic physical boundary of within the Earth's interior. The CMB is the interface between the rocky, convecting mantle and the liquid iron outer core. A major unsolved problem is what the pattern of mantle convection looks like just above the CMB, and how that flow pattern interacts with convective motions in the rest of the mantle and their surface expressions in plate tectonic features. The overarching goal of this project was to use observations of seismic waves that have passed through the lowermost mantle to constrain the pattern of mantle flow just above the CMB.</span></p> <p><span>In order to accomplish this goal, we carried out a number of individual studies that either presented new observations of seismic anisotropy (that is, the directional dependence of seismic wave speed) from the base of the mantle, carried out new synthetic modeling work aimed at understanding how seismic anisotropy manifests itself in seismic waves, or executed studies that combined inferences from both seismology and mineral physics to understand anisotropy. In the first category, we published papers that probed seismic anisotropy at the base of the mantle in a number of regions of the Earth, including beneath Australia and New Zealand (Creasy et al., 2017), the eastern Pacific Ocean (Deng et al., 2017), Africa (Reiss et al., 2019), Iceland (Wolf et al., 2019), and North America (Lutz et al., 2020). In the second category, we developed a new technique for modeling wave propagation through anisotropic media and applied it to study anisotropy at the base of the mantle (Tesoniero et al., 2020) and investigated what kind of seismic data sets are necessary to fully constrain lowermost mantle anisotropy (Creasy et al., 2019). In the third category, we collaborated with a mineral physicist to develop a library of models for the elastic properties of the lowermost mantle (Creasy et al., 2020), and developed a model for anisotropy and mantle flow beneath Siberia that demonstrates that the remnants of subducted slabs at the base of the mantle are likely driving flow to the southwest, towards the Perm Anomaly (Creasy et al., in preparation). Our project has showed that structures at the base of the mantle known as Large Low Shear Velocity Provinces (LLSVPs) often have strong anisotropy at their edges, helping to constriain models for their formation and evolution. We have developed and applied new observational strategies that allow us to measure seismic anisotropy and interpret it in terms of mantle flow directions. Going forward, our new strategies for observing and modeling seismic anisotropy in the lowermost mantle will open up new avenues for understanding the pattern of flow in the deep Earth and what forces drive that flow.</span></p> <p>This project provided research opportunities to a diverse group of trainees, including two postdoctoral researchers, two graduate students, and two undergraduate students. Each of these trainees took part in a multi-disciplinary project with a component of international collaboration. Results from this project were incorporated into public talks on the deep Earth given by the PI and were disseminated via peer-reviewed publications and presentations given at national and international meetings.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 09/23/2020<br>      Modified by: Maureen&nbsp;D&nbsp;Long</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The core-mantle boundary (CMB) is the most dramatic physical boundary of within the Earth's interior. The CMB is the interface between the rocky, convecting mantle and the liquid iron outer core. A major unsolved problem is what the pattern of mantle convection looks like just above the CMB, and how that flow pattern interacts with convective motions in the rest of the mantle and their surface expressions in plate tectonic features. The overarching goal of this project was to use observations of seismic waves that have passed through the lowermost mantle to constrain the pattern of mantle flow just above the CMB.  In order to accomplish this goal, we carried out a number of individual studies that either presented new observations of seismic anisotropy (that is, the directional dependence of seismic wave speed) from the base of the mantle, carried out new synthetic modeling work aimed at understanding how seismic anisotropy manifests itself in seismic waves, or executed studies that combined inferences from both seismology and mineral physics to understand anisotropy. In the first category, we published papers that probed seismic anisotropy at the base of the mantle in a number of regions of the Earth, including beneath Australia and New Zealand (Creasy et al., 2017), the eastern Pacific Ocean (Deng et al., 2017), Africa (Reiss et al., 2019), Iceland (Wolf et al., 2019), and North America (Lutz et al., 2020). In the second category, we developed a new technique for modeling wave propagation through anisotropic media and applied it to study anisotropy at the base of the mantle (Tesoniero et al., 2020) and investigated what kind of seismic data sets are necessary to fully constrain lowermost mantle anisotropy (Creasy et al., 2019). In the third category, we collaborated with a mineral physicist to develop a library of models for the elastic properties of the lowermost mantle (Creasy et al., 2020), and developed a model for anisotropy and mantle flow beneath Siberia that demonstrates that the remnants of subducted slabs at the base of the mantle are likely driving flow to the southwest, towards the Perm Anomaly (Creasy et al., in preparation). Our project has showed that structures at the base of the mantle known as Large Low Shear Velocity Provinces (LLSVPs) often have strong anisotropy at their edges, helping to constriain models for their formation and evolution. We have developed and applied new observational strategies that allow us to measure seismic anisotropy and interpret it in terms of mantle flow directions. Going forward, our new strategies for observing and modeling seismic anisotropy in the lowermost mantle will open up new avenues for understanding the pattern of flow in the deep Earth and what forces drive that flow.  This project provided research opportunities to a diverse group of trainees, including two postdoctoral researchers, two graduate students, and two undergraduate students. Each of these trainees took part in a multi-disciplinary project with a component of international collaboration. Results from this project were incorporated into public talks on the deep Earth given by the PI and were disseminated via peer-reviewed publications and presentations given at national and international meetings.       Last Modified: 09/23/2020       Submitted by: Maureen D Long]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
