<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Collaborative Research: STEM Workforce Training: A Quasi-Experimental Approach Using the Effects of Research Funding</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>05/18/2015</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>211973.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>211973</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>11010000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>EHR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DGE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Graduate Education</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Earnestine Psalmonds</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>eeaster@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032928112</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>EHR Core Research &lt;br/&gt;Workforce Development &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This is a collaborative project involving Ohio State University (lead institution), Pennsylvania State University, American Institutes for Research, University of Illinois-Urbana, and the University of Iowa. The project examines the impact of different research funding structures on the training of graduate students and postdoctoral fellows and the impact of their subsequent outcomes. The rationale for the study is the recognition that research teams are organized differently in composition, size, and reliance of graduate students versus postdoctoral fellows. In addition, funding agencies change the structure of science training by creating programs that ?encourage? interdisciplinary groups, multi-university collaborations, or large research centers that focus on specific research questions. However, little research has been done about how these factors shape the career preparation of STEM professionals. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The PIs will begin by examining the different contexts of research funding and training and then (1) relate measures of team structure to the structure of funding to determine the extent to which funding agency policies shape research teams and (2) capture the trajectories of the students and postdoctoral fellows during and after their contact with the teams to quantify how the structure of teams affects training. They will use longitudinal administrative data that to capture information about sources of funding for the training and support of Ph.D.s and Postdocs from 13 major research institutions that participate in the Committee on Institutional Cooperation. They will then identify the nature of the research training through a text analysis of pertinent documents and use a quasi-experimental design to estimate the causal impact of the structure of research and length of training on trainee outcomes. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The project will have broad implications for the entire field of STEM education policy and research. The underlying algorithms and tools will be made available to the academic research community and can be leveraged to link internal human resources data sets to external data sets. This new data infrastructure also will facilitate the assessment of the effects of research investments on research productivity as well as undergraduate and graduate curriculum development.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/08/2015</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>12/10/2015</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.076</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1547507</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Julia</FirstName>
<LastName>Lane</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Julia Lane</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>julia.lane@nyu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2129926523</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000620356</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/08/2015</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>New York University</Name>
<CityName>NEW YORK</CityName>
<ZipCode>100121019</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2129982121</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>70 WASHINGTON SQUARE S</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>10</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NY10</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>041968306</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>NEW YORK UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>041968306</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[New York University]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<ZipCode>100036677</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>10</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NY10</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7980</Code>
<Text>ECR-EHR Core Research</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8816</Code>
<Text>Workforce Development</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0413</Code>
<Name>NSF Education &amp; Human Resource</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040106</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2013~211973</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The US makes large investments in research and one of the most important aspects of those investments are the people who are trained conducting research. Yet little is known about the outcomes of students who are trained on research projects or about the companies that hire them. This project supported the development of &ldquo;big data&rdquo; infrastructure to provide rigorous information about the economic value of the skills that graduate students obtain through their work on research projects. Our data have now expanded to 32 participating institutions representing 25% of federally funded R&amp;D and are now self-supporting. They are accessible (with appropriate security provisions) and have been accessed by close to 100 researchers, with formal training programs now available to facilitate usage among interested researchers and train researchers in applying big data methods to related problems.</p> <p>Our own analyses of these data show that most of the people employed on research projects at universities are trainees (undergraduates, graduate students, or postdocs), with faculty being a small minority. Our work also shows that the post-graduation outcomes of graduate students trained on research projects are consistent with them having skills that are valuable in new innovation economy. Specifically, they disproportionately work for large, high-wage, R&amp;D-performing firms in knowledge-intensive industries. We also show a surprisingly high degree of localization, with more graduate students from our member institutions remaining in the states in which they trained than going to any other single state for the vast majority of universities from which we have data. We also show large gender disparities in early career outcomes &ndash; women earn one third less than men. This gap can be accounted for entirely by field of study and presence of children and marital status. We also track people to startup businesses for which they work.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 11/30/2017<br>      Modified by: Julia&nbsp;Lane</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The US makes large investments in research and one of the most important aspects of those investments are the people who are trained conducting research. Yet little is known about the outcomes of students who are trained on research projects or about the companies that hire them. This project supported the development of "big data" infrastructure to provide rigorous information about the economic value of the skills that graduate students obtain through their work on research projects. Our data have now expanded to 32 participating institutions representing 25% of federally funded R&amp;D and are now self-supporting. They are accessible (with appropriate security provisions) and have been accessed by close to 100 researchers, with formal training programs now available to facilitate usage among interested researchers and train researchers in applying big data methods to related problems.  Our own analyses of these data show that most of the people employed on research projects at universities are trainees (undergraduates, graduate students, or postdocs), with faculty being a small minority. Our work also shows that the post-graduation outcomes of graduate students trained on research projects are consistent with them having skills that are valuable in new innovation economy. Specifically, they disproportionately work for large, high-wage, R&amp;D-performing firms in knowledge-intensive industries. We also show a surprisingly high degree of localization, with more graduate students from our member institutions remaining in the states in which they trained than going to any other single state for the vast majority of universities from which we have data. We also show large gender disparities in early career outcomes &ndash; women earn one third less than men. This gap can be accounted for entirely by field of study and presence of children and marital status. We also track people to startup businesses for which they work.          Last Modified: 11/30/2017       Submitted by: Julia Lane]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
