<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>SBIR Phase I:  A Novel Platform to Enable Directed Delivery of Therapeutics into Brain Injuries</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>01/01/2016</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2016</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>149757.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>149757</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07070000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>IIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Industrial Innovation &amp; Partnersh</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Jesus Soriano Molla</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>jsoriano@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927795</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The broader impact/commercial potential of this Small Business Innovation Research (SBIR) Phase I project is to enable transformative advances into the treatment of traumatic brain injury (TBI) and positively impact the lives of injury victims, such as soldiers, their families and the society in general by reducing the degree of disability and increasing independence. With over 10 million people worldwide sustaining TBI annually, it is the leading cause of death and disability in the most active segment of the population. The enormous financial and human suffering burden of TBI provides a compelling rationale for the development of novel and innovative agents and approaches to TBI management. Despite an obvious need, there are currently no clinically proven, effective drugs to limit secondary injury or enhance repair in TBI. Precision-guided delivery of drugs specifically to injured areas in the TBI brain may result in a paradigm shift in the clinical management of TBI. The potential for clinical application of such an approach is high, as the targeted delivery technology can be used for delivering any therapeutic or diagnostic agent. Such a targeting technology has not previously been available for treatment of brain injury and therefore there exists a huge commercial opportunity. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The proposed project focuses on developing a targeting platform for site-specific delivery of drugs to brain injury. One of the reasons for the failure of many neuro-protective agents in clinical trials is due to the dose limiting effects of these drugs. Incorporating a targeted delivery strategy can circumvent this. We have identified a novel targeting peptide that specifically recognizes TBI. Using animal models, we propose to demonstrate that combining therapeutics with this peptide can improve delivery of drugs to brain injury. In this proposal, we will test two different types of drugs (a protein therapeutic and antisense nucleic acids) in conjunction with our targeting peptide to demonstrate the validity of the principle of therapeutic targeting. We expect that an intravenous administration of targeted drugs will lead to a higher accumulation in brain injury than untargeted drug. This strategy can be expected to improve therapy, and also diagnosis, of brain injuries. It may also advance the understanding of the molecular changes associated with brain injuries and may provide new therapeutic targets. With this platform technology, transformative advances in brain injury treatment in the form of increased efficacy, reduced side effects, and ease of administration are expected to ensue</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>12/01/2015</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>12/01/2015</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1548490</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Sazid</FirstName>
<LastName>Hussain</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Sazid Hussain</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>aivocode@gmail.com</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>8182677912</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000696733</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>12/01/2015</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>AIVOCODE</Name>
<CityName>Encinitas</CityName>
<ZipCode>920244931</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>8322877308</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>4350 Manchester Ave</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>49</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CA49</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>079725125</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>AIVOCODE, INC.</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Aivocode]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>920371005</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[10901 North Torrey Pines Road]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>49</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CA49</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>5371</Code>
<Text>SBIR Phase I</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>008E</Code>
<Text>Gene and Drug Delivery</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>5371</Code>
<Text>SMALL BUSINESS PHASE I</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8038</Code>
<Text>Biotechnology</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8042</Code>
<Text>Health and Safety</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0116</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2016~149757</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><span>Traumatic brain injury (TBI) is a major clinical problem that annually affects 10 million people worldwide. It is a leading cause of death and permanent disability as survivors of TBI can develop long-term impairments in physical, cognitive, and psychosocial functions. An estimated 5.3 million people are living with a permanent TBI-related disability and need help in performing daily activities. There are no treatments available to forestall the long-term effects of TBI. Precision-guided delivery of drugs to the site of brain injury will provide tremendous benefit, and may result in a paradigm shift in the clinical management of TBI.</span></p> <p><span>AivoCode has been employing a propriety platform technology for the delivery of systemically administered (through the circulatory system) drugs to mouse brain with experimental acute brain injuries. This platform peptide has impressive specificity and goes to the site of injured brain tissue as compared to healthy normal brain. In the Phase I proof-of-concept study, AivoCode demonstrated the application of this technology as a targeting platform for clinical applications. We were able to show the delivery of a therapeutic protein with the help of this targeting peptide to injured brains. Moreover, this platform was also successful in delivering a synthetic nucleic acid, called siRNA, to silence a gene at the site of injury.&nbsp;</span></p> <p><span>The promising results from the Phase I study demonstrate that the peptide platform is highly versatile and modular. It can be used for the delivery of diagnostics as well as therapeutics to indications of the central nervous system in which the blood brain barrier (BBB) is breached and the binding receptor is elevated as a result of the injury. This phenomenon occurs in many types of brain injuries, including TBI, spinal cord injury, multiple sclerosis etc. This makes the peptide platform unique in that it can potentially target these different types of damage in a diagnostic or therapeutic setting.</span></p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 08/30/2016<br>      Modified by: Sazid&nbsp;Hussain</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Traumatic brain injury (TBI) is a major clinical problem that annually affects 10 million people worldwide. It is a leading cause of death and permanent disability as survivors of TBI can develop long-term impairments in physical, cognitive, and psychosocial functions. An estimated 5.3 million people are living with a permanent TBI-related disability and need help in performing daily activities. There are no treatments available to forestall the long-term effects of TBI. Precision-guided delivery of drugs to the site of brain injury will provide tremendous benefit, and may result in a paradigm shift in the clinical management of TBI.  AivoCode has been employing a propriety platform technology for the delivery of systemically administered (through the circulatory system) drugs to mouse brain with experimental acute brain injuries. This platform peptide has impressive specificity and goes to the site of injured brain tissue as compared to healthy normal brain. In the Phase I proof-of-concept study, AivoCode demonstrated the application of this technology as a targeting platform for clinical applications. We were able to show the delivery of a therapeutic protein with the help of this targeting peptide to injured brains. Moreover, this platform was also successful in delivering a synthetic nucleic acid, called siRNA, to silence a gene at the site of injury.   The promising results from the Phase I study demonstrate that the peptide platform is highly versatile and modular. It can be used for the delivery of diagnostics as well as therapeutics to indications of the central nervous system in which the blood brain barrier (BBB) is breached and the binding receptor is elevated as a result of the injury. This phenomenon occurs in many types of brain injuries, including TBI, spinal cord injury, multiple sclerosis etc. This makes the peptide platform unique in that it can potentially target these different types of damage in a diagnostic or therapeutic setting.          Last Modified: 08/30/2016       Submitted by: Sazid Hussain]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
