<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>"Strengthening the Collaboration and Partnership between US and African Engineering Programs by Working Closely with the African Engineering Deans Council (AEDC)</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/15/2015</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>99257.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>99257</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07050000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>EEC</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Engineering Education and Centers</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Carmina Londono</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>clondono@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927053</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Countries around the globe, whether developed or developing, recognize that having a well trained workforce in science and engineering is critical for economic success.  To successfully address global challenges there is a serious need for engineering education and appropriate pedagogy that includes hands-on experience and that is based on global perspectives, expertise and "success-stories".  One innovation in engineering education that has the potential to completely transform the way hands-on engineering is taught in engineering programs in the developing world and in areas that are economically disadvantaged in the developed world is the "Mobile Studio Technology and Pedagogy". The Mobile Studio Project (originally funded by NSF) has developed pedagogy and supporting hardware and software that provides functionality similar to that of standard laboratory equipment (oscilloscope, function generator, power supplies, among others) typically associated with a highly instrumented laboratory.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The PIs are convening a "Summit to Strengthen Collaboration and Partnership between the US and African Engineering Programs" to be held in Addis Ababa in Ethiopia on September 27-28, 2015. Applications that will employ the Mobile Studio Project pedagogy in new curricula will be presented and discussed at the Summit. The main objectives of the Summit are to: (a) ) establish collaborations between universities with engineering programs in Sub-Saharan Africa; and (2) lay the foundation for long term collaborations and partnerships with US universities with engineering programs. The effectiveness of the Summit will be evaluated by two teams. The internal (on-site) team will be responsible for local, immediate data collection, on-site interviews and assessment of Summit activities. The data will be forwarded to the external evaluation team for review, verification and analysis. The external evaluation team will be responsible for the design of the evaluation methodology, preparation of all instruments, data analysis, and report preparation including recommendations for change.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>09/18/2015</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>09/18/2015</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1548542</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Craig</FirstName>
<LastName>Scott</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>J</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Craig J Scott</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>craig.scott@morgan.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>4438853073</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000229400</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/18/2015</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Yacob</FirstName>
<LastName>Astatke</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Yacob Astatke</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>yacob.astatke@morgan.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>4438854208</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000586589</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/18/2015</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Peter</FirstName>
<LastName>Kilpatrick</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Peter Kilpatrick</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>pkilpat1@nd.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5746317432</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000598798</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/18/2015</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Morgan State University</Name>
<CityName>Baltimore</CityName>
<ZipCode>212510002</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>4438853200</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1700 East Cold Spring Lane</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Maryland</StateName>
<StateCode>MD</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MD07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>879941318</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>MORGAN STATE UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>879941318</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Morgan State University]]></Name>
<CityName>Baltimore</CityName>
<StateCode>MD</StateCode>
<ZipCode>212510002</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[1700 East Cold Spring Lane]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Maryland</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MD07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1480</Code>
<Text>ERC-Eng Research Centers</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>0000</Code>
<Text>UNASSIGNED</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>113E</Code>
<Text>ENG CURRICULUMN DEVELOPMENT</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1480</Code>
<Text>ENGINEERING RESEARCH CENTERS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>OTHR</Code>
<Text>OTHER RESEARCH OR EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0115</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2015~99257</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The Global Engineering Deans Council (GEDC) in collaboration with the African Engineering Deans Council (AEDC) and the International Federation of Engineering Education Societies (IFEES) organized and successfully held three conferences on the continent of Africa between 2015 and 2017.</p> <p>The first conference was held as a two day summit in Addis Ababa Ethiopia in September 17-18 2015. The summit was well attended an attracted around 100 participants, with <em>18 from the USA</em>, around <em>30 from Ethiopia</em> (the host country), and <em>around 50 from the rest of Africa</em>, <em>Canada, Latin America, Europe, Asia and the Middle East</em>. We were able to take 18 participants from 13 different US universities through the support of the <em>National Science Foundation (NSF) grant.</em> The US participants included Engineering Deans, department chairs, faculty members, and graduate students.&nbsp; Nine of the participants from the US (50%) presented their work, participated in the panel discussions, or conducted hands-on workshops. The <em>three graduate (PhD)</em> <em>students </em>from Morgan State, Purdue and Marquette universities partnered with an international organization called <em>&ldquo;Student Platform for Engineering Education Development&rdquo; (SPEED</em><strong>), </strong>to conduct a very constructive meeting with about 23 engineering students from Ethiopia and Nigeria.&nbsp; An external assessment team conducted a detailed analysis of the various questionnaires and interviews that were conducted during the conference in Addis Ababa. Two areas were evaluated: Perceptions and&nbsp; Outcomes of the Summit.&nbsp; Participants had a very positive perception of the GEDC Summit; 100% reported high satisfaction with involvement and that the content was of interest (97%) and relevant to their work (97%). Representative responses about the experience included: &ldquo;quality was great&rdquo;, &ldquo;excellent&rdquo;, &ldquo;the quality and usefulness of this meeting was incredibly high&rdquo;, and &ldquo;great and useful content and [great] from a networking point of view&rdquo;. Summit participants also indicated multiple immediate and short-term outcomes that resulted from participation; these included increased awareness of 21st Century Student needs, new methods of enriched instruction, and tools that would support these methods. <strong></strong></p> <p><strong><em>&nbsp;</em></strong>The 2016 AEDC/GEDC conference was held in South Africa in collaboration with the African Engineering Education Association (AEEA). Two engineering deans were able to attend this conference. We also sponsored one student from Purdue University to conduct the &ldquo;African Student Forum for Engineering Education&rdquo; during a two day pre-conference meeting in collaboration with SPEED. The student workshop was attended by close to 70 students mainly from South Africa, but also from Nigeria, and Ethiopia. The students were able to generate 4 action plans that were presented to the leaders of the university and also executive committee members of the GEDC and AEDC. Some of the comments we received from the engineering students from the USA who participated in the GEDC/AEDC conferences are as follows : &ldquo;&hellip;. <em>students from four different countries, Nigeria, Ethiopia, South Africa, and the United States, shared and compared their experiences with engineering, and other aspects of being students</em>;&rdquo; &ldquo; &hellip;. <em>my&nbsp; travels to Africa have solidified my decision to practice engineering, as I now see that my previous experiences fit into a broader picture of engineers, students and academia.&rdquo;</em></p> <p>&nbsp;The GEDC and AEDC held their 3rd annual conference on July 24-26, 2017 in Ota region, Nigeria . The conference was hosted by Covenant University with the participation and support of the African Union (AU) and the Nigerian Engineering Deans Association. There was also participation from UNESCO,&nbsp; ABET, and leaders from several private corporations in Nigeria, India, the USA, and Canada. The keynote speakers were the former President of the Republic of Nigeria, his excellency Mr.&nbsp; Olusegun Obansanjo, and Minister of Education Mr. Alpha Amoadou Bana Berry who has attending the conference on behalf of the current President of the African Union (AU) and President of the Republic of Guinee, Prof Alpha Conde.&nbsp; More than 250 delegates attended the AEDC 2017 conference in Nigeria.&nbsp; &nbsp;</p> <p>In conclusion, we believe that the grant allowed several engineering Deans from the USA to have <em>&nbsp;high visibility and access to some of the top Engineering Deans on the Continent of Africa, including in Ethiopia, Nigeria, and South Africa from 2015 until 2017.</em> It has laid the foundation for a very strong partnership and long term collaboration between the US universities and with the top engineering programs in Africa.&nbsp; The involvement of the African Union at the conference in Nigeria in July 2017 has opened the door for the possibility of a long term capacity building partnership between engineering programs in the USA and those in Africa. Our goal is to present our vision at the next AU annual or regional meetings and get the support and funding from the AU.&nbsp; Once again, we want to thank NSF, GEDC, AEDC, IFEES, the private and corporate sponsors, and the all host universities in Ethiopia, South Africa and Nigeria for their support and collaboration.&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 10/18/2017<br>      Modified by: Yacob&nbsp;Astatke</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Images (<span id="selectedPhoto0">1</span> of <span class="totalNumber"></span>)           </div> <div class="galControls" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1548542/1548542_10400966_1508365221159_AEDC-GEDCGroupPicatAAiTpt1--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1548542/1548542_10400966_1508365221159_AEDC-GEDCGroupPicatAAiTpt1--rgov-800width.jpg" title="AEDC-GEDC Group Pic In Addis"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1548542/1548542_10400966_1508365221159_AEDC-GEDCGroupPicatAAiTpt1--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="AEDC-GEDC Group Pic In Addis"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Group picture of AEDC-GEDC conference participants in Addis Ababa Ethiopia (September 2015)</div> <div class="imageCredit">yacob astatke</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Yacob&nbsp;Astatke</div> <div class="imageTitle">AEDC-GEDC Group Pic In Addis</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1548542/1548542_10400966_1508365429491_NAESessionpic1--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1548542/1548542_10400966_1508365429491_NAESessionpic1--rgov-800width.jpg" title="AEDC-GEDC Conf in Ethiopia pt2"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1548542/1548542_10400966_1508365429491_NAESessionpic1--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="AEDC-GEDC Conf in Ethiopia pt2"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Presentation by members of the National Academy of Engineering (NAE) during AEDC-GEDC Conference in Ethiopia (September 2015)</div> <div class="imageCredit">yacob astatke</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Yacob&nbsp;Astatke</div> <div class="imageTitle">AEDC-GEDC Conf in Ethiopia pt2</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1548542/1548542_10400966_1508365568033_DrPines-McCraryandUrielPic1--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1548542/1548542_10400966_1508365568033_DrPines-McCraryandUrielPic1--rgov-800width.jpg" title="AEDC-GEDC Conf in Ethiopia pt3"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1548542/1548542_10400966_1508365568033_DrPines-McCraryandUrielPic1--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="AEDC-GEDC Conf in Ethiopia pt3"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Presentation by engineering Deans and VP of research during AEDC-GEDC Conference in Ethiopia (September 2015)</div> <div class="imageCredit">yacob astatke</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Yacob&nbsp;Astatke</div> <div class="imageTitle">AEDC-GEDC Conf in Ethiopia pt3</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1548542/1548542_10400966_1508365684080_SPEEDPresentationatAEDC-GEDC--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1548542/1548542_10400966_1508365684080_SPEEDPresentationatAEDC-GEDC--rgov-800width.jpg" title="AEDC-GEDC Conf in Ethiopia pt4"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1548542/1548542_10400966_1508365684080_SPEEDPresentationatAEDC-GEDC--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="AEDC-GEDC Conf in Ethiopia pt4"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Presentation by PhD engineering students in the USA during AEDC-GEDC Conference in Ethiopia (September 2015)</div> <div class="imageCredit">yacob astatke</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Yacob&nbsp;Astatke</div> <div class="imageTitle">AEDC-GEDC Conf in Ethiopia pt4</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1548542/1548542_10400966_1508365942645_StudentForumPic2a--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1548542/1548542_10400966_1508365942645_StudentForumPic2a--rgov-800width.jpg" title="AEDC-GEDC Conf in South Africa"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1548542/1548542_10400966_1508365942645_StudentForumPic2a--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="AEDC-GEDC Conf in South Africa"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Presentation by undergraduate student from USA during AEDC-GEDC Conference in South Africa (September 2016)</div> <div class="imageCredit">yacob astatke</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Yacob&nbsp;Astatke</div> <div class="imageTitle">AEDC-GEDC Conf in South Africa</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1548542/1548542_10400966_1508366154656_AEDC2017atCovenantUnivPic1--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1548542/1548542_10400966_1508366154656_AEDC2017atCovenantUnivPic1--rgov-800width.jpg" title="AEDC-GEDC Conf in Nigeria"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1548542/1548542_10400966_1508366154656_AEDC2017atCovenantUnivPic1--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="AEDC-GEDC Conf in Nigeria"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Group picture during AEDC-GEDC Conference in Nigeria (July 2017)</div> <div class="imageCredit">yacob astatke</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Yacob&nbsp;Astatke</div> <div class="imageTitle">AEDC-GEDC Conf in Nigeria</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The Global Engineering Deans Council (GEDC) in collaboration with the African Engineering Deans Council (AEDC) and the International Federation of Engineering Education Societies (IFEES) organized and successfully held three conferences on the continent of Africa between 2015 and 2017.  The first conference was held as a two day summit in Addis Ababa Ethiopia in September 17-18 2015. The summit was well attended an attracted around 100 participants, with 18 from the USA, around 30 from Ethiopia (the host country), and around 50 from the rest of Africa, Canada, Latin America, Europe, Asia and the Middle East. We were able to take 18 participants from 13 different US universities through the support of the National Science Foundation (NSF) grant. The US participants included Engineering Deans, department chairs, faculty members, and graduate students.  Nine of the participants from the US (50%) presented their work, participated in the panel discussions, or conducted hands-on workshops. The three graduate (PhD) students from Morgan State, Purdue and Marquette universities partnered with an international organization called "Student Platform for Engineering Education Development" (SPEED), to conduct a very constructive meeting with about 23 engineering students from Ethiopia and Nigeria.  An external assessment team conducted a detailed analysis of the various questionnaires and interviews that were conducted during the conference in Addis Ababa. Two areas were evaluated: Perceptions and  Outcomes of the Summit.  Participants had a very positive perception of the GEDC Summit; 100% reported high satisfaction with involvement and that the content was of interest (97%) and relevant to their work (97%). Representative responses about the experience included: "quality was great", "excellent", "the quality and usefulness of this meeting was incredibly high", and "great and useful content and [great] from a networking point of view". Summit participants also indicated multiple immediate and short-term outcomes that resulted from participation; these included increased awareness of 21st Century Student needs, new methods of enriched instruction, and tools that would support these methods.    The 2016 AEDC/GEDC conference was held in South Africa in collaboration with the African Engineering Education Association (AEEA). Two engineering deans were able to attend this conference. We also sponsored one student from Purdue University to conduct the "African Student Forum for Engineering Education" during a two day pre-conference meeting in collaboration with SPEED. The student workshop was attended by close to 70 students mainly from South Africa, but also from Nigeria, and Ethiopia. The students were able to generate 4 action plans that were presented to the leaders of the university and also executive committee members of the GEDC and AEDC. Some of the comments we received from the engineering students from the USA who participated in the GEDC/AEDC conferences are as follows : "&hellip;. students from four different countries, Nigeria, Ethiopia, South Africa, and the United States, shared and compared their experiences with engineering, and other aspects of being students;" " &hellip;. my  travels to Africa have solidified my decision to practice engineering, as I now see that my previous experiences fit into a broader picture of engineers, students and academia."   The GEDC and AEDC held their 3rd annual conference on July 24-26, 2017 in Ota region, Nigeria . The conference was hosted by Covenant University with the participation and support of the African Union (AU) and the Nigerian Engineering Deans Association. There was also participation from UNESCO,  ABET, and leaders from several private corporations in Nigeria, India, the USA, and Canada. The keynote speakers were the former President of the Republic of Nigeria, his excellency Mr.  Olusegun Obansanjo, and Minister of Education Mr. Alpha Amoadou Bana Berry who has attending the conference on behalf of the current President of the African Union (AU) and President of the Republic of Guinee, Prof Alpha Conde.  More than 250 delegates attended the AEDC 2017 conference in Nigeria.     In conclusion, we believe that the grant allowed several engineering Deans from the USA to have  high visibility and access to some of the top Engineering Deans on the Continent of Africa, including in Ethiopia, Nigeria, and South Africa from 2015 until 2017. It has laid the foundation for a very strong partnership and long term collaboration between the US universities and with the top engineering programs in Africa.  The involvement of the African Union at the conference in Nigeria in July 2017 has opened the door for the possibility of a long term capacity building partnership between engineering programs in the USA and those in Africa. Our goal is to present our vision at the next AU annual or regional meetings and get the support and funding from the AU.  Once again, we want to thank NSF, GEDC, AEDC, IFEES, the private and corporate sponsors, and the all host universities in Ethiopia, South Africa and Nigeria for their support and collaboration.        Last Modified: 10/18/2017       Submitted by: Yacob Astatke]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
