<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Collaborative Research: EAGER: Enhancing Pyroelectric Effects in Nanostructured Materials for High-Efficiency Energy Conversion</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2015</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>75000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>75000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07010000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>ECCS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Electrical, Commun &amp; Cyber Sys</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Eyad Abed</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>eabed@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032920000</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>A large amount of energy is lost as waste heat in many engineering systems such as automobiles and turbomachinery. Significant energy gains may be obtained by efficiently scavenging such waste heat through appropriate energy conversion mechanisms. One particularly promising opportunity lies in the conversion of temperature gradients in time into electricity, referred to as the pyroelectric effect. This project will utilize experiments and theoretical modeling to explore the pyroelectric effect in nanowires, and will build prototype pyroelectric-based energy harvesting microdevices. Research will help understand the nature of pyroelectric effect in nanowires, including the amount of energy that may be realistically harvested from nanowire based devices, performance limits, etc. which will help guide further development of potential energy conversion devices. All three institutions involved in this collaborative research are minority serving institutions located in highly populated Hispanic areas. PIs will leverage this opportunity to excite and recruit minority and women students to the emerging nano/microscale energy harvesting area. The PIs will carry out outreach to local high schools to excite K-12 students about energy harvesting, and encourage them to consider further STEM education and careers.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The technical goal of this combined experimental and theoretical-simulation research is to measure and characterize the pyroelectric effect in nanowires (GaN, ZnO, etc.) for developing micro- and nano-scale devices for thermal energy harvesting and sensors applications. Despite its potential to convert waste heat into usable electricity, the pyroelectric effect has been largely unexplored, in particular at the micro/nanoscale. This is partially due to lack of methodologies for characterization of this effect at small scales. Recent theoretical findings suggest a dramatically higher pyroelectric coefficient in nanowires, similar to enhancements observed in thermoelectric and piezoelectric performance of nanowires, albeit this prediction has not been confirmed experimentally. In this effort, a methodology based on microfabricated devices will be developed to quantitatively measure and characterize the pyroelectric properties of individual suspended nanowires. In addition, theoretical models and computational tools will be developed for (i) interpretation and analysis of the experimental pyroelectric data; (ii) prediction of the pyroelectric response of various nanostructured materials (individual nanowires; nanowires arrays); and (iii) optimization of the nanostructure parameters (material composition, size, shape, interface) for enhancing the pyroelectric voltage. The proposed models will include strong non-uniformity of the polarization distribution in nanostructures and possible phonon and electron confinement effects. Based on the learning from experiment and theory, prototype pyroelectric-based energy harvesting microdevices will be built using a single and an array of nanowires. Experimental data on pyroelectric coefficient of nanowires and dependence on nanowire size, temperature, etc. will contribute to the fundamental understanding of this effect. A fundamental understanding of pyroelectric transport in single nanowires may lead to a new paradigm of high efficiency energy conversion devices that take advantage of nanoscale engineering of materials to optimize pyroelectric performance.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>09/04/2015</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>09/04/2015</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1549942</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Alexander</FirstName>
<LastName>Balandin</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>A</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Alexander A Balandin</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>balandin@ee.ucr.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>9518272351</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000292614</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/04/2015</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of California-Riverside</Name>
<CityName>RIVERSIDE</CityName>
<ZipCode>925210217</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>9518275535</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>Research &amp; Economic Development</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[245 University Office Building]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>44</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CA44</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>627797426</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>REGENTS OF THE UNIVERSITY OF CALIFORNIA AT RIVERSIDE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>071549000</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of California-Riverside]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>925210001</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>41</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CA41</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7607</Code>
<Text>EPCN-Energy-Power-Ctrl-Netwrks</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7423</Code>
<Text>Energy collection &amp; storage</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7916</Code>
<Text>EAGER</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0115</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2015~75000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><span><span style="font-size: small;">This project was dedicated to investigation of novel low-dimensional materials and pyroelectric effect for potential applications in nano and microscale energy harvesting and sensing devices. Pyroelectric effect refers to the coupling between the time-varying temperature and voltage generation in materials with certain crystalline structure. The pyroelectric effect is different from the well-known thermoelectric effect that requires spatial-temperature gradient for generation of electricity. Although thermoelectric effect has been widely investigated at various scales, the pyroelectric effect has been largely unexplored, in particular, at nanoscale. Prior theoretical studies suggested a possibility of higher pyroelectric coefficients in semiconductor nanowires owing to the quantum confinement effects, similar to the enhancements of the figure of merit observed in thermoelectric and piezoelectric nanowires. Part of the project activities was focused on theoretical and computational investigation of the effects of the acoustic phonon confinement on the pyroelectric coefficients. Phonons are quanta of crystal lattice vibrations associated with ionic motion. Phonons carry heat and scatter electrons in the crystals. The phonon dispersion was calculated for nanowires using both elastic continuum and atomic models. It was found that spatial confinement of acoustic phonons does not produce major effect on the pyroelectric coefficients in semiconductor nanowires. For this reason, it was concluded that two-dimensional materials and heterostructures, which allow for possibility of changing phonon dispersion in a wider energy range, constitute better candidates for the phonon engineering approach to pyroelectric coefficient enhancement. Another part of the project activities was dedicated to micro-Raman spectroscopy and optical microscopy characterization of relevant materials, and development of approaches for assessment of the grain structure and defects. The project team has also conducted experiments with several solid solutions of barium titanate, materials with pyroelectric and piezoelectric effects, produced by the current activated pressure assisted densification. The experiments provided information on the possibility of voltage control of the thermal conductivity in such nanostructured materials. The research conducted in the framework of this project helped in gaining knowledge about pyroelectric effects in nanoscale and nanostructured bulk materials. Metrology and materials resulting from this work may find applications in other experimental investigations of nanoscale energy conversion. Three PhD graduate students, who were involved in this project, received training in various aspects of materials characterization, including micro-Raman spectroscopy, thermal conductivity and thermal diffusivity measurements, electrical characterization, optical microscopy, atomic force microscopy, and scanning electron microscopy. Two of the participating graduate students belong to the category of underrepresented minorities in science and engineering. One graduate student defended her PhD in Electrical Engineering in December 2016, and accepted a job as a Lecturer at the University of California, Riverside. Two other graduate students are continuing education toward their PhDs in Materials Science and Engineering. The project has also contributed to undergraduate student education by offering experimental training opportunities for several engineering students.<span>&nbsp; </span><span>&nbsp;</span></span></span></p> <p><span><span style="font-size: small;">&nbsp;</span></span></p> <p><strong>&nbsp;</strong><em>&nbsp;</em></p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 12/07/2017<br>      Modified by: Alexander&nbsp;A&nbsp;Balandin</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ This project was dedicated to investigation of novel low-dimensional materials and pyroelectric effect for potential applications in nano and microscale energy harvesting and sensing devices. Pyroelectric effect refers to the coupling between the time-varying temperature and voltage generation in materials with certain crystalline structure. The pyroelectric effect is different from the well-known thermoelectric effect that requires spatial-temperature gradient for generation of electricity. Although thermoelectric effect has been widely investigated at various scales, the pyroelectric effect has been largely unexplored, in particular, at nanoscale. Prior theoretical studies suggested a possibility of higher pyroelectric coefficients in semiconductor nanowires owing to the quantum confinement effects, similar to the enhancements of the figure of merit observed in thermoelectric and piezoelectric nanowires. Part of the project activities was focused on theoretical and computational investigation of the effects of the acoustic phonon confinement on the pyroelectric coefficients. Phonons are quanta of crystal lattice vibrations associated with ionic motion. Phonons carry heat and scatter electrons in the crystals. The phonon dispersion was calculated for nanowires using both elastic continuum and atomic models. It was found that spatial confinement of acoustic phonons does not produce major effect on the pyroelectric coefficients in semiconductor nanowires. For this reason, it was concluded that two-dimensional materials and heterostructures, which allow for possibility of changing phonon dispersion in a wider energy range, constitute better candidates for the phonon engineering approach to pyroelectric coefficient enhancement. Another part of the project activities was dedicated to micro-Raman spectroscopy and optical microscopy characterization of relevant materials, and development of approaches for assessment of the grain structure and defects. The project team has also conducted experiments with several solid solutions of barium titanate, materials with pyroelectric and piezoelectric effects, produced by the current activated pressure assisted densification. The experiments provided information on the possibility of voltage control of the thermal conductivity in such nanostructured materials. The research conducted in the framework of this project helped in gaining knowledge about pyroelectric effects in nanoscale and nanostructured bulk materials. Metrology and materials resulting from this work may find applications in other experimental investigations of nanoscale energy conversion. Three PhD graduate students, who were involved in this project, received training in various aspects of materials characterization, including micro-Raman spectroscopy, thermal conductivity and thermal diffusivity measurements, electrical characterization, optical microscopy, atomic force microscopy, and scanning electron microscopy. Two of the participating graduate students belong to the category of underrepresented minorities in science and engineering. One graduate student defended her PhD in Electrical Engineering in December 2016, and accepted a job as a Lecturer at the University of California, Riverside. Two other graduate students are continuing education toward their PhDs in Materials Science and Engineering. The project has also contributed to undergraduate student education by offering experimental training opportunities for several engineering students.                    Last Modified: 12/07/2017       Submitted by: Alexander A Balandin]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
