<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>STTR Phase I:  Commercializing an intelligent reading tutor for mobile devices</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>01/01/2016</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>224609.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>224609</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07070000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>IIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Industrial Innovation &amp; Partnersh</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Benaiah Schrag</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>bschrag@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032928323</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This STTR Phase I project will commercialize a reading intelligent tutor and take it from a university-based research environment to a commercially viable product.  Phase I will concentrate on the research objectives of finalizing technical innovations and testing and hardening the software for commercial use. A unique feature of this intelligent tutor is its content authoring capability that provides teachers and support staffs the ability to create reading material to best meet the needs of their learners without having to know anything about programming, linguistics or speech recognition.  Another innovation of this tutor is the ability to provide error correction while reading and promoting fluency. The initial impact of this project is the ability to improve literacy for children using an intelligent tutor that's commercially available on today's mobile devices and easy to use and author personalized content. The broader impact is to leverage and design the software for adult learners. Literacy itself is more important than ever in today's global, high-tech economy. The proposed research of this STTR project will address literacy at all ages using an environment that's personalized, accessible, mobile, and adapted for all users.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This Small Business Technology Transfer Phase I project will focus on the commercialization of a research based reading intelligent tutor.  The two technical hurdles are user interface (UI) and providing fluent speech recognition.  One of the major difficulties in developing content that relies on the computer to provide coaching is providing the needed pronunciation information for each word. A crucial success is the ability for the reading tutor to allow the teachers and others to create content for the system without having to know anything about programming, linguistics or speech recognition. Another crucial success is the ability to allow the teachers to specify custom word pronunciations for out of dictionary words using brackets and the normal 26 characters of the English alphabet. There are not any reading fluency programs in the commercial market that combine this technical process with a "teacher friendly" user interface. This innovation enables teachers to truly create and add relevant reading materials to the reading intelligent tutor for their learners. The goal of the research in this proposal is to address the technical hurdles and prepare the reading intelligent tutoring software for commercialization across multiple platforms and mobile devices.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>12/07/2015</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>12/07/2015</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1549808</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>John</FirstName>
<LastName>Carney</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>John Carney</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>john.carney@mari.com</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>7039696800</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000710575</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>12/07/2015</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Gwendolyn</FirstName>
<LastName>Cartledge</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Gwendolyn Cartledge</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>Cartledge.1@osu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6146888735</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000710707</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>12/07/2015</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Carney Labs, LLC</Name>
<CityName>Alexandria</CityName>
<ZipCode>223143134</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>7039696800</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>100 N. Pitt St.</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[Suite 310]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Virginia</StateName>
<StateCode>VA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>08</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>VA08</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>078737163</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>MARI LLC</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Carney Labs, LLC]]></Name>
<CityName>Alexandria</CityName>
<StateCode>VA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>223143144</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[100 N. Pitt St.]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Virginia</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>08</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>VA08</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1505</Code>
<Text>STTR Phase I</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>118E</Code>
<Text>GRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1505</Code>
<Text>STTR PHASE I</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8031</Code>
<Text>Education Products</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8032</Code>
<Text>Software Services and Applications</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8039</Code>
<Text>Information, Communication &amp; Computing</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9177</Code>
<Text>ELEMENTARY/SECONDARY EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0116</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2016~224609</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><em>OVERVIEW</em></p> <p><span>This STTR Phase I project, <span>Commercializing an Intelligent Reading Tutor for Mobile Devices,</span>&nbsp;concentrated on researching and solving three the key technical challenges required for a commercially successful reading fluency tutor. &nbsp;</span><strong>First</strong><span>, the tutor needed to be created from scratch on a technology platform that schools are currently using and/or trending toward. The original tutor software, created by our STTR research partner, Ohio State University, existed on a PC client-server environment and schools were now moving toward low-cost mobile platforms like tablets and Chromebooks.&nbsp;</span><strong>Second</strong><span>, the PC platform used a mouse as a primary interface and we were moving to a tablet environment with a touch-driven interface. &nbsp;Would this work well for students with this type of reading intervention? &nbsp;Would using a touch screen create frustation and difficulty? &nbsp;</span><strong>Third</strong><span>, and perhaps the most significant objective, was to significantly improve the accuracy of the reading fluency automated speech recognizer (ASR) from the PC platform to the tablet. The requirements for a "fluency" speech recognizer differ in major ways from a recognizer that is listening only for pronunciation or a conversational recognizer like Siri. &nbsp;A more accurate speech recognizer for fluency would not only improve the student experience but would solve a myriad of implementation challenges for the school and the teachers that were identified in Ohio State University's research findings. &nbsp;At the end of the project our goal was to achieve technical equivalency between the PC client-server software and the re-written tablet software along with significantly improved fluency speech recognition.</span></p> <p><em>ACCOMPLISHMENTS</em></p> <p><span>The Andoid reading fluency tutor was field tested in the Ohio Avenue Elementary School in Columbus, Ohio. Ohio State University graduate assistant students supervised the students using the tablet reading tutor. The graduate students reported that the native Android tutor did provide a technically equivalent solution to the Ohio State PC client-server environment. With regard to the automated speach recognition, the Android tablet performed better than or equal to the PC version. The graduate assistants also reported that students had difficulty in navigated the Maze Activity which is the last item in their daily list of activities. &nbsp;We believe this is a UI issue in designing the maze for touchscreen interface and we will address this in Phase II. Phase II will also focus on a more robust automated speech recognizer that is more specifically trained to the types of speech patterns of new readers: missed words, repeated words, skipped lines, and long pauses.</span></p> <p>Close to 100,000 lines of code were written to cover the primary functionality as identified by our research partner, Ohio State University. &nbsp;There were nine primary areas created in native software for the tablet: (1) Login and User Management, (2) Introduction and Overview, (3) Practice Works, (4) Read to Me, (5) Read Along, (6) Listen to me, (7) Timed Reading, (8) Maze Activity, and (9) Reports and Feedback.</p> <p><em>IMPACT</em></p> <p>This project had the impact of creating a technically equivalent tablet-based tutor to the PC version that was used to validate Ohio State University's resreach findings. &nbsp;Further commerciallization work will create a viable fluency tutor serving the needs of individuals of all ages on mobile technology platforms that are readily being adopted by schools. &nbsp;The MARi Reading Fluency Tutor will be able to use the scientifically validated "repeated readings" methodology to improve students' fluency at scale. &nbsp;</p> <p>Teaching reading fluency is a resource intensive effort. &nbsp;Deploying the tutor on a low-cost mobile device that can be used in classrooms with limited teacher involvement will have a significant positive impact on reading fluency outcomes.</p> <div class="tinyMCEContent"> <p>Reading skills are at the heart of learning. For many students and adults, a lack of core reading skills becomes a major impediment for continued academic and workplace growth. &nbsp;Disadvantaged students in particular lack early age exposure to books and people that read to them on a regular basis. &nbsp;Acquiring solid reading skills at an early age has the potential of a multiplier effect for future learning efforts. &nbsp;The MARi Reading Fluency Tutor is continuously linked to a student's skill profile which MARi can use with the appropriate permissions to inform other third-party intelligent tutors regarding a student's fluency rate, vocabulary, and comprehension skills. &nbsp;Using this information, tutors in math and science will be able to tailor their exercises to the particular skills of the student. &nbsp;Students who know how to solve math and science word problems will not be tripped up by unfamiliar vocabulary and syntax. &nbsp;The Reading Fluency Tutor, linked into MARi, will create a positive multiplier effect for the student in any other field served by automated learning systems and teachers using these tools.&nbsp;</p> </div><br> <p>            Last Modified: 09/01/2017<br>      Modified by: John&nbsp;Carney</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ OVERVIEW  This STTR Phase I project, Commercializing an Intelligent Reading Tutor for Mobile Devices, concentrated on researching and solving three the key technical challenges required for a commercially successful reading fluency tutor.  First, the tutor needed to be created from scratch on a technology platform that schools are currently using and/or trending toward. The original tutor software, created by our STTR research partner, Ohio State University, existed on a PC client-server environment and schools were now moving toward low-cost mobile platforms like tablets and Chromebooks. Second, the PC platform used a mouse as a primary interface and we were moving to a tablet environment with a touch-driven interface.  Would this work well for students with this type of reading intervention?  Would using a touch screen create frustation and difficulty?  Third, and perhaps the most significant objective, was to significantly improve the accuracy of the reading fluency automated speech recognizer (ASR) from the PC platform to the tablet. The requirements for a "fluency" speech recognizer differ in major ways from a recognizer that is listening only for pronunciation or a conversational recognizer like Siri.  A more accurate speech recognizer for fluency would not only improve the student experience but would solve a myriad of implementation challenges for the school and the teachers that were identified in Ohio State University's research findings.  At the end of the project our goal was to achieve technical equivalency between the PC client-server software and the re-written tablet software along with significantly improved fluency speech recognition.  ACCOMPLISHMENTS  The Andoid reading fluency tutor was field tested in the Ohio Avenue Elementary School in Columbus, Ohio. Ohio State University graduate assistant students supervised the students using the tablet reading tutor. The graduate students reported that the native Android tutor did provide a technically equivalent solution to the Ohio State PC client-server environment. With regard to the automated speach recognition, the Android tablet performed better than or equal to the PC version. The graduate assistants also reported that students had difficulty in navigated the Maze Activity which is the last item in their daily list of activities.  We believe this is a UI issue in designing the maze for touchscreen interface and we will address this in Phase II. Phase II will also focus on a more robust automated speech recognizer that is more specifically trained to the types of speech patterns of new readers: missed words, repeated words, skipped lines, and long pauses.  Close to 100,000 lines of code were written to cover the primary functionality as identified by our research partner, Ohio State University.  There were nine primary areas created in native software for the tablet: (1) Login and User Management, (2) Introduction and Overview, (3) Practice Works, (4) Read to Me, (5) Read Along, (6) Listen to me, (7) Timed Reading, (8) Maze Activity, and (9) Reports and Feedback.  IMPACT  This project had the impact of creating a technically equivalent tablet-based tutor to the PC version that was used to validate Ohio State University's resreach findings.  Further commerciallization work will create a viable fluency tutor serving the needs of individuals of all ages on mobile technology platforms that are readily being adopted by schools.  The MARi Reading Fluency Tutor will be able to use the scientifically validated "repeated readings" methodology to improve students' fluency at scale.    Teaching reading fluency is a resource intensive effort.  Deploying the tutor on a low-cost mobile device that can be used in classrooms with limited teacher involvement will have a significant positive impact on reading fluency outcomes.   Reading skills are at the heart of learning. For many students and adults, a lack of core reading skills becomes a major impediment for continued academic and workplace growth.  Disadvantaged students in particular lack early age exposure to books and people that read to them on a regular basis.  Acquiring solid reading skills at an early age has the potential of a multiplier effect for future learning efforts.  The MARi Reading Fluency Tutor is continuously linked to a student's skill profile which MARi can use with the appropriate permissions to inform other third-party intelligent tutors regarding a student's fluency rate, vocabulary, and comprehension skills.  Using this information, tutors in math and science will be able to tailor their exercises to the particular skills of the student.  Students who know how to solve math and science word problems will not be tripped up by unfamiliar vocabulary and syntax.  The Reading Fluency Tutor, linked into MARi, will create a positive multiplier effect for the student in any other field served by automated learning systems and teachers using these tools.         Last Modified: 09/01/2017       Submitted by: John Carney]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
