<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>SBIR Phase I:  Designing High-Strength Thermally-Stable Aluminum Casting Alloys for Cylinder Head Applications</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>01/01/2016</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2016</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>149991.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>149991</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07070000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>IIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Industrial Innovation &amp; Partnersh</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Benaiah Schrag</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>bschrag@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032928323</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This Small Business Innovation Research Phase I project involves development of a new family of thermally-stable, high-strength aluminum casting alloys for engine cylinder head applications. There is a strong push globally to improve internal combustion (IC) engine efficiency, through down-sizing, turbo or supercharged boost, and through the use of alternative fuels. All of these approaches increase the operational temperature of the engine beyond what current aluminum engine alloys can sustain, leading to dimensional changes which can cause engine failure. At these higher temperatures, the new alloys to be developed will retain engine performance and life, while maintaining the low weight, castability, and cost-effectiveness of standard aluminum alloys. Our initial focus is on two-wheeled motorcycles and other recreational vehicles that represent a total market capitalization of $35 million, just for cylinder heads. There are many follow-on markets including diesel generators, and engines for outboard marine, small aircraft and even automobile vehicles, where the total markets are estimated in the billions of dollars. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The intellectual merit of this project is the replacement of traditional gravity- and die-cast aluminum alloys with higher performing materials at a competitive cost. These aluminum alloys will contain heat-resistant nano-precipitates, which will not dissolve at high operating temperature and pressure, thus retaining the component strength, toughness and microhardness. With production of millions of IC engines each year, a new high-temperature alloy will lead to significant energy reductions. Current automotive and motorcycle aluminum engine components, such as cylinder heads, blocks and pistons, are limited to an operating temperature of roughly 220  deg. C. Modern and future engines require higher operating temperatures of up to 290  deg. C and pressures up to 21 MPa to meet demands for higher engine efficiency, reduced vehicle mass and fuel consumption, increases in the power-to-mass ratio, and lower emissions. The 2025 Corporate Average Fuel Economy (CAFE) regulations require an efficiency of 54.5 miles per gallon for light duty vehicles by 2025. The need for improved IC engine efficiency is urgent, thus increasing the demand for novel high temperature aluminum casting alloys.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>11/02/2015</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>11/02/2015</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1549282</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Nhon</FirstName>
<LastName>Vo</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>Q</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Nhon Q Vo</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>nvo@nanoal.com</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2177210317</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000657729</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>11/02/2015</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>NanoAl LLC</Name>
<CityName>Skokie</CityName>
<ZipCode>600773479</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2177210317</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>7135 Laramie Ave</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Illinois</StateName>
<StateCode>IL</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>09</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>IL09</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>079180585</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>NANOAL LLC</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>080824515</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[NanoAl LLC]]></Name>
<CityName>Skokie</CityName>
<StateCode>IL</StateCode>
<ZipCode>600775315</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[8025 Lamon Ave, Suite 446]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Illinois</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>09</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>IL09</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>5371</Code>
<Text>SBIR Phase I</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>123E</Code>
<Text>CENTERS: ADVANCED MATERIALS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>5371</Code>
<Text>SMALL BUSINESS PHASE I</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8025</Code>
<Text>Advanced Materials Processing</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0116</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2016~149991</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Based on NanoAl&rsquo;s conducted customer discovery during the program, the target application for the technology has been changed from&nbsp;the automotive&nbsp;cylinder head to beverage can.&nbsp;The automotive engine market is too expensive to penetrate, and it takes too long.&nbsp;The annual aluminum can production is a staggering 320 billion cans per year, equating to 4.2 billion kilograms of aluminum. The production of aluminum cans is enormous, so an efficiency improvement comes with a giant multiplicative effect; a single gram of weight saved in the can saves over 200 thousand metric tons of aluminum globally per year. Thus lightweighting the can has been a front-burner issue for decades. In this Small Business Innovation Research Phase I project, NanoAl has demonstrated that, utilizing its nano-precipitation technology, performance of the aluminum material, utilized in the beverage cans, can be improved across the board, which potentially reduces &gt;10% of material from the can. The intellectual merit of this project is the replacement of traditional aluminum alloys with higher performing materials at a competitive cost to reduce the can&rsquo;s weight, reducing material cost.&nbsp;Together with the material cost reduction, can production burns less energy releasing lower CO<sub>2&nbsp;</sub>emissions &ndash; both key metrics in sustainability of the environment. Additionally, the lightness of aluminum cans helps save resources during filling, storage, transportation and scrap at the end of the product&rsquo;s life. The newly developed aluminum can also be used and will bring efficiencies in aluminum packaging for food, pet food, and other beverages. The nano-precipitate technology is a foundation to improve many&nbsp;other&nbsp;aluminum products, from beverage cans to cars to wire for overhead power and micro-grids and electric batteries. This project results in two patent applications and leads to a product development program, a joint development, between NanoAl and its partnered aluminum sheet producer.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 03/02/2017<br>      Modified by: Nhon&nbsp;Q&nbsp;Vo</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Based on NanoAl?s conducted customer discovery during the program, the target application for the technology has been changed from the automotive cylinder head to beverage can. The automotive engine market is too expensive to penetrate, and it takes too long. The annual aluminum can production is a staggering 320 billion cans per year, equating to 4.2 billion kilograms of aluminum. The production of aluminum cans is enormous, so an efficiency improvement comes with a giant multiplicative effect; a single gram of weight saved in the can saves over 200 thousand metric tons of aluminum globally per year. Thus lightweighting the can has been a front-burner issue for decades. In this Small Business Innovation Research Phase I project, NanoAl has demonstrated that, utilizing its nano-precipitation technology, performance of the aluminum material, utilized in the beverage cans, can be improved across the board, which potentially reduces &gt;10% of material from the can. The intellectual merit of this project is the replacement of traditional aluminum alloys with higher performing materials at a competitive cost to reduce the can?s weight, reducing material cost. Together with the material cost reduction, can production burns less energy releasing lower CO2 emissions &ndash; both key metrics in sustainability of the environment. Additionally, the lightness of aluminum cans helps save resources during filling, storage, transportation and scrap at the end of the product?s life. The newly developed aluminum can also be used and will bring efficiencies in aluminum packaging for food, pet food, and other beverages. The nano-precipitate technology is a foundation to improve many other aluminum products, from beverage cans to cars to wire for overhead power and micro-grids and electric batteries. This project results in two patent applications and leads to a product development program, a joint development, between NanoAl and its partnered aluminum sheet producer.          Last Modified: 03/02/2017       Submitted by: Nhon Q Vo]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
