<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Evaluating Convective Parameterization Schemes and Their Scale-awareness Using Simulated Convection in a Hierarchy of Models</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>04/01/2016</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>03/31/2020</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>526406.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>626629</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>06020106</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>GEO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>AGS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Atmospheric &amp; Geospace Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Eric DeWeaver</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>edeweave@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032928527</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This project will yield new insight into factors governing the onset and amount of convection. It will lead to a much better understanding of the strengths and weaknesses of existing representations of atmospheric convection in major climate models in the world. As the global climate model grid spacing decreases to ~10 km or less, representing atmospheric convection in such models is a great challenge. The proposed work to use cloud-resolving model simulation of atmospheric convection to evaluate the accuracy and scale-awareness of widely used algorithms for representing convection is innovative, and will pave the way for further improving global climate models. The representation of convection and associated clouds strongly affects the statistics of extreme events in both current and future climates. It is also a major source of uncertainty in climate change projection. Thus, the proposed research will contribute to the simulation and prediction of the occurrence of natural disasters associated with climate variability at different timescales. The project will also contribute to educating future generation climate scientists through training of a postdoctoral researcher and providing learning opportunities for undergraduate summer interns.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The representation of the effects of atmospheric convection is one of the most challenging scientific issues in climate modeling. Over the last few decades, despite tremendous efforts going into improving the treatment of physical processes in climate models, major problems still exist in simulating important climate systems. These deficiencies are largely associated with the lack of accurate representation of atmospheric convection in the models. This project proposes to systematically investigate the criteria used for determining the onset of convection and assumptions that determine the amount of convective activity (known as closure assumptions) in representations of atmospheric convection using a hierarchy of numerical models. The goal is to evaluate the many different ways of representing atmospheric convection in state-of-the-science global climate models, thereby identifying their strengths and weakness and further improving them. To achieve this goal, simulations of atmospheric convection by fine-resolution numerical models that can resolve convection are used to evaluate the onset criteria and closure assumptions for convection. Statistical analysis methods, including skill score calculation, lead-lag correlation, and composite techniques, will be used to analyze the model output data. The simulations of convection will also be used to investigate whether the algorithms of representing convection in current global climate models can still be used when the grid spacing of the models decreases to ~10 km or less, the so-called grey zone scales, from the current spacing of ~100 km or larger. New ideas and formulations for representing convection in global climate models resulting from the analysis will be tested using the Community Atmosphere Model, CAM5.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>03/21/2016</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/13/2018</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.050</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1549259</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Guang</FirstName>
<LastName>Zhang</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>J</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Guang J Zhang</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>gzhang@ucsd.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>8585347535</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000489117</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>03/21/2016</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of California-San Diego Scripps Inst of Oceanography</Name>
<CityName>LA JOLLA</CityName>
<ZipCode>920930210</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>8585341293</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>8602 La Jolla Shores Dr</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[Univ of California-San Diego]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>49</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CA49</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>175104595</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF CALIFORNIA SAN DIEGO</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>071549000</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[UCSD - Scripps Institution of Oceanography]]></Name>
<CityName>La Jolla</CityName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>920930221</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[9500 Gilman Dr]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>49</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CA49</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>5740</Code>
<Text>Climate &amp; Large-Scale Dynamics</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>OTHR</Code>
<Text>OTHER RESEARCH OR EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0116</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0118</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2016~526406</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2018~100223</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>This project used cloud model simulation of convection to evaluate the accuracy and scale-awareness of widely used convection parameterization schemes. It yielded new insights into factors governing the triggering of convection and led to a better understanding of the strengths and weaknesses of existing convection parameterization schemes used in global climate models (GCM). It is found that the generation of convective instability by large-scale atmospheric circulation is a better indicator for the potential of convection than convective instability itself. Based on the results, a convection scheme was revised to improve the simulation of climate in the National Center for Atmospheric Research (NCAR) Community Earth System Model version 1 (CESM1). It significantly improved the simulation of tropical precipitation, particularly the precipitation distribution associated with the tropical convergence zone in the coupled atmosphere-ocean model. Further analysis of the model simulation shows that the improved simulation of precipitation is through a chain of complex atmosphere-ocean interactions.</p> <p>This project also investigated the role of vertical structure of diabatic heating from condensation in convection in the simulation intraseasonal oscillation known as Madden Julian Oscillation (MJO).&nbsp;By modifying the convective heating profile to include top heating and bottom cooling to mimic mesoscale heating structure in the NCAR GCM, it is found that including stratiform-like heating and cooling reproduces many observed features of MJO, including a clear eastward propagation, a westward-tilt vertical structure of MJO-scale anomalies of dynamic and thermodynamic fields. Further analysis shows an abundance of shallow convection ahead of MJO deep convection resulting from this heating modification, confirming the role of shallow convection in preconditioning the atmosphere by moistening the lower troposphere ahead of deep convection during MJO life cycle. These features suggest that the mesoscale stratiform heating, especially its low-level cooling component, is important to MJO simulation in GCMs.</p> <p>As GCM grid size decreases in high resolution models, the stochasticity of convection becomes more important because there are fewer clouds within a GCM grid box. We investigated the effect of including the stochasticity in the NCAR GCM by introducing a stochastic convection parameterization into the model. The simulation of precipitation intensity is significantly improved. The extreme precipitation occurs more frequently while the light rain occurs much less frequently compared to that without the stochastic representation. The project also improved the simulation of Indian summer monsoon. By further&nbsp;linking the stochastic generation of convective clouds to the change of large-scale vertical motion in midtroposphere to better account for the relationship between convection and the large-scale environment, the stochastic convection representation improved the annual cycle of rainfall over central India and the onset date of Indian summer monsoon.</p> <p>In summary, the research will facilitate further development of future generations of global climate models.&nbsp;<span>The scale-aware convection scheme together with the incorporation of the stochastic behavior of convection in convection parameterization pave</span>&nbsp;the way for further advancing convection parameterization in future high-resolution global climate models. The representation of convection and associated clouds strongly affects the statistics of extreme events in both current and future climates. It is also a major source of uncertainty in climate change projection. It is well known that the simulation of climate variability at different timescales is closely linked to convective parameterization. Thus, our research will contribute to the simulation and prediction of the occurrence of natural disasters associated with these variabilities.&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 07/02/2020<br>      Modified by: Guang&nbsp;J&nbsp;Zhang</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ This project used cloud model simulation of convection to evaluate the accuracy and scale-awareness of widely used convection parameterization schemes. It yielded new insights into factors governing the triggering of convection and led to a better understanding of the strengths and weaknesses of existing convection parameterization schemes used in global climate models (GCM). It is found that the generation of convective instability by large-scale atmospheric circulation is a better indicator for the potential of convection than convective instability itself. Based on the results, a convection scheme was revised to improve the simulation of climate in the National Center for Atmospheric Research (NCAR) Community Earth System Model version 1 (CESM1). It significantly improved the simulation of tropical precipitation, particularly the precipitation distribution associated with the tropical convergence zone in the coupled atmosphere-ocean model. Further analysis of the model simulation shows that the improved simulation of precipitation is through a chain of complex atmosphere-ocean interactions.  This project also investigated the role of vertical structure of diabatic heating from condensation in convection in the simulation intraseasonal oscillation known as Madden Julian Oscillation (MJO). By modifying the convective heating profile to include top heating and bottom cooling to mimic mesoscale heating structure in the NCAR GCM, it is found that including stratiform-like heating and cooling reproduces many observed features of MJO, including a clear eastward propagation, a westward-tilt vertical structure of MJO-scale anomalies of dynamic and thermodynamic fields. Further analysis shows an abundance of shallow convection ahead of MJO deep convection resulting from this heating modification, confirming the role of shallow convection in preconditioning the atmosphere by moistening the lower troposphere ahead of deep convection during MJO life cycle. These features suggest that the mesoscale stratiform heating, especially its low-level cooling component, is important to MJO simulation in GCMs.  As GCM grid size decreases in high resolution models, the stochasticity of convection becomes more important because there are fewer clouds within a GCM grid box. We investigated the effect of including the stochasticity in the NCAR GCM by introducing a stochastic convection parameterization into the model. The simulation of precipitation intensity is significantly improved. The extreme precipitation occurs more frequently while the light rain occurs much less frequently compared to that without the stochastic representation. The project also improved the simulation of Indian summer monsoon. By further linking the stochastic generation of convective clouds to the change of large-scale vertical motion in midtroposphere to better account for the relationship between convection and the large-scale environment, the stochastic convection representation improved the annual cycle of rainfall over central India and the onset date of Indian summer monsoon.  In summary, the research will facilitate further development of future generations of global climate models. The scale-aware convection scheme together with the incorporation of the stochastic behavior of convection in convection parameterization pave the way for further advancing convection parameterization in future high-resolution global climate models. The representation of convection and associated clouds strongly affects the statistics of extreme events in both current and future climates. It is also a major source of uncertainty in climate change projection. It is well known that the simulation of climate variability at different timescales is closely linked to convective parameterization. Thus, our research will contribute to the simulation and prediction of the occurrence of natural disasters associated with these variabilities.              Last Modified: 07/02/2020       Submitted by: Guang J Zhang]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
