<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>SBIR Phase I: Decoding Obfuscated Text to Find Trafficking Victims</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>01/01/2016</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2016</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>149900.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>179879</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07070000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>IIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Industrial Innovation &amp; Partnersh</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Peter Atherton</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>patherto@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032928772</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The broader impact/commercial potential of this Small Business Innovation Research (SBIR) Phase I project goes beyond combating sex trafficking in the United States.  The proposed technology finds compounded influence with extension to countries in North America, Asia, and Europe, especially those with sufficient Internet penetration.  This innovation will enable previously impossible information extraction algorithms to be applied to data on trafficking activity.  The United States will lead by example by empowering its law enforcement to find and rescue victims of human trafficking and prosecute their exploiters, showing the world that exploitation will not be tolerated in our society.  The proposed innovation will also increase collaboration across fragmented jurisdictions domestically and internationally, streamlining investigative workflows and enhancing productivity.  The capability to decode Unicode characters into meaningful intelligence is an important and novel innovation impacting other investigations related to black market economies, which are becoming increasingly commonplace.  Many detectives need analogous capabilities in domains including drug, gun, and animal trafficking and the sale of counterfeit goods online (e.g. pharmaceuticals, licensed merchandise) to empower them to find patterns left by perpetrators.  Both international expansion of existing tools and expansion of domains served will multiply the commercial potential of this project.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This Small Business Innovation Research (SBIR) Phase I project will develop new machine learning technology to decode patterns of text used by sex traffickers in online advertisements to evade prosecution. Recently, criminals have developed new ways to avoid law enforcement detection, particularly by use of look-alike Unicode characters and symbols, which cannot be easily translated by a computer for automated search or deeper analysis. There is no existing solution that can comprehensively and accurately decode the obfuscated information. We will apply machine learning methods to train a model to predict the appropriate Latin character translation most likely to be represented by alternative symbols, allowing us to automatically and predictively decode obfuscated text. We will produce a set of algorithms to solve this problem, empowering law enforcement to stay ahead of criminal tactics. Beyond the United States, we will deploy the innovation internationally, as well as into new domains, including but not limited to, drug, gun, and animal trafficking, spam, phishing schemes, and attempts to avoid keyword-based alerting systems. These illicit activities are a significant detriment to both our society and economy, and urgent solutions are needed to give those who combat these activities the tools they need to stay ahead.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>12/16/2015</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/29/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1549015</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Emily</FirstName>
<LastName>Kennedy</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>C</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Emily C Kennedy</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>emily@marinusanalytics.com</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>9162051245</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000672604</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>12/16/2015</StartDate>
<EndDate>02/10/2016</EndDate>
<RoleCode>Former Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Andreas</FirstName>
<LastName>Olligschlaeger</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Andreas Olligschlaeger</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>olli@marinusanalytics.com</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>8669452803</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000718017</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>02/10/2016</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Marinus Analytics LLC</Name>
<CityName>Pittsburgh</CityName>
<ZipCode>152133715</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>8669452803</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>4620 Henry Street</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Pennsylvania</StateName>
<StateCode>PA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>18</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>PA18</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>079410657</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>MARINUS ANALYTICS LLC</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Marinus Analytics LLC]]></Name>
<CityName>Pittsburgh</CityName>
<StateCode>PA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>152133715</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[4620 Henry Street]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Pennsylvania</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>18</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>PA18</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>5371</Code>
<Text>SBIR Phase I</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>163E</Code>
<Text>SBIR Phase IB</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>5371</Code>
<Text>SMALL BUSINESS PHASE I</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8032</Code>
<Text>Software Services and Applications</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0116</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2016~179879</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Sex trafficking is a global epidemic that impacts millions of victims each year. The FBI estimates it is the world&rsquo;s fastest growing type of organized crime and the third largest in the world. The National Center for Missing and Exploited Children estimates 1 out of 5 runaway children have been trafficked for sex. Put plainly, sex trafficking is a form of modern day slavery and as such represents one of the top priorities of law enforcement agencies at all levels.</p> <p>The Internet has fostered the growth of numerous adult escort sites, which make it easy for prostitutes to advertise their services. The sheer volume of ads is staggering. We estimate upwards of a million escort ads are placed online each day in the United States. Hiding among the noise of at-will adult escort ads are victims of sex trafficking. For law enforcement, this presents a significant challenge: how to identify ads that are associated with sex trafficking? Police have limited human and technical resources. Manually sifting through thousands of ads, in the hopes of finding something suspicious, is not a good use of those resources, even if they know what they are looking for. Leveraging artificial intelligence to empower those dedicated to &ldquo;protecting and serving&rdquo; the most vulnerable in our community is the main focus of our SBIR grant.</p> <p>Like other criminals, sex traffickers are fairly technologically savvy. They know the police are using search engines and other automated tools to scan for suspicious ads. So, it is naturally in the criminals&rsquo; best interest to prevent police from being able to find those postings advertising victims. From our prior research as well as that conducted during our SBIR grant, we found criminals use three methods to accomplish this: use messy text, obfuscate phone numbers, and hide information in images; these methods make it impossible to search for ads using conventional spellings and numbers. Examples of each type of obfuscation are described below and through the attached pictures.&nbsp;</p> <p>Example 1: Text is obfuscated using non-ASCII characters (readable by humans, but not by search engines).&nbsp; See image Example 1.</p> <p>Example 2: Phone numbers are obfuscated by substituting words for numbers or randomly interjecting symbols.&nbsp; See image Example 2.</p> <p>Example 3: Escorts hold up signs in images containing their phone number and other information.&nbsp; See image Example 3.</p> <p>Therefore, our goal for the purpose of this grant was threefold: one, employ machine learning techniques to make obfuscated ads and phone numbers machine readable and, by extension, searchable. Two, develop classifiers to identify suspicious ads automatically based on certain types of images or suspicious text content. Finally, we designed and implemented a scalable computing infrastructure required to support deployment, so this work can be utilized in real investigations.&nbsp;</p> <p>As a direct result of this grant we were able to develop multiple techniques to solve the challenges identified during the course of our research. Specifically, we created algorithms that are over 90% accurate in deobfuscating masked text and phone numbers. We applied image classifiers using deep learning artificial neural networks and computer vision technology to automatically detect ads showing people holding up signs or containing text superimposed on them, likely indicators of suspicious posters. Finally, we implemented a cloud-based platform which accomplishes all of this in near real time and allows investigators 24/7 access to our database of hundreds of millions of ads.</p> <p>This Small Business Innovation Research Phase I grant has already had a significant impact on the ability of law enforcement agencies to fight human trafficking. The breadth of technologies developed and deployed has impacted thousands of investigations and helped hundreds of victims. Much more work remains to be done, but we at Marinus Analytics are extremely grateful to the National Science Foundation for supporting our efforts and helping us make a difference in the human tragedy that is sex trafficking.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 01/10/2017<br>      Modified by: Andreas&nbsp;Olligschlaeger</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Images (<span id="selectedPhoto0">1</span> of <span class="totalNumber"></span>)           </div> <div class="galControls" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1549015/1549015_10405644_1484077207889_Example1--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1549015/1549015_10405644_1484077207889_Example1--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Example 1"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1549015/1549015_10405644_1484077207889_Example1--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Example 1"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Example 1</div> <div class="imageCredit">Marinus Analytics</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Andreas&nbsp;Olligschlaeger</div> <div class="imageTitle">Example 1</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1549015/1549015_10405644_1484077488949_Example2--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1549015/1549015_10405644_1484077488949_Example2--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Example 2"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1549015/1549015_10405644_1484077488949_Example2--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Example 2"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Example 2</div> <div class="imageCredit">Marinus Analytics</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Andreas&nbsp;Olligschlaeger</div> <div class="imageTitle">Example 2</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1549015/1549015_10405644_1484077604591_Example3--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1549015/1549015_10405644_1484077604591_Example3--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Example 3"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1549015/1549015_10405644_1484077604591_Example3--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Example 3"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Example 3</div> <div class="imageCredit">Marinus Analytics</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Andreas&nbsp;Olligschlaeger</div> <div class="imageTitle">Example 3</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Sex trafficking is a global epidemic that impacts millions of victims each year. The FBI estimates it is the world?s fastest growing type of organized crime and the third largest in the world. The National Center for Missing and Exploited Children estimates 1 out of 5 runaway children have been trafficked for sex. Put plainly, sex trafficking is a form of modern day slavery and as such represents one of the top priorities of law enforcement agencies at all levels.  The Internet has fostered the growth of numerous adult escort sites, which make it easy for prostitutes to advertise their services. The sheer volume of ads is staggering. We estimate upwards of a million escort ads are placed online each day in the United States. Hiding among the noise of at-will adult escort ads are victims of sex trafficking. For law enforcement, this presents a significant challenge: how to identify ads that are associated with sex trafficking? Police have limited human and technical resources. Manually sifting through thousands of ads, in the hopes of finding something suspicious, is not a good use of those resources, even if they know what they are looking for. Leveraging artificial intelligence to empower those dedicated to "protecting and serving" the most vulnerable in our community is the main focus of our SBIR grant.  Like other criminals, sex traffickers are fairly technologically savvy. They know the police are using search engines and other automated tools to scan for suspicious ads. So, it is naturally in the criminals? best interest to prevent police from being able to find those postings advertising victims. From our prior research as well as that conducted during our SBIR grant, we found criminals use three methods to accomplish this: use messy text, obfuscate phone numbers, and hide information in images; these methods make it impossible to search for ads using conventional spellings and numbers. Examples of each type of obfuscation are described below and through the attached pictures.   Example 1: Text is obfuscated using non-ASCII characters (readable by humans, but not by search engines).  See image Example 1.  Example 2: Phone numbers are obfuscated by substituting words for numbers or randomly interjecting symbols.  See image Example 2.  Example 3: Escorts hold up signs in images containing their phone number and other information.  See image Example 3.  Therefore, our goal for the purpose of this grant was threefold: one, employ machine learning techniques to make obfuscated ads and phone numbers machine readable and, by extension, searchable. Two, develop classifiers to identify suspicious ads automatically based on certain types of images or suspicious text content. Finally, we designed and implemented a scalable computing infrastructure required to support deployment, so this work can be utilized in real investigations.   As a direct result of this grant we were able to develop multiple techniques to solve the challenges identified during the course of our research. Specifically, we created algorithms that are over 90% accurate in deobfuscating masked text and phone numbers. We applied image classifiers using deep learning artificial neural networks and computer vision technology to automatically detect ads showing people holding up signs or containing text superimposed on them, likely indicators of suspicious posters. Finally, we implemented a cloud-based platform which accomplishes all of this in near real time and allows investigators 24/7 access to our database of hundreds of millions of ads.  This Small Business Innovation Research Phase I grant has already had a significant impact on the ability of law enforcement agencies to fight human trafficking. The breadth of technologies developed and deployed has impacted thousands of investigations and helped hundreds of victims. Much more work remains to be done, but we at Marinus Analytics are extremely grateful to the National Science Foundation for supporting our efforts and helping us make a difference in the human tragedy that is sex trafficking.       Last Modified: 01/10/2017       Submitted by: Andreas Olligschlaeger]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
