<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>STTR Phase I:  Triboluminescent sensor system for quasi-distributed load sensing on wind blades for active control of wind turbines</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>01/01/2016</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2016</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>224999.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>224999</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07070000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>IIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Industrial Innovation &amp; Partnersh</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Benaiah Schrag</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>bschrag@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032928323</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This Small Business Technology Transfer Phase I project is for the development of a triboluminescent sensor system (ITOFPress) for quasi-distributed load sensing along the length of a wind blade for active control of wind turbines. According to experts, this innovation could result in a 20% increase in wind turbine power generation through enhanced inputs for active turbine control and better understanding of the load profile along the span of a blade. Such knowledge is critical as wind blades become larger and are installed higher. This new system will also help to protect the blades and other expensive components from damage and overload, thereby reducing operation &amp; maintenance (O&amp;M) costs and making wind energy more attractive to investors. The installation of the ITOFPress system would increase the initial capital costs of a large wind turbine by a very small amount (about a half a percent), creating a strong value proposition for turbine manufacturers and operators.  The estimated market potential for this system is expected to be $1.5 billion in 2018.   &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The intellectual merit of this project addresses the technical hurdles in developing the proposed sensor system.  The ITOFPress technology is highly sensitive to deformation-induced excitation and can withstand high loading cycles. The sensor combines the light-emitting property of ZnS:Mn with the highly desirable features of optical fibers (i.e. they are lightweight, smaller, immune to electromagnetic interference, and have the capacity for distributed sensing). The ITOFPress does not require external power at the sensing location or for signal transmission to the blade's hub, which makes it very attractive for use in wind turbines.  The sensor can accurately detect loads that are not anticipated by models which rely on inputs from inflow sensors like anemometers. In this effort, increased sensor sensitivity will be achieved through experimental design studies involving critical design factors. The sensor's long term stability will be studied by subjecting samples to flexural and compressive load cycles. Finite element analysis will be performed to establish relationships between sensor response, sensor deformation and applied load. Strain gages and load sensors will be used for sensor calibration. A lab-sized wind blade will also be instrumented and tested under compressive cyclic loading to demonstrate quasi-distributed load sensing with the new sensor system.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>12/07/2015</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>12/07/2015</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1549716</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Okenwa</FirstName>
<LastName>Okoli</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>O</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Okenwa O Okoli</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>okoli@eng.famu.fsu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>8504106352</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000484010</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>12/07/2015</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>David</FirstName>
<LastName>Olawale</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>O</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>David O Olawale</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>seunmart@gmail.com</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>8503398877</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000672801</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>12/07/2015</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Nanotechnology Patronas Group Inc</Name>
<CityName>Tallahassee</CityName>
<ZipCode>323111256</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>8504435326</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>4743 Planter Ridge Drive</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Florida</StateName>
<StateCode>FL</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>FL05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>079420057</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>NANOTECHNOLOGY PATRONAS GROUP, INC.</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[High-Performance Materials Institute, Florida State University]]></Name>
<CityName>Tallahassee</CityName>
<StateCode>FL</StateCode>
<ZipCode>323105754</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[2005 Levy Ave]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Florida</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>FL05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1505</Code>
<Text>STTR Phase I</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>036E</Code>
<Text>CIVIL INFRASTRUCTURE</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>123E</Code>
<Text>CENTERS: ADVANCED MATERIALS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1505</Code>
<Text>STTR PHASE I</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8034</Code>
<Text>Hardware Components</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0116</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2016~224999</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>This report provides information on progress made in the development of the new Triboluminescent-based sensor system (ITOFPress) for wind turbines. The ITOFPress sensor is designed to provide quasi-distributed real time load information along the length of a wind turbine blade for active control of a wind turbine. According to experts, this capability can significantly increase the power generation from existing and new turbines. It will also help in protecting the blades and other expensive turbine components like the gear train from damage due to excessive loads.</p> <p>The specific products from this project include the newly developed ITOFPress sensor system, an automated coating machine, glass fiber wind blades and an instrumented demo. The project has moved the ITOFPress sensor from an idea/concept to an actual sensor responding to cyclic compressive loading though further work is still needed in its development. Five generations of the sensor was developed and the PRR (a measure of the repeatability and reproducibility) of the signal from the sensor was reduced from 75.81 to 42.01 %. The desired value is 30 % or less.</p> <p>In addition, results of simulation studies from this project show enhanced power production (as high as 111 %) that may occur due to quasi-distributed load sensing resulting from use of sensors like the ITOFPress on the wind turbine blade.</p> <p>Five technical articles (conference and journal papers) have been produced or are in the works from this project. Extensive customer discovery and market research conducted with the NSF Beat-the Odds Boot Camp and during the project period revealed that potential customers are happy with 1 -2 % improvement in performance or power production from the use of the new sensor.</p> <p>In addition, this NSF-sponsored project has helped in increasing the research as well as technology commercialization capacities and awareness of the team (students and young engineers) that worked on the project. It has helped to expose the students and young engineers to knowledge about the wind energy sector and the operations of wind turbines. As a result of this project, NPGroup was able to host an intern and a professor on a South Hub Big Data internship program. The doctoral student was exposed to Big Data problems and opportunities in the wind energy sector. Developing the human capital needed for the renewable energy sector is critical in ensuring that the US achieves her 2020 wind energy vision as set by the US Department of Energy (DOE).</p> <p>Furthermore, our Project Engineer is starting her own technology-based business based on the knowledge and mentoring she received working at NPGroup on this project. In addition, a leader of a local angel investors group has shown great interest in the technology to bring in local investors once the sensor development has moved past the high risk early development stages. The venture arm of a multibillion dollar Japanese firm has also been in talks with NPGroup and has expressed willingness to partner with NPGroup towards the development and commercialization of the sensor technology.</p> <p>The successful development of the ITOFPress sensor for wind turbines will help to increase the power production from wind turbines. This will further help in increasing the world's clean energy production and reducing the environmental and health-wise effects of air pollution from fossil fuels. It will also help in global water conservation by reducing the number of thermal plants and the water lost in cooling such systems. Finally, it will help in protecting the nation from terrorist attacks through a more distributed and diversified energy source.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 12/30/2016<br>      Modified by: David&nbsp;O&nbsp;Olawale</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ This report provides information on progress made in the development of the new Triboluminescent-based sensor system (ITOFPress) for wind turbines. The ITOFPress sensor is designed to provide quasi-distributed real time load information along the length of a wind turbine blade for active control of a wind turbine. According to experts, this capability can significantly increase the power generation from existing and new turbines. It will also help in protecting the blades and other expensive turbine components like the gear train from damage due to excessive loads.  The specific products from this project include the newly developed ITOFPress sensor system, an automated coating machine, glass fiber wind blades and an instrumented demo. The project has moved the ITOFPress sensor from an idea/concept to an actual sensor responding to cyclic compressive loading though further work is still needed in its development. Five generations of the sensor was developed and the PRR (a measure of the repeatability and reproducibility) of the signal from the sensor was reduced from 75.81 to 42.01 %. The desired value is 30 % or less.  In addition, results of simulation studies from this project show enhanced power production (as high as 111 %) that may occur due to quasi-distributed load sensing resulting from use of sensors like the ITOFPress on the wind turbine blade.  Five technical articles (conference and journal papers) have been produced or are in the works from this project. Extensive customer discovery and market research conducted with the NSF Beat-the Odds Boot Camp and during the project period revealed that potential customers are happy with 1 -2 % improvement in performance or power production from the use of the new sensor.  In addition, this NSF-sponsored project has helped in increasing the research as well as technology commercialization capacities and awareness of the team (students and young engineers) that worked on the project. It has helped to expose the students and young engineers to knowledge about the wind energy sector and the operations of wind turbines. As a result of this project, NPGroup was able to host an intern and a professor on a South Hub Big Data internship program. The doctoral student was exposed to Big Data problems and opportunities in the wind energy sector. Developing the human capital needed for the renewable energy sector is critical in ensuring that the US achieves her 2020 wind energy vision as set by the US Department of Energy (DOE).  Furthermore, our Project Engineer is starting her own technology-based business based on the knowledge and mentoring she received working at NPGroup on this project. In addition, a leader of a local angel investors group has shown great interest in the technology to bring in local investors once the sensor development has moved past the high risk early development stages. The venture arm of a multibillion dollar Japanese firm has also been in talks with NPGroup and has expressed willingness to partner with NPGroup towards the development and commercialization of the sensor technology.  The successful development of the ITOFPress sensor for wind turbines will help to increase the power production from wind turbines. This will further help in increasing the world's clean energy production and reducing the environmental and health-wise effects of air pollution from fossil fuels. It will also help in global water conservation by reducing the number of thermal plants and the water lost in cooling such systems. Finally, it will help in protecting the nation from terrorist attacks through a more distributed and diversified energy source.       Last Modified: 12/30/2016       Submitted by: David O Olawale]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
