<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Collaborative Research: EAGER: Renewables: A function space theory for continuous-time flexibility scheduling in electricity markets</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/15/2015</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>02/28/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>149604.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>149604</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07010000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>ECCS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Electrical, Commun &amp; Cyber Sys</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Eyad Abed</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>eabed@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032920000</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Current electric power grid operating procedures have worked well for many years in compensating for the variability and uncertainty of electric power load by programmed changes in generation. This has contributed to the reliable and economic delivery of electric power to millions of customers. However, the rising level of renewable generation injected into the power grid adds a higher level of variability and uncertainty. Moreover, in several markets that are aggressively pursuing green energy, large, fast, and unexpected power changes are leading to frequent sudden demands for ramping power generation, so-called ramping scarcity events, while increasing the operating cost of the systems. This project takes a new modeling that is expected to yield algorithms for scheduling of generation resources that is more effective for systems with high renewable penetration. The main focus of the work is what is known as the unit commitment problem, which involves scheduling of generating units to compensate for variability in power demand. While currently unit commitment is considered in terms of generation schedules that change on an hourly basis, the project considers a scheduling over shorter time intervals to adequately track changing supply and demand in highly variable power networks. This research can eliminate a fundamental barrier to large-scale renewable integration, thus paving the way to sustainable, reliable, and economic integration of renewable electricity resources. This would contribute to reaching national targets on energy independence and greenhouse gas reductions. While the approach offers a radically different point of view, it does not fundamentally alter the architecture of the wholesale market, nor the complexity of the scheduling problem, so the integration of the project's ideas in real markets is expected to be practically feasible.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The main hypothesis in this work is that ramping scarcity events are evidence of a severe bottleneck that lies in the prevalent discrete time formulation of the power system operation problem in general, and in particular to two interdependent factors: 1) the approximation behind the structure of the unit commitment (UC) problem decision space, and 2) the structure of the operating cost functions of the generating units and other flexible resources, who are allowed to bid for energy but not for ramping. The current UC decision space includes only hourly commitment decision points and hourly generation schedules, which form a piecewise constant generation trajectory for each generating unit. These trajectories are a zero-order approximation of their higher-order continuous-time counterparts that populate the actual UC decision space. In fact, the information about the variability of the net-load is poorly captured in the hourly UC model, and a wealth of information about the variations of the net-load is lost. In order to address the increased ramping demand, instead of limiting the decision space to the commitment state and generation trajectory, it would be advantageous to also include the first derivative of the generation trajectory, i.e. the ramping trajectory, as a decision variable among the degrees of freedom, opening the door to receiving competitive offers that capture the joint cost of generation and of ramping at each time instant. Recognizing that a continuous-time trajectory bears additional degrees of freedom that could be chosen as part of the optimization decision space, a new approach is proposed that incorporates variables that directly represent additional degrees of freedom and can facilitate appropriately pricing them. The notion utilized is the well-established notion of function space that allows the UC problem to be formulated as a Mixed Integer Linear Programming (MILP) problem, currently in vogue, but with additional degrees of freedom to balance the variability. Preliminary results clearly show that the introduction of explicit ramping trajectory variables alter the priority given to different units in the schedule, reduces the total operation cost, and considerably reduces ramping scarcity events. It is also noticed that introducing sub-hourly decision variables is more complex and leads to decreased efficiency compared to the function space representation, which is tailored to increase the accuracy in representing both objectives and constraints.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>09/11/2015</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>09/11/2015</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1549923</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Anna</FirstName>
<LastName>Scaglione</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Anna Scaglione</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>Anna.Scaglione@asu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6072270401</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000384260</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/11/2015</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Arizona State University</Name>
<CityName>TEMPE</CityName>
<ZipCode>852816011</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>4809655479</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>ORSPA</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[660 South Mill Avenue, Suite 310]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Arizona</StateName>
<StateCode>AZ</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>09</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>AZ09</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>943360412</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>ARIZONA STATE UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>806345658</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Arizona State University]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>AZ</StateCode>
<ZipCode>852816011</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Arizona</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>09</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>AZ09</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7607</Code>
<Text>EPCN-Energy-Power-Ctrl-Netwrks</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>155E</Code>
<Text>Electric power networks</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7916</Code>
<Text>EAGER</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0114</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2015~149604</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><!-- p.p1 {margin: 0.0px 0.0px 0.0px 0.0px; font: 12.0px Helvetica; -webkit-text-stroke: #000000} span.s1 {font-kerning: none} --> <p class="p1"><span class="s1">In this project we studied the formulation of classic optimization problems in power systems, such as Economic Dispatch, Optimal Power Flow and Unit Communtment, in continuous time.&nbsp;</span></p> <p class="p1">The motivation for looking at this problem is the scarcity of ramping resources and their increasing importance motivated by the variability of power resources, particularly due to the addition of solar power, which exacerbates the need of fast ramping units in the early morning and early evening hours. From our formulation we can show that the solution for the marginal price can be found through Euler-Lagrange equations and we argue that this price signal better reflects the market value of power in the presence of significant ramps in net-load.</p> <p class="p1">More importantly, our work has shown that it is possible to map the continuous time variational problem in a tractable numerical problem that is asymptotically optimal, using a signal space representation of the continuous time load and the corresponding decision variables, i.e. the generation trajectories. We have shown that a spline expansion onto Bernstein polynomial is most appropriate as a signal space and discussed how enforcing continuity of the trajectory changes how the commitment decisions are handled, to allow for the smooth transition of the tranjectory from off to on and viceversa. Our framework can allow a complete representation of contraints on the derivative and the integral of the power trajectories, allowing the suppliers in power system operations to also bid for ramping and energy in addition to power.&nbsp;</p> <p class="p1">In the last part of this project, we looked at the stochastic counterpart of the unit commintment formulation, introducing a Stochastic Continuous Time Unit Commitment (SCTUC).</p> <p class="p1">This entailed two main advances:</p> <p class="p1">1) A dynamic formulation of the SUC, which allows to update commitment decisiond over a rolling horizon.&nbsp;</p> <p class="p1">2) The construction of a scenario tree that represents continuous time trajectories that approximate in the mean-square sense the actual sigma-algebra of the continuous time continuous space process.</p> <p class="p1">In addition to providing a smooth transition for all generation trajectories that are potentially needed to cover the bundle of scenarios that are possible, what we have shown is that the spline representation of scenarios has the added benefit of allowing a better representation error with far fewer scenarios, thereby allowing to extend the interval that correspond to a certain stage of the optimization and, correspondly, reduce the number of stages necessary to cover a decision horizon. Because the complexity of Stochastic UC problems is exponential with the number of stages, our result shows that we can not only better capture interhourly variations of the net-load demand, but that we can generally represent with fewer representative scenarios the future, reducing the complexity of the stochastic optimization problem. &nbsp; &nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 04/13/2017<br>      Modified by: Anna&nbsp;Scaglione</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ In this project we studied the formulation of classic optimization problems in power systems, such as Economic Dispatch, Optimal Power Flow and Unit Communtment, in continuous time.  The motivation for looking at this problem is the scarcity of ramping resources and their increasing importance motivated by the variability of power resources, particularly due to the addition of solar power, which exacerbates the need of fast ramping units in the early morning and early evening hours. From our formulation we can show that the solution for the marginal price can be found through Euler-Lagrange equations and we argue that this price signal better reflects the market value of power in the presence of significant ramps in net-load. More importantly, our work has shown that it is possible to map the continuous time variational problem in a tractable numerical problem that is asymptotically optimal, using a signal space representation of the continuous time load and the corresponding decision variables, i.e. the generation trajectories. We have shown that a spline expansion onto Bernstein polynomial is most appropriate as a signal space and discussed how enforcing continuity of the trajectory changes how the commitment decisions are handled, to allow for the smooth transition of the tranjectory from off to on and viceversa. Our framework can allow a complete representation of contraints on the derivative and the integral of the power trajectories, allowing the suppliers in power system operations to also bid for ramping and energy in addition to power.  In the last part of this project, we looked at the stochastic counterpart of the unit commintment formulation, introducing a Stochastic Continuous Time Unit Commitment (SCTUC). This entailed two main advances: 1) A dynamic formulation of the SUC, which allows to update commitment decisiond over a rolling horizon.  2) The construction of a scenario tree that represents continuous time trajectories that approximate in the mean-square sense the actual sigma-algebra of the continuous time continuous space process. In addition to providing a smooth transition for all generation trajectories that are potentially needed to cover the bundle of scenarios that are possible, what we have shown is that the spline representation of scenarios has the added benefit of allowing a better representation error with far fewer scenarios, thereby allowing to extend the interval that correspond to a certain stage of the optimization and, correspondly, reduce the number of stages necessary to cover a decision horizon. Because the complexity of Stochastic UC problems is exponential with the number of stages, our result shows that we can not only better capture interhourly variations of the net-load demand, but that we can generally represent with fewer representative scenarios the future, reducing the complexity of the stochastic optimization problem.           Last Modified: 04/13/2017       Submitted by: Anna Scaglione]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
