<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Dynamics and Kinematics of the Monsoon Anticyclones</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>03/01/2016</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>02/29/2020</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>291049.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>291049</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>06020106</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>GEO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>AGS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Atmospheric &amp; Geospace Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Varavut Limpasuvan</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>vlimpasu@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922746</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The Asian monsoon is one of the most important weather and climate systems on Earth.  During the summer, warm moist air from the tropical oceans moves onto the southern and eastern parts of the Asian continent.  This leads to convective storms, which provide critical precipitation and water supplies for a region that is home to several billion people.  A similar but weaker monsoon circulation exists over North America.  Monsoon storms also transport water and human-produced pollutants to great altitudes.  These pollutants can have major effects on the chemistry of the atmosphere, including the stratospheric ozone layer, which protects living things from harmful solar radiation.  Using computer simulations and atmospheric observations, this research will investigate the physical processes responsible for the Asian and North American monsoons and how they transport pollutants from near the Earth's surface throughout the atmosphere.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The monsoons directly affect billions of people around the globe and have important indirect effects on the Earth's climate and the composition of the atmosphere.  Changes in the circulation and composition of the atmosphere have the potential to disrupt physical, economic, social, and political systems around the globe.  By improving our understanding of the physical processes responsible for the monsoon circulations, this study will advance our understanding of the present climate and reduce uncertainties in predictions of future climate change.  This will lead to better guidance for social and economic policymakers.  In addition, this project will train graduate students for careers in science and related fields.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>02/16/2016</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>02/16/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.050</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1550611</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Kenneth</FirstName>
<LastName>Bowman</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>P</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Kenneth P Bowman</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>k-bowman@tamu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>9798624060</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000417410</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>02/16/2016</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Texas A&amp;M University</Name>
<CityName>College Station</CityName>
<ZipCode>778454375</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>9798626777</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>400 Harvey Mitchell Pkwy South</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[Suite 300]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Texas</StateName>
<StateCode>TX</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>17</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>TX17</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>020271826</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>TEXAS A &amp; M UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>042915991</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Texas A&M University Main Campus]]></Name>
<CityName>College Station</CityName>
<StateCode>TX</StateCode>
<ZipCode>778433150</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[3150 TAMU]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Texas</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>17</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>TX17</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>5740</Code>
<Text>Climate &amp; Large-Scale Dynamics</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>OTHR</Code>
<Text>OTHER RESEARCH OR EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0116</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2016~291049</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>During the summer season (June through August) in the northern hemisphere, the largest feature of the atmospheric circulation is the Asian monsoon. &nbsp;Near the Earth's surface, warm moist air from the Indian and Pacific Oceans flows onto the southern and eastern parts of the Asian continent, where it provides the energy source for convective storms that produce heavy rainfall. &nbsp;A large part of the Earth's population depends on monsoon rains for agriculture and water supplies. &nbsp;The air that rises in monsoon storms produces a huge high-pressure system (anticyclone) in the upper troposphere. &nbsp;In the northern hemisphere the air in an anticyclone circulates clockwise. &nbsp;The troposphere is the lowest layer of the atmosphere and contains most of the storms, clouds, and other weather phenomena; above the troposphere is the stratosphere. &nbsp;The stratosphere contains the ozone layer, which protects the Earth's surface from harmful ultraviolet radiation from the sun. &nbsp;Monsoon storms carry water into the upper troposphere, along with pollution and atmospheric particles. &nbsp;These pollutants can affect the chemistry and climate of the atmosphere, including stratospheric ozone.</p> <p><br />A similar, though weaker, monsoon circulation exists over North America. &nbsp;It also has an anticyclone in the upper troposphere, but the processes the produce the North American monsoon are not well understood.</p> <p><br />The purpose of this project is to answer two main scientific questions: &nbsp;Is the North American monsoon driven by storms and precipitation over North America, or is it somehow connected to the stronger Asian monsoon? &nbsp;How does air escape from the anticyclones into the rest of the atmosphere?</p> <p><br />Using a state-of-the-art computer model of the atmospheric circulation, we have demonstrated that the North American monsoon anticyclone is driven by convection over and near North America and is not directly related to the Asian monsoon. &nbsp;That is, the Asian and North American monsoons are independent of each other. &nbsp;We also showed that the Asian monsoon is stronger than the North American monsoon because more rain falls over Asia than over North America, and because the rain falls at higher latitudes. &nbsp;The differences in the location and intensity of the rainfall arise from the different geography of the Asian and North American continents and the surrounding oceans.</p> <p><br />Using observations of the circulation of the Asian monsoon, we show that the shape and strength of the monsoon anticyclone varies considerably from day to day. &nbsp;These variations can stir the air within the anticyclone quickly. &nbsp;Air from the anticyclone can break off and form separate, smaller anticyclones. &nbsp;At times these smaller anticyclones can move eastward all the way across the Pacific Ocean to North America, carrying air from the Asian monsoon anticyclone with them. &nbsp;On rare occasions smaller anticyclones break off from the western end of the main anticyclone and move westward across Africa.</p> <p>This research will help us to understand how the monsoon circulation will change in the future as the composition of the atmosphere changes and the climate warms. &nbsp;It is also a step toward a better understanding of how pollutants are transported from the Earth's surface, where the are produced, throughout the global atmosphere.</p> <p><br />This project trained a Ph.D. student in atmospheric science.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 04/02/2020<br>      Modified by: Kenneth&nbsp;P&nbsp;Bowman</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ During the summer season (June through August) in the northern hemisphere, the largest feature of the atmospheric circulation is the Asian monsoon.  Near the Earth's surface, warm moist air from the Indian and Pacific Oceans flows onto the southern and eastern parts of the Asian continent, where it provides the energy source for convective storms that produce heavy rainfall.  A large part of the Earth's population depends on monsoon rains for agriculture and water supplies.  The air that rises in monsoon storms produces a huge high-pressure system (anticyclone) in the upper troposphere.  In the northern hemisphere the air in an anticyclone circulates clockwise.  The troposphere is the lowest layer of the atmosphere and contains most of the storms, clouds, and other weather phenomena; above the troposphere is the stratosphere.  The stratosphere contains the ozone layer, which protects the Earth's surface from harmful ultraviolet radiation from the sun.  Monsoon storms carry water into the upper troposphere, along with pollution and atmospheric particles.  These pollutants can affect the chemistry and climate of the atmosphere, including stratospheric ozone.   A similar, though weaker, monsoon circulation exists over North America.  It also has an anticyclone in the upper troposphere, but the processes the produce the North American monsoon are not well understood.   The purpose of this project is to answer two main scientific questions:  Is the North American monsoon driven by storms and precipitation over North America, or is it somehow connected to the stronger Asian monsoon?  How does air escape from the anticyclones into the rest of the atmosphere?   Using a state-of-the-art computer model of the atmospheric circulation, we have demonstrated that the North American monsoon anticyclone is driven by convection over and near North America and is not directly related to the Asian monsoon.  That is, the Asian and North American monsoons are independent of each other.  We also showed that the Asian monsoon is stronger than the North American monsoon because more rain falls over Asia than over North America, and because the rain falls at higher latitudes.  The differences in the location and intensity of the rainfall arise from the different geography of the Asian and North American continents and the surrounding oceans.   Using observations of the circulation of the Asian monsoon, we show that the shape and strength of the monsoon anticyclone varies considerably from day to day.  These variations can stir the air within the anticyclone quickly.  Air from the anticyclone can break off and form separate, smaller anticyclones.  At times these smaller anticyclones can move eastward all the way across the Pacific Ocean to North America, carrying air from the Asian monsoon anticyclone with them.  On rare occasions smaller anticyclones break off from the western end of the main anticyclone and move westward across Africa.  This research will help us to understand how the monsoon circulation will change in the future as the composition of the atmosphere changes and the climate warms.  It is also a step toward a better understanding of how pollutants are transported from the Earth's surface, where the are produced, throughout the global atmosphere.   This project trained a Ph.D. student in atmospheric science.       Last Modified: 04/02/2020       Submitted by: Kenneth P Bowman]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
