<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>I-Corps:  D-Ready Mobile Guide</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2015</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>01/31/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>50000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>50000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07070000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>IIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Industrial Innovation &amp; Partnersh</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Steven Konsek</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>skonsek@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927021</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This project focuses on techniques for survey analysis that can inform decision making -- potentially in a broad range of areas.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;D-Ready will use contemporary machine learning techniques to process and filter the data the team will collate regarding such areas as choice preferences. The proposed technology will be deployed with two goals in mind.  A survey design methodology will be used to help ensure that decision-selection guidelines are unbiased for individual user. This is important because the more unbiased the decision support product, the more widely it will be trusted and used. The team will also use cursor-tracking technology to develop an in-depth statistical picture of how individual users view decision-support site-apps. This will allow for the team to use nonlinear regression and classification methods to segment users into distinct types. The insights learned from these analyses will be valuable to support decision makers in a broad range of applications. Applying the customer discovery process during the I-Corps curriculum, the team intends to come up with a more complete value proposition that it will provide and refine the product features that will be most useful.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;D-Ready is envisioned as an online and mobile decision support guide that creates customized information for users that is simple, convenient and unbiased. The proposed technology has potentially broad applications in several areas including marketing, for example, where a three-step strategy of 1) defining an attraction for a certain population, 2) harvesting detailed interactive behavior data while users react to that attraction, and finally 3) analyzing that data for the purpose of market segmentation, represents a powerful new form of survey collection.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/23/2015</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>12/21/2015</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1550507</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Paul</FirstName>
<LastName>Hahn</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>R</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Paul R Hahn</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>prhahn@asu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>4803109997</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000699286</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/23/2015</StartDate>
<EndDate>12/21/2015</EndDate>
<RoleCode>Former Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Paula</FirstName>
<LastName>Worthington</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Paula Worthington</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>pworthington@uchicago.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>7737028669</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000702246</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>12/21/2015</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Ethan</FirstName>
<LastName>Bueno de Mesquita</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Ethan Bueno de Mesquita</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>bdm@uchicago.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>7738349874</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000084768</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>12/21/2015</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Chicago</Name>
<CityName>Chicago</CityName>
<ZipCode>606372612</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>7737028669</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>6054 South Drexel Avenue</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[Suite 300]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Illinois</StateName>
<StateCode>IL</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>IL01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>005421136</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF CHICAGO, THE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>005421136</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Chicago]]></Name>
<CityName>Chicago</CityName>
<StateCode>IL</StateCode>
<ZipCode>606371610</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[5807 S. Woodlawn Avenue]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Illinois</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>IL01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>8023</Code>
<Text>I-Corps</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0115</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2015~50000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>BallotReady is a nonpartisan online voter guide to every race and referendum on the ballot. Through this project, BallotReady sought to assist voters in making decisions all the way down the ballot and increase voter turnout.</p> <p>BallotReady began by interviewing 100 voters about their voting habits, sources of information, and civic engagement. Our interviews validated the central problem. Most voters enter the voting booth prepared to vote for president but unprepared for everything else. As a result, voters told us that they guess or left blanks. Some voters also said that they didn't vote in local elections because they didn't understand the ballot.</p> <p>Our broader take-away based on this research was that voters lacked a coherent schema for making sense of local politics. While civically-engaged voters can compare candidates at the federal level based on traditional categories - left wing, right wing, Democrat, Republican - those terms often did not apply to nonpartisan or municipal offices. For instance, voters in Chicago were asked to choose between a field of all Democrats where cleavages between candidates and sides were much more opaque.</p> <p>BallotReady used the results of this research to build a pilot online voter guide for the Kentucky election. We had over 13,000 voters come to the site and we gained valueable insight into how we could improve our platform.</p> <p>Over the following 6 months, we continued to iterate with voter guides for the Illinois, Colorado, Maryland, and Kentucky primaries. In the fall of 2016, we launched in 12 states, covering 15,000 candidates and with over 1 million visits to our site. &nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 02/01/2017<br>      Modified by: Ethan&nbsp;Bueno De Mesquita</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ BallotReady is a nonpartisan online voter guide to every race and referendum on the ballot. Through this project, BallotReady sought to assist voters in making decisions all the way down the ballot and increase voter turnout.  BallotReady began by interviewing 100 voters about their voting habits, sources of information, and civic engagement. Our interviews validated the central problem. Most voters enter the voting booth prepared to vote for president but unprepared for everything else. As a result, voters told us that they guess or left blanks. Some voters also said that they didn't vote in local elections because they didn't understand the ballot.  Our broader take-away based on this research was that voters lacked a coherent schema for making sense of local politics. While civically-engaged voters can compare candidates at the federal level based on traditional categories - left wing, right wing, Democrat, Republican - those terms often did not apply to nonpartisan or municipal offices. For instance, voters in Chicago were asked to choose between a field of all Democrats where cleavages between candidates and sides were much more opaque.  BallotReady used the results of this research to build a pilot online voter guide for the Kentucky election. We had over 13,000 voters come to the site and we gained valueable insight into how we could improve our platform.  Over the following 6 months, we continued to iterate with voter guides for the Illinois, Colorado, Maryland, and Kentucky primaries. In the fall of 2016, we launched in 12 states, covering 15,000 candidates and with over 1 million visits to our site.         Last Modified: 02/01/2017       Submitted by: Ethan Bueno De Mesquita]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
