<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Scavenging Thermal-noise Energy and Quantum Fluctuations for Self-powered Time-stamping and Sensing</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/15/2015</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2020</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>344387.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>352387</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07010000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>ECCS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Electrical, Commun &amp; Cyber Sys</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Mohammod Ali</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This research project is investigating self-powered sensing devices, circuits and algorithms for event time stamping and event reconstruction. As a proof-of-concept we are applying these techniques for designing passive, battery-less structural health monitoring (SHM) sensors that can continuously sense and time-stamp important and rare events that could have occurred during the operating life span of the structure. For instance in orthopedic implants like knee or hip implants, the use of these techniques would be able convey temporal information about any mechanical misalignment or any abnormal usage of the implant. This information could be useful to surgeons in diagnosing and planning of any revision surgery. For civil and aerospace structures, these techniques could be used to determine when the structure was subjected to large mechanical deformations or strains; or when a rare, unwanted mechanical impact with the structure could have occurred.  In combination with computer models, the time-stamped event information could be used in prognosticating impending failures and can be used in determining condition-based maintenance schedules.  Thus, the proposed self-powered sensing technology could be a key facilitator in achieving the grand vision for the internet-of-things, where millions of passive, inexpensive sensors could become an integral part of "smart" structures (civil, aerospace, mechanical and biomechanical) that can self-diagnose its own catastrophic failure. As a part of the outreach activities, the project is developing a cross-disciplinary forum between the electrical, structural and biomedical engineers; and includes design of educational modules and organization of tutorial and special sessions in the area of self-powered sensors. Also, in addition to the mentoring of graduate and undergraduate students, the project is also fostering student entrepreneurship activities in the area of sensors and structural health monitoring.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The intellectual merit of the proposed research lies in the investigation of thermodynamically and quantum-mechanically driven electron transport phenomena that can be used to implement perpetual timers and clocks. Different device and layout topologies are being investigated that will lead to timers with different dynamical responses and to timers that can continuously operate over the entire monitoring period. The physics of the timer is being combined with the physics of the piezoelectricity driven impact-ionized hot-electron injection process to achieve self-powered monitoring of mechanical strain when the sensor is embedded or implanted inside a mechanically active structure. Using an array of these timer-modulated hot-electron injectors, the project is investigating sparse reconstruction algorithms that will be able to time stamp salient strain-related events. As a proof-of-concept, the circuits implementing the self-powered timers and the self-powered strain sensors are being prototyped in a standard CMOS process are also being integrated with previously developed radio-frequency identification (RFID) and wireless sensing system-on-chip architectures. This hybrid energy scavenging configuration will not only enable continuous, self-powered monitoring of salient and rare events but will also enable wireless retrieval of the sensor data along with remote initialization and configuration of the sensor under user command and control.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/20/2015</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/30/2019</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1550096</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Shantanu</FirstName>
<LastName>Chakrabartty</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Shantanu Chakrabartty</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>shantanu@wustl.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>3149354583</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000491083</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/20/2015</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Washington University</Name>
<CityName>Saint Louis</CityName>
<ZipCode>631304862</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>3147474134</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>CAMPUS BOX 1054</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[1 Brookings Drive]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Missouri</StateName>
<StateCode>MO</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MO01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>068552207</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>WASHINGTON UNIVERSITY, THE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>068552207</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Washington University]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>MO</StateCode>
<ZipCode>631304899</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Missouri</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MO01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7564</Code>
<Text>CCSS-Comms Circuits &amp; Sens Sys</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>096E</Code>
<Text>High freq comm/sensing circuits</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9251</Code>
<Text>REU SUPP-Res Exp for Ugrd Supp</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0115</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0116</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2015~344387</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2016~8000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Self-powering of integrated circuits is attractive for sensing applications where the availability of energy is scarce, for instance, embedded or implantable applications or for applications where large-scale remote powering is not practical, such as passive Internet of Things. Unlike conventional energy scavenging systems, self-powered sensors scavenge their operational energy directly from the signal being sensed, thus obviating the need for periodic sampling or wake-up interrupts. Unfortunately, compared with a conventional interrupt-based paradigm, the asynchronous self-powering paradigm is unable to sense the time-of-occurrence for an event. This is due to the unavailability of a time reference or a watch-dog clock, both of which require continuous powering.</p> <p><span style="white-space: pre;"> </span>In this research project, we investigated a hybrid self-powered sensor architecture (shown in Figure. 1.) that can facilitate self-powered time stamping of mechanical events, for example physical impact or changes in structural strain. The intellectual merits of this project involved investigation into the three modules, as shown in Figure.1.&nbsp; (a) Self-Powered time-keeping module - which serves as a source of a precision time reference over a desired monitoring period. Since the monitoring period could be more than three years, the power levels at which a chip-scale timekeeping device needs to operate (using only the energy stored on an integrated capacitor) have to be below an atto-watt. We reported an time-keeping device based on the physics of Fowler-Nordheim (FN) quantum tunneling that is able to operate at this power level. We showed that a self-compensating physics of electron tunneling through a triangular FN tunneling barrier can implement a precision time reference. (b) Self-Powered Injector - While thermodynamic and quantum fluctuations could potentially be used to implement system clocks and timers, the energy is too scarce for sensing, computation, or data storage. In the proposed system, we combine the operational primitives of the FN timers with the physics of a piezoelectricity-driven impact-ionized hot-electron injector (p-IHEI) device to time stamp mechanical events and for non-volatile storage within a pico-watt to nano-watt power budget. Fig. 2. shows the prototype of a hybrid timer-injector device that was developed in this project and the measured results show the self-powered time-stamping of mechanical events. (c) Programming and Readout module - which is used for initialization, calibration, or transfer of the stored measurements.&nbsp;</p> <p><span style="white-space: pre;"> </span>With respect to the broader impacts of this project, the proposed self-powered sensing methods could be the key facilitator for achieving the grand vision where millions of sensors could become an integral part of the next generation of smart structures. Due to their small form factor and low-cost these sensors could be embedded inside composites, civil infrastructure or attached to the surface of hard-to-access structural components such as rotors of aircrafts, aircraft wings, and turbine blades, without compromising the structural or aerodynamic integrity of the host structure. The project has supported the doctoral thesis of three Ph.D. students, two of them are female students. The project has also provided research opportunities for several undergraduate students. The project has resulted in several research publications in IEEE journals and conferences. The research has resulted in one issued US patent and the project has also supported technology translation activities pertaining to the self-powered time-keeping device.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 11/15/2020<br>      Modified by: Shantanu&nbsp;Chakrabartty</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Images (<span id="selectedPhoto0">1</span> of <span class="totalNumber"></span>)           </div> <div class="galControls" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2020/1550096/1550096_10363321_1605451956030_NSFOutcomeFigure1--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2020/1550096/1550096_10363321_1605451956030_NSFOutcomeFigure1--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Concept of hybrid self-powered sensor"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2020/1550096/1550096_10363321_1605451956030_NSFOutcomeFigure1--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Concept of hybrid self-powered sensor"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Fig. 1. Multi-scale powering requirements for self-powered sensing of event time-of-occurrence.</div> <div class="imageCredit">shantanu chakrabartty</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Shantanu&nbsp;Chakrabartty</div> <div class="imageTitle">Concept of hybrid self-powered sensor</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2020/1550096/1550096_10363321_1605452169263_NSFOutcomeFigure2--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2020/1550096/1550096_10363321_1605452169263_NSFOutcomeFigure2--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Prototype self-powered time-of-occurrence sensor"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2020/1550096/1550096_10363321_1605452169263_NSFOutcomeFigure2--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Prototype self-powered time-of-occurrence sensor"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Fig. 2. Micrographs and measured results obtained from the FN-timer chipset and hot-electron injector chipsets used to design for designing self-powered time-of-occurrence sensor.</div> <div class="imageCredit">shantanu chakrabartty</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Shantanu&nbsp;Chakrabartty</div> <div class="imageTitle">Prototype self-powered time-of-occurrence sensor</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Self-powering of integrated circuits is attractive for sensing applications where the availability of energy is scarce, for instance, embedded or implantable applications or for applications where large-scale remote powering is not practical, such as passive Internet of Things. Unlike conventional energy scavenging systems, self-powered sensors scavenge their operational energy directly from the signal being sensed, thus obviating the need for periodic sampling or wake-up interrupts. Unfortunately, compared with a conventional interrupt-based paradigm, the asynchronous self-powering paradigm is unable to sense the time-of-occurrence for an event. This is due to the unavailability of a time reference or a watch-dog clock, both of which require continuous powering.   In this research project, we investigated a hybrid self-powered sensor architecture (shown in Figure. 1.) that can facilitate self-powered time stamping of mechanical events, for example physical impact or changes in structural strain. The intellectual merits of this project involved investigation into the three modules, as shown in Figure.1.  (a) Self-Powered time-keeping module - which serves as a source of a precision time reference over a desired monitoring period. Since the monitoring period could be more than three years, the power levels at which a chip-scale timekeeping device needs to operate (using only the energy stored on an integrated capacitor) have to be below an atto-watt. We reported an time-keeping device based on the physics of Fowler-Nordheim (FN) quantum tunneling that is able to operate at this power level. We showed that a self-compensating physics of electron tunneling through a triangular FN tunneling barrier can implement a precision time reference. (b) Self-Powered Injector - While thermodynamic and quantum fluctuations could potentially be used to implement system clocks and timers, the energy is too scarce for sensing, computation, or data storage. In the proposed system, we combine the operational primitives of the FN timers with the physics of a piezoelectricity-driven impact-ionized hot-electron injector (p-IHEI) device to time stamp mechanical events and for non-volatile storage within a pico-watt to nano-watt power budget. Fig. 2. shows the prototype of a hybrid timer-injector device that was developed in this project and the measured results show the self-powered time-stamping of mechanical events. (c) Programming and Readout module - which is used for initialization, calibration, or transfer of the stored measurements.    With respect to the broader impacts of this project, the proposed self-powered sensing methods could be the key facilitator for achieving the grand vision where millions of sensors could become an integral part of the next generation of smart structures. Due to their small form factor and low-cost these sensors could be embedded inside composites, civil infrastructure or attached to the surface of hard-to-access structural components such as rotors of aircrafts, aircraft wings, and turbine blades, without compromising the structural or aerodynamic integrity of the host structure. The project has supported the doctoral thesis of three Ph.D. students, two of them are female students. The project has also provided research opportunities for several undergraduate students. The project has resulted in several research publications in IEEE journals and conferences. The research has resulted in one issued US patent and the project has also supported technology translation activities pertaining to the self-powered time-keeping device.          Last Modified: 11/15/2020       Submitted by: Shantanu Chakrabartty]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
