<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Mutational Analysis of Maize Embryo Development</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>03/01/2016</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>201110.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>201110</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>08090000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>BIO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>IOS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Integrative Organismal Systems</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Clifford Weil</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>cweil@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924668</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This action supports a research and training plan to broaden participation of Native American Indians in biology. The project will support Dale C. Brunelle to complete doctoral research at the University of North Dakota in the lab of sponsoring scientist Dr. William F. Sheridan. The goal of the research is to identify and characterize genes crucial for all aspects of maize embryo development using functional genomics as well as traditional genetics and molecular biology strategies.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Training objectives include genetics, developmental biology, and functional genomics. Broader impacts include broadening the participation of Native American Indians as independent investigators with Ph.D.s in the Biological Sciences.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>02/29/2016</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/17/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.074</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1550315</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>William</FirstName>
<LastName>Sheridan</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>F</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>William F Sheridan</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>bill.sheridan@und.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>7017774479</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000262829</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>02/29/2016</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of North Dakota Main Campus</Name>
<CityName>Grand Forks</CityName>
<ZipCode>582027306</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>7017774151</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>264 Centennial Dr Stop 7306</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>North Dakota</StateName>
<StateCode>ND</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>00</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>ND00</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>102280781</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF NORTH DAKOTA</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>102280781</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of North Dakota Main Campus]]></Name>
<CityName>Grand Forks</CityName>
<StateCode>ND</StateCode>
<ZipCode>582029019</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[Stop 9019]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>North Dakota</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>00</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>ND00</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1329</Code>
<Text>Plant Genome Research Project</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1228</Code>
<Text>MINORITY INVOLVEMENT -- BIO</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7577</Code>
<Text>PLANT GENOME RESEARCH RESOURCE</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9109</Code>
<Text>AGRICULTURAL BIOTECHNOLOGY</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9179</Code>
<Text>GRADUATE INVOLVEMENT</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>BIOT</Code>
<Text>BIOTECHNOLOGY</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0116</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2016~201110</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><strong>Project Outcomes Report for the General Public</strong></p> <p>There are three broader impacts of this NSF-supported project.</p> <p><strong>Project Goals </strong></p> <p>First, this project aimed to increase the number of Native American Indians Ph.Ds. in the STEM disciplines by supporting Dale C. Brunelle in his graduate studies in the Biology department at UND.&nbsp; Dale is a registered member of the Turtle Mountain Band of the Chippewa.</p> <p>Second, this project aimed to extend the knowledge base for understanding the genetic regulation of maize embryo development.&nbsp; This was successfully pursued by conducting a screening of a large collection of mutations we produced by chemical mutagenesis. We searched for lethal mutations that specifically impaired embryo development but did not significantly affect the endosperm, which comprises the bulk of the maize kernel.&nbsp; Our isolation and genetic and morphological characterization of the mutants has set the stage for mapping these genes to their precise locations in the maize chromosomes and the subsequent analysis of the DNA sequences of these genes and the analysis of the proteins or RNA molecules these genes code for.</p> <p>Third, this project aimed to report the progress on the project to the maize genetics community and the larger scientific world by presenting our results at scientific conferences and by publishing our results in the peer-reviewed journal titled G3:GeneslGenomeslGenetics.</p> <p><strong>Outcomes</strong></p> <p>First, Dale Brunelle completed his graduate program and received his PhD degree on December 8, 2018.&nbsp; Dr. Brunelle is the first Native American Indian to receive a PhD degree from the Biology department at the University of North Dakota since the founding of the university in 1883.</p> <p>Second, we have succeeded in isolating 45 heritable recessive mutations and examined the mutant embryo morphology of 34 of these mutants.&nbsp; By genetic testing we have identified two pairs of mutations where each mutation of a pair resulted from an independent mutation event but both members of the pair are located in the same gene.&nbsp; This is important because this favorable situation will aid in the mapping and DNA sequencing of the mutated gene.</p> <p>Third, we have published our initial results on the screening and genetic and morphological analysis of 34 of our 45 mutants in a research paper titled &ldquo;Genetic Screening for EMS-Induced Maize Embryo-Specific Mutants Altered in Embryo Morphogenesis&rdquo; in the November 2017 issue of G3:GeneslGenomeslGenetics 7:3559-3570.&nbsp; We also have regularly reported our research progress at the Annual Maize Genetics Conferences.</p> <p><strong>Future Global Outcomes</strong></p> <p>An additional potential outcome of our basic research is to aid in increasing worldwide food production by genetic modification of three major cereal crops:&nbsp; corn (maize), sorghum, and millet.&nbsp; This potential increase will result from both extending the geographic range of cultivation of these cereals, but also in modifying their growth characteristics so as to increase their yield and tolerance of environmental stresses.&nbsp; The entire DNA sequences of all three species has been determined.&nbsp; Our future successes and those of other investigators in identifying and characterizing the genes in these cereals that control plant development and reproduction will enable the use of new molecular techniques to modify the genes of corn, sorghum, and millet.&nbsp; We can anticipate the exchange of genetic information (genes) among these three species by molecular techniques so as to produce new hybrids exhibiting the most favorable features of each.&nbsp; This will be particularly valuable for crop production in the western regions of the Dakotas in the U.S. and in the Horn of Africa (Ethiopia, Sudan, and Somalia). &nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 09/23/2019<br>      Modified by: William&nbsp;F&nbsp;Sheridan</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Project Outcomes Report for the General Public  There are three broader impacts of this NSF-supported project.  Project Goals   First, this project aimed to increase the number of Native American Indians Ph.Ds. in the STEM disciplines by supporting Dale C. Brunelle in his graduate studies in the Biology department at UND.  Dale is a registered member of the Turtle Mountain Band of the Chippewa.  Second, this project aimed to extend the knowledge base for understanding the genetic regulation of maize embryo development.  This was successfully pursued by conducting a screening of a large collection of mutations we produced by chemical mutagenesis. We searched for lethal mutations that specifically impaired embryo development but did not significantly affect the endosperm, which comprises the bulk of the maize kernel.  Our isolation and genetic and morphological characterization of the mutants has set the stage for mapping these genes to their precise locations in the maize chromosomes and the subsequent analysis of the DNA sequences of these genes and the analysis of the proteins or RNA molecules these genes code for.  Third, this project aimed to report the progress on the project to the maize genetics community and the larger scientific world by presenting our results at scientific conferences and by publishing our results in the peer-reviewed journal titled G3:GeneslGenomeslGenetics.  Outcomes  First, Dale Brunelle completed his graduate program and received his PhD degree on December 8, 2018.  Dr. Brunelle is the first Native American Indian to receive a PhD degree from the Biology department at the University of North Dakota since the founding of the university in 1883.  Second, we have succeeded in isolating 45 heritable recessive mutations and examined the mutant embryo morphology of 34 of these mutants.  By genetic testing we have identified two pairs of mutations where each mutation of a pair resulted from an independent mutation event but both members of the pair are located in the same gene.  This is important because this favorable situation will aid in the mapping and DNA sequencing of the mutated gene.  Third, we have published our initial results on the screening and genetic and morphological analysis of 34 of our 45 mutants in a research paper titled "Genetic Screening for EMS-Induced Maize Embryo-Specific Mutants Altered in Embryo Morphogenesis" in the November 2017 issue of G3:GeneslGenomeslGenetics 7:3559-3570.  We also have regularly reported our research progress at the Annual Maize Genetics Conferences.  Future Global Outcomes  An additional potential outcome of our basic research is to aid in increasing worldwide food production by genetic modification of three major cereal crops:  corn (maize), sorghum, and millet.  This potential increase will result from both extending the geographic range of cultivation of these cereals, but also in modifying their growth characteristics so as to increase their yield and tolerance of environmental stresses.  The entire DNA sequences of all three species has been determined.  Our future successes and those of other investigators in identifying and characterizing the genes in these cereals that control plant development and reproduction will enable the use of new molecular techniques to modify the genes of corn, sorghum, and millet.  We can anticipate the exchange of genetic information (genes) among these three species by molecular techniques so as to produce new hybrids exhibiting the most favorable features of each.  This will be particularly valuable for crop production in the western regions of the Dakotas in the U.S. and in the Horn of Africa (Ethiopia, Sudan, and Somalia).            Last Modified: 09/23/2019       Submitted by: William F Sheridan]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
