<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>CAREER:  Air-sea Exchange of Volatile Organic Compounds--Impacts on Climate and Atmospheric Chemistry</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2015</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>257266.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>257266</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>06020104</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>GEO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>AGS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Atmospheric &amp; Geospace Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Sylvia Edgerton</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>sedgerto@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032928522</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Biogenic volatile organic compounds (BVOC), emitted from photosynthetic organisms, play a controlling role in both regulating oxidant loadings and setting the production rate of secondary organic aerosol (SOA) in both terrestrial and marine environments. To date, the vast majority of research has focused on terrestrial sources of BVOC, with specific attention to the factors that control the emission rates of isoprene, monoterpenes, and sesquiterpenes. In comparison, considerably less is known about marine BVOC emissions. Similar to terrestrial processes, the spatio-temporal distribution of marine BVOC emissions is thought to be highly variable, depending on the number concentration and species of photosynthetic organism. It has been suggested that marine BVOC emissions in highly productive regions of the oceans: 1) impact oxidant loadings in the marine boundary layer (MBL), 2) contribute to SOA production, and 3) alter particle size and microphysical properties, thus impacting cloud formation and persistence in the MBL. At present, there exists an extreme paucity of experimental data of BVOC fluxes to constrain global models of ocean BVOC emissions and their subsequent impact on climate and atmospheric chemistry. This multi-scale investigation is designed to link detailed laboratory investigations of isoprene and total monoterpene production from isolated monocultures of an array of relevant marine organisms with direct measurements of isoprene and total monoterpene emissions made via eddy correlation during coastal algae blooms from the Scripps Institution of Oceanography (SIO) pier and during a research cruise in a region of high biological activity and high wind speeds.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The educational component of the effort involves coupling with the Birch Aquarium, the educational outreach center of SIO, and their Summer Learning Adventure Camp programs to: 1) Develop a hands-on experiment, for students in 7-9th grade, to investigate the uptake of carbon dioxide by the ocean and its impact on ocean acidity. The lesson will discuss fundamental scientific concepts (e.g., solubility, acid-base chemistry), while investigating how the atmosphere and oceans are linked. Further, the experiment will be designed with the intent of teaching students the scientific process in which hypotheses are designed and tested. 2) Connect graduate students, who have designed miniature carbon dioxide sensors as part of an existing analytical chemistry graduate class, with 7-9th grade students who will then use these sensors in their hands-on experiment. 3) Engage 7-9th grade students as they discover active research alongside graduate student guides and participate in hands-on experiments. Students will make observations, collect data, and learn about a variety of scientific instruments and their applications.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/11/2015</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/31/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.050</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1550177</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Timothy</FirstName>
<LastName>Bertram</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>H</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Timothy H Bertram</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>tbertram@chem.wisc.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6088903422</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000547904</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/11/2015</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Wisconsin-Madison</Name>
<CityName>MADISON</CityName>
<ZipCode>537151218</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6082623822</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>21 North Park Street</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[Suite 6401]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Wisconsin</StateName>
<StateCode>WI</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>WI02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>161202122</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF WISCONSIN SYSTEM</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>041188822</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Wisconsin-Madison]]></Name>
<CityName>Madison</CityName>
<StateCode>WI</StateCode>
<ZipCode>537151218</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[21 N. Park Street]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Wisconsin</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>WI02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1524</Code>
<Text>Atmospheric Chemistry</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1045</Code>
<Text>CAREER-Faculty Erly Career Dev</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>OTHR</Code>
<Text>OTHER RESEARCH OR EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0114</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0115</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0116</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~29888</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2015~111699</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2016~115679</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><span style="font-family: Calibri; font-size: small;">The emission and deposition of reactive gases at the ocean surface alters the chemical composition of the marine atmosphere. To date, direct measurements of the transfer of reactive gases between the ocean and atmosphere have been limited to a select few molecules. In this project, we developed new analytical techniques for direct measurements of the air-sea transfer of an array of reduced sulfur and volatile organic compounds. These molecules play a central role in both regulating oxidant concentrations and setting the production rate of secondary organic aerosol in marine environments. Using both laboratory investigations and data acquired from research cruises, we determined the sea-to-air flux of dimethyl sulfide, isoprene, and monoterpenes and assessed the impact that these compounds have on new particle formation rates and secondary organic aerosol production in marine environments. The results of these studies indicate that mean isoprene and monoterpene sea?to?air vertical fluxes, in the North Atlantic, are significantly lower than mean DMS fluxes. Rare, intense monoterpene sea?to?air fluxes were observed, coincident with elevated monoterpene mixing ratios. Calculations of secondary organic aerosol (SOA)production rates for mean isoprene and monoterpene emission rates sampled here indicate were small. Despite modest SOA production rates, low particle number concentrations permit a sizable role for condensational growth of monoterpene oxidation products in altering particle size distributions and the concentration of cloud condensation nuclei during episodic monoterpene emission events from the ocean.</span></p> <p><span style="font-family: Calibri; font-size: small;">As part of this award, we developed a series of outreach activities focused on hands-on experimentation for students in 7-9th grade, to investigate the uptake of carbon dioxide by the ocean and its impact on ocean acidity. The lesson discussed fundamental scientific concepts, while investigating how the atmosphere and oceans are linked. As part of this activity, my group designed miniature, hand-held carbon dioxide sensors that were used within this camp. Students used the sensors to explore gradients in carbon dioxide concentrations around campus.</span></p> <p><strong>&nbsp;</strong><em>&nbsp;</em></p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 09/04/2018<br>      Modified by: Timothy&nbsp;H&nbsp;Bertram</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Image         </div> <div class="galControls onePhoto" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation onePhoto" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1550177/1550177_10151842_1536117862284_IMG_1676--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1550177/1550177_10151842_1536117862284_IMG_1676--rgov-800width.jpg" title="HiWinGS"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1550177/1550177_10151842_1536117862284_IMG_1676--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="HiWinGS"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">North Atlantic Ocean during the 2013 High Wind Gas Study (HiWinGS).</div> <div class="imageCredit">Michelle Kim</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Timothy&nbsp;H&nbsp;Bertram</div> <div class="imageTitle">HiWinGS</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The emission and deposition of reactive gases at the ocean surface alters the chemical composition of the marine atmosphere. To date, direct measurements of the transfer of reactive gases between the ocean and atmosphere have been limited to a select few molecules. In this project, we developed new analytical techniques for direct measurements of the air-sea transfer of an array of reduced sulfur and volatile organic compounds. These molecules play a central role in both regulating oxidant concentrations and setting the production rate of secondary organic aerosol in marine environments. Using both laboratory investigations and data acquired from research cruises, we determined the sea-to-air flux of dimethyl sulfide, isoprene, and monoterpenes and assessed the impact that these compounds have on new particle formation rates and secondary organic aerosol production in marine environments. The results of these studies indicate that mean isoprene and monoterpene sea?to?air vertical fluxes, in the North Atlantic, are significantly lower than mean DMS fluxes. Rare, intense monoterpene sea?to?air fluxes were observed, coincident with elevated monoterpene mixing ratios. Calculations of secondary organic aerosol (SOA)production rates for mean isoprene and monoterpene emission rates sampled here indicate were small. Despite modest SOA production rates, low particle number concentrations permit a sizable role for condensational growth of monoterpene oxidation products in altering particle size distributions and the concentration of cloud condensation nuclei during episodic monoterpene emission events from the ocean.  As part of this award, we developed a series of outreach activities focused on hands-on experimentation for students in 7-9th grade, to investigate the uptake of carbon dioxide by the ocean and its impact on ocean acidity. The lesson discussed fundamental scientific concepts, while investigating how the atmosphere and oceans are linked. As part of this activity, my group designed miniature, hand-held carbon dioxide sensors that were used within this camp. Students used the sensors to explore gradients in carbon dioxide concentrations around campus.              Last Modified: 09/04/2018       Submitted by: Timothy H Bertram]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
