<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Workshop: The Past, Present, and Future of NSF's Macrosystems Biology Program, August 5-6, 2015, Arlington, Virginia</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2015</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2016</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>25000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>25000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>08040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>BIO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>EF</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Emerging Frontiers</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>timothy kratz</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This award will partially cover participant support for the 2015 MacroSystem Biology (MSB) principal investigator meeting on August 5-6 at NSF headquarters in Arlington, Virginia. This is the last MSB meeting under the current program solicitation. Goals of the meeting include highlighting program successes and discussing future directions for MSB science. Support will be allocated to about 10 participants on a case need basis. Inclusion of these participants will facilitate achieving meeting goals by helping to ensure full participation of MSB projects and enabling full assessment the progress of MSB science over the course of the program. Large-scale atmosphere-biosphere feedbacks and interactions are a large source of uncertainty in predicting the impact of future climate change. The MSB program has served as a catalyst to understand this issue by encouraging interdisciplinary collaborations with researchers in computer science, geography, climatology, biology and ecology. The MSB program is currently on hiatus to reassess program priorities and restructure future iterations. This MSB meeting will be an integral part of this process, as it will highlight the successes and discuss logistical challenges for MSB research. Participant support requested in this proposal is especially important for allowing greater participation and reflection among the diverse group of MSB projects.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Understanding atmosphere-biosphere interactions and feedbacks under a changing climate is an urgent need facing society. However, such large scale understanding requires an interdisciplinary approach because of the complexity of scaling up observations and model predictions in time and space. The MSB program was formed in order to address this need and to provide a venue to support inter-disciplinary collaborations. At this meeting, participants will reflect upon the successes of and challenges facing MSB type research in the future through a series of oral and poster presentations and breakout sessions.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/05/2015</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/05/2015</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.074</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1550171</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Adrian</FirstName>
<LastName>Rocha</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>V</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Adrian V Rocha</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>arocha1@nd.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5746319438</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000574063</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/05/2015</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Notre Dame</Name>
<CityName>NOTRE DAME</CityName>
<ZipCode>465565708</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5746317432</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>940 Grace Hall</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Indiana</StateName>
<StateCode>IN</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>IN02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>824910376</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF NOTRE DAME DU LAC</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>048994727</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Notre Dame]]></Name>
<CityName>Notre Dame</CityName>
<StateCode>IN</StateCode>
<ZipCode>465565708</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[940 Grace Hall]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Indiana</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>IN02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7959</Code>
<Text>MacroSysBIO &amp; NEON-Enabled Sci</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7959</Code>
<Text>MACROSYSTEM BIOLOGY</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0115</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2015~25000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Funds were used for participant support for the 2015 MacroSystems Biology (MSB) meeting on August 3<sup>rd</sup>-4<sup>th</sup>&nbsp;at NSF headquarters in Arlington, Virginia.&nbsp; These participants were necessary to increase meeting attendance, and gather feedback and perspectives from as many MSB funded projects as possible. The goals of the meeting were to: 1) provide an overview MSB funded projects, 2) highlight the programs&rsquo; success, and 3) to discuss future directions for MSB science.&nbsp; The meeting was successful with over 50 participants and 15 participants supported with acquired funds.&nbsp;&nbsp;The meeting highlighted MSB projects through a series of power point presentations during the first day, and a series of breakout discussions on future recommendations for the program during the second day. &nbsp;The meeting concluded with a better understanding of the past, present and future of NSF&rsquo;s MSB program.&nbsp; Other outcomes from the meeting included the organization of a special session (B12: MacroSystems Ecology: Thresholds in Ecological Processes and Response across Temporal and Spatial Scales) at the 2015 American Geophysical Union meeting in San Francisco. This session was&nbsp;one of the larger sessions in the AGU Biogeosciences section; garnering 24 talks and 37 poster presentations.&nbsp;&nbsp;A small portion of funds also were used to support the dissemination of MSB research through a MSB special issue in Landscape Ecology.<strong>&nbsp;</strong></p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 08/05/2016<br>      Modified by: Adrian&nbsp;V&nbsp;Rocha</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Funds were used for participant support for the 2015 MacroSystems Biology (MSB) meeting on August 3rd-4th at NSF headquarters in Arlington, Virginia.  These participants were necessary to increase meeting attendance, and gather feedback and perspectives from as many MSB funded projects as possible. The goals of the meeting were to: 1) provide an overview MSB funded projects, 2) highlight the programs? success, and 3) to discuss future directions for MSB science.  The meeting was successful with over 50 participants and 15 participants supported with acquired funds.  The meeting highlighted MSB projects through a series of power point presentations during the first day, and a series of breakout discussions on future recommendations for the program during the second day.  The meeting concluded with a better understanding of the past, present and future of NSF?s MSB program.  Other outcomes from the meeting included the organization of a special session (B12: MacroSystems Ecology: Thresholds in Ecological Processes and Response across Temporal and Spatial Scales) at the 2015 American Geophysical Union meeting in San Francisco. This session was one of the larger sessions in the AGU Biogeosciences section; garnering 24 talks and 37 poster presentations.  A small portion of funds also were used to support the dissemination of MSB research through a MSB special issue in Landscape Ecology.           Last Modified: 08/05/2016       Submitted by: Adrian V Rocha]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
