<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>The Second Enhancing Access to the Radio Spectrum (EARS) Workshop</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2015</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2016</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>99998.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>99998</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>05050000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>CSE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CNS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Computer and Network Systems</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Thyagarajan Nandagopal</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>tnandago@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924550</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Enhancing Access to the Radio Spectrum (EARS) is a multi-disciplinary activity whose goal is to improve the efficiency with which the radio spectrum is utilized and to improve access to the radio spectrum in support of current and new technologies. Achieving these goals will, among other impacts, improve the availability of wireless broadband to Americans presently without broadband access. Because the radio spectrum is a valuable but finite natural resource, improvements in spectrum efficiency will have significant economic impact to the nation and the world. Building upon the NSF EARS research program, this invitational workshop will bring together some of the key researchers and other stakeholders involved in radio spectrum access to discuss the state of current research and policy in this area, and chart a course forward for research and technology. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;All relevant fields will be represented, including science, engineering, economics, and policy. Key federal agencies with stakes in wireless spectrum management and usage will be invited as well. The output of the workshop will include a vision for the future of radio spectrum access and use, and a prioritized list of research areas that can help achieve that vision.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/31/2015</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/31/2015</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.070</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1550729</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Jeffrey</FirstName>
<LastName>Reed</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>H</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Jeffrey H Reed</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>reedjh@vt.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5402312972</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000468929</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/31/2015</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Jung-Min</FirstName>
<LastName>Park</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Jung-Min Park</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>jungmin@vt.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5718583317</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000298482</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/31/2015</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University</Name>
<CityName>BLACKSBURG</CityName>
<ZipCode>240610001</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5402315281</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>Sponsored Programs 0170</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[300 Turner Street NW, Suite 4200]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Virginia</StateName>
<StateCode>VA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>09</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>VA09</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>003137015</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>VIRGINIA POLYTECHNIC INSTITUTE AND STATE UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>003137015</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>VA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>240610001</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Virginia</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>09</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>VA09</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7976</Code>
<Text>EARS</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7556</Code>
<Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0115</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2015~99998</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><span id="docs-internal-guid-79f82f21-9597-572b-a198-4ce8cb5b199d"> </span></p> <p dir="ltr"><span>Wireless systems and devices have proven to be significant productivity enablers in almost every sector of the national economy. Emerging applications such as the Internet of Things (IoT), wireless healthcare, and mobile cloud computing are powered by ubiquitous wireless Internet connectivity and fueled by user demands for increased mobility. However, these applications will place greater demands on precious spectrum resources.</span></p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p dir="ltr"><span>To ensure the continuation of these benefits to society, new technologies and policies need to be adopted to enable more flexible and efficient access to the wireless spectrum. The Second Enhancing Access to the Radio Spectrum (EARS) Workshop brought together experts from the wireless community including academic researchers, industry professionals, and policymakers to address future barriers to ubiquitous shared spectrum access. The workshop focused on discussion of near- and long-term obstacles to shared spectrum access, recent research discoveries that can enable improved spectrum sharing between wireless devices, and identifying future goals that will ensure wireless technologies continue to enable national productivity and facilitate economic and societal progress.</span></p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p dir="ltr"><span>The workshop culminated in the following recommendations for enhancing fundamental and applied research to meet the challenges of ensuring ample availability of spectrum resources as well as the continued growth of wireless systems and technologies that support interconnected cyber-physical societies:</span></p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <ol> <li dir="ltr"> <p dir="ltr"><span>Emphasize the necessity of interconnected research efforts that tie together science (e.g. astronomical science, computer science), engineering, policy, sociology, and economic domains</span></p> </li> <li dir="ltr"> <p dir="ltr"><span>Encourage technology transfer from universities to the wireless industry and facilitate the collaboration between the two by creating funding mechanisms that foster such activities</span></p> </li> <li dir="ltr"> <p dir="ltr"><span>Proactively disseminate and highlight the findings and the potential impact of EARS-supported projects</span></p> </li> <li dir="ltr"> <p dir="ltr"><span>Use the EARS program to experiment with new forms of university and industry collaboration</span></p> </li> <li dir="ltr"> <p dir="ltr"><span>Support the research and development of emerging technologies for access above 6 GHz</span></p> </li> </ol> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p dir="ltr"><span>The workshop participants identified high-potential research areas that have the potential to advance knowledge and enable future wireless systems to provide ubiquitous access to shared spectrum resources:</span></p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <ul> <li dir="ltr"> <p dir="ltr"><span>Advances in Hardware and the Physical Layer to Improve Sharing and Efficiency</span></p> </li> <li dir="ltr"> <p dir="ltr"><span>Coexistence of Heterogeneous Wireless Systems and Applications</span></p> </li> <li dir="ltr"> <p dir="ltr"><span>Security, Privacy, Compliance and Enforcement Issues</span></p> </li> <li dir="ltr"> <p dir="ltr"><span>Wireless Policy Challenges and Opportunities: Economic, Regulatory, Technology, and International Factors</span></p> </li> <li dir="ltr"> <p dir="ltr"><span>Prototypes, Testbeds, and Community Research Infrastructure</span></p> </li> </ul> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p dir="ltr"><span>Furthermore, the workshop identified several grand challenges to pursue as part of a future vision for ubiquitous spectrum sharing among diverse wireless applications and services. The grand challenges emphasize the interplay of technical, societal, and policy factors that will need to be addressed along the road towards an interconnected cyber-physical society:</span></p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <ol> <li dir="ltr"> <p dir="ltr"><span>Achieving Harmonious Coexistence in Heterogeneous Wireless Networks and Systems</span></p> <ol> <li dir="ltr"> <p dir="ltr"><span>Creating Metrics to Assess How Well Devices can Coexist Together</span></p> </li> <li dir="ltr"> <p dir="ltr"><span>Risk Assessment Techniques for Evaluating When and How to Share Spectrum Resources Between Users</span></p> </li> <li dir="ltr"> <p dir="ltr"><span>Identifying Policies for Resolving Disputes</span></p> </li> <li dir="ltr"> <p dir="ltr"><span>Interference mitigation techniques</span></p> </li> <li dir="ltr"> <p dir="ltr"><span>Large-scale Simulations that Assess Potential Coexistence Techniques and Policies</span></p> </li> </ol></li> <li dir="ltr"> <p dir="ltr"><span>Development of Automated Enforcement Mechanisms and Compliance Certification Methods</span></p> <ol> <li dir="ltr"> <p dir="ltr"><span>Evaluating the Sociology of Privacy, Enforcement Mechanisms, and Potential Penalties</span></p> </li> <li dir="ltr"> <p dir="ltr"><span>Automating the Detection and Identification of Interference Sources</span></p> </li> <li dir="ltr"> <p dir="ltr"><span>Creating Mechanisms for Rapidly Enforcing Policy Changes on Radio Devices</span></p> </li> <li dir="ltr"> <p dir="ltr"><span>Evaluating the Economic Tradeoffs in </span><span>Proactive</span><span> and </span><span>Reactive</span><span> Mechanisms</span></p> </li> </ol></li> <li dir="ltr"> <p dir="ltr"><span>Evolving Spectrum Sharing Architectures for Future Wireless Applications and Usage Scenarios</span></p> <ol> <li dir="ltr"> <p dir="ltr"><span>Assessing the Economic Trade-offs of Incentivizing Spectrum Sharing Under Multiple Scenarios</span></p> </li> <li dir="ltr"> <p dir="ltr"><span>Devising Models and Processes that can Operate on Huge Datasets of Wireless Feedback, Rapidly Assess Spectrum Usage, and Adjust Spectrum Sharing Parameters in Real-time</span></p> </li> <li dir="ltr"> <p dir="ltr"><span>Understanding what Data from Spectrum Usage can be Collected and Analyzed to Assess Spectrum Utilization without Infringing on Users&rsquo; Privacy</span></p> </li> <li dir="ltr"> <p dir="ltr"><span>Facilitating Radio-Frequency Propagation Measurements that Provide a Baseline for Expected Sharing Efficiency in Different Bands</span></p> </li> <li dir="ltr"> <p dir="ltr"><span>Researching Protocols, Policies, Models, and Frameworks to Enable Future Spectrum Sharing Architectures</span></p> </li> </ol></li> <li dir="ltr"> <p dir="ltr"><span>Exploration of Emerging Technologies as a Vehicle for Bold New Approaches, including Academic-Industrial-Regulatory Interaction</span></p> </li> </ol> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 10/05/2016<br>      Modified by: Jeffrey&nbsp;H&nbsp;Reed</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[   Wireless systems and devices have proven to be significant productivity enablers in almost every sector of the national economy. Emerging applications such as the Internet of Things (IoT), wireless healthcare, and mobile cloud computing are powered by ubiquitous wireless Internet connectivity and fueled by user demands for increased mobility. However, these applications will place greater demands on precious spectrum resources.    To ensure the continuation of these benefits to society, new technologies and policies need to be adopted to enable more flexible and efficient access to the wireless spectrum. The Second Enhancing Access to the Radio Spectrum (EARS) Workshop brought together experts from the wireless community including academic researchers, industry professionals, and policymakers to address future barriers to ubiquitous shared spectrum access. The workshop focused on discussion of near- and long-term obstacles to shared spectrum access, recent research discoveries that can enable improved spectrum sharing between wireless devices, and identifying future goals that will ensure wireless technologies continue to enable national productivity and facilitate economic and societal progress.    The workshop culminated in the following recommendations for enhancing fundamental and applied research to meet the challenges of ensuring ample availability of spectrum resources as well as the continued growth of wireless systems and technologies that support interconnected cyber-physical societies:      Emphasize the necessity of interconnected research efforts that tie together science (e.g. astronomical science, computer science), engineering, policy, sociology, and economic domains   Encourage technology transfer from universities to the wireless industry and facilitate the collaboration between the two by creating funding mechanisms that foster such activities   Proactively disseminate and highlight the findings and the potential impact of EARS-supported projects   Use the EARS program to experiment with new forms of university and industry collaboration   Support the research and development of emerging technologies for access above 6 GHz      The workshop participants identified high-potential research areas that have the potential to advance knowledge and enable future wireless systems to provide ubiquitous access to shared spectrum resources:      Advances in Hardware and the Physical Layer to Improve Sharing and Efficiency   Coexistence of Heterogeneous Wireless Systems and Applications   Security, Privacy, Compliance and Enforcement Issues   Wireless Policy Challenges and Opportunities: Economic, Regulatory, Technology, and International Factors   Prototypes, Testbeds, and Community Research Infrastructure      Furthermore, the workshop identified several grand challenges to pursue as part of a future vision for ubiquitous spectrum sharing among diverse wireless applications and services. The grand challenges emphasize the interplay of technical, societal, and policy factors that will need to be addressed along the road towards an interconnected cyber-physical society:      Achieving Harmonious Coexistence in Heterogeneous Wireless Networks and Systems   Creating Metrics to Assess How Well Devices can Coexist Together   Risk Assessment Techniques for Evaluating When and How to Share Spectrum Resources Between Users   Identifying Policies for Resolving Disputes   Interference mitigation techniques   Large-scale Simulations that Assess Potential Coexistence Techniques and Policies    Development of Automated Enforcement Mechanisms and Compliance Certification Methods   Evaluating the Sociology of Privacy, Enforcement Mechanisms, and Potential Penalties   Automating the Detection and Identification of Interference Sources   Creating Mechanisms for Rapidly Enforcing Policy Changes on Radio Devices   Evaluating the Economic Tradeoffs in Proactive and Reactive Mechanisms    Evolving Spectrum Sharing Architectures for Future Wireless Applications and Usage Scenarios   Assessing the Economic Trade-offs of Incentivizing Spectrum Sharing Under Multiple Scenarios   Devising Models and Processes that can Operate on Huge Datasets of Wireless Feedback, Rapidly Assess Spectrum Usage, and Adjust Spectrum Sharing Parameters in Real-time   Understanding what Data from Spectrum Usage can be Collected and Analyzed to Assess Spectrum Utilization without Infringing on Users? Privacy   Facilitating Radio-Frequency Propagation Measurements that Provide a Baseline for Expected Sharing Efficiency in Different Bands   Researching Protocols, Policies, Models, and Frameworks to Enable Future Spectrum Sharing Architectures    Exploration of Emerging Technologies as a Vehicle for Bold New Approaches, including Academic-Industrial-Regulatory Interaction               Last Modified: 10/05/2016       Submitted by: Jeffrey H Reed]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
