<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Constraining the Source of Ancient, Surface-derived Sulfur in the Bushveld Complex</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2016</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>134316.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>142359</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>06030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>GEO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>EAR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Earth Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Jennifer Wade</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>jwade@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924739</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The Bushveld Complex, South Africa, is the world's largest body of rock that crystallized beneath the Earth's surface from molten rock over two billion years ago. It is host to Earth's largest resource of platinum group elements (PGE) and also a significant resource for chromium (Cr) and vanadium (V). The enrichment of the Bushveld Complex in these elements is likely related to a number of factors, including the original source of the melt and processes occurring during its ascent and emplacement into the crust. Studying the Bushveld is important not only for the understanding the formation of PGE ore deposits but also to comprehend the Earth processes that led to such a large and unusual body of rock. The Bushveld melt was rich in magnesium, which suggests it was originally derived from the Earth's mantle, but puzzling crustal isotopic signatures, including heterogeneous isotopic compositions of Sr, Nd, Pb, O and S, suggest that it endured a complicated history of ascent, interactions with its surroundings and possible incorporation of crust. The recent discovery of a thick succession of highly magnesian rocks (the Basal Ultramafic Sequence) below what have generally been accepted as the lowermost layers of the Bushveld provides a unique opportunity to investigate rocks derived from the most pristine melts associated with the Bushveld and to test hypotheses about the sources of these crustal signatures. A novel approach that uses the isotopic composition of the element sulfur (S) will be used to investigate how deep magma interacted with the shallower crust to yield these rocks and constrain which Earth processes that led to the formation of the largest PGE deposit on Earth.&lt;br/&gt; &lt;br/&gt;The Basal Ultramafic Sequence provides the opportunity to investigate rocks that have experienced minimal alteration during emplacement and crystallization (Wilson 2012; 2015). Existing chemical and mineralogical data and planned Sr and Nd isotope analyses will be compared to measurements of Del33S on the same samples. Questions to be addressed include (1) whether there is a signal of surface-derived S in these lowermost Bushveld igneous rocks, (2) whether these lowermost units are uniform in Del33S values, and (3) how S isotopic compositions correlate with other indicators of crust such as Sr and Nd isotopes. Several hypotheses for the source of the crustal isotopic signals will be tested including (1) crustal signatures of the Bushveld derived from sub-continental lithospheric mantle, (2) crustal signatures derived from continental crust perhaps in a deep crustal staging chamber, (3) crustal signatures derived from interaction with wall rock upon emplacement, and (4) exchange between silicate melt and immiscible sulfide melt which enriched the sulfide in crustal S. The Sr isotopic composition of the Bushveld Complex varies throughout the igneous stratigraphy, and this variation has been interpreted as the result of incorporation of different amounts of crustal material in different magmas ? with varying opinions on the numbers of different pulses of magma (e.g., Sharpe, 1985; Kruger, 1994). So far, it appears that the Sr and S isotopic systems are not linked in the Bushveld Complex, since there are distinct variations in Sr isotopes, but the S isotopic composition appears to be uniform. However, there are no studies in which both these systems have been measured on the same samples. This project provides the opportunity to investigate these two isotopic systems, both indicators of crust, on the same samples.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/15/2016</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/21/2017</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.050</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1551196</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Sarah</FirstName>
<LastName>Penniston-Dorland</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Sarah Penniston-Dorland</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>sarahpd@umd.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>3014056239</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000248975</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/15/2016</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Maryland, College Park</Name>
<CityName>College Park</CityName>
<ZipCode>207425141</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>3014056269</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>3112 LEE BLDG 7809 Regents Drive</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Maryland</StateName>
<StateCode>MD</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MD05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>790934285</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF MARYLAND, COLLEGE PARK</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>003256088</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Maryland, College Park]]></Name>
<CityName>College Park</CityName>
<StateCode>MD</StateCode>
<ZipCode>207425141</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[3112 LEE BLDG 7809 Regents Drive]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Maryland</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MD05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1573</Code>
<Text>Petrology and Geochemistry</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1580</Code>
<Text>Instrumentation &amp; Facilities</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0116</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0117</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2016~134316</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2017~8043</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Intellectual Merit:</p> <p>This project has focused on the sulfur isotope composition of the Bushveld Magmatic Province (BMP), South Africa to determine the source of ancient surface-derived sulfur in these mantle-derived rocks. The BMP contains the world's largest reserves of platinum-group elements, which are essential for industry, technology and medicine.&nbsp;</p> <p>Our studies have shown that rocks from different intrusions within the BMP all contain sulfur that was once on the surface of the Earth during the Archean (more than 2.45 billion years ago). The BMP, however, is derived from a melt that has come from the Earth's mantle. Therefore this surface-derived sulfur has been cycled from the surface deep in the Earth prior to the intrusion of the BMP (at about 2.1 billion years ago). The surface-sulfur signature is similar among the different intrusions, which suggests that it resulted from a process at depth (Magalhaes et al., 2019). Small variations in the sulfur isotope compositions are associated with variations in other geochemical parameters, suggesting multiple distinct reservoirs for the magma (Magalhaes et al., 2018).&nbsp;</p> <p>This work has resulted in a deeper understanding of this famous PGE deposit, providing new geochemical information to further our understanding of the processes that formed this economically valuable deposit. It also has further implications about Early Earth geodynamics and processes of recycling of material from the surface of the Earth to great depths inside the Earth.</p> <p>Broader Impacts:</p> <p>The project supported an international PhD student from Brazil, who gained experience in the process of doing scientific research through this project. She was responsible for all levels of the project, from selecting the samples for analysis at the beginning, through analyzing the samples, to interpreting the results and writing about the data. She also presented the results of her research at multiple international conferences and has authored two published papers, with a third in review.</p> <p>The project also gave the PhD student the opportunity to mentor undergraduate students as part of a separate REU project run through Pennsylvania State University. She traveled with the REU program to South Africa and several REU students came to work in the lab at the University of Maryland under her guidance. These students were given valuable experience in sample analysis and research methods.</p> <p>A number of new collaborative relationships were established due to this proposal, including collaborations with researchers at Witswatersrand University (South Africa), Pennsylvania State University, and the Carnegie Institution for Science&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 10/29/2019<br>      Modified by: Sarah&nbsp;Penniston-Dorland</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Intellectual Merit:  This project has focused on the sulfur isotope composition of the Bushveld Magmatic Province (BMP), South Africa to determine the source of ancient surface-derived sulfur in these mantle-derived rocks. The BMP contains the world's largest reserves of platinum-group elements, which are essential for industry, technology and medicine.   Our studies have shown that rocks from different intrusions within the BMP all contain sulfur that was once on the surface of the Earth during the Archean (more than 2.45 billion years ago). The BMP, however, is derived from a melt that has come from the Earth's mantle. Therefore this surface-derived sulfur has been cycled from the surface deep in the Earth prior to the intrusion of the BMP (at about 2.1 billion years ago). The surface-sulfur signature is similar among the different intrusions, which suggests that it resulted from a process at depth (Magalhaes et al., 2019). Small variations in the sulfur isotope compositions are associated with variations in other geochemical parameters, suggesting multiple distinct reservoirs for the magma (Magalhaes et al., 2018).   This work has resulted in a deeper understanding of this famous PGE deposit, providing new geochemical information to further our understanding of the processes that formed this economically valuable deposit. It also has further implications about Early Earth geodynamics and processes of recycling of material from the surface of the Earth to great depths inside the Earth.  Broader Impacts:  The project supported an international PhD student from Brazil, who gained experience in the process of doing scientific research through this project. She was responsible for all levels of the project, from selecting the samples for analysis at the beginning, through analyzing the samples, to interpreting the results and writing about the data. She also presented the results of her research at multiple international conferences and has authored two published papers, with a third in review.  The project also gave the PhD student the opportunity to mentor undergraduate students as part of a separate REU project run through Pennsylvania State University. She traveled with the REU program to South Africa and several REU students came to work in the lab at the University of Maryland under her guidance. These students were given valuable experience in sample analysis and research methods.  A number of new collaborative relationships were established due to this proposal, including collaborations with researchers at Witswatersrand University (South Africa), Pennsylvania State University, and the Carnegie Institution for Science        Last Modified: 10/29/2019       Submitted by: Sarah Penniston-Dorland]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
