<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>SoCS: Collaborative Research: Data-Driven, Computational Models for Discovery and Analysis of Framing</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2015</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>09/30/2016</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>38540.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>38540</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>05020000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>CSE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>IIS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Information &amp; Intelligent Systems</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>William Bainbridge</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>wbainbri@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032928930</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This project studies framing, a central concept in political communication that refers to portraying an issue from one perspective with corresponding de-emphasis of competing perspectives.  Framing is known to significantly influence public attitudes toward policy issues and policy outcomes.  As social media allow greater citizen engagement in political discourse, scientific study of the political world requires reliable analysis of how issues are framed, not only by traditional media and elites but by citizens participating in public discourse. Yet conventional content analysis for frame discovery and classification is complex and labor-intensive. Additionally, existing methods are ill-equipped to capture those many instances when one frame evolves into another frame over time. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project therefore develops new computational modeling methods, grounded in data-driven computational linguistics, aimed at improving the scientific understanding of how issues are framed by political elites, the media, and the public.  This collaboration between political scientists and computer scientists has four goals: (a) developing novel methods for semi-automated frame discovery, whereby computational models guided by political scientists? expert knowledge speed up and augment their analytical process; (b) developing novel algorithms based on natural language processing for automatic frame analysis, producing measurably accurate results comparable with reliable human coders; (c) establishing the validity of these processes on well-understood cases; and (d) applying these methods to several current policy issues, using data across years and across traditional and social media streams. The resulting evolutionary framing data will help unpack the mechanisms of framing and help predict trends in public opinion and policy.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/29/2015</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/29/2015</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.070</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1551192</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Justin</FirstName>
<LastName>Gross</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>H</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Justin H Gross</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>jhgross@umass.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>4135452438</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000581677</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/29/2015</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Massachusetts Amherst</Name>
<CityName>Hadley</CityName>
<ZipCode>010359450</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>4135450698</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>Research Administration Building</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[100 Venture Way, Suite 201]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
<StateCode>MA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MA02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>153926712</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF MASSACHUSETTS</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>079520631</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Massachusetts Amherst]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>MA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>010039242</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MA02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7953</Code>
<Text>SOCIAL-COMPUTATIONAL SYSTEMS</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7953</Code>
<Text>SOCIAL-COMPUTATIONAL SYSTEMS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0112</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2012~38540</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>An important part of what determines how information will be interpreted by an audience is how that information is framed. Framing is a phenomenon largely studied and debated in the social sciences, where, for example, researchers explore how news media shape debate around policy issues by determining which aspects of an issue to emphasize, and which to exclude. Theories of framing posit that these decisions give rise to thematic sets of interrelated ideas, imagery, and arguments, which tend to cohere and persist over time.</p> <p>This project, part of a collaboration with computer scientists Noah Smith (Carnegie Mellon University and University of Washington) and Philip Resnik (University of Maryland) and political scientist Amber Boydstun (UC Davis), focused on new approaches to the study of &nbsp;framing, a central concept in political communication that refers to portraying an issue from one perspective with corresponding de-emphasis of competing perspectives. The framing of communications is known to significantly influence public attitudes toward policy issues and policy outcomes, and, conversely, looking at how people and organizations frame issues provides a window into their underlying attitudes, ideology, and mental state.</p> <p>Members of the team developed annotation methods and statistical models for framing and related phenomena in text data. &nbsp;One major product is the first version of the Media Frames Corpus, a collection of tens of thousands of news articles about immigration, same-sex marriage, and tobacco/smoking policy annotated according to fifteen cross-cutting "dimensions" of framing. &nbsp;This dataset will enable future empirical work on framing and provides a template for exploring framing on other social issues.</p> <p>This project also contributed several new statistical modeling approaches and ways to evaluate improvements to these models:</p> <ul> <li>Discovery of latent event classes for events between two political actors (e.g., nations) across time</li> <li>Measurement of ideological positioning in political candidates' speeches</li> <li>Modeling of utility-maximizing behavior by authors of text, e.g., briefs written to influence judges</li> <li>Discovery of political import of statements in partisan text (e.g., political blog comments)</li> <li>Discovery of cue terms as indicators of authors&rsquo; communicated core political values, employed in framing news and policy debates</li> </ul> <p>Each of the above models constitutes a contribution to natural language processing as well as a contribution to quantitative social science.&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 01/03/2017<br>      Modified by: Justin&nbsp;H&nbsp;Gross</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ An important part of what determines how information will be interpreted by an audience is how that information is framed. Framing is a phenomenon largely studied and debated in the social sciences, where, for example, researchers explore how news media shape debate around policy issues by determining which aspects of an issue to emphasize, and which to exclude. Theories of framing posit that these decisions give rise to thematic sets of interrelated ideas, imagery, and arguments, which tend to cohere and persist over time.  This project, part of a collaboration with computer scientists Noah Smith (Carnegie Mellon University and University of Washington) and Philip Resnik (University of Maryland) and political scientist Amber Boydstun (UC Davis), focused on new approaches to the study of  framing, a central concept in political communication that refers to portraying an issue from one perspective with corresponding de-emphasis of competing perspectives. The framing of communications is known to significantly influence public attitudes toward policy issues and policy outcomes, and, conversely, looking at how people and organizations frame issues provides a window into their underlying attitudes, ideology, and mental state.  Members of the team developed annotation methods and statistical models for framing and related phenomena in text data.  One major product is the first version of the Media Frames Corpus, a collection of tens of thousands of news articles about immigration, same-sex marriage, and tobacco/smoking policy annotated according to fifteen cross-cutting "dimensions" of framing.  This dataset will enable future empirical work on framing and provides a template for exploring framing on other social issues.  This project also contributed several new statistical modeling approaches and ways to evaluate improvements to these models:  Discovery of latent event classes for events between two political actors (e.g., nations) across time Measurement of ideological positioning in political candidates' speeches Modeling of utility-maximizing behavior by authors of text, e.g., briefs written to influence judges Discovery of political import of statements in partisan text (e.g., political blog comments) Discovery of cue terms as indicators of authors? communicated core political values, employed in framing news and policy debates   Each of the above models constitutes a contribution to natural language processing as well as a contribution to quantitative social science.        Last Modified: 01/03/2017       Submitted by: Justin H Gross]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
