<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Organic Carbon Oxidation and Iron Remobilization by West Antarctic Shelf Sediments</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2015</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>02/29/2020</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>780391.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>780391</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>06090300</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>GEO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>OPP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Office of Polar Programs (OPP)</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Michael E. Jackson</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>mejackso@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927120</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>General Statement: &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The continental shelf region west of the Antarctic Peninsula has recently undergone dramatic changes and ecosystem shifts, and the community of organisms that live in, or feed off, the sea floor sediments is being impacted by species invasions from the north. Previous studies of these sediments indicate that this community may consume much more of the regional productivity than previously estimated, suggesting that sediments are a rich and important component of this ecosystem and one that may be ripe for dramatic change. Furthermore, under richer sediment conditions, iron is mobilized and released back to the water column. Since productivity in this ecosystem is thought to be limited by the availability of iron, increased rates of iron release from these sediments could stimulate productivity and promote greater overall ecosystem change. In this research, a variety of sites across the shelf region will be sampled to accurately evaluate the role of sediments in consuming ecosystem productivity and to estimate the current level of iron release from the sediments. This project will provide a baseline set of sediment results that will present a more complete picture of the west Antarctic shelf ecosystem, will allow for comparison with water column measurements and for evaluation of the fundamental workings of this important ecosystem. This is particularly important since high latitude systems may be vulnerable to the effects of climate fluctuations. Both graduate and undergraduate students will be trained. Presentations will be made at scientific meetings, at other universities, and at outreach events. A project web site will present key results to the public and explain how this new information improves understanding of Antarctic ecosystems. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Technical Description of Project: &lt;br/&gt;In order to determine the role of sediments within the west Antarctic shelf ecosystem, this project will determine the rates of sediment organic matter oxidation at a variety of sites across the Palmer Long Term Ecosystem Research (LTER) study region. To estimate the rates of release of iron and manganese from the sediments, these same sites will be sampled for detailed vertical distributions of the concentrations of these metals both in the porewaters and in important mineral phases. Since sediment sampling will be done at LTER sites, the sediment data can be correlated with the rich productivity data set from the LTER. In detail, the project: a) will determine the rates of oxygen consumption, organic carbon oxidation, nutrient release, and iron mobilization by shelf sediments west of the Antarctic Peninsula; b) will investigate the vertical distribution of diagenetic reactions within the sediments; and c) will assess the regional importance of these sediment rates. Sediment cores will be used to determine sediment-water fluxes of dissolved oxygen, total carbon dioxide, nutrients, and the vertical distributions of these dissolved compounds, as well as iron and manganese in the pore waters. Bulk sediment properties of porosity, organic carbon and nitrogen content, carbonate content, biogenic silica content, and multiple species of solid-phase iron, manganese, and sulfur species will also be determined. These measurements will allow determination of total organic carbon oxidation and denitrification rates, and the proportion of aerobic versus anaerobic respiration at each site. Sediment diagenetic modeling will link the processes of organic matter oxidation to metal mobilization. Pore water and solid phase iron and manganese distributions will be used to model iron diagenesis in these sediments and to estimate the iron flux from the sediments to the overlying waters. Finally, the overall regional average and distribution of the sediment processes will be compared with the distributions of seasonally averaged chlorophyll biomass and productivity.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/19/2015</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>09/22/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.078</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1551195</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>John</FirstName>
<LastName>Christensen</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>P</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>John P Christensen</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>jchriste@newenglandoceanlab.org</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2077250681</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000283232</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/19/2015</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>David</FirstName>
<LastName>Burdige</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>J</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>David J Burdige</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>dburdige@odu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>7576834930</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000170240</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/19/2015</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Old Dominion University Research Foundation</Name>
<CityName>Norfolk</CityName>
<ZipCode>235082561</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>7576834293</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>4111 Monarch Way</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[Suite 204]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Virginia</StateName>
<StateCode>VA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>VA03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>077945947</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>OLD DOMINION UNIVERSITY RESEARCH FOUNDATION</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Old Dominion University]]></Name>
<CityName>Norfolk</CityName>
<StateCode>VA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>235290001</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[5115 Hampton Blvd.]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Virginia</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>VA02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>5112</Code>
<Text>ANT Earth Sciences</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<Appropriation>
<Code>02XX</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2015~780391</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The Antarctic Peninsula, the northernmost part of the continent of Antarctica, has seen massive environmental changes in recent years, including invasions of multiple species of warmer-water animals into the peninsula?s ecosystem.&nbsp;&nbsp;In contrast, the degree of phytoplankton (plant) growth in the surface waters of the region does not appear to have changed and is now believed to be limited by the availability of the micro-nutrient iron.&nbsp;&nbsp;Given the paucity of atmospheric dust in the Southern Ocean, the current conjecture is that lacking any change in dust deposition on the ocean, the level of ecosystem productivity will remain stagnant, even though the species composition is changing. &nbsp;</p> <p>This project investigated the distribution of dissolved and solid phase iron in sediments along the western edge of the Antarctic Peninsula (i.e., the West Antarctic Shelf), as well as the biogeochemical processes occurring in these sediments that exert a major control on sediment iron distributions.&nbsp;&nbsp;In many coastal and continental margin regions, including those along the west side of the Antarctic Peninsula, sediments appear to represent a potentially important, but poorly quantified, source of iron to the overlying water column to support primary productivity.&nbsp;&nbsp;Sediment concentrations of iron are high (relative to those in seawater), and processes in the sediments may allow iron to ?leak? from the sediments to the overlying waters, which could then support productivity driven by this ?recycled? iron.&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;</p> <p>The sediments on the open continental shelf on the West Antarctic Shelf receive a moderate amount of sinking organic debris which results in moderately oxidized surface sediments.&nbsp;&nbsp;Our results show that dissolved oxygen penetrates ~1 to 4 cm into the sediments and this maintains an active oxygen dependent biological community.&nbsp;&nbsp;Soluble iron is produced in these sediments below the depth of oxygen penetration, although this condition may prevent dissolved iron from escaping from these greater depths in the sediments.&nbsp;&nbsp;This occurs because when soluble iron moves upwards and reaches the oxygen-containing zone in the sediments, it tends to precipitate back into the solid phase in a variety of forms of ?rust? (i.e., amorphous, reactive iron oxides).&nbsp;&nbsp;In contrast, near-shore sediments on the West Antarctic Shelf have greater inputs of sinking organic matter, and these sediments are more oxygen-deprived (i.e., oxygen penetration depths are less than ~1 cm).&nbsp;&nbsp;This may then allow a greater fraction of sedimentary iron to be returned in soluble form to the bottom waters.</p> <p>The benthic flux of soluble iron released from sediments is likely the most directly ?bioavailable? form of iron for organisms to take up, however studies have shown that amorphous, reactive iron oxides are also biologically accessible to organisms by a number of different of solubilization processes.&nbsp;&nbsp;At the sites we studied we have observed that in the surface sediments (0-2 cm below the sediment surface) the concentration of total iron in the sediments is 4-5 wt% Fe and that amorphous, reactive iron oxides represent 10-20% of this total sediment iron.&nbsp;&nbsp;More importantly, the processes described above concentrate these amorphous, reactive iron oxides in the surface sediments, since below 10 cm in the sediments total iron in the sediments does not change appreciably but the relative concentrations of reactive iron oxides are roughly half what they are near the surface.&nbsp;Resuspension of surface sediments containing these reactive amorphous iron oxides may therefore represent another possible source of iron that is biologically accessible to iron-limited primary-producing organisms in the water column.&nbsp;&nbsp;Given the highly dynamic nature of the West Antarctic shelf region (e.g., benthic storms, bottom ice scour), this sediment resuspension flux may actually be more important than benthic fluxes of soluble dissolved iron.</p> <p>Overall, the project has enhanced our collective scientific knowledge by providing a more detailed view of iron dynamics in coastal and shelf sediments of the Southern Ocean.&nbsp;&nbsp;This project supported at various levels (in total) 10 faculty, students, and other workers (e.g., laboratory technicians).&nbsp;This included two undergraduate students and two graduate students as well as a faculty member from a predominantly undergraduate-teaching institution (University of New England).&nbsp;All of these individuals were active participants in the scientific work we carried out on our research cruise.&nbsp;&nbsp;The undergraduate and graduate students had never before participated in an oceanographic or earth sciences field project.&nbsp; So, from the point of view of our impact on these students, they gained considerable experience and first-hand knowledge of such field operations. &nbsp;One of the graduate students on the cruise also used samples collected on the cruise for a part of his PhD dissertation.</p> <p>This work (and support from this project) resulted in 4 published abstracts based on presentations at international scientific meetings, 4 published peer-reviewed articles or book chapters, 3 unpublished conference presentations (posters) and 1 Ph.D. dissertation.&nbsp;&nbsp;Two additional manuscripts are also in preparation.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 06/12/2020<br>      Modified by: David&nbsp;J&nbsp;Burdige</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The Antarctic Peninsula, the northernmost part of the continent of Antarctica, has seen massive environmental changes in recent years, including invasions of multiple species of warmer-water animals into the peninsula?s ecosystem.  In contrast, the degree of phytoplankton (plant) growth in the surface waters of the region does not appear to have changed and is now believed to be limited by the availability of the micro-nutrient iron.  Given the paucity of atmospheric dust in the Southern Ocean, the current conjecture is that lacking any change in dust deposition on the ocean, the level of ecosystem productivity will remain stagnant, even though the species composition is changing.    This project investigated the distribution of dissolved and solid phase iron in sediments along the western edge of the Antarctic Peninsula (i.e., the West Antarctic Shelf), as well as the biogeochemical processes occurring in these sediments that exert a major control on sediment iron distributions.  In many coastal and continental margin regions, including those along the west side of the Antarctic Peninsula, sediments appear to represent a potentially important, but poorly quantified, source of iron to the overlying water column to support primary productivity.  Sediment concentrations of iron are high (relative to those in seawater), and processes in the sediments may allow iron to ?leak? from the sediments to the overlying waters, which could then support productivity driven by this ?recycled? iron.        The sediments on the open continental shelf on the West Antarctic Shelf receive a moderate amount of sinking organic debris which results in moderately oxidized surface sediments.  Our results show that dissolved oxygen penetrates ~1 to 4 cm into the sediments and this maintains an active oxygen dependent biological community.  Soluble iron is produced in these sediments below the depth of oxygen penetration, although this condition may prevent dissolved iron from escaping from these greater depths in the sediments.  This occurs because when soluble iron moves upwards and reaches the oxygen-containing zone in the sediments, it tends to precipitate back into the solid phase in a variety of forms of ?rust? (i.e., amorphous, reactive iron oxides).  In contrast, near-shore sediments on the West Antarctic Shelf have greater inputs of sinking organic matter, and these sediments are more oxygen-deprived (i.e., oxygen penetration depths are less than ~1 cm).  This may then allow a greater fraction of sedimentary iron to be returned in soluble form to the bottom waters.  The benthic flux of soluble iron released from sediments is likely the most directly ?bioavailable? form of iron for organisms to take up, however studies have shown that amorphous, reactive iron oxides are also biologically accessible to organisms by a number of different of solubilization processes.  At the sites we studied we have observed that in the surface sediments (0-2 cm below the sediment surface) the concentration of total iron in the sediments is 4-5 wt% Fe and that amorphous, reactive iron oxides represent 10-20% of this total sediment iron.  More importantly, the processes described above concentrate these amorphous, reactive iron oxides in the surface sediments, since below 10 cm in the sediments total iron in the sediments does not change appreciably but the relative concentrations of reactive iron oxides are roughly half what they are near the surface. Resuspension of surface sediments containing these reactive amorphous iron oxides may therefore represent another possible source of iron that is biologically accessible to iron-limited primary-producing organisms in the water column.  Given the highly dynamic nature of the West Antarctic shelf region (e.g., benthic storms, bottom ice scour), this sediment resuspension flux may actually be more important than benthic fluxes of soluble dissolved iron.  Overall, the project has enhanced our collective scientific knowledge by providing a more detailed view of iron dynamics in coastal and shelf sediments of the Southern Ocean.  This project supported at various levels (in total) 10 faculty, students, and other workers (e.g., laboratory technicians). This included two undergraduate students and two graduate students as well as a faculty member from a predominantly undergraduate-teaching institution (University of New England). All of these individuals were active participants in the scientific work we carried out on our research cruise.  The undergraduate and graduate students had never before participated in an oceanographic or earth sciences field project.  So, from the point of view of our impact on these students, they gained considerable experience and first-hand knowledge of such field operations.  One of the graduate students on the cruise also used samples collected on the cruise for a part of his PhD dissertation.  This work (and support from this project) resulted in 4 published abstracts based on presentations at international scientific meetings, 4 published peer-reviewed articles or book chapters, 3 unpublished conference presentations (posters) and 1 Ph.D. dissertation.  Two additional manuscripts are also in preparation.          Last Modified: 06/12/2020       Submitted by: David J Burdige]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
