<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>CAREER: Dynamic transcription factor activity profiling for investigating mechanisms guiding early stage ovarian folliculogenesis</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>03/01/2016</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>02/28/2021</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>500000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>500000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07020000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CBET</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Chem, Bioeng, Env, &amp; Transp Sys</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Stephanie George</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>stgeorge@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032920000</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>PI: Shikanov, Ariella    &lt;br/&gt;Proposal Number: 1552580&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Young women and prepubescent girls undergoing toxic treatments for cancer or autoimmune diseases have limited options to preserve their fertility. Fertility preservation is especially challenging in female patients, because females are born with an ovarian reserve comprised of a finite number of follicles that carry immature eggs. Cryopreservation of ovarian tissue prior to toxic treatments and subsequent culture of immature follicles is a promising and novel way to preserve fertility. The challenge is that follicles have low survival and maturation rates in culture, which are attributed to the complex and poorly understood signaling and interactions between the cells in a follicle. The central objective of this CAREER proposal is to discover the key signaling factors involved in the early stage development of ovarian follicles by using systems biology approach. This system will lead to the development of culture conditions for successful follicle culture to be translated to human follicles for fertility preservation, serve as a platform to screen therapeutic compounds, identify pathways with aberrant activity that could be targeted for therapy, or design environments that promote specific cellular processes in regenerative medicine and toxicology. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The proposed research will identify numerous transcription factors and establish their role in the growth of early-stage ovarian follicles in vitro. These fundamental studies might provide the foundation for the development of a culture system that can support the development of early stage follicles. In the bench-to-bed translation, this knowledge may be used for fertility preservation in young female cancer survivors suffering from chemotherapy-induced infertility. Our overall research objective is to: (a) establish the dynamic activity of transcription factors during early-stage follicle development in vitro; (b) identify signaling pathways that are responsible for promoting follicle survival and growth through follicle-follicle and follicle-support cells interactions; (c) determine the secretome of cultured early-stage follicles in conditions that allow follicle-follicle and follicle-stroma interactions and correlate the functional paracrine signaling factors with the activity of transcription factors (TFs) to identify the key factors and processes driving successful folliculogenesis. To achieve this objective, we will employ a systems level approach utilizing quantitative experimental characterization with multivariate analysis and modeling. Previous investigator's work has already demonstrated how optimizing biomaterial design can enhance follicle survival rates.  We will build upon this system and use the new TRACER technology (TRanscription Activity CEll aRray) to discover the identity, timing and activity pattern of TFs and secreted growth factors involved in folliculogenesis. The key transcription and secreted factors during the development of primary follicles will be investigated in vitro and compared to what is already known for in vivo development. The generated network of transcription factors predicted to be located downstream of the identified secreted factors will describe currently unknown signaling pathway active during early folliculogenesis. The broader research impact of this work will result in culture systems that can maximize ovarian follicle development and provide high quality oocytes for fertility preservation and toxicology screening. This approach has a strong potential to shed light on the mechanism of biological processes of ovarian follicle maturation, which are largely unknown and might benefit basic biologists, bioengineers, clinicians and women facing infertility altogether. The educational outreach program of this proposal integrates middle and high school students with undergraduate and graduate students to the benefit of both groups. The program will incorporate reproductive tissue engineering and biomaterials-related content and projects and will inspire K-12 students to pursue science and engineering careers through conducting K-12 outreach. The investigator is also committed to support women and minority retention in science and engineering through organizational activities and one-on-one mentoring.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>02/16/2016</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>02/16/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1552580</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Ariella</FirstName>
<LastName>Shikanov</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Ariella Shikanov</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>shikanov@umich.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>7347636438</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000674856</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>02/16/2016</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Regents of the University of Michigan - Ann Arbor</Name>
<CityName>Ann Arbor</CityName>
<ZipCode>481091274</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>7347636438</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>3003 South State St. Room 1062</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Michigan</StateName>
<StateCode>MI</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>12</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MI12</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>073133571</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>REGENTS OF THE UNIVERSITY OF MICHIGAN</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>073133571</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Michigan Ann Arbor]]></Name>
<CityName>Ann Arbor</CityName>
<StateCode>MI</StateCode>
<ZipCode>481091274</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[3003 S. State Street]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Michigan</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>12</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MI12</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>5345</Code>
<Text>Engineering of Biomed Systems</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1045</Code>
<Text>CAREER-Faculty Erly Career Dev</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0116</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2016~500000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Healthy reproduction is critical for the survival of all species, including humans. Unfortunately, over 50 million couples are subfertile or infertile worldwide, and premature ovarian insufficiency is often responsible for female infertility. Ovarian follicles are the functional units of the ovary and are responsible for woman&rsquo;s fertility and ovarian endocrine function. <span style="text-decoration: underline;">This CAREER project aimed to understand the fundamental mechanisms of the early ovarian follicles development through the profiling of the transcription factor activity.</span> Understanding of these mechanisms is crucial for successful <em>in vitro </em>culture of early-stage human ovarian follicles. Current options for fertility preservation, such as egg preservation, are limited to adult patients, while cryopreservation of ovarian tissue can be a solution for all patients, including prepubertal girls and women who cannot delay anticancer treatments. Importantly, the vast majority of the follicles that survive the cryopreservation are early-stage primary and primordial follicles, and the success rate of their development and maturation <em>in vitro </em>is very low. It is mainly attributed to the poorly understood complex paracrine, autocrine and endocrine signaling between the cells in a follicle. <span style="text-decoration: underline;">We hypothesize that profiling of the transcription factor activity during early stage follicle development will identify the key signals and lead to a culture system design that maximizes follicle growth and healthy development.</span></p> <p>Our <strong>overall research objective</strong> was to identify transcription factors that are active during the early-stage follicle development, correlate our findings with the secreted factors at the same developmental stage and establish networks of functional relations between active transcription factors, receptors and secreted factors. First, we investigated the synergy of paracrine signaling in early-stage mouse ovarian follicle development in vitro using a hydrogel-based culture system. We hypothesized that paracrine factors secreted from neighboring follicles may be crucial for improving the survival of early-stage follicles in vitro. To test our hypothesis, we investigated the bi-directional crosstalk between cell-secreted cytokines and transcription factors (TFs), in follicles encapsulated in alginate in groups of five (5X) and ten (10X). The differential profiles of transcription factor activity and secretome during folliculogenesis were analyzed using TRanscriptional Activity CEllular aRray (TRACER) and data-driven multivariate modeling approach. The analysis of TRACER and secreted cytokines revealed critical early interactions between cytokines, such as VEGF-A and angiopoietin-2, and TFs, such as the mechano- and oxygen-responsive NF-&kappa;B and HIF1, exhibited a unique upregulation signature in 10X follicles, which correlated with the observed phenotypical and functional differences between follicles cultured in groups of five and ten. Next, using the same culture system, we conducted a time-course experiment for murine follicles encapsulated in 0.3% alginate hydrogels and compared between two conditions: groups of 5 (5X) versus groups of 10 (10X). For every 2 days during the course of 12 days, follicles were dissociated and somatic cells were isolated for microarray-based gene expression analysis (n = 380 follicles for 5X and n = 430 follicles for 10X). Gene activities in follicles co-cultured in larger groups (10X) had a distinct transcriptomic profile of key genes and pathways such as prolactin signaling and angiogenesis-related genes when compared to cells from follicles co-cultured in the smaller cohort (5X). We have identified four clusters of genes that had distinct temporal profiles, such as &ldquo;early activators&rdquo; that showed enrichment for gene ontology terms associated with cell-substrate adhesion, as well as survival and proliferation and &ldquo;delayed activators&rdquo; that were enriched for terms related to steroidogenesis. The transcriptional activity of the &ldquo;transient&rdquo; cluster peaked in the middle of culture and was enriched for cell cycle-related genes which agrees with the rapid cell proliferation throughout follicle development in vivo. In summary, we identified unique signatures of synergism between ovarian follicles during early-stage development, leading to successful follicle development. These findings bring us closer to understanding of mechanisms underlying the downstream effects of interactions between the extracellular microenvironment and early-stage folliculogenesis in vitro. In terms of the <strong>broader impacts</strong> our work contributed to the development of a universal approach to culture early-stage ovarian follicles. This system can be a central technology to quantify activity of numerous transcription factors and signaling pathways, which can provide a platform to screen therapeutic compounds, identify pathways with aberrant activity that could be targeted for therapy, or design environments that promote specific cellular processes in regenerative medicine and toxicology.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 05/31/2021<br>      Modified by: Ariella&nbsp;Shikanov</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Healthy reproduction is critical for the survival of all species, including humans. Unfortunately, over 50 million couples are subfertile or infertile worldwide, and premature ovarian insufficiency is often responsible for female infertility. Ovarian follicles are the functional units of the ovary and are responsible for woman’s fertility and ovarian endocrine function. This CAREER project aimed to understand the fundamental mechanisms of the early ovarian follicles development through the profiling of the transcription factor activity. Understanding of these mechanisms is crucial for successful in vitro culture of early-stage human ovarian follicles. Current options for fertility preservation, such as egg preservation, are limited to adult patients, while cryopreservation of ovarian tissue can be a solution for all patients, including prepubertal girls and women who cannot delay anticancer treatments. Importantly, the vast majority of the follicles that survive the cryopreservation are early-stage primary and primordial follicles, and the success rate of their development and maturation in vitro is very low. It is mainly attributed to the poorly understood complex paracrine, autocrine and endocrine signaling between the cells in a follicle. We hypothesize that profiling of the transcription factor activity during early stage follicle development will identify the key signals and lead to a culture system design that maximizes follicle growth and healthy development.  Our overall research objective was to identify transcription factors that are active during the early-stage follicle development, correlate our findings with the secreted factors at the same developmental stage and establish networks of functional relations between active transcription factors, receptors and secreted factors. First, we investigated the synergy of paracrine signaling in early-stage mouse ovarian follicle development in vitro using a hydrogel-based culture system. We hypothesized that paracrine factors secreted from neighboring follicles may be crucial for improving the survival of early-stage follicles in vitro. To test our hypothesis, we investigated the bi-directional crosstalk between cell-secreted cytokines and transcription factors (TFs), in follicles encapsulated in alginate in groups of five (5X) and ten (10X). The differential profiles of transcription factor activity and secretome during folliculogenesis were analyzed using TRanscriptional Activity CEllular aRray (TRACER) and data-driven multivariate modeling approach. The analysis of TRACER and secreted cytokines revealed critical early interactions between cytokines, such as VEGF-A and angiopoietin-2, and TFs, such as the mechano- and oxygen-responsive NF-&kappa;B and HIF1, exhibited a unique upregulation signature in 10X follicles, which correlated with the observed phenotypical and functional differences between follicles cultured in groups of five and ten. Next, using the same culture system, we conducted a time-course experiment for murine follicles encapsulated in 0.3% alginate hydrogels and compared between two conditions: groups of 5 (5X) versus groups of 10 (10X). For every 2 days during the course of 12 days, follicles were dissociated and somatic cells were isolated for microarray-based gene expression analysis (n = 380 follicles for 5X and n = 430 follicles for 10X). Gene activities in follicles co-cultured in larger groups (10X) had a distinct transcriptomic profile of key genes and pathways such as prolactin signaling and angiogenesis-related genes when compared to cells from follicles co-cultured in the smaller cohort (5X). We have identified four clusters of genes that had distinct temporal profiles, such as "early activators" that showed enrichment for gene ontology terms associated with cell-substrate adhesion, as well as survival and proliferation and "delayed activators" that were enriched for terms related to steroidogenesis. The transcriptional activity of the "transient" cluster peaked in the middle of culture and was enriched for cell cycle-related genes which agrees with the rapid cell proliferation throughout follicle development in vivo. In summary, we identified unique signatures of synergism between ovarian follicles during early-stage development, leading to successful follicle development. These findings bring us closer to understanding of mechanisms underlying the downstream effects of interactions between the extracellular microenvironment and early-stage folliculogenesis in vitro. In terms of the broader impacts our work contributed to the development of a universal approach to culture early-stage ovarian follicles. This system can be a central technology to quantify activity of numerous transcription factors and signaling pathways, which can provide a platform to screen therapeutic compounds, identify pathways with aberrant activity that could be targeted for therapy, or design environments that promote specific cellular processes in regenerative medicine and toxicology.          Last Modified: 05/31/2021       Submitted by: Ariella Shikanov]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
