<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Collaborative Research: CEDAR--Life Cycle of the Quasi Two-Day Wave in the Southern Hemisphere</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>03/15/2016</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>02/28/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>74874.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>74874</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>06020201</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>GEO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>AGS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Atmospheric &amp; Geospace Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Carrie E. Black</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>cblack@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922426</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The Coupling, Energetics, and Dynamics of Atmospheric Regions (CEDAR) program, a broad-based, community-guided, upper atmospheric research program, is aimed at understanding the behavior of atmospheric regions from the lower atmosphere upward through the ionized upper layers of the atmosphere. One of the major themes of this program is the measurement of the transfer of atmospheric wave activity from the lower atmosphere into the mesosphere and lower thermosphere, which overlaps the lower ionosphere. An important dynamical phenomenon associated with this wave coupling is called the quasi two-day wave (QTDW), which is a large-scale wave structure seen in the middle atmosphere winds and temperatures that is particularly pronounced within the southern hemisphere region with a spatial extent over many thousands of km. The lifetime of this structure varies between one and two weeks with a rapid growth, evolution, and decay profile that is not understood. The research of this award would utilize simultaneous data from two NASA satellites to follow the spatial progression of this structure with high temporal resolution. The 10 years extent of the database will allow this phenomenon to be intercompared from year to year and for the two periods of solar maximum and solar minimum.  This research would determine through the application of a theoretical primitive equation model what might be the predominant excitation source generating this wave structure. Two possible candidates would be investigated. One (baroclinic instability) is the development of a dynamical instability mechanism energized by the poleward edge of the stratospheric jet stream. The other (inertial instability) is an instability process energized near the geographic equator as a result of the very weak magnitude of the Coriolis force.  The broader impact of this award is the improvement of our overall understanding of fundamental MLT dynamics. A graduate student would receive half-time support.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The proposed activity will directly address questions regarding the coupling between atmospheric height regions, and possible energetics feedbacks between the QTDW wave phenomenology and the zonal mean circulation. The QTDW structure will be holistically investigated from the generation region into the 110 km region. Momentum and energy exchange across the stratopause and mesopause boundaries will be examined. The study will encompass a decade of observations, 2002-present, which will allow study of contrasting years, e.g., the possible influence of stratospheric warmings.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>03/07/2016</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>09/18/2017</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.050</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1552255</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>David</FirstName>
<LastName>Ortland</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>A</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME>Dr.</PI_SUFX_NAME>
<PI_FULL_NAME>David A Ortland</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>ortland@nwra.com</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>4255569055</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000332435</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>03/07/2016</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>NorthWest Research Associates, Incorporated</Name>
<CityName>Redmond</CityName>
<ZipCode>980525164</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>4255569055</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>4118 148th Ave NE</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Washington</StateName>
<StateCode>WA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>WA01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>151471349</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>NORTHWEST RESEARCH ASSOCIATES, INC.</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>151471349</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[NorthWest Research Associates, Incorporated]]></Name>
<CityName>Redmond</CityName>
<StateCode>WA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>980525164</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[4118 148th Ave NE]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Washington</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>WA01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1521</Code>
<Text>AERONOMY</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0116</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0117</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2016~24346</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2017~50528</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Our work under this grant set the stage for a study that examines the life-cycle of the Quasi Two-Day Wave &nbsp;(QTDW) and its associated production of an Mean Meridional Circulation (MMC).&nbsp; In an atmosphere starting at rest, the QTDW is a normal mode, an oscillation that will continue indefinitely if there are no damping mechanisms, much like the note played by a guitar string when plucked.&nbsp; The oscillation has three cycles around a latitude circle (Zonal wavenumber s=3) and repeats with a frequency close to two days.&nbsp; There are many such 'notes' that the atmosphere plays when perturbed.&nbsp; The QTDW is one of the largest observed.&nbsp; For the general state of motion of the atmosphere the normal mode character is not perfectly preserved because the oscillation tends to propagate away.&nbsp; However, during summer solstice there is evidence that the mode becomes unstable.&nbsp; It grows rapidly to have amplitude much larger than normal.&nbsp; This growth has global implications in terms of meridional circulation cells - that is in a plane that passes through the polar axis of the earth. &nbsp;This circulation affects the chemical content of the atmosphere, polar mesospheric clouds in particular.&nbsp; The QTDW and circulation also extend into the thermosphere, so has implications for space weather prediction.</p> <p>Our study was accomplished through analysis of the temperature measurements obtained from the orbiting MLS satellite during the period from 2005 to 2016.&nbsp; This analysis produced the construction of realistic daily zonal mean zonal winds and temperatures from 15-95 km as well as a determination of the QTDW in the temperature field in the atmosphere.&nbsp; The resulting zonal mean fields were used to constrain the zonal mean background in a 3D time dependent nonlinear mechanistic wave model.&nbsp; Our goal was to determine if having a realistic zonal mean background in the model would reproduce the observed life-cycle of the QTDW.&nbsp; The structure of the background determines whether or not the QTDW is unstable and to what degree it is unstable, in terms of the duration of the state of instability and the growth rate of the unstable QTDW.</p> <p>A continuous model run from 2005-2016 spontaneously produced the QTDW in the southern northern hemispheres every year during summer solstice.&nbsp; Ours is one of few model simulations that produces a QTDW without the addition of artificial forcing, and essentially demonstrates that the QTDW arises from an unstabe&nbsp; mean flow.&nbsp; Further analysis of the model simulations confirms this.&nbsp; However, the life-cycle of the QTDW in the model did not reproduce the observed life-cycle in detail.&nbsp; The amplitudes attained in each year and the time range in which an enhanced QTDW was present did not match.&nbsp; But since the model QTDW is similar in structure and temporal evolution to the observed QTDW, our inability to reproduce the observed life-cycle suggesting that the excitation of the QTDW is either subject to random interactions with other waves in the atmosphere that were not captured in the model, or that the QTDW is hypersensitive to details in mean-flow structure that we were unable to resolve in our data analysis if satellite measurements. &nbsp;&nbsp;</p> <p>We also conducted several idealized experiments using our model to determine how the QTDW might be excited.&nbsp; We found several types of anomalously large wave events that could excite the QTDW.&nbsp; These included various large wavenumber s=3 anomalies: 1) in the weather pattern that extend into the stratosphere; 2) in the planetary waves that are prevalent in the winter hemisphere stratosphere; 3) planetary-scale waves forced in the tropics by large-scale patterns in latent heating produced during thunderstorms; and 4) a nonlinear interaction between two other quasi-normal modes at zonal wavenumbers s=1 and s=2 that are also present in the atmosphere.&nbsp; The fact that winter hemisphere planetary waves can excite the QTDW provides an example of interhemispheric coupling of wave and circulation dynamics.&nbsp; Such couplings are often observed in correlation studies but difficult to explain.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 10/14/2019<br>      Modified by: David&nbsp;A&nbsp;Ortland</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Our work under this grant set the stage for a study that examines the life-cycle of the Quasi Two-Day Wave  (QTDW) and its associated production of an Mean Meridional Circulation (MMC).  In an atmosphere starting at rest, the QTDW is a normal mode, an oscillation that will continue indefinitely if there are no damping mechanisms, much like the note played by a guitar string when plucked.  The oscillation has three cycles around a latitude circle (Zonal wavenumber s=3) and repeats with a frequency close to two days.  There are many such 'notes' that the atmosphere plays when perturbed.  The QTDW is one of the largest observed.  For the general state of motion of the atmosphere the normal mode character is not perfectly preserved because the oscillation tends to propagate away.  However, during summer solstice there is evidence that the mode becomes unstable.  It grows rapidly to have amplitude much larger than normal.  This growth has global implications in terms of meridional circulation cells - that is in a plane that passes through the polar axis of the earth.  This circulation affects the chemical content of the atmosphere, polar mesospheric clouds in particular.  The QTDW and circulation also extend into the thermosphere, so has implications for space weather prediction.  Our study was accomplished through analysis of the temperature measurements obtained from the orbiting MLS satellite during the period from 2005 to 2016.  This analysis produced the construction of realistic daily zonal mean zonal winds and temperatures from 15-95 km as well as a determination of the QTDW in the temperature field in the atmosphere.  The resulting zonal mean fields were used to constrain the zonal mean background in a 3D time dependent nonlinear mechanistic wave model.  Our goal was to determine if having a realistic zonal mean background in the model would reproduce the observed life-cycle of the QTDW.  The structure of the background determines whether or not the QTDW is unstable and to what degree it is unstable, in terms of the duration of the state of instability and the growth rate of the unstable QTDW.  A continuous model run from 2005-2016 spontaneously produced the QTDW in the southern northern hemispheres every year during summer solstice.  Ours is one of few model simulations that produces a QTDW without the addition of artificial forcing, and essentially demonstrates that the QTDW arises from an unstabe  mean flow.  Further analysis of the model simulations confirms this.  However, the life-cycle of the QTDW in the model did not reproduce the observed life-cycle in detail.  The amplitudes attained in each year and the time range in which an enhanced QTDW was present did not match.  But since the model QTDW is similar in structure and temporal evolution to the observed QTDW, our inability to reproduce the observed life-cycle suggesting that the excitation of the QTDW is either subject to random interactions with other waves in the atmosphere that were not captured in the model, or that the QTDW is hypersensitive to details in mean-flow structure that we were unable to resolve in our data analysis if satellite measurements.     We also conducted several idealized experiments using our model to determine how the QTDW might be excited.  We found several types of anomalously large wave events that could excite the QTDW.  These included various large wavenumber s=3 anomalies: 1) in the weather pattern that extend into the stratosphere; 2) in the planetary waves that are prevalent in the winter hemisphere stratosphere; 3) planetary-scale waves forced in the tropics by large-scale patterns in latent heating produced during thunderstorms; and 4) a nonlinear interaction between two other quasi-normal modes at zonal wavenumbers s=1 and s=2 that are also present in the atmosphere.  The fact that winter hemisphere planetary waves can excite the QTDW provides an example of interhemispheric coupling of wave and circulation dynamics.  Such couplings are often observed in correlation studies but difficult to explain.             Last Modified: 10/14/2019       Submitted by: David A Ortland]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
