<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>EAGER: The Europa Mission: Cyber-Human Systems in Formation</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2015</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>278743.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>278743</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>05020000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>CSE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>IIS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Information &amp; Intelligent Systems</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>William Bainbridge</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>wbainbri@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032928930</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This exploratory research will study the development of NASA's mission to Jupiter's moon Europa, in order to understand how large, complex, cyber-human systems get started; how their team members develop and then implement a shared vision for their system given heterogeneous backgrounds and collaborative experiences; and what role these activities play in future science and technology outcomes. The Europa robot space probe will repeatedly scan this icy moon that may possess subsurface lakes comparable to those in Antarctica, using nine distinct computerized instruments, including cameras, spectrometers, a magnetometer, and a thermal instrument.  While no hardware or software for the Europa mission yet exists, over the period of the research members of the planetary science community will engage in a frenzy of mission activity to turn their plans for space exploration into tangible technologies, building the cyber-human system that will enable their collaborative mission to the Jupiter system. This is a rare opportunity to observe a highly innovative cyber-human team forming for the first time, before their system is constructed, as they ask the questions and articulate the values that will establish the core elements of their eventual information system. &lt;br/&gt; &lt;br/&gt;Four elements of this cyber-human system will be studied during their formation: the question of integration (of science, hardware and software), the question of data management (how to balance expertise and sharing), the question of heritage (individuals with multiple mission heritages and different institutions), and the question of trajectory (how decisions early in the project affect activity downstream). Findings will prove crucial to our understanding of how a group dynamic becomes established that ultimately affects the developed information system from the ground up especially in the case of a long-lived system. The project will also contribute to our understanding of data management and standards-setting in scientific groups, and presents an unusual opportunity to engage ethnographically with a community with an interest in how cyber-human systems research might inform their work. Findings about data management, integration, and long-livedness that can take into account the nested, overlapping, and co-extensive nature of these collaborations will go further to support upcoming collaborations at NASA and beyond.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/24/2015</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/24/2015</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.070</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1552469</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Janet</FirstName>
<LastName>Vertesi</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>A</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Janet A Vertesi</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>jvertesi@princeton.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6092588724</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000184378</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/24/2015</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Princeton University</Name>
<CityName>Princeton</CityName>
<ZipCode>085442020</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6092583090</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>Off. of Research &amp; Proj. Admin.</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[P.O. Box 36]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New Jersey</StateName>
<StateCode>NJ</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>12</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NJ12</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>002484665</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>TRUSTEES OF PRINCETON UNIVERSITY, THE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>002484665</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Department of Sociology]]></Name>
<CityName>Princeton</CityName>
<StateCode>NJ</StateCode>
<ZipCode>085441005</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[Wallace Hall]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New Jersey</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>12</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NJ12</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7367</Code>
<Text>HCC-Human-Centered Computing</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7367</Code>
<Text>Cyber-Human Systems</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7916</Code>
<Text>EAGER</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0115</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2015~278743</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>What makes a successful project team? How can scientists work together across disciplinary boundaries to solve complex, big problems - such as the search for life in our solar system? And how can we guide such groups to embrace productive disagreements and diverse perspectives, without jeopardizing the functionality of their organization in the long term? These are the questions that this EAGER grant addressed over two years of working with the Europa Clipper Mission team, and its counterpart studies for a lander.<br />Europa is one of Jupiter&rsquo;s moons. Coated in a sheath of solid ice, the moon likely harbors a global ocean that might be the perfect location for life to arise beyond Earth. Intrigued by images of Europa captured by the Voyagers and Galileo spacecraft, planetary scientists have hoped to return with a dedicated mission to explore Europa and answer its enigmatic questions. The team was assembled in 2014 and meetings began in earnest between 2015-2017, over the course of this grant period. This NSF-funded project immersed an ethnographer within the Europa Clipper Mission (and lander preparatory discussions) during this critical period of mission formation.<br />There is much to learn from this team&rsquo;s assembly. The group hopes to craft interdisciplinary scientific knowledge of Europa, which means putting aside disciplinary and institutional differences to work on common questions and sharing data across discrete subteams: no easy task. Additionally, team members were selected from among planetary scientists who had previously worked on diverse missions with many different norms and structures. Some were used to a single, charismatic leader; others were used to extensive arguments; others still normalized consensus or hierarchies as the best way to get mission work done. Amid all this heterogeneity, the team had to articulate and coalesce around a shared set of goals as well as a mission architecture, instrumentation, and patterns of cooperative work. As such, the Europa team shares much in common with other scientific collaborations, as well as innovative project teams in technology development.<br />The EAGER project developed several key outcomes. Among its intellectual outcomes are social scientific publications, of which several are forthcoming, about how teams form and work together in conditions of tremendous uncertainty. One significant outcome of the project is a planned book project on the work of determining a shared future among innovative, interdisciplinary, heterogeneous team projects. This is expected to speak to innovative industries in the technology sector and beyond with a detailed look at the organizational factors that impact team integration. More broadly, the project contributes to scientific communities by sharing lessons learned through planned policy and research publications in the science of team science community. The next few years will be dedicated to analyzing and writing up this research for science policy and team management practitioners as well as for researchers in the cyberinfastructure community.<br />The project was also impactful as the ethnographer participated on the Europa Clipper science team&nbsp; as an observer and collaboration domain expert during the critical formation period. She&nbsp; contributed to project decisions with respect to meeting management, collaborative routines, data management across institutional boundaries, to virtual and on-site communication practices. These interactions set this multi-billion dollar publicly funded mission up for success, promising publishable and sharable lessons learned. Ethnographic participation also took place during discussions about the diversification of the field; the sociologist not only studied these interactions but also disseminated research from the social sciences to produce more robust, diverse teams. This and&nbsp; related work had a broad impact on the collaborative structures and social relations within planetary science as the field grapples with how best to meet the requirements of scientific merit through diversification of networks and attention to social factors impacting their scientific work.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 12/06/2018<br>      Modified by: Janet&nbsp;A&nbsp;Vertesi</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ What makes a successful project team? How can scientists work together across disciplinary boundaries to solve complex, big problems - such as the search for life in our solar system? And how can we guide such groups to embrace productive disagreements and diverse perspectives, without jeopardizing the functionality of their organization in the long term? These are the questions that this EAGER grant addressed over two years of working with the Europa Clipper Mission team, and its counterpart studies for a lander. Europa is one of Jupiter?s moons. Coated in a sheath of solid ice, the moon likely harbors a global ocean that might be the perfect location for life to arise beyond Earth. Intrigued by images of Europa captured by the Voyagers and Galileo spacecraft, planetary scientists have hoped to return with a dedicated mission to explore Europa and answer its enigmatic questions. The team was assembled in 2014 and meetings began in earnest between 2015-2017, over the course of this grant period. This NSF-funded project immersed an ethnographer within the Europa Clipper Mission (and lander preparatory discussions) during this critical period of mission formation. There is much to learn from this team?s assembly. The group hopes to craft interdisciplinary scientific knowledge of Europa, which means putting aside disciplinary and institutional differences to work on common questions and sharing data across discrete subteams: no easy task. Additionally, team members were selected from among planetary scientists who had previously worked on diverse missions with many different norms and structures. Some were used to a single, charismatic leader; others were used to extensive arguments; others still normalized consensus or hierarchies as the best way to get mission work done. Amid all this heterogeneity, the team had to articulate and coalesce around a shared set of goals as well as a mission architecture, instrumentation, and patterns of cooperative work. As such, the Europa team shares much in common with other scientific collaborations, as well as innovative project teams in technology development. The EAGER project developed several key outcomes. Among its intellectual outcomes are social scientific publications, of which several are forthcoming, about how teams form and work together in conditions of tremendous uncertainty. One significant outcome of the project is a planned book project on the work of determining a shared future among innovative, interdisciplinary, heterogeneous team projects. This is expected to speak to innovative industries in the technology sector and beyond with a detailed look at the organizational factors that impact team integration. More broadly, the project contributes to scientific communities by sharing lessons learned through planned policy and research publications in the science of team science community. The next few years will be dedicated to analyzing and writing up this research for science policy and team management practitioners as well as for researchers in the cyberinfastructure community. The project was also impactful as the ethnographer participated on the Europa Clipper science team  as an observer and collaboration domain expert during the critical formation period. She  contributed to project decisions with respect to meeting management, collaborative routines, data management across institutional boundaries, to virtual and on-site communication practices. These interactions set this multi-billion dollar publicly funded mission up for success, promising publishable and sharable lessons learned. Ethnographic participation also took place during discussions about the diversification of the field; the sociologist not only studied these interactions but also disseminated research from the social sciences to produce more robust, diverse teams. This and  related work had a broad impact on the collaborative structures and social relations within planetary science as the field grapples with how best to meet the requirements of scientific merit through diversification of networks and attention to social factors impacting their scientific work.       Last Modified: 12/06/2018       Submitted by: Janet A Vertesi]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
