<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>SBIR Phase II:  Imaging Flow Cytometer for High-Throughput High-Content Screening</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>04/01/2016</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>03/31/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>749999.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>749999</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07070000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>IIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Industrial Innovation &amp; Partnersh</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Ruth Shuman</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>rshuman@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922160</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The broader impact/commercial potential of this Small Business Innovation Research (SBIR) Phase II project will be to develop an imaging flow cytometer to enable high-throughput, precision analysis of biological cells for the drug discovery and biotechnology industries. The goal for this project is to provide order-of-magnitude throughput improvements versus other high content cell analysis technologies, which will ultimately lead to an increase in the efficiency of drug discovery. A high throughput imaging flow cytometer is an ideal solution for the pharmaceutical and biotechnology industries, as well as flow cytometry core facilities, because of the demand for higher throughput cellular analysis. In addition to drug discovery, the imaging capability of this flow cytometer will enable researchers to perform rare cell detection with higher precision than is currently available, and ultimately, in vitro hematology and oncology diagnostics using imaging flow cytometry. Finally, a high throughput flow cytometer with an order of magnitude greater throughput will dramatically reduce the time researchers spend in flow cytometry core facilities, ultimately enabling a general increase in biomedical research productivity.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This SBIR Phase II project proposes to improve the efficiency of drug discovery by introducing a higher throughput, high content screening (HCS) instrument. HCS investigates the effects and associated mechanisms of action of therapeutic compounds by measuring multiple parameters from individual cells, typically using imaging. Although HCS has been highly effective in discovery new drugs, it, unfortunately, has significant throughput limitations. Namely, HCS requires data to be collected at the single cell level versus the population level. Typically, low-throughput readout techniques, such as flow cytometry and fluorescence imaging, are used to collect this data. This project aims to alleviate the speed limitations associated with imaging in drug discovery by introducing a high-throughput imaging flow cytometer capable of performing sub-cellular imaging at the speeds of traditional high throughput screening. The project leverages a high-speed fluorescence imaging modality based on frequency domain multiplexing, which was developed and demonstrated in Phase I, to provide market-leading imaging performance. Expanding this technology into a full flow cytometer by the end of Phase II, the goal is to have a 3-laser, 10-color imaging flow cytometer ready for researchers performing HCS as well as the general biomedical research community.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>03/27/2016</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>03/27/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1555947</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Eric</FirstName>
<LastName>Diebold</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>D</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Eric D Diebold</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>diebold.e@gmail.com</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>4014390159</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000669881</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>03/27/2016</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Omega Biosystems Incorporated</Name>
<CityName>Los Angeles</CityName>
<ZipCode>900644514</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>4014390159</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>10316 Bannockburn Dr</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>37</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CA37</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>079309785</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>OMEGA BIOSYSTEMS INCORPORATED</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Omega Biosystems Incorporated]]></Name>
<CityName>Los Angeles</CityName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>900958352</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[570 Westwood Plaza Suite 6350]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>33</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CA33</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>5373</Code>
<Text>SBIR Phase II</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>5373</Code>
<Text>SMALL BUSINESS PHASE II</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8038</Code>
<Text>Biotechnology</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0116</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2016~749999</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>In this Phase II SBIR project, Omega Biosystems has made excellent  progress towards developing and commercializing a high throughput  imaging flow cytometer. We have met all technical goals and deliverables  that we set out to complete during this period, and even exceeded our  own expectations of commercial progress at this point.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>From a technical perspective, we have made extraordinary progress on  the software front, nearly completing a fully-functional instrument  control, data acquisition, and data analysis software package, known as  Metis. The Metis platform allows for unprecedented visualization and  analysis of flow cytometry data, accompanied by the insight of  multi-spectral images rendered for the user at video rate upon demand.  This unprecedented capability in flow cytometry allows the instrument  user to immediately confirm or reject hypotheses surrounding their flow  data, leading to enhanced confidence in experiments, as well as  providing an incredible depth of information about each cell. This  real-time feedback capability brings true single-cell resolution to flow  cytometry, and has been a completely differentiating feature of our  product.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>On the hardware front, we have completed not only a full  optomechanical model of the system, but we have completed construction  of a fully-functional beta unit imaging flow cytometer. This instrument  is constructed from partially off-the-shelf components, in addition to a  custom-machined optomechanical hardware system, designed in-house by  Omega Biosystems. This hardware system enables low-cost fabrication  using simple machining techniques, and also leverages the use of  off-the-shelf optical mounts where precision alignments are required.  This system represents a mid-way point in the system development between  fully off-the-shelf and fully customized components, which achieves a  balance of performance and cost effectiveness in our beta unit.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>With respect to commercial progress, we have sold our first unit to a  customer at a high-profile academic laboratory. This customer is  working with us to provide feedback on the system operation in order to  help us further refine our product. There is regular interaction and  feedback between the customer and our company, as we work  collaboratively to refine the product design for full commercialization.  In this customer's hands, the first data collected has been recently  used as the basis for a peer-reviewed publication, which has served as  validation of the applicability of our product in the research market.  This specific publication addressed outstanding problems in the  renewable energy space, which highlights the broad applicability of the  developed technology in areas beyond traditional immunology and cell  biology, which we were initially targeting.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;<br /><strong>&nbsp;</strong></p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 05/15/2019<br>      Modified by: Eric&nbsp;D&nbsp;Diebold</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ In this Phase II SBIR project, Omega Biosystems has made excellent  progress towards developing and commercializing a high throughput  imaging flow cytometer. We have met all technical goals and deliverables  that we set out to complete during this period, and even exceeded our  own expectations of commercial progress at this point.     From a technical perspective, we have made extraordinary progress on  the software front, nearly completing a fully-functional instrument  control, data acquisition, and data analysis software package, known as  Metis. The Metis platform allows for unprecedented visualization and  analysis of flow cytometry data, accompanied by the insight of  multi-spectral images rendered for the user at video rate upon demand.  This unprecedented capability in flow cytometry allows the instrument  user to immediately confirm or reject hypotheses surrounding their flow  data, leading to enhanced confidence in experiments, as well as  providing an incredible depth of information about each cell. This  real-time feedback capability brings true single-cell resolution to flow  cytometry, and has been a completely differentiating feature of our  product.     On the hardware front, we have completed not only a full  optomechanical model of the system, but we have completed construction  of a fully-functional beta unit imaging flow cytometer. This instrument  is constructed from partially off-the-shelf components, in addition to a  custom-machined optomechanical hardware system, designed in-house by  Omega Biosystems. This hardware system enables low-cost fabrication  using simple machining techniques, and also leverages the use of  off-the-shelf optical mounts where precision alignments are required.  This system represents a mid-way point in the system development between  fully off-the-shelf and fully customized components, which achieves a  balance of performance and cost effectiveness in our beta unit.     With respect to commercial progress, we have sold our first unit to a  customer at a high-profile academic laboratory. This customer is  working with us to provide feedback on the system operation in order to  help us further refine our product. There is regular interaction and  feedback between the customer and our company, as we work  collaboratively to refine the product design for full commercialization.  In this customer's hands, the first data collected has been recently  used as the basis for a peer-reviewed publication, which has served as  validation of the applicability of our product in the research market.  This specific publication addressed outstanding problems in the  renewable energy space, which highlights the broad applicability of the  developed technology in areas beyond traditional immunology and cell  biology, which we were initially targeting.               Last Modified: 05/15/2019       Submitted by: Eric D Diebold]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
