<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Meeting: Identifying, understanding, and overcoming technical issues in identifier systems, Oracle, Arizona, winter 2015-16</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2015</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>03/31/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>49986.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>49986</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>08040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>BIO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>EF</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Emerging Frontiers</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Elizabeth Blood</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>eblood@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924349</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>A growing awareness of the need for permanent, globally unique identifiers for both physical specimens and digital data has led to the development of new systems for minting, tracking, resolving, and querying identifiers. While work has been published on identifier type characteristics and best practices for their application, there has been little empirical research on the functionality of identifiers or the services that support them, especially on elements of the data lifecycle that occur before publication. Practitioners working with identifiers are aware of the technical and social issues and limitations in the application and use of identifier systems. Yet, there is limited understanding of whether and how systems will scale to support very large, multidisciplinary datasets, or time to imagine and address next generation challenges. This award will support a meeting to bring together experienced identifier practitioners for facilitated activities to document the current state of the field, identify and elucidate the technical issues, and propose solutions. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This workshop will focus on identifier solutions to big, interdisciplinary data. Multi-disciplinary participants will be tasked with imagining, discussing, proposing, and hacking next generation solutions for data identifiers. In addition, a portion of the workshop will serve as a hackathon, so that participants have opportunities to develop some initial implementations.  This meeting will seek synergy across disciplines by inviting diverse participants from multiple domains who might not otherwise work together, opening potential for new, cross-community collaborations. A meeting report and peer reviewed articles will be written on the workshop outcomes, and any software produced during the hackathon activities will be available for public access through Github. Inclusion of early career scientists will provide training and promote the adoption of new solutions and technologies, and care will be taken to ensure participation by under-represented groups.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/18/2015</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/18/2015</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.074</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1555491</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Ramona</FirstName>
<LastName>Walls</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>L</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Ramona L Walls</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>rwalls@iplantcollaborative.org</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5168858008</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000238532</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/18/2015</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Arizona</Name>
<CityName>Tucson</CityName>
<ZipCode>857194824</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5206266000</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>888 N Euclid Ave</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Arizona</StateName>
<StateCode>AZ</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>AZ03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>806345617</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF ARIZONA</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>072459266</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Arizona]]></Name>
<CityName>Tucson</CityName>
<StateCode>AZ</StateCode>
<ZipCode>857194511</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[1657 E. Helen Street]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Arizona</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>AZ03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7414</Code>
<Text>NSF Public Access Initiative</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0115</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2015~49986</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p class="normal">The growing importance of data science for answering general scientific questions has made managing data one of major hurdles for scientific advancement at this time. Cross-disciplinary research to address the technical and social barriers of data management &ndash; and the role identifiers play in overcoming those barriers &ndash; is sorely needed. &ldquo;Identifiers&rdquo; in this context refers to globally unique, persistent strings of characters that are used to unambiguously identify physical or data objects. Practical Hacking On Identifier Systems at BioSphere2 (PHOIBOS2) was a meeting and hackathon held in Oracle, Arizona that was designed to capitalize on and catalyze the expertise, innovation, and creativity of multi-disciplinary participants &ndash; those generating data as well as those tasked with building the systems to manage data. Meeting participants were asked to imagine, discuss, propose, and develop next generation solutions for identifiers. The goal was to give researchers the opportunity to step out of their usual sphere and work on next generation problems related to identifiers for big data.&nbsp;</p> <p class="normal">Collectively, PHOIBOS2 participants identified the key accomplishments,gaps, and challenges in identifier technology. Although the list of existing solutions in is small compared to the list of remaining challenges, it does indicate that some resources are available for use right now. Existing identifier types (DOIs, UUIDs, URIs, ISGNs), distributed version control systems (although not for big data), semantic web technologies, and ontologies are all useful for managing research data. Key challenges that remain include a limited ability to parse and resolve identifiers, a lack of systems for data discovery, metadata and interoperability issues, social challenges including fiscal sustainability and governance, and issues with preservation of both digital and physical resources.</p> <p class="normal">After summarizing the current state of identifier technology, participants broke into five groups to develop prototype solutions for pressing needs. The five projects were:</p> <p class="normal">1. A collection of identifier workflow use cases.</p> <p class="normal">2. A workflow and code for discovering and counting the use of specimens based on their identifiers.</p> <p class="normal">3. A digital object tracking system to track changes and versions of records within a dataset.</p> <p class="normal">4. Metadata to describe the persistence of identifiers and identified objects, available through yamz.net.</p> <p class="normal">5.&nbsp; A brief, machine readable metadata profile for physical specimens that can be implemented as a specimen &ldquo;birth-certificate&rdquo; template to be used on expeditions.&nbsp;</p> <p class="normal">The outcomes of this workshop have the potential to impact the way identifiers are applied and used across science and even more broadly. The inclusion of early career scientists and researchers from diverse fields promoted the dissemination and adoption of new solutions and technologies.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 07/14/2017<br>      Modified by: Ramona&nbsp;Walls</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[The growing importance of data science for answering general scientific questions has made managing data one of major hurdles for scientific advancement at this time. Cross-disciplinary research to address the technical and social barriers of data management &ndash; and the role identifiers play in overcoming those barriers &ndash; is sorely needed. "Identifiers" in this context refers to globally unique, persistent strings of characters that are used to unambiguously identify physical or data objects. Practical Hacking On Identifier Systems at BioSphere2 (PHOIBOS2) was a meeting and hackathon held in Oracle, Arizona that was designed to capitalize on and catalyze the expertise, innovation, and creativity of multi-disciplinary participants &ndash; those generating data as well as those tasked with building the systems to manage data. Meeting participants were asked to imagine, discuss, propose, and develop next generation solutions for identifiers. The goal was to give researchers the opportunity to step out of their usual sphere and work on next generation problems related to identifiers for big data.  Collectively, PHOIBOS2 participants identified the key accomplishments,gaps, and challenges in identifier technology. Although the list of existing solutions in is small compared to the list of remaining challenges, it does indicate that some resources are available for use right now. Existing identifier types (DOIs, UUIDs, URIs, ISGNs), distributed version control systems (although not for big data), semantic web technologies, and ontologies are all useful for managing research data. Key challenges that remain include a limited ability to parse and resolve identifiers, a lack of systems for data discovery, metadata and interoperability issues, social challenges including fiscal sustainability and governance, and issues with preservation of both digital and physical resources. After summarizing the current state of identifier technology, participants broke into five groups to develop prototype solutions for pressing needs. The five projects were: 1. A collection of identifier workflow use cases. 2. A workflow and code for discovering and counting the use of specimens based on their identifiers. 3. A digital object tracking system to track changes and versions of records within a dataset. 4. Metadata to describe the persistence of identifiers and identified objects, available through yamz.net. 5.  A brief, machine readable metadata profile for physical specimens that can be implemented as a specimen "birth-certificate" template to be used on expeditions.  The outcomes of this workshop have the potential to impact the way identifiers are applied and used across science and even more broadly. The inclusion of early career scientists and researchers from diverse fields promoted the dissemination and adoption of new solutions and technologies.          Last Modified: 07/14/2017       Submitted by: Ramona Walls]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
