<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>SBIR Phase II:  Novel Capacitor-less Dynamic Random Access Memory Technology with Energy Efficiency, Manufacturability, and Scalability</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>03/01/2016</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>744115.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>744115</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07070000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>IIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Industrial Innovation &amp; Partnersh</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Muralidharan Nair</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>mnair@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927059</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The broader impact/commercial potential of this Small Business Innovation Research (SBIR) Phase II project is to produce a new type of computer memory called Ferroelectric Dynamic Random Access Memory (FEDRAM). FEDRAM is cheap and can be mass-produced in current semiconductor manufacturing facilities. It also uses much less energy than current-state-of-the-art memories, and enables electronic devices to be much smaller in physical size. Commercially, FEDRAM works best as an embedded memory, which means they are ideally suited for products such as mobile phones where the processor and memory are on the same chip. Additionally, the same block of FEDRAM can be configured for high performance applications in addition to longer storage applications. This means that future devices will adapt to maximize power, performance, and usability. Due to the factors of price, performance, and low power, once FEDRAM is proven to work, it can potenitally be adopted in nearly every electronic device.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This Small Business Innovation Research (SBIR) Phase II project addresses the commercialization questions of Ferroelectric Dynamic Random Access Memory (FEDRAM).  In SBIR Phase I, it was shown that FEDRAM cells can be manufactured in an existing foundry with no new materials or equipment changes, and that FEDRAM has leading performance characteristics. The next step is to prove the same characteristics in an array, which would be considered a minimum viable product; this is the goal of SBIR Phase II. By proving this array,  it will be possible to quickly scale the FEDRAM memory array into embedded applications for commercial deployment.  The performance characteristics to be demonstrated are read/write latency, switching time, endurance, retention, and energy use.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>02/29/2016</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/28/2019</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1555875</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Dechao</FirstName>
<LastName>Guo</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Dechao Guo</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>dechao@alacritysemi.com</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2034354377</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000700971</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>02/29/2016</StartDate>
<EndDate>10/18/2016</EndDate>
<RoleCode>Former Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Yuri</FirstName>
<LastName>Zadorozhny</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Yuri Zadorozhny</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>zador703@yahoo.com</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6099541970</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000733298</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>10/18/2016</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Alacrity Semiconductors Inc</Name>
<CityName>Branford</CityName>
<ZipCode>064056506</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>9492336821</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>4 Pin Oak Dr</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[Ste B]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Connecticut</StateName>
<StateCode>CT</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CT03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>079389293</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>ALACRITY SEMICONDUCTORS, INC.</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Alacrity Semiconductors Inc]]></Name>
<CityName>New Haven</CityName>
<StateCode>CT</StateCode>
<ZipCode>065101301</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[55 Whitney Ave]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Connecticut</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CT03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>5373</Code>
<Text>SBIR Phase II</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>107E</Code>
<Text>Magnetics and spin electronics</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>5373</Code>
<Text>SMALL BUSINESS PHASE II</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8035</Code>
<Text>Hardware Devices</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0116</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2016~744115</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Alacrity Semiconductors, Inc. (Alacrity) is creating a more energy-efficient and scalable substitute for conventional computer memory that can be manufactured at a lower cost compared to all other emerging memory technologies. This is accomplished by developing a memory technology that is fully compatible with the advanced semiconductor manufacturing processes pioneered over the last decade. The resulting memory devices can be fabricated directly alongside processing logic in modern embedded computing architectures.</p> <p>In the course of the project, Alacrity was able to investigate a swath of innovative fabrication approaches, including the use different materials, structures, and processing techniques in order to produce memory cells that are consistent, efficient, and manufacturable. These cells were then characterized to provide physical parameters for a newly developed model, which was in turn used in the design and simulation of a complete memory array, along with its supporting circuitry. Once such a memory array is designed, it serves as a building block for constructing larger memory systems.</p> <p>The main outcome of the project has thus been a production-ready memory technology with a game-changing potential. Further, Alacrity has developed a partnership with a cutting-edge lab that will support future design and development efforts. We are currently looking for industry partners and investors to enable the next step of fabricating commercial-grade memory chips.&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 11/01/2019<br>      Modified by: Yuri&nbsp;Zadorozhny</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Alacrity Semiconductors, Inc. (Alacrity) is creating a more energy-efficient and scalable substitute for conventional computer memory that can be manufactured at a lower cost compared to all other emerging memory technologies. This is accomplished by developing a memory technology that is fully compatible with the advanced semiconductor manufacturing processes pioneered over the last decade. The resulting memory devices can be fabricated directly alongside processing logic in modern embedded computing architectures.  In the course of the project, Alacrity was able to investigate a swath of innovative fabrication approaches, including the use different materials, structures, and processing techniques in order to produce memory cells that are consistent, efficient, and manufacturable. These cells were then characterized to provide physical parameters for a newly developed model, which was in turn used in the design and simulation of a complete memory array, along with its supporting circuitry. Once such a memory array is designed, it serves as a building block for constructing larger memory systems.  The main outcome of the project has thus been a production-ready memory technology with a game-changing potential. Further, Alacrity has developed a partnership with a cutting-edge lab that will support future design and development efforts. We are currently looking for industry partners and investors to enable the next step of fabricating commercial-grade memory chips.        Last Modified: 11/01/2019       Submitted by: Yuri Zadorozhny]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
