<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>SEES: Sustainable Energy Infrastructure Planning</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/16/2015</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>123709.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>123709</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07020000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CBET</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Chem, Bioeng, Env, &amp; Transp Sys</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Bruce Hamilton</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>bhamilto@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927066</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This interdisciplinary project will explore the design of a new generation of policy incentives for sustainable modernization and expansion of U.S. electric power infrastructure systems in order to ensure a climate resilient infrastructure that can meet society's projected future energy demands. The research will contribute to: 1) quantifying risks posed to power systems by climate hazard under different climate scenarios and policy responses, 2) developing electric power infrastructure reliability models, both economic and engineering, for the Gulf Coast and East Coast regions of the United States, 3) assessing macroeconomic consequences of climate extremes on power systems infrastructure under different climate scenarios, and 4) devising policy incentives for sustainably expanding electric generation and transmission capacity to ensure climate resilience.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt; Ensuring the sustainability and resilience of the U.S. electric power infrastructure is one of the grand challenges facing the nation.  Due to the complex interdependencies that exist between energy infrastructure and other critical lifelines, disruption in the electric sector can adversely affect national security, digital economy, public health, and the environment, and have debilitating socio-economic impacts on society.  Energy infrastructure is in urgent need of modernization to meet projected future demands securely and safely. While this modernization should be done in a sustainable manner that ensures resilience of the power systems in the face of changing climate, current energy system planning does not fully account for and integrate the multi-disciplinary aspects of the problem and fails to provide incentive mechanisms capable of successfully fostering the needed transition.  This study is intended to provide a framework for the required planning effort.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The project will involve collaborations among government, academic and industry organizations, both domestically and internationally, and will include development of a university course on energy infrastructure sustainability and outreach to high school students.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project is supported under the NSF Science, Engineering and Education for Sustainability Fellows (SEES Fellows) program, with the goal of helping to enable discoveries needed to inform actions that lead to environmental, energy and societal sustainability while creating the necessary workforce to address these challenges.  With SEES Fellows support, this project will enable a promising early career researcher to establish themselves in an independent research career related to sustainability.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>09/04/2015</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>09/04/2015</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1555582</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Roshanak</FirstName>
<LastName>Nateghi</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Roshanak Nateghi</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>rnateghi@purdue.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>4437943349</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000605908</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/04/2015</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Purdue University</Name>
<CityName>West Lafayette</CityName>
<ZipCode>479072114</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>7654941055</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>Young Hall</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[155 S Grant Street]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Indiana</StateName>
<StateCode>IN</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>IN04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>072051394</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>PURDUE UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>072051394</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Purdue University]]></Name>
<CityName>West Lafayette</CityName>
<StateCode>IN</StateCode>
<ZipCode>479072114</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[155 S Grant Street Young Hall]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Indiana</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>IN04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>2878</Code>
<Text>Special Projects - CCF</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>8055</Code>
<Text>SEES Fellows</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8055</Code>
<Text>Capacity-Building Projects</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8060</Code>
<Text>SEES Unsolicited</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0112</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2012~123707</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>This funded project helped establish a novel, multi-hazard risk assessment framework to probabilistically estimate the impacts of extreme weather and climate events (with short, medium and long-term lead times) on the U.S. electric power grid, at local and regional scales. Moreover, it helped develop a flexible methodology, that can be easily integrated with many existing energy-economy models, to enable (i) accounting for the impacts of climate variability and change on the evolution of future energy load at local, regional and national scales; (ii) and estimating inadequacy risks in the electricity&nbsp;sector due to unanticipated shifts in demand.</p> <p>The results from the project provided the basis for developing various undergraduate and graduate-level courses, such as energy analytics, energy systems planning, risk and decision analysis, advanced data analytics and predictive modeling, that were developed and taught at Purdue University. It also helped train three female graduate students and one female undergraduate student, in the departments of Industrial Engineering and Environmental and Ecological Engineering at Purdue university, to conduct rigorous, data-driven research on infrastructure sustainability and resilience. The overall challenges of the project and its key outcomes were presented to the freshman engineering students at Purdue to inform them about the most pressing sustainability and resiliency challenges of the existing critical infrastructure systems. The project's research outcomes were disseminated via active engagement with local and regional stakeholders and decision-makers as well as presenting at scientific meetings (attended by both industry and academia) and various peer reviewed journal publications and conference proceedings.&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 11/06/2017<br>      Modified by: Roshanak&nbsp;Nateghi</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ This funded project helped establish a novel, multi-hazard risk assessment framework to probabilistically estimate the impacts of extreme weather and climate events (with short, medium and long-term lead times) on the U.S. electric power grid, at local and regional scales. Moreover, it helped develop a flexible methodology, that can be easily integrated with many existing energy-economy models, to enable (i) accounting for the impacts of climate variability and change on the evolution of future energy load at local, regional and national scales; (ii) and estimating inadequacy risks in the electricity sector due to unanticipated shifts in demand.  The results from the project provided the basis for developing various undergraduate and graduate-level courses, such as energy analytics, energy systems planning, risk and decision analysis, advanced data analytics and predictive modeling, that were developed and taught at Purdue University. It also helped train three female graduate students and one female undergraduate student, in the departments of Industrial Engineering and Environmental and Ecological Engineering at Purdue university, to conduct rigorous, data-driven research on infrastructure sustainability and resilience. The overall challenges of the project and its key outcomes were presented to the freshman engineering students at Purdue to inform them about the most pressing sustainability and resiliency challenges of the existing critical infrastructure systems. The project's research outcomes were disseminated via active engagement with local and regional stakeholders and decision-makers as well as presenting at scientific meetings (attended by both industry and academia) and various peer reviewed journal publications and conference proceedings.           Last Modified: 11/06/2017       Submitted by: Roshanak Nateghi]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
