<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>STTR Phase II:  Scale-Up of An Innovative Spray Pyrolysis Process for Producing Pyrochlore Catalysts</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>02/15/2016</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>10/31/2021</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>750000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>1399989</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07070000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>IIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Industrial Innovation &amp; Partnersh</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Anna Brady-Estevez</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>abrady@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927077</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The broader impact/commercial potential of this Business Innovation Research Phase II project is to commercialize Pyrochem Catalyst Company's (PCC) catalyst materials.   These catalyst materials are unique in that the catalytically active metal is atomically dispersed in a rigid crystalline matrix.  This imparts unparalleled thermal stability, even at temperatures in excess of 1000°C.  Conventional catalysts typically require much higher precious metal loadings (as much as 20 times) to achieve the same activity as the materials developed in this project and at high temperatures those active metals can agglomerate into large clusters reducing their performance and the lifetime of the catalyst.  The series of catalysts developed in this project are designed in a way that all precious metal is optimally utilized and protected.  This includes resistance from sulfur poisoning and the accumulation of carbon when operating under severe conditions.  This makes these materials ideal for high temperature processes such as steam methane reforming for hydrogen generation, autothermal reforming for syngas production, syngas generation in oxygen transport membranes (OTM), and exhaust oxidation in automotive catalytic convertors.     &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The objectives of this Phase II STTR program are to build on the success of the Phase I objectives that developed a low cost and continuous catalyst manufacturing method for producing the pyrochlore powders that are the basis for the proposed catalyst product.  The method may be equally effective for producing other types of mixed metal oxides like perovskites and fluorites. In Phase II, PCC will construct and test a scaled-up production platform, following the design elements of the proof of concept demonstrated in Phase I.  The new unit will be designed to manufacture proprietary pyrochlore powders at a rate with a hundred-fold increase over production rates of the Phase I unit.  The Phase II technical efforts also examine a range of catalyst synthesis parameters like oxidant gas concentration/composition, temperature distribution in the production unit, precursor residence times, synthesis solution chemistry, and optimizing heat and mass transport.  Through a subaward, powders produced from the process will be characterized and tested for activity by the National Energy Technology Labs, Morgantown, WV.  The overall goal of this project is the development of a high throughput / high yield manufacturing process that produces high performance catalysts for commercial sale.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>02/11/2016</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/26/2019</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1555958</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Jeffrey</FirstName>
<LastName>Harrison</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Jeffrey Harrison</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>jbharrison@pyrochemcatalyst.com</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6098649746</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000646887</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>02/11/2016</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>David</FirstName>
<LastName>Berry</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>A</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME>Mr.</PI_SUFX_NAME>
<PI_FULL_NAME>David A Berry</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>david.berry@netl.doe.gov</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>3042854430</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000700936</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>02/11/2016</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Pyrochem Catalyst Company</Name>
<CityName>Louisville</CityName>
<ZipCode>402990000</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6098649746</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>11361 Decimal Drive</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Kentucky</StateName>
<StateCode>KY</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>12</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>KY12</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>078843126</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>PYROCHEM CATALYST COMPANY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Pyrochem Catalyst Company]]></Name>
<CityName>Louisville</CityName>
<StateCode>KY</StateCode>
<ZipCode>402992445</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[11361 Decimal Dr]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Kentucky</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>KY03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1591</Code>
<Text>STTR Phase II</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>044E</Code>
<Text>CATALYSIS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1591</Code>
<Text>STTR PHASE II</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>165E</Code>
<Text>SBIR Phase IIB</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>169E</Code>
<Text>SBIR Tech Enhan Partner (TECP)</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8030</Code>
<Text>Chemical Technology</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0116</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0117</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0119</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2016~750000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2017~149999</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2019~499990</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Crystalline pyrochlore-based oxides have proven to be effective catalysts for the reforming and oxidation of hydrocarbons. &nbsp;They display high chemical and thermal stability under demanding conditions: high temperature, feed impurities and environments that cause metal agglomeration (sintering) in conventional heterogeneous catalysts.&nbsp; The pyrochlore structure is especially accommodating to the substitution of a wide variety of different metals, which enables the catalytic activity to be tailored for many different feedstocks, reactions and operating conditions.&nbsp; In particular, the substitution of a catalytically active metal (Ni, Rh, Pt, Pd, Ru) into the pyrochlore structure makes the catalyst fundamentally different compared to traditional supported metals catalysts by creating structured near neighbor effects, crystal defects and the atomic distribution of the catalytically active metals.</p> <p>Until now, the synthesis of these crystalline mixed-metal oxides required long and labor intensive batch scale procedures that made them economically non-competitive with conventional materials.&nbsp; With the discovery and validation of a small-scale spray pyrolysis process (SPP) in a Phase 1 STTR, Pyrochem Catalyst Company focused on the scale-up of the SPP to the preparation of kilogram quantities of a broad range of pyrochlore catalysts covering applications ranging from steam methane reforming (SMR) to three-way automotive exhaust catalysts.</p> <p>Intellectual Merit</p> <p>Built around the concepts of rapid heat transfer to small droplets created from a high frequency or pneumatic spray nozzle, the SPP offers a low cost manufacturing approach to the continuous production of mixed metal oxide powders using water-soluble precursors.&nbsp; &nbsp;&nbsp;What used to take hours and days can now be done in seconds.&nbsp; In terms of their catalytic activity for hydrocarbon oxidation and reforming, the powders produced in our scaled up Phase 2 SPP reactor have the same sparkling performance as the batch materials.</p> <p>Our Phase 2 objectives were directed at scale-up of the SPP process from lab proof of concept to a pilot unit that represents the penultimate step to a commercial process.&nbsp; These include actual construction of a SPP prototype with a throughput 100 times the Phase 1 unit, detailed understanding of the design parameters that impact scale-up, production of powders for existing and new customers, and an engineering design for the commercial unit.</p> <p>Through the NSF Technical Enhancement for Commercial Partnerships program (TECP), we developed a three-way automotive exhaust catalyst based on a pyrochlore formulation and produced using the spray pyrolysis process.&nbsp; These catalysts target low temperature lightoff for CO and hydrocarbon oxidation and low temperature activity for NOx reduction.&nbsp; The materials are currently being evaluated by automotive OEMs and catalyst manufacturers. &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;</p> <p>Broader/Commercial Impact.</p> <p>Mixed metal oxide (MMO) catalysts are a mainstay of the chemical and refining industries.&nbsp; They are used in a wide range of catalyzed reactions: oxidations, isomerization, alkylation, cracking, etc. &nbsp;&nbsp;Crystalline mixed metal oxides are a subclass of these materials that include perovskites, pyrochlores, and V-Mo-O oxides as just a few examples.&nbsp; These crystalline mixed metal oxides can accommodate substitution of a wide range of different metals that enables their catalytic activity to be tailored to different types of reactions and feedstocks.&nbsp;&nbsp; With the ability to control the catalytic properties through the selection and structural configuration of metal cations, introduction of nearest neighbor effects, dispersion of the catalytic metals at an atomic level and high thermal stability, crystalline MMOs offer advantages that are not available in conventional supported catalysts.&nbsp;</p> <p>Of particular interest to us are the markets using catalysts for automotive exhaust abatement, hydrogen generation (refining, chemicals production, fuel cells, etc.), syngas generation (methanol and Fischer-Tropsch synthesis) and solid oxide fuel cells using hydrocarbon feedstocks.&nbsp; Collectively, these markets have annual catalyst sales exceeding $20 billion.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 08/23/2018<br>      Modified by: Jeffrey&nbsp;Harrison</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Image         </div> <div class="galControls onePhoto" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation onePhoto" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1555958/1555958_10410274_1535033841660_SPRAlone--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1555958/1555958_10410274_1535033841660_SPRAlone--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Spray Pyrolysis Reactor"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1555958/1555958_10410274_1535033841660_SPRAlone--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Spray Pyrolysis Reactor"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">A rapid and simple process for the synthesis of mixed metal oxide catalyst powders</div> <div class="imageCredit">Jeffrey Harrison</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Jeffrey&nbsp;Harrison</div> <div class="imageTitle">Spray Pyrolysis Reactor</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Crystalline pyrochlore-based oxides have proven to be effective catalysts for the reforming and oxidation of hydrocarbons.  They display high chemical and thermal stability under demanding conditions: high temperature, feed impurities and environments that cause metal agglomeration (sintering) in conventional heterogeneous catalysts.  The pyrochlore structure is especially accommodating to the substitution of a wide variety of different metals, which enables the catalytic activity to be tailored for many different feedstocks, reactions and operating conditions.  In particular, the substitution of a catalytically active metal (Ni, Rh, Pt, Pd, Ru) into the pyrochlore structure makes the catalyst fundamentally different compared to traditional supported metals catalysts by creating structured near neighbor effects, crystal defects and the atomic distribution of the catalytically active metals.  Until now, the synthesis of these crystalline mixed-metal oxides required long and labor intensive batch scale procedures that made them economically non-competitive with conventional materials.  With the discovery and validation of a small-scale spray pyrolysis process (SPP) in a Phase 1 STTR, Pyrochem Catalyst Company focused on the scale-up of the SPP to the preparation of kilogram quantities of a broad range of pyrochlore catalysts covering applications ranging from steam methane reforming (SMR) to three-way automotive exhaust catalysts.  Intellectual Merit  Built around the concepts of rapid heat transfer to small droplets created from a high frequency or pneumatic spray nozzle, the SPP offers a low cost manufacturing approach to the continuous production of mixed metal oxide powders using water-soluble precursors.    What used to take hours and days can now be done in seconds.  In terms of their catalytic activity for hydrocarbon oxidation and reforming, the powders produced in our scaled up Phase 2 SPP reactor have the same sparkling performance as the batch materials.  Our Phase 2 objectives were directed at scale-up of the SPP process from lab proof of concept to a pilot unit that represents the penultimate step to a commercial process.  These include actual construction of a SPP prototype with a throughput 100 times the Phase 1 unit, detailed understanding of the design parameters that impact scale-up, production of powders for existing and new customers, and an engineering design for the commercial unit.  Through the NSF Technical Enhancement for Commercial Partnerships program (TECP), we developed a three-way automotive exhaust catalyst based on a pyrochlore formulation and produced using the spray pyrolysis process.  These catalysts target low temperature lightoff for CO and hydrocarbon oxidation and low temperature activity for NOx reduction.  The materials are currently being evaluated by automotive OEMs and catalyst manufacturers.         Broader/Commercial Impact.  Mixed metal oxide (MMO) catalysts are a mainstay of the chemical and refining industries.  They are used in a wide range of catalyzed reactions: oxidations, isomerization, alkylation, cracking, etc.   Crystalline mixed metal oxides are a subclass of these materials that include perovskites, pyrochlores, and V-Mo-O oxides as just a few examples.  These crystalline mixed metal oxides can accommodate substitution of a wide range of different metals that enables their catalytic activity to be tailored to different types of reactions and feedstocks.   With the ability to control the catalytic properties through the selection and structural configuration of metal cations, introduction of nearest neighbor effects, dispersion of the catalytic metals at an atomic level and high thermal stability, crystalline MMOs offer advantages that are not available in conventional supported catalysts.   Of particular interest to us are the markets using catalysts for automotive exhaust abatement, hydrogen generation (refining, chemicals production, fuel cells, etc.), syngas generation (methanol and Fischer-Tropsch synthesis) and solid oxide fuel cells using hydrocarbon feedstocks.  Collectively, these markets have annual catalyst sales exceeding $20 billion.          Last Modified: 08/23/2018       Submitted by: Jeffrey Harrison]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
