<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>I-Corps Teams: Membrane Adsorbers for Biologics Purification</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2015</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>02/28/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>50000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>50000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07070000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>IIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Industrial Innovation &amp; Partnersh</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Steven Konsek</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>skonsek@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927021</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Rising rates of chronic conditions such as cancer and cardiovascular diseases are driving the demand for biologic drugs used to treat them. Currently, there are over 130 biologics approved for use in the US, with a market exceeding $140 B. Over 900 new biologics targeting more than 100 diseases are under development. New product commercialization will require significant expansions in production capacity and improvements in manufacturing flexibility to meet future market demands. In addition, the emergence of biosimilars, biobetters, and increasing competition will apply economic pressure on biomanufacturers to innovate new drug manufacturing technologies to lower production costs. Innovations are especially needed in downstream drug purification, which often limits the production capacity and contributes 30-40% of the overall manufacturing cost. This I-Corps team is developing a platform (PuriTM membranes) to dramatically enhance production capacity and flexibility in the downstream purification of biologic drugs. The disposable nature of the PuriTM platform is expected to reduce biomanufacturing production costs significantly.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project is expected to accelerate market entry of PuriTM membrane innovations by developing the entrepreneurial knowledge and skills of the I-Corps team that are needed to translate the innovation from the academic laboratory to the industry sector. PuriTM adsorptive membrane modules are single-use membrane products that purify biologic drugs. They are characterized by high drug binding capacity, high selectivity, and high tolerance to feedstock conditions. Laboratory research has demonstrated that the firstgeneration PuriTM membranes specifically address all of the known customer pain points. Through customer interviews and use of the business model canvas, the team will test the proposition that these single-use adsorptive membrane innovations will derive commercial value from their abilities to increase the production capacity and flexibility of biomanufacturing facilities and lower the manufacturing cost of biologics. Identification of early acceptance customers also is expected as an outcome of the project. The team will develop alpha prototypes and work closely with potential customers on external validation of these prototypes. Completion of external validation will provide additional opportunities for the team to understand customer needs and test assumptions about the product utility and design. It also will provide vital data to attract external investors and new customers. A validated business plan and minimum viable products are&lt;br/&gt;expected at the end of the I-Corps program.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/25/2015</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/25/2015</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1556563</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Scott</FirstName>
<LastName>Husson</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>M</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Scott M Husson</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>shusson@clemson.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>8646564502</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000225098</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/25/2015</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Clemson University</Name>
<CityName>CLEMSON</CityName>
<ZipCode>296345701</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>8646562424</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>230 Kappa Street</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[Suite 200]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>South Carolina</StateName>
<StateCode>SC</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>SC03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>042629816</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>CLEMSON UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>042629816</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Clemson University]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>SC</StateCode>
<ZipCode>296340001</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>South Carolina</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>SC03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>8023</Code>
<Text>I-Corps</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0115</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2015~50000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The goal of this I-Corps project was to learn strategies for customer and business model development leading to the commercialization of a membrane innovation that was developed by NSF-funded research. A primary aim of the project was to test the original proposition that the commercial value of the innovation derives from its abilities to increase the production capacity and flexibility and simultaneously lower the manufacturing cost of biologics, which are a class of drugs in high demand for treating a number of chronic diseases. A primary objective of the project was to identify and test the &ldquo;problem/solution fit&rdquo; through customer interviews.</p> <p>The team including the Principal Investigator (PI), the Entrepreneurial Lead (EL), and the Mentor participated in a 7-week NSF DC I-Corps cohort to receive training on lean startup methodology and to collect more than 100 interviews from experts and leaders in the target biopharmaceutical industry, as well as potential partners, customers, competitors, etc. After the 7-week I-Corps program, the team continued to apply lean startup methodology through interviews to validate business model segments.</p> <p>A key outcome of this process was that the team identified and validated that there are significant unmet needs to improve biologics purification speed during drug discovery and early stage development. This finding provided the basis for the team to develop minimum viable products and continue to validate product/market fit. Another key outcome was that the EL was able to use findings from this project in the development of proposals that he submitted as principal investigator for Purilogics<sup>TM</sup>, LLC (http://www.purilogics.com), a startup company that the EL and the PI cofounded to commercialize the technology. The company has secured an exclusive option and limited use license with the Clemson University Research Foundation for the patent. The EL applied learnings from I-Corps to develop an NIH SBIR Phase-I proposal that was awarded. He joined Purilogics full-time and serves as the principal investigator on the award. A second Phase I proposal has been reviewed and is under consideration for an award. An SBIR Phase II proposal was submitted in April 2017 that is based on the successful completion of the first Phase I feasibility study. The company is partnering with three biopharmaceutical companies on these SBIR projects and hopes to launch its first product in 2019.</p> <p>This I-Corps project had a major impact on the commercialization strategy for the membrane innovation that was developed in the NSF lineage projects. Furthermore, the impact on training and professional development was extensive. The team learned strategies for customer and business model development leading to the commercialization of a membrane innovation. I-Corps instructors trained these individuals, two of whom had no prior business training, to use the lean startup methodology and guided the team through an aggressive customer discovery process. The I-Corps instructors supported and encouraged the team to get out of the building! The PI introduced the EL to a number of professional contacts to help establish his professional network. As a result of the over 150 interviews held at the end of the project, the EL has established a network of business leaders; entrepreneurs; and potential partners, customers, and investors. The PI gave the EL training and major responsibilities for identifying grant opportunities and writing competitive grants. The team also had opportunities to attend multiple conferences. Through the presentations, interviews, and training sessions at these conferences, the team tested business canvas hypotheses, learned industry trends, advances and challenges.</p> <p>The team has shared its experiences and learnings in several venues. The PI and EL gave a presentation at the SCBIO-University of South Carolina Faber Center Life Science Startup University workshop in Columbia, SC (Feb 2016) that shared NSF I-Corps experience and outcomes. The EL gave a presentation to a Clemson University MBA class and participated with SCBIO President Wayne Roper in a panel discussion at the SC SBIR Road Show at Greenville, SC in April 2016. In both events, the EL shared the concept of lean startup, the customer discovery process and the team&rsquo;s experience in the NSF I-Corps program. The team prepared two videos that were posted on Youtube.com. The first is a Purilogics&trade; I-Corps: Technical Video (https://youtu.be/LiIVLJgAU4Q). The second is Purilogics&trade; I-Corps Journey: Lessons Learned (https://youtu.be/CIlgWwtwxIs). Together these videos have been viewed over 125 times.</p> <p>Finally, the outcomes of this I-Corps project are expected to have a major impact on society. Numerous campaigns are underway to develop biologics for chronic conditions such as cancer, cardiovascular diseases, and autoimmune disorders, but the process from biologics discovery to a commercial medicine takes years and billions of dollars. Commercialization of products that increase purification speed at all stages, from discovery to manufacturing, will have a major impact on the cost and availability of new biologic drugs and, ultimately, human health.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 04/20/2017<br>      Modified by: Scott&nbsp;M&nbsp;Husson</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The goal of this I-Corps project was to learn strategies for customer and business model development leading to the commercialization of a membrane innovation that was developed by NSF-funded research. A primary aim of the project was to test the original proposition that the commercial value of the innovation derives from its abilities to increase the production capacity and flexibility and simultaneously lower the manufacturing cost of biologics, which are a class of drugs in high demand for treating a number of chronic diseases. A primary objective of the project was to identify and test the "problem/solution fit" through customer interviews.  The team including the Principal Investigator (PI), the Entrepreneurial Lead (EL), and the Mentor participated in a 7-week NSF DC I-Corps cohort to receive training on lean startup methodology and to collect more than 100 interviews from experts and leaders in the target biopharmaceutical industry, as well as potential partners, customers, competitors, etc. After the 7-week I-Corps program, the team continued to apply lean startup methodology through interviews to validate business model segments.  A key outcome of this process was that the team identified and validated that there are significant unmet needs to improve biologics purification speed during drug discovery and early stage development. This finding provided the basis for the team to develop minimum viable products and continue to validate product/market fit. Another key outcome was that the EL was able to use findings from this project in the development of proposals that he submitted as principal investigator for PurilogicsTM, LLC (http://www.purilogics.com), a startup company that the EL and the PI cofounded to commercialize the technology. The company has secured an exclusive option and limited use license with the Clemson University Research Foundation for the patent. The EL applied learnings from I-Corps to develop an NIH SBIR Phase-I proposal that was awarded. He joined Purilogics full-time and serves as the principal investigator on the award. A second Phase I proposal has been reviewed and is under consideration for an award. An SBIR Phase II proposal was submitted in April 2017 that is based on the successful completion of the first Phase I feasibility study. The company is partnering with three biopharmaceutical companies on these SBIR projects and hopes to launch its first product in 2019.  This I-Corps project had a major impact on the commercialization strategy for the membrane innovation that was developed in the NSF lineage projects. Furthermore, the impact on training and professional development was extensive. The team learned strategies for customer and business model development leading to the commercialization of a membrane innovation. I-Corps instructors trained these individuals, two of whom had no prior business training, to use the lean startup methodology and guided the team through an aggressive customer discovery process. The I-Corps instructors supported and encouraged the team to get out of the building! The PI introduced the EL to a number of professional contacts to help establish his professional network. As a result of the over 150 interviews held at the end of the project, the EL has established a network of business leaders; entrepreneurs; and potential partners, customers, and investors. The PI gave the EL training and major responsibilities for identifying grant opportunities and writing competitive grants. The team also had opportunities to attend multiple conferences. Through the presentations, interviews, and training sessions at these conferences, the team tested business canvas hypotheses, learned industry trends, advances and challenges.  The team has shared its experiences and learnings in several venues. The PI and EL gave a presentation at the SCBIO-University of South Carolina Faber Center Life Science Startup University workshop in Columbia, SC (Feb 2016) that shared NSF I-Corps experience and outcomes. The EL gave a presentation to a Clemson University MBA class and participated with SCBIO President Wayne Roper in a panel discussion at the SC SBIR Road Show at Greenville, SC in April 2016. In both events, the EL shared the concept of lean startup, the customer discovery process and the team?s experience in the NSF I-Corps program. The team prepared two videos that were posted on Youtube.com. The first is a Purilogics&trade; I-Corps: Technical Video (https://youtu.be/LiIVLJgAU4Q). The second is Purilogics&trade; I-Corps Journey: Lessons Learned (https://youtu.be/CIlgWwtwxIs). Together these videos have been viewed over 125 times.  Finally, the outcomes of this I-Corps project are expected to have a major impact on society. Numerous campaigns are underway to develop biologics for chronic conditions such as cancer, cardiovascular diseases, and autoimmune disorders, but the process from biologics discovery to a commercial medicine takes years and billions of dollars. Commercialization of products that increase purification speed at all stages, from discovery to manufacturing, will have a major impact on the cost and availability of new biologic drugs and, ultimately, human health.       Last Modified: 04/20/2017       Submitted by: Scott M Husson]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
