<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Collaborative Research: Continuous Metabolism and Nutrient Uptake Across the River Continuum</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2016</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>393359.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>393359</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>08010209</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>BIO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DEB</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Environmental Biology</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Matthew Kane</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>mkane@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927186</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Rivers are the major pathways connecting the land to the sea, conveying water, sediments and nutrients.  As water flows through river networks, the materials it carries are transported, stored, processed, and released in response to changing physical, chemical and biological characteristics.  The goal of this project is to better understand how river systems process carbon, retain nutrients, influence ecosystem health globally, and ultimately support healthy ecosystems, both in the rivers and the water bodies into which they drain.  One of the concepts upon which river ecosystem science is founded is that rivers change their characteristics and processing rates with size and/or distance downstream.  This idea, called the River Continuum Concept (RCC), has helped organize decades of river research and management.  However, while the RCC has been a useful conceptual model, it remains relatively poorly tested, which seriously limits the ability of scientists to predict how river functions will respond to ongoing and future changes on Earth. This work seeks to fill that important knowledge gap about how rivers function, and thus has implications for how humans manage land and water resources.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;One constraint to providing information about river function along the river continuum has been technological; we simply have not had the tools to measure these functions along river networks.  A second constraint has been that the simple conceptual model of the RCC neglects key features of rivers, specifically that they are frequently impacted by discontinuities like dams and lakes, tributary confluences, and geologic divides.  This project alleviates both constraints by coupling state-of-the-art water quality sensor technologies to new sampling methods in carefully selected river sites.  Together, these advances are expected to provide new insights about the river continuum, the role of discontinuities in changing river functions, and ultimately about how to best manage and protect aquatic resources.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>05/20/2016</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/20/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.074</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1556937</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Michael</FirstName>
<LastName>Gooseff</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>N</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Michael N Gooseff</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>michael.gooseff@colorado.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>3037355333</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000374541</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/20/2016</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Colorado at Boulder</Name>
<CityName>Boulder</CityName>
<ZipCode>803031058</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>3034926221</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>3100 Marine Street, Room 481</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[572 UCB]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Colorado</StateName>
<StateCode>CO</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CO02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>007431505</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>REGENTS OF THE UNIVERSITY OF COLORADO, THE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>007431505</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Colorado at Boulder]]></Name>
<CityName>Boulder</CityName>
<StateCode>CO</StateCode>
<ZipCode>803090450</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[3100 Marine Street, Room 481]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Colorado</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CO02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1181</Code>
<Text>ECOSYSTEM STUDIES</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9169</Code>
<Text>BIODIVERSITY AND ECOSYSTEM DYNAMICS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>EGCH</Code>
<Text>ENVIRONMENT AND GLOBAL CHANGE</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0116</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2016~393359</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Our project had the goal of investigating the ecological function of river networks using new techniques in which we track parcels of water and quantify how their water quality evolves from headwaters to mainstems.&nbsp; This is part of a collaborative effort with colleagues at the University of Florida.&nbsp; We therefore have been working across local watersheds in each location.&nbsp; In Florida, we focused on the Santa Fe River watershed, and in Colorado, the Upper Colorado River watershed.&nbsp; Our research design of tracking the evolution of water parcels required that we use techniques in which we could essentially &lsquo;go with the flow&rsquo; and make water quality sensor measurements as we moved with the current.&nbsp; In headwater streams this proved more difficult than anticipated as any attempt to move in the downstream direction with manually carried sensors resulted in kicking up material from the streambed that was subsequently measured downstream.&nbsp; We therefore determined that we had to work upstream in these systems, going against the flow.&nbsp; We also determined that the sequence of data collection (going upstream versus going downstream) could be accounted for by factoring in streamflow velocity in each section of stream that we measured.&nbsp; As we moved down the basin and into the larger river sections, we were able to use water craft (rafts, canoes, and motor boats) to collect data. We have two major outcomes from this project: 1) our &lsquo;go with the flow&rsquo; water quality data clearly shows where significant changes in water quality occur be they point sources (i.e., tributaries or springs) or non-point sources, which can be quite illuminating for water quality managers, and 2) our data collections above and below dams and diversions across the upper Colorado River basin demonstrates that these &lsquo;discontinuities&rsquo; have differential influences on water quality including water temperature, dissolved oxygen concentrations, and overall dissolved ion loads.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 03/05/2020<br>      Modified by: Michael&nbsp;N&nbsp;Gooseff</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Images (<span id="selectedPhoto0">1</span> of <span class="totalNumber"></span>)           </div> <div class="galControls" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2020/1556937/1556937_10425633_1583448371082_DSCN0894--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2020/1556937/1556937_10425633_1583448371082_DSCN0894--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Upper Colorado River Sampling, Utah"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2020/1556937/1556937_10425633_1583448371082_DSCN0894--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Upper Colorado River Sampling, Utah"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Our research group used several different watercraft to collect water quality data along the Colorado River in the low flows of summer 2018, including inflatable kayaks as seen here.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Talley Cain</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Royalty-free (unrestricted use)</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Michael&nbsp;N&nbsp;Gooseff</div> <div class="imageTitle">Upper Colorado River Sampling, Utah</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2020/1556937/1556937_10425633_1583448253646_2019finalreportpictures--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2020/1556937/1556937_10425633_1583448253646_2019finalreportpictures--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Sampling Watercraft Colorado River"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2020/1556937/1556937_10425633_1583448253646_2019finalreportpictures--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Sampling Watercraft Colorado River"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">We collected water quality data at high frequency (60 seconds or less) along the Upper Colorado River in the summers of 2018 and 2019 using a watercraft outfitted with special sensors and sampling equipment</div> <div class="imageCredit">Michael Gooseff</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Royalty-free (unrestricted use)</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Michael&nbsp;N&nbsp;Gooseff</div> <div class="imageTitle">Sampling Watercraft Colorado River</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Our project had the goal of investigating the ecological function of river networks using new techniques in which we track parcels of water and quantify how their water quality evolves from headwaters to mainstems.  This is part of a collaborative effort with colleagues at the University of Florida.  We therefore have been working across local watersheds in each location.  In Florida, we focused on the Santa Fe River watershed, and in Colorado, the Upper Colorado River watershed.  Our research design of tracking the evolution of water parcels required that we use techniques in which we could essentially ‘go with the flow’ and make water quality sensor measurements as we moved with the current.  In headwater streams this proved more difficult than anticipated as any attempt to move in the downstream direction with manually carried sensors resulted in kicking up material from the streambed that was subsequently measured downstream.  We therefore determined that we had to work upstream in these systems, going against the flow.  We also determined that the sequence of data collection (going upstream versus going downstream) could be accounted for by factoring in streamflow velocity in each section of stream that we measured.  As we moved down the basin and into the larger river sections, we were able to use water craft (rafts, canoes, and motor boats) to collect data. We have two major outcomes from this project: 1) our ‘go with the flow’ water quality data clearly shows where significant changes in water quality occur be they point sources (i.e., tributaries or springs) or non-point sources, which can be quite illuminating for water quality managers, and 2) our data collections above and below dams and diversions across the upper Colorado River basin demonstrates that these ‘discontinuities’ have differential influences on water quality including water temperature, dissolved oxygen concentrations, and overall dissolved ion loads.       Last Modified: 03/05/2020       Submitted by: Michael N Gooseff]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
