<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>SBIR Phase II:  High-Performance Self-Cleaning, Anti-Reflective Coating for Photovoltaic Glass</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>02/15/2016</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>01/31/2021</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>746366.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>1298004</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07070000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>IIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Industrial Innovation &amp; Partnersh</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Benaiah Schrag</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>bschrag@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032928323</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The broader impact/commercial potential of this Small Business Innovation Research (SBIR) Phase II project is to reduce the cost of solar generated electricity by increasing the efficiency of panels and reducing cleaning and maintenance costs. This improvement is created using a nanoscale glass coating that increases transmittance of single side coated solar PV glass and creates an antifogging and self-cleaning surface.  These savings increase with photovoltaic device efficiencies as well, so as the next generation of solar cells will see even greater benefit from the proposed innovation. Reducing the cost per watt of solar generated electricity is one of the grand energy challenges and has immense societal and governmental impacts. The proposed project is one component of addressing that challenge. The technical advances made in this project will also be applicable to additional market opportunities in LED lighting and other cutting-edge markets. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This Small Business Innovation Research (SBIR) Phase II project investigates the deposition of water-based nanoparticle solutions using industrially scalable methods and results in valuable scientific knowledge that is not currently available in the field. Nanoparticle-based antireflective glass coatings have been presented in both the scientific literature and commercial products. However, most coatings suffer from either high deposition costs, or a trade-off between durability and performance. In this project, methods to increase the durability of a low-cost, high-performance nanoparticle that were developed in the Phase I project are scaled to high throughput and low cost fabrication methods. The process/structure/property relationships of this novel coating will be investigated and lead to new scientific knowledge related to the large-scale deployment of nanoparticle based technologies. The coated glass will be subjected to industry standard reliability and durability tests. The expected outcome of this work is the demonstration of this technology at a pilot level with industry collaborators.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>02/01/2016</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>09/10/2018</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1556072</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Corey</FirstName>
<LastName>Thompson</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Corey Thompson</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>corey@wattglass.com</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5018505659</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000671370</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>02/01/2016</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>WattGlass LLC</Name>
<CityName>Fayetteville</CityName>
<ZipCode>727017175</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5018505659</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>700 Research Center Blvd.</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Arkansas</StateName>
<StateCode>AR</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>AR03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>079423186</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>WATTGLASS, INC</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[WattGlass LLC]]></Name>
<CityName>Fayetteville</CityName>
<StateCode>AR</StateCode>
<ZipCode>727017175</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[700 W Research Center Blvd]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Arkansas</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>AR03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>5373</Code>
<Text>SBIR Phase II</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>123E</Code>
<Text>CENTERS: ADVANCED MATERIALS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>165E</Code>
<Text>SBIR Phase IIB</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>5373</Code>
<Text>SMALL BUSINESS PHASE II</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7423</Code>
<Text>Energy collection &amp; storage</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8240</Code>
<Text>SBIR/STTR CAP</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0116</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0117</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0118</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2016~746366</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2017~10000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2018~541638</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The goals of this Phase II project were to demonstrate and develop a unique water-based antireflective coating solution for glass substrates. The progress made in the first six months of the Phase II project was focused on the key areas of coating chemistry development and optimization, demonstration of the coating on an industry standard tool, and development of a low-temperature cure process. In months 6-12 of the project, the efforts were focused on further improving the chemistry of the coating composition, evaluating self-cleaning behavior, and understanding wetting properties of the coated glass. In months 12 ? 18 of the project, the efforts were focused on optimizing the coating process using the newly installed tool, validating cost and performance with an early adopter in the LED lighting market, and understanding and optimizing the anti-fogging properties of our coating. The outcome of our Phase II project was a pilot partnership in the LED lighting market that led to customer adoption of the coating in two lens designs for roadway and parking lot applications.&nbsp;</p> <p>During the Phase II project, WattGlass purchased and installed a commercial roll coating machine. This tool has been used to optimize the coating solution for maximum increase in solar weighted transmittance and durability. The installation was completed on August 3, 2017. The initial results yielded solar weighted transmittances of over 3%; however, additional process optimization was needed to improve spatial uniformity and to remove edge effects. Within 3 months of installation, all of the aesthetic requirements for the solar industry on float glass substrates were met. As a result of the project, a minimum viable product was brought to market in the LED lighting space. Additional optimization of&nbsp;&nbsp;the chemistry of the coating were made throughout the Phase II project.&nbsp;</p> <p>Additionally, during the Phase II project we devoted significant effort into understanding the needs of our customer base and tuning our value proposition.&nbsp;We have worked to develop a cost model that is specific to our chemistry, deposition method, and throughput capabilities.&nbsp;Additionally, WattGlass was able to utilize the Phase II research tasks to significantly improve our understanding of the coating chemistry and develop methods to optimize and control the behavior of the surface. For example, we&nbsp;developed a method to measure the soiling and cleaning cycle using an indoor test method. Using this test method, we identified two unique phenomenon that are related to our coating. This early understanding led to additional research work that was conducted in collaboration with Stanford Linear Accelerator Center (SLAC) that conclusively showed the antisoiling behavior of the WattGlass coating when compared to uncoated glass.&nbsp;</p> <p>Also during the Phase II work, we successfully passed the three most rigorous tests for antireflective coatings: damp heat (pressure cooker test), abrasion, and water immersion.&nbsp;</p> <p>A TECP project was funded with a commercial partner to meet industry needs for an antifog and antifrost coating for commercial refrigerated doors. The coatings produced exhibited a correlation between the coating thickness and the degree of anti-fog and anti-frost behavior. Small samples (4? x 4?) were successfully coated that demonstrated no frost formation after removing from a freezer. Unfortunately, the film thickness required is on the order of 200-500 microns which is substantially thicker than our reverse gravure roll-coating tool can produce. These film thicknesses are easily achieved with direct gravure coaters which are commonly used in painting type applications in the glass and wood industry. WattGlass is currently working with a coating equipment provider to deposit the coating on full scale freezer doors as a prototype.</p> <p>A Phase II-B project was also funded that led to significant developments in the understanding of water-based coatings for the solar industry. A tape-peel test is utilized in the solar market to replicate the transfer of material to the surface of the glass during the lay-up and lamination steps of the module production process. The silicone and EVA used in the process can adhere to the surface of the module and result in aesthetic and performance problems. The original coating formulation did not perform well in the tape-peel test due to high surface energy and high nanoscale surface roughness that allows strong adhesion of the tape. When the tape is peeled from the surface, a large amount of the adhesive remains. By controlling the interaction between binders and particles, we were able to increase the binder concentration to create a surface structure that was less adhesive to the tape, and ultimately passed the tape-peel test.</p> <p>Significant advances in the fundamental science and formulation of water-based silica coatings was achieved in this project. The resulting knowledge will have significant impacts on the formulation of nanoscale functional coatings that do not require hazardous solvents or alkoxysilanes to produce.&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 03/25/2020<br>      Modified by: Corey&nbsp;Thompson</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Image         </div> <div class="galControls onePhoto" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation onePhoto" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2020/1556072/1556072_10409239_1585108754000_Presentation2--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2020/1556072/1556072_10409239_1585108754000_Presentation2--rgov-800width.jpg" title="WattGlass Coating"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2020/1556072/1556072_10409239_1585108754000_Presentation2--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="WattGlass Coating"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">WattGlass has developed a water-based nanoparticle coating to increase the amount of light transmitted by glass used in LED lighting, Solar, and Thin-Film Solar markets.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Corey Thompson</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Corey&nbsp;Thompson</div> <div class="imageTitle">WattGlass Coating</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The goals of this Phase II project were to demonstrate and develop a unique water-based antireflective coating solution for glass substrates. The progress made in the first six months of the Phase II project was focused on the key areas of coating chemistry development and optimization, demonstration of the coating on an industry standard tool, and development of a low-temperature cure process. In months 6-12 of the project, the efforts were focused on further improving the chemistry of the coating composition, evaluating self-cleaning behavior, and understanding wetting properties of the coated glass. In months 12 ? 18 of the project, the efforts were focused on optimizing the coating process using the newly installed tool, validating cost and performance with an early adopter in the LED lighting market, and understanding and optimizing the anti-fogging properties of our coating. The outcome of our Phase II project was a pilot partnership in the LED lighting market that led to customer adoption of the coating in two lens designs for roadway and parking lot applications.   During the Phase II project, WattGlass purchased and installed a commercial roll coating machine. This tool has been used to optimize the coating solution for maximum increase in solar weighted transmittance and durability. The installation was completed on August 3, 2017. The initial results yielded solar weighted transmittances of over 3%; however, additional process optimization was needed to improve spatial uniformity and to remove edge effects. Within 3 months of installation, all of the aesthetic requirements for the solar industry on float glass substrates were met. As a result of the project, a minimum viable product was brought to market in the LED lighting space. Additional optimization of  the chemistry of the coating were made throughout the Phase II project.   Additionally, during the Phase II project we devoted significant effort into understanding the needs of our customer base and tuning our value proposition. We have worked to develop a cost model that is specific to our chemistry, deposition method, and throughput capabilities. Additionally, WattGlass was able to utilize the Phase II research tasks to significantly improve our understanding of the coating chemistry and develop methods to optimize and control the behavior of the surface. For example, we developed a method to measure the soiling and cleaning cycle using an indoor test method. Using this test method, we identified two unique phenomenon that are related to our coating. This early understanding led to additional research work that was conducted in collaboration with Stanford Linear Accelerator Center (SLAC) that conclusively showed the antisoiling behavior of the WattGlass coating when compared to uncoated glass.   Also during the Phase II work, we successfully passed the three most rigorous tests for antireflective coatings: damp heat (pressure cooker test), abrasion, and water immersion.   A TECP project was funded with a commercial partner to meet industry needs for an antifog and antifrost coating for commercial refrigerated doors. The coatings produced exhibited a correlation between the coating thickness and the degree of anti-fog and anti-frost behavior. Small samples (4? x 4?) were successfully coated that demonstrated no frost formation after removing from a freezer. Unfortunately, the film thickness required is on the order of 200-500 microns which is substantially thicker than our reverse gravure roll-coating tool can produce. These film thicknesses are easily achieved with direct gravure coaters which are commonly used in painting type applications in the glass and wood industry. WattGlass is currently working with a coating equipment provider to deposit the coating on full scale freezer doors as a prototype.  A Phase II-B project was also funded that led to significant developments in the understanding of water-based coatings for the solar industry. A tape-peel test is utilized in the solar market to replicate the transfer of material to the surface of the glass during the lay-up and lamination steps of the module production process. The silicone and EVA used in the process can adhere to the surface of the module and result in aesthetic and performance problems. The original coating formulation did not perform well in the tape-peel test due to high surface energy and high nanoscale surface roughness that allows strong adhesion of the tape. When the tape is peeled from the surface, a large amount of the adhesive remains. By controlling the interaction between binders and particles, we were able to increase the binder concentration to create a surface structure that was less adhesive to the tape, and ultimately passed the tape-peel test.  Significant advances in the fundamental science and formulation of water-based silica coatings was achieved in this project. The resulting knowledge will have significant impacts on the formulation of nanoscale functional coatings that do not require hazardous solvents or alkoxysilanes to produce.           Last Modified: 03/25/2020       Submitted by: Corey Thompson]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
