<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Doctorial Dissertation Research: Classification Representation in the Sciences: the Epistemology and Ontology of Botanical Taxonomic Systems</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2016</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>17702.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>17702</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>04050000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>SBE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>SES</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Divn Of Social and Economic Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Frederick Kronz</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>fkronz@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927283</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>General Audience Summary &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This dissertation project will combine international archival and qualitative fieldwork to better understand the evolution of taxonomic forms. The project begins with an examination of Pre-Linnaean bound manuscripts and Enlightenment-era printed texts. It culminates with a careful examination of the contemporary Catalogue of Life, a federated database containing the largest cache of taxonomic information of the known forms of life on Earth. One goal of the project is to show how taxonomy-disseminating technologies influence the construction and use of classification systems. Attention will be given to the Western-centric nature of these scientific systems of organization, and how one method of classification may not fit all of our global needs. The taxonomies that are the focus of this study arose from distinctly Western traditions, and evolved with their presuppositions engrained in their infrastructure. As a result, their taxonomic conventions can conflict with culturally and geographically local and endemic descriptive methods. Another goal of this study is to bring some of these cultural biases to light. By broadening discussion about these systems, new modes of cross-communicable and flexible taxonomic infrastructures between communities are more likely to occur. By bridging local biodiversity knowledge (endemic, underrepresented, cultural marginalized, citizen science, etc.) with larger scientific infrastructures, and by pooling our global knowledge resources in a more open, culturally attentive way, the chances of maintaining what natural biological species exist today increases exponentially.  &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Technical Summary &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project will contribute to our understanding of how the forms in which we disseminate taxonomic information influence the way that information is used and understood to fundamentally relate to our knowledge of the world, and to the way in which their ontological organization is influenced by inherited epistemologies from previous taxonomic systems. Additionally, given the widespread use of taxonomy databases in number of disciplines, this study can shed light on the multivariate uses of taxonomies and promote more inter-disciplinary collaboration and communication regarding the construction, organization, and flexibility of these infrastructures. Finally, by looking at scientific knowledge organization systems from an historical, information, and technical framework, we can learn much about how the contemporary world deals with, and can potentially solve, the often-incommensurate information structures embedded into the myriad of digital systems, software, and idiosyncratic computational platforms that are encountered daily, a problem assured to amplify in the future.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>01/14/2016</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>01/14/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.075</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1556062</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Johanna</FirstName>
<LastName>Drucker</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Johanna Drucker</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>drucker@gseis.ucla.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>3107940102</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000675405</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>01/14/2016</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Robert</FirstName>
<LastName>Montoya</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>D</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Robert D Montoya</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>montoya@indiana.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>8128562369</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000699909</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>01/14/2016</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of California-Los Angeles</Name>
<CityName>LOS ANGELES</CityName>
<ZipCode>900951406</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>3107940102</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>10889 Wilshire Boulevard</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[Suite 700]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>33</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CA33</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>092530369</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF CALIFORNIA, LOS ANGELES</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>071549000</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of California-Los Angeles]]></Name>
<CityName>Los Angeles</CityName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>900951406</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[11000 Kinross Ave, Suite 211]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>33</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CA33</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7603</Code>
<Text>STS-Sci, Tech &amp; Society</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1353</Code>
<Text>Hist &amp; Philosophy of SET</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7603</Code>
<Text>SCIENCE, TECH &amp; SOCIETY</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9179</Code>
<Text>GRADUATE INVOLVEMENT</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0116</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2016~17702</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The Doctoral Dissertation Research Improvement Grant (DDRIG) allowed Robert D. Montoya to collect the data necessary for his doctoral work, and to subsequently complete his dissertation, which was successfully defended in May 2017. This dissertation strove to understand the evolution of taxonomic forms in the biodiversity domains, and to better examine how contemporary global taxonomies were balancing various taxonomic viewpoints within one database infrastructure. To do so, Montoya examined the Catalogue of Life, a global management taxonomy, to see how global biodiversity data is being standardized and reconciled into a structured global species checklist and management hierarchy.</p> <p>The most active period for the DDRIP grant encompassed data collection between the months of June 2016 and November 2016. Data collection broadly encompassed two collection methods: archival documentary research and semi-structured interviews. This work encompassed nearly two months of travel, including nine archives/field study sites, the examination of approximately seventy-five archival and documentary collections, thirty interviews, and organizational meeting attendance. The main archives of interest were those at the Natural History Museum in London, the Linnean Society, and Royal Botanical Gardens, Kew. The documents viewed focused on the development of historical taxonomic systems, as well as how these historical systems were organized in early computational and informatics environments. The DDRIG also facilitated a number of interviews with taxonomists, biodiversity informaticians, and museum administrators, both within and without the Catalogue of Life organization. Sites included the Smithsonian National Museum of Natural History, home to the administrative offices of the Integrated Taxonomic Information System (ITIS); the Natural History Museum of London; Royal Botanical Gardens, Kew; Naturalis Biodiversity Center; and the Natural History Museum in Copenhagen, Denmark, home to the Secretariat of the Global Biodiversity Information Facility (GBIF), one of the largest repositories of biodiversity open data infrastructures on the globe. Collectively, this data provided Montoya the ability to examine how biodiversity taxonomies balance various taxonomic traditions, in addition to the more general challenge of controlling biodiversity data and documentation in global, distributed computational spaces.</p> <p>The fundamental questions I ask in this project relate to how we can think about extending the concepts of Information Studies (encompassing the subdiscipline of Library &amp; Information Science) outward to think about classificatory domains that otherwise have received very little notice in our discipline, or at least that have not received much in-depth notice in quite some time. This project has produced a balanced view of the strengths and limitations of Knowledge Organization in the biodiversity sciences, as well as how such approaches can inform diversification practices within Information Studies. Likewise, there is a broad range of skills and theories within Information Studies that can benefit the biodiversity community. Information Studies has a long tradition of social justice and equal access to information. Attending to issues related to diversity within the field of Information Studies happens at many levels within the profession, including how we conduct our research in culturally-attentive ways, design inclusive information systems, diversify the students that make their way into the profession, and support certain communities over others as part of our work in information institutions.&nbsp;</p> <p>The theoretical findings of this project show how global biodiversity systems necessarily make various consensus-based negotiations regarding biodiversity taxonomies and data coordination. Such decisions are made in order to make this data structured, useable, and as &ldquo;universal&rdquo; as possible. In the process of negotiating these global standards, some information is necessarily omitted or altered in order to make a cohesive system. In light of this process, this dissertation identified what kinds of excluded information needs to be attended to in future biodiversity systems to create more comprehensive data caches. Reconciling such issues is vital since global, aggregated biodiversity taxonomic systems are deeply embedded in teaching practices at all levels and is routinely consulted to make domestic and international governmental policy decisions. Further, these taxonomies are used to structure other information organizing systems in ancillary disciplines such as environmental science, ecological studies, among others, making them very powerful information artifacts. Lastly, given that this dissertation was completed within the field of Information Studies&mdash;a field broadly interested in promoting open access, culturally-relevant information sources, net neutrality, etc.&mdash;this dissertation further sheds light on how computational and organizational systems in general have engrained limitations based on their commitments to certain kinds of institutional and cultural knowledge sets. Building on existing critical data and knowledge organizing literature, this research lays the foundation for, and contextualizes, the next steps required to create more inclusive information systems beyond those examined the scientific environment.</p> <p>The research performed under the DDRIG has also laid the foundation for the next phase of my project that will bring together expertise from multiple domains to develop <em>implementable</em> systems that allow for the application of diverse and interoperable classifications (and ontologies) using networked technologies, text-mining methodologies, and qualitative modes of analysis.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 07/21/2017<br>      Modified by: Robert&nbsp;D&nbsp;Montoya</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The Doctoral Dissertation Research Improvement Grant (DDRIG) allowed Robert D. Montoya to collect the data necessary for his doctoral work, and to subsequently complete his dissertation, which was successfully defended in May 2017. This dissertation strove to understand the evolution of taxonomic forms in the biodiversity domains, and to better examine how contemporary global taxonomies were balancing various taxonomic viewpoints within one database infrastructure. To do so, Montoya examined the Catalogue of Life, a global management taxonomy, to see how global biodiversity data is being standardized and reconciled into a structured global species checklist and management hierarchy.  The most active period for the DDRIP grant encompassed data collection between the months of June 2016 and November 2016. Data collection broadly encompassed two collection methods: archival documentary research and semi-structured interviews. This work encompassed nearly two months of travel, including nine archives/field study sites, the examination of approximately seventy-five archival and documentary collections, thirty interviews, and organizational meeting attendance. The main archives of interest were those at the Natural History Museum in London, the Linnean Society, and Royal Botanical Gardens, Kew. The documents viewed focused on the development of historical taxonomic systems, as well as how these historical systems were organized in early computational and informatics environments. The DDRIG also facilitated a number of interviews with taxonomists, biodiversity informaticians, and museum administrators, both within and without the Catalogue of Life organization. Sites included the Smithsonian National Museum of Natural History, home to the administrative offices of the Integrated Taxonomic Information System (ITIS); the Natural History Museum of London; Royal Botanical Gardens, Kew; Naturalis Biodiversity Center; and the Natural History Museum in Copenhagen, Denmark, home to the Secretariat of the Global Biodiversity Information Facility (GBIF), one of the largest repositories of biodiversity open data infrastructures on the globe. Collectively, this data provided Montoya the ability to examine how biodiversity taxonomies balance various taxonomic traditions, in addition to the more general challenge of controlling biodiversity data and documentation in global, distributed computational spaces.  The fundamental questions I ask in this project relate to how we can think about extending the concepts of Information Studies (encompassing the subdiscipline of Library &amp; Information Science) outward to think about classificatory domains that otherwise have received very little notice in our discipline, or at least that have not received much in-depth notice in quite some time. This project has produced a balanced view of the strengths and limitations of Knowledge Organization in the biodiversity sciences, as well as how such approaches can inform diversification practices within Information Studies. Likewise, there is a broad range of skills and theories within Information Studies that can benefit the biodiversity community. Information Studies has a long tradition of social justice and equal access to information. Attending to issues related to diversity within the field of Information Studies happens at many levels within the profession, including how we conduct our research in culturally-attentive ways, design inclusive information systems, diversify the students that make their way into the profession, and support certain communities over others as part of our work in information institutions.   The theoretical findings of this project show how global biodiversity systems necessarily make various consensus-based negotiations regarding biodiversity taxonomies and data coordination. Such decisions are made in order to make this data structured, useable, and as "universal" as possible. In the process of negotiating these global standards, some information is necessarily omitted or altered in order to make a cohesive system. In light of this process, this dissertation identified what kinds of excluded information needs to be attended to in future biodiversity systems to create more comprehensive data caches. Reconciling such issues is vital since global, aggregated biodiversity taxonomic systems are deeply embedded in teaching practices at all levels and is routinely consulted to make domestic and international governmental policy decisions. Further, these taxonomies are used to structure other information organizing systems in ancillary disciplines such as environmental science, ecological studies, among others, making them very powerful information artifacts. Lastly, given that this dissertation was completed within the field of Information Studies&mdash;a field broadly interested in promoting open access, culturally-relevant information sources, net neutrality, etc.&mdash;this dissertation further sheds light on how computational and organizational systems in general have engrained limitations based on their commitments to certain kinds of institutional and cultural knowledge sets. Building on existing critical data and knowledge organizing literature, this research lays the foundation for, and contextualizes, the next steps required to create more inclusive information systems beyond those examined the scientific environment.  The research performed under the DDRIG has also laid the foundation for the next phase of my project that will bring together expertise from multiple domains to develop implementable systems that allow for the application of diverse and interoperable classifications (and ontologies) using networked technologies, text-mining methodologies, and qualitative modes of analysis.          Last Modified: 07/21/2017       Submitted by: Robert D Montoya]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
