<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Collaborative Research: How Do U.S. Immigration Courts Decide Gender-based Asylum Cases?</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>02/15/2016</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>01/31/2020</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>42551.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>79497</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>04050000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>SBE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>SES</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Divn Of Social and Economic Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Reggie Sheehan</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>rsheehan@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032925389</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>How do immigration judges decide when to grant someone asylum when they claim protection on the basis of gender?  This collaborative study will illuminate the decision making processes in the evolving field of gender-based asylum law. It is especially timely because the legal refugee definition does not explicitly designate gender as a ground for protection, gender-based claims are fraught. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The researchers will undertake a study of the largest known repository of immigration court asylum decisions from around the country (more than 760 decisions) housed at the Center for Gender &amp; Refugee Studies of UC Hastings and supplement those with decisions obtained through FOIA requests. They will create an original data set to systematically examine how factors such as case facts patterns and legal precedent affect legal outcomes. This unique study will examine a level of immigration bureaucracy never before studied in this regard.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>02/10/2016</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>03/14/2018</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.075</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1556551</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Anna</FirstName>
<LastName>Law</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Anna Law</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>alaw@brooklyn.cuny.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>7189515622</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000686531</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>02/10/2016</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>CUNY Brooklyn College</Name>
<CityName>Brooklyn</CityName>
<ZipCode>112102889</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>7189515622</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>Office of Research &amp; Sponsored P</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[2900 Bedford Ave]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>09</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NY09</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>620127691</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>RESEARCH FOUNDATION OF THE CITY UNIVERSITY OF NEW YORK</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>073268849</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[CUNY Brooklyn College]]></Name>
<CityName>Brooklyn</CityName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<ZipCode>112102850</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[2900 Bedford Avenue]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>09</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NY09</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1372</Code>
<Text>LSS-Law And Social Sciences</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1372</Code>
<Text>LAW AND SOCIAL SCIENCES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0116</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0117</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0118</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2016~60000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2017~16946</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2018~2551</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>How do Immigration Judges (IJs) and Members of the Board of Immigration Appeals (BIA) decide gender-based asylum cases, and why? Because past studies on U.S. asylum law were largely focused on the influence of foreign policy, those studies treated administrative and/or judicial institutions as unitary actors when the diverse immigration bureaucracy includes layers of Executive Branch administrative agencies and the federal courts of appeal. Our study focuses on executive agency-level adjudication of asylum claims, based on decisions of: (1) IJs, the linchpins of the adversarial asylum framework who decide cases in the first instance; and (2) BIA Members, who adjudicate appeals of IJ decisions. We concentrate our research here because of the criticism these bodies have received over their politicization and disparate treatment of asylum claims and because they dictate the vast majority of asylum case outcomes. Applicants very rarely appeal their denials of protection to the federal courts of appeal, and individuals who do appeal face uphill battles in seeking to obtain reversal.</p> <p>Administrative agency decision-making is difficult to study. While the published and unpublished decisions of the federal courts of appeals and the Supreme Court are available on searchable public databases, most agency decisions are not. Previous studies of IJ decision-making have thus primarily relied on quantitative data supplied by the Executive Office of Immigration Review (EOIR) or data that was otherwise publicly available .</p> <p>In this study, we have sought to build on prior quantitative studies of agency decision-making based on EOIR data by quantitatively and qualitatively analyzing a set of agency decisions in more depth. To accomplish this, we&nbsp; built an original dataset from the largest-known repository of IJ and BIA asylum decisions, maintained by the Center for Gender and Refugee Studies (CGRS) at UC Hastings, consisting of 509 IJ decisions and 271 BIA decisions. We devised more than 40 variables to analyze the most important issues in asylum adjudication, and in gender-based asylum specifically. The variables address: (1) characteristics of asylum applicants (e.g. age, gender, nationality); (2) characteristics of adjudicators (e.g. gender, prior employment background, asylum grant rate); (3) institutional factors (e.g. detention status, type of legal counsel if any); (4) case facts (e.g. type of persecution, nature of past harm) and (5) legal issues and analysis (e.g. whether the applicant was found credible, whether the adjudicator found the applicant failed to establish certain legal elements required to establish eligibility for relief. The cross-tabbing of these variables with legal outcomes in asylum, withholding of removal, and Convention Against Torture claims will be very revealing.</p> <p>At this point, we have coded the complete dataset and have almost completed our verification of intercoder reliability, allowing us to begin engaging in an in-depth analysis. Our analysis is both quantitative and qualitative, deploying a textual and interpretative analysis of the IJ and BIA decisions. Our research output, which will be based on crosstabs of our variables with decision outcomes, will take the form of policy papers and law review and social science journal articles, which we hope to compile into a book-length analysis.</p> <p>Our main intellectual contribution is to re-evaluate and extend theories of decision-making by analyzing legal and non-legal variables directly relevant to U.S. asylum law in IJ and BIA decisions.<em> </em>Our innovation is to systematically code case facts and legal analysis based on actual written decisions. This enables us to go beyond the analysis of quantitative EOIR data, which tells us what the IJs decided, in order to analyze <em>why</em> IJs and BIA members decided as they did in certain types of cases. Asylum law presents a particularly productive area for exploring administrative decision-making given the tensions in the institutional expectations placed upon adjudicators. IJs are trained and expected to neutrally apply principles of law; yet, as Executive Branch employees, they lack the guarantees of lifetime tenure, leading to detrimental pressures, a problem about which IJs themselves have spoken out.</p> <p>Our research will have significant impacts on academia, policy, and practitioner communities. The U.S. asylum adjudication system is central not only to our international legal obligations, but also to trust in our immigration system. At a time when Donald Trump has made immigration policy a centerpiece of his presidency and implemented policies further limiting the independence of agency adjudicators, the role of individual IJs and BIA members within this system has garnered much attention and criticism. These concerns are especially pressing in light of the ongoing arrival of migrants seeking asylum protection, and the controversies surrounding policy responses to these flows such as increased detention. We hope this research will enable us to recommend policies to improve the quality and fairness of agency adjudication. Our findings will also be timely should a Democratic president win the 2020 election and wish to revisit policies relating to immigration court and BIA administration and decision-making.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 05/30/2020<br>      Modified by: Anna&nbsp;Law</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ How do Immigration Judges (IJs) and Members of the Board of Immigration Appeals (BIA) decide gender-based asylum cases, and why? Because past studies on U.S. asylum law were largely focused on the influence of foreign policy, those studies treated administrative and/or judicial institutions as unitary actors when the diverse immigration bureaucracy includes layers of Executive Branch administrative agencies and the federal courts of appeal. Our study focuses on executive agency-level adjudication of asylum claims, based on decisions of: (1) IJs, the linchpins of the adversarial asylum framework who decide cases in the first instance; and (2) BIA Members, who adjudicate appeals of IJ decisions. We concentrate our research here because of the criticism these bodies have received over their politicization and disparate treatment of asylum claims and because they dictate the vast majority of asylum case outcomes. Applicants very rarely appeal their denials of protection to the federal courts of appeal, and individuals who do appeal face uphill battles in seeking to obtain reversal.  Administrative agency decision-making is difficult to study. While the published and unpublished decisions of the federal courts of appeals and the Supreme Court are available on searchable public databases, most agency decisions are not. Previous studies of IJ decision-making have thus primarily relied on quantitative data supplied by the Executive Office of Immigration Review (EOIR) or data that was otherwise publicly available .  In this study, we have sought to build on prior quantitative studies of agency decision-making based on EOIR data by quantitatively and qualitatively analyzing a set of agency decisions in more depth. To accomplish this, we  built an original dataset from the largest-known repository of IJ and BIA asylum decisions, maintained by the Center for Gender and Refugee Studies (CGRS) at UC Hastings, consisting of 509 IJ decisions and 271 BIA decisions. We devised more than 40 variables to analyze the most important issues in asylum adjudication, and in gender-based asylum specifically. The variables address: (1) characteristics of asylum applicants (e.g. age, gender, nationality); (2) characteristics of adjudicators (e.g. gender, prior employment background, asylum grant rate); (3) institutional factors (e.g. detention status, type of legal counsel if any); (4) case facts (e.g. type of persecution, nature of past harm) and (5) legal issues and analysis (e.g. whether the applicant was found credible, whether the adjudicator found the applicant failed to establish certain legal elements required to establish eligibility for relief. The cross-tabbing of these variables with legal outcomes in asylum, withholding of removal, and Convention Against Torture claims will be very revealing.  At this point, we have coded the complete dataset and have almost completed our verification of intercoder reliability, allowing us to begin engaging in an in-depth analysis. Our analysis is both quantitative and qualitative, deploying a textual and interpretative analysis of the IJ and BIA decisions. Our research output, which will be based on crosstabs of our variables with decision outcomes, will take the form of policy papers and law review and social science journal articles, which we hope to compile into a book-length analysis.  Our main intellectual contribution is to re-evaluate and extend theories of decision-making by analyzing legal and non-legal variables directly relevant to U.S. asylum law in IJ and BIA decisions. Our innovation is to systematically code case facts and legal analysis based on actual written decisions. This enables us to go beyond the analysis of quantitative EOIR data, which tells us what the IJs decided, in order to analyze why IJs and BIA members decided as they did in certain types of cases. Asylum law presents a particularly productive area for exploring administrative decision-making given the tensions in the institutional expectations placed upon adjudicators. IJs are trained and expected to neutrally apply principles of law; yet, as Executive Branch employees, they lack the guarantees of lifetime tenure, leading to detrimental pressures, a problem about which IJs themselves have spoken out.  Our research will have significant impacts on academia, policy, and practitioner communities. The U.S. asylum adjudication system is central not only to our international legal obligations, but also to trust in our immigration system. At a time when Donald Trump has made immigration policy a centerpiece of his presidency and implemented policies further limiting the independence of agency adjudicators, the role of individual IJs and BIA members within this system has garnered much attention and criticism. These concerns are especially pressing in light of the ongoing arrival of migrants seeking asylum protection, and the controversies surrounding policy responses to these flows such as increased detention. We hope this research will enable us to recommend policies to improve the quality and fairness of agency adjudication. Our findings will also be timely should a Democratic president win the 2020 election and wish to revisit policies relating to immigration court and BIA administration and decision-making.       Last Modified: 05/30/2020       Submitted by: Anna Law]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
