<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>I-Corps: Materials for CO2 Capture</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2015</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2016</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>50000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>50000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07070000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>IIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Industrial Innovation &amp; Partnersh</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Steven Konsek</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>skonsek@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927021</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>CO2 appears as a contaminant or impurity in gas mixtures in oil industries, and because of the environmental impacts of CO2 emissions, lawmakers are beginning to require the separation of CO2 from combustion products. Consequently, CO2 separation is an issue in power plants, heavy industries, hydrogen production, natural gas sweetening, and air purification plants, among other industries. However, the currently available options for CO2 separation are limited and uneconomical. One contemporary method is absorption, a well-matured but energy-intensive and expensive approach. For example, the benchmark for chemical absorption based on monoethanolamine (MEA), a widely used absorbent, currently imposes costs of over $70 per metric ton of CO2 due to the high cost of solvent regeneration;  overall, capturing CO2 emissions from power plants using conventional technologies requires 20-30% of the plant's energy output.  This high cost is the single largest obstacle for the widespread industrial adoption of CO2 capture technologies. Therefore, industry has an urgent need for the development of high-performance and low-cost technologies and materials that enable capital-efficient CO2 capture. A promising alternative process for CO2 capture is adsorption by porous materials: candidate adsorbents for CO2 separation should selectively adsorb CO2 from gas mixtures and have large surface areas to accommodate CO2 molecules into the pores. Based on a novel, suitable adsorbent recently developed by members of the proposed I-Corps team, the aim of this project is to commercialize a new series of adsorbents (zeolitic imidazolate frameworks, or ZIFs) that exhibit superior selectivity for separating CO2 from other gases and that have significant surface area to store it. This technology has been developed at a critical time for the CO2 capture market. Strict emission standards have been imposed by the U.S. government and several other countries and entities such as Canada, China, and the European Union, but there is not yet an optimal or even existing product available to meet the required needs. The proposed ZIF, with its outstanding capability for high-selectivity CO2 capture, therefore provides a revolutionary solution at a time of severe market need. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Metal-organic frameworks (MOFs) are hybrid porous materials constructed from organic linkers and metal-containing nodes. The typical specific surface areas - and hence, gas adsorption capacities - that MOFs provide are an order of magnitude higher than those of zeolites.  ZIFs are a subfamily of MOFs. They have an M(Im)4 zeolite-type framework in which tetrahedral elements, M, are transition metals bridged by imidazolate (Im) moieties. ZIFs can adsorb CO2 emissions and store five times more than existing adsorbents before requiring regeneration. For example, each unit volume of ZIF-69 can store up to 83 times its volume in CO2.  Moreover, ZIFs can exhibit high chemical and thermal stability,  and therefore can be robust processes for CO2 capture. In this comprehensive study, we propose the synthesis of a new subclass of ZIFs that, as indicated by Monte-Carlo-based simulation, have a 100-fold-increased CO2 capture capacity compared to the isostructural ZIFs. This increase in CO2 capture capacity was accompanied by only negligible changes in capture capacity for CH4, H2, and N2; therefore, the uptake ratio of CO2 to the other gases increased significantly, indicating very high selectivity for CO2 separation in our novel ZIFs. This set of abilities could significantly reduce the cost of carbon separation and capture at combustion-based power plants, heavy industries, natural gas processing, and hydrogen production companies.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/25/2015</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/25/2015</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1556442</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Reza</FirstName>
<LastName>Foudazi</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Reza Foudazi</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>rfoudazi@nmsu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5756461590</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000667786</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/25/2015</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Theresa</FirstName>
<LastName>Lombard</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>A</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Theresa A Lombard</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>tlombard@nmsu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5756461590</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000700965</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/25/2015</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>New Mexico State University</Name>
<CityName>Las Cruces</CityName>
<ZipCode>880038002</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5756461590</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>Corner of Espina St. &amp; Stewart</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[MSC OGC, Box 30002]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New Mexico</StateName>
<StateCode>NM</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NM02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>173851965</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>NEW MEXICO STATE UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>861367373</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[New Mexico State University]]></Name>
<CityName>Las Cruces</CityName>
<StateCode>NM</StateCode>
<ZipCode>880038002</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[Corner of Espina St. & Stewart]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New Mexico</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NM02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>8023</Code>
<Text>I-Corps</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0115</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2015~50000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><span>In a previous study, we synthesized a new <span>zeolitic</span> <span>imidazolate</span> framework (<span>ZIF</span>). <span>ZIFs</span> are a subclass of metal-organic frameworks (<span>MOFs</span>). The simulation study predicted superior selectivities for separating CO2 from other gases and a 100-fold increase in the capacity to adsorb and store CO2. Through I-Corps program, we tried to identify the optimal approach for bringing our technology to market, offering its cost-saving benefits to industry and its environmental benefits to the world. By participating in the University of Michigan Center for Entrepreneurship (<span>CFE</span>) and working with the experienced I-Corps instructors, the principal investigator, mentor, and&nbsp;entrepreneur lead:</span></p> <ul> <li>have been trained for fundamental of entrepreneurship, customer discovery, business models;</li> <li>performed weekly update and presentation of business canvas model; and,</li> <li>carried out customer discovery (more than 100 interviews).</li> </ul> <p><span>Figure 1 shows the value proposition, customer relationship, and customer segments sections of the final business canvas model developed in this project. The acquired skills are likely to be used by the team in future for commercializing their other research results beyond what this I-Corps project promotes. The main learning outcome for the principal investigator and entrepreneurial lead is that scientists need to get in touch with general population (potential customers) during technology development since identifying potential problems through customer discovery is critical to take a technology from lab to the market. Secondly, technologies discovered in the laboratory are not necessarily <span>commercializable</span>.</span></p> <p>Through customer discovery, it was found that carbon capture market could be divided into two categories: first, the market at which CO<sub>2</sub> is a contaminant in the product and thus, its separation is a must. The example of such markets is natural gas, hydrogen production, and air purification industries. Although this market is not big but it is sustainable. Second category is the market at which CO<sub>2</sub> is not a contaminant (for example is a by-product of combustion), thus, the associated industrial sectors are not willing to perform carbon capture; however, policy makers force them to do so by applying regulatory approaches such as carbon tax. In this project, we focused on the second category, which is potentially very vast. The example of such markets is power plants that are being forced to first control carbon emission, and later capture part of their emissions.</p> <p>About eight years ago, countermeasures for global warming were declared in U.S.A. Consequently, carbon capture projects have been supported by major governmental departments such as the Department of Energy and the Environmental Protection Agency. Our customer discovery revealed that such supports have changed the status of the United States from a passive country to a leader in the area of carbon capture and storage; the role that European countries could not effectively perform due to their weaknesses in resources and international influence. However, we found that uncertainty and being policy-driven are still the biggest obstacles for taking the materials for CO2 capture to market in the current economy of U.S.A.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 12/08/2016<br>      Modified by: Reza&nbsp;Foudazi</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Image         </div> <div class="galControls onePhoto" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation onePhoto" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2016/1556442/1556442_10391709_1481236563978_FinalCanvas--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2016/1556442/1556442_10391709_1481236563978_FinalCanvas--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Figure 1"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2016/1556442/1556442_10391709_1481236563978_FinalCanvas--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Figure 1"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">The value proposition, customer relationship, and customer segments sections of the final business canvas model developed in this project</div> <div class="imageCredit">Authors</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Reza&nbsp;Foudazi</div> <div class="imageTitle">Figure 1</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ In a previous study, we synthesized a new zeolitic imidazolate framework (ZIF). ZIFs are a subclass of metal-organic frameworks (MOFs). The simulation study predicted superior selectivities for separating CO2 from other gases and a 100-fold increase in the capacity to adsorb and store CO2. Through I-Corps program, we tried to identify the optimal approach for bringing our technology to market, offering its cost-saving benefits to industry and its environmental benefits to the world. By participating in the University of Michigan Center for Entrepreneurship (CFE) and working with the experienced I-Corps instructors, the principal investigator, mentor, and entrepreneur lead:  have been trained for fundamental of entrepreneurship, customer discovery, business models; performed weekly update and presentation of business canvas model; and, carried out customer discovery (more than 100 interviews).   Figure 1 shows the value proposition, customer relationship, and customer segments sections of the final business canvas model developed in this project. The acquired skills are likely to be used by the team in future for commercializing their other research results beyond what this I-Corps project promotes. The main learning outcome for the principal investigator and entrepreneurial lead is that scientists need to get in touch with general population (potential customers) during technology development since identifying potential problems through customer discovery is critical to take a technology from lab to the market. Secondly, technologies discovered in the laboratory are not necessarily commercializable.  Through customer discovery, it was found that carbon capture market could be divided into two categories: first, the market at which CO2 is a contaminant in the product and thus, its separation is a must. The example of such markets is natural gas, hydrogen production, and air purification industries. Although this market is not big but it is sustainable. Second category is the market at which CO2 is not a contaminant (for example is a by-product of combustion), thus, the associated industrial sectors are not willing to perform carbon capture; however, policy makers force them to do so by applying regulatory approaches such as carbon tax. In this project, we focused on the second category, which is potentially very vast. The example of such markets is power plants that are being forced to first control carbon emission, and later capture part of their emissions.  About eight years ago, countermeasures for global warming were declared in U.S.A. Consequently, carbon capture projects have been supported by major governmental departments such as the Department of Energy and the Environmental Protection Agency. Our customer discovery revealed that such supports have changed the status of the United States from a passive country to a leader in the area of carbon capture and storage; the role that European countries could not effectively perform due to their weaknesses in resources and international influence. However, we found that uncertainty and being policy-driven are still the biggest obstacles for taking the materials for CO2 capture to market in the current economy of U.S.A.       Last Modified: 12/08/2016       Submitted by: Reza Foudazi]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
