<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>EAGER: Investigations of pulsed focused ultrasound for increasing the average pore size in brain tissue</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>05/15/2016</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>04/30/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>154000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>154000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07020000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CBET</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Chem, Bioeng, Env, &amp; Transp Sys</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Susan Muller</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>CBET - 1557922&lt;br/&gt;PI: Frenkel, Victor&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The goal of this project is to determine whether exposure of brain tissue to pulsed focused ultrasound increases the spaces between cells, which could enhance the motion of therapeutic compounds and nanoparticle drug carriers through the brain.  The motion of therapeutic compounds such as proteins, small molecule drugs, antibodies, and drug carriers is usually restricted, owing to the limited space between cells and the extracellular matrix that fills this space.  Therefore, a method to increase the average pore size in brain tissue, without causing cell damage, could improve drug delivery methods to treat a variety of neurological disorders.  The investigators will design nanoparticles that are coated with polymers to promote their motion, and they will track the motion of the nanoparticles with and without exposure of the tissue to ultrasound.  Results of the study will improve knowledge of the extracellular space in the brain and provide guidance in the design of more effective drug delivery strategies.  The project will enlist high school students and undergraduates, including underrepresented students from West Baltimore City.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This EAGER award will support experiments to study pulsed ultrasound exposure as a means of effectively altering the microstructure of the extracellular space with the goal of improving the dispersion of nanometer-sized therapeutic agents in the brain.  Previous studies have shown that pulsed focused ultrasound increases penetration of nanoparticles, antibodies, and proteins in a variety of tissue types. This project will extend these studies to brain tissue.  The average pore size will be quantified using high-resolution multiple particle tracking methods.  The motion of polystyrene nanoparticles, densely coated to prevent their adhesion and ranging in diameter from 40 to 500 nanometers, will be examined in thin brain slices.  Effects of the ultrasound on tissue microstructure will be evaluated using transmission electron microscopy and tissue histology.  Results of the project will be useful for improving interstitial drug delivery to the brain by methods such as convection-enhanced delivery.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>05/19/2016</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/19/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1557922</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Victor</FirstName>
<LastName>Frenkel</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Victor Frenkel</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>vfrenkel@som.umaryland.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>4107067783</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000629270</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/19/2016</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Graeme</FirstName>
<LastName>Woodworth</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>F</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Graeme F Woodworth</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>gwoodworth@smail.umaryland.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>4103286148</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000701351</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/19/2016</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Anthony</FirstName>
<LastName>Kim</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>J</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Anthony J Kim</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>akim@smail.umaryland.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>4107063255</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000701352</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/19/2016</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Maryland at Baltimore</Name>
<CityName>Baltimore</CityName>
<ZipCode>212011508</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>4107063559</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>620 W Lexington St, 4th Floor</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[ORD]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Maryland</StateName>
<StateCode>MD</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MD07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>188435911</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF MARYLAND</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>003256088</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Maryland at Baltimore]]></Name>
<CityName>Baltimore</CityName>
<StateCode>MD</StateCode>
<ZipCode>212221509</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[655 West Baltimore Street]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Maryland</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MD02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1415</Code>
<Text>PMP-Particul&amp;MultiphaseProcess</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7916</Code>
<Text>EAGER</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0116</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2016~154000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><strong>&ldquo;Investigations of pulsed focused ultrasound for increasing the average pore size in brain tissue&rdquo; awarded to Victor Frenkel, Anthony J. Kim and Graeme F. Woodworth.</strong></p> <p>The goal of the proposed one-year project was to investigate the ability of pulsed focused ultrasound exposures to increase the effective pore size of brain parenchyma to enable improved dispersion of nanoscale agents within the brain. This was a multi-disciplinary project that combined the expertise of the three investigators in the fields of ultrasound biophysics, nanotechnology, and neurosurgery.</p> <p>For this project, we developed a procedure that involved harvesting fresh brain slices from rodents that were placed between two layers of a hydrogel. This was done in order to support the tissue and provide an acoustically compatible substrate for treating the brain tissue with the ultrasound exposures. Transmission electron microscopy was used to investigate the effects of ultrasound on the brain tissue cytoarchitecture; specifically, the changes in pore sizes within the brain extracellular and perivascular spaces (ECS, PVS). We developed an image processing procedure to quantify and compare the ultrasound-induced effects in both the ECS and PVS. Immediately following the ultrasound exposures, specially formulated, non-adhesive nanoparticle probes of various diameters were injected directly in to the tissue. These nanoparticles were imaged and tracked using custom methods (multiple particle tracking) with fluorescence microscopy. Ultrasound was found to significantly enlarge both the ECS and PVS. Significant increases were also found in the diffusion of 100, 200 &amp; 500 nm nanoparticles in the ultrasound treated tissue but not the 2000 nm nanoparticles. Histology and viability stains showed these effects could be produced without damaging the tissue.</p> <p>In addition to the methods developed specifically for this study, the major accomplishments from this grant include the demonstration that ultrasound exposures can nondestructively and noninvasively enlarge the ECS and PVS of freshly harvested <em>ex vivo </em>brain slices. These effects were then shown to be effective for improving the dispersion of relatively large nanoparticle probes, that normally would have restricted movement. The results from this study have provided the motivation to investigate if these effects can also be generated within the living brain; the data collected so far are encouraging. The ability to enhance the movement of large particulate drug carriers in the brain could have major implications for developing new treatment paradigms in the brain, which to date have been limited because of limited penetration and dispersion of therapeutic agents. The ultrasound effects themselves may also be beneficial for clearing the products of inflammatory and degenerative processes.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 05/03/2017<br>      Modified by: Victor&nbsp;Frenkel</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ "Investigations of pulsed focused ultrasound for increasing the average pore size in brain tissue" awarded to Victor Frenkel, Anthony J. Kim and Graeme F. Woodworth.  The goal of the proposed one-year project was to investigate the ability of pulsed focused ultrasound exposures to increase the effective pore size of brain parenchyma to enable improved dispersion of nanoscale agents within the brain. This was a multi-disciplinary project that combined the expertise of the three investigators in the fields of ultrasound biophysics, nanotechnology, and neurosurgery.  For this project, we developed a procedure that involved harvesting fresh brain slices from rodents that were placed between two layers of a hydrogel. This was done in order to support the tissue and provide an acoustically compatible substrate for treating the brain tissue with the ultrasound exposures. Transmission electron microscopy was used to investigate the effects of ultrasound on the brain tissue cytoarchitecture; specifically, the changes in pore sizes within the brain extracellular and perivascular spaces (ECS, PVS). We developed an image processing procedure to quantify and compare the ultrasound-induced effects in both the ECS and PVS. Immediately following the ultrasound exposures, specially formulated, non-adhesive nanoparticle probes of various diameters were injected directly in to the tissue. These nanoparticles were imaged and tracked using custom methods (multiple particle tracking) with fluorescence microscopy. Ultrasound was found to significantly enlarge both the ECS and PVS. Significant increases were also found in the diffusion of 100, 200 &amp; 500 nm nanoparticles in the ultrasound treated tissue but not the 2000 nm nanoparticles. Histology and viability stains showed these effects could be produced without damaging the tissue.  In addition to the methods developed specifically for this study, the major accomplishments from this grant include the demonstration that ultrasound exposures can nondestructively and noninvasively enlarge the ECS and PVS of freshly harvested ex vivo brain slices. These effects were then shown to be effective for improving the dispersion of relatively large nanoparticle probes, that normally would have restricted movement. The results from this study have provided the motivation to investigate if these effects can also be generated within the living brain; the data collected so far are encouraging. The ability to enhance the movement of large particulate drug carriers in the brain could have major implications for developing new treatment paradigms in the brain, which to date have been limited because of limited penetration and dispersion of therapeutic agents. The ultrasound effects themselves may also be beneficial for clearing the products of inflammatory and degenerative processes.          Last Modified: 05/03/2017       Submitted by: Victor Frenkel]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
