<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Mathematics Education Intensive Residency Project Focusing on Veterans</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>04/01/2016</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>03/31/2022</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>1165182.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>1165182</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>11040100</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>EHR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DUE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Undergraduate Education</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Michael Ferrara</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>mferrara@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922635</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>With funding from the National Science Foundation's Robert Noyce Teacher Scholarship program, the Mathematics Education Intensive Residency Project Focusing on Veterans will recruit veterans with strong mathematics backgrounds and prepare them to become grade 7-12 grade mathematics teachers. The project will fund twenty scholarships/fellowships over four years. In this project, Mercy College will collaborate with the Yonkers Public School District. The program will implement a clinically rich master's degree program in secondary mathematics education to investigate the nexus between theory and practice, and will benefit Noyce Scholars through the partnership between school practitioners and college faculty. The program will provide recipients with the content and methodology necessary to work effectively in inclusive and traditional mathematics classrooms. Particular emphasis will be given to helping candidates understand the spirit, intent, and content of the Common Core State Standards for Mathematics, and will investigate multiple strategies for implementing successful research-based mathematics education in high-need classrooms. At the conclusion of this 14-month master's degree program, candidates will be eligible for certification and employment. &lt;br/&gt; &lt;br/&gt;The project will correlate with current education reform practice to support a cohort model, clinical residency and follow-up induction services as a means for preparing and retaining successful teachers, and will follow the professional development model suggested by data from the Council for the Accreditation of Educator Preparation (CAEP) and the Center for Teaching Quality. It will guide each cohort through a sequence of activities designed to integrate theory and practice, including research-based courses in teaching, the use of technology in the classroom, differentiated teaching strategies, and implementing the Common Core State Standards for Mathematics.  The program will provide a coherent curriculum and sequenced courses requiring increasing levels of knowledge for application to the clinical residency and emphasize authentic classroom teaching under the mentorship of a well-qualified mathematics teacher and guidance from visiting Mercy College clinical faculty. A year of follow-up support for each cohort will be provided through online seminars, SKYPE and after-school learning workshops. Through multiple sources -- coursework, the internship, certification tests, and the awarding of the degree -- the project will verify candidates' level of competence to teach mathematics curricula in secondary schools, and will evaluate the progress of student achievement in their classes. Data collected from this project will provide an understanding of 1) whether veterans can serve as successful role models for at-risk youngsters by bringing the value-added strengths of maturity and teamwork skills to secondary school teaching and school capacity-building and 2) whether an ongoing learning community will empower a successful transition to civilian life, enable veterans to become effective teachers upon entering the profession, and work productively with diverse populations of secondary school students and educator colleagues.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>04/04/2016</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/06/2018</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.076</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1557307</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Nagaraj</FirstName>
<LastName>Rao</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Nagaraj Rao</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>nrao@mercy.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>9146747519</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000110935</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/04/2016</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>William</FirstName>
<LastName>Farber</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>William Farber</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>wfarber@mercy.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>9146934500</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000643628</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/04/2016</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Terri Lynne</FirstName>
<LastName>Germain-Williams</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Terri Lynne Germain-Williams</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>tgermainwilliams@mercy.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>9146934500</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000700586</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/04/2016</StartDate>
<EndDate>07/06/2018</EndDate>
<RoleCode>Former Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Mercy College</Name>
<CityName>Dobbs Ferry</CityName>
<CountyName/>
<ZipCode>105221134</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>9146934500</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>555 Broadway</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>17</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NY17</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>044827764</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>MERCY COLLEGE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>044827764</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Mercy College]]></Name>
<CityName>Dobbs Ferry</CityName>
<CountyName/>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<ZipCode>105221186</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[555 Broadway]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>17</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NY17</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1795</Code>
<Text>Robert Noyce Scholarship Pgm</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9178</Code>
<Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0416</Code>
<Name>NSF Education &amp; Human Resource</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040106</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2016~1165182</FUND_OBLG>
</Award>
</rootTag>
