<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>QuBBD: Large Scale Modeling of Big Multi-cohort Data for Cardiovascular Diseases and Type 2 Diabetes</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/15/2015</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>93653.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>93653</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DMS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Nandini Kannan</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>nakannan@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032928104</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Cardiovascular disease and Type 2 diabetes are leading causes of death in the United States.  It is well known that these diseases are the result of multiple genetic, environmental, and lifestyle risk factors. Understanding the complex interplay of these risk factors will lead to identification of key and causal risk factors that will provide the foundation for developing personalized prevention and treatment strategies.  To this end, decades of research efforts have focused on the collection of comprehensive data from large populations.  However, many challenges remain in how to model and uncover the complex disease mechanisms from such big datasets, and thus, gaps remain in how to best diagnose, treat, and prevent these diseases.  This award supports initiation of a collaborative research project that brings together cardiovascular/diabetes scientists and statisticians to address these challenges.  The project addresses the development of large-scale mathematical models of genetic, environmental, and lifestyle risk factors, using existing datasets from three reputable national studies, including the Framingham Heart Study, the Jackson Heart Study, and the Women's Health Initiative.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project will first develop large-scale network models for high dimensional risk factors.  Specifically, this project will develop large-scale and computationally feasible graphical models for heterogeneous data with mixed data types and complex dependence, and then employ graph theoretical approaches to identify the key drivers.  Based on the identified networks and key drivers, novel and interpretable predictive rules will be developed.  These modeling results will be validated systematically using multi-cohort data.  Finally, this project will deploy a web-based portal for disseminating the modeling results, which will serve as a core tool for research and learning.  This award is supported by the National Institutes of Health Big Data to Knowledge (BD2K) Initiative in partnership with the National Science Foundation Division of Mathematical Sciences.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>09/11/2015</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>09/11/2015</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1557467</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Xi</FirstName>
<LastName>Luo</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Xi Luo</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>Xi_Luo_1@brown.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>4018636321</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000685511</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/11/2015</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Brown University</Name>
<CityName>Providence</CityName>
<ZipCode>029129002</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>4018632777</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>BOX 1929</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[350 Eddy Street]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Rhode Island</StateName>
<StateCode>RI</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>RI01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>001785542</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>BROWN UNIVERSITY IN PROVIDENCE IN THE STATE OF RHODE ISLAND AND PROVIDENCE PLANTATIONS</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>001785542</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Brown University]]></Name>
<CityName>Providence</CityName>
<StateCode>RI</StateCode>
<ZipCode>029129093</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[Office of Sponsored Projects]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Rhode Island</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>RI01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>O402</Code>
<Text/>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>O470</Code>
<Text/>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0115</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2015~93653</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The goal of this project was to develop new statistical methods and models for predicting and understanding cardiovascular diseases and type 2 diabetes. This planning project also helped foster new collaborations between quantitative researchers and clinicians to investigate those challenging problems, leveraging the power of Big Data and quantitative methods. The goals of this project include integrating multiple massive existing datasets from multiple studies, developing quantitative methods to analyze these data with heterogeneous formats and experimental designs, and demonstrating the feasibility of making the results of these big data findings available to the public.</p> <p><br />This project was successful in achieving the goals of these planning activities. Our project team obtained and standardized three large datasets with various genetic, environmental and lifestyle risk factors. To address the challenge of heterogeneous measurements across different datasets, we further developed a new model for associating these risk factors across time with the disease events. This flexibility of this model also allows the integration of many big data predictive techniques for such heterogeneous data. Our work showed that indeed these big data techniques improved the prediction accuracy compared with popular existing cardiovascular disease and type 2 diabetes risk prediction algorithm. We also developed a prototype of a web-based risk calculator for illustrating the feasibility of disseminating these complicated risk algorithms to the public. Based on the results of these planning efforts, our project team is well positioned to pursue the next phase of research on these important scientific problems through method development for big data.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 12/28/2017<br>      Modified by: Xi&nbsp;Luo</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The goal of this project was to develop new statistical methods and models for predicting and understanding cardiovascular diseases and type 2 diabetes. This planning project also helped foster new collaborations between quantitative researchers and clinicians to investigate those challenging problems, leveraging the power of Big Data and quantitative methods. The goals of this project include integrating multiple massive existing datasets from multiple studies, developing quantitative methods to analyze these data with heterogeneous formats and experimental designs, and demonstrating the feasibility of making the results of these big data findings available to the public.   This project was successful in achieving the goals of these planning activities. Our project team obtained and standardized three large datasets with various genetic, environmental and lifestyle risk factors. To address the challenge of heterogeneous measurements across different datasets, we further developed a new model for associating these risk factors across time with the disease events. This flexibility of this model also allows the integration of many big data predictive techniques for such heterogeneous data. Our work showed that indeed these big data techniques improved the prediction accuracy compared with popular existing cardiovascular disease and type 2 diabetes risk prediction algorithm. We also developed a prototype of a web-based risk calculator for illustrating the feasibility of disseminating these complicated risk algorithms to the public. Based on the results of these planning efforts, our project team is well positioned to pursue the next phase of research on these important scientific problems through method development for big data.       Last Modified: 12/28/2017       Submitted by: Xi Luo]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
