<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Doctoral Dissertation Research: Analyzing Tropical Alpine Glacier Dynamics During Middle-Holocene Warming</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>03/01/2016</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>02/28/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>15644.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>15644</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>04040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>SBE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>BCS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Behavioral and Cognitive Sci</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Thomas Baerwald</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This doctoral dissertation research project will develop records of past glacier extents in one set of mountains in a tropical setting and will assess the sensitivity of glaciers in this and similar regions to changes in climatic conditions, such as alternate temperature and precipitation regimes.  The project will provide new information and insights to address the degree to which alpine tropical glaciers are especially sensitive to changing climatic and other environmental conditions.  The study region is one for which previous evidence seemed to indicate that alpine glaciers persisted during the middle of the Holocene Epoch, a period when evidence indicates that temperatures were as warm as or warmer than the present time period.  The project helps to assess the sensitivity of these glaciers to warming temperatures in order to better ascertain both the timing and magnitude of past glacier fluctuations.  By reconstructing past glacier extents in tropical regions like this, this project will improve basic understanding about the factors and dynamics that affect tropical glaciers as well as their sensitivity to a changing environment.  The project also will provide information that will yield more accurate predictions of future glacier mass loss, project findings will facilitate planning and development activities in tropical regions, where glaciers provide crucial freshwater resources and ongoing glacier recession will impact directly the livelihoods and wellbeing of communities.  The project will provide additional education and training benefits by engaging undergraduate students in some facets of the project and through presentations based on the project in elementary and secondary school classrooms in Vermont and New Hampshire.  As a Doctoral Dissertation Research Improvement award, this award also will provide support to enable a promising student to establish a strong independent research career.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The ongoing retreat of tropical glaciers has been highlighted as one manifestation of contemporary change in environmental conditions around the Earth, but the sensitivity of these glaciers to projected future climate conditions is uncertain.  Through this dissertation research project, the doctoral student will improve the understanding of tropical glacier response to warmer temperatures by determining the extents of glaciers in tropical eastern Africa over a period roughly 8,000 to 4,000 years ago, when the region was as warm as or warmer than at present.  The student will use detailed geomorphic mapping and surface exposure dating of glacial deposits in the Rwenzori Mountains to determine glacier extents during the current interglacial period known as the Holocene Epoch, which extends from about 11,600 years ago to the present.  She will employ a surface-exposure dating method that relies on measurements of the cosmogenic nuclide beryllium-10, which is produced in rock surfaces over time due to the influx of cosmic rays.  The project will be the first study to develop a beryllium-10-based chronology of Holocene glacier extents in tropical eastern Africa.  The student will compare the Rwenzori glacier chronology with records of temperature, precipitation, and glacier extents from other locations in tropical East Africa in order to assess the regional climate conditions and patterns of glacier fluctuations.  These results will be compared with Holocene glacier extents in tropical South America.  Determining whether glaciers across the global tropics fluctuated synchronously or asynchronously during the Holocene Epoch will provides information for evaluating the dynamics associated with changing global climatic conditions.  Project results will advance efforts to model glaciers within future warming scenarios, thereby providing a means to test hypotheses about the possible mechanisms that transmitted climate signals across the globe during the Holocene Epoch.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>02/25/2016</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>02/25/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.075</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1558358</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Meredith</FirstName>
<LastName>Kelly</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>A</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Meredith A Kelly</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>Meredith.A.Kelly@Dartmouth.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6036469647</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000286187</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>02/25/2016</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Margaret</FirstName>
<LastName>Jackson</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Margaret Jackson</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>Margaret.S.Jackson.GR@dartmouth.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6036463007</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000700787</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>02/25/2016</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Dartmouth College</Name>
<CityName>HANOVER</CityName>
<ZipCode>037551421</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6036463007</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>OFFICE OF SPONSORED PROJECTS</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[11 ROPE FERRY RD #6210]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New Hampshire</StateName>
<StateCode>NH</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NH02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>041027822</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>TRUSTEES OF DARTMOUTH COLLEGE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>041027822</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Dartmouth College]]></Name>
<CityName>Hanover</CityName>
<StateCode>NH</StateCode>
<ZipCode>037553716</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[19 Fayerweather]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New Hampshire</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NH02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1352</Code>
<Text>Geography and Spatial Sciences</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1304</Code>
<Text>EARTH SYSTEM HISTORY</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1352</Code>
<Text>GEOGRAPHY AND SPATIAL SCIENCES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9179</Code>
<Text>GRADUATE INVOLVEMENT</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9186</Code>
<Text>RESOURCE USE AND MANAGEMENT</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0116</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2016~15644</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The ongoing retreat of tropical glaciers is a totemic emblem of global warming. Yet there is evidence that glaciers in tropical Africa may have persisted during periods when temperatures were as warm as, or warmer than, today. The aim of this project is to improve the understanding of the response of tropical African glaciers to warmer temperatures by developing a record of glacier fluctuations during the Holocene, which spans the last ~11.6 ka and includes periods when tropical climate was perhaps as warm as modern. In particular, this project focuses upon the Rwenzori Mountains in Uganda, where little work on dating past glacier fluctuations has been completed. The major goals of this project are to (i) determine the timing and magnitude of Holocene glacier fluctuations in the Rwenzori Mountains, and (ii) assess the potential synchrony of glacier extent changes in tropical Africa during Holocene time.&nbsp;</p> <p>In order to evaluate past glacier response to warming, in the summer of 2016 the PIs (Jackson and Kelly) mapped and collected samples for surface-exposure dating using the cosmogenic nuclide <sup>10</sup>Be (hereinafter referred to as <sup>10</sup>Be dating) from presumed Holocene-age glacial deposits in the Rwenzori Mountains. During the field season, Jackson improved and refined glacial-geomorphic maps of the Rwenzori. These maps are ready for publication, and will be included in planned peer-reviewed publications. Jackson processed the collected samples for <sup>10</sup>Be dating at the Dartmouth College Cosmogenic Nuclide Laboratory. All processed samples were measured at the Center for Accelerator Mass Spectrometry at Lawrence Livermore National Laboratory.</p> <p>The results of this project are being prepared for publication, and constitute a significant portion of Jackson's dissertation.&nbsp; Jackson processed 30 <sup>10</sup>Be samples from the 2016 field season of deglacial and Holocene age. These samples reveal that (i) during deglaciation (~20-10 ka) glacier fluctuations in the Rwenzori were similar to those reported at sites in the tropical Andes, suggesting that tropical glaciers responded to a common forcing, most likely temperature; (ii) ice in the Rwenzori retreated rapidly after ~11 ka, and likely remained inboard of its near-historical position (400-200 yr ago) throughout Holocene time; (iii) Rwenzori glaciers and glaciers elsewhere in tropical Africa behaved similarly during the Holocene. Ice in the African tropics was restricted throughout the Holocene. Although there exists evidence that glaciers fluctuated in certain regions between ~3-2 ka, ice apparently remained inboard of its ~400-200 yr ago position.</p> <p class="Default">The final <sup>10</sup>Be results of this project will be uploaded to the open ICE-D Alpine Glacier database [alpine.ice-d.org] for use by other researchers. In addition, the project also afforded Jackson the opportunity to mentor an undergraduate student on research related to the Rwenzori chronology. His project tested the applicability of this site for calibrating cosmogenic nuclide production rates, with positive results.&nbsp; This would be the first Holocene-age tropical cosmogenic nuclide production rate calibration, and (to our knowledge) the first cosmogenic nuclide production rate calibration site in Africa.&nbsp; Thus, it would be a major step forward in applying surface exposure dating to understand past glacier changes in Africa and across the wider tropics.</p> <p>Determining the response of African tropical glaciers to middle-Holocene temperatures ~2-3&ordm;C warmer than present provides valuable information as to the response of these glaciers to projected climate changes. Tropical glaciers provide drinking water for millions of people around the globe, and feed rivers that drive hydropower plants and irrigate crops. The accurate prediction of future glacier mass loss are essential for planning and development in regions where reduced glacier reservoirs will impact the wellbeing of communities. These data can also be used to evaluate models of future glacier change, crucial for planning and mitigation efforts in regions that depend upon the resources glaciers provide.</p> <p class="Default">While in Uganda, the team met with officials from the Ugandan Wildlife Authority (UWA) to discuss the aims and outcomes of the June-July 2016 expedition, as well as to share initial findings from the ongoing project. The Rwenzori glaciers are a major tourist attraction and serve as a point of pride in local communities. Jackson will provide information to UWA officials about Rwenzori Holocene glacier fluctuations.</p> <p class="Default">&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 05/22/2018<br>      Modified by: Margaret&nbsp;Jackson</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The ongoing retreat of tropical glaciers is a totemic emblem of global warming. Yet there is evidence that glaciers in tropical Africa may have persisted during periods when temperatures were as warm as, or warmer than, today. The aim of this project is to improve the understanding of the response of tropical African glaciers to warmer temperatures by developing a record of glacier fluctuations during the Holocene, which spans the last ~11.6 ka and includes periods when tropical climate was perhaps as warm as modern. In particular, this project focuses upon the Rwenzori Mountains in Uganda, where little work on dating past glacier fluctuations has been completed. The major goals of this project are to (i) determine the timing and magnitude of Holocene glacier fluctuations in the Rwenzori Mountains, and (ii) assess the potential synchrony of glacier extent changes in tropical Africa during Holocene time.   In order to evaluate past glacier response to warming, in the summer of 2016 the PIs (Jackson and Kelly) mapped and collected samples for surface-exposure dating using the cosmogenic nuclide 10Be (hereinafter referred to as 10Be dating) from presumed Holocene-age glacial deposits in the Rwenzori Mountains. During the field season, Jackson improved and refined glacial-geomorphic maps of the Rwenzori. These maps are ready for publication, and will be included in planned peer-reviewed publications. Jackson processed the collected samples for 10Be dating at the Dartmouth College Cosmogenic Nuclide Laboratory. All processed samples were measured at the Center for Accelerator Mass Spectrometry at Lawrence Livermore National Laboratory.  The results of this project are being prepared for publication, and constitute a significant portion of Jackson's dissertation.  Jackson processed 30 10Be samples from the 2016 field season of deglacial and Holocene age. These samples reveal that (i) during deglaciation (~20-10 ka) glacier fluctuations in the Rwenzori were similar to those reported at sites in the tropical Andes, suggesting that tropical glaciers responded to a common forcing, most likely temperature; (ii) ice in the Rwenzori retreated rapidly after ~11 ka, and likely remained inboard of its near-historical position (400-200 yr ago) throughout Holocene time; (iii) Rwenzori glaciers and glaciers elsewhere in tropical Africa behaved similarly during the Holocene. Ice in the African tropics was restricted throughout the Holocene. Although there exists evidence that glaciers fluctuated in certain regions between ~3-2 ka, ice apparently remained inboard of its ~400-200 yr ago position. The final 10Be results of this project will be uploaded to the open ICE-D Alpine Glacier database [alpine.ice-d.org] for use by other researchers. In addition, the project also afforded Jackson the opportunity to mentor an undergraduate student on research related to the Rwenzori chronology. His project tested the applicability of this site for calibrating cosmogenic nuclide production rates, with positive results.  This would be the first Holocene-age tropical cosmogenic nuclide production rate calibration, and (to our knowledge) the first cosmogenic nuclide production rate calibration site in Africa.  Thus, it would be a major step forward in applying surface exposure dating to understand past glacier changes in Africa and across the wider tropics.  Determining the response of African tropical glaciers to middle-Holocene temperatures ~2-3&ordm;C warmer than present provides valuable information as to the response of these glaciers to projected climate changes. Tropical glaciers provide drinking water for millions of people around the globe, and feed rivers that drive hydropower plants and irrigate crops. The accurate prediction of future glacier mass loss are essential for planning and development in regions where reduced glacier reservoirs will impact the wellbeing of communities. These data can also be used to evaluate models of future glacier change, crucial for planning and mitigation efforts in regions that depend upon the resources glaciers provide. While in Uganda, the team met with officials from the Ugandan Wildlife Authority (UWA) to discuss the aims and outcomes of the June-July 2016 expedition, as well as to share initial findings from the ongoing project. The Rwenzori glaciers are a major tourist attraction and serve as a point of pride in local communities. Jackson will provide information to UWA officials about Rwenzori Holocene glacier fluctuations.                  Last Modified: 05/22/2018       Submitted by: Margaret Jackson]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
