<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Collaborative Research: Constraints on Interseismic Deformation Offshore Oregon from Calibrated Continuous Pressure Records</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>05/15/2016</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>04/30/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>360868.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>390868</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>06040200</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>GEO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>OCE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Ocean Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Deborah K. Smith</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>dksmith@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927978</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The Cascadia Subduction zone lies off the coast of the Pacific Northwest and is of both scientific and public interest because it is the site of catastrophic earthquakes similar to those that have occurred over the last decade in Japan, Chile, and Sumatra. On land, networks of instruments are available to measure the build-up of strain across the Cascadia subduction zone fault. Similar observations are required offshore to understand the dynamics of the subduction zone better, and to place stronger constraints on the earthquakes and tsunamis the fault produces every few hundred years.  This project uses calibrated seafloor pressure sensors to make accurate measurements of the elevation of the seafloor at six sites off the coast of central Oregon.  The project will initiate a decadal study that will measure changes in seafloor elevation that result from the build-up, and potentially the release, of strain across the subduction zone fault.  The study will constrain the width of the locked portion of the fault that will break in the next large subduction zone earthquake. The project will involve two graduate students, and include at least four undergraduates on each research expedition.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;High-quality offshore vertical geodetic measurements will be used to provide a baseline suitable for resolving secular strain caused by locking across the Cascadia subduction zone, and for detecting slow slip events. Several previous studies have shown that seafloor pressure measurements can detect slow-slip events, but the drift of seafloor pressure sensors has limited their application to measuring secular strain. The University of Washington (UW) and Scripps Institution of Oceanography (SIO) have collaborated to build and successfully test a campaign version of the SIO seafloor calibrated pressure recorder, the Absolute Seafloor Calibrated Pressure Recorder (ASCPR).  This instrument measures absolute pressures to an accuracy equivalent to ~1 cm of water depth.  Repeat measurements with the ASCPR on stable seafloor benchmarks equipped with a continuously recording bottom pressure gauge will be used to remove the drift from pressure time series and enable measurements of secular strain. The UW and SIO have deployed a trench-perpendicular profile of 6 benchmarks and bottom pressure recorders off central Oregon. This project supports repeat campaign-style absolute pressure measurements over two years on each benchmark to fully characterize the repeatability of ASCPR measurements and initiate a decadal study required to measure secular strain. By utilizing stable, undisturbed benchmarks to make accurate absolute pressure measurements, this effort could transform our capabilities for making long-term geodetic observations offshore. Complementary geodetic and physical oceanographic modeling studies are being used to further understand the expected geodetic signals and develop improved methods to separate geodetic and oceanographic components of pressure.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>05/11/2016</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/26/2017</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.050</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1558468</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Mark</FirstName>
<LastName>Zumberge</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>A</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Mark A Zumberge</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>mzumberge@ucsd.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6195340852</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000330482</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/11/2016</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Glenn</FirstName>
<LastName>Sasagawa</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>S</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Glenn S Sasagawa</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>gsasagawa@ucsd.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>8585344329</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000474994</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/11/2016</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of California-San Diego Scripps Inst of Oceanography</Name>
<CityName>LA JOLLA</CityName>
<ZipCode>920930210</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>8585341293</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>8602 La Jolla Shores Dr</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[Univ of California-San Diego]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>49</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CA49</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>175104595</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF CALIFORNIA SAN DIEGO</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>071549000</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of California-San Diego Scripps Inst of Oceanography]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>920930225</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>49</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CA49</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>034y</Code>
<Text/>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1620</Code>
<Text>Marine Geology and Geophysics</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0116</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0117</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2016~360868</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2017~30000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The largest earthquakes we know about occur at subduction zones &ndash; where an oceanic tectonic plate slides beneath a continental tectonic plate.&nbsp;&nbsp;The region is called a subduction zone because the oceanic plate is subducted beneath the continental plate.&nbsp;&nbsp;The low angle of the fault through the brittle crustal structure (it is the brittle zone where earthquakes develop) creates a large surface area between the two plates where great stress can be developed, unlike the case of vertical vaults (e.g., the San Andreas), where the area of the fault in the brittle crustal zone is smaller.&nbsp;&nbsp;Some sections of subduction zone faults are thought to be locked or "stuck," while other sections creep.&nbsp;&nbsp;The greatest stress is developed in the locked sections.&nbsp;&nbsp;If a section is locked, the continental plate may bow upwards because it is being pushed by the plate behind it with nowhere to go.&nbsp;&nbsp;This upward bowing may only amount to a cm per year, which is very hard to notice at the bottom of the ocean.&nbsp;&nbsp;We have developed a method that uses ocean water pressure, measured at marked locations on the seafloor, to detect this upward bowing, and in so doing help determine where the fault is locked.&nbsp;&nbsp;This research has just begun &ndash; we established measurements along a profile perpendicular to the boundary between the incoming ocean crust and the continental crust offshore Oregon.&nbsp;&nbsp;Many more profiles must be established, and it may take decades to determine how the Cascadia subduction zone is deforming in the Pacific Northwest.&nbsp;&nbsp;However we have taken the first step.&nbsp;&nbsp;We, and other scientists many years into the future, can go back to our seafloor markers where our measurements have been made and make repeated measurements.&nbsp;&nbsp;The differences between older pressure values and current ones show how much the seafloor has risen or fallen in the intervening time.&nbsp;&nbsp;The longer the period spanned by the series of measurements is, the more accurate the determination of the vertical deformation is.&nbsp;&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>The instrument we developed for these is called a Self Calibrated Pressure Recorder.&nbsp;&nbsp;It uses precise quartz pressure gauges to measure the pressure, and it calibrates the gauges while the data are collected to provide adequate accuracy in the results.&nbsp;&nbsp;First, we emplace seafloor benchmarks, which are several-hundred-pound concrete discs, on the bottom of the ocean.&nbsp;&nbsp;Next, a remotely operated vehicle (ROV) carries our instrument from the surface vessel down to the benchmarks and sets the instrument on the benchmark.&nbsp;&nbsp;It remains there for several hours while the pressure is measured and the gauge is calibrated.&nbsp;&nbsp;We have made several annual trips to a series of seven benchmarks and repeated the measurements at precisely the same locations.&nbsp;&nbsp;We have found that we can determine the rate of vertical motion to an accuracy of about 1 cm per year if we make annual measurements for four years.&nbsp;We plan to establish other profiles of benchmarks and make repeat measurements at the ones established in this program in the near future.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 08/09/2018<br>      Modified by: Mark&nbsp;A&nbsp;Zumberge</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The largest earthquakes we know about occur at subduction zones &ndash; where an oceanic tectonic plate slides beneath a continental tectonic plate.  The region is called a subduction zone because the oceanic plate is subducted beneath the continental plate.  The low angle of the fault through the brittle crustal structure (it is the brittle zone where earthquakes develop) creates a large surface area between the two plates where great stress can be developed, unlike the case of vertical vaults (e.g., the San Andreas), where the area of the fault in the brittle crustal zone is smaller.  Some sections of subduction zone faults are thought to be locked or "stuck," while other sections creep.  The greatest stress is developed in the locked sections.  If a section is locked, the continental plate may bow upwards because it is being pushed by the plate behind it with nowhere to go.  This upward bowing may only amount to a cm per year, which is very hard to notice at the bottom of the ocean.  We have developed a method that uses ocean water pressure, measured at marked locations on the seafloor, to detect this upward bowing, and in so doing help determine where the fault is locked.  This research has just begun &ndash; we established measurements along a profile perpendicular to the boundary between the incoming ocean crust and the continental crust offshore Oregon.  Many more profiles must be established, and it may take decades to determine how the Cascadia subduction zone is deforming in the Pacific Northwest.  However we have taken the first step.  We, and other scientists many years into the future, can go back to our seafloor markers where our measurements have been made and make repeated measurements.  The differences between older pressure values and current ones show how much the seafloor has risen or fallen in the intervening time.  The longer the period spanned by the series of measurements is, the more accurate the determination of the vertical deformation is.       The instrument we developed for these is called a Self Calibrated Pressure Recorder.  It uses precise quartz pressure gauges to measure the pressure, and it calibrates the gauges while the data are collected to provide adequate accuracy in the results.  First, we emplace seafloor benchmarks, which are several-hundred-pound concrete discs, on the bottom of the ocean.  Next, a remotely operated vehicle (ROV) carries our instrument from the surface vessel down to the benchmarks and sets the instrument on the benchmark.  It remains there for several hours while the pressure is measured and the gauge is calibrated.  We have made several annual trips to a series of seven benchmarks and repeated the measurements at precisely the same locations.  We have found that we can determine the rate of vertical motion to an accuracy of about 1 cm per year if we make annual measurements for four years. We plan to establish other profiles of benchmarks and make repeat measurements at the ones established in this program in the near future.          Last Modified: 08/09/2018       Submitted by: Mark A Zumberge]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
