<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Collaborative Research: Sea level induced hydrothermal activity as a trigger for glacial terminations</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2016</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>70125.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>70125</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>06040200</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>GEO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>OCE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Ocean Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Candace Major</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>cmajor@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927597</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The last million years of earth's history are characterized the growth and decay of continental ice sheets that covered large portions of North America and Europe.   Growth of the ice sheets transferred water from the ocean to the continents and caused sea level to drop by nearly 400 feet.   While it has long been known that the pacing of the ice ages is related to changes in the Earth's orbit around the sun, the triggering mechanism for the end ice ages, known as terminations, has yet to be fully explained.   Lowering of sea level releases pressure on the global mid-ocean ridge system, a nearly continuous chain of submerged volcanoes that span 30,000 miles of the sea floor.   The pressure release should drive enhanced submarine volcanism, which may in turn influence climate by introducing heat and carbon dioxide into the deep ocean.   The aim of the proposed work is to assess magmatism along mid-ocean ridges in the eastern South Pacific using geologic archives of volcanic activity.   Sediment cores retrieved from the East Pacific Rise (EPR) and Pacific Antarctic Ridge (PAR) will be used to assess hydrothermal plume activity near the ridge crest.  Hydrothermal plumes are created through superheating of cold deep ocean water by hot oceanic crust, which is itself heated by magma.  Thus, sedimentary archives can be used to assess glacial-interglacial changes in magmatism and test whether enhanced submarine volcanism occurs during glacial terminations. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The proposed work will focus on a series of cores from 10°S to 40°S along the EPR and PAR.  Preliminary oxygen isotope data indicates that sediments in this region accumulate at a rate sufficient to constrain glacial-interglacial timescales.   Hydrothermal activity will be inferred by estimating the flux of Fe, Mn, V, and As to ridge crest sediments.  All fluxes will be constrained using the 3He normalization technique.   A finding of coherent variations in metal flux at multiple sites would indicate there were regional changes in magmatic activity.  Additionally, the timing of anomalous metal fluxes will be compared with climate proxies to assess the feasibility that mid-ocean ridge magmatism acts as a negative feedback on ice sheet size.   Finally, a petrologic model will be used to simulate the impact of sea level variations on CO2-bearing melt production in the upper mantle.  Simulations of carbon flux from the global mid-ocean ridge system will be used to assess whether variations in carbon flux could have feasibly driven atmospheric CO2 on glacial-interglacial timescales.  &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The proposed work could transform our understanding of the climate system by constraining the interactions between the fluid and solid earth on glacial-interglacial timescales.   The broader educational impacts of the proposed work includes the participation of a postdoctoral scholar and two undergraduates at the University of Connecticut, plus an additional undergraduate at Caltech.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/27/2016</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/27/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.050</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1558372</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Paul</FirstName>
<LastName>Asimow</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>D</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Paul D Asimow</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>asimow@gps.caltech.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6263956111</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000444327</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/27/2016</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>California Institute of Technology</Name>
<CityName>PASADENA</CityName>
<ZipCode>911250600</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6263956219</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1200 E California Blvd</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[Mail Code 273-6]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>27</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CA27</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>009584210</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>CALIFORNIA INSTITUTE OF TECHNOLOGY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>009584210</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[California Institute of Technology]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>911250001</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>27</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CA27</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1620</Code>
<Text>Marine Geology and Geophysics</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1304</Code>
<Text>EARTH SYSTEM HISTORY</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1312</Code>
<Text>GREENHOUSE GAS DYNAMICS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0116</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2016~70125</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>This award was part of a collaborative effort to extend our studies of the influence of glacially-driven sealevel variations on magmatism at the seafloor volcanoes called mid-ocean ridges. It is known that the growth and decay of large continental ice sheets drives sealevel up and down by more than 100 m, sometimes at rates of centimeters per year. The resulting rates of pressure change on the seafloor are comparable to the rates at which parcels of the Earth's mantle ascend towards the surface due to plate tectonics and therefore it is possible that the Earth's climate cycles modulate the generation of magma in the interior. In turn, it is possible that this modulated magma production feeds back in some ways that shape the Earth's climate. The main award, to University of Connecticut, funded continuing studies of marine sediment cores collected near mid-ocean ridges, focusing on records of the variability of hydrothermal activity as a proxy for the magma flux to the ridge. The award to Caltech focused on developing the ability to model the variations in carbon dioxide flux from the ridge that would be associated with these climate-driven variations in magmatic activity. Rather than develop an ad hoc method of estimating the carbon flux variations, we took this opportunity to work on a major advance in the capability of the most advanced model of mantle melting (pMELTS) by incorporating carbon dioxide and related components into the model.</p> <p>A thermodynamic model is a distinctive approach to describing natural processes that strives to be internally consistent and to predict the outcomes of melting, crystallization, degassing, and other changes in magmatic systems using fundamental data on the properties of minerals and magmas. Each chemical component in such a model has to considered in a range of possible states. To add carbon dioxide, one needs to consider the fluid phase (pure CO2), carbonate minerals (calcite, dolomite, aragonite, magnesite), and the liquid phase (varying from silicate liquids with some dissolved carbonate all the way to mostly carbonate liquids with minor silicate components, known as carbonatites). Our efforts under this award focused on compiling all the basic data on the physical properties of these materials that we need, as well as calibration points where carbon-bearing liquids (silicate, carbonatite, or both) coexist with known phases like CO2 fluid or carbonate minerals. We also focused on extending our strategies for using these experimental data points to optimally estimate the parameters of our model in order to calibrate it. Althiough we have not yet reached the point of being able to model sea-level driven carbon flux variations, we have a preliminary version of the new underlying model, pMELTS+CO2, which will have many additional uses in petrology, geochemistry, and carbon cycle science. Our software incorporating the new model will be relased as open-source software for the benefit of all researchers in these areas.</p> <p>Another aspect of the overall study of sealevel and mid-ocean ridge activity arose serendipitously during this study and we pursued it with support from this award. A layer of volcanic glass shards was found in a marine sediment core that coincided in time with the end of a major ice age and that was deposited an extraordinary distance (8 km) from the nearest mid-ocean ridge volcano. We showed the the glass shards did come from the mid-ocean ridge and are therefore evidence of a period of unusually large explosive eruptions there. We proposed that this is linked to the sealevel cycle, with the magma chamber cooling and becoming more viscous during a lull in activity following a sealevel rise and then being explosively reactived a few thousand years later when magma flux rises following a fall in sealevel. We are now looking for other similar layers of glass shards to discover whether this is a general behavior of mid-ocean ridges subjected to pressure cycling.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 08/31/2018<br>      Modified by: Paul&nbsp;D&nbsp;Asimow</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Images (<span id="selectedPhoto0">1</span> of <span class="totalNumber"></span>)           </div> <div class="galControls" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1558372/1558372_10436460_1535673276031_PreviewScreenSnapz038--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1558372/1558372_10436460_1535673276031_PreviewScreenSnapz038--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Schematic of sea-level trigger of explosive mid-ocean ridge eruption"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1558372/1558372_10436460_1535673276031_PreviewScreenSnapz038--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Schematic of sea-level trigger of explosive mid-ocean ridge eruption"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">(a) Normal melt flux and magma chamber of normal composition. (b) 190?220 kyr: Rising sea level suppresses melting and decreases melt flux; magma chamber cools. (c) 180?190 kyr: Sea level drops, driving a pulse of melting that percolates up. (d) 120-140 kyr: High melt flux reactivates cool chamber.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Madeline Lewis</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Paul&nbsp;D&nbsp;Asimow</div> <div class="imageTitle">Schematic of sea-level trigger of explosive mid-ocean ridge eruption</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1558372/1558372_10436460_1535765162607_heghfcbhgjkkkfkc--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1558372/1558372_10436460_1535765162607_heghfcbhgjkkkfkc--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Compositions of liquids added to pMELTS+CO2 calibration"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1558372/1558372_10436460_1535765162607_heghfcbhgjkkkfkc--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Compositions of liquids added to pMELTS+CO2 calibration"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Our new model of phase relations involving carbon dioxide in the mantle includes both carbonated silicate liquids and true carbonates. This plot shows the compositions of liquids added to the calibration database for this project.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Paula Antoshechkina</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Public Domain</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Paul&nbsp;D&nbsp;Asimow</div> <div class="imageTitle">Compositions of liquids added to pMELTS+CO2 calibration</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ This award was part of a collaborative effort to extend our studies of the influence of glacially-driven sealevel variations on magmatism at the seafloor volcanoes called mid-ocean ridges. It is known that the growth and decay of large continental ice sheets drives sealevel up and down by more than 100 m, sometimes at rates of centimeters per year. The resulting rates of pressure change on the seafloor are comparable to the rates at which parcels of the Earth's mantle ascend towards the surface due to plate tectonics and therefore it is possible that the Earth's climate cycles modulate the generation of magma in the interior. In turn, it is possible that this modulated magma production feeds back in some ways that shape the Earth's climate. The main award, to University of Connecticut, funded continuing studies of marine sediment cores collected near mid-ocean ridges, focusing on records of the variability of hydrothermal activity as a proxy for the magma flux to the ridge. The award to Caltech focused on developing the ability to model the variations in carbon dioxide flux from the ridge that would be associated with these climate-driven variations in magmatic activity. Rather than develop an ad hoc method of estimating the carbon flux variations, we took this opportunity to work on a major advance in the capability of the most advanced model of mantle melting (pMELTS) by incorporating carbon dioxide and related components into the model.  A thermodynamic model is a distinctive approach to describing natural processes that strives to be internally consistent and to predict the outcomes of melting, crystallization, degassing, and other changes in magmatic systems using fundamental data on the properties of minerals and magmas. Each chemical component in such a model has to considered in a range of possible states. To add carbon dioxide, one needs to consider the fluid phase (pure CO2), carbonate minerals (calcite, dolomite, aragonite, magnesite), and the liquid phase (varying from silicate liquids with some dissolved carbonate all the way to mostly carbonate liquids with minor silicate components, known as carbonatites). Our efforts under this award focused on compiling all the basic data on the physical properties of these materials that we need, as well as calibration points where carbon-bearing liquids (silicate, carbonatite, or both) coexist with known phases like CO2 fluid or carbonate minerals. We also focused on extending our strategies for using these experimental data points to optimally estimate the parameters of our model in order to calibrate it. Althiough we have not yet reached the point of being able to model sea-level driven carbon flux variations, we have a preliminary version of the new underlying model, pMELTS+CO2, which will have many additional uses in petrology, geochemistry, and carbon cycle science. Our software incorporating the new model will be relased as open-source software for the benefit of all researchers in these areas.  Another aspect of the overall study of sealevel and mid-ocean ridge activity arose serendipitously during this study and we pursued it with support from this award. A layer of volcanic glass shards was found in a marine sediment core that coincided in time with the end of a major ice age and that was deposited an extraordinary distance (8 km) from the nearest mid-ocean ridge volcano. We showed the the glass shards did come from the mid-ocean ridge and are therefore evidence of a period of unusually large explosive eruptions there. We proposed that this is linked to the sealevel cycle, with the magma chamber cooling and becoming more viscous during a lull in activity following a sealevel rise and then being explosively reactived a few thousand years later when magma flux rises following a fall in sealevel. We are now looking for other similar layers of glass shards to discover whether this is a general behavior of mid-ocean ridges subjected to pressure cycling.       Last Modified: 08/31/2018       Submitted by: Paul D Asimow]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
