<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>REU Site: Bioinformatics Research and Interdisciplinary Training Experience in Analysis and Interpretation of Information-Rich Biological Data Sets (REU-BRITE)</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/15/2016</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>292295.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>292295</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>08080000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>BIO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DBI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Biological Infrastructure</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Sally O'Connor</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>soconnor@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924552</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This REU Site award to Boston University (BU), located in Boston, MA, will support the training of 8 students for 10 weeks during the summers of 2017-2019. The program will focus on computational and mathematical analysis of bioinformatics data. Research projects will include studying gene regulatory networks, the microbiome, and the linkage between genetic variation and phenotypes. Students will learn to analyze high-throughput sequencing data, gain experience in statistical and machine learning methods, and learn dynamic systems modeling. Full-time research with a Bioinformatics faculty mentor will be supplemented by workshops covering 1) bioinformatics programming, 2) parallel and cloud computing, 3) creating a scientific poster, 4) applying to graduate school, and 5) scientific ethics and responsible conduct of research. Additional activities will include tours of local science facilities, and participation in BU Bioinformatics symposia. A stipend, housing, meal, and travel allowances will be provided. Students will be selected based on relevant coursework in biology, mathematics, and computing, a good academic record, enthusiasm for bioinformatics research, and evidence of involvement in community activities and community service. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;It is anticipated that a total of 24 students will be trained in the program with an emphasis on recruiting women, members of groups underrepresented in the sciences, and students from schools with limited research opportunities. Students will learn how research is conducted and many will present posters at national, regional, or BU sponsored undergraduate research conferences. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;A common web-based assessment tool used by all REU programs funded by the Division of Biological Infrastructure (Directorate for Biological Sciences) will be used to determine the effectiveness of the training program. A Research Experience Wiki will be used for weekly recording of skills learned. Students will be tracked after the program to determine career paths using BU Bioinformatics LinkedIn and Facebook pages. Students will be asked to respond to an automatic email sent via the NSF reporting system. More information is available at http://www.bu.edu/bioinformatics/research/undergraduate-research, or by contacting the PI (Dr. Gary Benson at gbenson@bu.edu) or the program coordinator (Ms. Caroline Lyman at clyman@bu.edu).</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>05/26/2016</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/04/2017</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.074</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1559829</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Gary</FirstName>
<LastName>Benson</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Gary Benson</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>gbenson@bu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6173582965</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000233553</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/26/2016</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Trustees of Boston University</Name>
<CityName>BOSTON</CityName>
<ZipCode>022151300</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6173534365</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>881 COMMONWEALTH AVE</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
<StateCode>MA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MA07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>049435266</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>TRUSTEES OF BOSTON UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>049435266</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Trustees of Boston University]]></Name>
<CityName>Boston</CityName>
<StateCode>MA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>022151300</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[881 Commonwealth Ave]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MA07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1139</Code>
<Text>RSCH EXPER FOR UNDERGRAD SITES</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7275</Code>
<Text>Cross-BIO Activities</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9250</Code>
<Text>REU SITE-Res Exp for Ugrd Site</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0116</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0117</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2016~194295</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2017~98000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The Boston University (BU) Bioinformatics Research and Interdisciplinary Training Experience - Research Experience for Undergraduates Program (BRITE - REU) operated for three summers, 2017-2019.&nbsp; During that time, it hosted 28 undergraduate researchers.&nbsp; Of those, 60% were women, 36% were underrepresented minorities, 11% were community college students, and 25% were first generation college students.&nbsp; The students conducted interdisciplinary computational research for 10 weeks in the labs of faculty members of the BU Bioinformatics Graduate Program.&nbsp; The research spanned the mathematical and computational aspects of a variety of bioinformatics topic areas including the study of: human genetic variation detection; relationship of genetic variation to cognitive decline in the elderly; effects of microbial species on human health and the environment; relationship of gene expression to human disease, coral bleaching, and cellular metabolism; design of synthetic biological systems; and ecological forecasting.&nbsp; Learning activities included 1) seven workshops on computer programming languages and tools frequently used in bioinformatics, 2) instruction on creating a scientific poster, 3) scientific symposia and talks on bioinformatics problems and analyses, 4) training in research ethics, 5) workshops on applying to graduate school, and professional development, and 6) networking opportunities.&nbsp; A variety of social and cultural activities introduced the students to many unique aspects of Boston.&nbsp; Seventeen faculty members and 36 graduate students and postdocs mentored the undergraduates.&nbsp; Surveys during and after the summer activities were used to evaluate the effectiveness of the program and student satisfaction with the activities. Students reported great gains in their ability to contribute to science and felt overwhelmingly that they were engaged in real-world research.&nbsp; At the end of each summer all undergraduates submitted a poster abstract to the Annual Biomedical Research Conference for Minority Students (ABRCMS), a top national undergraduate research conference.&nbsp; All undergraduates had their abstracts accepted and 25 presented their posters at the conference.&nbsp; Four students were honored with travel awards from the ABRCMS organization to defray costs of conference attendance and three others received travel awards from the National Science Foundation, BIO REU travel awards program.&nbsp; As of fall 2019, eleven of the program alumni had received undergraduate degrees and 10 of those had started graduate school in a scientific field (primarily bioinformatics or related), 7 seeking a PhD degree and 3 seeking a Masters degree.&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 11/18/2019<br>      Modified by: Gary&nbsp;Benson</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The Boston University (BU) Bioinformatics Research and Interdisciplinary Training Experience - Research Experience for Undergraduates Program (BRITE - REU) operated for three summers, 2017-2019.  During that time, it hosted 28 undergraduate researchers.  Of those, 60% were women, 36% were underrepresented minorities, 11% were community college students, and 25% were first generation college students.  The students conducted interdisciplinary computational research for 10 weeks in the labs of faculty members of the BU Bioinformatics Graduate Program.  The research spanned the mathematical and computational aspects of a variety of bioinformatics topic areas including the study of: human genetic variation detection; relationship of genetic variation to cognitive decline in the elderly; effects of microbial species on human health and the environment; relationship of gene expression to human disease, coral bleaching, and cellular metabolism; design of synthetic biological systems; and ecological forecasting.  Learning activities included 1) seven workshops on computer programming languages and tools frequently used in bioinformatics, 2) instruction on creating a scientific poster, 3) scientific symposia and talks on bioinformatics problems and analyses, 4) training in research ethics, 5) workshops on applying to graduate school, and professional development, and 6) networking opportunities.  A variety of social and cultural activities introduced the students to many unique aspects of Boston.  Seventeen faculty members and 36 graduate students and postdocs mentored the undergraduates.  Surveys during and after the summer activities were used to evaluate the effectiveness of the program and student satisfaction with the activities. Students reported great gains in their ability to contribute to science and felt overwhelmingly that they were engaged in real-world research.  At the end of each summer all undergraduates submitted a poster abstract to the Annual Biomedical Research Conference for Minority Students (ABRCMS), a top national undergraduate research conference.  All undergraduates had their abstracts accepted and 25 presented their posters at the conference.  Four students were honored with travel awards from the ABRCMS organization to defray costs of conference attendance and three others received travel awards from the National Science Foundation, BIO REU travel awards program.  As of fall 2019, eleven of the program alumni had received undergraduate degrees and 10 of those had started graduate school in a scientific field (primarily bioinformatics or related), 7 seeking a PhD degree and 3 seeking a Masters degree.        Last Modified: 11/18/2019       Submitted by: Gary Benson]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
