<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Collaborative Research:  Evaluating Indigenous Strategies Of Multicultural Interaction</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>04/01/2016</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>03/31/2020</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>104755.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>104755</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>04040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>SBE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>BCS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Behavioral and Cognitive Sci</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>John Yellen</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>jyellen@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032928759</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Drs. Lee Panich, of Santa Clara University, and Tsim Schneider, of the University of California Santa Cruz, will direct a collaborative research project to understand how Native American societies persisted under Euro-American colonialism. While common understandings of colonial impacts on indigenous peoples in the Americas have focused on depopulation and loss of cultural traditions, archaeological research is uniquely positioned to offer insight into the active strategies Native Americans employed to navigate the changes of the colonial period. Archaeological data can be used to track developments that are not well represented in historical documents, such as long-term adjustments to indigenous social organization, mobility, and economic connections. By examining how Native Americans drew upon existing social and cultural patterns to negotiate increasingly complex interactions with Euro-American colonists, scholars can better understand the autonomy exercised by indigenous societies despite the challenges they faced in the colonial era. Because contemporary notions of Native American sovereignty largely hinge on the events of the colonial period, this research is directly relevant to broader debates about indigenous culture change and the popular and governmental recognition of Native American groups today. It is also relevant to understanding the nature of multi-ethnic interactions which occur in many regions of the contemporary world and how ethnic groups negotiate with and are incorporated into nation states.&lt;br/&gt;The project expands the focus of archaeological studies of colonialism beyond European settlements and first contact situations to investigate how native people living outside of direct colonial control selectively engaged with different colonial institutions over time. Drs. Panich and Schneider, along with their research team, will examine these issues on the Pacific Coast of central California, where local Coast Miwok groups lived at the crossroads of the Spanish, Russian, Mexican, and American frontiers. The research is designed to evaluate Native Americans' different strategies for maintaining autonomy at four politically and economically important village sites that were occupied from prehistoric times through the colonial period. Data will be drawn from targeted archaeological investigations, state-of-the-art laboratory analysis of archaeological materials collected during the mid-twentieth century, a GIS database of regional archaeological sites, and a systematic review of relevant ethnographic and historical literature. Working in conjunction with the Federated Indians of Graton Rancheria, the researchers will provide training in archaeological methods to tribal scholars as well as university students. The investigators will work closely with the tribe and local landowners to use the results of the project to develop culturally sensitive stewardship guidelines and public interpretive materials.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>02/12/2016</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>02/12/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.075</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1559666</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Lee</FirstName>
<LastName>Panich</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>M</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Lee M Panich</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>lpanich@scu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>4085513325</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000277508</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>02/12/2016</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Santa Clara University</Name>
<CityName>Santa Clara</CityName>
<ZipCode>950504345</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>4085544764</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>500 El Camino Real</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>17</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CA17</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>054800214</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>PRESIDENT AND BOARD OF TRUSTEES OF SANTA CLARA COLLEGE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>054800214</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Santa Clara University]]></Name>
<CityName>Santa Clara</CityName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>950504345</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[500 El Camino Real]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>17</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CA17</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1391</Code>
<Text>Archaeology</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1391</Code>
<Text>ARCHAEOLOGY</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0116</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2016~104755</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><span>Our NSF-funded research explored the autonomy of indigenous communities of Central California who selectively engaged with diverse colonial programs&mdash;including missions, mercantile colonies, and other Euroamerican projects&mdash;on their own terms. In doing so, our research methods and reporting sidestep the common approach in archaeology to solely focus on newly-established colonial settlements or archival documents to tell the story of indigenous responses to colonial intrusion. Our primary focus was the Marin Peninsula (Marin County, California), a homeland of where indigenous Coast Miwok people found refuge, safety, and spaces to face and survive colonialism. To understand how the choices of Native people structured their experiences of colonialism in this region, we marshaled archaeological evidence and historical documents to examine how protracted histories and relationships to place supported the persistence of indigenous communities and cultural identities between the 1770s to 1870s. This collaborative research carried out with the permission and support of the Federated Indians of Graton Rancheria also advances a narrative of presence that brings colonial history in line with the interests and goals of the living and sovereign community of Coast Miwok and Southern Pomo people.</span></p> <p><span>&nbsp;</span>To identify and understand the changes and continuities taking place within colonized Coast Miwok communities, we conducted archaeological investigations at three sites on Toms Point, Tomales Bay, in western Marin County. We also reanalyzed existing archaeological collections at regional museums and we consulted mission sacramental registers, historical maps, and other nineteenth-century accounts. A total of thirty radiocarbon dates from the three study sites demonstrate lengthy histories of occupation extending minimally to 5,000 years before present. Coast Miwok people would also continue to live at Toms Point during and after the mission period. From the late-1700s to the mid-1800s, Coast Miwok villages around Tomales Bay became part of a borderland between the empires of Spain (at San Francisco Bay) and Russia (at Colony Ross). At this time, mission records carrying important demographic information such as the names of baptized individuals and their home villages suggest that Coast Miwok peoples living in this region were able to engage and avoid colonial projects entering in their homeland. They also continued to hunt, fish, gather, and make and exchange tools, beads, and raw material. By the late-1840s, a trading post established on Toms Point incorporated Coast Miwok laborers who knew the land and its resources and also possessed skills in blacksmithing, hide working, and other trades. Two of the three archaeological sites show evidence of this undertheorized post-mission time period when some Coast Miwok people participated as laborers in newly emerging Californian economies to be able to remain living on lands that were quickly being taken from them. Mixtures of materials frequently collected or traded for in the region (e.g., obsidian, chert, marine shell) and introduced glass, metal, and ceramic artifacts suggest Coast Miwok people who actively maintained and modified their social traditions and economies.</p> <p><span>To contextualize our studies at Toms Point, we also investigated several contemporaneous sites along Tomales Bay. This work included brief field inspections, archival research, and the analysis of previous archaeological collections at multiple regional repositories. To further broaden our understanding of the choices of Coast Miwok people in the colonial period, we conducted laboratory analyses on materials from Spanish period sites that were partially inhabited by Coast Miwok people (Mission San Jos&eacute; and the Rancho San Pedro y San Pablo, an outstation of Mission San Francisco de As&iacute;s). Lastly, we conducted targeted laboratory analysis on materials from other contemporary sites from the broader central California region where key materials related to our studies had been previously recovered (Missions San Carlos Borremeo, Santa Clara, and San Juan Bautista).</span></p> <p>The broader impacts of this research are threefold. First, we successfully applied low-impact field and laboratory methods and researched existing museum collections to generate an enhanced understanding of the dynamic &ldquo;hinterland&rdquo; landscapes where indigenous peoples regularly found safety and formed contexts for maintaining their communities and identities&mdash;networks of interaction that linked to, but ultimately extended far beyond the well-known colonial outposts such as missions and forts. Second, our research on the mid-nineteenth century occupation of Toms Point and Tomales Bay provides an expanded picture of a time period more often viewed as an era of indigenous cultural loss and village abandonment. This overlooked phase of continuity and adjustment connects remote colonial history to a living Native American community (Graton Rancheria) who continue to care for the lands, waters, and cultural places comprising their homeland. Third, archaeological and archival finds documenting how Coast Miwok maintained a sense of history and place by resisting and sometimes adopting new ideas and materials ultimately underscores the theme of indigenous &ldquo;presence&rdquo;&mdash;a theme we intend to explore in forthcoming publications and a concept best reflected in the participation, feedback, and interest of Graton Rancheria citizens in this project.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 04/10/2020<br>      Modified by: Lee&nbsp;M&nbsp;Panich</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Our NSF-funded research explored the autonomy of indigenous communities of Central California who selectively engaged with diverse colonial programs&mdash;including missions, mercantile colonies, and other Euroamerican projects&mdash;on their own terms. In doing so, our research methods and reporting sidestep the common approach in archaeology to solely focus on newly-established colonial settlements or archival documents to tell the story of indigenous responses to colonial intrusion. Our primary focus was the Marin Peninsula (Marin County, California), a homeland of where indigenous Coast Miwok people found refuge, safety, and spaces to face and survive colonialism. To understand how the choices of Native people structured their experiences of colonialism in this region, we marshaled archaeological evidence and historical documents to examine how protracted histories and relationships to place supported the persistence of indigenous communities and cultural identities between the 1770s to 1870s. This collaborative research carried out with the permission and support of the Federated Indians of Graton Rancheria also advances a narrative of presence that brings colonial history in line with the interests and goals of the living and sovereign community of Coast Miwok and Southern Pomo people.   To identify and understand the changes and continuities taking place within colonized Coast Miwok communities, we conducted archaeological investigations at three sites on Toms Point, Tomales Bay, in western Marin County. We also reanalyzed existing archaeological collections at regional museums and we consulted mission sacramental registers, historical maps, and other nineteenth-century accounts. A total of thirty radiocarbon dates from the three study sites demonstrate lengthy histories of occupation extending minimally to 5,000 years before present. Coast Miwok people would also continue to live at Toms Point during and after the mission period. From the late-1700s to the mid-1800s, Coast Miwok villages around Tomales Bay became part of a borderland between the empires of Spain (at San Francisco Bay) and Russia (at Colony Ross). At this time, mission records carrying important demographic information such as the names of baptized individuals and their home villages suggest that Coast Miwok peoples living in this region were able to engage and avoid colonial projects entering in their homeland. They also continued to hunt, fish, gather, and make and exchange tools, beads, and raw material. By the late-1840s, a trading post established on Toms Point incorporated Coast Miwok laborers who knew the land and its resources and also possessed skills in blacksmithing, hide working, and other trades. Two of the three archaeological sites show evidence of this undertheorized post-mission time period when some Coast Miwok people participated as laborers in newly emerging Californian economies to be able to remain living on lands that were quickly being taken from them. Mixtures of materials frequently collected or traded for in the region (e.g., obsidian, chert, marine shell) and introduced glass, metal, and ceramic artifacts suggest Coast Miwok people who actively maintained and modified their social traditions and economies.  To contextualize our studies at Toms Point, we also investigated several contemporaneous sites along Tomales Bay. This work included brief field inspections, archival research, and the analysis of previous archaeological collections at multiple regional repositories. To further broaden our understanding of the choices of Coast Miwok people in the colonial period, we conducted laboratory analyses on materials from Spanish period sites that were partially inhabited by Coast Miwok people (Mission San Jos&eacute; and the Rancho San Pedro y San Pablo, an outstation of Mission San Francisco de As&iacute;s). Lastly, we conducted targeted laboratory analysis on materials from other contemporary sites from the broader central California region where key materials related to our studies had been previously recovered (Missions San Carlos Borremeo, Santa Clara, and San Juan Bautista).  The broader impacts of this research are threefold. First, we successfully applied low-impact field and laboratory methods and researched existing museum collections to generate an enhanced understanding of the dynamic "hinterland" landscapes where indigenous peoples regularly found safety and formed contexts for maintaining their communities and identities&mdash;networks of interaction that linked to, but ultimately extended far beyond the well-known colonial outposts such as missions and forts. Second, our research on the mid-nineteenth century occupation of Toms Point and Tomales Bay provides an expanded picture of a time period more often viewed as an era of indigenous cultural loss and village abandonment. This overlooked phase of continuity and adjustment connects remote colonial history to a living Native American community (Graton Rancheria) who continue to care for the lands, waters, and cultural places comprising their homeland. Third, archaeological and archival finds documenting how Coast Miwok maintained a sense of history and place by resisting and sometimes adopting new ideas and materials ultimately underscores the theme of indigenous "presence"&mdash;a theme we intend to explore in forthcoming publications and a concept best reflected in the participation, feedback, and interest of Graton Rancheria citizens in this project.          Last Modified: 04/10/2020       Submitted by: Lee M Panich]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
