<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Compact Bayesian Models of Massive Social Graphs</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>05/01/2016</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>04/30/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>150000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>150000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>04050000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>SBE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>SES</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Divn Of Social and Economic Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Cheryl Eavey</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>ceavey@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927269</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This research project will develop and apply new statistical models that capture dynamic, local structure in large-scale social networks.  As digital technologies proliferate around the world, social science researchers increasingly have access to data that reflect granular and nuanced patterns of human interactions and social behavior.  This is a change from traditional research on social networks, which requires expensive and time-consuming survey modules.  Given the cost of collecting network data from surveys, most knowledge about the role of individuals' social networks in behavior comes from data about relatively small networks observed at a single time period.  In contrast, the investigators will apply their methods to data that are unsolicited and arise as electronic logs generated through social media and communication services.  In such instances, interactions occur in real time and involve millions of unique individuals.  Examining such data provides insights into the patterns of day-to-day interactions that shape individuals' social context.  The techniques to be developed will model rich network structure with intuitive and simplified representations that will make them easier to integrate into social science research.  Open-source software will be made available through CRAN and the Python Package Repository.  Aggregated data and related materials required to replicate results of published articles will be available thru ICPSR or GitHub.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project will develop a Bayesian framework that parsimoniously represent the sub-structures of very large graphs with a novel approach to sparse coding.  The project also will provide an intuitive set of methods that are designed to enable social scientists to better understand the latent structure in new forms of massive social network data.  Despite the promise of unsolicited data sources, the size and granularity of the data present substantial challenges.  From a statistical perspective, the massive size and heterogeneity of the data confound existing computational tools.  From a social science perspective, the data represent the manifestations of deeper social relationships.  This project bridges the gap between the mathematical/statistical descriptions of these large social network graphs and the underlying social structure.  The Bayesian representation of local network structure will build upon related research on network motifs and random graph models, enabling meaningful inference about real-world network processes.  The sparse coding approach will allow for the compact and scalable representation of extremely large groups.  The project will contribute to related statistical literatures in Bayesian models for social networks, Bayesian model uncertainty, and network inference.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>04/26/2016</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>04/26/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.075</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1559778</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Joshua</FirstName>
<LastName>Blumenstock</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>E</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Joshua E Blumenstock</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>jblumenstock@berkeley.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5106424583</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000557046</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/26/2016</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Tyler</FirstName>
<LastName>McCormick</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Tyler McCormick</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>tylermc@u.washington.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2065434043</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000616078</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/26/2016</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Washington</Name>
<CityName>Seattle</CityName>
<ZipCode>981950001</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2065434043</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>4333 Brooklyn Ave NE</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Washington</StateName>
<StateCode>WA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>WA07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>605799469</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF WASHINGTON</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>042803536</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Washington]]></Name>
<CityName>Seattle</CityName>
<StateCode>WA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>981954320</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[Padelford Hall]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Washington</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>WA07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1269</Code>
<Text>STATISTICS</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1333</Code>
<Text>Methodology, Measuremt &amp; Stats</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8083</Code>
<Text>Big Data Science &amp;Engineering</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0116</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2016~150000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>For this project, we developed statistical methods to analyze massive network data.&nbsp; In particular, we focused on networks collected through interactions such as being in close proximity or calling on a cellphone.&nbsp; Understanding networks is important for several aspects of behavior.&nbsp; The people you know are essential for (among other things) finding jobs, learning about culture/norms, and transmitting disease.&nbsp; The work in this project will help scientists better understand how our social relationships impact these outcomes.&nbsp;</p> <p>Analyzing massive network data is challenging for (at least) two reasons.&nbsp;</p> <p>First, the relationships we observe with digital records don't always match the relationships of sociological or economic interest.&nbsp; You wouldn't necessarily loan money to everyone that you've talked to on the phone in the past few months, for example.&nbsp; Similarly, if you're looking for a job in a new city you might reach out to someone that you don't call frequently but is an important contact in this particular context.&nbsp; To address this challenge, we've developed statistical models that attempt to represent the structure in the network in a way that is more stable and can be linked to specific social or economic behaviors.&nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp;</p> <p>Second, the scale of these networks makes it exceedingly difficult to analyze them using sophisticated statistical methods.&nbsp; To address this, we've developed a series of computational strategies that allow researchers to analyze these graphs in a much more efficient way.&nbsp; Our methods do this while preserving the properties of the computational methods that are essential for results to be reliable and interpretable.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 09/30/2019<br>      Modified by: Tyler&nbsp;Mccormick</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ For this project, we developed statistical methods to analyze massive network data.  In particular, we focused on networks collected through interactions such as being in close proximity or calling on a cellphone.  Understanding networks is important for several aspects of behavior.  The people you know are essential for (among other things) finding jobs, learning about culture/norms, and transmitting disease.  The work in this project will help scientists better understand how our social relationships impact these outcomes.   Analyzing massive network data is challenging for (at least) two reasons.   First, the relationships we observe with digital records don't always match the relationships of sociological or economic interest.  You wouldn't necessarily loan money to everyone that you've talked to on the phone in the past few months, for example.  Similarly, if you're looking for a job in a new city you might reach out to someone that you don't call frequently but is an important contact in this particular context.  To address this challenge, we've developed statistical models that attempt to represent the structure in the network in a way that is more stable and can be linked to specific social or economic behaviors.       Second, the scale of these networks makes it exceedingly difficult to analyze them using sophisticated statistical methods.  To address this, we've developed a series of computational strategies that allow researchers to analyze these graphs in a much more efficient way.  Our methods do this while preserving the properties of the computational methods that are essential for results to be reliable and interpretable.       Last Modified: 09/30/2019       Submitted by: Tyler Mccormick]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
