<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>EAGER:   Establishing Techniques of Dendronitrogen Measurement</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>06/15/2016</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>09/30/2020</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>53988.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>53988</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03090000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CHE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Chemistry</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Anne-Marie Schmoltner</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>aschmolt@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924716</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>In this project funded by the Environmental Chemical Sciences Program in the Chemistry Division, Professor Paul R. Sheppard of the University of Arizona is establishing techniques to measure the levels of nitrogen present in tree rings (dendronitrogen). The quantity of dendronitrogen correlates with nitrogen availability to the ecosystem and therefore permits the long term profiling of nutrient availability. Professor Shepard is studying ways to overcome two challenges to understanding the mobility of nitrogen between tree rings. First, some nitrogen-containing species are mobile across plant tissues that include tree rings, so the ratio of mobile to immobile species needs to be determined. Second, nitrogen is difficult to measure accurately and precisely in whole wood samples. These difficulties have historically cast uncertainty on the accuracy of dendronitrogen data and correlating the temporal variation in dendronitrogen to the environmental availability of nitrogen. Professor Shepard is working to establish a wood pretreatment strategy that will permit measurements that reflect availability of nitrogen at the time of ring formation and to develop protocols for accurately measuring nitrogen content in wood samples. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;There is a measurable component of nitrogen in tree rings that is immobile in the form of proteins within cell walls.  That immobile component can reflect environmental nitrogen availability at the time of ring formation. Wood can be pretreated to effectively remove mobile nitrogen while preserving the immobile component. This is achieved in two steps. First, the tree cores are sliced into thin sections in the tangential orientation using a rotary microtome, a novel approach. Second, these slices are then treated with a mild combination of organic solvents in a sonication bath, to remove mobile nitrogen, while allowing the tracheid cells to remain intact and undamaged. This is key to preserving the structural, immobile nitrogen contained in the cell walls. Combustion elemental analysis and isotope-ratio mass spectrometry, specifically optimized for nitrogen, are used to quantitatively assess the amount of dendronitrogen as a function of time. This research directly impacts our understanding of forest and ecosystem health and dynamics, and improves our general awareness about impacts of human society on ecosystem health.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/07/2016</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/09/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1559818</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Paul</FirstName>
<LastName>Sheppard</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>R</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Paul R Sheppard</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>sheppard@ltrr.arizona.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5206216474</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000444980</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/07/2016</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Arizona</Name>
<CityName>Tucson</CityName>
<ZipCode>857194824</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5206266000</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>888 N Euclid Ave</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Arizona</StateName>
<StateCode>AZ</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>AZ03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>806345617</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF ARIZONA</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>072459266</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Arizona]]></Name>
<CityName>Tucson</CityName>
<StateCode>AZ</StateCode>
<ZipCode>857210001</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[888 N Euclid Ave]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Arizona</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>AZ03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>6882</Code>
<Text>Environmental Chemical Science</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7916</Code>
<Text>EAGER</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8650</Code>
<Text>Sustainable Chemistry</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0116</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2016~53988</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Anthropogenic fixation of nitrogen has been increasing globally for decades now, to the point of at least doubling the natural rate of nitrogen fixation, and effects of this new glut of available nitrogen on forest health have been the focus of abundant research.&nbsp; Chemical analysis of plant tissues, including tree rings extending back in time to before anthropogenic influence on nitrogen fixation, should be a part of research on effects of nitrogen deposition on plant growth.&nbsp; For this, it would be ideal to measure and interpret nitrogen in tree rings themselves to complete the link of N deposition-availability-uptake-assimilation from before anthropogenic increases in global nitrogen to the present.&nbsp; This scientific subdiscipline can be dubbed dendronitrogen.</p> <p>However, difficulties exist in interpreting nitrogen in tree rings.&nbsp; In particular, nitrogen is mobile across plant tissues, including wood and therefore tree rings, making N content in tree rings problematic as an indicator of past N availability.&nbsp; Chemical pretreatment of wood has been attempted to solve the problem of N mobility, including a new wood pretreatment method developed in this project.</p> <p>The new wood pretreatment of this project begins with a novel physical reduction of tree-ring samples by thin-slicing increment cores tangentially.&nbsp; Slicing is done with a mechanized, programmable rotary microtome.&nbsp; Tree-ring cores were sliced tangentially into sections 10 um thick, thereby ensuring the opening of intact cells of the wood.</p> <p>The new pretreatment process continues with a novel chemical extraction of the thin slices.&nbsp; Instead of soaking in harsh acids or bases at high temperature, organic solvents with differing relative polarities were tested and used at room temperature.&nbsp; In between solvents, di-water is forcefully drawn through the wood slices, thereby removing cytoplasmic material dislodged from cells of the wood during each step of this wood pretreatment method.</p> <p>This new pretreatment process typically results in a reduction in oven-dry wood mass of about 15-20%, indicating that material is indeed being removed from the tree-ring samples.&nbsp; Testing using UV-visible absorbance confirms that proteins and/or other nitrogenous compounds are part of what is removed from the tree-ring samples.&nbsp; These compounds might be the mobile nitrogen that confounds the study of dendronitrogen.&nbsp;</p> <p>Meanwhile, as shown in microphotographs of thin sections, tracheids, the dominant cell type of conifer wood, are not damaged by this new pretreatment strategy and therefore should retain the meshing proteins embedded in their cell walls, leaving sufficient nitrogen in pretreated slices to detect in measurement.&nbsp; Cell-wall nitrogen could potentially reflect nitrogen availability at the time of ring formation.&nbsp; That is, dendronitrogen should be doable after this wood pretreatment and it might yield accurate signals of environmental N availability through time.</p> <p>For measurement of nitrogen in wood, elemental analysis is used for determining N concentration and isotope-ratio mass spectroscopy is used for determining d15N ratio.&nbsp; This measurement is complicated by the fact that wood is predominantly carbon with comparatively little nitrogen.&nbsp; In this project, various instrument settings and add-ons were tried to ensure repeatable, accurate values.&nbsp; This measurement task remains difficult and is still open for research to refine it and improve the accuracy and repeatability of measurements.</p> <p>To test this new wood pretreatment method, nitrogen was measured in tree-ring samples from two sites.&nbsp; Loblolly pines growing in North Carolina that were subjected to a spike in 15N were tested.&nbsp; Results from a representative tree show that the d15N signal in the tree rings was improved as a result of the wood pretreatment of this project.&nbsp; Additionally, red firs growing in the northern Sierra Nevada, California, that were subjected to a forestry fertilization of regular nitrogen (14N) were tested.&nbsp; Results from this site do not show clear signals in N content, but with different settings/configurations of the measurement instruments, it might still be possible to do dendronitrogen with nitrogen content.</p> <p>The new wood pretreatment method developed in this project is improved anatomically and chemically. &nbsp;This method removes mobile nitrogen from wood while leaving tracheids in good shape and still containing the protein embedded in their cell walls.&nbsp; The new pretreatment process developed in this project is not difficult to perform.&nbsp; At a minimum, this pretreatment method should be done on tree-ring samples in addition to samples not pretreated to ensure that mobility of nitrogen across rings is not obscuring environmental signals of dendronitrogen.&nbsp; In that case, dendronitrogen can serve a role in ecological study of global nitrogen and effects of increased nitrogen deposition on forest ecosystems due to the doubling of fixation of nitrogen due to humans.</p> <p>Broader impacts of this project include the possibility of international collaborations in dendronitrogen.&nbsp; Global nitrogen truly is a global phenomenon, and anywhere with long-lived trees with dateable growth rings would be eligible for dendronitrogen studies.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 01/28/2021<br>      Modified by: Paul&nbsp;R&nbsp;Sheppard</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Images (<span id="selectedPhoto0">1</span> of <span class="totalNumber"></span>)           </div> <div class="galControls" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/1559818/1559818_10431605_1611869103634_PORFig1--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/1559818/1559818_10431605_1611869103634_PORFig1--rgov-800width.jpg" title="wood thin sections"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/1559818/1559818_10431605_1611869103634_PORFig1--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="wood thin sections"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Micro images of tangential sections of tree-ring wood, untreated (left) and pretreated using the strategy developed in this research (right).  In both cases, a ray structure is circled.  Untreated: Dark spots are cytoplasm.  Pretreated: Cytoplasm is mostly removed.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Alex Wiedenhoeft, Paul Sheppard</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Paul&nbsp;R&nbsp;Sheppard</div> <div class="imageTitle">wood thin sections</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/1559818/1559818_10431605_1611869674852_PORFig2--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/1559818/1559818_10431605_1611869674852_PORFig2--rgov-800width.jpg" title="d15N data"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/1559818/1559818_10431605_1611869674852_PORFig2--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="d15N data"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Time series of d15N for a tree spiked with 15N after 1998.  Pretreating the wood samples improved dendronitrogen signal.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Paul Sheppard</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Paul&nbsp;R&nbsp;Sheppard</div> <div class="imageTitle">d15N data</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/1559818/1559818_10431605_1611870039610_PORFig3--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/1559818/1559818_10431605_1611870039610_PORFig3--rgov-800width.jpg" title="N content data"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2021/1559818/1559818_10431605_1611870039610_PORFig3--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="N content data"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Time series of N content for a tree That was fertilized after 1980.  Pretreating the wood samples improved dendronitrogen signal slightly.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Paul Sheppard</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Paul&nbsp;R&nbsp;Sheppard</div> <div class="imageTitle">N content data</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Anthropogenic fixation of nitrogen has been increasing globally for decades now, to the point of at least doubling the natural rate of nitrogen fixation, and effects of this new glut of available nitrogen on forest health have been the focus of abundant research.  Chemical analysis of plant tissues, including tree rings extending back in time to before anthropogenic influence on nitrogen fixation, should be a part of research on effects of nitrogen deposition on plant growth.  For this, it would be ideal to measure and interpret nitrogen in tree rings themselves to complete the link of N deposition-availability-uptake-assimilation from before anthropogenic increases in global nitrogen to the present.  This scientific subdiscipline can be dubbed dendronitrogen.  However, difficulties exist in interpreting nitrogen in tree rings.  In particular, nitrogen is mobile across plant tissues, including wood and therefore tree rings, making N content in tree rings problematic as an indicator of past N availability.  Chemical pretreatment of wood has been attempted to solve the problem of N mobility, including a new wood pretreatment method developed in this project.  The new wood pretreatment of this project begins with a novel physical reduction of tree-ring samples by thin-slicing increment cores tangentially.  Slicing is done with a mechanized, programmable rotary microtome.  Tree-ring cores were sliced tangentially into sections 10 um thick, thereby ensuring the opening of intact cells of the wood.  The new pretreatment process continues with a novel chemical extraction of the thin slices.  Instead of soaking in harsh acids or bases at high temperature, organic solvents with differing relative polarities were tested and used at room temperature.  In between solvents, di-water is forcefully drawn through the wood slices, thereby removing cytoplasmic material dislodged from cells of the wood during each step of this wood pretreatment method.  This new pretreatment process typically results in a reduction in oven-dry wood mass of about 15-20%, indicating that material is indeed being removed from the tree-ring samples.  Testing using UV-visible absorbance confirms that proteins and/or other nitrogenous compounds are part of what is removed from the tree-ring samples.  These compounds might be the mobile nitrogen that confounds the study of dendronitrogen.   Meanwhile, as shown in microphotographs of thin sections, tracheids, the dominant cell type of conifer wood, are not damaged by this new pretreatment strategy and therefore should retain the meshing proteins embedded in their cell walls, leaving sufficient nitrogen in pretreated slices to detect in measurement.  Cell-wall nitrogen could potentially reflect nitrogen availability at the time of ring formation.  That is, dendronitrogen should be doable after this wood pretreatment and it might yield accurate signals of environmental N availability through time.  For measurement of nitrogen in wood, elemental analysis is used for determining N concentration and isotope-ratio mass spectroscopy is used for determining d15N ratio.  This measurement is complicated by the fact that wood is predominantly carbon with comparatively little nitrogen.  In this project, various instrument settings and add-ons were tried to ensure repeatable, accurate values.  This measurement task remains difficult and is still open for research to refine it and improve the accuracy and repeatability of measurements.  To test this new wood pretreatment method, nitrogen was measured in tree-ring samples from two sites.  Loblolly pines growing in North Carolina that were subjected to a spike in 15N were tested.  Results from a representative tree show that the d15N signal in the tree rings was improved as a result of the wood pretreatment of this project.  Additionally, red firs growing in the northern Sierra Nevada, California, that were subjected to a forestry fertilization of regular nitrogen (14N) were tested.  Results from this site do not show clear signals in N content, but with different settings/configurations of the measurement instruments, it might still be possible to do dendronitrogen with nitrogen content.  The new wood pretreatment method developed in this project is improved anatomically and chemically.  This method removes mobile nitrogen from wood while leaving tracheids in good shape and still containing the protein embedded in their cell walls.  The new pretreatment process developed in this project is not difficult to perform.  At a minimum, this pretreatment method should be done on tree-ring samples in addition to samples not pretreated to ensure that mobility of nitrogen across rings is not obscuring environmental signals of dendronitrogen.  In that case, dendronitrogen can serve a role in ecological study of global nitrogen and effects of increased nitrogen deposition on forest ecosystems due to the doubling of fixation of nitrogen due to humans.  Broader impacts of this project include the possibility of international collaborations in dendronitrogen.  Global nitrogen truly is a global phenomenon, and anywhere with long-lived trees with dateable growth rings would be eligible for dendronitrogen studies.       Last Modified: 01/28/2021       Submitted by: Paul R Sheppard]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
