<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Conference: 2016 Bioinspired Materials Gordon Research Conference and Gordon Research Seminar</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>04/15/2016</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>03/31/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>20000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>20000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03070000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DMR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Materials Research</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Aleksandr Simonian</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>asimonia@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922191</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Intellectual Merit:&lt;br/&gt;Biological systems have evolved means to create polymeric and mineralized materials that are exquisitely designed for high functionality in specific applications. In many cases, the materials of nature display structure-function relationships that exceed our current ability to reproduce in synthetic materials. Nevertheless, our understanding of these designs and the means by which they are produced is now sufficient to encourage efforts to harness or mimic these designs and the methods used in nature to achieve them. This conference will bring together young scientists and experts in the field of bioinspired materials to share recent advances and new methodologies. It is anticipated that international interactions, including student exchanges and research collaborations, will emerge from the conference that will advance both research and education in this area.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Broader Impacts:&lt;br/&gt;Enhancing young scientist (graduate student, postdoc, junior faculty) participation in the worldwide activities of bioinspired materials research, which leads to broadening of their professional experiences, stimulating interactions and collaborations with the international bioinspired materials community, and fostering the development of a new generation of young scientists, is a primary goal of this conference. This Gordon Research Conference (GRC) and Gordon Research Seminar (GRS) will have broad impacts through the promotion and cross-disciplinary fertilization of new ideas in the emerging field of Bioinspired Materials and will stimulate international exchanges and interactions between young scientists, underrepresented minority scientists, junior faculty, and prominent senior investigators. It will do so by bringing together a diverse group of researchers at one venue who have common interests that span the field of Bioinspired Materials. By doing so, the PIs hope to stimulate the growth of this area of research, and professional development of researchers in this field, by providing a single venue for the dissemination and exchange of results and ideas. The ultimate, long-term goal for the Bioinspired Materials GRC is to be the first choice for researchers in this field. If PIs succeed in building a cohesive community of scholars through this GRC, as other GRCs have done for many other interdisciplinary fields, PIs believe that this GRC will have had a broad impact on the field of Bioinspired Materials. The broader impacts of the GRC are enhanced in 2016 by incorporating an accompanying GRS on Bioinspired Materials. The GRS will provide a unique venue where young researchers can interact in a forum of their own design and develop professional networks, discuss scientific advances, as well as receive career advice from a panel of senior investigators. The organizers will endeavor to involve as many younger scientists and scientist from groups underrepresented in the STEM workforce as possible.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>04/08/2016</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>04/08/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1560787</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Timothy</FirstName>
<LastName>Deming</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>J</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Timothy J Deming</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>demingt@seas.ucla.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>3102674450</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000445370</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/08/2016</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Gordon Research Conferences</Name>
<CityName>West Kingston</CityName>
<ZipCode>028921502</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>4017834011</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>512 Liberty Lane</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Rhode Island</StateName>
<StateCode>RI</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>RI02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>075712877</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>GORDON RESEARCH CONFERENCES</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Gordon Research Conferences]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>RI</StateCode>
<ZipCode>028921502</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Rhode Island</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>RI02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1491</Code>
<Text>Cellular &amp; Biochem Engineering</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1773</Code>
<Text>POLYMERS</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7298</Code>
<Text>International Research Collab</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7623</Code>
<Text>BIOMATERIALS PROGRAM</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>5936</Code>
<Text>GERMANY (F.R.G.)</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>5937</Code>
<Text>SWEDEN</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>5950</Code>
<Text>SWITZERLAND</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7556</Code>
<Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7573</Code>
<Text>BIO-RELATED MATERIALS RESEARCH</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8007</Code>
<Text>BioMaPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0116</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2016~20000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><strong><span style="text-decoration: underline;">Operational Summary</span></strong></p> <p>The Gordon Research Conference (GRC) and Gordon Research Seminar (GRS) on Bioinspired Materials were held at the Les Diablerets Conference Center in Les Diablerets, Switzerland from June 4-101, 2016.&nbsp;&nbsp; The meeting covered a variety of scientific topics and the content presented was highly rated by participants.</p> <p class="Default">&nbsp;</p> <p class="Default"><strong><span style="text-decoration: underline;"> </span></strong><strong><span style="text-decoration: underline;">Conference Participants</span></strong></p> <p>The Conference was well-attended with 148 participants. Scientists from academia represented 99% of the participants while attendees from government accounted for 1%. The meeting also attracted a strong mix of young investigators and senior scientists.&nbsp; Students and post-docs accounted for 50% of all attendees. Approximately 39% of the participants at the 2016 meeting were women.</p> <p class="Default">&nbsp;</p> <p class="Default"><strong>Seminar Participants</strong></p> <p>The Seminar was well-attended with 46 participants. Scientists from academia represented 100% of the participants. Students and post docs combined accounted for 91% of all attendees. Approximately 39% of the participants at the 2016 seminar were women.</p> <p class="CM2"><strong><span style="text-decoration: underline;"></span></strong></p> <p class="CM2"><strong><span style="text-decoration: underline;">Conference Program</span></strong></p> <p>The emerging, interdisciplinary field of Bioinspired Materials focuses on developing a fundamental understanding of the synthesis, directed self-assembly and hierarchical organization of natural occurring materials, and uses this understanding to engineer new "bioinspired" artificial materials for diverse applications. The 2016 Gordon Conference on Bioinspired Materials aimed to capture the excitement of this burgeoning field by a cutting-edge scientific program that focused on fundamental research in Bioinspired Materials Science, chemistry and biology, and the myriad applications that stem from this fundamental research. To do so we assembled a roster of distinguished invited speakers and discussion leaders who addressed the key issues in the field. Topics covered a wide range of building blocks of bioinspired materials, the synthesis of bioinspired materials made from or inspired by these building blocks, their self-assembly, their system-level integration to create nano-mesoscale scale functional devices, characterization and simulation self-assembly, biological interactions of these materials, and the application of these materials in different domains. The conference was intended to promote cross-disciplinary fertilization of new ideas in the emerging field of Bioinspired Materials and stimulate interactions between young scientists, underrepresented minority scientists, and junior faculty with prominent senior investigators.</p> <p>The Gordon Research Seminar on Bioinspired Materials focused on the design principles and applications of innovative materials with biological inspiration. The mentorship component covered topics on performing translational research for the attendees defining and designing both individual projects and independent research programs.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p><strong><span style="text-decoration: underline;">Conference Feedback</span></strong></p> <p>Participants had an opportunity to provide feedback at the end of the Conference. The feedback collected from the meeting was extremely positive. Evaluations included numerous positive remarks regarding broad range of talks, informal discussions, diversity of speakers and the opportunity to network with the speakers.&nbsp; Evaluations from the GRS included positive comments regarding the panel discussion, tutorial lectures and the opportunity to network with peers.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p class="Default">GRC would like to thank the National Science Foundation for its continued support of the meetings.&nbsp; The contributions received from the National Science Foundation have been critical to the success of the conferences and are having a measurable impact in advancing the frontiers of science worldwide.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 10/13/2016<br>      Modified by: Timothy&nbsp;J&nbsp;Deming</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Operational Summary  The Gordon Research Conference (GRC) and Gordon Research Seminar (GRS) on Bioinspired Materials were held at the Les Diablerets Conference Center in Les Diablerets, Switzerland from June 4-101, 2016.   The meeting covered a variety of scientific topics and the content presented was highly rated by participants.    Conference Participants  The Conference was well-attended with 148 participants. Scientists from academia represented 99% of the participants while attendees from government accounted for 1%. The meeting also attracted a strong mix of young investigators and senior scientists.  Students and post-docs accounted for 50% of all attendees. Approximately 39% of the participants at the 2016 meeting were women.   Seminar Participants  The Seminar was well-attended with 46 participants. Scientists from academia represented 100% of the participants. Students and post docs combined accounted for 91% of all attendees. Approximately 39% of the participants at the 2016 seminar were women.  Conference Program  The emerging, interdisciplinary field of Bioinspired Materials focuses on developing a fundamental understanding of the synthesis, directed self-assembly and hierarchical organization of natural occurring materials, and uses this understanding to engineer new "bioinspired" artificial materials for diverse applications. The 2016 Gordon Conference on Bioinspired Materials aimed to capture the excitement of this burgeoning field by a cutting-edge scientific program that focused on fundamental research in Bioinspired Materials Science, chemistry and biology, and the myriad applications that stem from this fundamental research. To do so we assembled a roster of distinguished invited speakers and discussion leaders who addressed the key issues in the field. Topics covered a wide range of building blocks of bioinspired materials, the synthesis of bioinspired materials made from or inspired by these building blocks, their self-assembly, their system-level integration to create nano-mesoscale scale functional devices, characterization and simulation self-assembly, biological interactions of these materials, and the application of these materials in different domains. The conference was intended to promote cross-disciplinary fertilization of new ideas in the emerging field of Bioinspired Materials and stimulate interactions between young scientists, underrepresented minority scientists, and junior faculty with prominent senior investigators.  The Gordon Research Seminar on Bioinspired Materials focused on the design principles and applications of innovative materials with biological inspiration. The mentorship component covered topics on performing translational research for the attendees defining and designing both individual projects and independent research programs.     Conference Feedback  Participants had an opportunity to provide feedback at the end of the Conference. The feedback collected from the meeting was extremely positive. Evaluations included numerous positive remarks regarding broad range of talks, informal discussions, diversity of speakers and the opportunity to network with the speakers.  Evaluations from the GRS included positive comments regarding the panel discussion, tutorial lectures and the opportunity to network with peers.    GRC would like to thank the National Science Foundation for its continued support of the meetings.  The contributions received from the National Science Foundation have been critical to the success of the conferences and are having a measurable impact in advancing the frontiers of science worldwide.       Last Modified: 10/13/2016       Submitted by: Timothy J Deming]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
