<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>EcoCAR 3:  Advancing STEM Education, Innovation, Diversity and Outreach through Advanced Vehicle Technology Competitions</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>02/01/2016</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>09/30/2020</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>339750.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>577144</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07070000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>IIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Industrial Innovation &amp; Partnersh</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Jesus Soriano Molla</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>jsoriano@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927795</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The DOE Advanced Vehicle Technology Competition (AVTC) program provides opportunity to thousands of students annually to solve our nation's energy and transportation challenges. The latest AVTC series, EcoCAR 3, tasks 16 universities to re-engineer a Chevrolet Camaro to reduce its environmental impact while maintaining the performance expected from this iconic American car. During the four-year program, EcoCAR 3 teams will follow a real-world Vehicle Development Process that will serve as a roadmap for the engineering process of designing, building and refining their advanced technology vehicles. The unique real-world engineering experience provides student engineers with hands-on research and development with leading-edge automotive propulsion, fuels, materials and emission-control technologies. Sponsored by the U.S. Department of Energy, General Motors and more than two dozen other government and industry leaders, the competition not only produces top engineering talent, but also accelerates the development and demonstration of innovative, advanced vehicle technologies that help reduce&lt;br/&gt;our nation's dependence on foreign oil and enable us to be competitive globally. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This NSF grant will support four areas of the EcoCAR 3 competition: the NSF Outstanding Faculty Advisor Award, the NSF Diversity in Engineering Awards, the NSF Innovation Initiative grants and awards, and on-site competition expenses. The NSF Outstanding Faculty Advisor Award recognizes outstanding EcoCAR Faculty Advisors who have successfully integrated EcoCAR goals, objectives and activities into the engineering curriculum and fostered a successful automotive engineering design process into their university engineering programs.  The NSF Diversity in Engineering Awards recognize teams who develop successful recruiting initiatives directed toward women and underrepresented minorities, demonstrate a culture of inclusion, and/or establish a positive network that will, in turn, attract a diverse group of team members.  The NSF Innovation Initiative grants and awards will enable and recognize achievement in innovative research and development activities in emerging areas such as energy efficiency, vehicle performance, consumer acceptability or emissions.  Support for the competition expenses will help to enable the annual face-to-face EcoCAR 3 competition that provides the opportunity for the public demonstration and evaluation of the student-designed advanced technology vehicles at the conclusion of each of the three academic years of the EcoCAR 3 program.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>01/21/2016</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>01/08/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1560873</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Rocio</FirstName>
<LastName>Chavela Guerra</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>C</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Rocio C Chavela Guerra</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>r.chavela@asee.org</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2023313500</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000629876</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>01/08/2020</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Ashok</FirstName>
<LastName>Agrawal</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Ashok Agrawal</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>a.agrawal@asee.org</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2023313500</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000650746</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>01/21/2016</StartDate>
<EndDate>01/08/2020</EndDate>
<RoleCode>Former Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>American Society For Engineering Education</Name>
<CityName>WASHINGTON</CityName>
<ZipCode>200362476</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2023313500</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1818 N ST NW STE 600</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>District of Columbia</StateName>
<StateCode>DC</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>00</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>DC00</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>020293395</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>AMERICAN SOCIETY FOR ENGINEERING EDUCATION</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>020293395</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[American Society For Engineering Education]]></Name>
<CityName>Washignton</CityName>
<StateCode>DC</StateCode>
<ZipCode>200362476</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[1818 N Street]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>District of Columbia</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>00</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>DC00</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1504</Code>
<Text>GOALI-Grnt Opp Acad Lia wIndus</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>5761</Code>
<Text>IUCRC-Indust-Univ Coop Res Ctr</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7680</Code>
<Text>EDA-Eng Diversity Activities</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>115E</Code>
<Text>RESEARCH EXP FOR TEACHERS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>116E</Code>
<Text>RESEARCH EXP FOR UNDERGRADS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>5761</Code>
<Text>INDUSTRY/UNIV COOP RES CENTERS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7218</Code>
<Text>RET SUPP-Res Exp for Tchr Supp</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7651</Code>
<Text>OTHER COLLABORATIONS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7680</Code>
<Text>ENG DIVERSITY ACTIVITIES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8019</Code>
<Text>Accelerating Innovation Rsrch</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8808</Code>
<Text>Veterans Research Supplements</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9251</Code>
<Text>REU SUPP-Res Exp for Ugrd Supp</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0116</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0117</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2016~339750</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2017~237394</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Since 1988, the U.S. Department of Energy has sponsored Advanced Vehicle Technology Competitions (AVTCs) in partnership with the North American automotive industry. AVTCs represent a unique coalition of government, industry and academic partners who join forces to execute North America's premier collegiate automotive engineering competitions. The program's mission is to train the next generation of automotive engineers in advanced energy-efficient powertrains and other emerging, advanced vehicle technologies and innovations. The unique real-world engineering experience provides student engineers with hands-on research and development with leading-edge automotive propulsion, fuels and emission-control technologies to advance next-generation mobility solutions that meet our nation's complex energy and transportation needs.</p> <p>This grant intersected two AVTC series: EcoCAR 3, initiated in 2014, and the EcoCAR Mobility Challenge, initiated in 2018. EcoCAR 3 is a four-year collegiate advanced vehicle technology engineering competition. The EcoCAR Mobility Challenge is co-sponsored by the U.S. Department of Energy, General Motors, MathWorks and more two dozen other government and industry leaders such as the National Science Foundation. Managed by Argonne National Laboratory in partnership with the American Society for Engineering Education, the competition involves twlelve North American universities including: Colorado State University, Embry-Riddle Aeronautical University, Georgia Tech, McMaster University, Mississippi State University, Ohio State University, University of Alabama, University of Tennessee, Knoxville, University of Washington, University of Waterloo, Virginia Tech, West Virginia University.</p> <p>Participating university teams are challenged to redesign a Chevrolet Camaro to reduce its environmental impact, while maintaining the muscle and performance expected from this iconic car. EcoCAR 3 puts students in the driver's seat, providing a real-world training ground for students to gain hands-on experience following a multi-year vehicle development process to design, integrate and refine efficient mobility solutions. Students incorporate advanced powertrains and alternative fuels as well as their own innovative technologies to maximize their vehicle efficiency and performance results. Students apply their theoretical knowledge to solve not only complex engineering challenges, but to also learn valuable leadership and project management skills, as well as public relations, marketing, and business development.</p> <p>This NSF grant supported four areas of the EcoCAR 3 competition:</p> <ol> </ol><ol> <li><strong>NSF Outstanding Faculty Advisor Award.</strong> The NSF award recognizes the critical importance of the faculty advisor in the success of their EcoCAR program and encourages universities to adopt multidisciplinary systems-level automotive engineering topics into their engineering curriculum. The prestigious award from the NSF has helped faculty obtain promotion and tenure recognition for their commitment and dedication to engineering education through the EcoCAR program, which helps to encourage and retain high-talent faculty participation. The NSF Outstanding EcoCAR Faculty Advisor award is presented annually.</li> <li><strong>Diversity &amp; Inclusion/STEM Outreach</strong>. EcoCAR includes a strong emphasis on diversity and inclusion and STEM Outreach to underrepresented youth. Teams focus heavily on promoting EcoCAR to the community to help promote the benefits and prepare the marketplace to adopt advanced vehicle technologies. Teams are also engaged with recruiting and STEM outreach, including outreach to underrepresented minority groups for the purpose of recruiting and retaining youth and underrepresented minorities into STEM careers. The NSF Equity, Diversity and Inclusion in Engineering awards were presented at the end-of-the-year competition.</li> <li><strong>NSF Innovation Initiative.</strong> &nbsp;This initiative was established in 2015 to emphasize research and development in the areas of energy efficiency, vehicle performance, consumer acceptability, safety or emissions. The initiative was expanded in 2018 to include emphasis on connected and automated vehicle technology. The NSF Excellence in Connected and Automated Vehicles awards were presented at the end-of-the-year competition.</li> <li><strong>Onsite Competition Support.</strong> The competition among EcoCAR universities allows to evaluate their designs and their viability for the build and integration phase. It provides means to assess and measure how the teams met the technical goals and objectives and overall learning and progress within the program. Winners of the competition are determined each year in overall top six places as well as more than two dozen other awards.</li> </ol> <p>While primarily a mechanical engineering project, EcoCAR has become increasingly more interdisciplinary to address vehicle systems-level challenges. This includes collaboration with Electrical Engineering, Computer Science and Software Engineering, Chemical Engineering and others. The program has also expanded to include students from Business and Communications. The lead faculty advisor serves as the key component tying in all the faculty and students from these departments. NSF funding also ensured that the adoption of EcoCAR and systems level engineering/advanced vehicle technologies are incorporated into the engineering curriculum at the participating universities.</p> <p>EcoCAR 3 is largely a workforce development program inspiring future generations to pursue STEM careers. More than 20,000 students have participated during the program?s 30-year history, helping to seed the automotive industry with a skilled workforce knowledgeable in advanced vehicle technology and transportation and energy challenges facing society in the 21st century.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 02/06/2021<br>      Modified by: Rocio&nbsp;C&nbsp;Chavela Guerra</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Since 1988, the U.S. Department of Energy has sponsored Advanced Vehicle Technology Competitions (AVTCs) in partnership with the North American automotive industry. AVTCs represent a unique coalition of government, industry and academic partners who join forces to execute North America's premier collegiate automotive engineering competitions. The program's mission is to train the next generation of automotive engineers in advanced energy-efficient powertrains and other emerging, advanced vehicle technologies and innovations. The unique real-world engineering experience provides student engineers with hands-on research and development with leading-edge automotive propulsion, fuels and emission-control technologies to advance next-generation mobility solutions that meet our nation's complex energy and transportation needs.  This grant intersected two AVTC series: EcoCAR 3, initiated in 2014, and the EcoCAR Mobility Challenge, initiated in 2018. EcoCAR 3 is a four-year collegiate advanced vehicle technology engineering competition. The EcoCAR Mobility Challenge is co-sponsored by the U.S. Department of Energy, General Motors, MathWorks and more two dozen other government and industry leaders such as the National Science Foundation. Managed by Argonne National Laboratory in partnership with the American Society for Engineering Education, the competition involves twlelve North American universities including: Colorado State University, Embry-Riddle Aeronautical University, Georgia Tech, McMaster University, Mississippi State University, Ohio State University, University of Alabama, University of Tennessee, Knoxville, University of Washington, University of Waterloo, Virginia Tech, West Virginia University.  Participating university teams are challenged to redesign a Chevrolet Camaro to reduce its environmental impact, while maintaining the muscle and performance expected from this iconic car. EcoCAR 3 puts students in the driver's seat, providing a real-world training ground for students to gain hands-on experience following a multi-year vehicle development process to design, integrate and refine efficient mobility solutions. Students incorporate advanced powertrains and alternative fuels as well as their own innovative technologies to maximize their vehicle efficiency and performance results. Students apply their theoretical knowledge to solve not only complex engineering challenges, but to also learn valuable leadership and project management skills, as well as public relations, marketing, and business development.  This NSF grant supported four areas of the EcoCAR 3 competition:   NSF Outstanding Faculty Advisor Award. The NSF award recognizes the critical importance of the faculty advisor in the success of their EcoCAR program and encourages universities to adopt multidisciplinary systems-level automotive engineering topics into their engineering curriculum. The prestigious award from the NSF has helped faculty obtain promotion and tenure recognition for their commitment and dedication to engineering education through the EcoCAR program, which helps to encourage and retain high-talent faculty participation. The NSF Outstanding EcoCAR Faculty Advisor award is presented annually. Diversity &amp; Inclusion/STEM Outreach. EcoCAR includes a strong emphasis on diversity and inclusion and STEM Outreach to underrepresented youth. Teams focus heavily on promoting EcoCAR to the community to help promote the benefits and prepare the marketplace to adopt advanced vehicle technologies. Teams are also engaged with recruiting and STEM outreach, including outreach to underrepresented minority groups for the purpose of recruiting and retaining youth and underrepresented minorities into STEM careers. The NSF Equity, Diversity and Inclusion in Engineering awards were presented at the end-of-the-year competition. NSF Innovation Initiative.  This initiative was established in 2015 to emphasize research and development in the areas of energy efficiency, vehicle performance, consumer acceptability, safety or emissions. The initiative was expanded in 2018 to include emphasis on connected and automated vehicle technology. The NSF Excellence in Connected and Automated Vehicles awards were presented at the end-of-the-year competition. Onsite Competition Support. The competition among EcoCAR universities allows to evaluate their designs and their viability for the build and integration phase. It provides means to assess and measure how the teams met the technical goals and objectives and overall learning and progress within the program. Winners of the competition are determined each year in overall top six places as well as more than two dozen other awards.   While primarily a mechanical engineering project, EcoCAR has become increasingly more interdisciplinary to address vehicle systems-level challenges. This includes collaboration with Electrical Engineering, Computer Science and Software Engineering, Chemical Engineering and others. The program has also expanded to include students from Business and Communications. The lead faculty advisor serves as the key component tying in all the faculty and students from these departments. NSF funding also ensured that the adoption of EcoCAR and systems level engineering/advanced vehicle technologies are incorporated into the engineering curriculum at the participating universities.  EcoCAR 3 is largely a workforce development program inspiring future generations to pursue STEM careers. More than 20,000 students have participated during the program?s 30-year history, helping to seed the automotive industry with a skilled workforce knowledgeable in advanced vehicle technology and transportation and energy challenges facing society in the 21st century.          Last Modified: 02/06/2021       Submitted by: Rocio C Chavela Guerra]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
