<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Atom Probe Tomography (APT) Workshop for Earth Sciences</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>11/15/2015</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>10/31/2016</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>46997.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>46997</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>06030200</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>GEO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>EAR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Earth Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>David Lambert</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>dlambert@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924736</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This award will provide funding to organize a workshop centered on atom-probe tomography for geoscientists. Atom-probe tomography is the highest spatial resolution analytical technique in existence for the characterization of materials.  However, atom-probe tomography is practically unknown to the geosciences community despite offering clear benefits to researchers in Earth Sciences. The aim of the workshop is to establish an open forum for the discussion of the potential uses and benefits of this technique, while providing information to colleagues from a geological perspective.  Besides the invitation of senior researchers, an additional goal of this workshop is the participation of graduate students.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The strength of this technique relies in the possibility of combining a 3D material reconstruction with chemical composition, including isotopes, at atomic scale with a near part-per-million analytical sensitivity. Recent advances in field emission microscopy and the atom probe technique have allowed the preliminary analysis of geological materials.  First results from the APT application to minerals have provided significant geochemical information at a spatial resolution that is not achieved with any current methodology. Thus, atom-probe tomography is emerging as a powerful technique that can revolutionize research in geochemistry and re-shape our understanding of geological processes from the nanoscale to the continental scale.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>10/26/2015</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>10/26/2015</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.050</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1560779</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Alberto</FirstName>
<LastName>Perez-Huerta</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Alberto Perez-Huerta</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>aphuerta@ua.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2053488382</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000535894</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>10/26/2015</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Alabama Tuscaloosa</Name>
<CityName>Tuscaloosa</CityName>
<ZipCode>354870001</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2053485152</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>801 University Blvd.</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[152 Rose Admin. / Box 870104]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Alabama</StateName>
<StateCode>AL</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>AL07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>045632635</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF ALABAMA</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>808245794</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Alabama Tuscaloosa]]></Name>
<CityName>Tuscaloosa</CityName>
<StateCode>AL</StateCode>
<ZipCode>354870001</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[801 University Blvd.]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Alabama</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>AL07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1580</Code>
<Text>Instrumentation &amp; Facilities</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7556</Code>
<Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0116</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2016~46997</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The study of the chemical composition of minerals has been a major source of information within Earth Sciences for more than a century, as minerals actively record geological processes during and after their formation. For example, this information has been used to estimate the age of our planet and other extraterrestrial bodies, to determine the chemical composition of oceans and the atmosphere in the past and to better predict volcanic activity. Atom probe tomography (APT) is an emerging technique that allows the characterization of the chemistry of minerals at nanoscale. However, the knowledge of APT by the geosciences community is still very limited and reduced to a few users that are familiar with the technique. The aim of this project was to organize a workshop for the discussion of the potential use and benefits of APT, while providing information on this technique to colleagues from a geological perspective. In parallel, a secondary objective was to evaluate the need and future demand for APT in Geosciences. The scientific outreach of the workshop was centered on three main themes: 1) Impact on research within Earth Sciences; 2) Improvement of educational activities; and 3) Impact on research at institutional level.</p> <p><strong>Impact on Research within Earth Sciences: </strong>The workshop represented an open forum for the discussion of the potential uses and benefits of APT, resulting in new research collaborations with geoscientists in several national and international universities and research centers: Geological Survey of Denmark, IPMA (Portugal), Curtin University (Australia), Mississippi State University, University of Wisconsin-Madison, and Texas A&amp;M University. Also, a subsequent workshop on the technique, in collaboration with colleagues from Curtin University, was organized within the context of the international Goldschmidt Conference held in Yokohama (Japan) in June 2016. Finally, a recent collaboration has been established between the UA Geosciences Atom Probe Group (<a href="http://uageoapt.ua.edu/">http://uageoapt.ua.edu</a>) and the NanoEarth Center (<a href="http://www.nce2ni.ictas.vt.edu/">http://www.nce2ni.ictas.vt.edu/</a>) at Virginia Tech to provide further APT access to the Geosciences community.</p> <p><strong>Improvement of Educational Activities:</strong> A main goal of workshop organizers was to open this event to the participation of graduate students and postdoctoral researchers, including the inclusion of participants from underrepresented groups. From a total of thirty-six registered participants, eight were graduate students and four postdoctoral researchers. As part of the inclusive efforts, 30% of participants were female and an additional 25% corresponded to participants from underrepresented minority groups. In addition to the educational goals of the workshop, the new collaboration with the NanoEarth Center at Virginia Tech is envisioned to further strengthen the educational activities for graduate students nationwide, mainly by providing training programs in microscopy and nanoscale analytical chemistry.</p> <p><strong>Impact on Research at Institutional Level: </strong>The University of Alabama is currently in transition to become a major research university at national level. Hosting the 1<sup>st</sup> Atom Probe Workshop on Earth Sciences was considered by the UA administration as a highlight to promote a new research environment, with additional benefits for the educational and service activities of the university. As a consequence of the support of the National Science Foundation and other federal agencies, the university decided to invest substantial funding to acquire the latest atom probe instrument (LEAP 5000 XS), the first of its kind in a US university. It is envisioned that this instrument will be available to the Geosciences community and that it will lead to further investment in cutting-edge instrumentation by the institution.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 11/14/2016<br>      Modified by: Alberto&nbsp;Perez-Huerta</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Images (<span id="selectedPhoto0">1</span> of <span class="totalNumber"></span>)           </div> <div class="galControls" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2016/1560779/1560779_10403225_1479152365375_APTW1--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2016/1560779/1560779_10403225_1479152365375_APTW1--rgov-800width.jpg" title="UA APT Workshop"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2016/1560779/1560779_10403225_1479152365375_APTW1--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="UA APT Workshop"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Workshop Introduction</div> <div class="imageCredit">PI</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Public Domain</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Alberto&nbsp;Perez-Huerta</div> <div class="imageTitle">UA APT Workshop</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2016/1560779/1560779_10403225_1479152437029_APTW2--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2016/1560779/1560779_10403225_1479152437029_APTW2--rgov-800width.jpg" title="UA APT Workshop"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2016/1560779/1560779_10403225_1479152437029_APTW2--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="UA APT Workshop"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Prof. John Valley during his keynote talk</div> <div class="imageCredit">PI</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Public Domain</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Alberto&nbsp;Perez-Huerta</div> <div class="imageTitle">UA APT Workshop</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2016/1560779/1560779_10403225_1479152559719_APTW3--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2016/1560779/1560779_10403225_1479152559719_APTW3--rgov-800width.jpg" title="UA APT Workshop"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2016/1560779/1560779_10403225_1479152559719_APTW3--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="UA APT Workshop"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Dinner for workshop participants</div> <div class="imageCredit">PI</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Public Domain</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Alberto&nbsp;Perez-Huerta</div> <div class="imageTitle">UA APT Workshop</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The study of the chemical composition of minerals has been a major source of information within Earth Sciences for more than a century, as minerals actively record geological processes during and after their formation. For example, this information has been used to estimate the age of our planet and other extraterrestrial bodies, to determine the chemical composition of oceans and the atmosphere in the past and to better predict volcanic activity. Atom probe tomography (APT) is an emerging technique that allows the characterization of the chemistry of minerals at nanoscale. However, the knowledge of APT by the geosciences community is still very limited and reduced to a few users that are familiar with the technique. The aim of this project was to organize a workshop for the discussion of the potential use and benefits of APT, while providing information on this technique to colleagues from a geological perspective. In parallel, a secondary objective was to evaluate the need and future demand for APT in Geosciences. The scientific outreach of the workshop was centered on three main themes: 1) Impact on research within Earth Sciences; 2) Improvement of educational activities; and 3) Impact on research at institutional level.  Impact on Research within Earth Sciences: The workshop represented an open forum for the discussion of the potential uses and benefits of APT, resulting in new research collaborations with geoscientists in several national and international universities and research centers: Geological Survey of Denmark, IPMA (Portugal), Curtin University (Australia), Mississippi State University, University of Wisconsin-Madison, and Texas A&amp;M University. Also, a subsequent workshop on the technique, in collaboration with colleagues from Curtin University, was organized within the context of the international Goldschmidt Conference held in Yokohama (Japan) in June 2016. Finally, a recent collaboration has been established between the UA Geosciences Atom Probe Group (http://uageoapt.ua.edu) and the NanoEarth Center (http://www.nce2ni.ictas.vt.edu/) at Virginia Tech to provide further APT access to the Geosciences community.  Improvement of Educational Activities: A main goal of workshop organizers was to open this event to the participation of graduate students and postdoctoral researchers, including the inclusion of participants from underrepresented groups. From a total of thirty-six registered participants, eight were graduate students and four postdoctoral researchers. As part of the inclusive efforts, 30% of participants were female and an additional 25% corresponded to participants from underrepresented minority groups. In addition to the educational goals of the workshop, the new collaboration with the NanoEarth Center at Virginia Tech is envisioned to further strengthen the educational activities for graduate students nationwide, mainly by providing training programs in microscopy and nanoscale analytical chemistry.  Impact on Research at Institutional Level: The University of Alabama is currently in transition to become a major research university at national level. Hosting the 1st Atom Probe Workshop on Earth Sciences was considered by the UA administration as a highlight to promote a new research environment, with additional benefits for the educational and service activities of the university. As a consequence of the support of the National Science Foundation and other federal agencies, the university decided to invest substantial funding to acquire the latest atom probe instrument (LEAP 5000 XS), the first of its kind in a US university. It is envisioned that this instrument will be available to the Geosciences community and that it will lead to further investment in cutting-edge instrumentation by the institution.             Last Modified: 11/14/2016       Submitted by: Alberto Perez-Huerta]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
