<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>REU Site: Preparing the Next Generation of Scholars through Geographic Information Systems and Citizen Science</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>03/01/2016</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2020</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>374480.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>449480</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>04010000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>SBE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>SMA</Abbreviation>
<LongName>SBE Off Of Multidisciplinary Activities</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Josie S. Welkom</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>jwelkom@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927376</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This project is funded from the Research Experiences for Undergraduates (REU) Sites program in the SBE Directorate. As such, it has both scientific and societal benefits, and it integrates research and education. The Community Geography and Geographic Information Systems (GIS) REU Site hosted by the University of Central Florida will: 1) critically assess the opportunities for and challenges to community-based models for international undergraduate research experiences; 2) engage 24 students over three years in community-based international fieldwork focused on community geography, GIS, and citizen science to examine social and environmental disparities related to marine debris and flooding/disaster management in Belize; and 3) disseminate a new conceptual and methodological framework for international community geography and GIS research by connecting theory with praxis.  Students will work collaboratively with a diverse group of international partners, including researchers at University of Central Florida, Georgia State University, the Smithsonian National Museum of Natural History's Caribbean Coral Reef Ecosystems Program, and University of Belize.  &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The mission of this REU Site is to provide international experiences for students in community geography and GIS that connect research to real-world problem solving that is inclusive of knowledge production from local stakeholders.  Student mastery of geospatial STEM research skills will be accomplished largely through students creating an open and freely available geospatial data infrastructure to address social and environmental disparities related to marine debris and flooding/disaster management in Belize. This objective will include the creation of an online, interactive geospatial data and mapping portal through ArcGIS Online, a service providing template-based web mapping applications.  This REU Site will provide free and open access to various research datasets, metadata, and geospatial training modules.  The geospatial infrastructure created by students will also include: quantitative datasets, qualitative data, GPS field data, geographic analyses, and maps/reports of findings.  Students will also co-lead GIS training and community-based fieldwork with Belizean residents and collaborators. This REU Site and the growing subfield of community geography and GIS contribute to several national STEM trends, including: 1) the National Science Foundation's continued emphasis on the Science of Broadening Participating in STEM; 2) NSF's efforts to increase public understanding of science and impact on broader society;  and 3) rapid growth in geospatial technology careers (identified as a U.S. Dept. of Labor high-growth industry).  The subfield of community geography and GIS is particularly useful for training students in international, community-based research as it provides opportunities to learn and apply geospatial STEM research skills, including GPS data collection, GIS analysis, qualitative data analysis, and geospatial database design. This project is co-funded by the NSF Office of International Science and Engineering (OISE).</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>02/23/2016</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/10/2017</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.075</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1560015</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Christy</FirstName>
<LastName>Visaggi</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Christy Visaggi</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>cvisaggi@gsu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>4044135755</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000626189</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>02/23/2016</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Timothy</FirstName>
<LastName>Hawthorne</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Timothy Hawthorne</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>timothy.hawthorne@ucf.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>4078821120</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000699608</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>02/23/2016</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>The University of Central Florida Board of Trustees</Name>
<CityName>Orlando</CityName>
<ZipCode>328168005</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>4078230387</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>4000 CNTRL FLORIDA BLVD</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Florida</StateName>
<StateCode>FL</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>FL07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>150805653</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF CENTRAL FLORIDA BOARD OF TRUSTEES, THE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>159621697</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Belize]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode/>
<ZipCode/>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>BH</CountryCode>
<CountryName>Belize</CountryName>
<StateName>RI REQUIRED</StateName>
<CountryFlag>0</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT/>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>""</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1139</Code>
<Text>RSCH EXPER FOR UNDERGRAD SITES</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7298</Code>
<Text>International Research Collab</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>5926</Code>
<Text>LATIN AMERICA, SDC</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9178</Code>
<Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9250</Code>
<Text>REU SITE-Res Exp for Ugrd Site</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9251</Code>
<Text>REU SUPP-Res Exp for Ugrd Supp</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0116</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0117</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2016~374480</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2017~75000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>This NSF REU Site has both scientific and societal benefits, and it integrates research and education as part of its Intellectual Merit and Broader Impacts. The Community Geography and Geographic Information Systems (GIS) REU Site hosted by the University of Central Florida supported 34 U.S. undergraduate students in exploring approaches to engaging in community-based research. This site included an international fieldwork component where 32 students travelled abroad (many for the first time) to work on GIS and geography focused work for 1 month in the field; 2 students were virtual in 2022 due to COVID-19 restrictions. All students also participated in an extended research experience, beyond fieldwork, with several additional weeks of pre-fieldwork research methods training and post-fieldwork data analysis/reporting of results with REU staff. In being part of a collaborative, interdisciplinary research team, all students and staff were able to: 1) critically assess the opportunities for and challenges to community-based models for international undergraduate research experiences; 2) engage in community-based international fieldwork focused on community geography, GIS, drones, and citizen science to examine social and environmental disparities related to marine debris, coastal/island resiliency, and flooding/disaster management in an international setting; and 3) disseminate a new conceptual and methodological framework for international community geography and GIS research by connecting theory with praxis through conference presentations, community reports, journal publications, and social media. Students were mentored by and worked collaboratively with a diverse group of U.S. and international partners, including researchers at University of Central Florida, Georgia State University, the Smithsonian National Museum of Natural History's Caribbean Coral Reef Ecosystems Program, and University of Belize.<br /> <br /> Students engaged in international research experiences in community geography and GIS that connected research to real-world problem solving that was inclusive of knowledge production from local stakeholders. Students created an open and freely available geospatial data infrastructure using an online GIS and mapping platform and drones to address social and environmental disparities related to marine debris; drones and spatial storytelling for coastal/island resiliency; and flooding/disaster management. The online platform and project website provide free and open access to various research datasets, metadata, K-12 activities, and research training modules. The REU Site contributes to several national STEM trends, including: 1) the National Science Foundation's continued emphasis on the Science of Broadening Participating in STEM where over 70% of our program&rsquo;s participants identified as being from such groups; 2) NSF's efforts to increase public understanding of science and impact on broader society as our work included both formal and informal science communication products through publications, conference presentations, community meetings, non-technical community reports, and social media; and 3) rapid growth in geospatial technology careers (identified as a U.S. Dept. of Labor high-growth industry). In using GIS and related geospatial technologies in a community-based research setting, all students were exposed to these in-demand STEM skills to be more competitive for academic and non-academic careers related to GIS; several students visited and presented with GIS industry leaders as part of their post-REU experience. The Intellectual Merit and Broader Impacts of the work focused on student mentoring and research in an interdisciplinary team that was committed to engaging with diverse stakeholders to address major social and environmental challenges that could be mapped and visualized using GIS, drones, and related geospatial technologies.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 04/30/2021<br>      Modified by: Timothy&nbsp;Hawthorne</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ This NSF REU Site has both scientific and societal benefits, and it integrates research and education as part of its Intellectual Merit and Broader Impacts. The Community Geography and Geographic Information Systems (GIS) REU Site hosted by the University of Central Florida supported 34 U.S. undergraduate students in exploring approaches to engaging in community-based research. This site included an international fieldwork component where 32 students travelled abroad (many for the first time) to work on GIS and geography focused work for 1 month in the field; 2 students were virtual in 2022 due to COVID-19 restrictions. All students also participated in an extended research experience, beyond fieldwork, with several additional weeks of pre-fieldwork research methods training and post-fieldwork data analysis/reporting of results with REU staff. In being part of a collaborative, interdisciplinary research team, all students and staff were able to: 1) critically assess the opportunities for and challenges to community-based models for international undergraduate research experiences; 2) engage in community-based international fieldwork focused on community geography, GIS, drones, and citizen science to examine social and environmental disparities related to marine debris, coastal/island resiliency, and flooding/disaster management in an international setting; and 3) disseminate a new conceptual and methodological framework for international community geography and GIS research by connecting theory with praxis through conference presentations, community reports, journal publications, and social media. Students were mentored by and worked collaboratively with a diverse group of U.S. and international partners, including researchers at University of Central Florida, Georgia State University, the Smithsonian National Museum of Natural History's Caribbean Coral Reef Ecosystems Program, and University of Belize.    Students engaged in international research experiences in community geography and GIS that connected research to real-world problem solving that was inclusive of knowledge production from local stakeholders. Students created an open and freely available geospatial data infrastructure using an online GIS and mapping platform and drones to address social and environmental disparities related to marine debris; drones and spatial storytelling for coastal/island resiliency; and flooding/disaster management. The online platform and project website provide free and open access to various research datasets, metadata, K-12 activities, and research training modules. The REU Site contributes to several national STEM trends, including: 1) the National Science Foundation's continued emphasis on the Science of Broadening Participating in STEM where over 70% of our program’s participants identified as being from such groups; 2) NSF's efforts to increase public understanding of science and impact on broader society as our work included both formal and informal science communication products through publications, conference presentations, community meetings, non-technical community reports, and social media; and 3) rapid growth in geospatial technology careers (identified as a U.S. Dept. of Labor high-growth industry). In using GIS and related geospatial technologies in a community-based research setting, all students were exposed to these in-demand STEM skills to be more competitive for academic and non-academic careers related to GIS; several students visited and presented with GIS industry leaders as part of their post-REU experience. The Intellectual Merit and Broader Impacts of the work focused on student mentoring and research in an interdisciplinary team that was committed to engaging with diverse stakeholders to address major social and environmental challenges that could be mapped and visualized using GIS, drones, and related geospatial technologies.          Last Modified: 04/30/2021       Submitted by: Timothy Hawthorne]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
