<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>REU Site: Research Experience for Undergraduates in Satellite and Ground-Based Remote Sensing at NOAA-CREST: Expanded Opportunities</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>06/15/2016</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2020</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>535484.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>642400</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>06020300</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>GEO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>AGS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Atmospheric &amp; Geospace Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Manda S. Adams</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>amadams@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924708</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Promising undergraduate students from two- and four-year institutions within the City University of New York (CUNY) system will have the opportunity to work with scientists and engineers while they conduct research in the area of Satellite and Ground-Based Remote Sensing. Remote Sensing is a critically important, unique, and young area of science, and it is relatively unknown to many of the undergraduate students in the CUNY system. The activities combine year-long (Summer/Fall/Spring) research experiences with multidimensional mentoring, academic support systems, and a robust learning community that will produce holistic and engaging stimuli for the scientific and academic growth and development of the student participants.  This REU site will allow the students to transfer learning from sciences and mathematics to technology, computer systems and engineering applications where fundamental principles learned in particular natural sciences and mathematics courses are applied to real-world problems. The targeted student population of this REU site is primarily underrepresented minorities in STEM, and thus these activities have the potential to broaden participation and create a more diverse remote sensing community. The activities will also allow the undergraduate researchers the opportunity to hone their acquired skills and knowledge by presenting to high school students in the New York City Public school system.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This REU site has the following primary objectives: 1) To engage a diverse cohort of undergraduates in collaborative, state-of-the-art satellite and ground based remote sensing research, 2) to create and sustain a community and pipeline of scholars in STEM, 3) to enable students with the tools and confidence to succeed in an authentic research environment, and 4) to train students in the ethical and responsible conduct of research.  Students will participate in mini courses in GIS, remote sensing, and MATLAB.  Of particular merit for this REU site is the inclusion of 3 students from community college, who receive additional mentoring and support through a multi-tiered mentoring structure.  REU participants will receive professional development on a host of topics including ethics, communication, applying to graduate school and resume development.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/06/2016</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>02/13/2019</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.050</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1560050</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Janet</FirstName>
<LastName>Liou-Mark</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Janet Liou-Mark</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>jliou-mark@citytech.cuny.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>7182548668</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000172106</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/06/2016</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Reginald</FirstName>
<LastName>Blake</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Reginald Blake</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>rblake@citytech.cuny.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>7182548582</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000187792</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/06/2016</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>CUNY New York City College of Technology</Name>
<CityName>Brooklyn</CityName>
<ZipCode>112012902</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>7182605560</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>300 Jay Street</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NY07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>611930657</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>RESEARCH FOUNDATION OF THE CITY UNIVERSITY OF NEW YORK</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>073268849</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[CUNY New York City College of Technology]]></Name>
<CityName>Brooklyn</CityName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<ZipCode>112012902</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[300 Jay Street]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NY07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1525</Code>
<Text>Physical &amp; Dynamic Meteorology</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7700</Code>
<Text>EDUCATIONAL LINKAGES</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1525</Code>
<Text>PHYSICAL &amp; DYNAMIC METEOROLOGY</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>4444</Code>
<Text>INTERDISCIPLINARY PROPOSALS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7700</Code>
<Text>EDUCATIONAL LINKAGES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9178</Code>
<Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9250</Code>
<Text>REU SITE-Res Exp for Ugrd Site</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>SMET</Code>
<Text>SCIENCE, MATH, ENG &amp; TECH EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0116</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0118</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0119</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2016~535484</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2018~30714</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2019~76202</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p class="TableContents"><strong>Project Outcomes Report </strong></p> <p class="TableContents"><strong>NSF Award No. </strong><strong>AGS - 1560050</strong></p> <p><strong>REU Site: Research Experiences for Undergraduates in Satellite and </strong></p> <p><strong>Ground-Based Remote Sensing at NOAA-CREST: Expanded Opportunities</strong></p> <p class="TableContents"><strong>&nbsp;</strong></p> <h4>This program provided undergraduate students (particularly those who are traditionally underrepresented in STEM) an opportunity to conduct full-time, collaborative satellite and ground-based remote sensing research with faculty mentors from within the National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration Cooperative Remote Sensing Science and Technology Center (NOAA-CREST) consortium. Under the program, each year from 2016 &ndash; Spring 2020, approximately ten STEM students from both 4-yr and community colleges within the City University of New York&rsquo;s (CUNY) 24 campus-wide institutions (and often students from other universities or CUNY students who are not funded by this program) were engaged in cutting-edge satellite and ground-based remote sensing research of the atmosphere, the hydrosphere, the biosphere, the cryosphere, and the lithosphere. For fifteen weeks (nine weeks in the Summer, three weeks in the Fall, and three weeks in the Spring) each academic year, these students became part of a community of research scholars who actively engaged in state-of-the-art remote sensing research and applications. Additionally, these scholars participated in research group meetings, seminars, and oral and poster presentations at local, regional, and national conferences. For the undergraduate scholars, the program promoted research careers, established a community of scholars, and provided students with opportunities to pursue Masters and Doctoral graduate programs in STEM or to join the STEM workforce.</h4> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>During the reporting period 2016 &ndash; Spring 2020 (2019 &ndash; 2020 was a no cost extension year), the REU program provided a comprehensive research experience for a total of 43 students. Of the forty-three (43) students, seven (7) students were in the REU program for two consecutive years. The ethnicity and gender demographics of all the cohorts of REU scholars are depicted below in figures 1 and 2. The overall diverse cohort of students was comprised of 30% (13) African-Americans, 33% (14) Hispanics, 30% (13) Asian- Americans, and 7% (3) Caucasians. Gender-wise the cohort of students was comprised of 37% (16) females and 63% (27) males.&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>From this overall REU cohort, eleven (11) students are presently in graduate school, five (5) have graduated with a STEM graduate degree and are now in the STEM workforce, six (6) have graduated with a STEM Bachelor&rsquo;s degree and are in the STEM workforce, and twenty-one (21) continue to pursue their STEM undergraduate degrees. Therefore, by providing students with opportunities for STEM research, by improving their academic performance, skills, and attitudes, and by allowing significant exposure to STEM, this REU program has contributed in meaningful ways to the diversity of our nation&rsquo;s 21<sup>st</sup> century STEM workforce.&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>In accordance, therefore, with the intellectual merit and broader impacts objectives of this program, the following are some of its primary outcomes:</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <ul> <li>Six REU Scholars won first      place and one REU Scholar won second place and one won third place for      their oral/poster presentations at international and national conferences. </li> <li>Five REU Scholars won      second place for poster presentations at regional conferences.</li> <li>Three REU Scholars won      second place for poster presentations at local conferences.</li> <li>Nineteen REU Scholars won      travel awards for national conferences.</li> <li>There was a total of <strong>213</strong> presentations made by the REU Scholars during 2016-2020 (112      international/national presentations, 21 regional presentations, and 80      local presentations)</li> <li>All Forty-three scholars participated      in the annual Research Mixer event at the New York City College of      Technology. </li> </ul> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>Additionally, program dissemination efforts by the Reginald Blake (PI) and Janet Liou-Mark (Co-PI) include:</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <ul> <li>Two book chapters published</li> <li>Three peer reviewed journal articles published</li> <li>Seven conference proceedings published</li> <li>Twenty-six oral/poster presentations at national conferences presented</li> <li>Four oral presentations at international conferences</li> </ul> <p>&nbsp;<strong>&nbsp;</strong></p> <p><strong>&nbsp;</strong></p> <p>This NSF REU program continues to create innovative methodologies and strategies to provide both access and success for undergraduate students (from 4-yr and community colleges), particularly for those unrepresented in STEM. By providing rich research experiences for the students and by guiding them towards graduate studies and towards the STEM workforce, the program plays a vital role in helping to ameliorate the nation&rsquo;s STEM crisis and in narrowing the supply-demand STEM workforce gap.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 09/04/2020<br>      Modified by: Reginald&nbsp;Blake</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[Project Outcomes Report  NSF Award No. AGS - 1560050  REU Site: Research Experiences for Undergraduates in Satellite and   Ground-Based Remote Sensing at NOAA-CREST: Expanded Opportunities   This program provided undergraduate students (particularly those who are traditionally underrepresented in STEM) an opportunity to conduct full-time, collaborative satellite and ground-based remote sensing research with faculty mentors from within the National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration Cooperative Remote Sensing Science and Technology Center (NOAA-CREST) consortium. Under the program, each year from 2016 &ndash; Spring 2020, approximately ten STEM students from both 4-yr and community colleges within the City University of New York’s (CUNY) 24 campus-wide institutions (and often students from other universities or CUNY students who are not funded by this program) were engaged in cutting-edge satellite and ground-based remote sensing research of the atmosphere, the hydrosphere, the biosphere, the cryosphere, and the lithosphere. For fifteen weeks (nine weeks in the Summer, three weeks in the Fall, and three weeks in the Spring) each academic year, these students became part of a community of research scholars who actively engaged in state-of-the-art remote sensing research and applications. Additionally, these scholars participated in research group meetings, seminars, and oral and poster presentations at local, regional, and national conferences. For the undergraduate scholars, the program promoted research careers, established a community of scholars, and provided students with opportunities to pursue Masters and Doctoral graduate programs in STEM or to join the STEM workforce.     During the reporting period 2016 &ndash; Spring 2020 (2019 &ndash; 2020 was a no cost extension year), the REU program provided a comprehensive research experience for a total of 43 students. Of the forty-three (43) students, seven (7) students were in the REU program for two consecutive years. The ethnicity and gender demographics of all the cohorts of REU scholars are depicted below in figures 1 and 2. The overall diverse cohort of students was comprised of 30% (13) African-Americans, 33% (14) Hispanics, 30% (13) Asian- Americans, and 7% (3) Caucasians. Gender-wise the cohort of students was comprised of 37% (16) females and 63% (27) males.      From this overall REU cohort, eleven (11) students are presently in graduate school, five (5) have graduated with a STEM graduate degree and are now in the STEM workforce, six (6) have graduated with a STEM Bachelor’s degree and are in the STEM workforce, and twenty-one (21) continue to pursue their STEM undergraduate degrees. Therefore, by providing students with opportunities for STEM research, by improving their academic performance, skills, and attitudes, and by allowing significant exposure to STEM, this REU program has contributed in meaningful ways to the diversity of our nation’s 21st century STEM workforce.      In accordance, therefore, with the intellectual merit and broader impacts objectives of this program, the following are some of its primary outcomes:     Six REU Scholars won first      place and one REU Scholar won second place and one won third place for      their oral/poster presentations at international and national conferences.  Five REU Scholars won      second place for poster presentations at regional conferences. Three REU Scholars won      second place for poster presentations at local conferences. Nineteen REU Scholars won      travel awards for national conferences. There was a total of 213 presentations made by the REU Scholars during 2016-2020 (112      international/national presentations, 21 regional presentations, and 80      local presentations) All Forty-three scholars participated      in the annual Research Mixer event at the New York City College of      Technology.       Additionally, program dissemination efforts by the Reginald Blake (PI) and Janet Liou-Mark (Co-PI) include:     Two book chapters published Three peer reviewed journal articles published Seven conference proceedings published Twenty-six oral/poster presentations at national conferences presented Four oral presentations at international conferences          This NSF REU program continues to create innovative methodologies and strategies to provide both access and success for undergraduate students (from 4-yr and community colleges), particularly for those unrepresented in STEM. By providing rich research experiences for the students and by guiding them towards graduate studies and towards the STEM workforce, the program plays a vital role in helping to ameliorate the nation’s STEM crisis and in narrowing the supply-demand STEM workforce gap.          Last Modified: 09/04/2020       Submitted by: Reginald Blake]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
