<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Collaborative Research: New Nonlinear Modal Analysis Framework for Multi-Scale Modeling of Structures with Bolted Interfaces</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2016</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2020</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>300000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>348000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CMMI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Civil, Mechanical, &amp; Manufact Inn</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Irina Dolinskaya</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>idolinsk@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927078</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Engineers in many industries use the finite element method to divide structures into small elements so that the equations governing each can be found and solved by computers.   This allows one to compute the stresses and deformation of structures with complicated shapes such as airplanes, machines, biomedical implants, etc. and to predict whether the structure can survive the loads it will experience in operation.  While this method has proven very effective in many scenarios, even modern computers are not powerful enough to model the interfaces between parts accurately.  As a result, billions of dollars are spent annually testing structures to determine the stiffness of interfaces, such as bolted connections, in order to adjust the simulation models so that they better capture the real behavior of the structure.  This makes new machines much more expensive and often leads to designs that break prematurely, potentially endangering lives.  Prediction is particularly difficult when a structure, such as an aircraft, experiences dynamic loads due to turbulence in the air passing over the wings.  This work will explore a new means of simulating the motion of structures with bolted interfaces and will perform experiments to seek to understand how to model friction and microscopic slip in the joints and its effect on vibration damping. The methodology can be easily integrated in existing finite element software, to facilitate its transition and broad adoption. The research will be complemented by outreach activities at the PIs institutions and a short course exposing students and researchers to the technique formulated as part of the project.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The physics that are responsible for energy dissipation in mechanical joints are complicated and span the full range of length scales.  While much has been learned in recent years about the nature of nano- and meso-scale contact interfaces, friction is exceedingly complicated and may be influenced by local elasticity, chemistry, plasticity, surface roughness and lubrication provided by oxides or thin layers of wear particles.  This work posits a new reduced order modeling framework that allows one to connect the physics of small scale contacts to the global motion of the assembly.  An extension to modal analysis that can then be used to obtain a wealth of insight into the response of the structure under a variety of loading conditions.  The methodology will be validated through simulations on various structures and through experiments on assemblies with bolted interfaces, providing new insights into the role of interfaces on a structure's response.  Simulations will be performed to understand how the features/parameters of various friction laws manifest themselves in the damping and nonlinearity of the global dynamic response.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/26/2016</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>04/02/2019</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1561810</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Matthew</FirstName>
<LastName>Allen</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>S</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Matthew S Allen</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>matt.allen@byu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>8014224401</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000500407</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/26/2016</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Michael</FirstName>
<LastName>Sracic</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Michael Sracic</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>sracic@msoe.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>4142777300</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000703296</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/26/2016</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Wisconsin-Madison</Name>
<CityName>MADISON</CityName>
<ZipCode>537151218</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6082623822</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>21 North Park Street</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[Suite 6401]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Wisconsin</StateName>
<StateCode>WI</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>WI02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>161202122</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF WISCONSIN SYSTEM</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>041188822</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Wisconsin-Madison]]></Name>
<CityName>Madison</CityName>
<StateCode>WI</StateCode>
<ZipCode>537061609</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[535 Engineering Research Buildin]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Wisconsin</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>WI02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7569</Code>
<Text>Dynamics, Control and System D</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>030E</Code>
<Text>CONTROL SYSTEMS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>031E</Code>
<Text>MECHATRONICS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>032E</Code>
<Text>SENSORS AND ACTUATORS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>033E</Code>
<Text>Smart and responsive structures</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>034E</Code>
<Text>Dynamical systems</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>035E</Code>
<Text>NOISE, ACOUSTICS, VIBRATIONS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>039E</Code>
<Text>STRUCTURAL SYSTEMS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>040E</Code>
<Text>Haz mitigation of structural sys</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>099E</Code>
<Text>High voltage switching &amp; conversion</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1059</Code>
<Text>SENSORS AND SENSOR SYSTEMS FOR CIS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>116E</Code>
<Text>RESEARCH EXP FOR UNDERGRADS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7234</Code>
<Text>SENSORS NON-SOLICITATION RESEA</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8024</Code>
<Text>Complex Systems</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9178</Code>
<Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9231</Code>
<Text>SUPPL FOR UNDERGRAD RES ASSIST</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9251</Code>
<Text>REU SUPP-Res Exp for Ugrd Supp</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0116</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0117</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0118</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0119</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2016~300000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2017~16000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2018~16000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2019~16000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Over the past fifty years the finite element method has developed to the point that one can now create remarkably accurate models of parts so long as they are constructed of a single piece of metal.&nbsp; However, airplanes, automobiles, machines and civil structures are all constructed from multiple parts joined by bolts, rivets or other fasteners and these joints introduce large uncertainties in the structural stiffness and in the energy dissipated when the structure deforms.&nbsp; Each year in the United States, billions of dollars are spent testing structures, often to address these uncertainties in the stiffness and damping of joints.&nbsp; Furthermore, joints can lead to unexpected failures or the structure may be over-designed to avoid failure, at the expense of increased weight, cost, fuel consumption, etc?</p> <p>This work developed a new framework for modeling structures with bolted joints, which reduced the computational cost by orders of magnitude.&nbsp; The new framework used commercial modeling software in a new way, reducing the cost of computational analysis for one of the test structures from decades (according to our projections) to hours.&nbsp; The framework combines well known concepts from linear modal analysis with quasi-static nonlinear analysis to predict how the effective damping and natural frequency of each nonlinear mode will vary with time.</p> <p>The proposed framework was first applied to a laboratory structure consisting of two beams connected by two bolted joints.&nbsp; Using this simplified model, the researchers were able to compare, for the first time, measurements of the stiffness and dissipation of some of the structure?s modes of vibration (akin to the musical notes that a piano string plays when it is struck) with predictions from a simulation model.&nbsp; This shed new light into the physics that are important in the bolted connections and the level of detail needed in the model to capture them.</p> <p>During the course of the research, the PI learned that engineers working for NASA were struggling to create a model that captured some nonlinearities observed in bolted joints in the Multi Purpose Crew Vehicle (MPCV).&nbsp; The MPCV is part of the new Space Launch System (SLS), a replacement for the space shuttle that is expected to carry astronauts to the moon and to Mars in the coming decades.&nbsp; The PI worked with engineers involved in the project and helped them to implement the new modeling framework, and the NASA engineers were able to perform many more simulations of the MPCV than were previously possible, eventually obtaining a very good simplified dynamics model of the structure that seemed to agree well with test measurements.&nbsp; The fact that such a new technology was implemented so quickly in a real industrial setting speaks both to the dire need in industry for improved methods to solve these problems and to fact that the new modeling framework has proven highly effective and accurate in all applications to date.</p> <p>Over the course of this work, two graduate students were funded, both of which are nearing completion of their graduate degrees.&nbsp; Six undergraduate students were also funded on the work to varying degrees, three of which are now pursuing PhDs in engineering, one of which is working in industry and the remaining two are completing their undergraduate studies.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 11/17/2020<br>      Modified by: Matthew&nbsp;S&nbsp;Allen</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Images (<span id="selectedPhoto0">1</span> of <span class="totalNumber"></span>)           </div> <div class="galControls" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2020/1561810/1561810_10444132_1605641776772_S4Beam_Picture--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2020/1561810/1561810_10444132_1605641776772_S4Beam_Picture--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Simulation of the Contact in a Bolted Joint"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2020/1561810/1561810_10444132_1605641776772_S4Beam_Picture--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Simulation of the Contact in a Bolted Joint"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">This figure shows a photograph of a bolted joint that was both tested and simulated through the course of this work.  The assembly of two beams is instrumented with devices to measure the vibration and the measurements were used to understand the energy dissipation and nonlinearity from the joint.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Matt Allen</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Matthew&nbsp;S&nbsp;Allen</div> <div class="imageTitle">Simulation of the Contact in a Bolted Joint</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2020/1561810/1561810_10444132_1605641854360_S4Beam_Results--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2020/1561810/1561810_10444132_1605641854360_S4Beam_Results--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Comparisons of Effective Natural Frequency (i.e. stiffness) and Damping between measurements and simulations"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2020/1561810/1561810_10444132_1605641854360_S4Beam_Results--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Comparisons of Effective Natural Frequency (i.e. stiffness) and Damping between measurements and simulations"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">The frequency and damping measured in the experiments shown in Figure 1 are compared to several simulation models in which the preload in the joint is varied.  This is the first time that a comparison such as this has been possible with a high fidelity model (thanks to the computational savings prov</div> <div class="imageCredit">Matt Allen</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Matthew&nbsp;S&nbsp;Allen</div> <div class="imageTitle">Comparisons of Effective Natural Frequency (i.e. stiffness) and Damping between measurements and simulations</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Over the past fifty years the finite element method has developed to the point that one can now create remarkably accurate models of parts so long as they are constructed of a single piece of metal.  However, airplanes, automobiles, machines and civil structures are all constructed from multiple parts joined by bolts, rivets or other fasteners and these joints introduce large uncertainties in the structural stiffness and in the energy dissipated when the structure deforms.  Each year in the United States, billions of dollars are spent testing structures, often to address these uncertainties in the stiffness and damping of joints.  Furthermore, joints can lead to unexpected failures or the structure may be over-designed to avoid failure, at the expense of increased weight, cost, fuel consumption, etc?  This work developed a new framework for modeling structures with bolted joints, which reduced the computational cost by orders of magnitude.  The new framework used commercial modeling software in a new way, reducing the cost of computational analysis for one of the test structures from decades (according to our projections) to hours.  The framework combines well known concepts from linear modal analysis with quasi-static nonlinear analysis to predict how the effective damping and natural frequency of each nonlinear mode will vary with time.  The proposed framework was first applied to a laboratory structure consisting of two beams connected by two bolted joints.  Using this simplified model, the researchers were able to compare, for the first time, measurements of the stiffness and dissipation of some of the structure?s modes of vibration (akin to the musical notes that a piano string plays when it is struck) with predictions from a simulation model.  This shed new light into the physics that are important in the bolted connections and the level of detail needed in the model to capture them.  During the course of the research, the PI learned that engineers working for NASA were struggling to create a model that captured some nonlinearities observed in bolted joints in the Multi Purpose Crew Vehicle (MPCV).  The MPCV is part of the new Space Launch System (SLS), a replacement for the space shuttle that is expected to carry astronauts to the moon and to Mars in the coming decades.  The PI worked with engineers involved in the project and helped them to implement the new modeling framework, and the NASA engineers were able to perform many more simulations of the MPCV than were previously possible, eventually obtaining a very good simplified dynamics model of the structure that seemed to agree well with test measurements.  The fact that such a new technology was implemented so quickly in a real industrial setting speaks both to the dire need in industry for improved methods to solve these problems and to fact that the new modeling framework has proven highly effective and accurate in all applications to date.  Over the course of this work, two graduate students were funded, both of which are nearing completion of their graduate degrees.  Six undergraduate students were also funded on the work to varying degrees, three of which are now pursuing PhDs in engineering, one of which is working in industry and the remaining two are completing their undergraduate studies.       Last Modified: 11/17/2020       Submitted by: Matthew S Allen]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
