<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Algebra Instruction at Community Colleges: An Exploration of its Relationship with Student Success</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>05/15/2016</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>04/30/2020</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>2370836.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>2370836</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>11040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>EHR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DUE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Undergraduate Education</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Beth Herbel Eisenmann</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>bherbele@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924278</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Community colleges serve a large portion of students who require mathematics at the undergraduate level and play an increasing role in STEM workforce development. There is a growing national interest in the role of community colleges for undergraduate education. The proposal seeks to investigate the conditions under which instruction in community college algebra courses can be associated with student learning gains and course performance. This information can be used to design programs to improve instruction and to support student success in algebra. The study involves six community colleges from three states and focuses on three key algebra topics: linear equations, rational equations, and exponential equations. The results will also have applications for mathematics courses at other institutions of higher education. This project is supported by NSF's EHR Core Research (ECR) program. The ECR program emphasizes fundamental STEM education research that generates foundational knowledge in the field. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The project will connect both levels of the classroom (students and instructors) in a model that examines personal characteristics of both groups (e.g., gender, ethnicity, educational background, student mathematics knowledge, and beliefs about mathematics) and aspects of classroom interaction (e.g., quality of mathematics, quality of instruction). The institutions represent urban, suburban, and rural communities, a range of institution sizes, and three different regions of the United States. A model is proposed for examining these related variables to examine what relationships exist. Quantitative and qualitative data will be collected in a mixed methods design in multiple project phases. The first phase will include pilot testing some of the instruments for the project and testing the models. Later phases include data collection and analysis across the institutions. Data collection includes student-level and instructor-level measures. For students, the project will examine measures of mathematics performance, mathematics beliefs, and perceptions of the classroom environment. For instructors, the project will examine knowledge, beliefs, and attitudes. Demographic information will be collected for all participants. In addition to the quantitative measures, classroom observations and video analysis will be used to document the nature of instruction.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>05/09/2016</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/03/2017</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.076</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1561436</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Irene</FirstName>
<LastName>Duranczyk</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Irene Duranczyk</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>duran026@umn.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6126264421</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000329462</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/09/2016</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Vilma</FirstName>
<LastName>Mesa</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Vilma Mesa</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>vmesa@umich.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>7347641817</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000261355</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/09/2016</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>April</FirstName>
<LastName>Strom</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>D</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>April D Strom</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>april.strom@scottsdalecc.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>4807318031</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000516412</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/09/2016</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Laura</FirstName>
<LastName>Watkins</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>L</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Laura L Watkins</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>laura.watkins@gccaz.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6238453718</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000649452</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/09/2016</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Nidhi</FirstName>
<LastName>Kohli</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Nidhi Kohli</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>nkohli@umn.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6126245599</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000701316</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/09/2016</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Maricopa County Community College District</Name>
<CityName>Tempe</CityName>
<ZipCode>852816941</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>4807318402</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>2411 W 14th St</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Arizona</StateName>
<StateCode>AZ</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>09</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>AZ09</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>074491515</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>MARICOPA COUNTY COMMUNITY COLLEGE DISTRICT</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>074491515</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Maricopa County Community College District]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>AZ</StateCode>
<ZipCode>852816942</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Arizona</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>09</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>AZ09</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7980</Code>
<Text>ECR-EHR Core Research</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8817</Code>
<Text>STEM Learning &amp; Learning Environments</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9178</Code>
<Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0416</Code>
<Name>NSF Education &amp; Human Resource</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040106</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0417</Code>
<Name>NSF Education &amp; Human Resource</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040106</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2016~1576242</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2017~794594</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The <em>Algebra Instruction at Community Colleges: An Exploration of its Relationship with Student Success (AI@CC)</em> was a four-year $2.37 million National Science Foundation (NSF) Education and Human Resources Core research project involving 9 partners: Glendale Community College (AZ), as the lead, Anoka-Ramsey Community College, Chandler-Gilbert Community College, Delta College, Macomb Community College, North Hennepin Community College, Scottsdale Community College, University of Michigan, and University of Minnesota. AI@CC&rsquo;s primary goal was to understand the conditions under which instruction in community college algebra courses can be associated with student learning gains and course performance and to use this information to design faculty development programs that support student success in algebra.</p> <p>Community colleges serve a large portion of students who require mathematics at the undergraduate level and play an increasing role in STEM workforce development. There is a growing national interest in the role of community colleges for undergraduate education. AI@CC investigated the conditions under which instruction in community college algebra courses were associated with student learning gains and course performance. The study focused on three key algebra topics: linear equations, rational equations, and exponential equations. The project analyzed data at classroom levels (students and instructors) in a model that examined personal characteristics of both groups (e.g., gender, ethnicity, educational background, beliefs about mathematics and mathematics teaching/learning,&nbsp; students&rsquo; mathematics knowledge, and teachers&rsquo; knowledge for teaching) and aspects of classroom interaction (e.g., quality of mathematics, quality of instruction). The eight institutions represented urban, suburban, and rural communities, a range of institution sizes, and three different regions of the United States. Quantitative and qualitative data were collected in a mixed methods design in multiple project phases via surveys, tests, artifacts (student work, syllabi), video and audio recordings of lessons, and instructors&rsquo; reflections on all the lessons recorded . The project examined measures of students&rsquo; mathematics performance, mathematics beliefs, and perceptions of the classroom environment; instructors&rsquo; knowledge for algebra teaching, beliefs, and attitudes; and qualities of instruction. To assess quality of instruction, the project developed an instrument, the Evaluating Quality Instruction in Post-Secondary Mathematics (EQIPM) which measured three components of the quality of instruction in community college algebra: the quality of student-content interaction, the quality of instructor-content interactions, and the quality of instructor-student interaction. In addition, the project improved on an instrument to assess covariational reasoning among community college students, the Algebra and Precalculus Concept Readiness test. The modeling confirmed prior results regarding student performance due to prior knowledge and personal characteristics on course performance. Further development of an instrument to assess knowledge is needed to assess student learning. Further diversification of the instructor sample is needed to assess the discriminatory power of EQIPM. Further development of an instrument to assess knowledge for teaching for community college instructors is needed to improve its discrimination power.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 07/11/2020<br>      Modified by: Laura&nbsp;L&nbsp;Watkins</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Images (<span id="selectedPhoto0">1</span> of <span class="totalNumber"></span>)           </div> <div class="galControls" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2020/1561436/1561436_10423745_1594441482939_StructureofEQIPM--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2020/1561436/1561436_10423745_1594441482939_StructureofEQIPM--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Structure of the EQIPM instrument"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2020/1561436/1561436_10423745_1594441482939_StructureofEQIPM--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Structure of the EQIPM instrument"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Structure of the EQIPM instrument illustrating how characteristics of student-content, instructor-content, and instructor-student interactions.</div> <div class="imageCredit">AI@CC Research Group</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Laura&nbsp;L&nbsp;Watkins</div> <div class="imageTitle">Structure of the EQIPM instrument</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2020/1561436/1561436_10423745_1594441289365_FinalModelofRelationships--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2020/1561436/1561436_10423745_1594441289365_FinalModelofRelationships--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Final model of relationships"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2020/1561436/1561436_10423745_1594441289365_FinalModelofRelationships--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Final model of relationships"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Final model of relationships between students, instructors, and instruction modeled by the AI@CC research group.</div> <div class="imageCredit">AI@CC Research Group</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Laura&nbsp;L&nbsp;Watkins</div> <div class="imageTitle">Final model of relationships</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2020/1561436/1561436_10423745_1594441144765_InitialModelofRelationships--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2020/1561436/1561436_10423745_1594441144765_InitialModelofRelationships--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Proposed model of relationships"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2020/1561436/1561436_10423745_1594441144765_InitialModelofRelationships--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Proposed model of relationships"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Proposed model of relationships between students, instructors, and instruction to be explored by the AI@CC study.</div> <div class="imageCredit">AI@CC Research Group</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Laura&nbsp;L&nbsp;Watkins</div> <div class="imageTitle">Proposed model of relationships</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The Algebra Instruction at Community Colleges: An Exploration of its Relationship with Student Success (AI@CC) was a four-year $2.37 million National Science Foundation (NSF) Education and Human Resources Core research project involving 9 partners: Glendale Community College (AZ), as the lead, Anoka-Ramsey Community College, Chandler-Gilbert Community College, Delta College, Macomb Community College, North Hennepin Community College, Scottsdale Community College, University of Michigan, and University of Minnesota. AI@CC’s primary goal was to understand the conditions under which instruction in community college algebra courses can be associated with student learning gains and course performance and to use this information to design faculty development programs that support student success in algebra.  Community colleges serve a large portion of students who require mathematics at the undergraduate level and play an increasing role in STEM workforce development. There is a growing national interest in the role of community colleges for undergraduate education. AI@CC investigated the conditions under which instruction in community college algebra courses were associated with student learning gains and course performance. The study focused on three key algebra topics: linear equations, rational equations, and exponential equations. The project analyzed data at classroom levels (students and instructors) in a model that examined personal characteristics of both groups (e.g., gender, ethnicity, educational background, beliefs about mathematics and mathematics teaching/learning,  students’ mathematics knowledge, and teachers’ knowledge for teaching) and aspects of classroom interaction (e.g., quality of mathematics, quality of instruction). The eight institutions represented urban, suburban, and rural communities, a range of institution sizes, and three different regions of the United States. Quantitative and qualitative data were collected in a mixed methods design in multiple project phases via surveys, tests, artifacts (student work, syllabi), video and audio recordings of lessons, and instructors’ reflections on all the lessons recorded . The project examined measures of students’ mathematics performance, mathematics beliefs, and perceptions of the classroom environment; instructors’ knowledge for algebra teaching, beliefs, and attitudes; and qualities of instruction. To assess quality of instruction, the project developed an instrument, the Evaluating Quality Instruction in Post-Secondary Mathematics (EQIPM) which measured three components of the quality of instruction in community college algebra: the quality of student-content interaction, the quality of instructor-content interactions, and the quality of instructor-student interaction. In addition, the project improved on an instrument to assess covariational reasoning among community college students, the Algebra and Precalculus Concept Readiness test. The modeling confirmed prior results regarding student performance due to prior knowledge and personal characteristics on course performance. Further development of an instrument to assess knowledge is needed to assess student learning. Further diversification of the instructor sample is needed to assess the discriminatory power of EQIPM. Further development of an instrument to assess knowledge for teaching for community college instructors is needed to improve its discrimination power.       Last Modified: 07/11/2020       Submitted by: Laura L Watkins]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
