<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Automatic grammar engineering for endangered languages based on cross-linguistic resources</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/15/2016</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>01/31/2021</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>429864.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>429864</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>05020000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>CSE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>IIS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Information &amp; Intelligent Systems</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>D.  Langendoen</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>dlangend@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032925088</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Grammar engineering is the process of creating computer models of the grammar of languages, including how words are formed from smaller meaningful parts, how words are put together into sentences, and how the meaning of sentences is built based on their structure and the meaning of their parts. This project is automatically creating computational grammars by combining computational techniques developed for well-studied languages, data collected and annotated by field linguists and a cross-linguistic grammar resource (the LinGO Grammar Matrix). Computational grammars enrich the results of language documentation because they can be used to automatically create further annotations (of word structure, sentence structure and meaning). Text annotated in this way can be searched both for word forms or structures of interest as well as for examples which fall outside of current hypotheses, helping linguists more rapidly zero in on the data of interest. Broader impacts include the training of graduate students and the development of computational tools of potential use to groups ranging from linguists to endangered or low resource language communities. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The AGGREGATION Project aims to bring the benefits of grammar engineering to the urgent task of documenting endangered languages. In Phase II, the AGGREGATION Project will pursue two related sets of goals: (1) Expanding the coverage of the cross-linguistic resource and the resulting computational grammars and (2) creating interfaces to realize the potential of the grammars, the annotations they produce, and the intermediate outputs of our grammar creation system as analytical tools for field linguists. The overall system and its interfaces are general tools, meant to bring the power of computational processing to field linguists. In order to ensure their broad applicability, the tools will be developed using three languages from different language families and different parts of the world as case studies: Chintang (a Kiranti language of Nepal), Matsigenka (an Arawak language of Peru), and Abui (an Alor-Pantar language of Indonesia). This project is supported by NSF's Robust Intelligence Program in CISE.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>03/22/2016</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>03/22/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.070</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1561833</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Emily</FirstName>
<LastName>Bender</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>M</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Emily M Bender</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>ebender@u.washington.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2065436914</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000429660</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>03/22/2016</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Fei</FirstName>
<LastName>Xia</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Fei Xia</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>fxia@u.washington.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2065439764</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000232098</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>03/22/2016</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Washington</Name>
<CityName>Seattle</CityName>
<ZipCode>981950001</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2065434043</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>4333 Brooklyn Ave NE</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Washington</StateName>
<StateCode>WA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>WA07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>605799469</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF WASHINGTON</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>042803536</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Washington]]></Name>
<CityName>Seattle</CityName>
<StateCode>WA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>981950001</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[4333 Brooklyn Ave NE]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Washington</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>WA07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7495</Code>
<Text>Robust Intelligence</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7719</Code>
<Text>DEL</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7495</Code>
<Text>ROBUST INTELLIGENCE</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7719</Code>
<Text>DEL</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9179</Code>
<Text>GRADUATE INVOLVEMENT</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0116</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2016~429864</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>&lt;p class="p1"&gt;The AGGREGATION Project is situated within work on applying computational methods to endangered language documentation. In particular, we are interested in automatically developing computational grammars for languages on the basis of two kinds of rich linguistic resources: collections of data annotated with morpheme-by-morpheme glosses and translations for the language, on the one hand, and a cross-linguistic grammar customization system (called the LinGO Grammar Matrix), on the other. The Grammar Matrix stores analyses for different kinds of grammatical phenomena that vary across languages (e.g., how a language expresses negation or forms questions). It takes in a grammar specification and outputs a working, machine-readable grammar that meets that specification. These grammars can take sentences written in the languages they go with and output grammatical structures including representations of the sentence meaning. Our goal in this project is to create software that can output the grammar specifications on the basis of annotated data collections produced by documentary linguists so that a grammar can automatically be generated.&lt;/p&gt;<br />&lt;p class="p1"&gt;The AGGREGATION Project (Phase II) has made the following advances:&lt;/p&gt;<br />&lt;ul&gt;<br />&lt;li&gt;We extended the Grammar Matrix to include analyses for subordinate clauses, &lt;em&gt;wh&lt;/em&gt; questions (&lt;em&gt;who&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;what&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;where&lt;/em&gt;), and other phenomena.&lt;/li&gt;<br />&lt;li&gt;We extended the AGGREGATION inference system to integrate lexical and morphological inference with syntactic inference, increased the richness of morphological rules by integrating syntactic features and extended the syntactic phenomena that can be handled.&lt;/li&gt;<br />&lt;li&gt;We built an integrated, end-to-end pipeline that starts with data collections from field linguists and produces working grammars.&lt;/li&gt;<br />&lt;li&gt;We evaluated the system with datasets from 14 languages from all around the world: Abui, Arapaho, Chintang, Hiaki, Hixkaryana, Lezgi, Matsigenka, Meithei, Nuuchahnulth, South Efate, Titan, Tsova-Tush, Wakhi and Wambaya.&lt;/li&gt;<br />&lt;li&gt;We built visualization software to help linguists who provide datasets explore the patterns that our inference system extracts.&lt;/li&gt;<br />&lt;li&gt;We held a workshop to train field linguists to use the software and elicit their feedback on how to improve it.&lt;/li&gt;<br />&lt;/ul&gt;<br />&lt;p class="p1"&gt;These systems have both immediate and long term impacts on linguistic research and speaker communities. For linguistic research, automatically derived computational grammars can help documentary linguists explore their data, discover counterexamples to proposed generalizations, and find further items of interest not already handled by their analyses. The implemented grammars also provide starting points for creating robust language resources which can in turn support language technology. We anticipate that our work will lead to more and better language documentation which in turn will support language revitalization efforts by communities around the world. Language revitalization has additional benefits in strengthening communities. Furthermore, language technology for endangered languages can enhance the prestige of those languages and thus their long-term maintenance.&lt;/p&gt;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 06/24/2021<br>      Modified by: Emily&nbsp;Bender</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ &lt;p class="p1"&gt;The AGGREGATION Project is situated within work on applying computational methods to endangered language documentation. In particular, we are interested in automatically developing computational grammars for languages on the basis of two kinds of rich linguistic resources: collections of data annotated with morpheme-by-morpheme glosses and translations for the language, on the one hand, and a cross-linguistic grammar customization system (called the LinGO Grammar Matrix), on the other. The Grammar Matrix stores analyses for different kinds of grammatical phenomena that vary across languages (e.g., how a language expresses negation or forms questions). It takes in a grammar specification and outputs a working, machine-readable grammar that meets that specification. These grammars can take sentences written in the languages they go with and output grammatical structures including representations of the sentence meaning. Our goal in this project is to create software that can output the grammar specifications on the basis of annotated data collections produced by documentary linguists so that a grammar can automatically be generated.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p class="p1"&gt;The AGGREGATION Project (Phase II) has made the following advances:&lt;/p&gt; &lt;ul&gt; &lt;li&gt;We extended the Grammar Matrix to include analyses for subordinate clauses, &lt;em&gt;wh&lt;/em&gt; questions (&lt;em&gt;who&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;what&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;where&lt;/em&gt;), and other phenomena.&lt;/li&gt; &lt;li&gt;We extended the AGGREGATION inference system to integrate lexical and morphological inference with syntactic inference, increased the richness of morphological rules by integrating syntactic features and extended the syntactic phenomena that can be handled.&lt;/li&gt; &lt;li&gt;We built an integrated, end-to-end pipeline that starts with data collections from field linguists and produces working grammars.&lt;/li&gt; &lt;li&gt;We evaluated the system with datasets from 14 languages from all around the world: Abui, Arapaho, Chintang, Hiaki, Hixkaryana, Lezgi, Matsigenka, Meithei, Nuuchahnulth, South Efate, Titan, Tsova-Tush, Wakhi and Wambaya.&lt;/li&gt; &lt;li&gt;We built visualization software to help linguists who provide datasets explore the patterns that our inference system extracts.&lt;/li&gt; &lt;li&gt;We held a workshop to train field linguists to use the software and elicit their feedback on how to improve it.&lt;/li&gt; &lt;/ul&gt; &lt;p class="p1"&gt;These systems have both immediate and long term impacts on linguistic research and speaker communities. For linguistic research, automatically derived computational grammars can help documentary linguists explore their data, discover counterexamples to proposed generalizations, and find further items of interest not already handled by their analyses. The implemented grammars also provide starting points for creating robust language resources which can in turn support language technology. We anticipate that our work will lead to more and better language documentation which in turn will support language revitalization efforts by communities around the world. Language revitalization has additional benefits in strengthening communities. Furthermore, language technology for endangered languages can enhance the prestige of those languages and thus their long-term maintenance.&lt;/p&gt;       Last Modified: 06/24/2021       Submitted by: Emily Bender]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
