<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Collaborative Research: Career Lifecycles of Enterprising Workers in R&amp;D Intensive Industries</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2016</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>50739.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>50739</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>04010000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>SBE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>SMA</Abbreviation>
<LongName>SBE Off Of Multidisciplinary Activities</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Cassidy Sugimoto</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Enterprising individuals build their careers, continuously making choices between staying at the start-ups they create, leaving to engage in serial entrepreneurship, or exiting into paid employment, either alone, as part of a small independent team, or as part of full company acquired by an established firm. These choices are shaped by experiences and constraints and, in turn, affect subsequent career choices and economic outcomes.  Greater attention to human capital dynamics by tracing career histories of innovative personnel within and across firm boundaries may provide richer insights into economic dynamism. An examination of factors that impact enterprising workers' career choices can inform science and innovation policy to promote knowledge creation and diffusion. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The US Census Bureau Longitudinal Employer-Household Dynamics (LEHD) Project provides near universal coverage that allows the construction of the career histories of enterprising individuals in R&amp;D intensive industries across the 18 year time period from 1991-2008.  The research focuses on the fates of these individuals after entrepreneurial activity by examining the paths that individuals take after exiting new ventures of different types and by examining the transferability of different entrepreneurial experiences outside of the entrepreneurial context.  Family composition constrains geographical mobility which in turn shapes how enterprising individuals build their careers through mobility and entrepreneurship.  Together the research explore important individual antecedents to, and consequences of, entrepreneurial activity.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/30/2016</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/30/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.075</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1561266</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Seth</FirstName>
<LastName>Carnahan</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Seth Carnahan</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>scarnaha@umich.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>7347639528</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000600934</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/30/2016</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Regents of the University of Michigan - Ann Arbor</Name>
<CityName>Ann Arbor</CityName>
<ZipCode>481091274</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>7347636438</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>3003 South State St. Room 1062</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Michigan</StateName>
<StateCode>MI</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>12</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MI12</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>073133571</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>REGENTS OF THE UNIVERSITY OF MICHIGAN</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>073133571</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Michigan Ann Arbor]]></Name>
<CityName>Ann Arbor</CityName>
<StateCode>MI</StateCode>
<ZipCode>481091234</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[701 Tappan St.]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Michigan</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>12</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MI12</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7626</Code>
<Text>SciSIP-Sci of Sci Innov Policy</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7626</Code>
<Text>SCIENCE OF SCIENCE POLICY</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0116</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2016~50739</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>This project examined the following  questions: (1) What are the fates of enterprising individuals who engage  in new venture creation?; and (2) How do mobility constraints create  market frictions and facilitators that impact the subsequent career  choices of enterprising individuals?</p> <p>Motivating these research questions is the premise that the vibrancy  of a knowledge economy is predicated on the enterprising action and  agency of knowledge workers. Accordingly, by examining by factors that  shape the antecedents and consequences of individuals? enterprising  experiences we inform science and innovation policy that promotes  knowledge creation and diffusion.&nbsp; While much current policy is focused  on shaping firm level outcomes, we demonstrated that deeper attention to  human capital dynamics with a primacy on tracing career histories of  innovative personnel within and across firm boundaries provides rich  insights into understanding and promoting economic dynamism.</p> <p>The research team focused on the core idea that as enterprising  individuals build their careers, they continuously make choices between  staying and growing the start-ups they create, leaving to engage in  serial entrepreneurship, or exiting into paid employment?either alone,  as part of a small independent team, or as part of full company acquired  by an established firm. These choices are shaped by their experiences  and constraints and, in turn, affect their subsequent career choices and  outcomes.&nbsp; This lens allowed the team to construct a framework for  understanding the fates, frictions and facilitators of enterprising  individuals? career choices. The research team explored the implications  of this framework from multiple perspectives using data from the  Longitudinal Establishment-Household Dynamics (LEHD) program of the US  Census Bureau augmented with other data sources. These data allowed the  team to examine (1) the paths that individuals take before joining and  after exiting new ventures of different types; (2) the transferability  of different classes of experiences within and outside of innovative  contexts; and (3) how a variety of constraints shape how enterprising  and innovative individuals build their careers through mobility and  entrepreneurship.</p> <p>&nbsp;This approach supported multiple studies that cumulatively  contribute to the scientific literature, to practitioners, and to policy  makers.&nbsp; The outcomes of the studies allowed the team to (1) document  and explain how prior experiences shape how new hires match to  entrepreneurs; (2) show the relative benefits of different aspects of  entrepreneurial team members? prior experiences on new venture  performance; (3) demonstrate the impact of within- and cross-industry  experience on new venture entry, performance, and survival; (4) document  the impact of patenting on inventor?s wages, mobility, and  entrepreneurship; (5) inform workers? career decisions about how firm  characteristics, geographical characteristics, and family  characteristics may facilitate or create impediments to successful  start-up entry and subsequent growth; and (6) help science and  innovation policy makers in understanding how deeper attention to human  capital dynamics with a primacy on tracing career histories of  innovative personnel within and across firm boundaries may provide a  richer measure of economic dynamism than a singular focus on new venture  creation and jobs associated with start-ups.</p> <p>&nbsp;The outcomes of the award include multiple working papers, leading  journal submissions, conference presentations and roundtable  discussions, seminar presentations and the successful training and  support of multiple doctoral students.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 01/18/2019<br>      Modified by: Seth&nbsp;Carnahan</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ This project examined the following  questions: (1) What are the fates of enterprising individuals who engage  in new venture creation?; and (2) How do mobility constraints create  market frictions and facilitators that impact the subsequent career  choices of enterprising individuals?  Motivating these research questions is the premise that the vibrancy  of a knowledge economy is predicated on the enterprising action and  agency of knowledge workers. Accordingly, by examining by factors that  shape the antecedents and consequences of individuals? enterprising  experiences we inform science and innovation policy that promotes  knowledge creation and diffusion.  While much current policy is focused  on shaping firm level outcomes, we demonstrated that deeper attention to  human capital dynamics with a primacy on tracing career histories of  innovative personnel within and across firm boundaries provides rich  insights into understanding and promoting economic dynamism.  The research team focused on the core idea that as enterprising  individuals build their careers, they continuously make choices between  staying and growing the start-ups they create, leaving to engage in  serial entrepreneurship, or exiting into paid employment?either alone,  as part of a small independent team, or as part of full company acquired  by an established firm. These choices are shaped by their experiences  and constraints and, in turn, affect their subsequent career choices and  outcomes.  This lens allowed the team to construct a framework for  understanding the fates, frictions and facilitators of enterprising  individuals? career choices. The research team explored the implications  of this framework from multiple perspectives using data from the  Longitudinal Establishment-Household Dynamics (LEHD) program of the US  Census Bureau augmented with other data sources. These data allowed the  team to examine (1) the paths that individuals take before joining and  after exiting new ventures of different types; (2) the transferability  of different classes of experiences within and outside of innovative  contexts; and (3) how a variety of constraints shape how enterprising  and innovative individuals build their careers through mobility and  entrepreneurship.   This approach supported multiple studies that cumulatively  contribute to the scientific literature, to practitioners, and to policy  makers.  The outcomes of the studies allowed the team to (1) document  and explain how prior experiences shape how new hires match to  entrepreneurs; (2) show the relative benefits of different aspects of  entrepreneurial team members? prior experiences on new venture  performance; (3) demonstrate the impact of within- and cross-industry  experience on new venture entry, performance, and survival; (4) document  the impact of patenting on inventor?s wages, mobility, and  entrepreneurship; (5) inform workers? career decisions about how firm  characteristics, geographical characteristics, and family  characteristics may facilitate or create impediments to successful  start-up entry and subsequent growth; and (6) help science and  innovation policy makers in understanding how deeper attention to human  capital dynamics with a primacy on tracing career histories of  innovative personnel within and across firm boundaries may provide a  richer measure of economic dynamism than a singular focus on new venture  creation and jobs associated with start-ups.   The outcomes of the award include multiple working papers, leading  journal submissions, conference presentations and roundtable  discussions, seminar presentations and the successful training and  support of multiple doctoral students.       Last Modified: 01/18/2019       Submitted by: Seth Carnahan]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
