<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>CSBR: Living Stocks: Enhancing the Quality and Efficiency of the Arabidopsis Biological Resource Center</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>04/15/2016</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>03/31/2020</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>499540.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>499540</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>08080000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>BIO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DBI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Biological Infrastructure</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Reed Beaman</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>rsbeaman@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927163</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The Arabidopsis Biological Resource Center (ABRC) was established in 1991 with the mission to collect, preserve, propagate and distribute diverse resources of Arabidopsis thaliana and related species. The Center has been serving the dynamically changing needs of the scientific community that uses Arabidopsis for research, and has grown to serve more than 27,000 investigators worldwide. The collection of almost one million stocks comprises seed, DNA, protein and cell culture stocks, as well as educational materials. With over 200,000 samples distributed annually, ABRC provides an essential service to the plant research community involved in understanding the basic processes in plant models, and ultimately leading to applications to accelerate crop improvement.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;In the next three years the Center will: 1) continue to enlarge and expand the collections of resources based on projected demand, including antibodies and DNA resources from other species; 2) procure, store and distribute novel types of resources as they are developed and driven by the needs of the community; 3) continue to increase the efficiency of the operation, thus providing higher quality of service without a budget increase; 4) continue developing partnerships with Nottingham Arabidopsis Stock Centre (arabidopsis.info) and the Arabidopsis Information Portal (www.araport.org) in order to provide online access to stock information and ordering; and 5) continue to expand the role of ABRC as a resource for education and outreach by developing new K-12 hands-on programs and by increasing the reach of the existing K-12 and college-level teaching activities. The updated procedures for stock handling and maintenance, along with the quality control protocols and statistics, can be found online (abrc.osu.edu). Education materials are also available online (abrcoutreach.osu.edu), including the detailed information about education kits.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>03/18/2016</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>03/06/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.074</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1561210</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Erich</FirstName>
<LastName>Grotewold</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Erich Grotewold</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>grotewol@msu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5173551600</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000122262</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>03/18/2016</StartDate>
<EndDate>11/15/2017</EndDate>
<RoleCode>Former Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>David</FirstName>
<LastName>Somers</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>E</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>David E Somers</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>somers.24@osu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6142922551</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000270865</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/22/2018</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>R. Keith</FirstName>
<LastName>Slotkin</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>R. Keith Slotkin</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>kslotkin@danforthcenter.org</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>3145871425</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000545716</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/04/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate>11/15/2017</EndDate>
<RoleCode>Former Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>R. Keith</FirstName>
<LastName>Slotkin</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>R. Keith Slotkin</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>kslotkin@danforthcenter.org</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>3145871425</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000545716</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>11/15/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate>06/22/2018</EndDate>
<RoleCode>Former Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Jelena</FirstName>
<LastName>Brkljacic</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Jelena Brkljacic</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>brkljacic.1@osu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6142929152</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000562134</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>03/18/2016</StartDate>
<EndDate>05/06/2019</EndDate>
<RoleCode>Former Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Emma</FirstName>
<LastName>Knee</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>M</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Emma M Knee</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>knee.2@osu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6142929371</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000799123</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/06/2019</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Ohio State University</Name>
<CityName>Columbus</CityName>
<ZipCode>432101016</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6146888735</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>Office of Sponsored Programs</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[1960 Kenny Road]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Ohio</StateName>
<StateCode>OH</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>OH03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>832127323</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>OHIO STATE UNIVERSITY, THE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>001964634</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[The Ohio State University]]></Name>
<CityName>Columbus</CityName>
<StateCode>OH</StateCode>
<ZipCode>432101012</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[1060 Carmack Rd, 012 Rightmire H]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Ohio</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>OH03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1197</Code>
<Text>BIOLOGICAL RESEARCH COLLECTION</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1197</Code>
<Text>BIOLOGICAL RESEARCH COLLECTION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0116</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0117</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0118</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2016~161637</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2017~167321</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2018~170582</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>This grant funds the core mission of the Arabidopsis Biological Resource Center (ABRC) to acquire, maintain and distribute resources of the model plant Arabidopsis thaliana for use in research and education. Arabidopsis was the first plant genome to be completely sequenced and is extensively used in research and education. Many resources have been generated through collaborative research funded by NSF and other agencies and it is important to the Arabidopsis community to preserve these resources and make them widely available.</p> <p>The ABRC collection contains almost 540,000 seed stocks and 450,000 non-seed stocks. Most of the seed stocks acquired during the granting period were Arabidopsis mutants that can be used to investigate gene function. Other members of the Brassica family, a number of which were used to generate full genome sequence, were also added to the collection. Of the non-seed stocks acquired during the granting period, many are resources for molecular research, including cloned Arabidopsis genes and multi-functional vectors. Collections of resources for K-12 and college education developed by researchers and educators were also acquired. All new stocks added to the collection enter ABRC&rsquo;s quality control pipeline to verify germination and stock identity. Stocks reported to be incorrect and stocks grown at ABRC are also subjected to quality control testing.</p> <p>ABRC has shipped over 500,000 samples to researchers in 67 countries during the granting period. We have shipped resources to 87 K-12 Educational institutions around the world. Education kits have been shipped to 49 states within the USA and to 19 other countries. Resources for K-12 education are provided free of charge. Other users of ABRC&rsquo;s resources pay a small fee to offset the costs of stock maintenance and distribution. The payment rate in recent years has been close to 99%. The NSF contribution to our operating budget is approximately 20%, while user fees represent approximately 60% of the total budget and the remaining support is provided by the university. Demand for stocks has been relatively stable throughout the granting period and might be expected to be sustained based on distribution for the first three months of 2020. However, towards the end of this period we have seen a significant drop in orders as a result of the COVID-19 pandemic which will impact orders and income for 2020 and potentially future years.</p> <p>In 2019 ABRC developed and launched a state-of-the-art database and web based ordering tool for Arabidopsis and other plant resources. This tool allows easy access to stock data through a web interface and allows for continued collaboration and exchange of data with other Arabidopsis data providers. Google analytics data shows that the site is widely used with approximately 2,000 users per week from 117 countries. The top three countries are the United States, which represents 30% of users, China (20%), and Japan (10%). The remaining countries represent less than 5% each. We share news about ABRC&rsquo;s activities through the news and events section of our website and via the ABRC Twitter feed @ABRC_News (614 followers). Newly released stocks are listed on the researcher home page of the web site. We also attend annual meetings such as the International Conference on Arabidopsis Research (ICAR), Plant Biology, and the Plant Animal Genome (PAG) meetings, on a regular basis.</p> <p>ABRC continues to reach out to a larger and more diverse audience through participation in community events, partnerships with community organizations and programming at local schools. During the granting period, ABRC reached 1,608 students, 3,337 teachers, and more than 14,000 families and other members of the general public. We provided programming to six different school districts, and partnered with local Columbus community organizations such as The Center of Science and Industry (COSI) and Franklin Park Conservatory. We organized teacher workshops, and gave annual presentations at the Science Education Council of Ohio&rsquo;s (SECO) Science Symposium and the Central Ohio Education Service Center. The West Campus Science and Technology Festival (WestFest) has become an annual event organized by ABRC in conjunction with three other centers at OSU featuring scientific research and innovations in technology across campus and throughout the community.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 05/29/2020<br>      Modified by: David&nbsp;E&nbsp;Somers</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ This grant funds the core mission of the Arabidopsis Biological Resource Center (ABRC) to acquire, maintain and distribute resources of the model plant Arabidopsis thaliana for use in research and education. Arabidopsis was the first plant genome to be completely sequenced and is extensively used in research and education. Many resources have been generated through collaborative research funded by NSF and other agencies and it is important to the Arabidopsis community to preserve these resources and make them widely available.  The ABRC collection contains almost 540,000 seed stocks and 450,000 non-seed stocks. Most of the seed stocks acquired during the granting period were Arabidopsis mutants that can be used to investigate gene function. Other members of the Brassica family, a number of which were used to generate full genome sequence, were also added to the collection. Of the non-seed stocks acquired during the granting period, many are resources for molecular research, including cloned Arabidopsis genes and multi-functional vectors. Collections of resources for K-12 and college education developed by researchers and educators were also acquired. All new stocks added to the collection enter ABRC’s quality control pipeline to verify germination and stock identity. Stocks reported to be incorrect and stocks grown at ABRC are also subjected to quality control testing.  ABRC has shipped over 500,000 samples to researchers in 67 countries during the granting period. We have shipped resources to 87 K-12 Educational institutions around the world. Education kits have been shipped to 49 states within the USA and to 19 other countries. Resources for K-12 education are provided free of charge. Other users of ABRC’s resources pay a small fee to offset the costs of stock maintenance and distribution. The payment rate in recent years has been close to 99%. The NSF contribution to our operating budget is approximately 20%, while user fees represent approximately 60% of the total budget and the remaining support is provided by the university. Demand for stocks has been relatively stable throughout the granting period and might be expected to be sustained based on distribution for the first three months of 2020. However, towards the end of this period we have seen a significant drop in orders as a result of the COVID-19 pandemic which will impact orders and income for 2020 and potentially future years.  In 2019 ABRC developed and launched a state-of-the-art database and web based ordering tool for Arabidopsis and other plant resources. This tool allows easy access to stock data through a web interface and allows for continued collaboration and exchange of data with other Arabidopsis data providers. Google analytics data shows that the site is widely used with approximately 2,000 users per week from 117 countries. The top three countries are the United States, which represents 30% of users, China (20%), and Japan (10%). The remaining countries represent less than 5% each. We share news about ABRC’s activities through the news and events section of our website and via the ABRC Twitter feed @ABRC_News (614 followers). Newly released stocks are listed on the researcher home page of the web site. We also attend annual meetings such as the International Conference on Arabidopsis Research (ICAR), Plant Biology, and the Plant Animal Genome (PAG) meetings, on a regular basis.  ABRC continues to reach out to a larger and more diverse audience through participation in community events, partnerships with community organizations and programming at local schools. During the granting period, ABRC reached 1,608 students, 3,337 teachers, and more than 14,000 families and other members of the general public. We provided programming to six different school districts, and partnered with local Columbus community organizations such as The Center of Science and Industry (COSI) and Franklin Park Conservatory. We organized teacher workshops, and gave annual presentations at the Science Education Council of Ohio’s (SECO) Science Symposium and the Central Ohio Education Service Center. The West Campus Science and Technology Festival (WestFest) has become an annual event organized by ABRC in conjunction with three other centers at OSU featuring scientific research and innovations in technology across campus and throughout the community.                Last Modified: 05/29/2020       Submitted by: David E Somers]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
