<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Capacity building: Understanding American Indian, Alaska Native, and Native Hawaiian student outcomes in the STEM education research literature</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>04/01/2016</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>03/31/2020</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>89699.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>89699</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>11060000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>EHR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>HRD</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Human Resource Development</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Jessie Dearo</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>jdearo@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032925350</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This project will result in a literature review of studies of American Indian, Alaskan Native, and Native Hawaiian and STEM education and learning as well as studies that include Indigenous populations as part of a larger underrepresented racial and ethnic minority group.  The ultimate educational significance of this project is to identify practical strategies to address the extreme dearth of Native Americans in STEM education and careers.  The outcomes of this project will set the stage for future programming to foster the participation of American Indian, Alaskan Native, and Native Hawaiian in STEM education and careers.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;One of the goals of this project is to understand how the STEM experiences and retention of American Indian, Alaskan Native, and Native Hawaiian populations can be best understood within the broader underrepresented minority discussion. To do this, the investigators will conduct a secondary literature review aiming to identify common themes.  This literature review will lead to a workshop of experts in STEM education and Indigenous populations.  The workshop participants will discuss the current state of research, identifying themes and gaps in the research in order to develop an action plan to guide future research as well as provide best practices for American Indian, Alaskan Native, and Native Hawaiian educational organizations like the American Indian Science and Engineering Society (AISES).</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>03/08/2016</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>03/08/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.076</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1561768</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Kathy</FirstName>
<LastName>DeerInWater</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Kathy DeerInWater</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>kdeerinwater@aises.org</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>7205526123</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000703688</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>03/08/2016</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>American Indian Science and Engineering Society (AISES)</Name>
<CityName>ALBUQUERQUE</CityName>
<ZipCode>871096708</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5057651052</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>4263 Montgomery Blvd NE.</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[Suite 200]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New Mexico</StateName>
<StateCode>NM</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NM01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>121394480</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>AMERICAN INDIAN SCIENCE AND ENGINEERING SOCIETY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[American Indian Science and Engineering Society]]></Name>
<CityName>Albuquerque</CityName>
<StateCode>NM</StateCode>
<ZipCode>871064313</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[2305 Renard SE, Suite 200]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New Mexico</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NM01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7980</Code>
<Text>ECR-EHR Core Research</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8212</Code>
<Text>Broaden Particip STEM Resrch</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0416</Code>
<Name>NSF Education &amp; Human Resource</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040106</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2016~89699</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The American Indian Science and Engineering Society (AISES) was awarded a National Science Foundation Education Core Research grant (Award: 1561768), titled <em>Capacity building: understanding American Indian, Alaska Native, and Native Hawaiian student outcomes in the STEM education research literature</em>. The purpose of the literature review is to develop an understanding of the strategies known to improve the educational outcomes of Native students. The scoping literature review focused primarily on the primary and secondary education of Native students to include American Indian, Alaska Native, Native Hawaiian, First Nations, and other Indigenous peoples.</p> <p>The current literature on STEM education for Native learners paints a clear picture of the importance and value of Indigenous ways of knowing and Indigenous science in engaging Native students and learners in STEM. An emphasis on adapting to community contexts, engaging community in development, and connecting to community benefits are all important fixtures of culturally relevant STEM education. Place-based and land-based education strategies are also prominent in the literature as a means for increasing engagement in STEM, particularly in the fields of environmental science and geoscience. Finally, storywork serves as a compelling way teach Indigenous knowledge as it is in and of itself an Indigenous way of knowing. Overall, the literature does support the notion that to improve the educational success of Native students and learners, STEM instruction must at least include, if not center, Indigenous ways of knowing and Indigenous science.</p> <p>The literature and outcomes from an AISES led convening of Indigenous STEM education researchers show the possibility for Indigenous science and Western science to work in concert rather than in conflict, with educational settings striving to support a multicultural lens rather than one of universalism and dominance. It is this area that AISES can work to promote and support the meaningful inclusion of Indigenous science as equal to and essential in providing comprehensive STEM education. Furthermore, this asset-based approach, emphasizing the value and contributions of Native people, communities, and cultures, may be developed in the literature but in mainstream society and education systems this is not the case. AISES seeks to learn from the literature, particularly that of Indigenous scholars, to improve the development and implementation of its K-12, STEM education programming. Incorporating the evidence-based strategies detailed in this literature review will position AISES and other organizations to have an even more meaningful and impactful presence in the field of STEM education for Native students and learners. &nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 08/29/2020<br>      Modified by: Kathy&nbsp;Deerinwater</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The American Indian Science and Engineering Society (AISES) was awarded a National Science Foundation Education Core Research grant (Award: 1561768), titled Capacity building: understanding American Indian, Alaska Native, and Native Hawaiian student outcomes in the STEM education research literature. The purpose of the literature review is to develop an understanding of the strategies known to improve the educational outcomes of Native students. The scoping literature review focused primarily on the primary and secondary education of Native students to include American Indian, Alaska Native, Native Hawaiian, First Nations, and other Indigenous peoples.  The current literature on STEM education for Native learners paints a clear picture of the importance and value of Indigenous ways of knowing and Indigenous science in engaging Native students and learners in STEM. An emphasis on adapting to community contexts, engaging community in development, and connecting to community benefits are all important fixtures of culturally relevant STEM education. Place-based and land-based education strategies are also prominent in the literature as a means for increasing engagement in STEM, particularly in the fields of environmental science and geoscience. Finally, storywork serves as a compelling way teach Indigenous knowledge as it is in and of itself an Indigenous way of knowing. Overall, the literature does support the notion that to improve the educational success of Native students and learners, STEM instruction must at least include, if not center, Indigenous ways of knowing and Indigenous science.  The literature and outcomes from an AISES led convening of Indigenous STEM education researchers show the possibility for Indigenous science and Western science to work in concert rather than in conflict, with educational settings striving to support a multicultural lens rather than one of universalism and dominance. It is this area that AISES can work to promote and support the meaningful inclusion of Indigenous science as equal to and essential in providing comprehensive STEM education. Furthermore, this asset-based approach, emphasizing the value and contributions of Native people, communities, and cultures, may be developed in the literature but in mainstream society and education systems this is not the case. AISES seeks to learn from the literature, particularly that of Indigenous scholars, to improve the development and implementation of its K-12, STEM education programming. Incorporating the evidence-based strategies detailed in this literature review will position AISES and other organizations to have an even more meaningful and impactful presence in the field of STEM education for Native students and learners.            Last Modified: 08/29/2020       Submitted by: Kathy Deerinwater]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
