<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Trace element analysis of ochre for modern and prehistoric pigment source use patterns</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>03/15/2016</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>10/31/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>45241.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>45241</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>04040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>SBE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>BCS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Behavioral and Cognitive Sci</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Rebecca Ferrell</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>rferrell@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927850</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Dependence on symbolism to communicate information and mark identities is an essential attribute of modern humans. The use of red and yellow ochre pigments for symbolic purposes is among the most widespread and persistent of human cultural behaviors. However, the study of archaeological ochre has been hindered by ambiguity over how to interpret this iron-based pigment in the absence of obvious symbolic applications such as cave or rock art. This project combines archaeological, geological, and ethnographic methods to investigate prehistoric through modern use of ochre pigments. The investigators have already conducted interviews with the Maasai and Samburu peoples of Kenya, many of whom still use ochre in their daily lives, and identified outcrops of ochre minerals that these groups exploit for symbolic and functional purposes. Geochemical techniques proven to be effective at telling apart ochre from different sources will be used to analyze samples collected from ochre deposits, and to match them to paint samples from rock art sites and ochre artifacts from archaeological sites in the region. This project will refine minimally destructive methods that can be used to analyze the composition of ochre and other iron-containing materials for anthropological, geological, materials science, and forensic applications. Improving techniques for determining the geographic and geologic origin of ochre pigments and related materials has significant implications for identifying looted heritage items and forgeries. The project will also provide opportunities for public science education via museum outreach, international collaborations, and mentoring in the STEM sciences for underrepresented minority students. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Recent discoveries of ochre pigments from Stone Age archaeological sites have shed light on the great temporal depth of human symbolic behavior. Our understanding of the evolutionary significance and potentially the meaning of ancient symbolism using pigments has been enhanced by novel geochemical techniques for provenance studies of ochre, particularly minimally destructive trace element fingerprinting by Inductively Coupled Plasma - Mass Spectrometry. The project builds on improvements in this method over the last decade by creating a database of trace element and stable isotope (strontium, lead, and iron) fingerprints for ochre sources currently or recently used by inhabitants of the Kenya Rift Valley. The Maasai and Samburu are among the few remaining peoples in East Africa with active rock art and ochre self-adornment traditions. They present the best opportunity for studying how modern humans interact with their geologic environment for symbolic purposes. Once completed, the source database will be used to determine the geologic provenance of ochre artifacts and rock art paints of Stone Age through recent origin that were sampled during field and museum research. This will allow for investigation of hypotheses about symbolically mediated versus least-cost (nearest source) models of mineral deposit exploitation, transport and trade of ochre pigments, and preferential use of specific pigment colors. In addition, the source fingerprint database will be made freely available online for other scientists to use in their own research upon completion of the project.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>03/10/2016</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>03/10/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.075</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1561176</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Stanley</FirstName>
<LastName>Ambrose</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>H</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Stanley H Ambrose</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>Ambrose@illinois.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2172443504</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000101602</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>03/10/2016</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Andrew</FirstName>
<LastName>Zipkin</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>M</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Andrew M Zipkin</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>andrew.zipkin@asu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5169874183</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000683102</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>03/10/2016</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign</Name>
<CityName>Champaign</CityName>
<ZipCode>618207406</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2173332187</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1901 South First Street</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[Suite A]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Illinois</StateName>
<StateCode>IL</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>13</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>IL13</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>041544081</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF ILLINOIS</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>041544081</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>IL</StateCode>
<ZipCode>618207473</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Illinois</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>13</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>IL13</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1391</Code>
<Text>Archaeology</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1391</Code>
<Text>ARCHAEOLOGY</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8819</Code>
<Text>Forensic Science</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9179</Code>
<Text>GRADUATE INVOLVEMENT</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>SMET</Code>
<Text>SCIENCE, MATH, ENG &amp; TECH EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0116</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2016~45241</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>This project sought to develop and apply chemical methods for determining the geological sources of iron-containing mineral pigments (ochres) found in archaeological sites and other cultural contexts in Kenya.&nbsp; The use of ochres in art work, self-adornment, and functional applications is a global human behavioral phenomenon, recognizable in the archaeological record from over 300,000 years ago to the present.&nbsp; Our research focused on Kenya because the record of ochre pigment use here spans the earliest human modified ochre to its current use in traditional societies. &nbsp;Natural sources of ochre are widespread in Kenya and are often associated with discrete volcanic or other geologic features. The Kenya Rift Valley is thus an ideal study area for refining ochre provenance methods and documenting cultural practices involving ochre.</p> <p>&nbsp;The project described here focused on characterization of the elemental composition of every ochre source that we identified in Kenya since 2010 to construct a geochemical reference database that archaeologists, anthropologists, cultural heritage professionals and geologists can use to assign culturally modified ochre to geological sources. Our reference dataset encompasses over 40 individual deposits of ochre which can be combined based on spatial association, chemical similarity, or both, allowing for finer or coarser scales of analysis.&nbsp; Our chemical characterization adapted a processing method widely used in analytical chemistry, lithium borate fusion, for use with ochres.&nbsp; This allowed us to transform heterogeneous ochres into homogeneous glass samples that are stable for long-term repeated analysis.&nbsp; Samples processed this way were characterized for 41 chemical elements using Laser Ablation-Inductively Coupled Plasma-Mass Spectrometry.&nbsp; Compared to other compositional analysis methods, this approach is fast, relatively inexpensive, and permits multiple minimally destructive replicate analyses. Quality control tests conducted using standard reference materials identified 24 chemical elements ranging in concentration from major (&gt;1%) to trace (part per million) that were measured within 10% of their certified reference values. All statistical analyses of ochre source and artifact data relied upon some combination of the most reliably measured elements.</p> <p>One major finding from this study was that all ochre sources included in our project could be assigned to one of two major groups, based on the ratio of strontium (Sr) and dysprosium (Dy).&nbsp; One group is restricted to the Central Kenya Perlalkaline Province (CKPP); the second includes all other sources outside of this region. &nbsp;All ochre sources of the CKPP have a Sr/Dy ratio of 0 - 1.24, while all other sources exhibit ratios between 1.56 and 155.71. This finding allows researchers attempting to source an artifact to rule out roughly one half of all analyzed ochre sources using a simple bivariate plot of two elements without relying on advanced statistical techniques.&nbsp; Ruling out as many sources as possible in the first stage of defining source composition groups is critical to effectively applying multivariate statistical techniques to refine artifact provenience to the scale of a specific geologic deposit.&nbsp;</p> <p>Two artifact sourcing cases studies undertaken as part of this project yielded notable results, and data analysis of cultural ochres from four additional archaeological sites is ongoing at this time.&nbsp; Two ochre samples from the Neolithic cremation burial site of Njoro River Cave, dating to ~1000 BC, were identified as not being derived from any of the nearby (25-30 km) red ochre sources of the CKPP currently used by the Maasai.&nbsp; One sample was unambiguously assigned to a source ~100 km south. These findings suggested a strong symbolic motivation to transport ochre over long distances rather than more efficiently exploiting nearby sources.&nbsp; In a second example, we sourced three ochre artifacts from the Later Stone Age site Ol Tepesi Rockshelter on the flanks of Mt. Eburru to two separate sources on Eburru itself, both roughly 12 km from the site.&nbsp; This further highlights the level of spatial resolution made possible by our approach, particularly considering that our reference dataset includes eight sources from the Eburru volcano.</p> <p>This project had impacts beyond the scope of the narrowly defined research program.&nbsp; First, NSF support made it possible to hire two undergraduate laboratory assistants who gained experience in geochemical analysis and archaeometric interpretation, and who have since graduated and gone on to careers as professional chemists.&nbsp; The methods developed as part of this project provide a basic standard operating procedure which other scientists may use verbatim or adopt to the needs of their own projects, improving access to ochre sourcing technology and helping to standardize methods across studies.&nbsp; The Kenya ochre reference dataset will be permanently hosted on The Digital Archaeological Record website for use by archaeologists seeking to source ochre or by anyone interested in exploring the geochemical diversity of the Kenya Rift.&nbsp; Finally, the reference dataset and pending publication of our methods will make it easier for cultural heritage protection professionals to identify the origin of ochre pigment-containing items from Kenya if provenance is in question.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 02/28/2018<br>      Modified by: Andrew&nbsp;M&nbsp;Zipkin</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Images (<span id="selectedPhoto0">1</span> of <span class="totalNumber"></span>)           </div> <div class="galControls" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1561176/1561176_10414130_1519847582222_1015_Zipkinetal.2018^JATAM_029--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1561176/1561176_10414130_1519847582222_1015_Zipkinetal.2018^JATAM_029--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Lithium borate fusion methods"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1561176/1561176_10414130_1519847582222_1015_Zipkinetal.2018^JATAM_029--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Lithium borate fusion methods"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Summary SOP for LiBo fusion processing of ochre</div> <div class="imageCredit">AM Zipkin</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Andrew&nbsp;M&nbsp;Zipkin</div> <div class="imageTitle">Lithium borate fusion methods</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1561176/1561176_10414130_1519847390945_SrvsDy,KenyaOchreSamples--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1561176/1561176_10414130_1519847390945_SrvsDy,KenyaOchreSamples--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Sr vs Dy Plot of Kenya Ochre Samples"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1561176/1561176_10414130_1519847390945_SrvsDy,KenyaOchreSamples--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Sr vs Dy Plot of Kenya Ochre Samples"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">All analyzed ochre sources in Kenya can be divided into two groups based on their Sr/Dy concentration ratio.</div> <div class="imageCredit">AM Zipkin</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Andrew&nbsp;M&nbsp;Zipkin</div> <div class="imageTitle">Sr vs Dy Plot of Kenya Ochre Samples</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ This project sought to develop and apply chemical methods for determining the geological sources of iron-containing mineral pigments (ochres) found in archaeological sites and other cultural contexts in Kenya.  The use of ochres in art work, self-adornment, and functional applications is a global human behavioral phenomenon, recognizable in the archaeological record from over 300,000 years ago to the present.  Our research focused on Kenya because the record of ochre pigment use here spans the earliest human modified ochre to its current use in traditional societies.  Natural sources of ochre are widespread in Kenya and are often associated with discrete volcanic or other geologic features. The Kenya Rift Valley is thus an ideal study area for refining ochre provenance methods and documenting cultural practices involving ochre.   The project described here focused on characterization of the elemental composition of every ochre source that we identified in Kenya since 2010 to construct a geochemical reference database that archaeologists, anthropologists, cultural heritage professionals and geologists can use to assign culturally modified ochre to geological sources. Our reference dataset encompasses over 40 individual deposits of ochre which can be combined based on spatial association, chemical similarity, or both, allowing for finer or coarser scales of analysis.  Our chemical characterization adapted a processing method widely used in analytical chemistry, lithium borate fusion, for use with ochres.  This allowed us to transform heterogeneous ochres into homogeneous glass samples that are stable for long-term repeated analysis.  Samples processed this way were characterized for 41 chemical elements using Laser Ablation-Inductively Coupled Plasma-Mass Spectrometry.  Compared to other compositional analysis methods, this approach is fast, relatively inexpensive, and permits multiple minimally destructive replicate analyses. Quality control tests conducted using standard reference materials identified 24 chemical elements ranging in concentration from major (&gt;1%) to trace (part per million) that were measured within 10% of their certified reference values. All statistical analyses of ochre source and artifact data relied upon some combination of the most reliably measured elements.  One major finding from this study was that all ochre sources included in our project could be assigned to one of two major groups, based on the ratio of strontium (Sr) and dysprosium (Dy).  One group is restricted to the Central Kenya Perlalkaline Province (CKPP); the second includes all other sources outside of this region.  All ochre sources of the CKPP have a Sr/Dy ratio of 0 - 1.24, while all other sources exhibit ratios between 1.56 and 155.71. This finding allows researchers attempting to source an artifact to rule out roughly one half of all analyzed ochre sources using a simple bivariate plot of two elements without relying on advanced statistical techniques.  Ruling out as many sources as possible in the first stage of defining source composition groups is critical to effectively applying multivariate statistical techniques to refine artifact provenience to the scale of a specific geologic deposit.   Two artifact sourcing cases studies undertaken as part of this project yielded notable results, and data analysis of cultural ochres from four additional archaeological sites is ongoing at this time.  Two ochre samples from the Neolithic cremation burial site of Njoro River Cave, dating to ~1000 BC, were identified as not being derived from any of the nearby (25-30 km) red ochre sources of the CKPP currently used by the Maasai.  One sample was unambiguously assigned to a source ~100 km south. These findings suggested a strong symbolic motivation to transport ochre over long distances rather than more efficiently exploiting nearby sources.  In a second example, we sourced three ochre artifacts from the Later Stone Age site Ol Tepesi Rockshelter on the flanks of Mt. Eburru to two separate sources on Eburru itself, both roughly 12 km from the site.  This further highlights the level of spatial resolution made possible by our approach, particularly considering that our reference dataset includes eight sources from the Eburru volcano.  This project had impacts beyond the scope of the narrowly defined research program.  First, NSF support made it possible to hire two undergraduate laboratory assistants who gained experience in geochemical analysis and archaeometric interpretation, and who have since graduated and gone on to careers as professional chemists.  The methods developed as part of this project provide a basic standard operating procedure which other scientists may use verbatim or adopt to the needs of their own projects, improving access to ochre sourcing technology and helping to standardize methods across studies.  The Kenya ochre reference dataset will be permanently hosted on The Digital Archaeological Record website for use by archaeologists seeking to source ochre or by anyone interested in exploring the geochemical diversity of the Kenya Rift.  Finally, the reference dataset and pending publication of our methods will make it easier for cultural heritage protection professionals to identify the origin of ochre pigment-containing items from Kenya if provenance is in question.             Last Modified: 02/28/2018       Submitted by: Andrew M Zipkin]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
