<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Collaborative Research: Using Data Mining and Observation to derive an enhanced theory of SRL in Science learning environments</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2016</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2020</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>629630.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>629630</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>11040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>EHR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DUE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Undergraduate Education</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Dawn Rickey</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>drickey@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924674</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This project aims to enhance theory and measurement of students' self-regulated learning (SRL) processes during science learning. SRL refers to learning that is guided by metacognition (thinking about one's thinking), strategic action (planning, monitoring, and evaluating personal progress against a standard), and motivation to learn. The project will accomplish this by developing a technology-based framework which leverages human expert judgment and machine learning methods to identify key moments during SRL and analyze these moments in depth. The project uses an existing science learning environment, Betty's Brain, that combines learning-by-modeling with critical thinking and problem solving skills to teach complex science topics. The environment is designed to have the student teach Betty science topics using concept maps (the critical elements of the science) and reading materials provided by the environment. A critical component of this project is to determine when a student using the system needs help. Using SRL as a basis, the additions to Betty's brain will identify key points in the SRL processes of metacognition, strategic action, and motivation. Some of these points can be determined automatically in recognizing key points while others require human intervention to recognize key points and then to determine what actions should be taken to enable the student. This information will be recorded and the experiences then are used   to update the automatic identification of key points.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The project's main intellectual merit is in integrating the power of data mining to rapidly sift through large amounts of data to find key inflection or change points in student reasoning and strategies, with the power of human beings to deeply understand other humans' SRL processes. This measurement framework, with the accompanying detectors of inflection points in students' SRL in online learning, has the potential to transform science learning and teaching in K-12 settings by providing insights into how SRL unfolds during learning through the interactions between affect, engagement, cognition and metacognition. Those insights will be used to extend an existing theory of SRL, increasing its richness, specificity, and predictive power. Self-regulated learning is important to student success, both in K-12 education and during life-long learning afterwards. Better understanding of SRL processes will support the development of computer-based science learning environments, such as Betty's Brain, with the capability to better support students' learning of SRL skills and strategies in science classrooms. By studying these issues within the diverse population of urban students who currently use Betty's Brain, success of the project will increase the  relevance of SRL to the full diversity of America's learners. The project's software will be available through the portal www.teachableagents.org.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/17/2016</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/17/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.076</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1561676</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Gautam</FirstName>
<LastName>Biswas</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Gautam Biswas</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>gautam.biswas@vanderbilt.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6153436204</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000110341</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/17/2016</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Vanderbilt University</Name>
<CityName>Nashville</CityName>
<ZipCode>372350002</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6153222631</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>Sponsored Programs Administratio</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[PMB 407749 2301 Vanderbilt Place]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Tennessee</StateName>
<StateCode>TN</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>TN05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>965717143</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>VANDERBILT UNIVERSITY, THE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>004413456</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Vanderbilt University]]></Name>
<CityName>Nashville</CityName>
<StateCode>TN</StateCode>
<ZipCode>372122809</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[1400 18th Avenue South]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Tennessee</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>TN05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7980</Code>
<Text>ECR-EHR Core Research</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8244</Code>
<Text>EHR CL Opportunities (NSF 14-302)</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8817</Code>
<Text>STEM Learning &amp; Learning Environments</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0416</Code>
<Name>NSF Education &amp; Human Resource</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040106</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2016~629630</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The focus of this project, jointly conducted by researchers from the University of Illinois, Pennsylvania and Vanderbilt University, has been to enhance theory and measurement of students&rsquo; self-regulated learning (SRL) processes during science learning in a technology-based framework. This framework leverages human expert judgment and machine learning methods to identify key events that define students&rsquo; SRL processes and analyze these moments in depth. We will study these issues in the context of Betty&rsquo;s Brain, an open-ended science learning environment that combines learning-by-modeling with critical thinking and problem solving skills to teach complex science topics.</p> <p>The novel measurement framework identifies key inflection points in the SRL processes driving students&rsquo; cognition, metacognition and affect, and informs researchers about these inflection points in real-time using an app that we have developed called Quick Red Fox (QRF) that communicates with the Betty&rsquo;s Brain server. This app allows researchers to conduct observations and interviews with the student right at the critical moments when the change is occurring. Using a combination of data collected in log files and the human observations, we have developed automated detectors of students&rsquo; affect using machine learning methods. This combined with other analyzes of students&rsquo; activity logs to understand their cognitive and metacognitive behaviors has provided us with a framework to link students&rsquo; SRL behaviors and their performance (i.e., their ability to construct a correct causal map of a scientific process) in the Betty's Brain environment. Our overall goal has been to refine and extend an existing theory of SRL, i.e., Winne&rsquo;s COPES framework, to increase its specificity and predictive power.</p> <p>We have run a number of studies in middle school classrooms in middle Tennessee to collect data for developing our automated detectors, and to demonstrate the effectiveness of our approach. More recently, we have analyzed students&rsquo; confusion and frustration as they work on their causal map building tasks in Betty&rsquo;s Brain. Our studies demonstrate differences in affect transitions between high and low performing students, and that a feeling of frustration often results in high performers putting in more effort to overcome their difficulties, whereas a feeling of frustration often leads to periods of disengagement for low performers. We have used our results to develop an adaptive scaffolding framework to help learners overcome their difficulties and succeed in their map building tasks.&nbsp; Current analyses of the effects of feedback have produced mixed results with differences in the effectiveness of the feedback among high and low performers. Overall, the project has produced interesting results, and has generated a number of journal and conference publications.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 01/12/2021<br>      Modified by: Gautam&nbsp;Biswas</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The focus of this project, jointly conducted by researchers from the University of Illinois, Pennsylvania and Vanderbilt University, has been to enhance theory and measurement of students’ self-regulated learning (SRL) processes during science learning in a technology-based framework. This framework leverages human expert judgment and machine learning methods to identify key events that define students’ SRL processes and analyze these moments in depth. We will study these issues in the context of Betty’s Brain, an open-ended science learning environment that combines learning-by-modeling with critical thinking and problem solving skills to teach complex science topics.  The novel measurement framework identifies key inflection points in the SRL processes driving students’ cognition, metacognition and affect, and informs researchers about these inflection points in real-time using an app that we have developed called Quick Red Fox (QRF) that communicates with the Betty’s Brain server. This app allows researchers to conduct observations and interviews with the student right at the critical moments when the change is occurring. Using a combination of data collected in log files and the human observations, we have developed automated detectors of students’ affect using machine learning methods. This combined with other analyzes of students’ activity logs to understand their cognitive and metacognitive behaviors has provided us with a framework to link students’ SRL behaviors and their performance (i.e., their ability to construct a correct causal map of a scientific process) in the Betty's Brain environment. Our overall goal has been to refine and extend an existing theory of SRL, i.e., Winne’s COPES framework, to increase its specificity and predictive power.  We have run a number of studies in middle school classrooms in middle Tennessee to collect data for developing our automated detectors, and to demonstrate the effectiveness of our approach. More recently, we have analyzed students’ confusion and frustration as they work on their causal map building tasks in Betty’s Brain. Our studies demonstrate differences in affect transitions between high and low performing students, and that a feeling of frustration often results in high performers putting in more effort to overcome their difficulties, whereas a feeling of frustration often leads to periods of disengagement for low performers. We have used our results to develop an adaptive scaffolding framework to help learners overcome their difficulties and succeed in their map building tasks.  Current analyses of the effects of feedback have produced mixed results with differences in the effectiveness of the feedback among high and low performers. Overall, the project has produced interesting results, and has generated a number of journal and conference publications.          Last Modified: 01/12/2021       Submitted by: Gautam Biswas]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
