<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Control of Screw Extruder Delay/Partial Differential Equation (PDE) Dynamics for 3D Printing</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2016</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>01/31/2021</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>326571.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>438134</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CMMI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Civil, Mechanical, &amp; Manufact Inn</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Robert Landers</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>rlanders@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922652</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Motivated by both the potential for a technological, economic, and social impact of additive manufacturing, the project is dedicated to the design of controllers to remove some of the key bottlenecks to achieving high speed and product quality in 3D printing. The project will build control and modeling methodologies that are both of high research value and are suitable for industrial use, going after improvements in the build speed and part quality. Compared to the standard Fused Deposition Modeling and Syringe Based extrusion processes, the novel configuration of the Screw Extruder process that we address may allow continuous feeding, speed up production, and upgrade the mixing capabilities, while efficiently reducing the thermal degradation of the melt and the cost for such processes. The PI has supervised two dozen students from underrepresented groups on past projects, such as women, Hispanics, and African-Americans, and the present project will involve specific individuals from underserved communities as advisees and collaborators. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Partial Differential Equation (PDE) models of mass and thermal flows in the Screw Extruder will be used to design accurate and robust controllers, to replace the existing control methods for 3D printing, which are typically constructed using conservative black-box or lumped models, which reduces their performance for a large range of materials. Moreover, control of the melt thermal behavior that impacts viscosity evolution and the solidification process will be addressed. The control design will be based on infinite-dimensional models of screw extruders, including a bi-zone model consisting of PDEs coupled through a moving interface described by an ordinary differential equation. Novel control design techniques from the PI's infinite-dimensional backstepping toolkit will be developed for this purpose. Implementation of the designed controller will be performed on an experimental platform developed in the PI's group. The project will provide advancements to the general area of control of PDEs that are coupled through a moving interface, which, besides extruders, arise in multi-phase flows, crystal growth, freeze-drying, and distillation processes.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/29/2016</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/04/2020</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1562366</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Miroslav</FirstName>
<LastName>Krstic</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Miroslav Krstic</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>krstic@ucsd.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>8588221374</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000487444</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/29/2016</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of California-San Diego</Name>
<CityName>La Jolla</CityName>
<ZipCode>920930934</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>8585344896</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>Office of Contract &amp; Grant Admin</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[9500 Gilman Drive, 0934]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>49</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CA49</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>804355790</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF CALIFORNIA, SAN DIEGO</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>071549000</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of California-San Diego]]></Name>
<CityName>La Jolla</CityName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>920930411</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[9500 Gilman Drive, #0411]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>49</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CA49</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1385</Code>
<Text>SSA-Special Studies &amp; Analysis</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1642</Code>
<Text>Special Initiatives</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7569</Code>
<Text>Dynamics, Control and System D</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>019Z</Code>
<Text>Grad Prep APG:Enhan. Experience</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>030E</Code>
<Text>CONTROL SYSTEMS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>034E</Code>
<Text>Dynamical systems</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>091Z</Code>
<Text>Data Initiatives</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8024</Code>
<Text>Complex Systems</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0116</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0118</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0120</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2016~326571</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2018~46249</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2020~65314</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The project focuses on the control of the physics of melting and re-solidification processes in additive manufacturing, with the objective of tightly regulating the deposition/printing of molten material, both by convection using a "screw extruder" framework, and in the laser sintering framework. With multiple models employed in the project, from models involving a state-dependent delay, with the state being the phase interface position and the delay being due to transport through the extruder, to more sophisticated ?Stefan problem? models, which model also the temperature dynamics (in addition to convection) in the extruder, the project has made significant advances in the development of control methodology for heretofore unexplored modeling of the phase change physics through PDEs with moving boundaries governed by ODEs.&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>The project's early results were on the high-performance control of the solid-liquid interface position in screw extruders. Such dynamics are modeled by a first-order hyperbolic PDE, on an interval with a moving boundary, and cascading into a nonlinear ODE. A predictor feedback design prevents instability that would be caused by a rapidly-varying delay. Using the PDE backstepping approach, the design compensates the varying delay and achieves quick regulation.&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>The project's later results incorporated also the dynamics of thermal conduction in the regulation of the liquid-solid interface, in both screw extruder-bases and laser sintering-based 3D printing. With the thermal conduction dominated by diffusion, control designs were developed for Stefan-type PDE-ODE systems, starting from single-phase non-convective models and advancing to two-phase and diffusion-advection models. Even thermal radiation through the melt in laser sintering, resulting in the control input appearing both on the boundary and throughout the domain (i.e., "non-locally," by PDE control terminology), was considered and a design suitable for such phenomena, which are typical of metals, was developed.&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>An equal amount of attention as to control was also dedicated to the design of observers of the unmeasured temperature state away from the solid-liquid interface. In addition to additive manufacturing, such estimators of unmeasured internal temperatures are important in forecasting the melting of sea ice in the polar regions of the Earth.&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>The project has gone from the control designs for the basic physical phenomena to the control design in the presence of engineering challenges in the implementation of the controllers: delays, sampled-data implementation, uncertainty in the heat conduction coefficient of the material used in additive manufacturing, and heat loss at the boundaries.&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>The primary theoretical technique, which was employed on the project for the controller and observer design, and advanced through the project, is PDE backstepping. The other important methodology used in the project is the input-to-state stability (ISS) for PDEs. Both backstepping and ISS for PDEs are techniques that the PI has pioneered in prior work supported by the NSF and used by many researchers nationwide and worldwide.&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>Finally, in addition to the theoretical designs, addressing the basic physics and implementation challenges, the control was experimentally demonstrated on a test rig in which the phase-changing material is paraffin, whose melting temperature is not much above the room temperature, allowing for an easy implementation in a benchtop university laboratory setting.&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>Of the two PhD students and one postdoc supported on the project, two are from the most underrepresented group in science and engineering. One of them has secured a faculty position at a prestigious university and even already won an NSF CAREER Award.&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>Seventeen papers in the most prestigious journals in the control field have been published, as well as two books. The premier product of the project is the book&nbsp;S. Koga and M. Krstic,&nbsp;<em>Materials Phase Change PDE Control and Estimation: From Additive Manufacturing to Polar Ice</em>, Birkhauser, 2020.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>One of the results published on the project has won the prestigious O. Hugo Schuck Best Paper Award at the American Control Conference.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 02/08/2021<br>      Modified by: Miroslav&nbsp;Krstic</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The project focuses on the control of the physics of melting and re-solidification processes in additive manufacturing, with the objective of tightly regulating the deposition/printing of molten material, both by convection using a "screw extruder" framework, and in the laser sintering framework. With multiple models employed in the project, from models involving a state-dependent delay, with the state being the phase interface position and the delay being due to transport through the extruder, to more sophisticated ?Stefan problem? models, which model also the temperature dynamics (in addition to convection) in the extruder, the project has made significant advances in the development of control methodology for heretofore unexplored modeling of the phase change physics through PDEs with moving boundaries governed by ODEs.      The project's early results were on the high-performance control of the solid-liquid interface position in screw extruders. Such dynamics are modeled by a first-order hyperbolic PDE, on an interval with a moving boundary, and cascading into a nonlinear ODE. A predictor feedback design prevents instability that would be caused by a rapidly-varying delay. Using the PDE backstepping approach, the design compensates the varying delay and achieves quick regulation.      The project's later results incorporated also the dynamics of thermal conduction in the regulation of the liquid-solid interface, in both screw extruder-bases and laser sintering-based 3D printing. With the thermal conduction dominated by diffusion, control designs were developed for Stefan-type PDE-ODE systems, starting from single-phase non-convective models and advancing to two-phase and diffusion-advection models. Even thermal radiation through the melt in laser sintering, resulting in the control input appearing both on the boundary and throughout the domain (i.e., "non-locally," by PDE control terminology), was considered and a design suitable for such phenomena, which are typical of metals, was developed.      An equal amount of attention as to control was also dedicated to the design of observers of the unmeasured temperature state away from the solid-liquid interface. In addition to additive manufacturing, such estimators of unmeasured internal temperatures are important in forecasting the melting of sea ice in the polar regions of the Earth.      The project has gone from the control designs for the basic physical phenomena to the control design in the presence of engineering challenges in the implementation of the controllers: delays, sampled-data implementation, uncertainty in the heat conduction coefficient of the material used in additive manufacturing, and heat loss at the boundaries.      The primary theoretical technique, which was employed on the project for the controller and observer design, and advanced through the project, is PDE backstepping. The other important methodology used in the project is the input-to-state stability (ISS) for PDEs. Both backstepping and ISS for PDEs are techniques that the PI has pioneered in prior work supported by the NSF and used by many researchers nationwide and worldwide.      Finally, in addition to the theoretical designs, addressing the basic physics and implementation challenges, the control was experimentally demonstrated on a test rig in which the phase-changing material is paraffin, whose melting temperature is not much above the room temperature, allowing for an easy implementation in a benchtop university laboratory setting.      Of the two PhD students and one postdoc supported on the project, two are from the most underrepresented group in science and engineering. One of them has secured a faculty position at a prestigious university and even already won an NSF CAREER Award.      Seventeen papers in the most prestigious journals in the control field have been published, as well as two books. The premier product of the project is the book S. Koga and M. Krstic, Materials Phase Change PDE Control and Estimation: From Additive Manufacturing to Polar Ice, Birkhauser, 2020.     One of the results published on the project has won the prestigious O. Hugo Schuck Best Paper Award at the American Control Conference.          Last Modified: 02/08/2021       Submitted by: Miroslav Krstic]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
