<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>FRG: Collaborative Research: Floer Homotopy Theory</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2016</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2020</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>365147.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>365147</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DMS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Swatee Naik</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>snaik@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924876</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Topology is the study of those properties of shapes that are unchanged by stretching and bending. Over the years, mathematicians have developed various topological invariants, or in other words, quantities that are associated to shapes and can distinguish between those that have different properties. Homology is a well-known such invariant, which can be associated to any multi-dimensional shape, and which is a quantitative measure of the number of holes in a space. A circle, for instance, has only a one-dimensional hole, whereas the surface of a doughnut has two one-dimensional holes, a meridian and a longitude, that are not filled in by the surface itself, and an additional two-dimensional hole. Floer homology is a more refined invariant that is responsible for some of the most important recent advances in the study of knotted closed loops in space, three-dimensional shapes, and shapes with a geometry known as a symplectic structure that is exhibited by phase spaces in classical mechanics. This project brings together several researchers working in different areas of topology and geometry to study Floer homology. The main goal of the project is the following: To every knot, three-dimensional shape, or symplectic shape, one should associate a different object, called a Floer space or a Floer homotopy type, whose (ordinary) homology is the Floer homology of the initial shape. This has been accomplished so far in a limited number of cases. A general theory of Floer spaces will lead to new advances in several areas. Furthermore, the study of Floer spaces will be based on techniques from a subfield of topology called homotopy theory. This project will create a community of scholars at the interface of these current and extremely research active areas of mathematics.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Floer homology is a fundamental tool in geometry and topology, whose applications range from the Arnold conjecture to the surgery characterization of various knots. Floer homology has also laid the basis for completely unexpected interconnections between algebraic and symplectic geometry in the form of homological mirror symmetry. Floer homotopy theory, an extension to spaces rather than homology groups, has been implemented in a small number of cases, leading to significant applications, for example, the resolution of the triangulation conjecture in high dimensions and work on immersed Lagrangian spheres. Further, the ideas behind Floer homotopy inspired the construction of a Khovanov homotopy type associated to knots in the three-sphere. The main scientific goal of this project is to give a general construction of Floer homotopy. The necessary foundational work will build upon recent advances in multiple areas. These include the conceptual advances in equivariant stable homotopy theory stemming from the resolution of Kervaire invariant one problem, and the development of new approaches to define virtual fundamental classes in Floer theory. The project aims to put the homotopical and homological variants of Floer theory on equal footing. As a consequence, new applications in both symplectic and low-dimensional topology are anticipated, for example: (i) a spectral Fukaya category associated to a symplectic manifold will be constructed; (ii) the Heegaard Floer theory of Ozsvath and Szabo will be used to produce a computable invariant parallel to the celebrated Bauer-Furuta invariant for four-manifolds; (iii) Seiberg-Witten Floer homotopy types will be studied using the tools of equivariant stable homotopy theory; and (iv) the Khovanov homotopy type will be extended to give invariants of knot cobordisms and tangles.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/22/2016</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/22/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1563615</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Ciprian</FirstName>
<LastName>Manolescu</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Ciprian Manolescu</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>cm5@stanford.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6507234157</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000106483</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/22/2016</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Michael</FirstName>
<LastName>Hill</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>A</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Michael A Hill</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>mikehill@math.ucla.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON/>
<NSF_ID>000516206</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/22/2016</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Sucharit</FirstName>
<LastName>Sarkar</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Sucharit Sarkar</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>sucharit@math.ucla.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>3108254048</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000648712</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/22/2016</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of California-Los Angeles</Name>
<CityName>LOS ANGELES</CityName>
<ZipCode>900951406</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>3107940102</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>10889 Wilshire Boulevard</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[Suite 700]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>33</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CA33</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>092530369</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF CALIFORNIA, LOS ANGELES</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>071549000</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of California-Los Angeles]]></Name>
<CityName>Los Angeles</CityName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>900951555</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[520 Portola Plaza, 6921 MSB]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>33</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CA33</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1267</Code>
<Text>TOPOLOGY</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1616</Code>
<Text>FOCUSED RESEARCH GROUPS IN MATH SCIENCES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0116</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2016~365147</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><span>The project studied certain theories in low-dimensional topology. Topology is the study of shapes of spaces, and low-dimensional topology is the study of spaces up to dimension 4. A plethora of recent invariants have been constructed in low-dimensional topology---including many originating in Floer theory---which associate chain complexes to low-dimensional objects; the homologies of these chain complexes are invariants of the underlying objects (that is, they only depend on the "shape" of the topological object, not on any extra data), and these homology groups provide a lot of valuable information about the topological objects being studied.</span><br /><br /><span>This project primarily studied the following specific homology theories: Khovanov homology and knot Floer homology, which are similar-looking, yet different, invariants for knots and links (closed strings inside 3-dimensional spaces).&nbsp; Regarding Khovanov homology, the project extended the theory to certain other 3-dimensional spaces (the theory originally was defined only for the usual 3-dimensional Euclidean space), and proved formulas for certain cobordisms (surfaces inside 4-dimensional objects), including cobordisms in the complex projective plane. The project also studied what the theory limits to when certain large number twists are added to links. The project also constructed stable homotopy refinements (which carry more information) of the homologies for certain variants of the theory, such as quantum annular homology, and infinite torus links. Regarding knot Floer homology, the project constructed a reformulation of a recent theory of tangles (open-ended strings inside 3-dimensional spaces) due to Ozsvath-Szabo in terms of an earlier framework of bordered Floer homology. The project also studied the behavior of knot Floer homology for cobordisms, concentrating on certain properties like naturality and functoriality. The project also obtained various formulas in Floer homology for cobordisms, including non-orientable ones.</span><br /><br /><span>Three postdocs and one graduate student were partially supported by the project, who worked on the research described earlier. In summer of 2017, a summer school and a conference were organized from this grant with around 140 participants. In December 2018, a conference with around 60 participants was organized from this grant.</span></p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 10/27/2020<br>      Modified by: Sucharit&nbsp;Sarkar</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The project studied certain theories in low-dimensional topology. Topology is the study of shapes of spaces, and low-dimensional topology is the study of spaces up to dimension 4. A plethora of recent invariants have been constructed in low-dimensional topology---including many originating in Floer theory---which associate chain complexes to low-dimensional objects; the homologies of these chain complexes are invariants of the underlying objects (that is, they only depend on the "shape" of the topological object, not on any extra data), and these homology groups provide a lot of valuable information about the topological objects being studied.  This project primarily studied the following specific homology theories: Khovanov homology and knot Floer homology, which are similar-looking, yet different, invariants for knots and links (closed strings inside 3-dimensional spaces).  Regarding Khovanov homology, the project extended the theory to certain other 3-dimensional spaces (the theory originally was defined only for the usual 3-dimensional Euclidean space), and proved formulas for certain cobordisms (surfaces inside 4-dimensional objects), including cobordisms in the complex projective plane. The project also studied what the theory limits to when certain large number twists are added to links. The project also constructed stable homotopy refinements (which carry more information) of the homologies for certain variants of the theory, such as quantum annular homology, and infinite torus links. Regarding knot Floer homology, the project constructed a reformulation of a recent theory of tangles (open-ended strings inside 3-dimensional spaces) due to Ozsvath-Szabo in terms of an earlier framework of bordered Floer homology. The project also studied the behavior of knot Floer homology for cobordisms, concentrating on certain properties like naturality and functoriality. The project also obtained various formulas in Floer homology for cobordisms, including non-orientable ones.  Three postdocs and one graduate student were partially supported by the project, who worked on the research described earlier. In summer of 2017, a summer school and a conference were organized from this grant with around 140 participants. In December 2018, a conference with around 60 participants was organized from this grant.       Last Modified: 10/27/2020       Submitted by: Sucharit Sarkar]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
