<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>EAGER: Advancing the future of U.S. seagoing oceanographic research through a Chief Scientist training cruise</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>01/01/2016</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2016</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>106005.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>106005</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>06040100</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>GEO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>OCE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Ocean Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Rose Dufour</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>rdufour@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032928811</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The study of oceanography requires seagoing research for collection of&lt;br/&gt;data and at sea experimentation. However, for first time researchers the planning, organizing,&lt;br/&gt;logistics and paper work involved in a major research cruise, especially one that involves&lt;br/&gt;work in foreign waters (EEZs) can be daunting. Additionally, at sea research involves substantial&lt;br/&gt;additional grant costs attributable to the ship operation. As a consequence, beginning in&lt;br/&gt;2011 the University National Oceanographic Laboratory System (UNOLS) began a program of Chief&lt;br/&gt;Scientist training cruises to introduce prospective early career scientists to the process&lt;br/&gt;of planning, acquiring, effectively utilizing, and reporting on time at sea for multi-disciplinary&lt;br/&gt;research and education. To date there have been 5 successful Chief Scientist training cruises,&lt;br/&gt;with a sixth cruise, focused on Robotic Platforms, scheduled to take place this November.&lt;br/&gt;This proposal would fund a sixth Chief Scientist Training Cruise training cruise to be conducted&lt;br/&gt;aboard the R/V Thomas G Thompson. The training program is modeled on the proven successful&lt;br/&gt;one that have already occurred. This would be the first training cruise conducted using a&lt;br/&gt;Global Class research vessel,&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;With this proposal funds will be used to conduct a general Chief Scientist Training Cruise in 2016.&lt;br/&gt;The training cruise will follow the proven model of previous successful ones and provide a&lt;br/&gt;forum for early career marine scientists to learn how to plan, acquire utilize and report on at sea&lt;br/&gt;research for multidisciplinary research and education. The cruise will utilize the R/V T.G.&lt;br/&gt;Thompson, and it will be the first Chief Scientist training cruise on one of UNOLS? Global Class&lt;br/&gt;research vessels. As such, the ship will be able to accommodate up to 20 trainees. In addition to&lt;br/&gt;instruction on duties and responsibilities of a Chief Scientist, the cruise will offer new&lt;br/&gt;investigators opportunities to test compelling research areas that could be used for the basis of&lt;br/&gt;future proposals. Given the declining number of vessels in the UNOLS fleet and the tight&lt;br/&gt;operations budget, the need to teach early career scientists how to use our limited infrastructure&lt;br/&gt;resources effectively and collaboratively is more important than ever.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>11/17/2015</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>11/17/2015</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.050</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1565461</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Allan</FirstName>
<LastName>Devol</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>H</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Allan H Devol</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>devol@u.washington.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2065431292</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000317046</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>11/17/2015</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Evelyn</FirstName>
<LastName>Lessard</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>J</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Evelyn J Lessard</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>elessard@u.washington.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2065438795</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000113909</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>11/17/2015</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Washington</Name>
<CityName>Seattle</CityName>
<ZipCode>981950001</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2065434043</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>4333 Brooklyn Ave NE</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Washington</StateName>
<StateCode>WA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>WA07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>605799469</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF WASHINGTON</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>042803536</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Washington]]></Name>
<CityName>Seattle</CityName>
<StateCode>WA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>981950001</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[4333 Brooklyn Ave. NE]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Washington</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>WA07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>5411</Code>
<Text>SHIP OPERATIONS</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7916</Code>
<Text>EAGER</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0116</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2016~106005</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The study of oceanography requires seagoing research for collection of data and at sea experimentation. &nbsp;However, for first time researchers the planning, organizing, logistics and paper work involved in a major research cruise, especially one that involves work in foreign waters (EEZs) can be daunting.&nbsp; Additionally, at sea research involves substantial additional grant costs attributable to the ship operation.&nbsp; Consequently, some early career scientists may be reluctant to submit proposals to fund their seagoing research. The main goal of our proposal was to conduct a workshop and training cruise for 20 early-career scientists aboard the R/V Thompson to introduce prospective early career scientists to the process of planning, acquiring, effectively utilizing, and reporting on time at sea for multi-disciplinary research and education. &nbsp;The hope was to demystify the process of ship operations and fulfill the intent of UNOLS (University-National Oceanographic Laboratory System) to improve access to existing and future facilities.&nbsp;&nbsp;<strong>&nbsp;</strong></p> <p>Applicant solicitation was done through the UNOLS website and personal communication.&nbsp; In total there were 44 applications, out of which 21 participants were selected.&nbsp; &nbsp;The training program began with a two day workshop in San Diego aboard the research vessel R/V T.G. Thompson during which the participants were introduced to UNOLS, the ship time request procedure, US State Department foreign clearance application, NSF ship selection and funding, &nbsp;etc.&nbsp;&nbsp;Presenters included the University of Washington professors, UNOLS representatives, NSF program directors, Scripps Institute of Oceanography personnel and the T.G. Thompsons Officers and marine technicians.&nbsp;</p> <p>Prior to the workshop the participants&nbsp; participated in a WEBEX meeting and subsequent&nbsp; e-mail and Skype meeting to plan the actual training cruise that immediately followed the workshop.&nbsp; Final tuning of the plan was done at the end of the second day of the workshop.&nbsp; The at-sea portion of the chief scientist training program began when the ship left the Port of San Diego on the morning of the third day, and continued until the afternoon of the tenth day, after which there was a wrap-up meeting, demobilization and departure of participants. &nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;The Chief Scientist Training program was successfully completed with 21 early-career oceanographers received training and exposure to the role of UNOLS, the process of planning, requesting and obtaining funding for a NSF sponsored research cruise and the responsibilities and duties of a chief scientist.&nbsp; They were also exposed to early career mentoring, training by highly qualified marine technicians while at sea, and they had the opportunity to use or get exposure to state of the art observations and equipment, which should stimulate new ideas for research and science communication with the broader public.</p> <p>All CTD and Bottle data collected during the Chief Scientist Training Cruise has been archived at the NOAA National Centers for Environmental Information (NCEI) data center and can be identified as NCEI Accession Number 0161328. The original data files can be accessed at link,&nbsp;<a href="http://accession.nodc.noaa.gov/0161328/data/0-data" target="_blank">http://accession.nodc.noaa.gov/0161328/data/0-data</a>.&nbsp; General project information is accessable at&nbsp;<a href="http://accession.nodc.noaa.gov/0161328" target="_blank">http://accession.nodc.noaa.gov/0161328</a>.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 07/12/2017<br>      Modified by: Allan&nbsp;H&nbsp;Devol</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The study of oceanography requires seagoing research for collection of data and at sea experimentation.  However, for first time researchers the planning, organizing, logistics and paper work involved in a major research cruise, especially one that involves work in foreign waters (EEZs) can be daunting.  Additionally, at sea research involves substantial additional grant costs attributable to the ship operation.  Consequently, some early career scientists may be reluctant to submit proposals to fund their seagoing research. The main goal of our proposal was to conduct a workshop and training cruise for 20 early-career scientists aboard the R/V Thompson to introduce prospective early career scientists to the process of planning, acquiring, effectively utilizing, and reporting on time at sea for multi-disciplinary research and education.  The hope was to demystify the process of ship operations and fulfill the intent of UNOLS (University-National Oceanographic Laboratory System) to improve access to existing and future facilities.     Applicant solicitation was done through the UNOLS website and personal communication.  In total there were 44 applications, out of which 21 participants were selected.   The training program began with a two day workshop in San Diego aboard the research vessel R/V T.G. Thompson during which the participants were introduced to UNOLS, the ship time request procedure, US State Department foreign clearance application, NSF ship selection and funding,  etc.  Presenters included the University of Washington professors, UNOLS representatives, NSF program directors, Scripps Institute of Oceanography personnel and the T.G. Thompsons Officers and marine technicians.   Prior to the workshop the participants  participated in a WEBEX meeting and subsequent  e-mail and Skype meeting to plan the actual training cruise that immediately followed the workshop.  Final tuning of the plan was done at the end of the second day of the workshop.  The at-sea portion of the chief scientist training program began when the ship left the Port of San Diego on the morning of the third day, and continued until the afternoon of the tenth day, after which there was a wrap-up meeting, demobilization and departure of participants.     The Chief Scientist Training program was successfully completed with 21 early-career oceanographers received training and exposure to the role of UNOLS, the process of planning, requesting and obtaining funding for a NSF sponsored research cruise and the responsibilities and duties of a chief scientist.  They were also exposed to early career mentoring, training by highly qualified marine technicians while at sea, and they had the opportunity to use or get exposure to state of the art observations and equipment, which should stimulate new ideas for research and science communication with the broader public.  All CTD and Bottle data collected during the Chief Scientist Training Cruise has been archived at the NOAA National Centers for Environmental Information (NCEI) data center and can be identified as NCEI Accession Number 0161328. The original data files can be accessed at link, http://accession.nodc.noaa.gov/0161328/data/0-data.  General project information is accessable at http://accession.nodc.noaa.gov/0161328.             Last Modified: 07/12/2017       Submitted by: Allan H Devol]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
