<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Functional interaction of synapsin and Rab3a in the presynaptic vesicle cycle</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>06/01/2015</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>452556.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>452556</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>08090200</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>BIO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>IOS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Integrative Organismal Systems</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Evan Balaban</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>ebalaban@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032928421</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Numerous neurological disorders result from disruptions in the communication between nerve cells. Neurons communicate by releasing neuronal transmitters from nerve endings. Impaired transmitter release may produce certain forms of epilepsy. Transmitter molecules are packed into synaptic vesicles, and the preparation of vesicles for release is regulated by numerous proteins. Synapsin is the most abundant synaptic vesicle protein, and its deficiency causes epileptic seizures. Past work shows elimination of another vesicle protein, Rab3a, rescues epilepsy caused by synapsin deletion. This project will investigate how these two proteins interact within nerve endings. To do this, genetically engineered mice that lack synapsin, Rab3a, or both proteins, will be studied. High resolution microscopy to observe vesicle dynamics, and electrical recording will be performed to monitor neuronal activity. In addition, a computational model of the nerve ending will be developed to test whether hypotheses of the protein interaction correctly predict how synapsin and Rab3a affect the release of transmitters. The results of our study will elucidate the mechanisms of synapsin-dependent epilepsy and will suggest new strategies for its treatment. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The Universidad Central del Caribe (UCC) is a Hispanic serving institution which strives to provide Puerto Rican students with first-rate education and scientific training. The present project creates a foundation for an excellent training program. The experiments will be performed by graduate, undergraduate, and medical students, and thus the project will provide a support for the students' careers. The project involves collaboration between the UCC and the Wayne State University, and this creates advantageous opportunities for Puerto Rico students to have a practice in a research intense institution. Thus, this project will integrate research and training, advance careers of Puerto Rico students, and help to promote workforce diversity.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>11/06/2015</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>11/06/2015</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.074</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1565476</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Maria</FirstName>
<LastName>Bykhovskaia</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Maria Bykhovskaia</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>mbykhovs@med.wayne.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>3135779744</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000243064</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>11/06/2015</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Wayne State University</Name>
<CityName>Detroit</CityName>
<ZipCode>482023622</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>3135772424</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>5057 Woodward</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[6th Floor]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Michigan</StateName>
<StateCode>MI</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>13</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MI13</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>001962224</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>WAYNE STATE UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>001962224</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Wayne State University]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>MI</StateCode>
<ZipCode>482023424</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Michigan</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>13</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MI13</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7275</Code>
<Text>Cross-BIO Activities</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7334</Code>
<Text>MATHEMATICAL BIOLOGY</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7454</Code>
<Text>MSPA-INTERDISCIPLINARY</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7712</Code>
<Text>Organization</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1096</Code>
<Text>NEURAL SYSTEMS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1228</Code>
<Text>MINORITY INVOLVEMENT -- BIO</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8007</Code>
<Text>BioMaPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9178</Code>
<Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9179</Code>
<Text>GRADUATE INVOLVEMENT</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0112</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2012~452553</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Intellectual merit:</p> <p>We investigated how deficiencies in neuronal communication affect excitability of neuronal networks in the brain. We focused on two neuronal proteins which affect neuronal communications, and took advantage of genetically engineered mice lacking either one or both proteins. It is known that deficiency of one of the proteins, SynII, produced predisposition to epilepsy, autism, and mental retardation. We also discovered earlier that the genetic deletion of the other protein, Rab3a, corrects epilepsy predisposition observed in SynII deleted mice. In this project, we investigated how these two proteins affect the release of neuronal transmitters from nerve terminals in the brain. We found that neurons deficient in SynII have elevated activity in the neurons responsible for neuronal excitation and the reduced activity in the neurons responsible for the neuronal inhibition. We also found that the inhibitory neuronal pathway is critical for the development of the epileptic phenotype observed in SynII deleted animals. We also pinpointed the neuronal deficiencies which are corrected by Rab3a deletion. Overall, our results elucidate the neuronal pathway which is critical for maintaining normal neuronal communication, and which prevents the development of brain disorders.</p> <p>Broader Impacts:</p> <p>The results of this project can be used in developing new strategies for epilepsy treatment. They were broadly disseminated in scientific communities. Three Ph.D. students, Hispanic Americans were trained within this project, and two of them obtained their Ph.D. degrees and secured postdoctoral positions in research intensive institutions.&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 10/02/2017<br>      Modified by: Maria&nbsp;Bykhovskaia</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Intellectual merit:  We investigated how deficiencies in neuronal communication affect excitability of neuronal networks in the brain. We focused on two neuronal proteins which affect neuronal communications, and took advantage of genetically engineered mice lacking either one or both proteins. It is known that deficiency of one of the proteins, SynII, produced predisposition to epilepsy, autism, and mental retardation. We also discovered earlier that the genetic deletion of the other protein, Rab3a, corrects epilepsy predisposition observed in SynII deleted mice. In this project, we investigated how these two proteins affect the release of neuronal transmitters from nerve terminals in the brain. We found that neurons deficient in SynII have elevated activity in the neurons responsible for neuronal excitation and the reduced activity in the neurons responsible for the neuronal inhibition. We also found that the inhibitory neuronal pathway is critical for the development of the epileptic phenotype observed in SynII deleted animals. We also pinpointed the neuronal deficiencies which are corrected by Rab3a deletion. Overall, our results elucidate the neuronal pathway which is critical for maintaining normal neuronal communication, and which prevents the development of brain disorders.  Broader Impacts:  The results of this project can be used in developing new strategies for epilepsy treatment. They were broadly disseminated in scientific communities. Three Ph.D. students, Hispanic Americans were trained within this project, and two of them obtained their Ph.D. degrees and secured postdoctoral positions in research intensive institutions.           Last Modified: 10/02/2017       Submitted by: Maria Bykhovskaia]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
