<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>SusChEM: Time Resolved In Situ Infrared Spectroscopy of Intermediates in the Electrochemical Reduction of Carbon Dioxide</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>05/01/2016</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>04/30/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>375000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>375000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03090000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CHE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Chemistry</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>George Janini</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>gjanini@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032928840</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Professor Matthias Waegele of Boston College is supported by the Chemical Catalysis program in the Division of Chemistry to develop a better understanding of how carbon dioxide is converted to hydrocarbons using readily-available copper as a catalyst.  The primary considerations that motivate this research are: the reduction of carbon dioxide could potentially serve as a sustainable source of hydrocarbon-based fuels, and the process may additionally provide a sustainable chemical route to ethylene and other essential chemicals.  A novel, time-resolved, infrared spectroscopic method is developed to detect intermediates of this complex multi-step chemical conversion process.  The new insight gained from conducting the research leads to a better understanding of the molecular origins that control the catalytic activity and selectivity of copper.  A better understanding on the molecular level informs the design and development of industrially-viable catalysts for the conversion of carbon dioxide to fuel and building block chemicals.  In addition to the technical broader impacts of the project, societal benefits are realized in the training of graduate and undergraduate students in advanced chemical research methods.  This research is under the SusChEM initiative as it uses a non-precious metal, copper, as the catalyst.&lt;br/&gt;   &lt;br/&gt;The principal goal of this research is to reveal the underlying molecular mechanism responsible for the unique catalytic ability of copper to reduce carbon dioxide to methane and ethylene in an aqueous electrochemical environment. Specifically, this research aims to delineate the mechanistic origins of the high over-potentials necessary to drive the reduction and the elementary steps which control the selectivity for one hydrocarbon product over the other.  While the electrochemical reduction of carbon dioxide has been an active area of research for over three decades, this project develops and employs a fundamentally different technique uniquely suited to address these key aims.  Specifically, an electrochemical cell is coupled to a time-resolved infrared spectrometer.  The potential of the electrochemical cell is rapidly jumped on a sub-microsecond timescale, providing a fast electrical trigger for the electro-reduction reaction.  The transient intermediates of the triggered reaction are monitored by the time-resolved infrared spectrometer.  The approach provides new thermodynamic, kinetic, and structural information essential for guiding the design of more efficient catalysts for this reaction.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>05/06/2016</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/06/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1565948</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Matthias</FirstName>
<LastName>Waegele</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Matthias Waegele</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>matthias.waegele@bc.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6175524312</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000704051</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/06/2016</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Boston College</Name>
<CityName>Chestnut Hill</CityName>
<ZipCode>024673800</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6175528000</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>140 Commonwealth Avenue</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
<StateCode>MA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MA04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>045896339</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>TRUSTEES OF BOSTON COLLEGE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>045896339</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Trustees of Boston College]]></Name>
<CityName>Chestnut Hill</CityName>
<StateCode>MA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>024673800</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[Commonwealth Avenue]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MA04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1401</Code>
<Text>Catalysis</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>6884</Code>
<Text>Chemical Catalysis</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1401</Code>
<Text>CATALYSIS AND BIOCATALYSIS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>6884</Code>
<Text>CHEMICAL CATALYSIS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8037</Code>
<Text>Advanced Manufacturing</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8248</Code>
<Text>SusChEM</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8396</Code>
<Text>Clean Energy Technology</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8398</Code>
<Text>Hydrocarbon Conversion</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8399</Code>
<Text>Energy Storage or Transmission</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8607</Code>
<Text>Solar Energy Capture&amp;Conver</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8650</Code>
<Text>Sustainable Chemistry</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0116</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2016~375000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Carbon dioxide is a reaction product in all combustion processes involving hydrocarbons. The chemical energy stored in the bonds of hydrocarbons can be safely and conveniently liberated by burning these compounds. Hydrocarbons, such as ethylene, are also essential precursors for many useful materials, such as plastics. Oil and natural gas are the main sources of industrially relevant hydrocarbons. The combustion of these fossil hydrocarbons (and their derivatives) has led to a rapid increase in atmospheric carbon dioxide, which is a major greenhouse gas. The production of hydrocarbons from renewable sources would enable their continued use without an increase in atmospheric carbon dioxide concentrations. The aqueous electrocatalytic reduction of carbon dioxide to valuable hydrocarbons, such as ethylene and ethanol, could provide a pathway to the renewable production of hydrocarbons. Although it has been shown that copper electrodes can catalyze the reduction of carbon dioxide, the rate of reduction and the reaction selectivity of this process are poor. Many different reduction products, such as methane, ethylene, carbon monoxide, and hydrogen from the competing reduction of water are formed during electrolysis. To improve the energy efficiency and reaction selectivity of electrocatalytic carbon dioxide reduction, it is essential to better understand the reaction mechanism and the relationship between reactivity and the properties of the electrocatalytic interface. Our research team employed surface-enhanced infrared absorption spectroscopy (SEIRAS) to elucidate the reaction mechanism on copper electrodes. Specifically, we focused on the reactivity of surface-adsorbed carbon dioxide, a key intermediate of the reduction process. The reduction of carbon monoxide is thought to determine the overall rate of carbon dioxide reduction. Elucidating its reactivity on the copper surface is therefore essential for improving the catalytic rates of this process. During our studies, we made the following discoveries: First, we were able to show that surface-adsorbed carbon monoxide induces a structural transition of the copper surface that leads to the formation of under-coordinated copper sites. Because these sites bind carbon monoxide more strongly (in comparison to more highly coordinated copper atoms on the surface), these sites are expected to be important catalytic centers. Our results highlight that this electrocatalyst readily undergoes structural transitions that likely impact its catalytic properties. In a related study, we explored the reactivity of carbon monoxide bound in two difference configurations: In the atop-bound configuration, carbon monoxide interacts with only one copper atom on the surface. In the bridge-bonded configuration, carbon monoxide interacts with multiple copper atoms. We elucidated the surface-dynamics of carbon monoxide in different configurations and found that the bridge-bonded configuration occurs at a higher surface concentration under alkaline conditions, likely because of a pH- and potential-induced morphological change of the copper surface. Importantly, we determined that bridge-bonded carbon monoxide is an irreversibly adsorbed species that does not further react to hydrocarbons. A second line of research focused on the impact of the electrolyte on the reactivity of surface-adsorbed carbon monoxide. We showed that Cs<sup>+</sup> ions of the supporting electrolyte promote the reduction of surface-adsorbed carbon monoxide (in comparison to Li<sup>+</sup>-containing electrolyte). On the basis of the spectroscopic data, we determined that the origin of this effect is due to the larger interfacial electric field in the presence of Cs<sup>+</sup>-ions. We also tuned the interfacial properties with a series of four quaternary alkyl ammonium cations of different sizes. We systematically determined the dependence of various interfacial properties (interfacial electric field strength, carbon monoxide surface coverage, interfacial water structure) on the cation in solution. Our detailed analysis revealed that the two largest cations of the series displaced water molecules from the interface and disrupted an interaction between water and surface-bound carbon monoxide. With differential electrochemical mass spectrometry (DEMS), we showed that the production of ethylene is shut down in the presence of these two cations. Our findings show that the interaction of water with surface-adsorbed carbon monoxide is essential for the production of ethylene. Taken together, our studies identified various interactions of surface-adsorbed carbon monoxide with the electrode surface and the electrolyte environment that greatly alter its reactivity. These insights are expected to aid the design of catalytic interfaces with desirable catalytic characteristics. This award supported the training of three female graduate students and one female undergraduate student. In addition, results from this research were incorporated into a course for graduate and undergraduate students at Boston College. Related to this research, the team also co-hosted an on-campus outreach event for high schools students and their parents.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 05/24/2019<br>      Modified by: Matthias&nbsp;Waegele</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Carbon dioxide is a reaction product in all combustion processes involving hydrocarbons. The chemical energy stored in the bonds of hydrocarbons can be safely and conveniently liberated by burning these compounds. Hydrocarbons, such as ethylene, are also essential precursors for many useful materials, such as plastics. Oil and natural gas are the main sources of industrially relevant hydrocarbons. The combustion of these fossil hydrocarbons (and their derivatives) has led to a rapid increase in atmospheric carbon dioxide, which is a major greenhouse gas. The production of hydrocarbons from renewable sources would enable their continued use without an increase in atmospheric carbon dioxide concentrations. The aqueous electrocatalytic reduction of carbon dioxide to valuable hydrocarbons, such as ethylene and ethanol, could provide a pathway to the renewable production of hydrocarbons. Although it has been shown that copper electrodes can catalyze the reduction of carbon dioxide, the rate of reduction and the reaction selectivity of this process are poor. Many different reduction products, such as methane, ethylene, carbon monoxide, and hydrogen from the competing reduction of water are formed during electrolysis. To improve the energy efficiency and reaction selectivity of electrocatalytic carbon dioxide reduction, it is essential to better understand the reaction mechanism and the relationship between reactivity and the properties of the electrocatalytic interface. Our research team employed surface-enhanced infrared absorption spectroscopy (SEIRAS) to elucidate the reaction mechanism on copper electrodes. Specifically, we focused on the reactivity of surface-adsorbed carbon dioxide, a key intermediate of the reduction process. The reduction of carbon monoxide is thought to determine the overall rate of carbon dioxide reduction. Elucidating its reactivity on the copper surface is therefore essential for improving the catalytic rates of this process. During our studies, we made the following discoveries: First, we were able to show that surface-adsorbed carbon monoxide induces a structural transition of the copper surface that leads to the formation of under-coordinated copper sites. Because these sites bind carbon monoxide more strongly (in comparison to more highly coordinated copper atoms on the surface), these sites are expected to be important catalytic centers. Our results highlight that this electrocatalyst readily undergoes structural transitions that likely impact its catalytic properties. In a related study, we explored the reactivity of carbon monoxide bound in two difference configurations: In the atop-bound configuration, carbon monoxide interacts with only one copper atom on the surface. In the bridge-bonded configuration, carbon monoxide interacts with multiple copper atoms. We elucidated the surface-dynamics of carbon monoxide in different configurations and found that the bridge-bonded configuration occurs at a higher surface concentration under alkaline conditions, likely because of a pH- and potential-induced morphological change of the copper surface. Importantly, we determined that bridge-bonded carbon monoxide is an irreversibly adsorbed species that does not further react to hydrocarbons. A second line of research focused on the impact of the electrolyte on the reactivity of surface-adsorbed carbon monoxide. We showed that Cs+ ions of the supporting electrolyte promote the reduction of surface-adsorbed carbon monoxide (in comparison to Li+-containing electrolyte). On the basis of the spectroscopic data, we determined that the origin of this effect is due to the larger interfacial electric field in the presence of Cs+-ions. We also tuned the interfacial properties with a series of four quaternary alkyl ammonium cations of different sizes. We systematically determined the dependence of various interfacial properties (interfacial electric field strength, carbon monoxide surface coverage, interfacial water structure) on the cation in solution. Our detailed analysis revealed that the two largest cations of the series displaced water molecules from the interface and disrupted an interaction between water and surface-bound carbon monoxide. With differential electrochemical mass spectrometry (DEMS), we showed that the production of ethylene is shut down in the presence of these two cations. Our findings show that the interaction of water with surface-adsorbed carbon monoxide is essential for the production of ethylene. Taken together, our studies identified various interactions of surface-adsorbed carbon monoxide with the electrode surface and the electrolyte environment that greatly alter its reactivity. These insights are expected to aid the design of catalytic interfaces with desirable catalytic characteristics. This award supported the training of three female graduate students and one female undergraduate student. In addition, results from this research were incorporated into a course for graduate and undergraduate students at Boston College. Related to this research, the team also co-hosted an on-campus outreach event for high schools students and their parents.       Last Modified: 05/24/2019       Submitted by: Matthias Waegele]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
