<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>GP IMPACT: INTEGRATING RECRUITMENT AND RETENTION TO IMPROVE UNDERGRADUATE GEOSCIENCE PATHWAYS</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2016</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2021</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>393813.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>393813</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>06010000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>GEO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>ICER</Abbreviation>
<LongName>ICER</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Brandon Jones</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>mbjones@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924713</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This project aims to fundamentally transform the undergraduate geoscience experience at the University of Hawai'i (UH) School of Ocean and Earth Science and Technology (SOEST) and Kapi'olani Community College (KCC), both in and out of the classroom, using evidence-based practices. The expected outcome is to contribute to the development of a diverse geoscience workforce equipped to tackle today's environmental challenges and the development of a national model for institutional transformation. The objectives of the project are to increase enrollment of newly declared SOEST undergraduate majors among Associate of Science in Natural Science (ASNS) degree holders, to increase retention of newly declared SOEST undergraduate majors during their first year at SOEST, and to increase underrepresented minority enrollment among SOEST undergraduate majors (with at least half of the increase among Native Hawaiians, Pacific Islanders, and Filipinos). These objectives will be accomplished through the implementation of four components. First, courses at SOEST will be transformed to incorporate student-centered strategies (e.g. active-learning, targeted interventions to stimulate student learning and success) and innovative assessment tools. The second component is professional development opportunities for the students through participation in a mentoring network, workshops, and outreach activities. Another important component will be the establishment of the Geoscience Learning Center at SOEST modeled after the KCC STEM center. The Center will have dedicated staff and space to promote STEM learning, networking, collaborations, and shared sense of purpose. The last component is support for KCC ocean science program by developing an introductory oceanography laboratory course and offering fieldtrips to the KCC students. Through a key cross-cutting strategic partnership, KCC students will be supported before, during, and after they transfer to SOEST.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/02/2016</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>01/23/2017</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.050</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1565950</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Charles</FirstName>
<LastName>Fletcher</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>H</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME>III</PI_SUFX_NAME>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Charles H Fletcher</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>fletcher@soest.hawaii.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>8089562582</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000205422</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/02/2016</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Louise</FirstName>
<LastName>Pagotto</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Louise Pagotto</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>pagotto@hawaii.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>8089567800</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000473539</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/02/2016</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Barbara</FirstName>
<LastName>Bruno</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>C</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Barbara C Bruno</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>barb@hawaii.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>8089560901</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000510130</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/02/2016</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Jennifer</FirstName>
<LastName>Engels</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Jennifer Engels</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>engels@hawaii.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>8089567800</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000731009</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>01/23/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Hawaii</Name>
<CityName>Honolulu</CityName>
<ZipCode>968222234</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>8089567800</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>2440 Campus Road, Box 368</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Hawaii</StateName>
<StateCode>HI</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>HI01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>965088057</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF HAWAII SYSTEMS</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>009438664</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Hawaii]]></Name>
<CityName>honolulu</CityName>
<StateCode>HI</StateCode>
<ZipCode>968222234</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[2525 Correa Road HIG214]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Hawaii</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>HI01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>9199</Code>
<Text>Unallocated Program Costs</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8209</Code>
<Text>Improv Undergrad STEM Ed(IUSE)</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0116</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2016~393813</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The<strong> intellectual merit</strong> of this proposal lies in an evidence-based, integrated approach for improving geoscience recruitment, retention, and instruction, as well as the collective administrative power of the project team to effect change. <strong>Broader impacts</strong> include the development of a diverse geoscience workforce equipped to tackle today's environmental challenges and the development of a national model for institutional transformation.&nbsp; Our long-range goal is to attract and prepare diverse undergraduates to pursue geoscience graduate study and careers that meet national needs. Toward this goal, we executed four components.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p><strong><em>Component 1: Course Transformation. </em></strong>We offered 42 activities aimed at transforming course pedagogies in the UH Manoa School of Ocean and Earth Science and Technology (SOEST). Our approach, based on the Carl Wieman Science Education initiative, invoked active-learning approaches, innovative assessments, and targeted interventions shown to be effective in facilitating student learning and stimulating student interest.&nbsp; Training focused on exposing geoscience faculty to research-based techniques, supporting faculty as they use these techniques in their classrooms, and collecting and analyzing data on their effectiveness.&nbsp; Additional activities focused on improving mentoring as well as the overall climate of SOEST, to one that promotes diversity, equity and inclusion.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p><strong><em>Component 2: Professional Development (PD)</em></strong><em>.&nbsp;</em> We launched a professional development workshop series aimed at helping students develop the skills and confidence necessary to succeed in a professional geoscience career. Twenty-three events were offered throughout the project period and attended by ~400 students at UHM and community colleges. &nbsp;Topics included: Career Exploration; Interview Skills; Writing CVs and Resumes; Applying to Internships and Scholarships;&nbsp; Applying to the NSF Graduate Research Fellowship Program; Applying for Financial Aid; Presentation Skills; and Joining Professional Societies.&nbsp; Through a cost-share between this grant and the Geological Society of America (GSA) Onto The Future program, we were able to bring a cohort of eleven Hawaii students to the 2019 GSA national meeting in Phoenix, Arizona.</p> <p><strong><em>&nbsp;</em></strong></p> <p><strong><em>Component 3. Geoscience Learning Center.&nbsp;</em></strong>We repurposed an existing space in the Hawai&lsquo;i Institute of Geophysics into a Geoscience Learning Center (GLC). This staffed space has office, laboratory, conference, and informal meeting areas designed to promote STEM learning, networking collaborations, and a shared sense of purpose.&nbsp; Bulletin boards advertise information and opportunities such as workshops, paid research experiences, and jobs, with a focus on opportunities and organizations that serve Native Hawaiian and Pacific Islander students, women, and community college students.. Laptops and iPads are available for student use. &nbsp;Posters featuring diverse students and inclusive messages (e.g., LGBTI Safe Zone) contribute to the welcoming, relaxing atmosphere.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p><strong><em>Component 4: Community College marine science</em></strong>. &nbsp;</p> <p>We supported introductory oceanography lecture (OCN201) and laboratory (OCN201L) at Kapiolani (KCC), Leeward (LCC) and Windward Community Colleges (WCC) through supporting equipment purchases, undergraduate research and &nbsp;twenty-three fieldtrips.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p><strong>Evaluation of Project Success</strong></p> <p>This project aimed to increase recruitment and enrollment among SOEST undergraduate majors, with a particular focus on under-represented students such as Native Hawaiians, Pacific Islanders, and Filipinos. &nbsp;&nbsp;An analysis of SOEST enrolment data for the past 5 academic years showed that the recruitment of newly declared SOEST undergraduate majors increased from 43 new majors to 72 new majors.&nbsp; This increase was statistically significant (p=0.004) with a Pearson correlation coefficient (r) of 0.98.&nbsp; During the same period, there was no statistically significant change in retention.&nbsp;&nbsp; Thus significantly increasing retention without impacting retention is a success.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>This work resulted in <strong>6 peer-reviewed publications</strong> in national and international journals.&nbsp; &nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 07/23/2021<br>      Modified by: Barbara&nbsp;C&nbsp;Bruno</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The intellectual merit of this proposal lies in an evidence-based, integrated approach for improving geoscience recruitment, retention, and instruction, as well as the collective administrative power of the project team to effect change. Broader impacts include the development of a diverse geoscience workforce equipped to tackle today's environmental challenges and the development of a national model for institutional transformation.  Our long-range goal is to attract and prepare diverse undergraduates to pursue geoscience graduate study and careers that meet national needs. Toward this goal, we executed four components.     Component 1: Course Transformation. We offered 42 activities aimed at transforming course pedagogies in the UH Manoa School of Ocean and Earth Science and Technology (SOEST). Our approach, based on the Carl Wieman Science Education initiative, invoked active-learning approaches, innovative assessments, and targeted interventions shown to be effective in facilitating student learning and stimulating student interest.  Training focused on exposing geoscience faculty to research-based techniques, supporting faculty as they use these techniques in their classrooms, and collecting and analyzing data on their effectiveness.  Additional activities focused on improving mentoring as well as the overall climate of SOEST, to one that promotes diversity, equity and inclusion.     Component 2: Professional Development (PD).  We launched a professional development workshop series aimed at helping students develop the skills and confidence necessary to succeed in a professional geoscience career. Twenty-three events were offered throughout the project period and attended by ~400 students at UHM and community colleges.  Topics included: Career Exploration; Interview Skills; Writing CVs and Resumes; Applying to Internships and Scholarships;  Applying to the NSF Graduate Research Fellowship Program; Applying for Financial Aid; Presentation Skills; and Joining Professional Societies.  Through a cost-share between this grant and the Geological Society of America (GSA) Onto The Future program, we were able to bring a cohort of eleven Hawaii students to the 2019 GSA national meeting in Phoenix, Arizona.     Component 3. Geoscience Learning Center. We repurposed an existing space in the Hawai‘i Institute of Geophysics into a Geoscience Learning Center (GLC). This staffed space has office, laboratory, conference, and informal meeting areas designed to promote STEM learning, networking collaborations, and a shared sense of purpose.  Bulletin boards advertise information and opportunities such as workshops, paid research experiences, and jobs, with a focus on opportunities and organizations that serve Native Hawaiian and Pacific Islander students, women, and community college students.. Laptops and iPads are available for student use.  Posters featuring diverse students and inclusive messages (e.g., LGBTI Safe Zone) contribute to the welcoming, relaxing atmosphere.     Component 4: Community College marine science.    We supported introductory oceanography lecture (OCN201) and laboratory (OCN201L) at Kapiolani (KCC), Leeward (LCC) and Windward Community Colleges (WCC) through supporting equipment purchases, undergraduate research and  twenty-three fieldtrips.     Evaluation of Project Success  This project aimed to increase recruitment and enrollment among SOEST undergraduate majors, with a particular focus on under-represented students such as Native Hawaiians, Pacific Islanders, and Filipinos.   An analysis of SOEST enrolment data for the past 5 academic years showed that the recruitment of newly declared SOEST undergraduate majors increased from 43 new majors to 72 new majors.  This increase was statistically significant (p=0.004) with a Pearson correlation coefficient (r) of 0.98.  During the same period, there was no statistically significant change in retention.   Thus significantly increasing retention without impacting retention is a success.     This work resulted in 6 peer-reviewed publications in national and international journals.             Last Modified: 07/23/2021       Submitted by: Barbara C Bruno]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
