<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Modular Synthesis of Natural Products via Site- and Stereoretentive Couplings of Secondary Csp3 Boronic Acids</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>05/01/2016</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>04/30/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>450000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>510000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03090000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CHE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Chemistry</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Jin Cha</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>jcha@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922461</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The Chemical Synthesis Program of the NSF Chemistry Division supports the research of Professor Martin Burke in the Department of Chemistry at The University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.  Professor Burke and his students are developing new methods for assembling molecular building blocks that contain non-planar "sp3" carbon atoms. Such methods have the potential to enable a simple, building block-based approach for making many different types of molecules with well-defined three-dimensional shapes. Such molecules have many potential applications, including serving as medicines, biological probes, diagnostics, agrochemicals, materials, molecular technologies, perfumes, sweeteners, and many other household products. One goal of the research is to develop new ligands for palladium that promote such assembly reactions in a manner that allows the three-dimensional shapes of the building blocks to be translated into the shapes of the final products. The project also aims to incorporate these new coupling methods and a readily accessible collection of building blocks into a fully automated platform for on-demand small molecule synthesis of a large family of biologically active molecules found in nature.  This research is well suited for the education of scientists at all levels.  Professor Burke's group is also well positioned to provide the highest level of education and training for students from groups that are underrepresented in science.  &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The development of new methods for site- and stereospecific cross-coupling of stereogenic sp3 carbon atoms largely comprise an actionable roadmap toward automated building block-based construction of many different types of small molecules. The proposed studies aim to develop such methods for coupling unactivated chiral secondary non-racemic boronic acids that possess one or more stereogenic sp3-hybridized carbon atoms. New phosphine ligands are targeted that promote such couplings by favoring transmetalation and reductive elimination at sp3-hybridized carbons while eliminating or minimizing undesired beta-hydride elimination reactions. These methods are evaluated for their capacity to enable fully automated total synthesis of an entire family of complex natural products from pre-assembled chiral building blocks. This research yields new strategies and methods that enable both the manual and automated synthesis of many different types of chiral Csp3-rich small molecules. This research program also contributes to the training of graduate and undergraduate students at the frontiers of organic synthesis.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>04/08/2016</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/23/2017</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1566071</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Martin</FirstName>
<LastName>Burke</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>D</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Martin D Burke</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>burke@scs.uiuc.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2172448726</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000228445</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/08/2016</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign</Name>
<CityName>Champaign</CityName>
<ZipCode>618207406</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2173332187</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1901 South First Street</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[Suite A]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Illinois</StateName>
<StateCode>IL</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>13</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>IL13</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>041544081</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF ILLINOIS</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>041544081</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Roger Adams Laboratory]]></Name>
<CityName>Urbana</CityName>
<StateCode>IL</StateCode>
<ZipCode>618013602</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[600 S Mathews Avenue]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Illinois</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>13</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>IL13</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>6878</Code>
<Text>Chemical Synthesis</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7433</Code>
<Text>CyberInfra Frmwrk 21st (CIF21)</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8037</Code>
<Text>Advanced Manufacturing</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8084</Code>
<Text>CDS&amp;E</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0116</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0117</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2016~450000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2017~60000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Peptides, oligonucleotides, and many oligosaccharides can now be automatically prepared from building blocks having all of the required functional groups, oxidation states, and stereochemistry pre-installed. The inherent modularity of many small molecule natural products and the rapidly expanding scope of boronic acid cross-coupling chemistry collectively suggest that many natural products may be accessible using a similarly modular and automated approach. Towards the aim of simplifying the synthesis of natural products and small organic molecules we have recently developed an automated iterative strategy based on the assembly of bifunctional building blocks which contain a halide and a MIDA protected boron centre. The halide participates in a cross-coupling reaction with a boronic acid to forge a C-C bond, subsequent deprotection of the MIDA boronate with NaOH activates the boron centre for further coupling reactions, establishing an iterative cycle. In this way, complex small molecules are broken down into simple building blocks which are then coupled together in an efficient and controlled manner. A limitation of this methodology is that the points of disconnection are best if they possess sp2 carbon atoms (unsaturation) as this facilitates the cross-coupling reaction. However, many of the natural products/natural product fragments which represent exceptionally promising starting points for new drug development are rich in sp3 but not sp2 carbons. In this regard, the development of Csp3 cross coupling reactions compatible with this building block-based approach to small molecule synthesis stands to unlock the substantial untapped potential of this automated synthesis platform for the discovery of new function within small molecule chemical space.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>In this NSF funded research project, we have focused on expanding the capacity of this synthesis platform to form sp3 bonds. We have approached this by developing a new palladium mediated Csp3 cross coupling reaction with the aim of preventing the formation of undesired and hard to separate mixtures. To enable these studies we first developed a versatile method for generating stereoisomerically pure Csp3 boronic acids through the separation of diastereoisomeric BIDA boronates. We then investigated the cross coupling of these Csp3 boronic acids with aryl halides and our identified phosphine ligand parameters which enable the fine tuning of reaction selectivity toward the desired coupled products. These new phosphine ligands have enabled the formation of new C-C bonds between Csp3 boronic acids and aryl halides without scrambling of 3-dimensional properties (stereochemistry) and without formation of linear isomers originating from palladium mediated beta-hydride elimination. We also found that vinyl halides participated in our cross-coupling reaction and using this methodology we performed the building block-based synthesis of each of the 4 stereoisomers of the antifungal natural product xylarinic acid. More broadly the fundamental principles of ligand design established herein stand to facilitate the development and discovery of other highly selective cross coupling reactions involving silicon or tin which operate through similar palladium mediated pathways. The continued development of Csp3 cross coupling methodologies will serve to expand the range of practically accessible compounds through automated synthesis.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 08/22/2019<br>      Modified by: Martin&nbsp;D&nbsp;Burke</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Image         </div> <div class="galControls onePhoto" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation onePhoto" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1566071/1566071_10418949_1566510837794_NSFRPPROutcomesTOC--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1566071/1566071_10418949_1566510837794_NSFRPPROutcomesTOC--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Image"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1566071/1566071_10418949_1566510837794_NSFRPPROutcomesTOC--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Image"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Axial shielding of Pd(II) complexes enables perfect stereoretention in Suzuki-Miyaura cross-coupling of Csp3 boronic acids</div> <div class="imageCredit">Daniel Blair</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Martin&nbsp;D&nbsp;Burke</div> <div class="imageTitle">Image</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Peptides, oligonucleotides, and many oligosaccharides can now be automatically prepared from building blocks having all of the required functional groups, oxidation states, and stereochemistry pre-installed. The inherent modularity of many small molecule natural products and the rapidly expanding scope of boronic acid cross-coupling chemistry collectively suggest that many natural products may be accessible using a similarly modular and automated approach. Towards the aim of simplifying the synthesis of natural products and small organic molecules we have recently developed an automated iterative strategy based on the assembly of bifunctional building blocks which contain a halide and a MIDA protected boron centre. The halide participates in a cross-coupling reaction with a boronic acid to forge a C-C bond, subsequent deprotection of the MIDA boronate with NaOH activates the boron centre for further coupling reactions, establishing an iterative cycle. In this way, complex small molecules are broken down into simple building blocks which are then coupled together in an efficient and controlled manner. A limitation of this methodology is that the points of disconnection are best if they possess sp2 carbon atoms (unsaturation) as this facilitates the cross-coupling reaction. However, many of the natural products/natural product fragments which represent exceptionally promising starting points for new drug development are rich in sp3 but not sp2 carbons. In this regard, the development of Csp3 cross coupling reactions compatible with this building block-based approach to small molecule synthesis stands to unlock the substantial untapped potential of this automated synthesis platform for the discovery of new function within small molecule chemical space.     In this NSF funded research project, we have focused on expanding the capacity of this synthesis platform to form sp3 bonds. We have approached this by developing a new palladium mediated Csp3 cross coupling reaction with the aim of preventing the formation of undesired and hard to separate mixtures. To enable these studies we first developed a versatile method for generating stereoisomerically pure Csp3 boronic acids through the separation of diastereoisomeric BIDA boronates. We then investigated the cross coupling of these Csp3 boronic acids with aryl halides and our identified phosphine ligand parameters which enable the fine tuning of reaction selectivity toward the desired coupled products. These new phosphine ligands have enabled the formation of new C-C bonds between Csp3 boronic acids and aryl halides without scrambling of 3-dimensional properties (stereochemistry) and without formation of linear isomers originating from palladium mediated beta-hydride elimination. We also found that vinyl halides participated in our cross-coupling reaction and using this methodology we performed the building block-based synthesis of each of the 4 stereoisomers of the antifungal natural product xylarinic acid. More broadly the fundamental principles of ligand design established herein stand to facilitate the development and discovery of other highly selective cross coupling reactions involving silicon or tin which operate through similar palladium mediated pathways. The continued development of Csp3 cross coupling methodologies will serve to expand the range of practically accessible compounds through automated synthesis.          Last Modified: 08/22/2019       Submitted by: Martin D Burke]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
