<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Spatio-Temporal and Site-Specific Chemical Dynamics at Interfaces</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2016</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>590000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>590000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03090000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CHE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Chemistry</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Colby Foss</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>cfoss@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032925327</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>In this project funded by the Chemical Structure, Dynamics and Mechanisms A program of the Chemistry Division, Professor Steven J. Sibener of The University of Chicago addresses several key issues in surface reaction dynamics, leading to advances in the fundamental understanding of molecular reactivity at interfaces. This scientific program has direct implications for advanced materials fabrication, heterogeneous catalysis, combustion, and the design of protective thin film coatings.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project focuses on surface chemical dynamics that include site specific reactivity, adiabatic and non-adiabatic gas-surface interactions such as dissociative chemisorption including energy dissipation and surface mobility, directionally-controlled deposition and film growth, and geometry-constrained and stereo-specific reaction studies in which energetic atomic species react with molecules that are pre-aligned due to the nature of their bonding and film structure. This is being accomplished using a combination of supersonic molecular beams, scanning tunneling/atomic force microscopy, and surface spectroscopies. Comparisons with theory and numerical simulations provide precision tests of calculated reaction potential energy surfaces and mechanistic reaction pathways. Direct visualization of reacting interfaces helps to reveal site-specific reactivity and spatio-temporal correlations as a function of local structure and reaction extent. In these studies, precise control over reagent energy, incident angle, intensity, and quantum state are applied. Interfacial chemistry is examined under non-equilibrium conditions. Societal broader impact occurs via outreach to the local minority community, including local public, charter, and private schools, and museum science activities that have substantial representation from underrepresented south-side Chicago populations.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/11/2016</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/08/2017</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1566364</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Steven</FirstName>
<LastName>Sibener</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>J</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Steven J Sibener</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>s-sibener@uchicago.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>7737027193</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000165571</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/11/2016</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Chicago</Name>
<CityName>Chicago</CityName>
<ZipCode>606372612</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>7737028669</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>6054 South Drexel Avenue</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[Suite 300]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Illinois</StateName>
<StateCode>IL</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>IL01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>005421136</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF CHICAGO, THE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>005421136</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Chicago]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>IL</StateCode>
<ZipCode>606375814</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Illinois</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>IL01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>9101</Code>
<Text>Chem Struct,Dynmcs&amp;Mechansms A</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8037</Code>
<Text>Advanced Manufacturing</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0116</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0117</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2016~410000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2017~180000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>In this project funded by the Chemical Structure, Dynamics and Mechanisms program of the Chemistry Division, Professor Steven J. Sibener of The University of Chicago addressed several key issues in surface reaction dynamics, leading to advances in the fundamental understanding of molecular reactivity at interfaces.&nbsp;&nbsp;This scientific program had direct implications for advanced materials fabrication, heterogeneous catalysis, combustion, and the design of protective passivating thin film coatings. It also contributed to STEM workforce development in areas of high interest to the nation.</p> <p>The Intellectual Merit of this project focussed on forefront issues in surface chemical dynamics that included atomically-resolved site specific reactivity, energy- and angle-dependent oxidative reactivity of graphite as well as atomic hydrogen reactions with self-assembled organic thin film coatings. &nbsp;Geometry-constrained studies in which energetic atomic species reacted with self-assembled organic thin films were explored with molecules that were pre-aligned due to the nature of their bonding and film structure.&nbsp;&nbsp;This was accomplished using a combination of supersonic molecular beams, scanning tunneling/atomic force microscopy, and surface spectroscopies.&nbsp;&nbsp;Comparisons with theory and numerical simulations provided precision tests of calculated reaction potential energy surfaces and mechanistic reaction pathways.&nbsp;&nbsp;The philosophy that underpinned this program, in order to achieve a more accurate understanding of surface chemistry and interfacial reactivity, was that we needed to elucidate how the correlations due to spatio-temporal averaging influenced ongoing surface reactions as they occur.&nbsp;&nbsp;Under the auspices of this grant our group pioneered such studies by examining the atomic-level details of surface morphological evolution in real-time and real-space using variable-temperature STM in conjunction with atomic and molecular beams. This approach allowed us to assess the influence that atomic and nanoscale surface structure and mass transport have on interfacial reaction rates and mechanistic pathways. Such studies enrich in important new ways our fundamental understanding of surface chemical processes extending to both equilibrium and non-equilibrium conditions.</p> <p>Societal Broader Impacts occurred <em>via</em> outreach to the local minority community, including local public, charter, and private schools, as well as museum and community science activities that have substantial representation from underrepresented south-side Chicago populations.&nbsp;&nbsp;This program trained researchers in critical STEM areas of endeavor including postdoctoral scholars as well as graduate and undergraduate researchers. The knowledge generated has contributed broadly to our understanding of heterogeneous chemical processes, important for the electronics, chemical, and aerospace communities.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 01/02/2020<br>      Modified by: Steven&nbsp;J&nbsp;Sibener</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ In this project funded by the Chemical Structure, Dynamics and Mechanisms program of the Chemistry Division, Professor Steven J. Sibener of The University of Chicago addressed several key issues in surface reaction dynamics, leading to advances in the fundamental understanding of molecular reactivity at interfaces.  This scientific program had direct implications for advanced materials fabrication, heterogeneous catalysis, combustion, and the design of protective passivating thin film coatings. It also contributed to STEM workforce development in areas of high interest to the nation.  The Intellectual Merit of this project focussed on forefront issues in surface chemical dynamics that included atomically-resolved site specific reactivity, energy- and angle-dependent oxidative reactivity of graphite as well as atomic hydrogen reactions with self-assembled organic thin film coatings.  Geometry-constrained studies in which energetic atomic species reacted with self-assembled organic thin films were explored with molecules that were pre-aligned due to the nature of their bonding and film structure.  This was accomplished using a combination of supersonic molecular beams, scanning tunneling/atomic force microscopy, and surface spectroscopies.  Comparisons with theory and numerical simulations provided precision tests of calculated reaction potential energy surfaces and mechanistic reaction pathways.  The philosophy that underpinned this program, in order to achieve a more accurate understanding of surface chemistry and interfacial reactivity, was that we needed to elucidate how the correlations due to spatio-temporal averaging influenced ongoing surface reactions as they occur.  Under the auspices of this grant our group pioneered such studies by examining the atomic-level details of surface morphological evolution in real-time and real-space using variable-temperature STM in conjunction with atomic and molecular beams. This approach allowed us to assess the influence that atomic and nanoscale surface structure and mass transport have on interfacial reaction rates and mechanistic pathways. Such studies enrich in important new ways our fundamental understanding of surface chemical processes extending to both equilibrium and non-equilibrium conditions.  Societal Broader Impacts occurred via outreach to the local minority community, including local public, charter, and private schools, as well as museum and community science activities that have substantial representation from underrepresented south-side Chicago populations.  This program trained researchers in critical STEM areas of endeavor including postdoctoral scholars as well as graduate and undergraduate researchers. The knowledge generated has contributed broadly to our understanding of heterogeneous chemical processes, important for the electronics, chemical, and aerospace communities.          Last Modified: 01/02/2020       Submitted by: Steven J Sibener]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
