<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>I-Corps:  Shrinkage Reducing Admixture Business Development</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>01/01/2014</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2015</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>50000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>50000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07070000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>IIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Industrial Innovation &amp; Partnersh</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Rathindra DasGupta</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The research team is developing a shrinkage reducing admixture for application in portland cement-based materials such as concrete. This technology focuses on reducing the surface tension of the pore solution by disrupting the hydrogen bonding of water molecules in the liquid phase at the vapor-liquid interface. The basis of this technology lies in the team?s ability to predict new structures using an intelligent computer aided molecular design methodology that utilizes quantitative structure property relationships (QSPR) and inverse design logic. This is one of the first demonstrations of the use of computer aided molecular design using QSPR to discover new admixtures for concrete.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Concrete is one of the major building blocks of roads and structures across the globe, and each year billions of dollars are spent replacing concrete damaged due to cracking-related issues. The admixture developed by this research team would serve to help reduce shrinkage of concrete, which is one of the main causes of concrete cracking, damage and failure. Concrete that is less prone to damage would result in less cost for repair and overall, stronger, more durable structures and roadways.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>12/03/2013</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>12/03/2013</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1400881</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Joseph</FirstName>
<LastName>Biernacki</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>J</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Joseph J Biernacki</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>jbiernacki@tntech.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>9313723667</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000273335</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>12/03/2013</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Tennessee Technological University</Name>
<CityName>Cookeville</CityName>
<ZipCode>385050001</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>9313723374</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>Dixie Avenue</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Tennessee</StateName>
<StateCode>TN</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>06</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>TN06</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>878648153</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>TENNESSEE TECHNOLOGICAL UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>878648153</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Tennessee Technological University]]></Name>
<CityName>Cookeville</CityName>
<StateCode>TN</StateCode>
<ZipCode>385050001</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[1 William L. Jones Drive]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Tennessee</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>06</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>TN06</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>8023</Code>
<Text>I-Corps</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0114</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~50000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><span style="font-family: Times New Roman; font-size: small;"> </span><span style="font-family: Calibri; font-size: small;">Shrinkage related cracks in concrete are responsible for a large fraction of early failure in concrete structures.<span style="mso-spacerun: yes;">&nbsp; </span>Mainly a problem in large segments of concrete, such as slabs for pavements or parking lot floors and slender sections such as curbs, shrinkage cracking can be reduced by introducing chemicals to the concrete mix that inhibit the processes that cause shrinkage.<span style="mso-spacerun: yes;">&nbsp; </span>Our team specializes in design of such compounds call shrinkage reducing admixtures (SRAs). <span style="mso-spacerun: yes;">&nbsp;</span>Having participated in an intensive customer discovery activity, our team found that a minimally viable product (MVP) might be introducible into the market and continues to be optimistic about moving our first generation compounds towards commercialization.</span></p> <p><span style="font-family: Times New Roman; font-size: small;"> </span><span style="font-family: Calibri; font-size: small;">Discovery of such compounds is not easy.<span style="mso-spacerun: yes;">&nbsp; </span>Existing strategies rely mainly on incremental approaches that utilize tedious selection of compounds that are identified by intuition and general knowledge about how small changes in compound structure might affect performance.<span style="mso-spacerun: yes;">&nbsp; </span>Our team&rsquo;s approach, however, synthesizes know outcomes for known chemical structures and by using a technique called inverse design, is able to identify potential compounds to be tested.<span style="mso-spacerun: yes;">&nbsp; </span>This methodology is of particular interest since it may be applicable to a wide range of compounds for use in the construction industry with the goal of finding new materials that have less impact on the environment, perform better in their application and reduce the overall cost and life-cycle impact of the materials we use to build things.</span></p> <p><span style="font-family: Times New Roman; font-size: small;"> </span><span style="font-family: Calibri; font-size: small;">Responding to the rapid pace of innovation, engineering programs across the country are creating environments that will promote entrepreneurship among their students.<span style="mso-spacerun: yes;">&nbsp; </span>At Tennessee Tech University (TTU), the PI of this grant has utilized his training to co-develop a mini-Lean Launchpad course for students, translating his I-Corps experience into an activity that promises to impact on students for years to come.<span style="mso-spacerun: yes;">&nbsp; </span>The lean Launchpad experience is an invaluable toolkit for any innovator that provides a firm foundation upon which they can focus their intellectual labors towards endeavors that can make immediate impacts.</span></p> <p><span style="font-family: Times New Roman; font-size: small;"> </span></p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 09/29/2015<br>      Modified by: Joseph&nbsp;J&nbsp;Biernacki</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[  Shrinkage related cracks in concrete are responsible for a large fraction of early failure in concrete structures.  Mainly a problem in large segments of concrete, such as slabs for pavements or parking lot floors and slender sections such as curbs, shrinkage cracking can be reduced by introducing chemicals to the concrete mix that inhibit the processes that cause shrinkage.  Our team specializes in design of such compounds call shrinkage reducing admixtures (SRAs).  Having participated in an intensive customer discovery activity, our team found that a minimally viable product (MVP) might be introducible into the market and continues to be optimistic about moving our first generation compounds towards commercialization.   Discovery of such compounds is not easy.  Existing strategies rely mainly on incremental approaches that utilize tedious selection of compounds that are identified by intuition and general knowledge about how small changes in compound structure might affect performance.  Our teamÆs approach, however, synthesizes know outcomes for known chemical structures and by using a technique called inverse design, is able to identify potential compounds to be tested.  This methodology is of particular interest since it may be applicable to a wide range of compounds for use in the construction industry with the goal of finding new materials that have less impact on the environment, perform better in their application and reduce the overall cost and life-cycle impact of the materials we use to build things.   Responding to the rapid pace of innovation, engineering programs across the country are creating environments that will promote entrepreneurship among their students.  At Tennessee Tech University (TTU), the PI of this grant has utilized his training to co-develop a mini-Lean Launchpad course for students, translating his I-Corps experience into an activity that promises to impact on students for years to come.  The lean Launchpad experience is an invaluable toolkit for any innovator that provides a firm foundation upon which they can focus their intellectual labors towards endeavors that can make immediate impacts.          Last Modified: 09/29/2015       Submitted by: Joseph J Biernacki]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
