<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>GOALI: Improving the Reliability of Aluminum Structures During Fire Through Computational Modeling</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>06/15/2014</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>349148.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>359148</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CMMI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Civil, Mechanical, &amp; Manufact Inn</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Yick Hsuan</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The research objective of this Grant Opportunity for Academic Liaison with Industry (GOALI) project is to construct a probabilistic computational framework for modeling response of aluminum structure in buildings subjected to fire. The results can have a profound impact on the design and analysis practices for aluminum structures (and ductile metal structures in general) by enabling probabilistically informed standards that account for variability in nonlinear material responses. Current methods employing simplistic safety factors apply a large penalty to account for fire risk. The processes developed through this work can result in significant cost saving for numerous industries ranging from civil structural design to automotive, aircraft, and naval vessel design. The research will also afford unique educational opportunities to high school students in the Baltimore area through joint academic-industry mentorship.  Graduate students involved in the project will benefit from professional exchange through internship at the industry partner. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project will serve to enhance understanding of the material response of aluminum under simultaneous stress and high temperature by quantifying the uncertainties associated with both the materials and the fire events. The research plan includes assessment of uncertainties at the material level as well as uncertainties related to temperature rate and fire exposure time. The goal is to develop probabilistic reliability analysis that can be incorporated in to finite element software. The program will couple state-of-the-art deterministic computational tools developed by the industry partner which have been shown to accurately model the creep rupture and elastoplastic failure of ductile metals with uncertainty quantification, stochastic simulation, and structural reliability methods developed at the institution. Validation of the analytical model will be done using the previously conducted experimental data available from other sources.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/15/2014</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>03/30/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1400387</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Michael</FirstName>
<LastName>Shields</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>D</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Michael D Shields</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>michael.shields@jhu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>4105168682</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000652930</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/15/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Pawel</FirstName>
<LastName>Woelke</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Pawel Woelke</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>pawel.woelke@wai.com</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2123673000</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000654187</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/15/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Johns Hopkins University</Name>
<CityName>Baltimore</CityName>
<ZipCode>212182686</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>4439971898</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1101 E 33rd St</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[Suite B001]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Maryland</StateName>
<StateCode>MD</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MD07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>001910777</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>JOHNS HOPKINS UNIVERSITY, THE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>001910777</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Johns Hopkins University]]></Name>
<CityName>Baltimore</CityName>
<StateCode>MD</StateCode>
<ZipCode>212182683</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[3400 N. Charles Street]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Maryland</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MD07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1504</Code>
<Text>GOALI-Grnt Opp Acad Lia wIndus</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1637</Code>
<Text>Structural and Architectural E</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>039E</Code>
<Text>STRUCTURAL SYSTEMS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>040E</Code>
<Text>Haz mitigation of structural sys</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>043E</Code>
<Text>EARTHQUAKE ENGINEERING</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>116E</Code>
<Text>RESEARCH EXP FOR UNDERGRADS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1504</Code>
<Text>GRANT OPP FOR ACAD LIA W/INDUS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9178</Code>
<Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9231</Code>
<Text>SUPPL FOR UNDERGRAD RES ASSIST</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9251</Code>
<Text>REU SUPP-Res Exp for Ugrd Supp</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0114</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0116</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~349148</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2016~10000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The project involved an experimental and computational study of the variability in the material properties of aluminum at high temperature and their influence on the response of aluminum structures during a fire. The experimental component of the project developed a large dataset to understand variability in the performance of aluminum at high temperature. In total 154 tests were conducted for 9 batches of material at 6 temperatures ranging from room temperature to 300 degrees C. The results of these experiments were analyzed statistically and were then used to model variability in the material performance and assess its impact on structures.</p> <p>The experimental data filled an important knowledge gap as it relates to the high temperature performance of aluminum. Prior to this investigation, it was not well understood to what extent the properties of the material varied and this dataset provides valuable insights in that regard. Moreover, this is expected to have a profound effect on the design and analysis of aluminum structures for fire hazards. By understanding the variability, the computational aspects of the project demonstrated that we can now perform probabilistic modeling of structures to assess their safety and reliability given the uncertainties in how the material will perform during a fire. &nbsp;</p> <p>The data generated in this project have been made publicly available with the intention that they will serve as a valuable seed from which future investigations can grow and that they will provide the basis for improvements in the state of practice as it relates to design and analysis of aluminum structures. Future investigations that are modeled after this one could cover other aluminum alloys including those manufactured using other techniques and, more broadly, may study other ductile metals to understand their temperature dependence and variability.&nbsp;</p> <p>The project supported several outreach efforts including the support of undergraduate researchers who gained their first exposure to scientific research. Several mentoring opportunities were afforded to the graduate students supported by this project. These students, who are in the early stages of their careers, have benefited tremendously from the opportunity to teach and advise both undergraduates and high school students. The PI and the graduate students also worked with 3rd through 5th grade students to improve STEM education through after-school programs in Baltimore city public schools that serve largely students who are under-represented in scientific disciplines.&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 09/27/2018<br>      Modified by: Michael&nbsp;D&nbsp;Shields</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The project involved an experimental and computational study of the variability in the material properties of aluminum at high temperature and their influence on the response of aluminum structures during a fire. The experimental component of the project developed a large dataset to understand variability in the performance of aluminum at high temperature. In total 154 tests were conducted for 9 batches of material at 6 temperatures ranging from room temperature to 300 degrees C. The results of these experiments were analyzed statistically and were then used to model variability in the material performance and assess its impact on structures.  The experimental data filled an important knowledge gap as it relates to the high temperature performance of aluminum. Prior to this investigation, it was not well understood to what extent the properties of the material varied and this dataset provides valuable insights in that regard. Moreover, this is expected to have a profound effect on the design and analysis of aluminum structures for fire hazards. By understanding the variability, the computational aspects of the project demonstrated that we can now perform probabilistic modeling of structures to assess their safety and reliability given the uncertainties in how the material will perform during a fire.    The data generated in this project have been made publicly available with the intention that they will serve as a valuable seed from which future investigations can grow and that they will provide the basis for improvements in the state of practice as it relates to design and analysis of aluminum structures. Future investigations that are modeled after this one could cover other aluminum alloys including those manufactured using other techniques and, more broadly, may study other ductile metals to understand their temperature dependence and variability.   The project supported several outreach efforts including the support of undergraduate researchers who gained their first exposure to scientific research. Several mentoring opportunities were afforded to the graduate students supported by this project. These students, who are in the early stages of their careers, have benefited tremendously from the opportunity to teach and advise both undergraduates and high school students. The PI and the graduate students also worked with 3rd through 5th grade students to improve STEM education through after-school programs in Baltimore city public schools that serve largely students who are under-represented in scientific disciplines.        Last Modified: 09/27/2018       Submitted by: Michael D Shields]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
