<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Travel support for ASPLOS 2014</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>01/15/2014</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2014</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>15000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>15000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>05010000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>CSE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CCF</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division of Computing and Communication Foundations</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Anindya Banerjee</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>abanerje@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927885</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This award provides student travel support for the 19th Annual International Conference on Architecture Support for Programming Languages and Operating Systems (ASPLOS) to be held from March 1-5 2014, in Salt Lake City, Utah. ASPLOS is the premier conference for multidisciplinary systems research spanning computer architecture and hardware, programming languages and compilers, operating systems and networking, as well as applications and user interfaces. The importance of such cross-cutting research continues to grow as we grapple with the end of Dennard scaling, the explosion of big data, scales ranging from ultra-low power wearable devices to exascale parallel and cloud computers, the need for sustainability, and increasingly human-centered applications. ASPLOS embraces systems research that directly targets these new problems in new ways.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The NSF support ensures participation of US students while paying attention to underrepresented groups. To broaden participation, the grant is intended specifically to increase the numbers of students who cannot otherwise attend, that is, students who do not have any financial support whatsoever, e.g., from their advisors, departments, universities. The broader impacts include building international community and cooperation in the research areas of the conference, and enhancing education of students with exposure to and interaction with leading-edge research and researchers. This award will therefore help train the next generation of architects, operating systems builders and language designers in interdisciplinary integration of their respective skills.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>01/13/2014</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>01/13/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.070</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1400472</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Matthew</FirstName>
<LastName>Might</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Matthew Might</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>might@cs.utah.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>4043763204</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000068857</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>01/13/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Utah</Name>
<CityName>SALT LAKE CITY</CityName>
<ZipCode>841128930</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>8015816903</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>75 S 2000 E</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[Second Floor]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Utah</StateName>
<StateCode>UT</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>UT02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>009095365</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF UTAH, THE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>009095365</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Utah]]></Name>
<CityName>Salt Lake City</CityName>
<StateCode>UT</StateCode>
<ZipCode>841129049</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[201 Presidents Circle]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Utah</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>UT02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7354</Code>
<Text>CSR-Computer Systems Research</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7798</Code>
<Text>Software &amp; Hardware Foundation</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7941</Code>
<Text>COMPUTER ARCHITECTURE</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7943</Code>
<Text>PROGRAMMING LANGUAGES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0114</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~15000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>This award enabled students (with priority given to U.S. citizens and permanent residents) that would otherwise not be able to attend this premier interdisciplinary event in research on architecture, operating systems, programming languages and systems programming the ability to attend this conference. Attendees were give the ability to network and collaborate with top researchers in these fields, an opportunity rarely afforded outside such conferences.</p> <p><strong>Intellectual Merit</strong></p> <p>Conferences are a well-recognized means of sparking and promoting collaboration between researchers.&nbsp; As students noted in the travel experience blog after the event, many had the opportunity to meet and initiate research with top scientists in their field.&nbsp; It is likely that the collaborations initiated at ASPLOS will lead to fruitful discoveries by students and other researchers in attendence at the conference.<strong><br /></strong></p> <p><strong>Broader Impacts</strong></p> <p>By allowing students to attend a top-tier conference in their field, they received a transformative experience for their scientific careers.&nbsp; This helps fill the ranks of young scientists so desperately needed to drive society forward.&nbsp; This award also allowed those students otherwise not able to attend the ability to do so.&nbsp; In an effort, to encourage under-represented groups to attend, all calls for participation and application for travel support encouraged members of these groups to apply.<strong><br /></strong></p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 01/02/2015<br>      Modified by: Matthew&nbsp;Might</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ This award enabled students (with priority given to U.S. citizens and permanent residents) that would otherwise not be able to attend this premier interdisciplinary event in research on architecture, operating systems, programming languages and systems programming the ability to attend this conference. Attendees were give the ability to network and collaborate with top researchers in these fields, an opportunity rarely afforded outside such conferences.  Intellectual Merit  Conferences are a well-recognized means of sparking and promoting collaboration between researchers.  As students noted in the travel experience blog after the event, many had the opportunity to meet and initiate research with top scientists in their field.  It is likely that the collaborations initiated at ASPLOS will lead to fruitful discoveries by students and other researchers in attendence at the conference.   Broader Impacts  By allowing students to attend a top-tier conference in their field, they received a transformative experience for their scientific careers.  This helps fill the ranks of young scientists so desperately needed to drive society forward.  This award also allowed those students otherwise not able to attend the ability to do so.  In an effort, to encourage under-represented groups to attend, all calls for participation and application for travel support encouraged members of these groups to apply.        Last Modified: 01/02/2015       Submitted by: Matthew Might]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
