<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Entropy and Singular Solutions for Conservation Laws; Pressureless Gas Dynamics and other applications</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>05/01/2014</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>04/30/2016</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>37000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>37000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DMS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Bruce P. Palka</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Abstract (Tudorascu, 1400168): &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award provides funding for a  workshop  on  Entropy and Singular Solutions for Conservation Laws; Pressureless Gas Dynamics and other applications, to be held  Sept. 19-21, 2014  at West Virginia University.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The workshop  focuses on the overlap of some research areas in Analysis   such as Pressureless Gas Dynamics, Conservation Laws and Optimal Transport. Selected specialists with significant contributions in these  areas have been invited and agreed to participate. The PI  makes an effort to ensure that the conference  topics will cover a fine spectrum between purely theoretical and applied topics. The PI plans to get help from university diversity officers in achieving a diversified participation of  the workshop. Ample opportunity for exchanging ideas between graduate students, postdocs, and senior researchers is provided.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>01/27/2014</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>01/27/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1400168</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Adrian</FirstName>
<LastName>Tudorascu</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Adrian Tudorascu</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>adriant@math.wvu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>3042932011</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000541763</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>01/27/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Charis</FirstName>
<LastName>Tsikkou</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Charis Tsikkou</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>chtsikkou@mail.wvu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>3042933998</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000653841</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>01/27/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>West Virginia University Research Corporation</Name>
<CityName>Morgantown</CityName>
<ZipCode>265066845</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>3042933998</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>P.O. Box 6845</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>West Virginia</StateName>
<StateCode>WV</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>WV01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>191510239</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>WEST VIRGINIA UNIVERSITY RESEARCH CORPORATION</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[West Virginia University]]></Name>
<CityName>Morgantown</CityName>
<StateCode>WV</StateCode>
<ZipCode>265066310</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[320 Armstrong Hall]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>West Virginia</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>WV01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1266</Code>
<Text>APPLIED MATHEMATICS</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1281</Code>
<Text>ANALYSIS PROGRAM</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7556</Code>
<Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0114</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~37000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><div class="page" title="Page 4"> <div class="layoutArea"> <div class="column"> <p><span>The questions of existence and uniqueness for the initial-value problem for multi- dimensional pressureless gases remains wide open. However, the talk by T. Nguyen (based on recent work in collaboration with A. Bressan) showed that the sticky-particle paradigm does not seem to provide the right constructive framework (as it does in 1D); this is, undoubtedly, great progress in the field, as it opens the door to investigating new construction principles. A recent preprint by M. Colombeau alludes to the possibility of constructing solutions by weak asymptotic methods, i.e. as limits of classical solutions of appropriately parametrized ODE systems. In the 1D case, different approaches by artificial viscosity were covered in our conference both in the talk by Nguyen, and by James; it is open to debate which one is more physical and why. </span></p> <p><span>At this meeting many other issues were discussed, and new developments were pre- sented which are at the forefront of current research with considerable impact on many important areas of mathematics and related sciences. Among these topics, the notion of&nbsp;</span>entropy played a central role throughout the conference. The theory of conservation laws is confronted with a major challenge. There is evidence that the current concepts of weak admissible solutions are not adequate for securing existence and uniqueness. The purpose of the meeting was to discuss related questions: How to define entropy solutions? What are the appropriate spaces for entropy solutions? What are the criteria for selecting entropy solutions among weak solutions? At least ten invited talks covered topics from existence, uniqueness, stability, regularity, shocks, and singular solutions.&nbsp;</p> </div> </div> </div> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 05/19/2016<br>      Modified by: Adrian&nbsp;Tudorascu</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[    The questions of existence and uniqueness for the initial-value problem for multi- dimensional pressureless gases remains wide open. However, the talk by T. Nguyen (based on recent work in collaboration with A. Bressan) showed that the sticky-particle paradigm does not seem to provide the right constructive framework (as it does in 1D); this is, undoubtedly, great progress in the field, as it opens the door to investigating new construction principles. A recent preprint by M. Colombeau alludes to the possibility of constructing solutions by weak asymptotic methods, i.e. as limits of classical solutions of appropriately parametrized ODE systems. In the 1D case, different approaches by artificial viscosity were covered in our conference both in the talk by Nguyen, and by James; it is open to debate which one is more physical and why.   At this meeting many other issues were discussed, and new developments were pre- sented which are at the forefront of current research with considerable impact on many important areas of mathematics and related sciences. Among these topics, the notion of entropy played a central role throughout the conference. The theory of conservation laws is confronted with a major challenge. There is evidence that the current concepts of weak admissible solutions are not adequate for securing existence and uniqueness. The purpose of the meeting was to discuss related questions: How to define entropy solutions? What are the appropriate spaces for entropy solutions? What are the criteria for selecting entropy solutions among weak solutions? At least ten invited talks covered topics from existence, uniqueness, stability, regularity, shocks, and singular solutions.                 Last Modified: 05/19/2016       Submitted by: Adrian Tudorascu]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
