<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Rebranding the 21st Century IT Technician</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2014</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>199850.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>199850</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>11040100</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>EHR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DUE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Undergraduate Education</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Elizabeth Teles</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>To address the need for more high-skilled Information Technology (IT) technicians in a six-county area district, Spokane Falls Community College (SFCC) is partnering with local school districts, community organizations, industry partners, the Spokane Workforce Consortium, and the Washington Center of Excellence for Information and Computing Technology. The project adjusts incoming students', enrolled students', and local employers' perceptions of IT technicians' ideal genders, skill sets, and degrees. The major activities are: (1) Offering IT summer camps for middle school girls, and professional development workshops for middle school teachers and counselors; (2) Teaching sections of science classes from the perspective of IT, and starting a chapter of American Women in Computing (AWS) on campus; and (3) Partnering with local employers to develop streamlined education-to-employment programs. The project increases the knowledge base of how to recruit and retain female students, and how to quickly make them post K-12 ready. It creates a curriculum that demonstrates interdependency between technology and science, and it develops procedures for establishing robust job shadowing and internship programs. The best practices established through this project can be extended to other STEM disciplines and technician training programs. Through a partnership with the Washington Center of Excellence for Information and Computing Technology; the project results will be available to instructors at all of the 34 community and technical colleges in that state. Through the ATE Mentor Connect program and the SC ATE Center, the results will be globally available on the SCATE.org and TeachingTechnician.org websites.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/12/2014</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/12/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.076</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1400451</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Asa</FirstName>
<LastName>Bradley</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>M</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Asa M Bradley</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>Asa.Bradley@sfcc.spokane.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5095333837</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000643402</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/12/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Max</FirstName>
<LastName>Josquin</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Max Josquin</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>max.josquin@spokanefalls.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5094345278</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000643544</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/12/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Michele</FirstName>
<LastName>Moore</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Michele Moore</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>Michele.Moore@spokanefalls.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5094345278</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000647976</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/12/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Community Colleges of Spokane</Name>
<CityName>Spokane</CityName>
<ZipCode>992176000</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5094345160</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>501 N Riverpoint Blvd MS1002</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[ATTN:  Mysti Reneau]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Washington</StateName>
<StateCode>WA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>WA05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>153805213</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>WASHINGTON STATE COMMUNITY COLLEGE DISTRICT 17</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>153805213</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Spokane Falls Community College]]></Name>
<CityName>Spokane</CityName>
<StateCode>WA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>992245288</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[3410 W. Fort George Wright Drive]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Washington</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>WA05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7412</Code>
<Text>Advanced Tech Education Prog</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1032</Code>
<Text>ADVANCED TECHNOLOGY EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9178</Code>
<Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>SMET</Code>
<Text>SCIENCE, MATH, ENG &amp; TECH EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0414</Code>
<Name>NSF Education &amp; Human Resource</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040106</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~199850</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><strong>Rebranding the 21st Century IT Technician Project Outcomes Report</strong></p> <p>Through funding from a National Science Foundation (NSF) Small Grant for Institutions New to the ATE Program grant, Spokane Falls Community College (SFCC) addressed the need for more high-skilled Information Technology (IT) technicians in the six-county area served by the college district. Our grant project also focused on making sure that the graduates from the college&rsquo;s Information Technology Associate in Applied Science (AAS) program have the skills and connections necessary for long term employability.</p> <p>SFCC partnered with local school districts and industry partners such as Greater Spokane Incorporated (GSI) to adjust the perceptions of IT technicians&rsquo; ideal genders, assumed skillset, and required degree. The project&rsquo;s three major goals were:</p> <p><strong>1)</strong>&nbsp;Increase the number of skilled IT technicians entering the workforce by recruiting students from populations traditionally underrepresented in the field, especially female students.</p> <p><strong>2)</strong>&nbsp;Ensure that our graduates have the skills necessary for long term employability by better modeling the interdependency of science and technology.</p> <p><strong>3)</strong>&nbsp;Create strong and long lasting partnerships between local businesses and the college in order to increase student employability.</p> <p>The major tasks we completed toward reaching those goals were:</p> <p><strong>1)</strong>&nbsp;Holding IT summer camps for middle school girls three summers in a row and professional development workshops for middle school teachers for two of those summers. The IT Camp curriculum was designed and delivered by SFCC female Science, Technology, Engineering, and Math (STEM) students who also majorly contributed to the teacher workshops.</p> <p><strong>2</strong><strong>)</strong>&nbsp;Creating and offering a Physics class three spring quarters in a row, which taught science from the perspective of how it pertains to IT.</p> <p><strong>3)</strong>&nbsp;Hosting various on-campus networking events where our students could get advice from and connect with STEM industry professionals.</p> <p>Our project added to the already existing body of research on how to recruit and retain female students in the IT field. Much of the current literature and research concentrates on high school populations for recruitment. This project instead targeted middle school students in order to guide them toward choosing high school science and math that are prerequisites for IT technician training and thus make them post K-12 academically ready quicker. The creation of a physics class focused on IT applications created model curriculum that can be used to demonstrate the interdependency between technology and science and the role of hard science classes in many technician training programs. Additionally, we strengthened and created new collaborations with local industry partners and made them more aware of who are students are and what they can do. Our most successful outcome of the project was the cohort of STEM female students who led the IT Camp for middle school girls. Their confidence and leadership skills increased tremendously and their completion rates were above any other programs on campus, including the male STEM students. Overall, our change data in terms of attitudes about IT and STEM of middle school students, middle school teachers, and SFCC students was consistently above that of other similar projects with similar activities to ours. &nbsp;&nbsp;</p> <p>Through partnerships with the urban and rural school district, our project connected with a large number of middle school students and teachers. Via partnerships with local businesses and Greater Spokane Incorporated, the project connected with IT employers in the local market and beyond. The results from our project was widely distributed locally through our school and industry partners. The grant project leaders presented their results at two NSF ATE conferences and through the ATE Mentor Connect program, the investigators created strong ties with leaders in the ATE community. Our recruitment materials, retention strategies, and project materials will be disseminated by the NSF/ATE various outlets and resource libraries.&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 11/30/2017<br>      Modified by: Asa&nbsp;M&nbsp;Bradley</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Rebranding the 21st Century IT Technician Project Outcomes Report  Through funding from a National Science Foundation (NSF) Small Grant for Institutions New to the ATE Program grant, Spokane Falls Community College (SFCC) addressed the need for more high-skilled Information Technology (IT) technicians in the six-county area served by the college district. Our grant project also focused on making sure that the graduates from the college?s Information Technology Associate in Applied Science (AAS) program have the skills and connections necessary for long term employability.  SFCC partnered with local school districts and industry partners such as Greater Spokane Incorporated (GSI) to adjust the perceptions of IT technicians? ideal genders, assumed skillset, and required degree. The project?s three major goals were:  1) Increase the number of skilled IT technicians entering the workforce by recruiting students from populations traditionally underrepresented in the field, especially female students.  2) Ensure that our graduates have the skills necessary for long term employability by better modeling the interdependency of science and technology.  3) Create strong and long lasting partnerships between local businesses and the college in order to increase student employability.  The major tasks we completed toward reaching those goals were:  1) Holding IT summer camps for middle school girls three summers in a row and professional development workshops for middle school teachers for two of those summers. The IT Camp curriculum was designed and delivered by SFCC female Science, Technology, Engineering, and Math (STEM) students who also majorly contributed to the teacher workshops.  2) Creating and offering a Physics class three spring quarters in a row, which taught science from the perspective of how it pertains to IT.  3) Hosting various on-campus networking events where our students could get advice from and connect with STEM industry professionals.  Our project added to the already existing body of research on how to recruit and retain female students in the IT field. Much of the current literature and research concentrates on high school populations for recruitment. This project instead targeted middle school students in order to guide them toward choosing high school science and math that are prerequisites for IT technician training and thus make them post K-12 academically ready quicker. The creation of a physics class focused on IT applications created model curriculum that can be used to demonstrate the interdependency between technology and science and the role of hard science classes in many technician training programs. Additionally, we strengthened and created new collaborations with local industry partners and made them more aware of who are students are and what they can do. Our most successful outcome of the project was the cohort of STEM female students who led the IT Camp for middle school girls. Their confidence and leadership skills increased tremendously and their completion rates were above any other programs on campus, including the male STEM students. Overall, our change data in terms of attitudes about IT and STEM of middle school students, middle school teachers, and SFCC students was consistently above that of other similar projects with similar activities to ours.     Through partnerships with the urban and rural school district, our project connected with a large number of middle school students and teachers. Via partnerships with local businesses and Greater Spokane Incorporated, the project connected with IT employers in the local market and beyond. The results from our project was widely distributed locally through our school and industry partners. The grant project leaders presented their results at two NSF ATE conferences and through the ATE Mentor Connect program, the investigators created strong ties with leaders in the ATE community. Our recruitment materials, retention strategies, and project materials will be disseminated by the NSF/ATE various outlets and resource libraries.        Last Modified: 11/30/2017       Submitted by: Asa M Bradley]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
