<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>NSF Postdoctoral Fellowship in Biology FY 2014</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>02/01/2015</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>01/31/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>138000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>138000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Fellowship Award</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>08080000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>BIO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DBI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Biological Infrastructure</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Amanda Simcox</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>NSF Postdoctoral Fellowships in Biology combine research and training components to prepare young scientists for careers in emerging areas where biology intersects with other scientific disciplines, in this case with mathematics.  The Fellows are expected to lead the nation's scientific workforce of the future.   This fellowship to Ross Cunning supports research and training to integrate quantitative genetic and modeling approaches to understand climate change impacts on coral symbiosis.  The host institutions for the Fellowship are the University of Hawaii and the University of California, Santa Barbara; the sponsoring scientists are Drs. Ruth Gates and Roger Nisbet.  Training goals include genomics, bioinformatics, and dynamic energy budget theory and modeling techniques to examine the coral-zooxanthellae symbiosis.  Educational outreach to students in Hawaii includes students from groups under-represented in STEM fields. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The research seeks to understand the dynamic interactions between reef-building corals and their symbiotic algae in an era of global environmental change. The future persistence of coral reef ecosystems depends on the integrity of this symbiosis; stress disrupts the symbiosis, but the processes underlying its regulation and stability, even in the absence of environmental stress, are poorly understood.   The approach is to extract molecular information from corals and sea anemones with zooxanthellae raised under various conditions, then model the results and test the outcomes of the models, resulting in a mechanistic understanding of the maintenance and breakdown of symbiosis and integrate "omics"-based molecular data within a Dynamic Energy Budget (DEB) model for coral symbiosis. The specific aims are to 1) develop a comprehensive DEB framework to model coral-algal symbiotic interactions, 2) assess environmental influences on symbiosis structure and function with quantitative metagenomic and transcriptomic datasets, and 3) integrate these data within the DEB modeling framework to test diverse hypotheses regarding the regulation and control of symbiosis and predict responses to complex changes in the environment.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/12/2014</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/12/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.074</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1400787</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Ross</FirstName>
<LastName>Cunning</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Ross Cunning</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress/>
<PI_PHON>3126922755</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000653128</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/12/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Cunning                 Ross</Name>
<CityName>Miami</CityName>
<ZipCode>331491098</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber/>
<StreetAddress/>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Florida</StateName>
<StateCode>FL</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>18</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>FL18</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM/>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME/>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Cunning                 Ross]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>FL</StateCode>
<ZipCode>331491234</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Florida</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>27</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>FL27</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>8054</Code>
<Text>Inters Biol and Math and Phys</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7137</Code>
<Text>POSTDOCTORAL FELLOWSHIPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7174</Code>
<Text>POSTDOC FELLOW IN SCI, MATH EN</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0114</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~138000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>This postdoctoral fellowship supported cross-disciplinary research on the symbioses between reef-building corals and dinoflagellate symbionts (<em>Symbiodinium</em> spp.) &ndash; whose performance and response to stress determine the fate of coral reef ecosystems under climate change. PI Cunning was trained in new disciplines including dynamic systems modeling, computational biology, and bioinformatics, to complement his background in molecular ecology and organismal biology. These integrated skills supported intersectional research resulting in 1) a dynamical model of coral symbiosis that reveals coral bleaching as an alternate stable state, 2) a stronger role for open, accessible theoretical tools in coral research, 3) custom bioinformatic pipelines for describing <em>Symbiodinium</em> communities using high-throughput sequencing, and 4) data-driven discovery surrounding <em>Symbiodinium</em> diversity and dynamics in Hawaii, American Samoa, and the U.S. Virgin Islands.</p> <p>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; The heart of this project was the development of an accessible and usable dynamic bioenergetic model for coral-<em>Symbiodinium</em> symbioses. This model was developed using open source R code (which is familiar to many biologists) incorporating mechanistic representations of photo-oxidative stress and coral bleaching in response to environmental stress. The model predicts coral growth and symbiosis dynamics (i.e., bleaching and recovery) as an integrated response to multiple, dynamic environmental factors, and reveals coral bleaching as an alternate stable state of the symbiotic system (Cunning et al. 2017b). Developed and distributed as a package for the R computing environment (github.com/jrcunning/coRal), the model is transformative in bringing accessible theoretical tools to coral biologists, who may use it to generate and test diverse hypotheses in both experimental and natural settings.</p> <p>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; To complement this theoretical work on the dynamics of coral symbioses, datasets were generated to describe <em>Symbiodinium</em> communities in American Samoa (Cunning et al. 2015), St. John, U.S. Virgin Islands (Cunning et al. 2017a), and Hawaii (Cunning et al. 2016). PI Cunning developed new bioinformatic pipelines to describe the structure of these communities using high-throughput sequencing data (github.com/jrcunning/SymITS2) &ndash; a critical step to understanding their ecological dynamics. Coral bleaching events in Hawaii in 2014 and 2015 also created the opportunity to study variation in stress susceptibility among coral individuals and temporal dynamics in their symbiont communities, which can be specifically compared with model predictions as an empirical test of this tool. Finally, host genetic signatures corresponding with heat tolerance were characterized from these corals, representing an unanticipated but highly significant outcome of this work.</p> <p>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; Through the course of these activities, many students (from high school to doctoral) were involved with field, lab, and data science activities under the mentorship of PI Cunning. In addition, PI Cunning championed open and reproducible research at his institution (University of Hawaii) through the development of code resources and data repositories associated with each component of this work (github.com/jrcunning). Cunning himself received transformative mentorship and training in theoretical/mathematical sciences and computational bioinformatics, establishing these disciplines &ndash; and their intersections with biological and ecological sciences &ndash; as core pillars of his activities as an early career researcher.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>Cunning R, Gates RD, Edmunds PJ. (2017a) Using high-throughput sequencing of ITS2 to describe <em>Symbiodinium</em> metacommunites in St. John, U.S. Virgin Islands. PeerJ Preprints 10.7287/peerj.preprints.2925v1</p> <p>Cunning R, Muller EB, Gates RD, Nisbet RM (2017b) A dynamic bioenergetic model for coral-<em>Symbiodinium</em> symbioses and coral bleaching as an alternate stable state. bioRxiv doi: 10.1101/120733</p> <p>Cunning R, Ritson-Williams R, Gates RD (2016) Patterns of bleaching and recovery of <em>Montipora capitata</em> in K?ne?ohe Bay, Hawai?i, USA. Mar Ecol Prog Ser 551:131-139. doi: 10.3354/meps11733</p> <p>Cunning R, Yost DM, Guarinello ML, Putnam HM, Gates RD (2015) Variability of <em>Symbiodinium</em> communities in waters, sediments, and corals of thermally distinct reef pools in American Samoa. PLOS ONE e0145099. doi:10.1371/journal.pone.0145099</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 05/01/2017<br>      Modified by: Ross&nbsp;Cunning</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Image         </div> <div class="galControls onePhoto" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation onePhoto" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1400787/1400787_10318257_1493676995360_Fig1--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1400787/1400787_10318257_1493676995360_Fig1--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Dynamic Bioenergetic model of coral-algal symbioses"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1400787/1400787_10318257_1493676995360_Fig1--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Dynamic Bioenergetic model of coral-algal symbioses"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Light, CO2, prey, and DIN are acquired from the external environment proportional to the biomass of the partner indicated by the black box for uptake. Mass fluxes are represented by j?s with subscripts indicating the type of mass, and in some cases the process.</div> <div class="imageCredit">doi:10.1101/120733</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Creative Commons</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Ross&nbsp;Cunning</div> <div class="imageTitle">Dynamic Bioenergetic model of coral-algal symbioses</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ This postdoctoral fellowship supported cross-disciplinary research on the symbioses between reef-building corals and dinoflagellate symbionts (Symbiodinium spp.) &ndash; whose performance and response to stress determine the fate of coral reef ecosystems under climate change. PI Cunning was trained in new disciplines including dynamic systems modeling, computational biology, and bioinformatics, to complement his background in molecular ecology and organismal biology. These integrated skills supported intersectional research resulting in 1) a dynamical model of coral symbiosis that reveals coral bleaching as an alternate stable state, 2) a stronger role for open, accessible theoretical tools in coral research, 3) custom bioinformatic pipelines for describing Symbiodinium communities using high-throughput sequencing, and 4) data-driven discovery surrounding Symbiodinium diversity and dynamics in Hawaii, American Samoa, and the U.S. Virgin Islands.              The heart of this project was the development of an accessible and usable dynamic bioenergetic model for coral-Symbiodinium symbioses. This model was developed using open source R code (which is familiar to many biologists) incorporating mechanistic representations of photo-oxidative stress and coral bleaching in response to environmental stress. The model predicts coral growth and symbiosis dynamics (i.e., bleaching and recovery) as an integrated response to multiple, dynamic environmental factors, and reveals coral bleaching as an alternate stable state of the symbiotic system (Cunning et al. 2017b). Developed and distributed as a package for the R computing environment (github.com/jrcunning/coRal), the model is transformative in bringing accessible theoretical tools to coral biologists, who may use it to generate and test diverse hypotheses in both experimental and natural settings.              To complement this theoretical work on the dynamics of coral symbioses, datasets were generated to describe Symbiodinium communities in American Samoa (Cunning et al. 2015), St. John, U.S. Virgin Islands (Cunning et al. 2017a), and Hawaii (Cunning et al. 2016). PI Cunning developed new bioinformatic pipelines to describe the structure of these communities using high-throughput sequencing data (github.com/jrcunning/SymITS2) &ndash; a critical step to understanding their ecological dynamics. Coral bleaching events in Hawaii in 2014 and 2015 also created the opportunity to study variation in stress susceptibility among coral individuals and temporal dynamics in their symbiont communities, which can be specifically compared with model predictions as an empirical test of this tool. Finally, host genetic signatures corresponding with heat tolerance were characterized from these corals, representing an unanticipated but highly significant outcome of this work.              Through the course of these activities, many students (from high school to doctoral) were involved with field, lab, and data science activities under the mentorship of PI Cunning. In addition, PI Cunning championed open and reproducible research at his institution (University of Hawaii) through the development of code resources and data repositories associated with each component of this work (github.com/jrcunning). Cunning himself received transformative mentorship and training in theoretical/mathematical sciences and computational bioinformatics, establishing these disciplines &ndash; and their intersections with biological and ecological sciences &ndash; as core pillars of his activities as an early career researcher.     Cunning R, Gates RD, Edmunds PJ. (2017a) Using high-throughput sequencing of ITS2 to describe Symbiodinium metacommunites in St. John, U.S. Virgin Islands. PeerJ Preprints 10.7287/peerj.preprints.2925v1  Cunning R, Muller EB, Gates RD, Nisbet RM (2017b) A dynamic bioenergetic model for coral-Symbiodinium symbioses and coral bleaching as an alternate stable state. bioRxiv doi: 10.1101/120733  Cunning R, Ritson-Williams R, Gates RD (2016) Patterns of bleaching and recovery of Montipora capitata in K?ne?ohe Bay, Hawai?i, USA. Mar Ecol Prog Ser 551:131-139. doi: 10.3354/meps11733  Cunning R, Yost DM, Guarinello ML, Putnam HM, Gates RD (2015) Variability of Symbiodinium communities in waters, sediments, and corals of thermally distinct reef pools in American Samoa. PLOS ONE e0145099. doi:10.1371/journal.pone.0145099          Last Modified: 05/01/2017       Submitted by: Ross Cunning]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
