<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Apollonian Circle Packings</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>04/01/2014</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>03/31/2016</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>27204.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>27204</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DMS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Andrew Pollington</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>adpollin@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924878</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This grant funds the participation of US-based lecturers, organizers, and students in the Apollonian Circle Packings Summer School at the Institut Mittag-Leffler, Stockholm, during June 23-27, 2014 (co-hosted by the European Women in Mathematics association and the European Mathematical Society as the 6th European Women in Mathematics Summer School). The summer school will feature lecture series by Dr. Elena Fuchs (Berkeley) and Prof. Hee Oh (Yale University) on Apollonian circle packings and related concepts such as orbits of thin groups, geometric group theory, equidistribution, the affine sieve, strong approximation and expanders. This area is on the cutting edge of current mathematics; many of the major breakthroughs have occurred in the last 5-7 years, and at least 17 papers on these subjects have appeared since 2011. Graduate students and postdocs will benefit from learning about these methods in a unified presentation that ties all of these ideas back into the irresistible beauty of Apollonian circle packings. Further information may be found on the summer school webpage: &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;http://www.math.ucsd.edu/~alina/ewm/&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This summer school will have potential for broad impact on the worldwide community of young number theorists, as it will provide an entry point to this fast-paced area of research, and will enrich the skills of graduate student and postdoc participants. In addition, due to its structural focus on gender parity, this summer school will serve a key role in retaining women who are already engaged in number theory, as well as in attracting more female researchers to the field. By highlighting the research of the two featured female lecturers on the international stage, the summer school will increase their visibility, particularly for younger researchers in the field. The school will also give participants the chance to gain specialized knowledge on fascinating new developments in number theory as well as an awareness of current open problems in the field. Finally, participants will learn about connections between number theory and other parts of mathematics while enlarging their mathematical toolboxes, thus supplementing their educations and aiding them in starting successful independent research programs.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>03/04/2014</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>03/04/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1400237</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Alina</FirstName>
<LastName>Bucur</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>I</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Alina I Bucur</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>abucur@ucsd.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>8585342644</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000545615</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>03/04/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of California-San Diego</Name>
<CityName>La Jolla</CityName>
<ZipCode>920930934</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>8585344896</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>Office of Contract &amp; Grant Admin</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[9500 Gilman Drive, 0934]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>49</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CA49</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>804355790</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF CALIFORNIA, SAN DIEGO</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>071549000</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of California-San Diego]]></Name>
<CityName>La Jolla</CityName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>920930934</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[Office of Contract &amp; Grant A]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>49</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CA49</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1264</Code>
<Text>ALGEBRA,NUMBER THEORY,AND COM</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7556</Code>
<Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0114</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~27204</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>&nbsp;</p> <p>The Apollonian Circle Packings Summer School was held at Institut Mittag-Leffler (IML) in Stockholm during June 23-27,2014. The Summer School featured lecture series presented by distinguished lecturers Hee Oh (Yale) and Elena Fuchs (Berkeley) as well as 10 presentations by pairs of participants. The summer school is documented in a 130 page handbook of expository papers written by the participants.&nbsp;The plan for the summer school was well-received by the international community, ultimately receiving the majority of its funding from the Clay Mathematics Institute (for international participants), the National Science Foundation (for US-based participants), lodging and meal support from the Institut Mittag-Leffler, and small contributions from the EMS and Number Theory Foundation.&nbsp;</p> <p>The focus of the Summer School was on Apollonian circle packings and related techniques such as investigating orbits of thin groups, geometric group theory, equidistribution, the affine sieve, strong approximation and expanders. Hee Oh centered her presentations on the role of dynamics, concluding the week with several applications of the Howe-Moore theorem on the decay of matrix coefficients, and appropriate measures. Elena Fuchs focused on arithmetic aspects of circle packings, and in particular the Fuchs-Sanden conjecture (a major open problem in the field): in any given integral primitive Apollonian circle packing, &nbsp;all integers (aside from finitely many exceptions) in allowable residue classes modulo 24 are represented as curvatures in the packing. Her lectures highlighted the way the combinatorial sieve and expanders can be used to control error terms, and culminated by bringing these methods together with a new variant of the circle method to prove that a positive proportion of integers are presented as curvatures in such a packing.</p> <p>Participants, lecturers, and organizers came from institutions in 8 countries, and spanned at least 13 nationalities.&nbsp;The student participants gave high reviews of the summer school, focusing on the quality and content of the featured lectures, the inclusive atmosphere and also on the process of writing the expository essays for the handbook. In fact, the majority of the students commented that the effort of writing the essay and preparing the lecture in advance was a very positive experience that served them well for understanding the featured lectures during the week, and taught them new mathematics in depth that they might not otherwise have learnt. The handbook will be a useful resource as they continue to read further in the field.<br /><br />The ambience of the summer school was significantly enriched by the lovely surroundings of the IML, including its exhaustive library and collections of journals. In particular, the provision of meals by the IML catering staff allowed for all the participants to speak casually with more senior members (organizers and lecturers). Six of the attending mathematicians are presently at a career juncture, changing either institution, level of job, or both, and the informal discussions were particularly useful for these participants.&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>Re:boot Number Theory 2016 was a 4 day intensive research retreat in March 2016 at Duke University, &nbsp;</p> <ul> <li>27 young female faculty in number theory, from all over the US</li> <li>the director of the NSA-Mathematical Science Program</li> <li>&nbsp;a former program director for the NSF</li> <li>(remote speaker) the president of the Association for Women in Mathematics\item one female number theorist who explained her career transition to genomics</li> </ul> <p>To our knowledge, this event was the first of its type in US mathematics.&nbsp;</p> <p>Funding was provided by the NSF, the NSA-MSP, Microsoft Research, the Number Theory Foundation, Duke University Natural Sciences Division, and Women in the Quanti...]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[    The Apollonian Circle Packings Summer School was held at Institut Mittag-Leffler (IML) in Stockholm during June 23-27,2014. The Summer School featured lecture series presented by distinguished lecturers Hee Oh (Yale) and Elena Fuchs (Berkeley) as well as 10 presentations by pairs of participants. The summer school is documented in a 130 page handbook of expository papers written by the participants. The plan for the summer school was well-received by the international community, ultimately receiving the majority of its funding from the Clay Mathematics Institute (for international participants), the National Science Foundation (for US-based participants), lodging and meal support from the Institut Mittag-Leffler, and small contributions from the EMS and Number Theory Foundation.   The focus of the Summer School was on Apollonian circle packings and related techniques such as investigating orbits of thin groups, geometric group theory, equidistribution, the affine sieve, strong approximation and expanders. Hee Oh centered her presentations on the role of dynamics, concluding the week with several applications of the Howe-Moore theorem on the decay of matrix coefficients, and appropriate measures. Elena Fuchs focused on arithmetic aspects of circle packings, and in particular the Fuchs-Sanden conjecture (a major open problem in the field): in any given integral primitive Apollonian circle packing,  all integers (aside from finitely many exceptions) in allowable residue classes modulo 24 are represented as curvatures in the packing. Her lectures highlighted the way the combinatorial sieve and expanders can be used to control error terms, and culminated by bringing these methods together with a new variant of the circle method to prove that a positive proportion of integers are presented as curvatures in such a packing.  Participants, lecturers, and organizers came from institutions in 8 countries, and spanned at least 13 nationalities. The student participants gave high reviews of the summer school, focusing on the quality and content of the featured lectures, the inclusive atmosphere and also on the process of writing the expository essays for the handbook. In fact, the majority of the students commented that the effort of writing the essay and preparing the lecture in advance was a very positive experience that served them well for understanding the featured lectures during the week, and taught them new mathematics in depth that they might not otherwise have learnt. The handbook will be a useful resource as they continue to read further in the field.  The ambience of the summer school was significantly enriched by the lovely surroundings of the IML, including its exhaustive library and collections of journals. In particular, the provision of meals by the IML catering staff allowed for all the participants to speak casually with more senior members (organizers and lecturers). Six of the attending mathematicians are presently at a career juncture, changing either institution, level of job, or both, and the informal discussions were particularly useful for these participants.      Re:boot Number Theory 2016 was a 4 day intensive research retreat in March 2016 at Duke University,    27 young female faculty in number theory, from all over the US the director of the NSA-Mathematical Science Program  a former program director for the NSF (remote speaker) the president of the Association for Women in Mathematics\item one female number theorist who explained her career transition to genomics   To our knowledge, this event was the first of its type in US mathematics.   Funding was provided by the NSF, the NSA-MSP, Microsoft Research, the Number Theory Foundation, Duke University Natural Sciences Division, and Women in the Quantitative Sciences at Duke University.     We heard strongly positive feedback from participants on how re:boot affected their level of preparation for submitting grants. As a result of this workshop, these facul...]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
