<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>RAPID: Sovereignty, Rights, Justice and the Manus Island Detention Center, Papua New Guinea</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>02/15/2014</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2015</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>25000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>25000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>04040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>SBE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>BCS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Behavioral and Cognitive Sci</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Jeffrey Mantz</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>jmantz@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927783</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Paige West of Barnard College proposes to explore how human migration and its social effects contribute to understanding human social relations as they are emerging in the context of environmental change and social upheaval. The research will be carried out in in a region of the world expected to be profoundly impacted by climate-related migration over the next fifty years, thus making it a test case for emergent international relations related to migration and refugee resettlement. This RAPID proposal documents the context that gave rise to and results from the Regional Resettlement Arrangement between Australia and Papua New Guinea (colloquially known as "The Papua New Guinea Solution"). As of July 2013, asylum seekers who attempt to reach Australia by boat are diverted to Manus Island, Papua New Guinea, for detention and processing, and then eventual resettlement in Papua New Guinea. The Manus detention facility provides an important predictive baseline for understanding how governments respond to volatility in refugee and migrant flows in climate insecure areas. The project entails interviews with key stakeholders in Papua New Guinea, Australia, and the United States; analysis and archiving of the policy-related documents and literature regarding this agreement; and community-based data collection with individuals living in Manus. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The research, a collaborative effort between American anthropologists and legal scholars from Papua New Guinea, will be of interest to researchers in anthropology, political science, environmental science, and international relations. The intellectual merit of the project is grounded in the anthropology of migration and immigration, the anthropology of intercultural relations, especially with regard to xenophobia, the anthropology of post-colonial relations between nations, and the anthropology of sovereignty.   &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This is an important test case for how nations will accommodate the estimated 330 million climate-related refugees that are expected over the next 50 years. The objectives of the proposed project are to understand the social, economic, and legal aspects of this situation and to examine it as a precursor to what is predicted to happen with climate-related migration and asylum seekers in the Pacific over the next fifty years. The outcomes and broader impacts will be predictive models that can be used in the governance of these migrations. Economic and national security perceptions and immigration policy in the United States and elsewhere will be shaped by important test cases such as this.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>01/22/2014</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>01/22/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.075</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1401341</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>J.C.</FirstName>
<LastName>Salyer</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>J.C. Salyer</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>JSalyer@gc.cuny.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2128546465</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000655073</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>01/22/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Paige</FirstName>
<LastName>West</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Paige West</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>cw2031@columbia.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2128546465</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000655548</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>01/22/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Barnard College</Name>
<CityName>New York</CityName>
<ZipCode>100276598</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2128542708</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>3009 BROADWAY</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>10</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NY10</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>068119601</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>BARNARD COLLEGE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>068119601</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Barnard College]]></Name>
<CityName>New York</CityName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<ZipCode>100276598</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[3009 BROADWAY]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>10</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NY10</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1390</Code>
<Text>Cultural Anthropology</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1390</Code>
<Text>CULTURAL ANTHROPOLOGY</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7914</Code>
<Text>RAPID</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0114</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~25000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><strong>Project Outcomes Report&nbsp; </strong></p> <p>In July 2013 the Prime Ministers of Australia and Papua New Guinea agreed to the <em>Regional Resettlement Arrangement between Australia and Papua New Guinea</em> (colloquially known as &ldquo;The Papua New Guinea Solution&rdquo;) an international agreement that diverts asylum seekers who attempt to reach Australia by boat to Manus Province, Papua New Guinea, for immediate detention and processing, and then eventual resettlement in Papua New Guinea. This project asked a series of questions about how this agreement affected the social and economic lives of people living in Manus, how much about this agreement was understood by the larger public in Papua New Guinea, and what are the broad political reactions to this agreement among government officials and others in places of power in Papua New Guinea. We conducted nine months of data collection for this project which included 150 interviews, the building of an archive of materials documenting <em>Regional Resettlement Arrangement between Australia and Papua New Guinea</em> and people&rsquo;s reactions to it, and village visits, detention center visits, and walking trips in and around the center and the town. We have several significant findings.</p> <p>We found that the residents of Manus province believe the Regional Resettlement Arrangement between Australia and Papua New Guinea to be a direct challenge to both the sovereignty of their province and their nation, that the broader population of Papua New Guinea also sees the Regional Resettlement Arrangement between Australia and Papua New Guinea as a direct challenge to their sovereignty. As well as what many of the national elites call a &ldquo;re colonization&rdquo; of Papua New Guinea by Australia. We also found that the Regional Resettlement Arrangement between Australia and Papua New Guinea generated significant, but sporadically distributed, economic benefits in Manus, as well as in Papua New Guinea in general. These benefits included formal development projects such as the redevelopment of the main market, formal employment related to the Regional Resettlement Arrangement between Australia and Papua New Guinea, and ancillary economic benefits.</p> <p><strong>Intellectual Merit</strong></p> <p>The Manus Island Detention Center calls the sovereignty of Manus Islanders into question and brings the newer discussions within anthropology regarding sovereignty to the Papua New Guinea context. This is important because scholars of Papua New Guinea, a place often cited in terms of the fact that 97 % of the land is owned by its indigenous peoples, have not engaged fruitfully with the growing literature on sovereignty within the discipline, even as others working in the Pacific have made this a center point to their research. The solution&rsquo;s origin, a private meeting between two heads of state, without consultation with the national parliament in either country calls into question the efficacy of political and legal process in both countries.</p> <p><strong>Broader Impacts</strong></p> <p>Site specifically, with PNG as a former colony of Australia, and the emerging national discourse in PNG around neo-colonial practice, our work calls into question how, given the migration that is predicted to happen over the next 50 years due to various drivers post-colonial societies and states are going to be coerced by their former colonizers to bear the burden of the global refugee problem. This project addresses issues of national sovereignty as they relate to controlling the boundaries of the nation-state as well as the allocation of the burdens of the international human rights obligations. These results have a broad impact in that they show us how these sorts of solutions to problems of migration and mobility are experienced on-the-ground.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 10/01/2015<br>      Modified by: Paige&nb...]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Project Outcomes Report    In July 2013 the Prime Ministers of Australia and Papua New Guinea agreed to the Regional Resettlement Arrangement between Australia and Papua New Guinea (colloquially known as "The Papua New Guinea Solution") an international agreement that diverts asylum seekers who attempt to reach Australia by boat to Manus Province, Papua New Guinea, for immediate detention and processing, and then eventual resettlement in Papua New Guinea. This project asked a series of questions about how this agreement affected the social and economic lives of people living in Manus, how much about this agreement was understood by the larger public in Papua New Guinea, and what are the broad political reactions to this agreement among government officials and others in places of power in Papua New Guinea. We conducted nine months of data collection for this project which included 150 interviews, the building of an archive of materials documenting Regional Resettlement Arrangement between Australia and Papua New Guinea and peopleÆs reactions to it, and village visits, detention center visits, and walking trips in and around the center and the town. We have several significant findings.  We found that the residents of Manus province believe the Regional Resettlement Arrangement between Australia and Papua New Guinea to be a direct challenge to both the sovereignty of their province and their nation, that the broader population of Papua New Guinea also sees the Regional Resettlement Arrangement between Australia and Papua New Guinea as a direct challenge to their sovereignty. As well as what many of the national elites call a "re colonization" of Papua New Guinea by Australia. We also found that the Regional Resettlement Arrangement between Australia and Papua New Guinea generated significant, but sporadically distributed, economic benefits in Manus, as well as in Papua New Guinea in general. These benefits included formal development projects such as the redevelopment of the main market, formal employment related to the Regional Resettlement Arrangement between Australia and Papua New Guinea, and ancillary economic benefits.  Intellectual Merit  The Manus Island Detention Center calls the sovereignty of Manus Islanders into question and brings the newer discussions within anthropology regarding sovereignty to the Papua New Guinea context. This is important because scholars of Papua New Guinea, a place often cited in terms of the fact that 97 % of the land is owned by its indigenous peoples, have not engaged fruitfully with the growing literature on sovereignty within the discipline, even as others working in the Pacific have made this a center point to their research. The solutionÆs origin, a private meeting between two heads of state, without consultation with the national parliament in either country calls into question the efficacy of political and legal process in both countries.  Broader Impacts  Site specifically, with PNG as a former colony of Australia, and the emerging national discourse in PNG around neo-colonial practice, our work calls into question how, given the migration that is predicted to happen over the next 50 years due to various drivers post-colonial societies and states are going to be coerced by their former colonizers to bear the burden of the global refugee problem. This project addresses issues of national sovereignty as they relate to controlling the boundaries of the nation-state as well as the allocation of the burdens of the international human rights obligations. These results have a broad impact in that they show us how these sorts of solutions to problems of migration and mobility are experienced on-the-ground.       Last Modified: 10/01/2015       Submitted by: Paige West]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
