<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>DISSERTATION RESEARCH: Evolutionary Responses of Plants to Urban Environments</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>06/01/2014</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2015</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>19719.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>19719</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>08010207</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>BIO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DEB</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Environmental Biology</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Samuel Scheiner</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>sscheine@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927175</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Cities are among the most heavily altered of human environments.  They are hotter, drier, and differ in in air quality than neighboring rural areas and thereby city-dwelling organisms experience environments distinctly different than those experienced in rural areas. Therefore, urban environments are likely similar to predicted future climate conditions.  Understanding how adaptations by plants allow them to thrive in cities will not only provide insight into how plant populations have survived in urban environments but also help us understand the potential effects of future climates on plant growth. A greenhouse study using seeds collected from Minneapolis and St. Paul, MN and neighboring rural areas revealed that plants from urban areas grow faster and larger than plants from rural areas. The proposed research, which will accompany ongoing manipulative experiments, is to sample multiple plant species from three other urban areas, (Chicago, Detroit and New York), in order to determine if there are similar suites of growth characteristics that differentiate urban from rural plant populations.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Understanding adaptation and acclimation to urban environments, the focus of the proposed research, is important for urban biodiversity and conservation, for management of urban parks and for developing plant varieties that thrive in urban environments. The study of urban plant populations also provides an ideal system for scientific outreach and education. Many people think of ecology as understanding organisms in pristine environments, and evolution as a slow process, but this is not true and this proposed research focuses on understanding the interplay between ecological processes and evolutionary forces in urban environments. This work is being carried out at multiple high schools and community colleges engaging students and community members to get involved in understanding how plant populations may respond to climate change scenarios, which are expected to be characterized by shifts in abiotic factors similar to those experienced by urban plant populations.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>04/08/2014</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>04/08/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.074</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1401222</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Peter</FirstName>
<LastName>Tiffin</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>L</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Peter L Tiffin</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>ptiffin@umn.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6126247406</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000380761</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/08/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Mohamed</FirstName>
<LastName>Yakub</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Mohamed Yakub</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>yakub002@umn.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6126246348</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000654588</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/08/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Minnesota-Twin Cities</Name>
<CityName>Minneapolis</CityName>
<ZipCode>554552070</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6126245599</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>200 OAK ST SE</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Minnesota</StateName>
<StateCode>MN</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MN05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>555917996</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>REGENTS OF THE UNIVERSITY OF MINNESOTA</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>117178941</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Minnesota-Twin Cities]]></Name>
<CityName>St. Paul</CityName>
<StateCode>MN</StateCode>
<ZipCode>551081095</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[1445 Gortner Avenue]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Minnesota</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MN04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7377</Code>
<Text>EVOLUTIONARY ECOLOGY</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9169</Code>
<Text>BIODIVERSITY AND ECOSYSTEM DYNAMICS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9179</Code>
<Text>GRADUATE INVOLVEMENT</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>EGCH</Code>
<Text>ENVIRONMENT AND GLOBAL CHANGE</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>SMET</Code>
<Text>SCIENCE, MATH, ENG &amp; TECH EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0114</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~19719</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><strong>Intellectual Merit</strong>:</p> <p>&nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp;Cities, the home to the majority of the world&rsquo;s human population, are also home to many plants and animals.&nbsp; From a biological perspective, cities are interesting environments because they are drastically different from rural and natural areas that surround them. &nbsp;Cities also are drastically different from the environments in which species evolved.&nbsp; This award provided support for sampling seeds of multiple plant species living in the urban cores (Minneapolis/Saint Paul, Chicago, Detroit, New York, and Baltimore) and surrounding rural areas, and then conducting experiments to compare the characteristics of the plants collected from these different areas when they were grown in common environments.&nbsp; The analyses completed thus far have revealed evidence for a genetic-based &ldquo;urban phenotype&rdquo; with plants from cities developing faster, having fewer leaves, and growing taller than rural plants.&nbsp; Genomic data also indicate that plants from the paired city/rural areas are more closely related than the different city populations are to one another.&nbsp; This indicates that the urban phenotype we found has evolved repeatedly, consistent with the urban-rural differences in plant traits representing adaptations to the urban environment.&nbsp; These results provide an example of how human activities shape evolution. &nbsp;Because urban environments differ from rural environments in ways that are similar to how climates are expected to differ from current climates (warmer, more irregular precipitation) the adaptations we identified also may reflect how populations will change with ongoing climate change.&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;<strong>Broader Impacts</strong>:</p> <p>&nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp;This award helped support several outreach and training activities.&nbsp; First, the research supported by the award was central to the doctoral dissertation work and training of Mohammed (Mo) Yakub, a student who grew up in Kenya and became a U.S. citizen while a graduate student.&nbsp; Second, four undergraduate students, including 3 women, received first-hand research experiences by either helping with the research or conducting experiments that were complimentary to this research.&nbsp; One of these students, a woman from an undergraduate serving institution, conducted an experiment that will be integrated into an upcoming publication. &nbsp;This student is planning to apply for graduate school in some area of the biological sciences.&nbsp; Finally, Mo is now working with Univ. Minnesota faculty to develop a research-laboratory based on urban/rural plant differences for the introductory biology Foundations course.&nbsp; No publications have yet resulted from the work, but at least two publications in peer-reviewed journals are expected within the next year.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 06/29/2015<br>      Modified by: Peter&nbsp;L&nbsp;Tiffin</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Intellectual Merit:       Cities, the home to the majority of the worldÆs human population, are also home to many plants and animals.  From a biological perspective, cities are interesting environments because they are drastically different from rural and natural areas that surround them.  Cities also are drastically different from the environments in which species evolved.  This award provided support for sampling seeds of multiple plant species living in the urban cores (Minneapolis/Saint Paul, Chicago, Detroit, New York, and Baltimore) and surrounding rural areas, and then conducting experiments to compare the characteristics of the plants collected from these different areas when they were grown in common environments.  The analyses completed thus far have revealed evidence for a genetic-based "urban phenotype" with plants from cities developing faster, having fewer leaves, and growing taller than rural plants.  Genomic data also indicate that plants from the paired city/rural areas are more closely related than the different city populations are to one another.  This indicates that the urban phenotype we found has evolved repeatedly, consistent with the urban-rural differences in plant traits representing adaptations to the urban environment.  These results provide an example of how human activities shape evolution.  Because urban environments differ from rural environments in ways that are similar to how climates are expected to differ from current climates (warmer, more irregular precipitation) the adaptations we identified also may reflect how populations will change with ongoing climate change.       Broader Impacts:       This award helped support several outreach and training activities.  First, the research supported by the award was central to the doctoral dissertation work and training of Mohammed (Mo) Yakub, a student who grew up in Kenya and became a U.S. citizen while a graduate student.  Second, four undergraduate students, including 3 women, received first-hand research experiences by either helping with the research or conducting experiments that were complimentary to this research.  One of these students, a woman from an undergraduate serving institution, conducted an experiment that will be integrated into an upcoming publication.  This student is planning to apply for graduate school in some area of the biological sciences.  Finally, Mo is now working with Univ. Minnesota faculty to develop a research-laboratory based on urban/rural plant differences for the introductory biology Foundations course.  No publications have yet resulted from the work, but at least two publications in peer-reviewed journals are expected within the next year.          Last Modified: 06/29/2015       Submitted by: Peter L Tiffin]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
