<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>I-Corps:  Commercialization Feasibility Study of Mesocale Planar Heliostats</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>01/01/2014</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>04/30/2016</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>50000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>50000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07070000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>IIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Industrial Innovation &amp; Partnersh</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>lydia mcclure</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This project plans to further develop an organic agriculture technology that has the potential to treat soil and water using a service-based model for farmers. Exploration of scaling of heliostats indicates that reducing the size of mirrors can lead to reduced weight and high speed control for fast maneuvering of focus spot. The scaling of mirrors and off- the-shelve actuators to move mirrors indicates that mesoscale heliostats that are planar is possible. These planar heliostats are capable of being attached to vertical surfaces, can be remotely actuated, and have low mass for easy installation on mobile platforms at a low cost. The mobility of the heliostat technology enables one to transport concentrated solar capability to anywhere, and hence enable a service based model for solar-thermal applications. An objective of the project is to determine the degree to which concentrated solar thermal systems can be useful. This will be done by studying the maximum power flux that can be achieved in the face of motion, under varying solar illumination, and in a safe way. The use of both UV and IR components presents a way to not only use purely thermal mechanism to treat agricultural material like soil, but also to use photo-chemical approaches. The understanding of these approaches would enable a paradigm for sustainable agriculture.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The potential to use solar concentrated sunlight to clean soils, can not only reduce the energy use, but also reduce the health and environmental harmful effects of pesticides. This work will aim at eliminating pesticides, leading to reduced contamination of soil with cancer-causing chemicals, making food safer both for farm-workers and consumers. The project aims to eliminate the use of gaseous pesticides such as methyl-bromide, which is a strong green- house gas, and reduce the rate of ozone depletion. By reducing the use of liquid pesticides, and the associated fossil-fuel used to make them, this technology will reduce the released CO2, decreasing the effect of farming on global warming. By enabling soil-sterilization using the sun, even in areas where sun is not bright enough, food yield can be increased while reducing cost of production. The team estimates that the cost of fruit production would drop by 15-20% percent to enable lower cost fruit availability.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>12/03/2013</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>04/01/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1401669</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Amit</FirstName>
<LastName>Lal</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Amit Lal</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>lal@ece.cornell.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6072559374</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000244509</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>12/03/2013</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Cornell University</Name>
<CityName>Ithaca</CityName>
<ZipCode>148502820</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6072555014</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>373 Pine Tree Road</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>23</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NY23</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>872612445</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>CORNELL UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>002254837</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Suntomics]]></Name>
<CityName>Ithaca</CityName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<ZipCode>148501294</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[95 Brown Road]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>23</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NY23</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>8023</Code>
<Text>I-Corps</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0114</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~50000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><span>1. As part of the I-Corps training we interviewed ~101 customers in the agriculture sector on eliminating pests using the solar concentrator technology. We determined the following market segments:</span></p> <p><span>a. Strawberry farmers that utilize methyl-bromide and chemical treatments - these farmers are forced to use more environmentally friendly approaches as hazards of chemicals to near-farm communities have been elucidated by data.&nbsp;</span></p> <p><span>b. Organic farmers growing many high value crops including strawberries: Organic farmers cannot use pesticides&nbsp;and hence need help in soil treatment for anything they grow.</span></p> <p><span>c. Citrus farmers _ the disease called the HLB greening has led to significant citrus tree death in Florida. We investigated a truck based solar treatment can heat the tree for treating the tree, possibly utilizing the UV in the sun as well.</span></p> <p><span>d. Weeding &ndash; many farmers indicated that the shield problem is labor cost in weeding plants. Hence, the ability to use concentrated solar energy to thermally weeds would be significant. </span></p> <p><span>2. We won the best team award at the ICORPS cohort.</span></p> <p><span>3. Using off-the-shelf pan-tilt stages, 3D printing, and arduino microcontrollers we realized an array of 12 mirror arrays. We developed software to focus the mirrors.</span></p> <p><span>4. We used this array to expose trees in Florida, working at the USDA laboratory in Florida. We demonstrated the ability to burn tree segments, and the damage to trees over time was observed, with eventually recovery of the leaves after the tree has healed. </span></p> <p><span>5. We demonstrated reduction of parasites in soil by 40% as verified by two independent lab results. One of the lab was ta Cornell, and another is a private soil analysis company.</span></p> <p><span>6. We wrote two proposals to NSF regarding further funding. These were not funded, although we did get very close to getting one funded but was not funded due to lack of funds at NSF. These proposals led to much needed feedback from industry experts.</span></p> <p><span>7. We wrote one proposal to USDA regarding HLB tree treatment &ndash; it was not funded. However, the joint work led to the establishment of the technique being able to treat trees.</span></p> <p><span>8. We have moved the prototype unit to California where experiments can be done remotely through the web. </span></p> <p><span>9. We collaborated with Cornell Crop Sciences Department to get contaminated soil from Cornell Geneva campus, on which we performed soil solarization experiments.</span></p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 03/31/2016<br>      Modified by: Amit&nbsp;Lal</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ 1. As part of the I-Corps training we interviewed ~101 customers in the agriculture sector on eliminating pests using the solar concentrator technology. We determined the following market segments:  a. Strawberry farmers that utilize methyl-bromide and chemical treatments - these farmers are forced to use more environmentally friendly approaches as hazards of chemicals to near-farm communities have been elucidated by data.   b. Organic farmers growing many high value crops including strawberries: Organic farmers cannot use pesticides and hence need help in soil treatment for anything they grow.  c. Citrus farmers _ the disease called the HLB greening has led to significant citrus tree death in Florida. We investigated a truck based solar treatment can heat the tree for treating the tree, possibly utilizing the UV in the sun as well.  d. Weeding &ndash; many farmers indicated that the shield problem is labor cost in weeding plants. Hence, the ability to use concentrated solar energy to thermally weeds would be significant.   2. We won the best team award at the ICORPS cohort.  3. Using off-the-shelf pan-tilt stages, 3D printing, and arduino microcontrollers we realized an array of 12 mirror arrays. We developed software to focus the mirrors.  4. We used this array to expose trees in Florida, working at the USDA laboratory in Florida. We demonstrated the ability to burn tree segments, and the damage to trees over time was observed, with eventually recovery of the leaves after the tree has healed.   5. We demonstrated reduction of parasites in soil by 40% as verified by two independent lab results. One of the lab was ta Cornell, and another is a private soil analysis company.  6. We wrote two proposals to NSF regarding further funding. These were not funded, although we did get very close to getting one funded but was not funded due to lack of funds at NSF. These proposals led to much needed feedback from industry experts.  7. We wrote one proposal to USDA regarding HLB tree treatment &ndash; it was not funded. However, the joint work led to the establishment of the technique being able to treat trees.  8. We have moved the prototype unit to California where experiments can be done remotely through the web.   9. We collaborated with Cornell Crop Sciences Department to get contaminated soil from Cornell Geneva campus, on which we performed soil solarization experiments.          Last Modified: 03/31/2016       Submitted by: Amit Lal]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
