<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Studies of Nuclear Reactions and Structure</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/15/2014</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>4560000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>4655000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03010000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>PHY</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Physics</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Allena K. Opper</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>aopper@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032928958</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This award funds a broad program of measurements in nuclear physics by faculty and students at Florida State University (FSU).  The experiments include studies of nuclear reactions and decays that play key roles in all stages of stellar processes.  This aspect of the program supports the large investment made and being made in astronomical observations worldwide.  Other experiments focus on the evolution of nuclear shell structure with increasing neutron number, especially near the magic numbers of 20 and 28.  The behavior of nuclei at ultra-high spin will be explored through discrete gamma spectroscopy using arrays of gamma detectors at FSU and at the National Superconducting Cyclotron Laboratory (NSCL).  The group will also exploit heavy ion collisions at the Relativistic Heavy Ion Collider (RHIC) to investigate the characteristics of the quark-gluon plasma.  The broader societal impacts of this project lie in the education and training of undergraduate and graduate students in a hands-on environment.  Florida State University has served as one of the leading educators in the field of nuclear physics (4th highest Ph.D. production in the U.S.) and this grant will enable the group to continue to attract and train the best and brightest graduate students in experimental nuclear physics.  Because of the students' training and hands-on work with high tech equipment in a forefront nuclear physics laboratory, FSU graduates are in high demand and now serve in key roles in homeland security, national defense, high-tech industry, leading edge research, and STEM education.   Finally, these measurements will be important for understanding stellar processes and the abundance of elements in our universe. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;A significant part of the proposed research uses short-lived rare nuclear isotopes from the FSU Fox Laboratory to study nuclear reactions and structure in unstable nuclei.  This is very important for reactions of astrophysical importance, many of which proceed through unstable nuclei.  These beams have low intensity and so will benefit from the ANASEN active target and detector array recently developed by FSU in collaboration with Louisiana State University.  A newly developed neutron detector array (RESONEUT) will be used to study (d,n) reactions in inverse kinematics with radioactive beams.  A series of experiments is planned to measure the critical parameter of lifetime following beta decay of heavy, neutron-rich nuclei on and close to the expected r-process path at TRIUMF.  The confrontation of state-of-the-art shell model calculations for multiple cross-shell excitations with proposed nuclear structure measurements will strengthen their reliability for extrapolation to the astrophysically important region.  The FSU 14C beam will be used to explore nuclear structure in more neutron-rich nuclei with a recently digitized Germanium detector array.  Measurements using gamma detector arrays (GRETINA and GAMMASPHERE) will explore newly proposed exotic shapes and ultra-high-spin structures in the atomic mass ~ 150 region.  Other work involves studying the quark-gluon plasma with heavy flavor probes using the PHENIX detector system, parts of which were constructed at FSU.  In this instance the FSU focus is on the effects of cold nuclear matter on heavy quarkonia production.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/03/2014</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/15/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1401574</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Samuel</FirstName>
<LastName>Tabor</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>L</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Samuel L Tabor</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>tabor@nucmar.physics.fsu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>8506445528</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000481648</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/03/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Paul</FirstName>
<LastName>Cottle</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>D</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Paul D Cottle</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>pcottle@fsu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>8506445777</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000113732</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/03/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Mark</FirstName>
<LastName>Riley</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>A</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Mark A Riley</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>mriley@nucmar.physics.fsu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>8506442867</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000347221</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/03/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Anthony</FirstName>
<LastName>Frawley</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>D</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Anthony D Frawley</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>frawley@fsunuc.physics.fsu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>8506444034</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000268457</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/03/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Ingo</FirstName>
<LastName>Wiedenhoever</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Ingo Wiedenhoever</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>iwiedenhover@physics.fsu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>8506441429</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000300632</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/03/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Florida State University</Name>
<CityName>TALLAHASSEE</CityName>
<ZipCode>323064166</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>8506445260</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>874 Traditions Way, 3rd Floor</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Florida</StateName>
<StateCode>FL</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>FL02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>790877419</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>FLORIDA STATE UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>159621697</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Florida State University]]></Name>
<CityName>Tallahassee</CityName>
<StateCode>FL</StateCode>
<ZipCode>323064166</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[1060 Atomic way]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Florida</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>FL02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1233</Code>
<Text>NUCLEAR STRUCTURE &amp; REACTIONS</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7201</Code>
<Text>NUCLEAR ASTROPHYSICS</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>0000</Code>
<Text>UNASSIGNED</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>OTHR</Code>
<Text>OTHER RESEARCH OR EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0114</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0115</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0116</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~1520000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2015~1615000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2016~1520000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>This grant supported the hands-on training in experimental nuclear physics for over a dozen Ph.D. students and a number of undergraduate physics majors.&nbsp; During the period Scott Miller, Justin Von Moss, David McPherson, Joseph Belarge, Jessica Baker, Sean Kuvin, Jeffrey Klatsky, Rutger Dungan, Pei-Luan Tai, and John Parker received Ph.D. degrees based on research supported by this grant and are now employed in homeland security, education, and industry.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>Major improvements have been made in our laboratory during this period including installation of a giant split-pole magnetic spectrometer previously located at Yale University and considerable upgrades of the gamma detector array, including an automatic liquid filling system, modern state of the art high voltage power supply, and the loan of 3 quad-crystal &ldquo;clover&rdquo; gamma spectrometers from Oak Ridge National Laboratory.&nbsp; Our facilities attract outside experimenters from other universities and national laboratories.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>Our almost world-unique radioactive 14C beam was used for a number of experiments detecting particle and gamma emission from hard to produce neutron-rich nuclei to extend a theoretical model of nuclear structure to help predict the behavior of even-more exotic nuclei to be studied in the near future at the national Facility for Rare-Ion Beams.&nbsp; A surprising discovery was the existence of 6 states in 19O and 3 in 27Mg&nbsp; which are unbound to neutron decay but decay instead by gamma emission despite the fact that neutron decay is typically a million times faster than gamma decay.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>Found that the lowest spin-parity 4+ state in exotic 44S is isomeric with a half-life of ~60 ps because of high-K character.&nbsp; A measurement of the 19Ne(p,gamma) reaction shows that it does not constitute a bottleneck in the breakout phase from astrophysical X-ray burst events.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>Made first direct observation of enhanced octupole collectivity in 144Ba and 146Ba confirming a previous theoretical prediction.&nbsp; The experiment used the advanced capabilities of the new GRETINA gamma tracking array and the CHICO2 heavy-ion counter at Argonne National Lab.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>Analyzed a measurement of the J/Psi nuclear modification factor with significantly better statistical and systematic precision than any previous measurements.&nbsp; Showed that in 200 GeV/nucleon collisions at the Relativistic Heavy-Ion Collider at Brookhaven National Lab. the J/Psi suppression is slightly weaker in U+U collisions than in Au+Au ones despite a ~20% higher energy density in U+U.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 07/31/2018<br>      Modified by: Samuel&nbsp;L&nbsp;Tabor</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ This grant supported the hands-on training in experimental nuclear physics for over a dozen Ph.D. students and a number of undergraduate physics majors.  During the period Scott Miller, Justin Von Moss, David McPherson, Joseph Belarge, Jessica Baker, Sean Kuvin, Jeffrey Klatsky, Rutger Dungan, Pei-Luan Tai, and John Parker received Ph.D. degrees based on research supported by this grant and are now employed in homeland security, education, and industry.     Major improvements have been made in our laboratory during this period including installation of a giant split-pole magnetic spectrometer previously located at Yale University and considerable upgrades of the gamma detector array, including an automatic liquid filling system, modern state of the art high voltage power supply, and the loan of 3 quad-crystal "clover" gamma spectrometers from Oak Ridge National Laboratory.  Our facilities attract outside experimenters from other universities and national laboratories.     Our almost world-unique radioactive 14C beam was used for a number of experiments detecting particle and gamma emission from hard to produce neutron-rich nuclei to extend a theoretical model of nuclear structure to help predict the behavior of even-more exotic nuclei to be studied in the near future at the national Facility for Rare-Ion Beams.  A surprising discovery was the existence of 6 states in 19O and 3 in 27Mg  which are unbound to neutron decay but decay instead by gamma emission despite the fact that neutron decay is typically a million times faster than gamma decay.     Found that the lowest spin-parity 4+ state in exotic 44S is isomeric with a half-life of ~60 ps because of high-K character.  A measurement of the 19Ne(p,gamma) reaction shows that it does not constitute a bottleneck in the breakout phase from astrophysical X-ray burst events.     Made first direct observation of enhanced octupole collectivity in 144Ba and 146Ba confirming a previous theoretical prediction.  The experiment used the advanced capabilities of the new GRETINA gamma tracking array and the CHICO2 heavy-ion counter at Argonne National Lab.     Analyzed a measurement of the J/Psi nuclear modification factor with significantly better statistical and systematic precision than any previous measurements.  Showed that in 200 GeV/nucleon collisions at the Relativistic Heavy-Ion Collider at Brookhaven National Lab. the J/Psi suppression is slightly weaker in U+U collisions than in Au+Au ones despite a ~20% higher energy density in U+U.             Last Modified: 07/31/2018       Submitted by: Samuel L Tabor]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
