<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Acquisition and Implementation of a Cameca SX-100 Electron Microprobe Laboratory, University of Oklahoma</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2014</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2016</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>143244.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>171892</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>06030202</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>GEO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>EAR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Earth Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>David Lambert</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>dlambert@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924736</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This award will fund the upgrade of a used, 5-spectrometer Cameca Instruments SX-100 that was decommissioned by Sandia National Laboratory and which the principal investigators claimed from surplus through DOE's Laboratory Equipment Donation Program. Along with other essential lab components, this award will bring this instrument to fully operational status, which will ensure that this regional facility remains open and ready for use well into the future. Equipment to be funded includes a new operational personal computer (PC), a PC-based automation package, associated firmware, a silicon-drifted solid-state energy-dispersive x-ray analyzer with Peltier cooler, and upgrades to the evaporative coater. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Regular users of the facility come mostly from geology, but faculty members and students of anthropology, other natural sciences, and engineering are frequent and sometimes lengthy users. Examples of research to be enabled by the upgraded instrument include:  experimental studies of isotope chemistry H and F among garnet, tourmaline, and silicate melts, experiments to define a stability field for kimzeyite, a Zr-rich garnet, and studies of crystal nucleation and fabric in silicate liquids.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/18/2014</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>10/20/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.050</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1401940</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>David</FirstName>
<LastName>London</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>David London</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>dlondon@ou.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>4053257626</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000362860</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/18/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>George</FirstName>
<LastName>Morgan</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>B</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME>VI</PI_SUFX_NAME>
<PI_FULL_NAME>George B Morgan</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>gmorgan@ou.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>4053252642</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000278413</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/18/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Oklahoma Norman Campus</Name>
<CityName>NORMAN</CityName>
<ZipCode>730199705</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>4053254757</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>201 Stephenson Parkway</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[Five Partners Place, Suite 3100]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Oklahoma</StateName>
<StateCode>OK</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>OK04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>848348348</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF OKLAHOMA</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>046862181</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Electron Microprobe Laboratory]]></Name>
<CityName>Norman</CityName>
<StateCode>OK</StateCode>
<ZipCode>730191001</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[100 E. Boyd St, Rm 106 SEC]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Oklahoma</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>OK04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1580</Code>
<Text>Instrumentation &amp; Facilities</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EPSCoR Co-Funding</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0114</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0115</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~143244</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2015~28648</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>We replaced a Cameca SX50 electron microprobe (27 years old) that was obtained with U.S. DoE grant&nbsp;DE-FG22-87FE1146 with a Cameca SX100 electron microprobe (12 years old) was was acquired through donation from the U.S. Department of Energy. This grant NSF EAR-1401940 covered approximately&nbsp;half of the cost of installation and computer upgrades, with the remainder provided by the Office of the Vice President of Research at the University of Oklahoma.</p> <p>The electron microprobe is the standard analytical instrument for the chemical and spatial analysis of solids, including minerals, metals, ceramics, and all nature of other materials for which characterization at the scale of micrometers to millimeters is needed.</p> <p>The Electron Microprobe Laboratory at the University of Oklahoma serves as one of the few such installations in the Central Plains that is available to all clients from academia, government, and private industry or individuals. In addition to personnel from the University of Oklahoma, our laboratory is heavily utilized by academic professionals from several universities in north Texas, from Kansas, and by researchers at the Los Alamos National Laboratory.</p> <p>The installation of the SX100 ensures the continued operation of this lab. This instrument also provides enhanced graphics and data analysis that were not obtainable on our ould SX50.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 09/30/2016<br>      Modified by: David&nbsp;London</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Image         </div> <div class="galControls onePhoto" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation onePhoto" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2016/1401940/1401940_10334391_1475254187504_SX100photoforpublicity--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2016/1401940/1401940_10334391_1475254187504_SX100photoforpublicity--rgov-800width.jpg" title="SX100 Electron Microprobe"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2016/1401940/1401940_10334391_1475254187504_SX100photoforpublicity--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="SX100 Electron Microprobe"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">The SX100 Electron Microprobe became operational in 2015. The instrument was acquired by donation from the U.S. Department of Energy.</div> <div class="imageCredit">George B. Morgan</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Public Domain</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">David&nbsp;London</div> <div class="imageTitle">SX100 Electron Microprobe</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ We replaced a Cameca SX50 electron microprobe (27 years old) that was obtained with U.S. DoE grant DE-FG22-87FE1146 with a Cameca SX100 electron microprobe (12 years old) was was acquired through donation from the U.S. Department of Energy. This grant NSF EAR-1401940 covered approximately half of the cost of installation and computer upgrades, with the remainder provided by the Office of the Vice President of Research at the University of Oklahoma.  The electron microprobe is the standard analytical instrument for the chemical and spatial analysis of solids, including minerals, metals, ceramics, and all nature of other materials for which characterization at the scale of micrometers to millimeters is needed.  The Electron Microprobe Laboratory at the University of Oklahoma serves as one of the few such installations in the Central Plains that is available to all clients from academia, government, and private industry or individuals. In addition to personnel from the University of Oklahoma, our laboratory is heavily utilized by academic professionals from several universities in north Texas, from Kansas, and by researchers at the Los Alamos National Laboratory.  The installation of the SX100 ensures the continued operation of this lab. This instrument also provides enhanced graphics and data analysis that were not obtainable on our ould SX50.       Last Modified: 09/30/2016       Submitted by: David London]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
