<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Collaborative Research: Nuclear Reaction and Structure Studies with Radioactive and Stable Beams</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2014</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>120000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>130000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03010000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>PHY</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Physics</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Allena K. Opper</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>aopper@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032928958</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The research funded by this award is designed to promote a better understanding of atomic nuclei, the basic building blocks of all normal matter in the Universe.  How did they form following the Big Bang, and how do they now interact to change their basic elemental nature?  Are there new forms of matter made up from very exotic types of atomic nuclei and how might we make and study these?  To this end the group will develop special new techniques in nuclear science, as well as train future scientists that can help answer some of these questions.  One important training component will be a continuation of the well-established and highly successful outreach to faculty and students at New Buffalo High School in Michigan that has introduced these students to interesting, important, and exciting careers in the sciences.  The technology developed and used in this research will have applications in other important areas, such as homeland security (nuclear terrorism), the safe storage and monitoring of nuclear wastes, and applications in nuclear medicine, including radiation therapy. The latter includes a new modality directly related to this research: the production and imaging of ion beams to treat particular forms of cancer tumors. Nearly 50% of graduate students and other personnel trained in the group's past research projects are currently pursuing careers in nuclear security or nuclear medicine, and it is anticipated that this will continue as a result of the present grant.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The proposed project will involve the study of nuclear reactions utilizing stable as well as short-lived radioactive nuclear beams, together with the development of instrumentation, techniques, and apparatus to facilitate such studies.  This includes use of the TwinSol low-energy radioactive ion-beam facility in operation at the University of Notre Dame (ND), developed jointly by the University of Michigan (UM) and ND.  Specific experiments will emphasize the investigation of the structure and reaction mechanisms of neutron- and proton-rich nuclei near the limits of nuclear stability to elucidate the effect that the exotic "nuclear halo" structure, which appears for weakly-bound systems at the limits of stability, has on fusion, transfer, inelastic excitation, and breakup probabilities near the Coulomb barrier.  Of particular interest here is the influence that higher-order couplings to and within the continuum have on the various reaction mechanisms, since proximity to the continuum is the characteristic defining feature of weakly-bound systems.  These studies will be carried out at TwinSol in collaboration with a group from the National Superconducting Cyclotron Laboratory (NSCL), utilizing a prototype active-target time-projection chamber (AT-TPC).  A related program will use the full AT-TPC recently commissioned at the reaccelerated beam facility (ReA3) at NSCL.  &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;In addition, the UM-UND collaboration, under the primary direction of the UM research group and their colleagues, will continue advanced development and application of deuterated scintillators for nuclear measurements involving neutrons.  This will include selected measurements of (d,n) and (3He,n) reactions involving both stable and unstable beams, and in particular 7Be(d,n) which is of interest in astrophysics.  Since these detectors permit neutron spectroscopy and cross section measurements without neutron time-of-flight, they have a particular advantage when used with the high-intensity, low-energy, non-pulsed accelerators suitable for nuclear astrophysics measurements.   The latter includes the new 5 MV accelerator recently installed at ND and we will pursue such experiments, and in particular several key (A,n) measurements, together with the nuclear astrophysics group at ND.  &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The unique neutron detector array the group has recently developed has potential for wide-spread applications both in nuclear science as well as in homeland-security and nuclear non-proliferation. As in the past, the proposed work will involve graduate and undergraduate students from ND and UM, together with faculty members and students from several primarily undergraduate schools located in close proximity to these universities. The highly-technical nature of the proposed research will thus contribute significantly to the training of a technically-literate work force.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/22/2014</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>04/14/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1401242</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Fred</FirstName>
<LastName>Becchetti</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>D</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Fred D Becchetti</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>fdb@umich.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>7347300664</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000386824</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/22/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Regents of the University of Michigan - Ann Arbor</Name>
<CityName>Ann Arbor</CityName>
<ZipCode>481091274</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>7347636438</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>3003 South State St. Room 1062</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Michigan</StateName>
<StateCode>MI</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>12</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MI12</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>073133571</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>REGENTS OF THE UNIVERSITY OF MICHIGAN</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>073133571</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Michigan Ann Arbor]]></Name>
<CityName>Ann Arbor</CityName>
<StateCode>MI</StateCode>
<ZipCode>481091040</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[450 Church Street]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Michigan</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>12</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MI12</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1233</Code>
<Text>NUCLEAR STRUCTURE &amp; REACTIONS</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9251</Code>
<Text>REU SUPP-Res Exp for Ugrd Supp</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0114</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0115</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0116</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~120000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2015~5000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2016~5000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>This work studied the properties of atomic nuclei not normally found in Nature.This included the devlopment of special advanced electronic instrumentation. The data obtained will help us better understand how the elements are made, how stars generate energy, and what determines their lifetime and eventual fate, including that of our Sun. The instrumentation&nbsp; developed can also be applied to many other outstanding problems in physics: What is the nature of the "missing" matter (dark matter) we see in gravity but do not see as regular matter (normal atomic elements in stars and galaxies). The instrumentation developed can also help in protecting our borders from nuclear threats, as an example to detect nuclear-weapons grade material being smuggled in trucks and cargo containers across our borders by terrorists. This project also provided new instrumention applicable to cancer therapy and in patrticular particle-beam therapy where it can help to better determine the dose to the patient and thus minimize irradiation of healthy tissue.&nbsp; It can also have applications in other areas of nuclear medicine. Finally as part of the above research, the project helped train many young scientists who will now teach at major colleges and universities, or work in industry, government research laboratories, or as medical physicists in hospitals, thus providing important services to our country and its citizens</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 10/01/2018<br>      Modified by: Fred&nbsp;D&nbsp;Becchetti</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ This work studied the properties of atomic nuclei not normally found in Nature.This included the devlopment of special advanced electronic instrumentation. The data obtained will help us better understand how the elements are made, how stars generate energy, and what determines their lifetime and eventual fate, including that of our Sun. The instrumentation  developed can also be applied to many other outstanding problems in physics: What is the nature of the "missing" matter (dark matter) we see in gravity but do not see as regular matter (normal atomic elements in stars and galaxies). The instrumentation developed can also help in protecting our borders from nuclear threats, as an example to detect nuclear-weapons grade material being smuggled in trucks and cargo containers across our borders by terrorists. This project also provided new instrumention applicable to cancer therapy and in patrticular particle-beam therapy where it can help to better determine the dose to the patient and thus minimize irradiation of healthy tissue.  It can also have applications in other areas of nuclear medicine. Finally as part of the above research, the project helped train many young scientists who will now teach at major colleges and universities, or work in industry, government research laboratories, or as medical physicists in hospitals, thus providing important services to our country and its citizens          Last Modified: 10/01/2018       Submitted by: Fred D Becchetti]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
