<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Radiative Double Electron Capture (RDEC) of Ions with Quasi-Free Electrons</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>10/01/2014</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>09/30/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>133532.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>133532</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03010000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>PHY</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Physics</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Alexander Cronin</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>acronin@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032920000</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Non-technical description:&lt;br/&gt;This project involves an investigation of how two of the smallest and most fundamental constituents of matter (electrons) exchange information with each other (the analog of "talking") when they are transferred from one atom to another as the two atoms move by each other quickly. In the process to be studied, the two electrons come from a target atom and are captured by a fast moving projectile ion (an atom missing some electrons on it initially) accompanied by the emission of a single x ray. The process can be thought of as the inverse of the double ionization (removal of two electrons) by a single photon. This two-electron process is similar to the one-electron process in which an electron is liberated by a single photon. The latter process is known as the photoelectric effect, which was explained by Einstein in 1905, for which he was awarded the Nobel Prize, and which underlies much of modern technology. During the two-electron process the electrons "talk" with each other and coordinate the double photo-ionization. The same must occur in the time-reversed case when two electrons are transferred to a projectile, giving up a photon. There is considerable interest in studying this "talking" process, from the point of view of collisions between ions and target atoms and from the time-reversed process of double photo-ionization of an atom by a single photon. Theorists have calculated probabilities for the two-electron process, with results differing by factors of 1,000 or even 10,000. This wide range leaves the field open for experiments that will determine the actual probability accurately. Up to now, five experiments of two-electron transfer with simultaneous emission of a photon have been attempted at laboratories in the U.S. and Germany. One of these experiments (in the U.S.) was partially successful, but the others were not, mostly due to the long measuring times required to see the events. Notably, photon collision researchers would be very much interested in measuring double photo-ionization of two-electron ions, something they cannot yet do, except for the two-electron atom helium. The involvement of Ph.D. students in the planned research gives them valuable training in state-of-the-art physics experiments, and along with the preparation of collaborative manuscripts and abstracts, help make them productive young scientists.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Technical description:&lt;br/&gt;The transfer of two electrons to an ion accompanied by the emission of a single photon is called radiative-double-electron capture, or RDEC for short. The intellectual merit of RDEC lies in its intrinsic fundamental interest in the field of ion collisions with quasi-free electrons, and its close relationship to photon interactions with highly-charged ions. This relationship is essentially the time inverse of RDEC, which is the process of double photo-ionization of ions. These inverse processes are particularly connected when RDEC occurs for incident fully-stripped ions and double photo-ionization for two-electron systems. RDEC has been investigated sparsely, and new studies will address complications of the previous data involving ion-solid interactions for oxygen and fluorine ions incident on a C foil, and will build upon these results by investigating RDEC for collisions with gas targets of He, N2 and Ne. An advantage of gas targets is that they do not introduce the effects of multiple collisions present for solid targets and the results are expected to clarify the questions that arose in the earlier work. RDEC can be compared with several theoretical calculations that differ by several orders of magnitude. By obtaining results for C-foil targets and for gas targets, both to be studied under this project, and by comparing the measurements with theory, it should be possible to obtain the first data that provides input to the theoretical calculations. The measurements will be done for fully-stripped fluorine ions using the tandem Van de Graaff at Western Michigan University. The particular apparatus for the proposed experiment, including the apparatus for the gaseous targets, is already in place (funded previously by the US DOE). Measurements will involve recording coincidences between x rays emitted and singly- and doubly-charged projectiles (the latter coincidences represent a signature for RDEC). The measurements are difficult due to the relatively small cross sections for RDEC (on the order of ~1 barn or less) and will require long counting times of more than a month.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>09/18/2014</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/08/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1401429</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>John</FirstName>
<LastName>Tanis</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>A</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>John A Tanis</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>john.tanis@wmich.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2693874960</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000318654</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/18/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Asghar</FirstName>
<LastName>Kayani</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>N</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Asghar N Kayani</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>asghar.kayani@wmich.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2693874957</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000279653</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/18/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Western Michigan University</Name>
<CityName>Kalamazoo</CityName>
<ZipCode>490085200</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2693878298</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1903 West Michigan Avenue</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Michigan</StateName>
<StateCode>MI</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>06</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MI06</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>622364479</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>WESTERN MICHIGAN UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>062230560</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Western Michigan University]]></Name>
<CityName>Kalamazoo</CityName>
<StateCode>MI</StateCode>
<ZipCode>490085252</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[1903 W. Michigan Ave.]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Michigan</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>06</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MI06</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1241</Code>
<Text>AMO Experiment/Atomic, Molecul</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0114</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0115</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0116</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~50138</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2015~48304</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2016~35090</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>This project investigates experimentally the communication, or &ldquo;talking&rdquo;, between two electrons in collisions between atomic particles. In such collisions, the electrons transfer from one particle to the other with the simultaneous emission of a photon (an x ray) (see first image to the right). The process is essentially the inverse of double photoionization (removal of two electrons) by a single photon (second image to the right). For either of these two-electron processes to occur, the electrons must &ldquo;talk&rdquo; with one another for both to be removed or attached. These two-electron processes are similar to the case of one electron being liberated by a single photon, a process known as the photoelectric electric effect, which was explained by Albert Einstein in 1905 leading to the awarding of the Nobel Prize.</p> <p>Interest in the process of the transfer of two electrons with the emission of a single photon goes back just over three decades. It was first predicted to occur in 1987, but no experimental work on it was done, due to the perceived difficulty, until 1995. This experimental work, done in Germany, did not produce positive results. Then, in 2003, the same researchers reported a second attempt, again without showing any evidence for the process. It was not until 2010 that an experiment in our laboratory provided the first real evidence for the process, followed by further measurements reported in 2016 that gave results similar to those from 2010. This history provided the motivation for the work done under this project, with the intention of finally obtaining the evidence for two-electron transfer with single photon emission.</p> <p>These &ldquo;talking&rdquo; processes are of interest because they are believed to occur in astrophysical plasmas, and, hence, in the development and evolvement of the universe. The observation of them is important, apart from a fundamental understanding of the &ldquo;talking&rdquo; mechanism, to a gain a better understanding of how the universe works. However, the processes are difficult to investigate because of the relatively small probabilities of occurrence. To date, the process of two-electron transfer with simultaneous photon emission has been tentatively observed in gaseous targets of molecular nitrogen and atomic neon, in addition to our earlier initial measurements with solid-state carbon. To emphasize the difficulty, recent measurements, running around the clock (24 hours!) for about six weeks, produced only a few events for the two gas targets just mentioned. Further data collection is underway to enhance the measurements already done.</p> <p>The involvement of Ph.D. students in this research project provides valuable training in state-of-the-art physics, and assists their development as productive young scientists. Students have the opportunity to set up experimental apparatus and electronics, collect data with a sophisticated acquisition system, and then to sort and interpret the data obtained. From these data and the conclusions drawn from them, the students write manuscripts for publication in peer-reviewed journals and also prepare material for presentation at meetings and conferences, which they are encouraged to attend. All of these tasks serve to help the students grow as scientists who will hopefully be capable of carrying out their own independent research.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 10/06/2017<br>      Modified by: John&nbsp;A&nbsp;Tanis</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Images (<span id="selectedPhoto0">1</span> of <span class="totalNumber"></span>)           </div> <div class="galControls" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1401429/1401429_10342276_1507146805726_20171004_154154--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1401429/1401429_10342276_1507146805726_20171004_154154--rgov-800width.jpg" title="RDECschematic"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1401429/1401429_10342276_1507146805726_20171004_154154--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="RDECschematic"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Schematic showing the process of radiative double electron capture of two electrons being transferred from an atom to an incoming ion accompanied by simultaneous emission of a single photon. Also shown is the communication, or "talking", between the two electrons that makes this process possible.</div> <div class="imageCredit">D. La Mantia</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Royalty-free (unrestricted use)</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">John&nbsp;A&nbsp;Tanis</div> <div class="imageTitle">RDECschematic</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1401429/1401429_10342276_1507158792331_20171004_190400_001--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1401429/1401429_10342276_1507158792331_20171004_190400_001--rgov-800width.jpg" title="DoubleIonSchematic"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1401429/1401429_10342276_1507158792331_20171004_190400_001--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="DoubleIonSchematic"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Schematic showing the process of double ionization by a single photon. Also shown is the communication, or "talking", between the electrons that allows liberation of both.</div> <div class="imageCredit">D. La Mantia</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Royalty-free (unrestricted use)</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">John&nbsp;A&nbsp;Tanis</div> <div class="imageTitle">DoubleIonSchematic</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ This project investigates experimentally the communication, or "talking", between two electrons in collisions between atomic particles. In such collisions, the electrons transfer from one particle to the other with the simultaneous emission of a photon (an x ray) (see first image to the right). The process is essentially the inverse of double photoionization (removal of two electrons) by a single photon (second image to the right). For either of these two-electron processes to occur, the electrons must "talk" with one another for both to be removed or attached. These two-electron processes are similar to the case of one electron being liberated by a single photon, a process known as the photoelectric electric effect, which was explained by Albert Einstein in 1905 leading to the awarding of the Nobel Prize.  Interest in the process of the transfer of two electrons with the emission of a single photon goes back just over three decades. It was first predicted to occur in 1987, but no experimental work on it was done, due to the perceived difficulty, until 1995. This experimental work, done in Germany, did not produce positive results. Then, in 2003, the same researchers reported a second attempt, again without showing any evidence for the process. It was not until 2010 that an experiment in our laboratory provided the first real evidence for the process, followed by further measurements reported in 2016 that gave results similar to those from 2010. This history provided the motivation for the work done under this project, with the intention of finally obtaining the evidence for two-electron transfer with single photon emission.  These "talking" processes are of interest because they are believed to occur in astrophysical plasmas, and, hence, in the development and evolvement of the universe. The observation of them is important, apart from a fundamental understanding of the "talking" mechanism, to a gain a better understanding of how the universe works. However, the processes are difficult to investigate because of the relatively small probabilities of occurrence. To date, the process of two-electron transfer with simultaneous photon emission has been tentatively observed in gaseous targets of molecular nitrogen and atomic neon, in addition to our earlier initial measurements with solid-state carbon. To emphasize the difficulty, recent measurements, running around the clock (24 hours!) for about six weeks, produced only a few events for the two gas targets just mentioned. Further data collection is underway to enhance the measurements already done.  The involvement of Ph.D. students in this research project provides valuable training in state-of-the-art physics, and assists their development as productive young scientists. Students have the opportunity to set up experimental apparatus and electronics, collect data with a sophisticated acquisition system, and then to sort and interpret the data obtained. From these data and the conclusions drawn from them, the students write manuscripts for publication in peer-reviewed journals and also prepare material for presentation at meetings and conferences, which they are encouraged to attend. All of these tasks serve to help the students grow as scientists who will hopefully be capable of carrying out their own independent research.       Last Modified: 10/06/2017       Submitted by: John A Tanis]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
