<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>NSF Postdoctoral Fellowship in Biology FY 2014</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2014</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2016</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>138000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>138000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Fellowship Award</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>08080000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>BIO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DBI</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Biological Infrastructure</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Amanda Simcox</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>NSF Postdoctoral Fellowships in Biology combine research and training components to prepare young scientists for careers in emerging areas where biology intersects with other scientific disciplines, in this case with mathematics and physical sciences.  The Fellows are expected to lead the nation's scientific workforce of the future. This fellowship to Colin T. Kremer involves mathematical modeling of the evolutionary responses of marine organisms to changing global oceans. The host institutions for this fellowship are Yale and Princeton Universities, and the sponsoring scientists are Drs. David Vasseur and Jorge Sarmiento. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Marine phytoplankton (tiny plant-like organisms)contribute roughly half of all annual primary productivity on earth and form the basis of marine food webs.  Rising ocean temperatures affect the growth of marine phytoplankton and thus are having effects on global nutrient cycles.  To survive changing environmental conditions, organisms must adapt or migrate.  This research investigates interactions between ecology and evolution, that is, competition and migration versus mutation and selection, that govern the distribution and abundance of phytoplankton communities. It uses existing numerical ocean circulation models describing physical, chemical, and even ecological processes in the ocean but adds the role of evolutionary processes.  The research synthesizes evolutionary theory, marine ecology, and physical oceanography to study the response of phytoplankton to environmental change using and modifying existing models and exposes the Fellow to interdisciplinary research and training, including career development activities.  &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Results are of interest and are being shared with both scientific and general audiences.  Knowledge gained from research on effects on nutrient cycling and food webs in changing ocean environments can inform policy making. Other outcomes include interactive educational materials and outreach efforts focusing on explaining how scientists use mathematical and computational tools to study the natural world.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/02/2014</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/02/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.074</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1402074</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Colin</FirstName>
<LastName>Kremer</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>T</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Colin T Kremer</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress/>
<PI_PHON>3108252590</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000653763</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/02/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Kremer                  Colin          T</Name>
<CityName>Hickory Corners</CityName>
<ZipCode>490609505</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber/>
<StreetAddress/>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Michigan</StateName>
<StateCode>MI</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>06</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MI06</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM/>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME/>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Yale University]]></Name>
<CityName>New Haven</CityName>
<StateCode>CT</StateCode>
<ZipCode>065208379</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Connecticut</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CT03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>8054</Code>
<Text>Inters Biol and Math and Phys</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7137</Code>
<Text>POSTDOCTORAL FELLOWSHIPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7174</Code>
<Text>POSTDOC FELLOW IN SCI, MATH EN</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0114</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~138000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Confronted by climate change, it is critical to understand and predict the fate of plankton over the next 100 years, as they are essential to global nutrient cycles and form the base of global fisheries. Evolution is one critical way that species can potentially adapt to harmful changes in their environment. However, the best available technology for predicting the future of global marine ecosystems &ndash; massive computational models &ndash; do not account for evolution. As a result, it is difficult to anticipate whether or not evolution will be able to mitigate the effects of climate change, and what other effects evolution might have on global ecosystems and fisheries.</p> <p>This project addressed part of this challenge, uniting ecological and evolutionary theory with oceanographic sciences. Specifically, we explored scenarios where phyto- and zoo-plankton responded to changing ocean temperatures over the next 100 years using either: (i) only their current levels of diversity and high temperature tolerance, or (ii) by adapting perfectly and instantly to the temperature of their environment. Rapid evolution can compensate for rising temperatures in the tropics. In contrast, if evolution is constrained or slow (relative to how fast the oceans warm), future tropical communities will be significantly less productive, especially during El Nino years.&nbsp; Critically, the actual rate at which plankton can adapt is unknown at present, although logically it must fall between the two extremes we studied. Refining these results requires additional experimental work to complement these advances in computation.</p> <p><strong>Intellectual Merit:</strong></p> <p>- This research led to several methodological advances (addressing the question: How can we model evolution in global ecosystem models?)</p> <p>- It also explored a specific, relevant case study, highlighting the consequences of different evolutionary scenarios. (How will rising temperatures affect the productivity and structure of marine plankton communities?)</p> <p>- Other sub-projects examined the interactive effects of temperature, nutrients, and body size on species responses to temperature change, influencing where in the oceans they occur, and their function within communities.</p> <p><strong>Broader Impacts:</strong></p> <p>- This project enhanced the capacity of marine ecologists and modelers to make predictions about the effects of climate change on global ecosystems and critical resources such as fisheries, in light of evolution/adaptation. This capacity is crucial for providing society and policymakers with high quality information, and the ability to explore different scenarios.</p> <p>- The principle investigator (PI) of this award is an early career scientist. Due to this support, the PI (an expert in ecology/evolution) received critical, interdisciplinary training in physical oceanography and global ecosystem modeling, along with other professional development.</p> <p>- Support from this project also allowed the PI to mentor multiple undergraduate research experiences, give lectures, and conduct outreach activities at the K-12 level expanding awareness of the science behind evolution and climate change.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 11/22/2016<br>      Modified by: Colin&nbsp;T&nbsp;Kremer</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Image         </div> <div class="galControls onePhoto" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation onePhoto" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2016/1402074/1402074_10306639_1479849839440_Project_outcomes_piccopy--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2016/1402074/1402074_10306639_1479849839440_Project_outcomes_piccopy--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Effect of evolutionary constraint on small phytoplankton abundance by 2100"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2016/1402074/1402074_10306639_1479849839440_Project_outcomes_piccopy--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Effect of evolutionary constraint on small phytoplankton abundance by 2100"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">As an example of just one of the many ecosystem variables we can study and predict, this map shows that the biomass of small phytoplankton will be ~4% lower in hot tropical regions by 2100 if they cannot evolve new levels of thermal tolerance.</div> <div class="imageCredit">CT Kremer</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Colin&nbsp;T&nbsp;Kremer</div> <div class="imageTitle">Effect of evolutionary constraint on small phytoplankton abundance by 2100</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Confronted by climate change, it is critical to understand and predict the fate of plankton over the next 100 years, as they are essential to global nutrient cycles and form the base of global fisheries. Evolution is one critical way that species can potentially adapt to harmful changes in their environment. However, the best available technology for predicting the future of global marine ecosystems &ndash; massive computational models &ndash; do not account for evolution. As a result, it is difficult to anticipate whether or not evolution will be able to mitigate the effects of climate change, and what other effects evolution might have on global ecosystems and fisheries.  This project addressed part of this challenge, uniting ecological and evolutionary theory with oceanographic sciences. Specifically, we explored scenarios where phyto- and zoo-plankton responded to changing ocean temperatures over the next 100 years using either: (i) only their current levels of diversity and high temperature tolerance, or (ii) by adapting perfectly and instantly to the temperature of their environment. Rapid evolution can compensate for rising temperatures in the tropics. In contrast, if evolution is constrained or slow (relative to how fast the oceans warm), future tropical communities will be significantly less productive, especially during El Nino years.  Critically, the actual rate at which plankton can adapt is unknown at present, although logically it must fall between the two extremes we studied. Refining these results requires additional experimental work to complement these advances in computation.  Intellectual Merit:  - This research led to several methodological advances (addressing the question: How can we model evolution in global ecosystem models?)  - It also explored a specific, relevant case study, highlighting the consequences of different evolutionary scenarios. (How will rising temperatures affect the productivity and structure of marine plankton communities?)  - Other sub-projects examined the interactive effects of temperature, nutrients, and body size on species responses to temperature change, influencing where in the oceans they occur, and their function within communities.  Broader Impacts:  - This project enhanced the capacity of marine ecologists and modelers to make predictions about the effects of climate change on global ecosystems and critical resources such as fisheries, in light of evolution/adaptation. This capacity is crucial for providing society and policymakers with high quality information, and the ability to explore different scenarios.  - The principle investigator (PI) of this award is an early career scientist. Due to this support, the PI (an expert in ecology/evolution) received critical, interdisciplinary training in physical oceanography and global ecosystem modeling, along with other professional development.  - Support from this project also allowed the PI to mentor multiple undergraduate research experiences, give lectures, and conduct outreach activities at the K-12 level expanding awareness of the science behind evolution and climate change.       Last Modified: 11/22/2016       Submitted by: Colin T Kremer]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
