<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>SusChEM: Redox Non-Innocence in N- and C-donor Chelate Complexes of 1st Row Transition Elements: Radical Character in Chemistry</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2014</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>600000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>600000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03090000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CHE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Chemistry</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Tingyu Li</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>tli@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924949</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This project, funded by the NSF Chemical Synthesis Program in the Division of Chemistry, supports the research of Professor Peter T. Wolczanski of Cornell University to explore the design and synthesis of first row transition metal complexes containing ligands that expand the chemistry of the metal, primarily through oxidation and reduction processes. The coordinating ligands feature nitrogen (N)- and carbon (C)-donors with multiredox capability, that is they are "redox non-innocent" (RNI) by virtue of giving or taking electrons from the metal, thereby increasing the metal's reactivity.  The Wolczanski group employs many first row transition metals such as iron and chromium, making complexes that are uniquely reactive and more environmentally-friendly and sustainable than current precious metal complexes.  Professor Wolczanski and his group are active in the local community, actively planning and participating in multi-week after-school experiments for the Chemistry Club at Caroline Elementary School in Ithaca, New York. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This research project focuses on experimental studies that seek to: expand the scope of first row transition metal complexes that express redox non-innocence, increase the field strengths about first row transition metals via chelation and metal-carbon bonds, prepare new species capable of unique carbon-carbon bond-forming processes, and generate metal-carbon clusters based on dicarbides.  Redox non-innocent (RNI) ligands "electronically buffer" transition metal centers and expand their ability to conduct redox events inherent to bond-making and bond-breaking reactions. This research project focuses on the application of N-donor chelates to the chemistry of first row transition metal complexes, with an emphasis on stabilizing metal-nitrogen and -carbon multiple bonds while rendering them reactive. Operational, functionality tolerant, first row olefin metathesis catalysts are a critical target.  The preparation of nitrogen and carbon-based chelates possessing the strong fields are necessary to transform first row transition metal complexes into those capable of second or third row reactivity.  Studies also focus on C-C bond-making, featuring metal-stabilized carbanions that possess radical character. Radical hydrocarbon bond activations have led to ligand design features for hydrogen-atom abstraction and C-C couplings; these bond-making processes are scrutinized with regard to scope and the potential for catalysis.  Graduate and undergraduate researchers are actively involved in both the experimental and theoretical aspects of the project.  The students receive training in several characterizational techniques including Electron Paramagnetic Resonance and Mossbauer spectroscopies as well as magnetometry and electronic structure calculations.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/12/2014</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/06/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1402149</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Peter</FirstName>
<LastName>Wolczanski</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>T</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Peter T Wolczanski</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>ptw2@cornell.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6072557220</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000156849</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/12/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Cornell University</Name>
<CityName>Ithaca</CityName>
<ZipCode>148502820</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6072555014</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>373 Pine Tree Road</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>23</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NY23</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>872612445</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>CORNELL UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>002254837</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Cornell University]]></Name>
<CityName>Ithaca</CityName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<ZipCode>148531301</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[Baker Laboratory, CCB]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>23</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NY23</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>6878</Code>
<Text>Chemical Synthesis</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8248</Code>
<Text>SusChEM</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8398</Code>
<Text>Hydrocarbon Conversion</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8650</Code>
<Text>Sustainable Chemistry</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8676</Code>
<Text>Critical Elements</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0114</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~600000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><!--   @font-face  {font-family:Times;  panose-1:2 0 5 0 0 0 0 0 0 0;  mso-font-charset:0;  mso-generic-font-family:auto;  mso-font-pitch:variable;  mso-font-signature:3 0 0 0 1 0;} @font-face  {font-family:"?? ??";  mso-font-charset:78;  mso-generic-font-family:auto;  mso-font-pitch:variable;  mso-font-signature:1 134676480 16 0 131072 0;} @font-face  {font-family:"Cambria Math";  panose-1:2 4 5 3 5 4 6 3 2 4;  mso-font-charset:0;  mso-generic-font-family:auto;  mso-font-pitch:variable;  mso-font-signature:-536870145 1107305727 0 0 415 0;} @font-face  {font-family:Cambria;  panose-1:2 4 5 3 5 4 6 3 2 4;  mso-font-charset:0;  mso-generic-font-family:auto;  mso-font-pitch:variable;  mso-font-signature:-536870145 1073743103 0 0 415 0;}   p.MsoNormal, li.MsoNormal, div.MsoNormal  {mso-style-unhide:no;  mso-style-qformat:yes;  mso-style-parent:";  margin:0in;  margin-bottom:.0001pt;  mso-pagination:widow-orphan;  font-size:12.0pt;  font-family:Cambria;  mso-ascii-font-family:Cambria;  mso-ascii-theme-font:minor-latin;  mso-fareast-font-family:"?? ??";  mso-fareast-theme-font:minor-fareast;  mso-hansi-font-family:Cambria;  mso-hansi-theme-font:minor-latin;  mso-bidi-font-family:"Times New Roman";  mso-bidi-theme-font:minor-bidi;} p  {mso-style-noshow:yes;  mso-style-priority:99;  mso-margin-top-alt:auto;  margin-right:0in;  mso-margin-bottom-alt:auto;  margin-left:0in;  mso-pagination:widow-orphan;  font-size:10.0pt;  font-family:Times;  mso-fareast-font-family:"?? ??";  mso-fareast-theme-font:minor-fareast;  mso-bidi-font-family:"Times New Roman";} .MsoChpDefault  {mso-style-type:export-only;  mso-default-props:yes;  font-family:Cambria;  mso-ascii-font-family:Cambria;  mso-ascii-theme-font:minor-latin;  mso-fareast-font-family:"?? ??";  mso-fareast-theme-font:minor-fareast;  mso-hansi-font-family:Cambria;  mso-hansi-theme-font:minor-latin;  mso-bidi-font-family:"Times New Roman";  mso-bidi-theme-font:minor-bidi;} @page WordSection1  {size:8.5in 11.0in;  margin:1.0in 1.25in 1.0in 1.25in;  mso-header-margin:.5in;  mso-footer-margin:.5in;  mso-paper-source:0;} div.WordSection1  {page:WordSection1;} --> <p>The first row of the transition metals in the periodic table constitute the so-called "base metals", which are characterized as inexpensive, and less toxic than their 2nd and 3rd row congeners. As a consequence, their utilization in materials, and as catalysts -- additives that lower the energy requirement for chemical reactivity -- for industrially important transformations, is highly desired. Unfortunately, these metals typically have a substantial ionic component in their bonding to their surrounding atoms, termed ligands. Whereas most desirable catalytic processes require formal 2-electron changes, the base metals often undergo deleterious 1-electron chemistry.</p> <p>This proposal addressed several approaches to expand the use of base metals in transformations featuring CC bond formation, and related CN chemistry, with a great deal of success. The modification of metals occurs via changing the atoms or groups of atoms -- termed ligands -- that surround the metal. Redox non-innocent (RNI) ligands are groups of atoms that can receive 1 or 2 electrons from the metal, and release those electrons back when a substrate binds. A new diamide, diimine ligand, termed "dadi", was designed to serve in this capacity, and a series of base metal complexes were synthesized. Iron and chromium complexes exhibited unique CC bond-breaking and CN bond forming reactions that manifest redox non-innocent behavior, thereby suggesting that RNI can be utilized to expand the reactivity of base metal species. To this point, a titanium complex containing dadi was shown to catalyze a reaction with carbon monoxide, a rare example of an early transition metal catalyzed carbonylation. Ongoing studies of various transition metal dadi complexes are being studied to determine spectroscopic means of recognizing RNI character.</p> <p>A means of increasing covalency -- the sharing of electrons -- between metal and ligands was explored via the utilization of chelates, ligands that bind at multiple sites, some of which contain metal-carbon bonds. The targeted reaction was olefin metathesis, the swapping of the ends of olefins, which is currently catalyzed by 2nd row transition metals. Olefin metathesis catalysts contain metal-carbon double bonds, termed alkylidenes, and are predicted to exist for certain electronic structures, such as iron in the formal oxidation state of four. Via judicious manipulation of the chelate ligands, ten such compounds were synthesized, and five were structurally characterized, when only one was known. While this was a synthetic success, olefin metathesis reactivity was not realized, and calculation and spectroscopic evaluation of the formally Fe(IV) alkylidenes revealed ionic character. A number of other approaches were attempted, and the research segued to low coordinate complexes surrounded by strong field ligands, groups of atoms that should introduce the necessary covalency.</p> <p>Ene-amide complexes were sought as agents for carbon-carbon bond formation. A variety of base metal species were synthesized, and via thermolyses, indolamides were prepared via the ene-amides. The bond formed was a tertiary CC bond, which is a difficult bond to make, hence this transformation may have utility. An experimental and calculational evaluation of the process was conducted, and the pathway to indolamides was shown to be an unusual one in which the primary activation was a hydrogen atom transfer akin to an organic ene-reaction. This process was reversible, and the actual product-determining step featured the CC bond-formation, a step that had a relatively small barrier. &nbsp;The reaction was catalyzed by a number of transition metal species, but the best catalyst is actually the lithium ene-amide precursor to the transition metal complexes.</p> <p>Ene-amides were also shown to be intriguing ligands toward CC bond formation via a metal-centered coupling reaction. Using ene-amides of iron and chromium, CC coupling reactions were discovered that take advantage of the radical, or unpaired electron, character on the ene-amide. These couplings were induced by oxidants that transposed radical character to the redox non-innocent ene-amides. These processes were stoichiometric, but the cheap metals used suggest that the reactions may be useful, especially in the synthesis of pyrroles. In addition, a modestly catalytic arylation of imines was discovered during the course of study.</p> <p>In all of the successful projects above, the concept of formal oxidation state, a means of "bookkeeping" electrons in transition metal complexes, was found to color judgment of the chemistry, and at times was misleading. Partly in response to this realization, a diametric opposite approach to bookkeeping "charge" in transiton metal systems was developed. This Charge Distribution Via Reporters (CDVR) provides an alternative to formal oxidation states, and is a new means of evaluating the stability transition metal complexes.</p> <p>The NSF grant also sponsored an outreach activity with Ithaca High School students. In three years three groups totaling 14 students were brought into the lab for 3 two-hour sessions in which they attempted to make transition metal complexes that had never been made before.&nbsp; Some were successful, some were not, proving some reality to research as they head off to college.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <!--   @font-face  {font-family:Times;  panose-1:2 0 5 0 0 0 0 0 0 0;  mso-font-charset:0;  mso-generic-font-family:auto;  mso-font-pitch:variable;  mso-font-signature:3 0 0 0 1 0;} @font-face  {font-family:"?? ??";  mso-font-charset:78;  mso-generic-font-family:auto;  mso-font-pitch:variable;  mso-font-signature:1 134676480 16 0 131072 0;} @font-face  {font-family:"?? ??";  mso-font-charset:78;  mso-generic-font-family:auto;  mso-font-pitch:variable;  mso-font-signature:1 134676480 16 0 131072 0;} @font-face  {font-family:Cambria;  panose-1:2 4 5 3 5 4 6 3 2 4;  mso-font-charset:0;  mso-generic-font-family:auto;  mso-font-pitch:variable;  mso-font-signature:-536870145 1073743103 0 0 415 0;}   p.MsoNormal, li.MsoNormal, div.MsoNormal  {mso-style-unhide:no;  mso-style-qformat:yes;  mso-style-parent:";  margin:0in;  margin-bottom:.0001pt;  mso-pagination:widow-orphan;  font-size:12.0pt;  font-family:Cambria;  mso-ascii-font-family:Cambria;  mso-ascii-theme-font:minor-latin;  mso-fareast-font-family:"?? ??";  mso-fareast-theme-font:minor-fareast;  mso-hansi-font-family:Cambria;  mso-hansi-theme-font:minor-latin;  mso-bidi-font-family:"Times New Roman";  mso-bidi-theme-font:minor-bidi;} p  {mso-style-noshow:yes;  mso-style-priority:99;  mso-margin-top-alt:auto;  margin-right:0in;  mso-margin-bottom-alt:auto;  margin-left:0in;  mso-pagination:widow-orphan;  font-size:10.0pt;  font-family:Times;  mso-fareast-font-family:"?? ??";  mso-fareast-theme-font:minor-fareast;  mso-bidi-font-family:"Times New Roman";} .MsoChpDefault  {mso-style-type:export-only;  mso-default-props:yes;  font-family:Cambria;  mso-ascii-font-family:Cambria;  mso-ascii-theme-font:minor-latin;  mso-fareast-font-family:"?? ??";  mso-fareast-theme-font:minor-fareast;  mso-hansi-font-family:Cambria;  mso-hansi-theme-font:minor-latin;  mso-bidi-font-family:"Times New Roman";  mso-bidi-theme-font:minor-bidi;} @page WordSection1  {size:8.5in 11.0in;  margin:1.0in 1.25in 1.0in 1.25in;  mso-header-margin:.5in;  mso-footer-margin:.5in;  mso-paper-source:0;} div.WordSection1  {page:WordSection1;} --><br> <p>            Last Modified: 08/04/2017<br>      Modified by: Peter&nbsp;T&nbsp;Wolczanski</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[  The first row of the transition metals in the periodic table constitute the so-called "base metals", which are characterized as inexpensive, and less toxic than their 2nd and 3rd row congeners. As a consequence, their utilization in materials, and as catalysts -- additives that lower the energy requirement for chemical reactivity -- for industrially important transformations, is highly desired. Unfortunately, these metals typically have a substantial ionic component in their bonding to their surrounding atoms, termed ligands. Whereas most desirable catalytic processes require formal 2-electron changes, the base metals often undergo deleterious 1-electron chemistry.  This proposal addressed several approaches to expand the use of base metals in transformations featuring CC bond formation, and related CN chemistry, with a great deal of success. The modification of metals occurs via changing the atoms or groups of atoms -- termed ligands -- that surround the metal. Redox non-innocent (RNI) ligands are groups of atoms that can receive 1 or 2 electrons from the metal, and release those electrons back when a substrate binds. A new diamide, diimine ligand, termed "dadi", was designed to serve in this capacity, and a series of base metal complexes were synthesized. Iron and chromium complexes exhibited unique CC bond-breaking and CN bond forming reactions that manifest redox non-innocent behavior, thereby suggesting that RNI can be utilized to expand the reactivity of base metal species. To this point, a titanium complex containing dadi was shown to catalyze a reaction with carbon monoxide, a rare example of an early transition metal catalyzed carbonylation. Ongoing studies of various transition metal dadi complexes are being studied to determine spectroscopic means of recognizing RNI character.  A means of increasing covalency -- the sharing of electrons -- between metal and ligands was explored via the utilization of chelates, ligands that bind at multiple sites, some of which contain metal-carbon bonds. The targeted reaction was olefin metathesis, the swapping of the ends of olefins, which is currently catalyzed by 2nd row transition metals. Olefin metathesis catalysts contain metal-carbon double bonds, termed alkylidenes, and are predicted to exist for certain electronic structures, such as iron in the formal oxidation state of four. Via judicious manipulation of the chelate ligands, ten such compounds were synthesized, and five were structurally characterized, when only one was known. While this was a synthetic success, olefin metathesis reactivity was not realized, and calculation and spectroscopic evaluation of the formally Fe(IV) alkylidenes revealed ionic character. A number of other approaches were attempted, and the research segued to low coordinate complexes surrounded by strong field ligands, groups of atoms that should introduce the necessary covalency.  Ene-amide complexes were sought as agents for carbon-carbon bond formation. A variety of base metal species were synthesized, and via thermolyses, indolamides were prepared via the ene-amides. The bond formed was a tertiary CC bond, which is a difficult bond to make, hence this transformation may have utility. An experimental and calculational evaluation of the process was conducted, and the pathway to indolamides was shown to be an unusual one in which the primary activation was a hydrogen atom transfer akin to an organic ene-reaction. This process was reversible, and the actual product-determining step featured the CC bond-formation, a step that had a relatively small barrier.  The reaction was catalyzed by a number of transition metal species, but the best catalyst is actually the lithium ene-amide precursor to the transition metal complexes.  Ene-amides were also shown to be intriguing ligands toward CC bond formation via a metal-centered coupling reaction. Using ene-amides of iron and chromium, CC coupling reactions were discovered that take advantage of the radical, or unpaired electron, character on the ene-amide. These couplings were induced by oxidants that transposed radical character to the redox non-innocent ene-amides. These processes were stoichiometric, but the cheap metals used suggest that the reactions may be useful, especially in the synthesis of pyrroles. In addition, a modestly catalytic arylation of imines was discovered during the course of study.  In all of the successful projects above, the concept of formal oxidation state, a means of "bookkeeping" electrons in transition metal complexes, was found to color judgment of the chemistry, and at times was misleading. Partly in response to this realization, a diametric opposite approach to bookkeeping "charge" in transiton metal systems was developed. This Charge Distribution Via Reporters (CDVR) provides an alternative to formal oxidation states, and is a new means of evaluating the stability transition metal complexes.  The NSF grant also sponsored an outreach activity with Ithaca High School students. In three years three groups totaling 14 students were brought into the lab for 3 two-hour sessions in which they attempted to make transition metal complexes that had never been made before.  Some were successful, some were not, proving some reality to research as they head off to college.              Last Modified: 08/04/2017       Submitted by: Peter T Wolczanski]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
