<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Thermally-induced Rayleigh-taylor like instabilities for nanoscale synthesis</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>06/15/2014</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>282276.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>282276</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07020000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CBET</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Chem, Bioeng, Env, &amp; Transp Sys</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Ying Sun</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>yisun@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927443</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>CBET-1402962&lt;br/&gt;Kalyanaraman&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;One way the United States can continue to be the global leader in technology innovation with a sound economic plan for the future is if it can employ large fractions of the population in high-tech manufacturing jobs. One potentially untapped, but high growth, area, is the manufacturing of sophisticated nanomaterials for use in solar cells, computer data storage devices, and sensors for disease detection. It is widely acknowledged that nature has found many ways to make useful and complex materials in economical fashion. One of the principles often found in nature is that of self-organization or self-assembly, in which competing forces lead to the emergence of a useful structure. For example, the Rayleigh-Taylor (RT) effect is at the heart of the formation of a uniform collection of water droplets on the underside of a ceiling. In this case, it is the result of gravity disturbing the water film-air interface that leads to droplet formation. Besides being evident in liquids, the RT effect can also be found in the behavior of astronomical structures such as black holes and supernova, and in geophysical phenomenon. If the RT effect can be applied to the nanoscale, a cost-effective way to make nanomaterials could result. However, since gravity rarely influences the nanoscale, other ways need to be found to create the RT effect. The research proposed here will explore the hypothesis that rapid heating of a material in liquid ambient can produce RT effects in the nanoscale. The experimental component will involve creating such a scenario by using laser pulses to heat the material of interest. A variety of microscopy and computer modeling techniques will be employed to study the resulting nanomaterials. During the course of this research, training of minority and underrepresented students from K-12, undergraduate, and graduate programs will be achieved. They will be trained in basic and applied principles of science and engineering, with the goal of making them future leaders of the society in STEM disciplines and/or in technologically relevant industries. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The research proposed here is an understanding of the Rayleigh-Taylor (RT) instability in the nanoscale. Recent experimental findings show that the RT instability can be observed in thin films melted by laser pulses in a fluid ambient. The preliminary hypothesis underlying the discovery is that the large thermal gradient that develop at the film/vapor interface due to the rapid heating under nanosecond laser pulses lead to large pressure gradients, which are ultimately responsible for the observed behavior. Early results of thermal modeling support this hypothesis. However, the role of fluid properties, laser parameters and other thin film hydrodynamic instabilities is presently lacking in order to unequivocally establish an understanding of this phenomenon. Motivated by this, several model systems based on a combination of fluid (glycerol, water, toluene), film (Au, Ag, Si, TiO2), and substrate (Glass, Si, Sapphire) properties have been identified. The following tasks will be performed. (1) Theoretical modeling of thermal transport to understand ns pulsed laser heating of various fluid/film/substrate systems. (2) Laser melting experiments of various combinations of fluid, film and substrate. (3) Characterization of pattern morphology, nanoparticle structure, and chemical composition by various nanoscale tools. This includes scanning and transmission electron microscopy, atomic force microscopy, Raman spectroscopy, electron energy loss spectroscopy, and optical spectroscopy. (4) Modeling of the experimental results in the context of fluid dynamics theories to explain the observations.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/06/2014</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/06/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1402962</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Ramki</FirstName>
<LastName>Kalyanaraman</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Ramki Kalyanaraman</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>kalyanaramanr@smccd.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6503063196</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000253925</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/06/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Tennessee Knoxville</Name>
<CityName>Knoxville</CityName>
<ZipCode>379163801</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>8659743466</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1331 CIR PARK DR</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Tennessee</StateName>
<StateCode>TN</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>TN02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>003387891</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF TENNESSEE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>003387891</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Tennessee Knoxville]]></Name>
<CityName>Knoxville</CityName>
<StateCode>TN</StateCode>
<ZipCode>379960003</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Tennessee</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>TN02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1406</Code>
<Text>TTP-Thermal Transport Process</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>150E</Code>
<Text>Conduction/Diffusion</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0114</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~282276</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Metallic nanoparticles on surfaces have applications in biosensing, reaction monitoring, and solar energy harvesting due their unique properties which are absent in the bulk metal. The size, spacing, shape, areal density and stability are some of the key parameters that determine suitability in applications. Metallic thin film melting in air has been investigated to produce nanoparticles with predictable size and spacing as a relatively inexpensive approach.&nbsp;However, the main limitation of this approach is that it is not possible to independently control the particle size and spacing.</p> <!-- p.p1 {margin: 0.0px 0.0px 0.0px 0.0px; font: 12.0px 'Helvetica Neue'} --> <p class="p1">The intellectual merit of this work was to investigate<span>&nbsp; </span>new phenomenon based on the unique effects when thin films and nanostructures submerged under different fluids are rapidly heated by nanosecond laser pulses.<span>&nbsp; &nbsp; </span>The successful outcomes of this project were as follows.&nbsp;</p> <p>1) A novel way to change the contact angle of a nanoparticle on a surface was discovered. By laser melting&nbsp; metal films or nanoparticles under different liquid ambients, we showed that the particle could either be hemispherical (90<sup>o</sup>&nbsp;contact angle) or close to a perfect sphere with contact angle near 180<sup>o</sup>). A theoretical basis for this effect was presented.&nbsp;</p> <p>2) An "anchoring" technique was discovered through which it was possible to make the&nbsp; Ag nanoparticles shaped as pyramids&nbsp; retain their shape even under heating to temperatures as high as 573 K. This was achieved by making bilayers of Ag pyramids with Cobalt (Co). The experimental effect was supported by a theoretical model.&nbsp;</p> <p>3) We advanced the use of laser melting under fluids as a way to control the size of particles. Specifically, under very high laser energies, explosive boiling of a metal submerged under a fluid was realized as a way to tune the particle size.&nbsp;</p> <p>4) We enhanced the profile of laser-underfluid melting as a promising approach to synthesize nanomaterials in a green and environmentally friendly way by demonstrating how it can turn a thin film deposit, which would typically be wasted due to its poor morphology, into a system of well defined nanostructures.</p> <p>The broader impacts of this research were focused on various aspects of collaboration, education, outreach and training. Some of the specific outcomes include the following.</p> <p>1. One graduate student received a Ph.D. degree based solely on the work done through this research.</p> <p>2. This same graduate student was trained and educated in areas of national need, such as thin film and nano technology. The student has been successfully hired by Intel corporation, where he will use his expertise in thin film and nanotechnologies to work on next-generation thin film technology tools.&nbsp;</p> <!-- p.p1 {margin: 0.0px 0.0px 0.0px 0.0px; font: 12.0px 'Helvetica Neue'} --> <p class="p1">3. Over the course of this research, several undergraduate researchers, including those underrepresented in STEM disciplines, were involved in hands-on research in national need areas.&nbsp;This included women students from various engineering programs, including mechanical engineering and chemical engineering. In addition, one woman graduate student from energy science and engineering was also involved in a secondary manner by helping train graduate and undergraduate students of this project in some of the techniques used in the laboratory.<span>&nbsp;</span></p> <p>4. A natural synergy between graduate students working on different projects in the laboratory resulted in the implementation of the shape control work done in this research to the demonstration of a reusable optical switch system. Thus, our work in materials science and engineering has lead to potential impact in the field of optics and plasmonics.&nbsp;&nbsp;</p> <p>5. The lead graduate student, (now Dr.) V. P. Sandireddy played a proactive role in a new collaboration with scientists in the mechanical engineering department. This work led to an exciting discovery of enhanced photocurrent generation from photosystem-I and has implications to the field of bio-inspired energy generation.&nbsp;</p> <!-- p.p1 {margin: 0.0px 0.0px 0.0px 0.0px; font: 12.0px 'Helvetica Neue'} --> <p class="p1">6. The research results have been disseminated through peer-reviewed publications in high impact as well as archival journals in the field, through invited and contributed conference presentations,&nbsp; through the PIs webpage, and through social media sites such as linkedin.&nbsp;</p> <p class="p1">7. As part of broader impacts, PI developed lectures on nanotechnology aimed at a broad and inter-disciplinary technical audience who were employed by high-tech industry. Several lectures were delivered at organizations like Applied Materials, LAM Research, and Coherent Lasers, as well as to primarily undergraduate and minority serving institutions like San Jose State University and University of San Francisco.&nbsp;</p> <p>8. PI incorporated several aspects of research results, such as use of lasers in nanomaterial synthesis, optical and plasmonic properties of&nbsp;nanomaterials, and applications of nanoparticles in energy harvesting and medicine into an upper level undergraduate class (MSE 408) titled &ldquo;Functional Nanomaterials: Properties, synthesis and applications&rdquo;. This class was offered every year and undergraduate as well as graduate students from multiple different engineering and science disciplines have taken this class over the years. This includes students from physics, mechanical engineering, nuclear engineering, materials science, and chemical engineering.</p> <p class="p1">&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 08/17/2019<br>      Modified by: Ramki&nbsp;Kalyanaraman</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Images (<span id="selectedPhoto0">1</span> of <span class="totalNumber"></span>)           </div> <div class="galControls" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1402962/1402962_10307825_1566071104552_Fig-Shape--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1402962/1402962_10307825_1566071104552_Fig-Shape--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Nanoscale Shape Tuning"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1402962/1402962_10307825_1566071104552_Fig-Shape--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Nanoscale Shape Tuning"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">The SEM image on the left shows the initial flat shape of Ag nanostructures. The Images in the right column show the same nanostructures have transformed into spheres with different contact angle based on the fluid ambient they were heated in.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Langmuir</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyright owner is an institution with an existing agreement allowing use by NSF</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Ramki&nbsp;Kalyanaraman</div> <div class="imageTitle">Nanoscale Shape Tuning</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1402962/1402962_10307825_1566071547584_Fig-Anchoring--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1402962/1402962_10307825_1566071547584_Fig-Anchoring--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Bilayer Anchoring"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1402962/1402962_10307825_1566071547584_Fig-Anchoring--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Bilayer Anchoring"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">The SEM images in the left column show various Ag nanostructures. The Images in the center column show the same nanostructures but after heating in air to 573 K. The Ag nanostructures in contact with Co retain their shape and plasmonic property while the pure Ag has changed dramatically.</div> <div class="imageCredit">ACS Applied Materials & Interfaces</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyright owner is an institution with an existing agreement allowing use by NSF</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Ramki&nbsp;Kalyanaraman</div> <div class="imageTitle">Bilayer Anchoring</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1402962/1402962_10307825_1566071779739_Fig-PSI--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1402962/1402962_10307825_1566071779739_Fig-PSI--rgov-800width.jpg" title="PS-I photocurrent enhancement"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1402962/1402962_10307825_1566071779739_Fig-PSI--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="PS-I photocurrent enhancement"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Discovery of enhanced photocurrent generation from Photosystem-I (PSI) through integrated plasmonic-PSI system.  the PSI on nanopyramidal Ag showed 6x enhancement in photocurrent at visible wavelengths as compared to PSI on Ag films.</div> <div class="imageCredit">J. of Physical Chemistry Letters</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyright owner is an institution with an existing agreement allowing use by NSF</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Ramki&nbsp;Kalyanaraman</div> <div class="imageTitle">PS-I photocurrent enhancement</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1402962/1402962_10307825_1566072814950_Figure1--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1402962/1402962_10307825_1566072814950_Figure1--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Explosive Vaporization"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1402962/1402962_10307825_1566072814950_Figure1--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Explosive Vaporization"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">An  initial ordered array of metallic nanopyramids is heated by nanosecond laser pulses under glycerol ambinet. The ensuring explosive vaporization produces an ultrafine collection of nanoparticles surrounding the initial "mother" nanoparticle.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Ramki Kalyanaraman</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Ramki&nbsp;Kalyanaraman</div> <div class="imageTitle">Explosive Vaporization</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Metallic nanoparticles on surfaces have applications in biosensing, reaction monitoring, and solar energy harvesting due their unique properties which are absent in the bulk metal. The size, spacing, shape, areal density and stability are some of the key parameters that determine suitability in applications. Metallic thin film melting in air has been investigated to produce nanoparticles with predictable size and spacing as a relatively inexpensive approach. However, the main limitation of this approach is that it is not possible to independently control the particle size and spacing.  The intellectual merit of this work was to investigate  new phenomenon based on the unique effects when thin films and nanostructures submerged under different fluids are rapidly heated by nanosecond laser pulses.    The successful outcomes of this project were as follows.   1) A novel way to change the contact angle of a nanoparticle on a surface was discovered. By laser melting  metal films or nanoparticles under different liquid ambients, we showed that the particle could either be hemispherical (90o contact angle) or close to a perfect sphere with contact angle near 180o). A theoretical basis for this effect was presented.   2) An "anchoring" technique was discovered through which it was possible to make the  Ag nanoparticles shaped as pyramids  retain their shape even under heating to temperatures as high as 573 K. This was achieved by making bilayers of Ag pyramids with Cobalt (Co). The experimental effect was supported by a theoretical model.   3) We advanced the use of laser melting under fluids as a way to control the size of particles. Specifically, under very high laser energies, explosive boiling of a metal submerged under a fluid was realized as a way to tune the particle size.   4) We enhanced the profile of laser-underfluid melting as a promising approach to synthesize nanomaterials in a green and environmentally friendly way by demonstrating how it can turn a thin film deposit, which would typically be wasted due to its poor morphology, into a system of well defined nanostructures.  The broader impacts of this research were focused on various aspects of collaboration, education, outreach and training. Some of the specific outcomes include the following.  1. One graduate student received a Ph.D. degree based solely on the work done through this research.  2. This same graduate student was trained and educated in areas of national need, such as thin film and nano technology. The student has been successfully hired by Intel corporation, where he will use his expertise in thin film and nanotechnologies to work on next-generation thin film technology tools.   3. Over the course of this research, several undergraduate researchers, including those underrepresented in STEM disciplines, were involved in hands-on research in national need areas. This included women students from various engineering programs, including mechanical engineering and chemical engineering. In addition, one woman graduate student from energy science and engineering was also involved in a secondary manner by helping train graduate and undergraduate students of this project in some of the techniques used in the laboratory.   4. A natural synergy between graduate students working on different projects in the laboratory resulted in the implementation of the shape control work done in this research to the demonstration of a reusable optical switch system. Thus, our work in materials science and engineering has lead to potential impact in the field of optics and plasmonics.    5. The lead graduate student, (now Dr.) V. P. Sandireddy played a proactive role in a new collaboration with scientists in the mechanical engineering department. This work led to an exciting discovery of enhanced photocurrent generation from photosystem-I and has implications to the field of bio-inspired energy generation.   6. The research results have been disseminated through peer-reviewed publications in high impact as well as archival journals in the field, through invited and contributed conference presentations,  through the PIs webpage, and through social media sites such as linkedin.  7. As part of broader impacts, PI developed lectures on nanotechnology aimed at a broad and inter-disciplinary technical audience who were employed by high-tech industry. Several lectures were delivered at organizations like Applied Materials, LAM Research, and Coherent Lasers, as well as to primarily undergraduate and minority serving institutions like San Jose State University and University of San Francisco.   8. PI incorporated several aspects of research results, such as use of lasers in nanomaterial synthesis, optical and plasmonic properties of nanomaterials, and applications of nanoparticles in energy harvesting and medicine into an upper level undergraduate class (MSE 408) titled "Functional Nanomaterials: Properties, synthesis and applications". This class was offered every year and undergraduate as well as graduate students from multiple different engineering and science disciplines have taken this class over the years. This includes students from physics, mechanical engineering, nuclear engineering, materials science, and chemical engineering.         Last Modified: 08/17/2019       Submitted by: Ramki Kalyanaraman]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
