<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Luminescence as a Structural Probe of Ultra-Small Rare Earth Oxide Nanoparticles</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/16/2013</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2016</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>442119.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>442119</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03090000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CHE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Chemistry</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>George Janini</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>gjanini@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032928840</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>James Dickerson at Vanderbilt University is supported by the Macromolecular, Supramolecular and Nanochemistry Program for research focusing on the concurrent experimental and theoretical analysis of ultra-small rare earth-based nanoparticles of potentially high luminescence efficiency.  This investigation will explore the synthesis, characterization, and theoretical modeling of these nanoparticles to assess the correlation among nanoparticle size, environmental conditions (symmetry, crystalline structure, surfactant properties, defects, etc.), and luminescence characteristics.  By studying theoretically and experimentally the luminescence properties of these nanophosphors, such as doped gadolinium sesquioxide, it is possible to better understand how surfactant molecules, crystal distortions, and other nanoscale structural and electronic effects influence various spectroscopic processes originating from rare earth ions.  The compounds chosen for these investigations [monodisperse, sub-3.0 nm europium (Eu2O3), terbium (Tb2O3), and doped gadolinium (Gd2O3:RE3+; RE = Eu, Tb) sesquioxide nanoparticles] have been selected due to their well-known, bulk phase luminescence characteristics, their simple crystallinity (bcc), and he unique expertise of this research group in the synthesis, the theoretical assessment, and the interpretation of their properties.  The investigation of these nanocrystalline properties can be exploited in phosphorescent device applications ranging from robust video displays to bio-imaging reagents and infrared telecommunications materials.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award focuses on the concurrent experimental and theoretical analysis of the high-efficiency light emission characteristics of extremely small, nanoscale materials comprised of rare earth elements.  This investigation will explore the production, analysis, and theoretical study of the properties of these nanoparticles to assess the relationship among their size, their intrinsic features, like symmetry and morphology, and their light emission characteristics.  By studying theoretically and experimentally these materials, a better understand will be obtained of how to optimize their properties for use in phosphorescent device applications ranging from robust, ultra-high definition video displays to next-generation, high-acuity medical imaging reagents, and high-speed telecommunications materials.  Diverse, underrepresented graduate and undergraduate students will participate in this project thanks to existing programs at Vanderbilt University, such as the Fisk-Vanderbilt Masters-to-PhD Bridge Program.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>11/25/2013</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>11/25/2013</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1402298</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>James</FirstName>
<LastName>Dickerson</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>H</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>James H Dickerson</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>nolongerinresearch@brown.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6153432957</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000225614</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>11/25/2013</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Brown University</Name>
<CityName>Providence</CityName>
<ZipCode>029129002</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>4018632777</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>BOX 1929</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[350 Eddy Street]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Rhode Island</StateName>
<StateCode>RI</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>RI01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>001785542</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>BROWN UNIVERSITY IN PROVIDENCE IN THE STATE OF RHODE ISLAND AND PROVIDENCE PLANTATIONS</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>001785542</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Brown University]]></Name>
<CityName>Providence</CityName>
<StateCode>RI</StateCode>
<ZipCode>029129002</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[BOX 1929]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Rhode Island</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>RI01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>6885</Code>
<Text>Macromolec/Supramolec/Nano</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>100E</Code>
<Text>Novel devices &amp; vacuum electronics</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>5560</Code>
<Text>ENERGY CONVERSION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7234</Code>
<Text>SENSORS NON-SOLICITATION RESEA</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7237</Code>
<Text>NANO NON-SOLIC SCI &amp; ENG AWD</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9161</Code>
<Text>SINGLE DIVISION/UNIVERSITY</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9263</Code>
<Text>COMPUTATIONAL SCIENCE &amp; ENGING</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>AMPP</Code>
<Text>ADVANCED MATERIALS &amp; PROCESSING PROGRAM</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0112</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0113</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2012~277119</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2013~165000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><span>The goal of this research project was to explore the relationship between the specific size of a nanocrystal (or nanoparticle), how the atoms that comprise the nanocrystal are arranged and/or become mis-arranged because of the size, and how light that may be produced by the nanocrystal could reveal information about the aforementioned arrangement or mis-arrangement. &nbsp;To accompany the use of luminescence (a fancy word for production of light) to probe the structure (or arrangement of atoms), we have used complementary techniques to probe the nanocrystal(s). &nbsp;The most effective complementary probe is x-ray total scattering experiments coupled an emerging theoretical modeling technique, called pair distribution functional (PDF) analysis. &nbsp;In particular, PDF analysis can reveal substantial structural information at the nanoscale not only to help elucidate the formation of rare earth nanocrystals, but also to characterize their crystal structure.</span></p> <p><span>&nbsp;</span></p> <p><span>Our experimental data clearly demonstrate two things: 1) that rare earth nanocrystals as small as 10 nm can be described, from a crystallographic point of view, as being bulk-like, macroscopic materials with distortions mainly affecting intra-chemical bonds within coordination polyhedra (short range order). &nbsp;This essentially means that, regarding the production of light in these specific rare earth materials, that 10 nanometer materials, 10 micrometer, 10 millimeter, and 10 centimeter materials behave<span>&nbsp;</span><strong><span style="text-decoration: underline;"><span>exactly the same way. &nbsp;</span></span></strong>However, smaller than 10 nanometers, the materials appear to behave differently. &nbsp;The direct consequence is that, optically speaking, discovering engineering-based mechanisms to improve significantly improve the light emission process efficiency in these nanomaterials compared to their bulk counterparts will be a significant challenge when only using physical size as a way to tune the properties. According to our data, nanocrystals with overall sizes lower than approximately 3.5 nm must be synthesized to see significant effects on the crystal structure. This size regime will be highly challenging to realize with the current knowledge base. &nbsp;</span></p> <p><span>&nbsp;</span></p> <p><span>We also discovered a phenomenon in light emission that bucks the conventional wisdom associated with rare earth-based light emitting materials. &nbsp;Our efforts demonstrated that in contrast to bulk-like europium-doped materials, when a high concentration of light emitting atoms (called activators) is present in a nanocrystal, this concentration is<span>&nbsp;</span><strong>NOT NECESSARILY&nbsp;</strong>detrimental to the luminescence process. &nbsp;Further, size confinement effects are the major factor in dramatic modification of the luminescence concentration quenching phenomenon. Although the exact mechanism for modification of optical behavior in these nanocrystals warrants further investigation, we established that the electromagnetic field that the atoms within the nanocrystal produces is an important parameter that has to be carefully considered when studying the optical properties of the nanocrystals. Further, the use of x-ray total scattering and PDF analyses revealed that the formation of a novel crystal structure for ultrathin (below ~3.5 nanometers) europium-doped nanocrystals can occur and is NOT identical to the arrangement of atoms that exists for its bulk counterpart.</span></p> <p><span>&nbsp;</span></p> <p><span>These results highlight that careful design and synthesis of rare earth nanostructures may lead to the observation of unforeseen physical phenomena that relate to their emission of light and, hence, could lead to major breakthroughs in their implementation in light emitting devices (in which rare earth materials have been used extensively), such as televisions or domestic and commercial lighting applications. &nbsp;</span></p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 01/23/2017<br>      Modified by: James&nbsp;H&nbsp;Dickerson</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The goal of this research project was to explore the relationship between the specific size of a nanocrystal (or nanoparticle), how the atoms that comprise the nanocrystal are arranged and/or become mis-arranged because of the size, and how light that may be produced by the nanocrystal could reveal information about the aforementioned arrangement or mis-arrangement.  To accompany the use of luminescence (a fancy word for production of light) to probe the structure (or arrangement of atoms), we have used complementary techniques to probe the nanocrystal(s).  The most effective complementary probe is x-ray total scattering experiments coupled an emerging theoretical modeling technique, called pair distribution functional (PDF) analysis.  In particular, PDF analysis can reveal substantial structural information at the nanoscale not only to help elucidate the formation of rare earth nanocrystals, but also to characterize their crystal structure.     Our experimental data clearly demonstrate two things: 1) that rare earth nanocrystals as small as 10 nm can be described, from a crystallographic point of view, as being bulk-like, macroscopic materials with distortions mainly affecting intra-chemical bonds within coordination polyhedra (short range order).  This essentially means that, regarding the production of light in these specific rare earth materials, that 10 nanometer materials, 10 micrometer, 10 millimeter, and 10 centimeter materials behave exactly the same way.  However, smaller than 10 nanometers, the materials appear to behave differently.  The direct consequence is that, optically speaking, discovering engineering-based mechanisms to improve significantly improve the light emission process efficiency in these nanomaterials compared to their bulk counterparts will be a significant challenge when only using physical size as a way to tune the properties. According to our data, nanocrystals with overall sizes lower than approximately 3.5 nm must be synthesized to see significant effects on the crystal structure. This size regime will be highly challenging to realize with the current knowledge base.       We also discovered a phenomenon in light emission that bucks the conventional wisdom associated with rare earth-based light emitting materials.  Our efforts demonstrated that in contrast to bulk-like europium-doped materials, when a high concentration of light emitting atoms (called activators) is present in a nanocrystal, this concentration is NOT NECESSARILY detrimental to the luminescence process.  Further, size confinement effects are the major factor in dramatic modification of the luminescence concentration quenching phenomenon. Although the exact mechanism for modification of optical behavior in these nanocrystals warrants further investigation, we established that the electromagnetic field that the atoms within the nanocrystal produces is an important parameter that has to be carefully considered when studying the optical properties of the nanocrystals. Further, the use of x-ray total scattering and PDF analyses revealed that the formation of a novel crystal structure for ultrathin (below ~3.5 nanometers) europium-doped nanocrystals can occur and is NOT identical to the arrangement of atoms that exists for its bulk counterpart.     These results highlight that careful design and synthesis of rare earth nanostructures may lead to the observation of unforeseen physical phenomena that relate to their emission of light and, hence, could lead to major breakthroughs in their implementation in light emitting devices (in which rare earth materials have been used extensively), such as televisions or domestic and commercial lighting applications.            Last Modified: 01/23/2017       Submitted by: James H Dickerson]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
