<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>COLLABORATIVE RESEARCH: ARWED - AUGMENTED PERCEPTION FOR UPPER-LIMB REHABILITATION</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/15/2014</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>152757.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>152757</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07020000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CBET</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Chem, Bioeng, Env, &amp; Transp Sys</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Aleksandr Simonian</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>asimonia@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922191</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>PI: Banerjee, Amarnath/Perez Gracia, Alba/Robson, Nina&lt;br/&gt;Proposal Number: 1403502/1403688/1404011&lt;br/&gt;Title: Collaborative Research: ARWED - Augmented Perception for Upper-Limb Rehabilitation&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Broader Significance &amp; Importance&lt;br/&gt;   Training and retraining the movement of individuals suffering loss of motor ability due to stroke is a challenging task. In many cases, only partial success is accomplished after long training sessions. Given the limitations of recovery for post-stroke patients, it is imperative that better tools and methods for retraining be developed. Even though several training hypotheses exist, such as need for an exact repetition of the training pattern, the solutions are still to be found. Overcoming some of these obstacles is the goal of this proposal. Recent studies show a direct link between human action perception and action execution. There is some evidence that the visual observation of human actions has an effect on the movement of the observer. This priming effect is reduced, or not present, when the motion is executed by a non-human device, such as a robot. This proposal aims to develop and test a novel wearable system for the training of the human arm. The system will allow the user to perceive the device as part of their upper limb (hence closing the perception/action loop). Training protocols based on observational learning findings will be implemented with the ARWED in order to develop it as rehabilitation training device for motor recovery in post-stroke patients.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Technical description&lt;br/&gt;   The intellectual merit centers on exploiting the link between action-observation and action execution in order to develop training protocols to facilitate rehabilitation following stroke. Currently, there are limited systems that utilize virtual reality in the relearning of biological movements. The proposed development of augmented wearable system (ARWED) requires solving several challenges in computer vision/modeling, and robot kinematic mapping. Testing the effectiveness of the device on priming the perception-action effect will require combined expertise from the areas of human kinematics, signal analysis, virtual reality, robotic fault recovery theory and rehabilitation. Therefore, the theoretical contributions emerging from this multidisciplinary collaborative research team will advance knowledge and understanding not only within the medical field, but also across the above-mentioned research areas.  The broader impact is based on the characteristics of the device to be developed, with an expanded ability in the training and re-training of patients with motor disabilities. Efficient design and manipulation will make the proposed ARWED system a reliable solution, which will be broadly utilized by medical professionals working in rehabilitation, sports therapy and convalescence. The proposed research will provide effective tools for the training and physical rehabilitation of patients with limb limitations at any scale, ranging from individuals suffering partial loss of motor ability to those with severe limitations in mobility due to strokes, birth defects or accidents. Motor learning theory shows that reducing feedback during practice benefits long term retention of motor skill training. Observational learning may offer greater benefits regarding transfer to ADLs, in comparison to robotic-based stroke training. Thus, a success indicator for these patients would be the beneficial transfer of training from the un-affected to affected limb or vice-versa. The ARWED system is expected to advance significantly the fundamentals of engineering and scientific knowledge, by implementing the device in experimental and educational work on cognition, telemanipulation and virtual reality. The medical community would also benefit from the development of the ARWED by furthering the understanding of how training using technology may enhance the recovery of motor control in diverse populations while providing a novel intervention that may prove more effective than what is currently available. The collaborative nature of the research team will lead to the education of undergraduate and graduate students in the areas of Engineering and Kinesiology. In the long run, the outcomes of the proposal will facilitate the communication between students that want to enter Physical and Occupational Therapy professions and those that want to design and develop mechanical devices that can aid in human recovery following neurological injury.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/06/2014</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/06/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1403688</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Marco</FirstName>
<LastName>Schoen</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>P</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Marco P Schoen</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>schomarc@isu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2082824377</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000379499</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/06/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Nancy</FirstName>
<LastName>Devine</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Nancy Devine</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>devinanc@isu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2082823992</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000589341</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/06/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Alba</FirstName>
<LastName>Perez Gracia</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Alba Perez Gracia</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>perealba@isu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2082822592</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000589476</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/06/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Idaho State University</Name>
<CityName>Pocatello</CityName>
<ZipCode>832090002</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2082822592</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>921 South 8th Avenue, Stop 8046</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[1651 Alvin Ricken Dr, Suite 116]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Idaho</StateName>
<StateCode>ID</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>ID02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>078341468</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>IDAHO STATE UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>078341468</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Idaho State University]]></Name>
<CityName>Pocatello</CityName>
<StateCode>ID</StateCode>
<ZipCode>832090002</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[921 S. 8th Ave]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Idaho</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>ID02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>5342</Code>
<Text>Disability &amp; Rehab Engineering</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>010E</Code>
<Text>DISABILITY RES &amp; HOMECARE TECH</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0114</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~152757</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>During this research, a tool for increasing the success of training and relearning for subjects suffering partial loss of motor ability has been developed and tested. This new Augmented Reality Wearable Device (ARWED) consists of virtual reality goggles and a depth camera, all integrated in a VR environment programmed in Unity. The system allows the creation of virtual scenarios but also the integration of the motion of the upper limbs, especially the hands, into the virtual reality. The goal is to tap into the visual information about action execution as a means to help overcome some of the proprioceptive loss that the patients experience.&#8232;The ARWED performs a symmetric reflection and real-time mapping of the stroke patient?s healthy limb onto the patient?s most affected limb. Using the ARWED, experiments were designed to test the extension of the action-observation priming effect linked to the mirror-neuron system on healthy subjects and then stroke patients.</p> <p>The completion of the proposed research resulted in the following outputs:</p> <ul> <li>Creation of two complete ARWED systems, with goggles, human arm sensing and processing power, and a suite of VR environments for training and analysis of human arm motion. The VR scenes allow direct and reflected sensing of both human forearms and hands.</li> <li>Determination of methods and models for precise human upper-limb kinematics, including skeleton synthesis and motion synergies.</li> <li>Development of a real-time based, upper-body motion identification system using surface EMG signals, artificial neural networks and fuzzy logic control.</li> <li>Successful testing of ARWED on healthy adult subjects to obtain the learning curves for performing a novel task within the VR direct and reflected views. Study of the effects on training stroke victims is under way and will be completed within a year.</li> </ul> <p>Future key outcomes could be developed from this research in the expanded application of virtual reality for human motion. We highlight the following possibilities:</p> <ul> <li>The results of the clinical trials will lead to decisions on the expansion of the ARWED system for rehabilitation and training of human motion.</li> <li>Add-on modules for the scalable design of mechanical motion augmentation devices such as exoskeletons or prostheses. </li> <li>Expansion to mixed reality devices for a more immersive experience.</li> <li>Development of faster models for human motion extraction.</li> </ul> <p>Intellectual merit</p> <p>Even though tapping on the mirror neurons for rehabilitation had been used before with the use of physical mirrors, the immersion in the virtual environment &nbsp;expands the field of action and the number of tasks that may be practiced.&nbsp; The results of the ongoing clinical trials will provide evidence regarding the effectiveness of using VR for utilizing the mirror neuron system in rehabilitation.</p> <p>Broader impact</p> <p>This project has allowed the creation and dissemination of new expertise in the use of engineering and technology in the health professions related to impaired human motion. We have accomplished this through specialized, interprofessional courses for university students and outreach to the local schools. We have experienced how virtual reality, in combination with human motion, is an excellent starting point to interest the general population in engineering and human health care. We envision this technology will be adopted to solve problems in many different activities.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 12/04/2018<br>      Modified by: Alba&nbsp;Perez Gracia</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ During this research, a tool for increasing the success of training and relearning for subjects suffering partial loss of motor ability has been developed and tested. This new Augmented Reality Wearable Device (ARWED) consists of virtual reality goggles and a depth camera, all integrated in a VR environment programmed in Unity. The system allows the creation of virtual scenarios but also the integration of the motion of the upper limbs, especially the hands, into the virtual reality. The goal is to tap into the visual information about action execution as a means to help overcome some of the proprioceptive loss that the patients experience.&#8232;The ARWED performs a symmetric reflection and real-time mapping of the stroke patient?s healthy limb onto the patient?s most affected limb. Using the ARWED, experiments were designed to test the extension of the action-observation priming effect linked to the mirror-neuron system on healthy subjects and then stroke patients.  The completion of the proposed research resulted in the following outputs:  Creation of two complete ARWED systems, with goggles, human arm sensing and processing power, and a suite of VR environments for training and analysis of human arm motion. The VR scenes allow direct and reflected sensing of both human forearms and hands. Determination of methods and models for precise human upper-limb kinematics, including skeleton synthesis and motion synergies. Development of a real-time based, upper-body motion identification system using surface EMG signals, artificial neural networks and fuzzy logic control. Successful testing of ARWED on healthy adult subjects to obtain the learning curves for performing a novel task within the VR direct and reflected views. Study of the effects on training stroke victims is under way and will be completed within a year.   Future key outcomes could be developed from this research in the expanded application of virtual reality for human motion. We highlight the following possibilities:  The results of the clinical trials will lead to decisions on the expansion of the ARWED system for rehabilitation and training of human motion. Add-on modules for the scalable design of mechanical motion augmentation devices such as exoskeletons or prostheses.  Expansion to mixed reality devices for a more immersive experience. Development of faster models for human motion extraction.   Intellectual merit  Even though tapping on the mirror neurons for rehabilitation had been used before with the use of physical mirrors, the immersion in the virtual environment  expands the field of action and the number of tasks that may be practiced.  The results of the ongoing clinical trials will provide evidence regarding the effectiveness of using VR for utilizing the mirror neuron system in rehabilitation.  Broader impact  This project has allowed the creation and dissemination of new expertise in the use of engineering and technology in the health professions related to impaired human motion. We have accomplished this through specialized, interprofessional courses for university students and outreach to the local schools. We have experienced how virtual reality, in combination with human motion, is an excellent starting point to interest the general population in engineering and human health care. We envision this technology will be adopted to solve problems in many different activities.          Last Modified: 12/04/2018       Submitted by: Alba Perez Gracia]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
