<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Interrogating Cadherin/Matrix Rigidity Dependent Neural Differentiation and Neuromuscular Junction Formation of Multipotent Stem Cells</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>06/15/2014</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>451416.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>451416</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07020000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CBET</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Chem, Bioeng, Env, &amp; Transp Sys</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Aleksandr Simonian</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>asimonia@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922191</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>PI: Kong, Hyunjoon    &lt;br/&gt;Proposal Number: 1403491&lt;br/&gt;Institution: University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign&lt;br/&gt;Title: Interrogating Cadherin/Matrix Rigidity Dependent Neural Differentiation and Neuromuscular Junction Formation of Multipotent Stem Cells&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Understanding and recreating neural networks represents a major scientific and engineering challenge with ramifications ranging from fundamental biology to clinical translation.  Stem cells residing in bone and fat tissue possess the potential to be converted to neurons that constitute neural networks. This cell conversion process is stimulated when cells contact each other and are cultured on a substrate that is not ?too hard? or ?too soft?, but that is ?just right?.  These neurons will help control muscle tissue movement, thus serving to create various biomedical tools used for fundamental and applied bioscience studies.  The studies in this proposal use a Jello-like hydrogel system linked with proteins involved in cell-cell communication and tuned to present a ?just right? softness. The successful completion of this project will therefore create an advanced cell culture platform that will be broadly useful for studying a wide array of stem cells and for exploiting this in neural tissue engineering.  The proposed work will also uncover the coordinate effects of cell-cell adhesions and matrix softness on stem cell fates, including differentiation into neurons. Finally, the results of the proposed study will be highly useful in creating various neural implants more efficiently than previously possible and intelligent, biological robots. Utilization of the results of this study as an educational module will have broad impacts by attracting future young scientists and encouraging them to pursue engineering careers.  This proposal is co-funded by the Biomedical Engineering Program in the Chemical, Bioengineering, Environmental and Transport Systems Division, and by the Biomaterials Program in the Division of Materials Research.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;There have been numerous attempts to reproduce neural networks and neuromuscular junctions in vitro for both fundamental and applied neuroscience studies that used neuronal cells differentiated from multipotent stem cells.  Therefore, it is crucial to regulate neural differentiation of stem cells in an elaborate manner, in terms of differentiation levels and glial-to-neural cell population.  The proposed research seeks to systematically understand and modulate the potential interplay between cell-cell adhesion and cell-matrix adhesion in regulating the neural differentiation of stem cells.  To this end, the goals of this proposed study are (1) to modulate the neural differentiation of multipotent, bone marrow stromal cells (BMSCs) by combining the effects of cadherin, a cell-cell adhesion protein, and matrix stiffness; and (2) to use the differentiated cholinergic neurons to build a functional, neuromuscular junction in vitro.  This goal will be accomplished by culturing BMSCs on a hydrogel chemically linked with a specific number of recombinant N- or E-cadherin, and further tailored to present controlled stiffness.  The integrative effects of cadherin and matrix rigidity on cellular differentiation, cell traction force, and Rac1-GTPase signal activation will be analyzed. Finally, differentiated cholinergic neurons will be co-cultured with skeletal myoblasts to form a neuromuscular junction and evaluate neural control over muscular contraction and relaxation. Successful completion of the proposed studies is expected to result in significant contributions in neuroscience and neuroengineering and stem cell technology.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/06/2014</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/06/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1403491</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Deborah</FirstName>
<LastName>Leckband</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Deborah Leckband</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>leckband@aries.scs.uiuc.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2172440793</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000453132</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/06/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Hyunjoon</FirstName>
<LastName>Kong</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Hyunjoon Kong</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>hjkong06@illinois.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2173331178</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000508487</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/06/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign</Name>
<CityName>Champaign</CityName>
<ZipCode>618207406</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2173332187</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1901 South First Street</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[Suite A]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Illinois</StateName>
<StateCode>IL</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>13</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>IL13</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>041544081</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF ILLINOIS</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>041544081</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign]]></Name>
<CityName>Urbana</CityName>
<StateCode>IL</StateCode>
<ZipCode>618013620</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[506 S. Wright Street]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Illinois</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>13</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>IL13</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>5345</Code>
<Text>Engineering of Biomed Systems</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7623</Code>
<Text>BIOMATERIALS PROGRAM</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>004E</Code>
<Text>BIOMEDICAL ENG AND DIAGNOSTICS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>017E</Code>
<Text>Cellular and Tissue Engineering</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>137E</Code>
<Text>Neural-engineering</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7573</Code>
<Text>BIO-RELATED MATERIALS RESEARCH</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8007</Code>
<Text>BioMaPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9102</Code>
<Text>WOMEN, MINORITY, DISABLED, NEC</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0114</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~451416</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Tissue-forming cells communicate with each other by forming bonds between protein molecules named cadherin. Such cross-talks between cells play significant roles in growth, conversion of cell type to another, and molecular secretion activities of cells. In the end, cells associated with cadherin molecules undergo normal development, regeneration, and remodeling of tissues and organs. For instance, neural cadherin denoted as N-cadherin is crucial for the formation and retention of neural networks. To this end, this study examined the hypothesis that immobilization of N-cadherin molecules synthesized in a bioreactor would be useful to recreating physiologically functional neural networks in vitro. This proposed study allowed us to accomplish three major outcomes as follows:</p> <p>(1)&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; We established advanced methods that immobilize N-cadherin molecules onto glass or hydrogel substrates tuned to present tissue-like softness. Briefly, N-cadherin molecules are tethered to a substrate using an antibody to molecules tagged to the end of N-cadherin molecules. Or, N-cadherin molecules are immobilized using a 2D material such as graphene oxide as a binder. The resulting substrate drove neural cells to form neural networks associated with glial cells. These neural networks were active to transport bioactive molecules and nanoparticle through extended neural axons as captured with a label-free microscopic imaging technique.</p> <p>(2)&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; We defined the sequence of N-cadherin that could significantly regulate mechanical force, biological signal transduction within cells, and secretion of protein molecules capable of stimulating the formation and retention of neural networks.</p> <p>(3)&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; We demonstrated that neural cells converted from stem cells can innervate muscle fibers in vitro and make the muscle contract with a neural stimulator and an inhibitor.</p> <p>(4)&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; This study also served to train two graduate students and two undergraduate students. Three of the students were women. One graduate student completed her thesis defense. Two undergraduate students became graduate students in other universities. We also used the results of this study in advancing Biotransport course, which aims to let students connect chemical engineering principles with physiology. In addition, we could use the results of this study to receive the NSF research training grant that aims to develop the next generation of brain scientists and engineers.</p> <p>&nbsp;Overall, this study successfully created in vitro platforms that could leverage biological effects of N-cadherin on neural network formation. The results of this study will be broadly useful to studying extents that N-cadherin modulate the in vitro development of other tissues such as bone and cartilage as well as the progress of various brain and neurological disorders and injuries.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 07/04/2019<br>      Modified by: Hyunjoon&nbsp;Kong</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Image         </div> <div class="galControls onePhoto" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation onePhoto" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1403491/1403491_10307805_1562286039069_Ellen_NeuronNetworks_2--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1403491/1403491_10307805_1562286039069_Ellen_NeuronNetworks_2--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Neuronal networks formed on N-cadherin-tethered substrate"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1403491/1403491_10307805_1562286039069_Ellen_NeuronNetworks_2--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Neuronal networks formed on N-cadherin-tethered substrate"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">The green color represents neuron, the red color represents glia, and the blue color represents cell nucleus.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Hyunjoon Kong</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Hyunjoon&nbsp;Kong</div> <div class="imageTitle">Neuronal networks formed on N-cadherin-tethered substrate</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Tissue-forming cells communicate with each other by forming bonds between protein molecules named cadherin. Such cross-talks between cells play significant roles in growth, conversion of cell type to another, and molecular secretion activities of cells. In the end, cells associated with cadherin molecules undergo normal development, regeneration, and remodeling of tissues and organs. For instance, neural cadherin denoted as N-cadherin is crucial for the formation and retention of neural networks. To this end, this study examined the hypothesis that immobilization of N-cadherin molecules synthesized in a bioreactor would be useful to recreating physiologically functional neural networks in vitro. This proposed study allowed us to accomplish three major outcomes as follows:  (1)            We established advanced methods that immobilize N-cadherin molecules onto glass or hydrogel substrates tuned to present tissue-like softness. Briefly, N-cadherin molecules are tethered to a substrate using an antibody to molecules tagged to the end of N-cadherin molecules. Or, N-cadherin molecules are immobilized using a 2D material such as graphene oxide as a binder. The resulting substrate drove neural cells to form neural networks associated with glial cells. These neural networks were active to transport bioactive molecules and nanoparticle through extended neural axons as captured with a label-free microscopic imaging technique.  (2)            We defined the sequence of N-cadherin that could significantly regulate mechanical force, biological signal transduction within cells, and secretion of protein molecules capable of stimulating the formation and retention of neural networks.  (3)            We demonstrated that neural cells converted from stem cells can innervate muscle fibers in vitro and make the muscle contract with a neural stimulator and an inhibitor.  (4)         This study also served to train two graduate students and two undergraduate students. Three of the students were women. One graduate student completed her thesis defense. Two undergraduate students became graduate students in other universities. We also used the results of this study in advancing Biotransport course, which aims to let students connect chemical engineering principles with physiology. In addition, we could use the results of this study to receive the NSF research training grant that aims to develop the next generation of brain scientists and engineers.   Overall, this study successfully created in vitro platforms that could leverage biological effects of N-cadherin on neural network formation. The results of this study will be broadly useful to studying extents that N-cadherin modulate the in vitro development of other tissues such as bone and cartilage as well as the progress of various brain and neurological disorders and injuries.             Last Modified: 07/04/2019       Submitted by: Hyunjoon Kong]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
