<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>P2C2:  Western Pacific Warm Pool Hydroclimate during the Last Glacial Maximum and the Deglaciation</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/15/2014</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>530005.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>530005</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>06020108</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>GEO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>AGS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Atmospheric &amp; Geospace Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>David Verardo</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>dverardo@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924695</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The West Pacific Warm Pool (WPWP) plays an important role in the global hydrological cycle, and its variability has significant socioeconomic consequences around the world. Understanding past climate conditions can improve predictions of future climate changes in this key region and beyond. This study will extend both the spatial and temporal resolution of paleoclimate data for the WPWP by studying cave formations (stalagmites) for two key periods: the Last Glacial Maximum (LGM; 19,000-21,000 years ago), when the mean climate was much colder than today, and the deglaciation (11,000-19,000 years ago), during which the global climate went through abrupt changes. Comparison between the cave data from a network of sites and model outputs will strengthen the climate interpretations made, and will improve the fidelity of both the reconstructions and the climate models. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This study will generate time series of stalagmite d18O, an established proxy for rainfall amount in the tropics, from the Philippines (eastern, central, and western sites), the Solomon Islands, and Vanuatu. These sites cover a wide range of precipitation variability, as seen during the modern era, and will provide information about past climate variability at sites that currently have little to no data. This study will sample the full range of the WPWP hydrologic response to climate change by reconstructing rainfall from the LGM to the Holocene. The end members of the cold LGM and the warm Holocene provide a measure of how sensitive WPWP rainfall is to global mean temperature. The temporal evolution during the deglaciation reveals the magnitude and spatial pattern of WPWP rainfall changes associated with abrupt climate events, and how much of a role the tropics participate in these events. The proxy data will be compared with various climate model simulations from the CMIP5 and PMIP2/PMIP3 archives and other sources, focusing on the spatial pattern and seasonality of climate changes, as well as the commonalities and diversity of different models. To investigate the teleconnection mechanisms of past abrupt climate changes, additional experiments will also be conducted with an atmospheric model. The proxy-model comparison will help validate climate models, which are being used for future climate projections, and the detailed model analysis and additional experiments will elucidate the mechanism of past abrupt climate changes. The research team will work closely with local scientists in the developing countries of Vanuatu and the Philippines, exchanging knowledge about climate issues and water availability, issues that have societal and security implications for small island nations. The project will provide a research experience an undergraduate student recruited through the GEOFORCE program, which is a selective outreach program of the Jackson School of Geosciences that trains high school students, mainly from demographic underrepresented in the geosciences, and involves them in fieldwork.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/09/2014</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/09/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.050</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1404003</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Judson</FirstName>
<LastName>Partin</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>W</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Judson W Partin</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>jpartin@ig.utexas.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>4042176888</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000532669</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/09/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Yuko</FirstName>
<LastName>Okumura</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Yuko Okumura</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>yukoo@ig.utexas.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5124710383</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000628708</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/09/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Texas at Austin</Name>
<CityName>Austin</CityName>
<ZipCode>787595316</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5124716424</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>3925 W Braker Lane, Ste 3.340</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Texas</StateName>
<StateCode>TX</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>10</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>TX10</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>170230239</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF TEXAS AT AUSTIN</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>042000273</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Texas Institute for Geophysics]]></Name>
<CityName>Austin</CityName>
<StateCode>TX</StateCode>
<ZipCode>787584445</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[10100 Burnet Rd., ROC/Bldg. 196]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Texas</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>10</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>TX10</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1530</Code>
<Text>Paleoclimate</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7754</Code>
<Text>CLIMATE VARIABILITY &amp; CHANGE</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8070</Code>
<Text>P2C2 Proposals</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>EGCH</Code>
<Text>ENVIRONMENT AND GLOBAL CHANGE</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0114</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~530005</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The western tropical Pacific is an important climate region, as the warm waters there affect the global atmospheric circulation. This project has discovered new ways in which western tropical Pacific rainfall varied in the past.&nbsp;Paleoclimate records of past rainfall changes provide perspective on longer-term rainfall variability in the&nbsp;western tropical Pacific&nbsp;that is not possible to have due to the short duration of the instrumental record.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>Paleoclimate proxies are indispensable not only for assessing the climate sensitivity to known forcing, but also for understanding the nature of climate variability that arises regardless of the presence of forcing. The importance of understanding natural climate variability was highlighted in the recent decade when a downturn of Pacific decadal variability is suggested to have stalled global warming. Modern observational records are far from sufficient to fully characterize such slow variability in the climate system. As part of the funded project, we explored the potential of paleoclimate proxy records for uncovering climate variability on time scales of 10-100 years. Specifically, we constructed a network of 60 annually resolved records of various proxies (coral, stalagmite, ice core, and ocean and lake sediment) covering varying periods over the last millennium collected from the NOAA paleoclimatology data archive and then extracted common signals of variability in the network using statistical technique. Our study is distinct from previous reconstructions of climate variability in that we do not make any assumptions about the patterns of variability based on modern observations, allowing discovery of new variability. The analysis indicates the dominance of natural decadal variability over the Pacific Ocean, confirming modern observations. The analysis also suggests the presence of previously unknown global pattern of variability. We plan to conduct a further study to confirm this finding.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>The Younger Dryas, a well-known period of abrupt climate change 12,000 years ago, occurred rapidly in northern latitudes but much more gradually in equatorial regions, a discovery that could prove important for understanding and responding to future climate change. The changes in temperature and rainfall are linked to a common cause: the slowdown of the ocean currents in the North Atlantic, which impact climate and temperature as they move warm water from the Gulf of Mexico up toward the Arctic. As the world warmed after the last ice age, glaciers melted and diluted northern seawater with freshwater. The resulting change in ocean water density disrupted the current and, in effect, the climate, causing a period of global cooling. This study discovered that the event also caused rainfall to decrease places as far away as the Philippines. However, while temperatures in Greenland responded quickly to the current shutdown, and subsequent reboot 1,000 years later, it took hundreds of years for rainfall in the Philippines to be impacted and to recover. Understanding the relationship between temperature and precipitation in the wake of climate change is particularly important because it previews what the future could have in store if the planet&rsquo;s ice sheets continue to lose mass and add freshwater to the North Atlantic.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 09/17/2018<br>      Modified by: Judson&nbsp;W&nbsp;Partin</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The western tropical Pacific is an important climate region, as the warm waters there affect the global atmospheric circulation. This project has discovered new ways in which western tropical Pacific rainfall varied in the past. Paleoclimate records of past rainfall changes provide perspective on longer-term rainfall variability in the western tropical Pacific that is not possible to have due to the short duration of the instrumental record.     Paleoclimate proxies are indispensable not only for assessing the climate sensitivity to known forcing, but also for understanding the nature of climate variability that arises regardless of the presence of forcing. The importance of understanding natural climate variability was highlighted in the recent decade when a downturn of Pacific decadal variability is suggested to have stalled global warming. Modern observational records are far from sufficient to fully characterize such slow variability in the climate system. As part of the funded project, we explored the potential of paleoclimate proxy records for uncovering climate variability on time scales of 10-100 years. Specifically, we constructed a network of 60 annually resolved records of various proxies (coral, stalagmite, ice core, and ocean and lake sediment) covering varying periods over the last millennium collected from the NOAA paleoclimatology data archive and then extracted common signals of variability in the network using statistical technique. Our study is distinct from previous reconstructions of climate variability in that we do not make any assumptions about the patterns of variability based on modern observations, allowing discovery of new variability. The analysis indicates the dominance of natural decadal variability over the Pacific Ocean, confirming modern observations. The analysis also suggests the presence of previously unknown global pattern of variability. We plan to conduct a further study to confirm this finding.     The Younger Dryas, a well-known period of abrupt climate change 12,000 years ago, occurred rapidly in northern latitudes but much more gradually in equatorial regions, a discovery that could prove important for understanding and responding to future climate change. The changes in temperature and rainfall are linked to a common cause: the slowdown of the ocean currents in the North Atlantic, which impact climate and temperature as they move warm water from the Gulf of Mexico up toward the Arctic. As the world warmed after the last ice age, glaciers melted and diluted northern seawater with freshwater. The resulting change in ocean water density disrupted the current and, in effect, the climate, causing a period of global cooling. This study discovered that the event also caused rainfall to decrease places as far away as the Philippines. However, while temperatures in Greenland responded quickly to the current shutdown, and subsequent reboot 1,000 years later, it took hundreds of years for rainfall in the Philippines to be impacted and to recover. Understanding the relationship between temperature and precipitation in the wake of climate change is particularly important because it previews what the future could have in store if the planet?s ice sheets continue to lose mass and add freshwater to the North Atlantic.          Last Modified: 09/17/2018       Submitted by: Judson W Partin]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
