<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Toroidal-spiral particles (TSPs) for co-delivery of multiple compounds of different sizes</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2014</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>390000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>390000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03070000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DMR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Materials Research</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Mohan Srinivasarao</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Nontechnical: This award by the Biomaterial program in the Division of Materials Research to University of Illinois Chicago is to develop a basic understanding of the materials-science basis for a new polymer-based technology to deliver a cocktail of therapeutic drugs locally to the sites of complex diseases such as brain tumors. Previous generations of polymeric drug-delivery vehicles have faced difficult challenges in encapsulation efficiency of expensive drugs, protecting the bioavailability of delicate protein drugs, and independent tuning of release profiles of multiple drugs for optimum therapeutic effect. Toroidal-spiral particles (donut shaped spiral particles - TSP) solve these problems via the novel internal structure and mechanism of particle formation and drug loading. The visually appealing nature of the experimental and computational results, as well as the societal relevance of the biomedical applications, represents a natural draw for high school students being recruited into chemical engineering. Publicity for educational modules and broader dissemination will occur through: 1) direct outreach to 21 Chicagoland high schools; 2) the annual American Institute of Chemical Engineers Chicago Section Student Symposium; and 3) "Science Minors" student workshops co-organized by the Principal Investigator and the Chicago Museum of Science and Industry.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Technical: This award enables research into key materials - science and functionality issues needed to unlock the technological and societal impact of a new polymeric platform for multi-drug delivery: toroidal-spiral particles (TSP). The toroidal-spiral (TS) structure of the particles is self-assembled through competitive kinetics of drop sedimentation, diffusion, and cross-linking. During the formation of the TSP, macromolecules such as therapeutic proteins and oligonucleotides can be auto-entrained into the TS channel, while a small molecular drug can be pre-blended into the polymer drops. Upon solidification into particles, the release of each compound occurs through a separate pathway and can be manipulated independently to reach therapeutic synergy. This project will address three main, enabling aspects of TSP technology:  (1) enhance many further biomedical and biotechnical applications, tunable biodegradation of TSP will be studied and measured; (2) independent manipulation of release profiles of cytotoxic drug versus therapeutic proteins will combine laboratory measurements with computational models to ascertain the structure-release relation and to optimize structures for biomedical applications; and (3) in vitro characterization the cellular association and activity of agents released from TSP will use model cell lines for brain tumors and endothelial tissue. In addition to multidisciplinary training of the graduate research assistants involved, fostering undergraduate research opportunities (emphasizing underrepresented minority student participation) and spin-offs in undergraduate engineering education, this project offers multiple avenues for outreach and dissemination among Chicago and grade 6-12 and community-college students.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/26/2014</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/26/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1404884</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Ludwig</FirstName>
<LastName>Nitsche</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>C</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Ludwig C Nitsche</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>Ludwig.Nitsche@udc.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>3123425998</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000380698</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/26/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Richard</FirstName>
<LastName>Gemeinhart</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>A</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Richard A Gemeinhart</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>rag@uic.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>3129962253</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000221963</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/26/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Ying</FirstName>
<LastName>Liu</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Ying Liu</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>liuying@uic.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>3129968249</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000526372</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/26/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Illinois at Chicago</Name>
<CityName>Chicago</CityName>
<ZipCode>606124305</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>3129962862</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>809 S. Marshfield Avenue</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[MB 502, M/C 551]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Illinois</StateName>
<StateCode>IL</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>IL07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>098987217</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF ILLINOIS</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>041544081</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Illinois at Chicago]]></Name>
<CityName>Chicago</CityName>
<StateCode>IL</StateCode>
<ZipCode>606124305</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Illinois</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>IL07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7623</Code>
<Text>BIOMATERIALS PROGRAM</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1711</Code>
<Text>MATERIALS EDUCATION AND RESEARCH</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7237</Code>
<Text>NANO NON-SOLIC SCI &amp; ENG AWD</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7573</Code>
<Text>BIO-RELATED MATERIALS RESEARCH</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0114</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~390000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Involving fundamental research (laboratory experiments integrated with computer simulations) informed by real-world biomedical applications, this research project advanced fluid-dynamic manufacturing of novel, polymeric particles (Toroidal Spiral Particles or &ldquo;TSP&rdquo;) that can be used as implantable carriers of drug cocktails and/or therapeutic cells. Complex diseases that could be potentially treated using the TSP platform include an aggressive kind of brain tumor known as glioblastoma multiforme (GBM) and type 1 diabetes. The basic idea behind our TSP manufacturing process is to form intricate shapes of a polymeric drop (including separate pockets to encapsulate multiple therapeutic agents) in the liquid phase and then solidify these shapes by UV- or chemically-triggered cross-linking. The resulting solid TSP contains, protects and dispenses the drugs for localized treatment at the disease site.</p> <p><span style="text-decoration: underline;">Liquid phase manufacturing.</span> The fluid dynamical manufacturing process involves a polymeric drop sedimenting slowly through a miscible, viscous liquid and self-assembling with several smaller satellite drops, each containing a different therapeutic agent to be encapsulated. Fine tuning these self-assembly kinetics required a combination of laboratory trials and computer simulations of drop deformation and sedimentation flow, and quantified the relation between experimental starting conditions and the internal fine structure and functionality of the resulting TSPs. Among other outcomes was a &ldquo;rule-of-thumb&rdquo; methodology for practitioners to set up starting conditions in the laboratory to achieve multi-drop coalescence into an optimum TSP without further trial-and-error. A scaling theory involving multiple physicochemical parameters was also developed for fast production of the TSPs of various sizes.</p> <p><span style="text-decoration: underline;">Localized disease treatment. </span>One potential application of TSPs is their use as post-surgical implantable polymeric devices for the treatment of complex diseases, such as glioblastoma multiforme (GBM). The use of biodegradable polymers for local delivery of chemotherapeutic agents overcomes the problems of systemic toxicity and inability of many drugs to cross the blood brain barrier (BBB). Local delivery also ensures a sufficiently high concentration of the drug at the site and reduces unnecessary harmful exposure to other organs.</p> <p><span style="text-decoration: underline;">Independently tunable multi-drug release. </span>Gliadel wafers were developed and used in clinical trials of GBM and showed promise for localized chemotherapy in the brain. However, for Gliadel wafers and other polymeric polymeric drug-delivery particles, release of multiple therapeutic agents on the ideal, separate release schedules of each remains challenging &ndash; especially when the therapeutic agents are of different molecular sizes. For example, consider small-molecule cytotoxic chemotherapy combined with large-molecule peptides or antibodies that require protection to preserve their function. Owing to their novel internal structure (an overall doughnut or toroidal shape with a well-defined, spiral-shaped internal channel near the surfaces), TSPs incorporate multiple pathways for drug release and can thereby fine-tune the release and protection of each agent independently to achieve optimum drug synergy for enhanced treatment of complex diseases.</p> <p><span style="text-decoration: underline;">Protection of therapeutic agents.</span> It was also demonstrated that TSPs could also be used to encapsulate therapeutic cells, including islet of Langerhans for treatment of type I diabetes. Islet transplant provides relatively long-term solution for type 1 diabetic patients. Although cell transplants are less intrusive than whole organ transplants, a closely matched donor for islet cells is still necessary and often patients need to take immune-suppressive drugs. The islets encapsulated in the TSPs were protected by the thin outer layer of the hydrogel to evade immune-system rejection, while the transport of small-molecular nutrients and insulin were not significantly hindered.</p> <p>This research project provided graduate and undergraduate students with interdisciplinary career-development opportunities to learn and apply computer simulations, advanced biomaterials techniques, material characterization skills, and appropriate handling of living materials. To disseminate the results of research, articles were published on high-impact journals and research findings were presented at national annual conferences by the graduate and undergraduate students. One patent has been issued for this technology (Self-assembled toroidal-spiral particles and manufacture and uses thereof, US 8852645 B2). An invention disclosure about islet cell encapsulation in TSPs is in preparation.</p> <p>In summary, integrating laboratory development with computer simulations, the results of this study provide the key fundamental-science basis for a novel way of manufacturing small particles with well-defined heterogeneous structures. Each part of the particles can be designed and manipulated individually to possess different material physicochemical and mechanical properties and provide unique biomedical advantages and functionalities when encapsulating drug compounds and/or therapeutic cells. Besides independently tunable drug-release schedules for drug synergy, the TSPs also provide a novel way of encapsulating implanted therapeutic cells to evade immune rejection while maintaining nutrient transport to the body. The TSPs provide a well-defined microenvironment to study cell viability, functionality, and differentiation. The physical principles of drop sedimentation and interaction developed by this study will have many applications in other field as well, such as printing, mixing, and droplet/particle production by an array of microfluidic capillaries in general.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 10/10/2018<br>      Modified by: Ying&nbsp;Liu</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Involving fundamental research (laboratory experiments integrated with computer simulations) informed by real-world biomedical applications, this research project advanced fluid-dynamic manufacturing of novel, polymeric particles (Toroidal Spiral Particles or "TSP") that can be used as implantable carriers of drug cocktails and/or therapeutic cells. Complex diseases that could be potentially treated using the TSP platform include an aggressive kind of brain tumor known as glioblastoma multiforme (GBM) and type 1 diabetes. The basic idea behind our TSP manufacturing process is to form intricate shapes of a polymeric drop (including separate pockets to encapsulate multiple therapeutic agents) in the liquid phase and then solidify these shapes by UV- or chemically-triggered cross-linking. The resulting solid TSP contains, protects and dispenses the drugs for localized treatment at the disease site.  Liquid phase manufacturing. The fluid dynamical manufacturing process involves a polymeric drop sedimenting slowly through a miscible, viscous liquid and self-assembling with several smaller satellite drops, each containing a different therapeutic agent to be encapsulated. Fine tuning these self-assembly kinetics required a combination of laboratory trials and computer simulations of drop deformation and sedimentation flow, and quantified the relation between experimental starting conditions and the internal fine structure and functionality of the resulting TSPs. Among other outcomes was a "rule-of-thumb" methodology for practitioners to set up starting conditions in the laboratory to achieve multi-drop coalescence into an optimum TSP without further trial-and-error. A scaling theory involving multiple physicochemical parameters was also developed for fast production of the TSPs of various sizes.  Localized disease treatment. One potential application of TSPs is their use as post-surgical implantable polymeric devices for the treatment of complex diseases, such as glioblastoma multiforme (GBM). The use of biodegradable polymers for local delivery of chemotherapeutic agents overcomes the problems of systemic toxicity and inability of many drugs to cross the blood brain barrier (BBB). Local delivery also ensures a sufficiently high concentration of the drug at the site and reduces unnecessary harmful exposure to other organs.  Independently tunable multi-drug release. Gliadel wafers were developed and used in clinical trials of GBM and showed promise for localized chemotherapy in the brain. However, for Gliadel wafers and other polymeric polymeric drug-delivery particles, release of multiple therapeutic agents on the ideal, separate release schedules of each remains challenging &ndash; especially when the therapeutic agents are of different molecular sizes. For example, consider small-molecule cytotoxic chemotherapy combined with large-molecule peptides or antibodies that require protection to preserve their function. Owing to their novel internal structure (an overall doughnut or toroidal shape with a well-defined, spiral-shaped internal channel near the surfaces), TSPs incorporate multiple pathways for drug release and can thereby fine-tune the release and protection of each agent independently to achieve optimum drug synergy for enhanced treatment of complex diseases.  Protection of therapeutic agents. It was also demonstrated that TSPs could also be used to encapsulate therapeutic cells, including islet of Langerhans for treatment of type I diabetes. Islet transplant provides relatively long-term solution for type 1 diabetic patients. Although cell transplants are less intrusive than whole organ transplants, a closely matched donor for islet cells is still necessary and often patients need to take immune-suppressive drugs. The islets encapsulated in the TSPs were protected by the thin outer layer of the hydrogel to evade immune-system rejection, while the transport of small-molecular nutrients and insulin were not significantly hindered.  This research project provided graduate and undergraduate students with interdisciplinary career-development opportunities to learn and apply computer simulations, advanced biomaterials techniques, material characterization skills, and appropriate handling of living materials. To disseminate the results of research, articles were published on high-impact journals and research findings were presented at national annual conferences by the graduate and undergraduate students. One patent has been issued for this technology (Self-assembled toroidal-spiral particles and manufacture and uses thereof, US 8852645 B2). An invention disclosure about islet cell encapsulation in TSPs is in preparation.  In summary, integrating laboratory development with computer simulations, the results of this study provide the key fundamental-science basis for a novel way of manufacturing small particles with well-defined heterogeneous structures. Each part of the particles can be designed and manipulated individually to possess different material physicochemical and mechanical properties and provide unique biomedical advantages and functionalities when encapsulating drug compounds and/or therapeutic cells. Besides independently tunable drug-release schedules for drug synergy, the TSPs also provide a novel way of encapsulating implanted therapeutic cells to evade immune rejection while maintaining nutrient transport to the body. The TSPs provide a well-defined microenvironment to study cell viability, functionality, and differentiation. The physical principles of drop sedimentation and interaction developed by this study will have many applications in other field as well, such as printing, mixing, and droplet/particle production by an array of microfluidic capillaries in general.          Last Modified: 10/10/2018       Submitted by: Ying Liu]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
