<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Searches for New Physics with Heavy-Flavor Rich Hadronic Final States in the Post-Higgs Era</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>05/15/2014</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>04/30/2015</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>465000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>155000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03010000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>PHY</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Physics</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Saul Gonzalez</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>sgonzale@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922093</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Overview:  A goal of experiments at the Large Hadron Collider (LHC) at CERN, Geneva, Switzerland is to understand the nature of the Higgs Boson, recently discovered there in 2012, and to discover new physics beyond the Standard Model of Elementary Particle Physics.  These goals are relevant to the understanding of the Universe at its most fundamental level in the fleeting fraction of a second just after the Big Bang, and to why we see the Universe as we do now.  To meet the challenges of this quest, new theories are advanced, new detectors and accelerators are developed and built, and new computing and analytical methodologies are created, all of which have significant broader impact for the training of young scientists in the near term and the advancement of technological benefits to society over the longer term.  &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The next three years represent a transition of the LHC physics program from a collision energy of 8 Teraelectronvole (TeV) data-taking and operation, to extended operations and data taking at nearly double the energy, 13-14 TeV.  Over a thousand scientists from the United States are involved with this scientific program on several major experiments.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Intellectual Merit: The research to be conducted under this award to Prof Miller of the University of Chicago and his group is aimed to address deep questions about the nature of the Universe from data collected with the ATLAS experiment, one of the major multipurpose detectors at the LHC.  Scientific questions addressed include: Is the newly discovered Higgs particle part of a larger theoretical picture that includes new particles that could be discovered at the new higher collision energy?  Why is the observed mass of the Higgs boson so low, found to be 126 billion electron volts, or roughly 135 times the mass of the proton?  In fact this low mass value is one of the most profound conundrums in all of science and is currently driving much of the scientific discourse in the field of particle physics.   What are the detailed properties of the heaviest of the quarks, the top quark, and the force carriers of the electroweak interaction, the W and Z bosons, at high energy?   These questions are critical to our understanding of the full context of the Standard Model of particle physics and to new physics that lies beyond the Standard Model.   &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Technically, Miller and his group will be preparing the ATLAS detector, particularly the calorimetry which measures particle energies, for operations at 13-14 TeV.  Analytically, they will be refining their physics analyses on the lower energy 8 TeV data in preparation for new measurements and potential discoveries in the high energy collisions.  When the high energy data comes in, the group will focus on searches for supersymmetry through the study of heavily boosted top quarks, which could provide information on extended models of Supersymmetry.  Such models, if shown to be valid, are theoretically attractive as they can accommodate the observed low value of the Higgs Mass. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Broader Impact: Miller and his group will lead activities will directly benefit the local community in Chicago as well as society at large, both by training students (high school, undergraduate, and graduate) and postdocs, and by enhancing the prominence of Science, Technology, Engineering, and Mathematics (STEM) in the community. A special new outreach program will be established with Lane Tech College Prep High School.  The proposed activities include directly mentoring and working with Lane Tech students to bring the excitement felt by High Energy Physicists today into the classroom and to truly stimulate the students using modern, high-tech, and real-life projects in science.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>05/06/2014</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>09/01/2015</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1404465</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>David</FirstName>
<LastName>Miller</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>W</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>David W Miller</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>David.W.Miller@uchicago.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>7737027671</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000652290</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/06/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Chicago</Name>
<CityName>Chicago</CityName>
<ZipCode>606372612</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>7737028669</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>6054 South Drexel Avenue</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[Suite 300]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Illinois</StateName>
<StateCode>IL</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>IL01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>005421136</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF CHICAGO, THE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>005421136</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Chicago]]></Name>
<CityName>Chicago</CityName>
<StateCode>IL</StateCode>
<ZipCode>606371433</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[5640 South Ellis Avenue]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Illinois</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>IL01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1221</Code>
<Text>HEP-High Energy Physics</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7483</Code>
<Text>PHYSICS OF THE UNIVERSE</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0114</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~155000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>&nbsp;&nbsp; The funding provided by NSF Award 1404465, titled "Searches for New Physics with Heavy-Flavor Rich Hadronic Final States in the Post-Higgs Era", have provided the support necessary to conduct ground breaking research at the energy frontier. Using the data provided by the Large Hadron Collider (LHC) and the intellectual and research facilities resources at the University of Chicago, my group has had a major impact on the development of pattern recognition algorithms needed to find evidence for completely new phenomena being produced in the highest energy collisions in the world. Moreover, we are building new electronic systems that are necessary to collect, sort and analyze a even greater volume of data in the future. In addition, I have continued to bring this research and the spirit of inquiry that my group embodies to the broader community through two key efforts, one aimed at elementary school students and the other at high school students.<br />&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; <br />&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; Along with one graduate student, Giordon Stark, two undergraduate students, Natalie Harrison and Daniel Sullivan, and one postdoctoral researcher, Reina Camacho, my group has made major progress in researching new ultrafast electronics for sifting in real-time through the enormous dataset produced by the LHC. With graduate student Miles Wu we have measured for the first time a process that is predicted to occur extremely rarely in nature, but which had never before been directly observed. This observation has significant implications for how we think about and predict the likelihood of observing other ompletely new phenomena in nature.<br />&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; <br />&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; With all of these extremely technical activities, it is easy to get lost in the research. But my group has made it a priority to deliver the most important of the fruits of our labor to the broader community: the excitement of asking, and then answering, questions. To this end, the Enrico Fermi Summer Interns program that I lead in summer 2014 was enormously successful. The potential impact of exposing 7th grade students in Chicago Public Schools to electronics design principles, software programming, and physics measurements is incalculable. It is very likely, especially given the large fraction of young girls who attended the program, that the program will impact these girls&rsquo; likelihood of enjoying math and science in school, and hopefully going on to have impactful careers in which they carry those crucial principles of critical thinking and logical design. In addition, the program that we engaged in at Lane Tech High School included a "Virtual Visit" of a Lane Tech High School physics classroom to the ATLAS Experiment Control Room. This visit was hosted locally by postdoctoral researcher Lauren Tompkins, graduate student Sam Meehan, and I. We had "bell-to-bell" questions from the students regarding what it was like to work at CERN and what we would recommend to high school students interested in physics research.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 12/04/2015<br>      Modified by: David&nbsp;W&nbsp;Miller</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Image         </div> <div class="galControls onePhoto" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation onePhoto" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2015/1404465/1404465_10301989_1449260855381_BoardTests--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2015/1404465/1404465_10301989_1449260855381_BoardTests--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Board tests of the gFEX trigger system"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2015/1404465/1404465_10301989_14492...]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[    The funding provided by NSF Award 1404465, titled "Searches for New Physics with Heavy-Flavor Rich Hadronic Final States in the Post-Higgs Era", have provided the support necessary to conduct ground breaking research at the energy frontier. Using the data provided by the Large Hadron Collider (LHC) and the intellectual and research facilities resources at the University of Chicago, my group has had a major impact on the development of pattern recognition algorithms needed to find evidence for completely new phenomena being produced in the highest energy collisions in the world. Moreover, we are building new electronic systems that are necessary to collect, sort and analyze a even greater volume of data in the future. In addition, I have continued to bring this research and the spirit of inquiry that my group embodies to the broader community through two key efforts, one aimed at elementary school students and the other at high school students.          Along with one graduate student, Giordon Stark, two undergraduate students, Natalie Harrison and Daniel Sullivan, and one postdoctoral researcher, Reina Camacho, my group has made major progress in researching new ultrafast electronics for sifting in real-time through the enormous dataset produced by the LHC. With graduate student Miles Wu we have measured for the first time a process that is predicted to occur extremely rarely in nature, but which had never before been directly observed. This observation has significant implications for how we think about and predict the likelihood of observing other ompletely new phenomena in nature.          With all of these extremely technical activities, it is easy to get lost in the research. But my group has made it a priority to deliver the most important of the fruits of our labor to the broader community: the excitement of asking, and then answering, questions. To this end, the Enrico Fermi Summer Interns program that I lead in summer 2014 was enormously successful. The potential impact of exposing 7th grade students in Chicago Public Schools to electronics design principles, software programming, and physics measurements is incalculable. It is very likely, especially given the large fraction of young girls who attended the program, that the program will impact these girlsÆ likelihood of enjoying math and science in school, and hopefully going on to have impactful careers in which they carry those crucial principles of critical thinking and logical design. In addition, the program that we engaged in at Lane Tech High School included a "Virtual Visit" of a Lane Tech High School physics classroom to the ATLAS Experiment Control Room. This visit was hosted locally by postdoctoral researcher Lauren Tompkins, graduate student Sam Meehan, and I. We had "bell-to-bell" questions from the students regarding what it was like to work at CERN and what we would recommend to high school students interested in physics research.       Last Modified: 12/04/2015       Submitted by: David W Miller]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
