<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Geometric structures and invariants of links and 3-manifolds</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>06/15/2014</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>224415.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>224415</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DMS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Joanna Kania-Bartoszynska</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>jkaniaba@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924881</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The research of this project falls in the area of 3-dimensional topology. The central objects of study in this area are spaces called 3-manifolds. A 3-manifold is an object that locally looks like the ordinary 3- dimensional space but whose global structure can be complicated. An important part of 3-dimensional topology is also the study of knots (loops embedded in some tangled way in 3-manifolds) and their classification. The solution of Thurston's Geometrization Conjecture has established that 3-manifolds (and complements of knots in them) decompose into pieces that admit explicit geometries and that hyperbolic geometry is the one that appears more often. In practice, however, 3-manifolds are often given in terms of combinatorial topological descriptions and it is both natural and important to seek ways to deduce geometric information from these descriptions. One of the ways that topologists have been approaching the study of 3- manifolds is through the use of invariants. In the last few decades ideas originated in physics led mathematicians to the discovery of a variety of invariants of knots and 3-manifolds. Understanding the connections of topological and combinatorial quantities and invariants to geometry is a central and important goal of low dimensional topology. The main theme of this project is to establish such connections and explore their ramifications and applications to other areas of mathematics.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project will establish relationships between geometry and combinatorial descriptions, properties, and quantum invariants of links and 3-manifolds. The PI has developed a setting for establishing new unexpected relations between the colored Jones link polynomials, the topology and geometry of essential surfaces in link complements, and hyperbolic geometry. One part of the project will continue developing this theory and exploring its applications. Another part, will combine several new techniques, to develop methods for recognizing geometric structures on 3-manifolds from purely combinatorial input, and derive estimates on geometric quantities from topological data. A third part will study skein link theory in 3-manifolds, its invariants, and its interaction with geometric decompositions of 3-manifolds.  A fourth part will explore the applicability of  quantum knot invariants to classical questions in knot theory and search for a classification of crossing changes that do not alter the topology of the underlying knots. The project also involves the  research of graduate students currently working with PI.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/12/2014</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/12/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1404754</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Efstratia</FirstName>
<LastName>Kalfagianni</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Efstratia Kalfagianni</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>kalfagia@math.msu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5173536333</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000148284</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/12/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Michigan State University</Name>
<CityName>East Lansing</CityName>
<ZipCode>488242600</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5173555040</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>Office of Sponsored Programs</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[426 Administration Bldg, Rm2]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Michigan</StateName>
<StateCode>MI</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>08</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MI08</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>193247145</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>MICHIGAN STATE UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>053343976</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Michigan State University]]></Name>
<CityName>East Lansing</CityName>
<StateCode>MI</StateCode>
<ZipCode>488241000</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Michigan</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>08</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MI08</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1267</Code>
<Text>TOPOLOGY</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0114</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~224415</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><br /><br /><span>The research of this project falls in the area of 3-dimensional topology. The central objects of study in this area are spaces called 3-manifolds. A 3-manifold is an object that locally looks like the ordinary 3- dimensional space but whose global structure can be complicated. An important part of 3-dimensional topology is also the study of knots (loops embedded in some tangled way in 3-manifolds) and their classification. The solution of Thurston's Geometrization Conjecture has established that 3-manifolds (and complements of knots in them) decompose into pieces that admit explicit geometries and that hyperbolic geometry is the one that appears more often. In practice, however, 3-manifolds are often given in terms of combinatorial topological descriptions and it is both natural and important to seek ways to deduce geometric information from these descriptions. One of the ways that topologists have been approaching the study of 3- manifolds is through the use of invariants. In the last few decades ideas originated in physics led mathematicians to the discovery of a variety of invariants of knots and 3-manifolds. Understanding the connections of topological and combinatorial quantities and invariants to geometry is a central and important goal of low dimensional topology.&nbsp;</span><br /><span>The &nbsp;project established such connections and explored their ramifications and applications to other areas of mathematics.</span><br /><br /><br /><span>This project has established relationships between geometry and combinatorial descriptions, properties, and quantum invariants of links and 3-manifolds. In one direction the PI</span><br /><span>developed settings for establishing new unexpected relations between the colored Jones link polynomials, the topology and geometry of essential surfaces in link complements, and hyperbolic geometry. In another direction the PI &nbsp;combined several new techniques, to develop methods for recognizing geometric structures on 3-manifolds from purely combinatorial input, and derived estimates on geometric quantities from topological data. A third part &nbsp;explored the applicability of quantum knot invariants to classical questions in knot theory and search for a classification of crossing changes that do not alter the topology of the underlying knots. The project also involved the research of PhD graduate students working with PI.</span><br /><br /><span>During the life of the award the PI and her graduate students published 12 papers, with research on this project, in peer reviewed journals. The PI also published a book chapter with a survey article that is suitable for graduate students and newcomers in the field of hyperbolic knot theory. </span></p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p><span>Three of the PI's PhD students graduated during the life of the award and have received positions in academia or industry. The PI offered graduate courses at Michigan State University on topics closely related to the research outcomes of this project. Some of the students registered in this courses are now working towards a PhD in mathematics under the direction of the PI. The PI is currently supervising five graduate students.</span><br /><br /><span>The PI presented research resulting from this project at several &nbsp;professional meetings and seminars, some of which were international. The PI also lectured at two conferences (one international and one in the USA)</span><br /><span>aiming to increase networking and collaboration among women mathematicians.</span></p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 07/01/2019<br>      Modified by: Efstratia&nbsp;Kalfagianni</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[   The research of this project falls in the area of 3-dimensional topology. The central objects of study in this area are spaces called 3-manifolds. A 3-manifold is an object that locally looks like the ordinary 3- dimensional space but whose global structure can be complicated. An important part of 3-dimensional topology is also the study of knots (loops embedded in some tangled way in 3-manifolds) and their classification. The solution of Thurston's Geometrization Conjecture has established that 3-manifolds (and complements of knots in them) decompose into pieces that admit explicit geometries and that hyperbolic geometry is the one that appears more often. In practice, however, 3-manifolds are often given in terms of combinatorial topological descriptions and it is both natural and important to seek ways to deduce geometric information from these descriptions. One of the ways that topologists have been approaching the study of 3- manifolds is through the use of invariants. In the last few decades ideas originated in physics led mathematicians to the discovery of a variety of invariants of knots and 3-manifolds. Understanding the connections of topological and combinatorial quantities and invariants to geometry is a central and important goal of low dimensional topology.  The  project established such connections and explored their ramifications and applications to other areas of mathematics.   This project has established relationships between geometry and combinatorial descriptions, properties, and quantum invariants of links and 3-manifolds. In one direction the PI developed settings for establishing new unexpected relations between the colored Jones link polynomials, the topology and geometry of essential surfaces in link complements, and hyperbolic geometry. In another direction the PI  combined several new techniques, to develop methods for recognizing geometric structures on 3-manifolds from purely combinatorial input, and derived estimates on geometric quantities from topological data. A third part  explored the applicability of quantum knot invariants to classical questions in knot theory and search for a classification of crossing changes that do not alter the topology of the underlying knots. The project also involved the research of PhD graduate students working with PI.  During the life of the award the PI and her graduate students published 12 papers, with research on this project, in peer reviewed journals. The PI also published a book chapter with a survey article that is suitable for graduate students and newcomers in the field of hyperbolic knot theory.      Three of the PI's PhD students graduated during the life of the award and have received positions in academia or industry. The PI offered graduate courses at Michigan State University on topics closely related to the research outcomes of this project. Some of the students registered in this courses are now working towards a PhD in mathematics under the direction of the PI. The PI is currently supervising five graduate students.  The PI presented research resulting from this project at several  professional meetings and seminars, some of which were international. The PI also lectured at two conferences (one international and one in the USA) aiming to increase networking and collaboration among women mathematicians.       Last Modified: 07/01/2019       Submitted by: Efstratia Kalfagianni]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
