<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Research in Novel Symmetries of Quantum Field and String Theory</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/15/2014</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>344886.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>344886</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03010000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>PHY</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Physics</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Bogdan Mihaila</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>bmihaila@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032928235</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This award funds the research of Professor Nikita Nekrasov of SUNY Stony Brook. All known interactions of elementary particles are described by mathematical symmetries called gauge symmetries. The Standard Model of elementary particles is described by such a gauge symmetry. In physical systems there are often several ground states which describe the system (ice and water at the freezing point has two ground states, for example), and gauge symmetries are no exception. This research will study the different ground states of various systems, including gauge theories. It has recently been realized that the ground states of some systems can be related closely to ground states of very different systems. For example, phase transitions in condensed matter systems are closely related to the possible ground states of gauge theories; ground states of strongly correlated electron systems are related to those in quantum information theory, etc. This synergistic research in mathematical physics offers the possibility of connecting what appear to be very different physical systems. Connections between apparently different systems have had great impact in the past. The study of superconductivity by Landau and Ginzburg led to the Higgs mechanism of the Standard Model, the purely mathematical study of the Riemann zeta function led to a better understanding of prime numbers and this has had major impact in cryptography, and the mathematical study of string theory has led to a better understanding of the properties of strongly interacting particles such as protons and pions.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award is for support of theoretical research and education on gauge theory in various space-time dimensions, models of statistical physics relevant for strongly correlated electron systems and the theory of phase transitions, and models of string theory relevant for studies of strongly coupled phenomena and the nature of space-time at fundamentally small scales. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The unique nature of this project is the broad impact of the cluster of questions being investigated. It touches upon the gauge theories describing the interactions of fundamental particles, the kind studied at the LHC experiment at CERN and at others machines all over the world, and the gauge theories with various degrees of supersymmetry, theoretical laboratories for testing ideas of importance for phenomenology; the quasi-one and two-dimensional strongly correlated electron systems studied in different laboratories in connection with quantum information on the one hand and superconductivity on the other hand; mathematical questions of algebraic geometric and topological nature, functional analysis and the study of spectra of Schroedinger operators and their  non-hermitian analogues; foundations of quantum mechanics and the very art of quantization; topological strings and the topological quantum gravity.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The unifying theme in all these problems is the reduction of the non-perturbative partition function of gauge/string theory computed in a specific supergravity background to a statistical mechanical model. The correlation functions of the statistical model are related to matrix elements of generators of some infinite dimensional algebraic structure.  It is planned to use the techniques and methods of all the fields of research mentioned above. Specifically, it is planned to generalize the Ward and Dyson-Schwinger identities of quantum field theory to incorporate non-perturbative phenomena. The intention is to establish, using these identities, that the gauge theories, at least supersymmetric gauge theories, possess a new type of symmetry, at least in the low-energy regime, which is a deformation of conventional symmetries of two dimensional conformal field theories. Using these symmetries it is hoped to find new geometric and algebraic structures in the landscape of vacua of grand unified theories and  possibly even string compactifications. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The research lies at the interface of several domains of theoretical physics and several domains of mathematics and provides a good environment for training graduate students.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/03/2014</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/26/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1404446</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Nikita</FirstName>
<LastName>Nekrasov</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Nikita Nekrasov</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>nikitastring@gmail.com</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6316321555</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000655366</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/03/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>SUNY at Stony Brook</Name>
<CityName>Stony Brook</CityName>
<ZipCode>117940001</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6316329949</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>WEST 5510 FRK MEL LIB</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NY01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>804878247</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>RESEARCH FOUNDATION FOR THE STATE UNIVERSITY OF NEW YORK, THE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>020657151</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Simons Center for Geometry and Physics, Stony Brook]]></Name>
<CityName>Stony Brook</CityName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<ZipCode>117943362</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[Simons Center]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NY01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1286</Code>
<Text>Elem. Particle Physics/Theory</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1287</Code>
<Text>MATHEMATICAL PHYSICS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0114</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0115</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0116</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~114962</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2015~114962</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2016~114962</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The project "Research in novel symmetries of quantum field theory and string theory" is dedicated to exploring the foundations of theories which describe the world of elementary particles. One of the major theoretical challenges which face physicists is the selection problem. Namely, the quantum theories describing not only the interactions of elementary particles carried by the exchange of spin one intermediary bosons, such as photons, W and Z bosons, and gluons, but also the gravitational interactions (the only viable candidate known to the PI is string theory) posess a multitude of ground states. The number of stable supersymmetric vacua is so large that simply enumerating them on a computer would take more time than the age of the observable Universe. On top of that, the nonsupersymmetric metastable states which are better describing our world are none less numerous. The principle which would explain why the parameters of the Standard Model are what they are (apart from the anthropic like principles) is still lacking.&nbsp;&nbsp;</p> <p>A tantalizing idea which&nbsp; could reduce the enormity of string landscape is a novel symmetry principle. Normally the vacua related to each other by some symmetry transformation are identified. But the conventional symmetries would ensure that all the parameters of the effective physics at the vacua are identical.&nbsp;</p> <p>However, recently the novel type of symmetries, acting between physically distinct vacua of supersymmetric theory, were discovered. They do not form a group, like the ordinary symmetries. Instead, they form one of the so-called quantum algebras, such as the Yangian or quantum affine algebra, which were found to be the spectrum generating algebras of spin chains.&nbsp;</p> <p>The major goal of the project was to find the observables in the supersymmetric gauge theory and string theory which are best suited for the exploiting the consequences of the non-perturbative Dyson-Schwinger equations, and which may form the maximal commutative part of the quantum algebra from the previous paragraph. The reason for starting with the commutative subalgebra is two-fold. First, the historical precedent. To construct the conventional non-abelian symmetry groups, such as the isospin SU(2) or the eightfold way SU(3) one may start with the maximal commutative subgroup and then add the generators corresponding to the so-called roots. In the irreducible representations (the building blocks of the symmetry realizations) the maximal commutative subalgebra is used to define a basis, by looking at the joint eigenvectors. For example,the proton and the neutron are the isospin eigenvectors. The second reason is the paradigm shift. The commutative subalgebra of the Landscape quantum algebra acts within a given quantum field theory, preserves its vacua, and therefore may be expected to be contained within the operator algebra of the given theory. The roots would correspond to the domain walls joining different vacua or different quantum field theories, and will be a subject of the future research.&nbsp;&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>This goal was succesfully accomplished by defining a class of local and semi-local observables, called the qq-characters, in the supersymmetric gauge theories in a broad range of dimensions, on regular and singular spacetimes, in the bulk and in the presence of various defects.&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>The award sponsored research led to the firm confirmation of the BPS/CFT correspondence proposed by the PI in 2004. The BPS/CFT principle states that the correlation functions of the supersymmetry protected operators in quantum field theories in various spacetime dimensions are equal to the conformal blocks and form-factors of two-dimensional conformal field theories and their massive integrable deformations. As a special case this principle establishes a connection between quantum integrable systems and supersymmetric vacua of gauge theories, the so-called Bethe/gauge-correspondence, discovered in a class of examples by the PI and S.Shatashvili circa 2006 and further explored by the research supported by the award.&nbsp;</p> <p>New venues of research both in quantum field and string theory and in the broad range of mathematical disciplines has been opened.&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>A long (~250pp) manuscript by the PI&nbsp; "BPS/CFT correspondence" split into five volumes has summarized the results of this research, accompanied by several papers published by the graduate students working under the PI's supervision.&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>A more detailed list of results&nbsp; is available in the&nbsp;Accomplishments file</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 12/01/2017<br>      Modified by: Nikita&nbsp;Nekrasov</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The project "Research in novel symmetries of quantum field theory and string theory" is dedicated to exploring the foundations of theories which describe the world of elementary particles. One of the major theoretical challenges which face physicists is the selection problem. Namely, the quantum theories describing not only the interactions of elementary particles carried by the exchange of spin one intermediary bosons, such as photons, W and Z bosons, and gluons, but also the gravitational interactions (the only viable candidate known to the PI is string theory) posess a multitude of ground states. The number of stable supersymmetric vacua is so large that simply enumerating them on a computer would take more time than the age of the observable Universe. On top of that, the nonsupersymmetric metastable states which are better describing our world are none less numerous. The principle which would explain why the parameters of the Standard Model are what they are (apart from the anthropic like principles) is still lacking.    A tantalizing idea which  could reduce the enormity of string landscape is a novel symmetry principle. Normally the vacua related to each other by some symmetry transformation are identified. But the conventional symmetries would ensure that all the parameters of the effective physics at the vacua are identical.   However, recently the novel type of symmetries, acting between physically distinct vacua of supersymmetric theory, were discovered. They do not form a group, like the ordinary symmetries. Instead, they form one of the so-called quantum algebras, such as the Yangian or quantum affine algebra, which were found to be the spectrum generating algebras of spin chains.   The major goal of the project was to find the observables in the supersymmetric gauge theory and string theory which are best suited for the exploiting the consequences of the non-perturbative Dyson-Schwinger equations, and which may form the maximal commutative part of the quantum algebra from the previous paragraph. The reason for starting with the commutative subalgebra is two-fold. First, the historical precedent. To construct the conventional non-abelian symmetry groups, such as the isospin SU(2) or the eightfold way SU(3) one may start with the maximal commutative subgroup and then add the generators corresponding to the so-called roots. In the irreducible representations (the building blocks of the symmetry realizations) the maximal commutative subalgebra is used to define a basis, by looking at the joint eigenvectors. For example,the proton and the neutron are the isospin eigenvectors. The second reason is the paradigm shift. The commutative subalgebra of the Landscape quantum algebra acts within a given quantum field theory, preserves its vacua, and therefore may be expected to be contained within the operator algebra of the given theory. The roots would correspond to the domain walls joining different vacua or different quantum field theories, and will be a subject of the future research.       This goal was succesfully accomplished by defining a class of local and semi-local observables, called the qq-characters, in the supersymmetric gauge theories in a broad range of dimensions, on regular and singular spacetimes, in the bulk and in the presence of various defects.      The award sponsored research led to the firm confirmation of the BPS/CFT correspondence proposed by the PI in 2004. The BPS/CFT principle states that the correlation functions of the supersymmetry protected operators in quantum field theories in various spacetime dimensions are equal to the conformal blocks and form-factors of two-dimensional conformal field theories and their massive integrable deformations. As a special case this principle establishes a connection between quantum integrable systems and supersymmetric vacua of gauge theories, the so-called Bethe/gauge-correspondence, discovered in a class of examples by the PI and S.Shatashvili circa 2006 and further explored by the research supported by the award.   New venues of research both in quantum field and string theory and in the broad range of mathematical disciplines has been opened.      A long (~250pp) manuscript by the PI  "BPS/CFT correspondence" split into five volumes has summarized the results of this research, accompanied by several papers published by the graduate students working under the PI's supervision.      A more detailed list of results  is available in the Accomplishments file       Last Modified: 12/01/2017       Submitted by: Nikita Nekrasov]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
