<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>CI-EN: Enhancing and Supporting a Community-Based Data Analysis, Visualization, and Provenance Platform</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2014</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>499962.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>499962</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>05050000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>CSE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CNS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Computer and Network Systems</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Sylvia Spengler</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>sspengle@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032928930</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Increasingly, scientific breakthroughs are being enabled by advanced computing capabilities that allow researchers to explore growing volumes of digital data. Unfortunately, the infrastructure to design and conduct computational experiments has not kept pace with our ability to gather and generate data, leading to an unprecedented situation: data exploration is now the bottleneck to discovery.  In this project, we will build infrastructure to streamline data exploration that supports a wide array of modern computational resources and tools, as well as enable transparency and reproducibility of scientific results.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project builds upon the successful VisTrails open-source system.  VisTrails provides unique support for data-intensive research, a comprehensive provenance infrastructure, and a user-centered design.  The system has been applied to a broad range of disciplines, including environmental science, physics, and bioinformatics, both for research and educational efforts.  With a view towards expanding the impact of the VisTrails system to the computer science community, we will extend it in three significant directions, notably: add support for multi-threaded and parallel execution and programming frameworks such as Mapreduce; improve the extensibility of the system through support for Java libraries as well as flexible mechanisms for scripting; and  design new infrastructure to simplify the creation and packaging of reproducible experiments. These improvements will enable new research opportunities by providing a platform for computationally-demanding experiments and supporting for large-scale data analysis, as well as for provenance research. In addition, we hope it will contribute to a broader adoption of verified reproducibility in computer science publications.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/05/2014</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/21/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.070</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1405927</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Juliana</FirstName>
<LastName>Freire</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Juliana Freire</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>juliana.freire@nyu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6469974128</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000183765</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/05/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>David</FirstName>
<LastName>Koop</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>A</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>David A Koop</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>dakoop@niu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>8157530378</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000632177</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/05/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>New York University</Name>
<CityName>NEW YORK</CityName>
<ZipCode>100121019</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2129982121</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>70 WASHINGTON SQUARE S</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>10</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NY10</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>041968306</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>NEW YORK UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>041968306</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Polytechnic University of New York]]></Name>
<CityName>Brooklyn</CityName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<ZipCode>112013826</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>08</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NY08</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7359</Code>
<Text>CCRI-CISE Cmnty Rsrch Infrstrc</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7359</Code>
<Text>COMPUTING RES INFRASTRUCTURE</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0114</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~499962</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>This project addressed what is fast becoming the most common, most severe bottleneck in computational science: the inability of scientists to explore data. The VisTrails infrastructure, extended in this project, has addressed this issue by streamlining exploration, helping users re-use knowledge, enhancing collaboration, and enabling greater sharing of the insights gained. VisTrails supports data analysis and visualization through a provenance-centered workflow environment. This project enhanced VisTrails by adding support for scalable execution, integration with scripts and computational notebooks, packaging for self-contained experiments, more documentation, and greater robustness. Because VisTrails is used by scientists and professionals in a number of domains for data analysis and visualization, this project has had broad impacts including many interdisciplinary research projects.<br />VisTrails relies on an comprehensive, integrated provenance infrastructure that helps users capture and recall information about how computational results are derived. This provenance both documents scientific research and aids in reproducing and validating past results. This project has extended the provenance infrastructure to support batch editing of multiple workflows, and to improve the storage of provenance data. VisTrails provides an extensible system for integrating libraries and packages. This project has extended that support with abilities to semi-automatically incorporate new libraries and to incorporate libraries that use the rich output capabilities of the Web. In addition, the project has added specific libraries including scikit-learn, Bokeh, and TensorFlow to VisTrails.<br />VisTrails exists in a strong ecosystem of tools and environments supporting computational science. This project has enhanced integration with existing tools including the Jupyter notebook environment and the ReproZip reproducible packaging system. In addition, it has improved the ability to work with scalable hardware including clusters by providing specific support for schedulers and parallel execution. This project has also supported the developer community involved with VisTrails by gathering information about usage, improving documentation, and adding better support for integrating libraries with VisTrails.<br />In summary, this project helped support the continued development and maintenance of VisTrails which helps users to understand and analyze the growing mountains of data being generated each day. The project added new features and supported existing users and developers.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 02/10/2018<br>      Modified by: Juliana&nbsp;Freire</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Images (<span id="selectedPhoto0">1</span> of <span class="totalNumber"></span>)           </div> <div class="galControls" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1405927/1405927_10328195_1518305182837_vistrails-github-activity-20180210--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1405927/1405927_10328195_1518305182837_vistrails-github-activity-20180210--rgov-800width.jpg" title="VisTrails on GitHub"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1405927/1405927_10328195_1518305182837_vistrails-github-activity-20180210--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="VisTrails on GitHub"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Activity for VisTrails development on GitHub</div> <div class="imageCredit">screenshot</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Public Domain</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Juliana&nbsp;Freire</div> <div class="imageTitle">VisTrails on GitHub</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1405927/1405927_10328195_1518305854986_overview_tree--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1405927/1405927_10328195_1518305854986_overview_tree--rgov-800width.jpg" title="VisTrails in action"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1405927/1405927_10328195_1518305854986_overview_tree--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="VisTrails in action"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">The VisTrails system manages computations, associate data  and provenance. The interface includes a version tree that allows users to navigate over past versions, a view where users can create or modify workflows, and a visual spreadsheet where results can be compared side by side.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Juliana Freire & David Koop</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Public Domain</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Juliana&nbsp;Freire</div> <div class="imageTitle">VisTrails in action</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ This project addressed what is fast becoming the most common, most severe bottleneck in computational science: the inability of scientists to explore data. The VisTrails infrastructure, extended in this project, has addressed this issue by streamlining exploration, helping users re-use knowledge, enhancing collaboration, and enabling greater sharing of the insights gained. VisTrails supports data analysis and visualization through a provenance-centered workflow environment. This project enhanced VisTrails by adding support for scalable execution, integration with scripts and computational notebooks, packaging for self-contained experiments, more documentation, and greater robustness. Because VisTrails is used by scientists and professionals in a number of domains for data analysis and visualization, this project has had broad impacts including many interdisciplinary research projects. VisTrails relies on an comprehensive, integrated provenance infrastructure that helps users capture and recall information about how computational results are derived. This provenance both documents scientific research and aids in reproducing and validating past results. This project has extended the provenance infrastructure to support batch editing of multiple workflows, and to improve the storage of provenance data. VisTrails provides an extensible system for integrating libraries and packages. This project has extended that support with abilities to semi-automatically incorporate new libraries and to incorporate libraries that use the rich output capabilities of the Web. In addition, the project has added specific libraries including scikit-learn, Bokeh, and TensorFlow to VisTrails. VisTrails exists in a strong ecosystem of tools and environments supporting computational science. This project has enhanced integration with existing tools including the Jupyter notebook environment and the ReproZip reproducible packaging system. In addition, it has improved the ability to work with scalable hardware including clusters by providing specific support for schedulers and parallel execution. This project has also supported the developer community involved with VisTrails by gathering information about usage, improving documentation, and adding better support for integrating libraries with VisTrails. In summary, this project helped support the continued development and maintenance of VisTrails which helps users to understand and analyze the growing mountains of data being generated each day. The project added new features and supported existing users and developers.             Last Modified: 02/10/2018       Submitted by: Juliana Freire]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
