<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>NeTS: JUNO: Cognitive Security: A New Approach to Securing Future Large Scale and Distributed Mobile Applications</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>05/01/2014</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>04/30/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>299999.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>299999</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>05050000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>CSE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CNS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Computer and Network Systems</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>John Brassil</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Authentication is the first step in securing a networked application. Traditional authentication relies on cryptographic algorithms that verify users identify based on certain pre-configured secrets. In a world with "trillions" of mobile objects ("computation in everything")  rigorous key management techniques are difficult, the traceability of pre-configured secrets is compromised, and crypto-based authentication schemes become ineffective.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project will investigate an alternative approach, referred to as cognitive security, to address this compelling problem. Cognitive security aims to supplement the crypto-based solutions with unique, unforgeable, and robust credentials that are inherent to the network entities such as mobile devices and users. For example, a location claim can be verified by a location "fingerprint" constructed from the ambient radio signals presented at the said location at the said time. A user's identity can be verified by knowledge the verifier learned from the user's online social networks.  These credentials are physical properties of the mobile devices or knowledge naturally known to the users, which do not have to be pre-configured or remembered. Mechanisms will be developed so that these credentials can be collected or learnt through the normal network operations and be used to securely verify a device or a user's identity or claims.  &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This is an international collaborative project, between US and Japan. The project will involve multiple areas of information technology, including security, wireless communications and networking, and machine learning. Cognitive security is a promising new approach to mobile network security where the security of the device or secrets stored in the device cannot be guaranteed.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>01/30/2014</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/15/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.070</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1405747</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Thomas</FirstName>
<LastName>Hou</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Thomas Hou</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>thou@vt.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5402312950</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000122250</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/15/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Thomas</FirstName>
<LastName>Hou</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Thomas Hou</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>thou@vt.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5402312950</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000122250</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>01/30/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate>08/15/2014</EndDate>
<RoleCode>Former Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Wenjing</FirstName>
<LastName>Lou</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Wenjing Lou</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>wjlou@vt.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>7035383774</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000192643</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>01/30/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate>08/15/2014</EndDate>
<RoleCode>Former Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University</Name>
<CityName>BLACKSBURG</CityName>
<ZipCode>240610001</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5402315281</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>Sponsored Programs 0170</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[300 Turner Street NW, Suite 4200]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Virginia</StateName>
<StateCode>VA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>09</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>VA09</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>003137015</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>VIRGINIA POLYTECHNIC INSTITUTE AND STATE UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>003137015</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>VA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>220432368</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Virginia</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>08</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>VA08</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1714</Code>
<Text>Special Projects - CNS</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7071</Code>
<Text>JUNO</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0114</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~299999</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>This project studied ways to secure large scale and distributed wireless networks and mobile applications. We investigated a new approach, which we call cognitive security, to enhance network security by supplementing the traditional crypto&shy;based solutions with unique, unforgeable, and robust credentials that are inherent to the network entities (e.g., mobile devices and users). Such credentials are unique physical properties of the mobile devices or knowledge naturally known to the users, which do not have to be pre&shy;configured and remembered by the network entities, but hard to forge or alter.&nbsp; Rather, these credentials can be collected or learnt through normal operations and be used to validate a node's identity or claims. We believe cognitive security will be an important and effective addition to the current mobile security solutions when individual users/devices are under loose security management where traditional crypto-based solutions fall short.&nbsp;</p> <p>In this project, we explored various physical properties of wireless signals and carefully examined their potential to be exploited for security and privacy purposes in securing mobile devices, networks, and applications.&nbsp; Location is a special information associated with a mobile device. Dishonest users may report false location information (i.e. location-cheating attack) while many privacy-conscious users are concerned with their location information being disclosed to other unwanted users or the service provider itself. In this project, we investigated proximity-based security techniques based on a real-time location tag, which is a &ldquo;fingerprint&rdquo; of the ambient wireless signals presented at a certain place at a certain time, as a proof of a mobile node&rsquo;s presence at the said place and time. We devised methods to construct location tags based on the features extracted from the wireless signals surrounding the mobile node, as well as privacy-preserving location tag matching algorithms and distance-bounding key establishment for nodes who do not have any pre-shared secrets but do present in the claimed proximity. Augmented reality is poised to become the next dominant computing paradigm over the next decade. In this project, we also designed a Looks Good to Me (LGTM) authentication that leverages the unique hardware and context provided with augmented reality headsets to bring innate human trust mechanisms into the digital world to solve authentication in a usable and secure way. LGTM works over point-to-point wireless communication so users can authenticate one another in any circumstance and is designed with usability at its core, requiring users to perform only two actions: one to initiate and one to confirm. Users intuitively authenticate one another, using seemingly only each other's faces, but under the hood LGTM uses a combination of facial recognition and wireless localization to bootstrap trust from a wireless signal, to a location, to a face, for secure and extremely usable authentication. Finally, we investigated the privacy impact of wireless signals collected from sensors, such as wearable devices used in augmented reality applications. We demonstrated that always-on gesture sensors are indeed a severe threat to privacy. Signals collected from those sensors, seemingly innocuous, could lead to severe privacy leakage. We demonstrated that sensitive information such as passwords typed on a keyboard and PIN sequences entered through a touchscreen could be recovered by analyzing the signals recorded from the electromyography (EMG) sensor and accelerometers on Myo.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 07/19/2018<br>      Modified by: Thomas&nbsp;Hou</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ This project studied ways to secure large scale and distributed wireless networks and mobile applications. We investigated a new approach, which we call cognitive security, to enhance network security by supplementing the traditional crypto&shy;based solutions with unique, unforgeable, and robust credentials that are inherent to the network entities (e.g., mobile devices and users). Such credentials are unique physical properties of the mobile devices or knowledge naturally known to the users, which do not have to be pre&shy;configured and remembered by the network entities, but hard to forge or alter.  Rather, these credentials can be collected or learnt through normal operations and be used to validate a node's identity or claims. We believe cognitive security will be an important and effective addition to the current mobile security solutions when individual users/devices are under loose security management where traditional crypto-based solutions fall short.   In this project, we explored various physical properties of wireless signals and carefully examined their potential to be exploited for security and privacy purposes in securing mobile devices, networks, and applications.  Location is a special information associated with a mobile device. Dishonest users may report false location information (i.e. location-cheating attack) while many privacy-conscious users are concerned with their location information being disclosed to other unwanted users or the service provider itself. In this project, we investigated proximity-based security techniques based on a real-time location tag, which is a "fingerprint" of the ambient wireless signals presented at a certain place at a certain time, as a proof of a mobile node?s presence at the said place and time. We devised methods to construct location tags based on the features extracted from the wireless signals surrounding the mobile node, as well as privacy-preserving location tag matching algorithms and distance-bounding key establishment for nodes who do not have any pre-shared secrets but do present in the claimed proximity. Augmented reality is poised to become the next dominant computing paradigm over the next decade. In this project, we also designed a Looks Good to Me (LGTM) authentication that leverages the unique hardware and context provided with augmented reality headsets to bring innate human trust mechanisms into the digital world to solve authentication in a usable and secure way. LGTM works over point-to-point wireless communication so users can authenticate one another in any circumstance and is designed with usability at its core, requiring users to perform only two actions: one to initiate and one to confirm. Users intuitively authenticate one another, using seemingly only each other's faces, but under the hood LGTM uses a combination of facial recognition and wireless localization to bootstrap trust from a wireless signal, to a location, to a face, for secure and extremely usable authentication. Finally, we investigated the privacy impact of wireless signals collected from sensors, such as wearable devices used in augmented reality applications. We demonstrated that always-on gesture sensors are indeed a severe threat to privacy. Signals collected from those sensors, seemingly innocuous, could lead to severe privacy leakage. We demonstrated that sensitive information such as passwords typed on a keyboard and PIN sequences entered through a touchscreen could be recovered by analyzing the signals recorded from the electromyography (EMG) sensor and accelerometers on Myo.          Last Modified: 07/19/2018       Submitted by: Thomas Hou]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
