<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>DISSERTATION RESEARCH: Phylogenetic Systematics and Biogeography of Iguanodontian Dinosaurs</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>06/01/2014</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2015</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>17531.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>17531</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>08010206</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>BIO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DEB</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Environmental Biology</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Simon Malcomber</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>smalcomb@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032928227</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Iguanodontian dinosaurs are a diverse group of herbivores that range from small to large ?duck-billed? hadrosaurs reaching 30 feet in length.  The group persisted for nearly 100 million years and is known from every modern continent.  The evolution of iguanodontians crossed many major anatomical boundaries, including those of size (small to huge), locomotion type (bipedal to quadrupedal), and feeding style (small-toothed croppers to plant-processing machines with hundreds of teeth).  To make sense of these evolutionary changes this study seeks to understand the diversification pattern, or phylogeny, of their evolution.  To this end, fossils of all known species of iguanodontians will be examined to study their changing anatomy through time.  A matrix of all observed anatomical changes will be compiled and examined using computer algorithms to determine the most likely phylogenetic relationships among iguanodontians.  The evolutionary relationships will then be used to examine their geographic distributions through time.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;A hypothesis of the evolutionary relationships of iguanodontians will create a framework to study their biology, such as changes in size, locomotion, and feeding mechanics.  This study will also test methods for including species known only from juvenile specimens in the phylogenetic analysis; this will have potential widespread application to other groups.  Finally, patterns in iguanodontian biogeography (evolution through time and space) will inform a better understanding of the biogeographic patterns of Mesozoic vertebrates.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>04/28/2014</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>04/28/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.074</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1405834</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Catherine</FirstName>
<LastName>Forster</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>A</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Catherine A Forster</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>forster@gwu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2029941008</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000382344</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/28/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Karen</FirstName>
<LastName>Poole</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Karen Poole</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>kepoole@gwmail.gwu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2029944627</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000633538</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/28/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>George Washington University</Name>
<CityName>Washington</CityName>
<ZipCode>200520086</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2029940728</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1922 F Street NW</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[4th Floor]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>District of Columbia</StateName>
<StateCode>DC</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>00</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>DC00</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>043990498</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>GEORGE WASHINGTON UNIVERSITY, THE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>043990498</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[George Washington University]]></Name>
<CityName>washington</CityName>
<StateCode>DC</StateCode>
<ZipCode>200520021</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[2023 G Street, NW Ste 340]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>District of Columbia</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>00</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>DC00</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1171</Code>
<Text>PHYLOGENETIC SYSTEMATICS</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9169</Code>
<Text>BIODIVERSITY AND ECOSYSTEM DYNAMICS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9179</Code>
<Text>GRADUATE INVOLVEMENT</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>EGCH</Code>
<Text>ENVIRONMENT AND GLOBAL CHANGE</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>SMET</Code>
<Text>SCIENCE, MATH, ENG &amp; TECH EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0114</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~17531</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>This grant allowed Karen E. Poole to visit 11 natural history museum collections in five countries to examine specimens of dinosaurs for her Ph.D. dissertation. Data collected included measurements, photographs, and detailed anatomical observations of the fossil bones of dinosaur specimens belonging to a group called Iguanodontia.&nbsp; Iguanodontians were plant-eating ornithischian dinosaurs that, through their long evolutionary history in the Jurassic and Cretaceous, developed dental specializations for highly efficient chewing, and shifted from two-legged to four-legged locomotion. &nbsp;</p> <p>Among the specimens examined with this DDIG grant were 17 holotype specimens, which stand as the &ldquo;prototype&rdquo; of all specimens assigned to that species.&nbsp; In total, 194 specimens were examined which provided important data that resulted in an increase in the (1) number of species, (2) amount of data, and (3) quality of data, in a final analysis of the evolutionary relationships (phylogeny) of this group of dinosaurs.</p> <p>Firsthand examination of specimens resulted in the discovery of 139 new anatomical characters not discernable through literature descriptions.&nbsp;&nbsp;In total, 73 species and 323 characters were used in the phylogenetic analysis, the largest and most complete study of iguanodontians to date.&nbsp; Importantly, skull anatomy dominated previous phylogenetic analyses, none of which were able to obtain results that fully clarified the evolutionary history of the group.&nbsp; This study added many characters from the rest of the skeleton so that 53% of all characters in the analysis were from the skeleton behind the skull.&nbsp; The additional characters and data gathered during these study trips altered the results of previous phylogenetic analyses, and provided the first well-supported and nearly fully resolved evolutionary history for iguanodontians. &nbsp;</p> <p>Understanding how iguanodontians are related to one another allows us to examine the pace and direction of a number of evolutionary advances. For example, features associated with the development of quadrupedality (4-legged locomotion) evolved quickly early in the evolution of iguanodontians, and evolved more than once.&nbsp; Similarly, dental specializations for efficient chewing appear to have evolved in slightly different ways among different groups of iguanodontians.&nbsp; &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;</p> <p>One unusual feature found in many iguanodontians is the fusion of their wrist bones, the fusion of the thumb onto the wrist, and the development of the thumb into a large and very pointed spike. &nbsp;To examine possible functions of this fused wrist "complex", we obtained CT (computed tomography) scans of two taxa: <em>Barilium</em> (fully fused complex) and <em>Camptosaurus </em>(partially fused complex). &nbsp;These were analyzed using an engineering methodology called &nbsp;Finite Element Analysis (FEA). &nbsp;&nbsp;We tested whether the fusion of the wrist and thumb was in response to: (1) use of a large thumb spike that fused to the wrist, or (2) strengthening the wrist for 4-legged locomotion.&nbsp; For both taxa, fusion of the thumb helped distribute stresses applied to the thumb.&nbsp; When the system was loaded to simulate 4-legged walking, the forces were directed up through the ulna and away from the thumb.</p> <p>Karen Poole presented the results of this work at the 2015 meeting of hte Society of Vertebrate Paleontology. She successfully completed her Ph.D., &nbsp;has submitted the results of her dissertation work for publication in a peer-reviewed journal, and has obtained a post-doctoral position.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 09/15/2016<br>      Modified by: Catherine&nbsp;A&nbsp;Forster</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ This grant allowed Karen E. Poole to visit 11 natural history museum collections in five countries to examine specimens of dinosaurs for her Ph.D. dissertation. Data collected included measurements, photographs, and detailed anatomical observations of the fossil bones of dinosaur specimens belonging to a group called Iguanodontia.  Iguanodontians were plant-eating ornithischian dinosaurs that, through their long evolutionary history in the Jurassic and Cretaceous, developed dental specializations for highly efficient chewing, and shifted from two-legged to four-legged locomotion.    Among the specimens examined with this DDIG grant were 17 holotype specimens, which stand as the "prototype" of all specimens assigned to that species.  In total, 194 specimens were examined which provided important data that resulted in an increase in the (1) number of species, (2) amount of data, and (3) quality of data, in a final analysis of the evolutionary relationships (phylogeny) of this group of dinosaurs.  Firsthand examination of specimens resulted in the discovery of 139 new anatomical characters not discernable through literature descriptions.  In total, 73 species and 323 characters were used in the phylogenetic analysis, the largest and most complete study of iguanodontians to date.  Importantly, skull anatomy dominated previous phylogenetic analyses, none of which were able to obtain results that fully clarified the evolutionary history of the group.  This study added many characters from the rest of the skeleton so that 53% of all characters in the analysis were from the skeleton behind the skull.  The additional characters and data gathered during these study trips altered the results of previous phylogenetic analyses, and provided the first well-supported and nearly fully resolved evolutionary history for iguanodontians.    Understanding how iguanodontians are related to one another allows us to examine the pace and direction of a number of evolutionary advances. For example, features associated with the development of quadrupedality (4-legged locomotion) evolved quickly early in the evolution of iguanodontians, and evolved more than once.  Similarly, dental specializations for efficient chewing appear to have evolved in slightly different ways among different groups of iguanodontians.        One unusual feature found in many iguanodontians is the fusion of their wrist bones, the fusion of the thumb onto the wrist, and the development of the thumb into a large and very pointed spike.  To examine possible functions of this fused wrist "complex", we obtained CT (computed tomography) scans of two taxa: Barilium (fully fused complex) and Camptosaurus (partially fused complex).  These were analyzed using an engineering methodology called  Finite Element Analysis (FEA).   We tested whether the fusion of the wrist and thumb was in response to: (1) use of a large thumb spike that fused to the wrist, or (2) strengthening the wrist for 4-legged locomotion.  For both taxa, fusion of the thumb helped distribute stresses applied to the thumb.  When the system was loaded to simulate 4-legged walking, the forces were directed up through the ulna and away from the thumb.  Karen Poole presented the results of this work at the 2015 meeting of hte Society of Vertebrate Paleontology. She successfully completed her Ph.D.,  has submitted the results of her dissertation work for publication in a peer-reviewed journal, and has obtained a post-doctoral position.                Last Modified: 09/15/2016       Submitted by: Catherine A Forster]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
