<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Collaborative Research: Indian Summer Monsoon Variability Reconstructed from  Tibetan Lake Sediments</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/15/2014</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2020</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>335505.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>343871</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>06030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>GEO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>EAR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Earth Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Jonathan G Wynn</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>jwynn@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924725</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The Indian Summer Monsoon directly impacts over one billion people, but very little is known about how variable it can be -- whether large increases or decreases in the amount of rainfall from year to year are normal or not. This research will investigate the variability of the monsoon by sampling bottom sediments from four lakes high in the southeastern Tibetan Plateau, which are believed to hold a record stretching back well over 6000 years into the past. Understanding the range of variability will help to improve climate models that are used to simulate the region's response to a range of abrupt and long term changes in temperature, wind circulation patterns, and moisture sources. In addition, understanding the past climate conditions of the region will allow a better understanding of the regional plant and animal populations and interactions, as well as changes in the human cultures of the area. This work will strengthen international scientific relationships between U.S. and Chinese scientific institutions, scientists, and students. Support will be provided for two earlier career scientists, a Ph.D. student and undergraduate students. The research team will collaborate with the Center for Earth and Environmental Sciences in Indiana to develop a new outreach module for 4th to 9th graders that will raise the awareness of issues surrounding water resources locally in Indianapolis, IN, and the United States as well as in the monsoon region.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This research will investigate Indian summer monsoon variability during the Holocene with decadally resolved sediment records from four alpine lakes on the southeastern Tibetan Plateau. The proposed research builds on previous NSF-supported work in the Nyainqentanglha Mountains, which are a major center of action in the summer monsoon system and a primary gateway for moisture entering the Tibetan Plateau. Results from previous work demonstrate that lakes in the region contain Holocene-length sediment archives which can be dated with radiometric techniques. These lakes also have decadal sedimentation rates and contain a diverse range of climate proxies that capture both local and synoptic monsoon variability. The team will reconstruct local monsoon variability with physical sedimentology and geochemistry, and synoptic variability with hydrogen isotope measurements on terrestrial leaf waxes. The results will be synthesized with paleoclimate records from the Tibetan Plateau and surrounding region, as well as with records from key regions in the global climate system, like the tropical Pacific and the North Atlantic, to address three central questions: (i) How did Indian Summer Monsoon rainfall vary on decadal timescales during the Holocene? (ii) Is there evidence for an Indian Summer Monsoon response to changing global climate boundary conditions during the middle Holocene at ~5300 years before present? (iii) Did the Medieval Climate Anomaly and Little Ice Age discernibly influence Indian Summer Monsoon precipitation?</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/11/2014</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/14/2019</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.050</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1405072</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Broxton</FirstName>
<LastName>Bird</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>W</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Broxton W Bird</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>bwbird@iupui.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>8128550516</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000631048</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/11/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Indiana University</Name>
<CityName>Bloomington</CityName>
<ZipCode>474013654</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>3172783473</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>509 E 3RD ST</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Indiana</StateName>
<StateCode>IN</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>09</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>IN09</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>006046700</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>TRUSTEES OF INDIANA UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>006046700</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Indiana University Purdue University Indianapolis]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>IN</StateCode>
<ZipCode>462022915</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[980 Indiana Ave, Lockefield 2232]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Indiana</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>IN07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1575</Code>
<Text>EDUCATION AND HUMAN RESOURCES</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1577</Code>
<Text>GLOBAL CHANGE</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1304</Code>
<Text>EARTH SYSTEM HISTORY</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1575</Code>
<Text>EDUCATION AND HUMAN RESOURCES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>EGCH</Code>
<Text>ENVIRONMENT AND GLOBAL CHANGE</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0114</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0115</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0116</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0118</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~104283</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2015~153749</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2016~77473</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2018~8366</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>[Scientific Merti]</p> <p>The major goal of this ongoing research project is to investigate Holocene Indian summer monsoon (ISM) variability at decadal to millennial timescales using the physical, geochemical, and isotopic properties of high-resolution sediment archives collected from four lakes on the central and southeastern Tibetan Plateau. On orbital-scales, results from the four lakes located on the Tibetan Plateau (Paru Co, Nir&rsquo;pa Co, Ruba Co, and Cuobu) indicate deep water conditions, increased runoff, and enhanced boreal summer convective precipitation during the early and middle Holocene between ca. 10,000 and 5000 year before present (yr BP). After 5000 yr BP, dry conditions predominated, with especially pronounced aridity between 4 and 2 ka. These trends largely tracked decreasing boreal summer insolation, a southward migration of the Intertropical Convergence Zone (ITCZ), and the transition from La Ni&ntilde;a-like to El Ni&ntilde;o-like Pacific SST gradients. In-phase centennial-scale lake-level and runoff variability were identified across the study area during the Holocene, indicating coherent high-frequency hydroclimate variability. These hydroclimate variations varied in-phase with reconstructed temperatures, where deeper lake conditions were associated with warming and vice versa for cooling. Similarly, the transition from strong to week ISM conditions around 5000 yr BP coincided with a step-wise reduction in surface air temperatures on the Tibetan Plateau and the onset of modern El Ni&ntilde;o variability, implicating these as primary driver of centennial and higher-frequency variability. The Medieval Climate Anomaly (MCA; 950-1250 CE) and Little Ice Age (LIA; 1350-1850 CE) were generally minor hydroclimate events on the Tibetan Plateau and were instead superimposed on a spatially coherent increase in ISM precipitation during the last 1500 to 1000 years. There are indications, however, that evaporation exceeded precipitation during the MCA whereas the opposite occurred during the LIA. This suggests that during the late Holocene, when ISM precipitation was generally decreased, increases in temperature increased evaporation and lowered lake levels.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>[Broader Impacts]</p> <p>This project supported research training for two IUPUI Ph.D. student and contributed to graduate and undergraduate training. The project also fostered U.S.-China international collaboration through an extended rese at IUPUI and Lamont Doherty Earth Observatory. International collaboration and capacity building was a significant part of this grant, with extensive cooperation between US and Chinese scientists, including a year-long visit by a Chinese colleague to IUPUI as a visiting Scholar. The knowledge produced by this research additionally enhances our understanding of ISM dynamics in response to different climatic forcings (e.g., orbital-scale insolation, ocean-atmosphere dynamics, atmospheric temperature variability) and provides paleoclimatic proxy data analogous to observational data that aid in validating climate model simulations. Ultimately, these findings will help inform predictions of how continued warming may impact the ISM and its associated water resources, which are relied upon by nearly one third of the worlds population. This research additionally contributed to the transfer and dissemination of knowledge through the creation of an educational module for 4<sup>th</sup> to 12<sup>th</sup> graders in the US that helps students understand what paleoclimatology is, the tools used to reconstruct past climates, and how our water resources have varied through time in response to different forcing mechanisms.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 11/24/2020<br>      Modified by: Broxton&nbsp;W&nbsp;Bird</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ [Scientific Merti]  The major goal of this ongoing research project is to investigate Holocene Indian summer monsoon (ISM) variability at decadal to millennial timescales using the physical, geochemical, and isotopic properties of high-resolution sediment archives collected from four lakes on the central and southeastern Tibetan Plateau. On orbital-scales, results from the four lakes located on the Tibetan Plateau (Paru Co, Nir’pa Co, Ruba Co, and Cuobu) indicate deep water conditions, increased runoff, and enhanced boreal summer convective precipitation during the early and middle Holocene between ca. 10,000 and 5000 year before present (yr BP). After 5000 yr BP, dry conditions predominated, with especially pronounced aridity between 4 and 2 ka. These trends largely tracked decreasing boreal summer insolation, a southward migration of the Intertropical Convergence Zone (ITCZ), and the transition from La Ni&ntilde;a-like to El Ni&ntilde;o-like Pacific SST gradients. In-phase centennial-scale lake-level and runoff variability were identified across the study area during the Holocene, indicating coherent high-frequency hydroclimate variability. These hydroclimate variations varied in-phase with reconstructed temperatures, where deeper lake conditions were associated with warming and vice versa for cooling. Similarly, the transition from strong to week ISM conditions around 5000 yr BP coincided with a step-wise reduction in surface air temperatures on the Tibetan Plateau and the onset of modern El Ni&ntilde;o variability, implicating these as primary driver of centennial and higher-frequency variability. The Medieval Climate Anomaly (MCA; 950-1250 CE) and Little Ice Age (LIA; 1350-1850 CE) were generally minor hydroclimate events on the Tibetan Plateau and were instead superimposed on a spatially coherent increase in ISM precipitation during the last 1500 to 1000 years. There are indications, however, that evaporation exceeded precipitation during the MCA whereas the opposite occurred during the LIA. This suggests that during the late Holocene, when ISM precipitation was generally decreased, increases in temperature increased evaporation and lowered lake levels.     [Broader Impacts]  This project supported research training for two IUPUI Ph.D. student and contributed to graduate and undergraduate training. The project also fostered U.S.-China international collaboration through an extended rese at IUPUI and Lamont Doherty Earth Observatory. International collaboration and capacity building was a significant part of this grant, with extensive cooperation between US and Chinese scientists, including a year-long visit by a Chinese colleague to IUPUI as a visiting Scholar. The knowledge produced by this research additionally enhances our understanding of ISM dynamics in response to different climatic forcings (e.g., orbital-scale insolation, ocean-atmosphere dynamics, atmospheric temperature variability) and provides paleoclimatic proxy data analogous to observational data that aid in validating climate model simulations. Ultimately, these findings will help inform predictions of how continued warming may impact the ISM and its associated water resources, which are relied upon by nearly one third of the worlds population. This research additionally contributed to the transfer and dissemination of knowledge through the creation of an educational module for 4th to 12th graders in the US that helps students understand what paleoclimatology is, the tools used to reconstruct past climates, and how our water resources have varied through time in response to different forcing mechanisms.          Last Modified: 11/24/2020       Submitted by: Broxton W Bird]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
