<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Improving the voltage of solar cells using photon management</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2014</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>311026.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>311026</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07010000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>ECCS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Electrical, Commun &amp; Cyber Sys</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Dominique Dagenais</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>ddagenai@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922980</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Title: Improving the voltage of solar cells using photon management &lt;br/&gt; &lt;br/&gt; &lt;br/&gt;This work focuses on the study of new approaches to enhance the efficiency of solar cells through novel approaches to manage photon absorption. The efficiency of solar cells is determined by both the photocurrent and the operating voltage. Currently, photocurrents in many leading cell technologies are approaching their upper limit, leaving little room for improvement. On the other hand, operating voltages are still lagging behind their predicted limit. Traditionally, the voltage could only be enhanced by improving the quality of solar cell materials, which tends to increase the cost significantly. In this effort new approaches will be developed based on optical designs to improve the operating voltage. Theoretical and experimental studies aim to establish new mechanisms and design principles for voltage enhancement based on photonic engineering. By investigating strategies for increasing cell voltage, the PI anticipates improved understanding of fundamental processes that will lead to higher efficiency of solar systems. There is a strong educational plan to involve students with the research effort and to collaborate with an industrial partner. The project will train undergraduate and graduate students in clean energy technologies which will have a profound impact on society. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The proposed work focuses on new approaches to enhance the operating voltage of solar cells. Several new mechanisms using photon management in semiconductor nanostructures will be investigated. The proposed photon management seeks to address issues beyond anti-reflection and light trapping. Photonics can improve the voltage through the Purcell effect where radiative recombination rates are enhanced or suppressed by engineering the optical density of states. Such effects become more important as solar cells reach high efficiencies, particularly for direct bandgap semiconductors. Near-field emission will be theoretically investigated in various nanostructures to reduce the loss of voltage in practical solar cells. The project combines detailed balance analysis and nanophotonic simulations. In particular, cell architectures will be investigated to achieve efficiency beyond the Shockley-Queisser limit.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/17/2014</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/17/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1405201</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Zongfu</FirstName>
<LastName>Yu</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Zongfu Yu</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>zyu54@wisc.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6082631643</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000652763</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/17/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Wisconsin-Madison</Name>
<CityName>MADISON</CityName>
<ZipCode>537151218</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6082623822</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>21 North Park Street</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[Suite 6401]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Wisconsin</StateName>
<StateCode>WI</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>WI02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>161202122</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF WISCONSIN SYSTEM</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>041188822</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Wisconsin-Madison]]></Name>
<CityName>Madison</CityName>
<StateCode>WI</StateCode>
<ZipCode>537061691</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[1415 Engineering Drive]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Wisconsin</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>WI02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1517</Code>
<Text>EPMD-ElectrnPhoton&amp;MagnDevices</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>091E</Code>
<Text>Light generation &amp; detection</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>103E</Code>
<Text>Energy efficient electronics</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0114</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~311026</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><strong>Intellectual Merit:</strong></p> <p>The major goal of this project is to provide a systematic understanding of how photon management can potentially enhance the open-circuit voltage of solar cells. The open-circuit voltage as well as the photocurrent of solar cells, are two quantities that primarily determine the efficiency of solar cells. Many photon management technologies have been developed to enhance the photocurrent of solar cells, and the highest photocurrent achieved is reaching the theoretical upper bound. On the other hand, the highest open-circuit voltage achieved in current solar-cell architectures is still lagging behind the theoretical upper bound. Further improvement of solar-cell efficiency thus will primarily rely on the enhancement of the open-circuit voltage.&nbsp; However, very little is known about the potential of photon management in open-circuit voltage enhancement. This project focused on developing fundamental understanding of the relationship between open-circuit voltage and photon management, and general strategies for enhancing the open-circuit voltage. Based on the developed strategies, this project further proposed new solar cell architectures to enhance the solar cell efficiency, with a potential to exceed the Shockley-Queisser limit.</p> <p>The photon management is found to be of great importance for the open-circuit voltage. In general, the open-circuit voltage increases as the solar cell absorbs more solar radiation and emits less radiation. An effective strategy to increase the cell?s solar absorption and reduce its radiation is to reduce the cell?s emission angle. A smaller emission angle allows less photons to escape from the cell. As a result, most of the radiation from the cell is trapped inside the cell due to total internal, leading to reduced emission. Furthermore, there are also more incoming solar radiation trapped inside the cell due to the smaller escape angle. The trapped incoming radiation eventually will be absorbed by the cell, leading to increased solar absorption.</p> <p>This strategy can be readily implemented using index-near-zero (INZ) materials. These materials have refractive index smaller than 1. When placed on top of photoactive materials that has a refractive index larger than 1, such as silicon, the INZ material reduces the escape angle of photons comparing to air. Consequently, the photon absorption of a thin film solar cell can be drastically increased. For instance, an INZ material with an index of 0.1 can increase the photon absorption by 100 times, resulting in greatly increased photocurrent.</p> <p>Meanwhile, the thermal emission from the solar cell is significantly suppressed. The total internal reflection at the interface between INZ material and photoactive material prevents a significant portion of internal thermal radiation from leaving the photoactive material. For an INZ material with an index of 0.1, the internal thermal radiation is reduced by 100 times. Such suppression of internal thermal emission greatly reduces the radiative recombination rate of photo-generated carriers, leading to increased open-circuit voltage.</p> <p>We numerically verified our strategy with standard analysis method by using GaAs as an example. For an INZ material with index of 0.1, the open-circuit voltage is increased by more than 100 mV, leading to a cell efficiency of 40%, which is well above the Shockley-Queisser limit of 33.7% for single-junction solar cells under one sun.</p> <p>In summary, the work funded by this award sheds light on the potential of photon management for increasing the open-circuit voltage and overall cell efficiency. The fundamental understandings developed in this project open up new possibilities of high-performance solar cells.</p> <p><strong>Broader impacts: </strong></p> <p>Photon management plays a significant role in light-matter interaction. The research funded by this NSF award demonstrated the general photon management strategies to create strong light-matter interactions. These strategies can be used to improve the performance of other optoelectronic devices that require strong light-matter interactions, such as photodetectors and modulators.</p> <p>Furthermore, this NSF award provides financial support for two students for their Ph.D. degrees, including one female student who obtained her Ph. D. degree in 2018. The training in this project provides the students the fundamental concepts and critical thinking skills of scientific research. This will contribute to formation of highly trained workforces and stimulate the interest of future researchers.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 10/30/2018<br>      Modified by: Zongfu&nbsp;Yu</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Intellectual Merit:  The major goal of this project is to provide a systematic understanding of how photon management can potentially enhance the open-circuit voltage of solar cells. The open-circuit voltage as well as the photocurrent of solar cells, are two quantities that primarily determine the efficiency of solar cells. Many photon management technologies have been developed to enhance the photocurrent of solar cells, and the highest photocurrent achieved is reaching the theoretical upper bound. On the other hand, the highest open-circuit voltage achieved in current solar-cell architectures is still lagging behind the theoretical upper bound. Further improvement of solar-cell efficiency thus will primarily rely on the enhancement of the open-circuit voltage.  However, very little is known about the potential of photon management in open-circuit voltage enhancement. This project focused on developing fundamental understanding of the relationship between open-circuit voltage and photon management, and general strategies for enhancing the open-circuit voltage. Based on the developed strategies, this project further proposed new solar cell architectures to enhance the solar cell efficiency, with a potential to exceed the Shockley-Queisser limit.  The photon management is found to be of great importance for the open-circuit voltage. In general, the open-circuit voltage increases as the solar cell absorbs more solar radiation and emits less radiation. An effective strategy to increase the cell?s solar absorption and reduce its radiation is to reduce the cell?s emission angle. A smaller emission angle allows less photons to escape from the cell. As a result, most of the radiation from the cell is trapped inside the cell due to total internal, leading to reduced emission. Furthermore, there are also more incoming solar radiation trapped inside the cell due to the smaller escape angle. The trapped incoming radiation eventually will be absorbed by the cell, leading to increased solar absorption.  This strategy can be readily implemented using index-near-zero (INZ) materials. These materials have refractive index smaller than 1. When placed on top of photoactive materials that has a refractive index larger than 1, such as silicon, the INZ material reduces the escape angle of photons comparing to air. Consequently, the photon absorption of a thin film solar cell can be drastically increased. For instance, an INZ material with an index of 0.1 can increase the photon absorption by 100 times, resulting in greatly increased photocurrent.  Meanwhile, the thermal emission from the solar cell is significantly suppressed. The total internal reflection at the interface between INZ material and photoactive material prevents a significant portion of internal thermal radiation from leaving the photoactive material. For an INZ material with an index of 0.1, the internal thermal radiation is reduced by 100 times. Such suppression of internal thermal emission greatly reduces the radiative recombination rate of photo-generated carriers, leading to increased open-circuit voltage.  We numerically verified our strategy with standard analysis method by using GaAs as an example. For an INZ material with index of 0.1, the open-circuit voltage is increased by more than 100 mV, leading to a cell efficiency of 40%, which is well above the Shockley-Queisser limit of 33.7% for single-junction solar cells under one sun.  In summary, the work funded by this award sheds light on the potential of photon management for increasing the open-circuit voltage and overall cell efficiency. The fundamental understandings developed in this project open up new possibilities of high-performance solar cells.  Broader impacts:   Photon management plays a significant role in light-matter interaction. The research funded by this NSF award demonstrated the general photon management strategies to create strong light-matter interactions. These strategies can be used to improve the performance of other optoelectronic devices that require strong light-matter interactions, such as photodetectors and modulators.  Furthermore, this NSF award provides financial support for two students for their Ph.D. degrees, including one female student who obtained her Ph. D. degree in 2018. The training in this project provides the students the fundamental concepts and critical thinking skills of scientific research. This will contribute to formation of highly trained workforces and stimulate the interest of future researchers.          Last Modified: 10/30/2018       Submitted by: Zongfu Yu]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
