<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Collaborative Research: Improving electric power dispatch to ensure reliable, secure and economic transmission.</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2014</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>200000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>200000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07010000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>ECCS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Electrical, Commun &amp; Cyber Sys</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Usha Varshney</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>uvarshne@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032925385</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Choosing the least-operating cost combination of electric power generation to meet demand is at the heart of utility and Independent System Operator (ISO) functions in the running of an electric power system.  Additionally, utilities and ISOs must ensure that transmission lines will be operated within limits both under normal conditions and in the event of an outage, or failure, of a line.  These transmission limitations can limit the choices available for dispatch of generators.  A generation and transmission system operated within these limits is said to be secure. Maintaining security while seeking to minimize the operating costs of generation is a central function of utility and ISO operations and involves pro-active consideration of the many possible outages that might occur.  If an outage does actually occur, then the dispatch must subsequently be changed so that the system can withstand the next outage.  Generally, however, these actions needed to restore security are not explicitly modeled in the procedures of utilities and ISOs.  The implication is that current systems might be operated in a manner that under-utilizes transmission capacity there resulting in more expensive dispatch than necessary or operated in a manner that could threaten reliability in the event of a single failure.  This work seeks systematic methods to better represent the limitations on transmission and better represent the post-contingency restoration to security so as to improve electric generator dispatch. The graduate students will be trained in electric power engineering, optimization theory, and control systems. Students will be provided opportunities to interact with the Texas Legislative and Public utility commission, and the STEM outreach activities will extend to the South Harlem middle and high schools that serve underrepresented minorities.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This proposal aims at improving representation of post-contingency states in Regional Transmission Organization (RTO) and Independent System Operator (ISO) dispatch optimization to better ensure that transmission capability is neither under-utilized nor operated at levels that jeopardize reliability. Improved utilization of transmission capacity will contribute to lowering the overall cost of electricity supply by enabling more of the lower cost resources to be dispatched, and contribute to enhancing the integration of renewable resources by reducing transmission-related wind curtailment. Conversely, in cases where transmission may be operated in an optimistic manner, improved representation of post-contingency states will improve reliability. These improvements will be achieved by more comprehensive dispatch methodologies, that explicitly model post-contingency corrective actions, rather than through costly transmission upgrades.  The capability of the transmission system to support flows of power is typically limited by both continuous and short-term thermal limits due to the interaction of resistive heating of lines and line temperature ratings. The limits vary from line to line and also depend to some extent on ambient conditions. These limits are incorporated into RTO/ISO dispatch models. Standard formulations of RTO/ISO dispatch use security-constrained optimal power flow (SCOPF) that represent contingencies by approximating the post-contingency flows on lines and other elements given a pre-contingency dispatch. Typically, the limits allowed for post-contingency flows reflect short-term transmission limits and are higher than the continuous ratings, with the implicit assumption that the flows can be reduced to being within continuous ratings through (unmodeled) post-contingency corrective actions before the temperature rise on the lines exceeds acceptable limits.  The approach is to utilize recent advances in fine-grain distributed optimal power flow to explicitly represent the trajectory of post-contingency flows into the optimal power flow formulation, so that the implied limit on pre-contingency flows will neither be conservative or optimistic. This will enable better utilization of existing transmission capacity.  Systematic methods to reduce the number of contingency constraints that must be explicitly represented in the optimization will also be investigated.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/08/2014</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/08/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1406894</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Ross</FirstName>
<LastName>Baldick</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Ross Baldick</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>baldick@ece.utexas.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5124715879</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000442306</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/08/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Texas at Austin</Name>
<CityName>Austin</CityName>
<ZipCode>787595316</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5124716424</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>3925 W Braker Lane, Ste 3.340</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Texas</StateName>
<StateCode>TX</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>10</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>TX10</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>170230239</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF TEXAS AT AUSTIN</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>042000273</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Texas at Austin]]></Name>
<CityName>Austin</CityName>
<StateCode>TX</StateCode>
<ZipCode>787121532</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[101 E. 27th St., Suite 5.300]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Texas</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>25</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>TX25</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7607</Code>
<Text>EPCN-Energy-Power-Ctrl-Netwrks</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>155E</Code>
<Text>Electric power networks</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0114</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~200000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Electricity systems are operated by Independent System Operators (ISOs) that issue dispatch instructions to generators on the basis of centralized calculations using submitted offers and bids.&nbsp; These instructions are updated at 5 minutely (or, for some systems, 15 minutely) intervals based on the result of optimal power flow (OPF) calculations and are typically binding requirements on generators to ramp towards a generation level over the upcoming 5 minute interval.&nbsp; Subsequent to initial implementations in the 1990s, ISO implementations have become more sophisticated, with some market models now considering multiple-intervals into the future in so-called lookahead dispatch.&nbsp; Currently, these formulations typically include the consideration of contingencies in both the upcoming interval and in the subsequent dispatch intervals that are further into the future over the lookahead horizon. However, as will be discussed in the next sections, these formulations have only limited representation of the implications of post-contingency states on the system on the subsequent dispatch intervals if a contingency were actually to occur. The over-arching objective is to better represent post-contingency states into dispatch.</p> <p>This work has responded to that objective through developing highly scalable approaches to representing transmission contingencies and developing representations of post-contingency frequency fluctuations.&nbsp; Work has been reported in: &nbsp;Sambuddha Chakrabarti and Ross Baldick, &ldquo;Look-Ahead SCOPF (LASCOPF) for Tracking Demand Variation via Auxiliary Proximal Message Passing (APMP) Algorithm,'' To appear in&nbsp;<em>International Journal of Electrical Power and Energy Systems</em>, volume 116, March 2020, and Manuel Garcia and Ross Baldick, &ldquo;Real-Time Co-Optimization: Interdependent Reserve Types for Primary Frequency Response,&rdquo; Proceedings of the&nbsp;<em>Tenth ACM International Conference on Future Energy Systems (e-Energy &rsquo;19)</em>, Phoenix, AZ, June 25&ndash;28, 2019.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 11/25/2019<br>      Modified by: Ross&nbsp;Baldick</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Electricity systems are operated by Independent System Operators (ISOs) that issue dispatch instructions to generators on the basis of centralized calculations using submitted offers and bids.  These instructions are updated at 5 minutely (or, for some systems, 15 minutely) intervals based on the result of optimal power flow (OPF) calculations and are typically binding requirements on generators to ramp towards a generation level over the upcoming 5 minute interval.  Subsequent to initial implementations in the 1990s, ISO implementations have become more sophisticated, with some market models now considering multiple-intervals into the future in so-called lookahead dispatch.  Currently, these formulations typically include the consideration of contingencies in both the upcoming interval and in the subsequent dispatch intervals that are further into the future over the lookahead horizon. However, as will be discussed in the next sections, these formulations have only limited representation of the implications of post-contingency states on the system on the subsequent dispatch intervals if a contingency were actually to occur. The over-arching objective is to better represent post-contingency states into dispatch.  This work has responded to that objective through developing highly scalable approaches to representing transmission contingencies and developing representations of post-contingency frequency fluctuations.  Work has been reported in:  Sambuddha Chakrabarti and Ross Baldick, "Look-Ahead SCOPF (LASCOPF) for Tracking Demand Variation via Auxiliary Proximal Message Passing (APMP) Algorithm,'' To appear in International Journal of Electrical Power and Energy Systems, volume 116, March 2020, and Manuel Garcia and Ross Baldick, "Real-Time Co-Optimization: Interdependent Reserve Types for Primary Frequency Response," Proceedings of the Tenth ACM International Conference on Future Energy Systems (e-Energy ’19), Phoenix, AZ, June 25&ndash;28, 2019.          Last Modified: 11/25/2019       Submitted by: Ross Baldick]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
