<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>TWC: Medium: Collaborative: Active Security</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2014</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>360000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>360000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>05050000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>CSE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CNS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Computer and Network Systems</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Shannon Beck</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Computer and network security is currently challenged by the need to secure diverse network environments including clouds and data-centers, PCs and enterprise infrastructures. This diversity of environments is coupled to increased attack sophistication. Today's tools for securing network and computing infrastructures can be painstakingly composed and configured using available components, but fail to automatically learn from their environment and actively protect it. This research introduces Active Security, which is an architectural approach with fundamental advantages for network defenders; Active Security continuously senses threats and adapts defenses to those threats, including those previously unseen.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Active Security prototyping and applications incorporate a novel high-rate decision procedure that avoids manual intervention.  The project addresses: (1) the characteristics of network 'sensors' most useful to an observe-orient-decide-act (OODA) loop; (2) decision and control algorithms for determining appropriate actions based on sensed events; (3) the infrastructure required for robust and trustworthy systems requiring minimal human-in-the-loop interaction; (4) automated defense approaches viable in diverse network settings that do no harm and are recoverable; and (5) metrics for performance assessment of an Active Security system such as responsiveness and accuracy.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Active Security's central themes of network security, network sensing, and automated defenses integrate naturally into both graduate and undergraduate education at participating institutions, including both midshipmen at the United States Naval Academy and cadets at the United States Military Academy.  Network security is an increasing concern for society at large, and an Active Security implementation is straightforward to deploy on networks equipped with programmable software defined networking (SDN) controllers, a technology increasingly present in data center, carrier and enterprise networks.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/25/2014</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/25/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.070</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1406225</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Jonathan</FirstName>
<LastName>Smith</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Jonathan Smith</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>jms@central.cis.upenn.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2158989509</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000090716</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/25/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Pennsylvania</Name>
<CityName>Philadelphia</CityName>
<ZipCode>191046205</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2158987293</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>Research Services</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[3451 Walnut St, 5th Flr Franklin]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Pennsylvania</StateName>
<StateCode>PA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>PA03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>042250712</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>TRUSTEES OF THE UNIVERSITY OF PENNSYLVANIA, THE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>042250712</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Pennsylvania]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>PA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>191046205</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Pennsylvania</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>PA03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>8060</Code>
<Text>Secure &amp;Trustworthy Cyberspace</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7434</Code>
<Text>CNCI</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7924</Code>
<Text>MEDIUM PROJECT</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0114</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~360000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Active Security was based on the observation that programmable networks, as in the SwitchWare Active Networking elements originated at Penn, could provide substantial benefits for security. Most importantly, a new vantage point from which network security problems could be observed, diagnosed and remedied was fleshed out in this project, giving a greenfield for novel analytic tools.</p> <p>Patent:</p> <p>Jonathan M. Smith, Eric R. Keller, Thomas W. Rondeau, and Kyle B. Super, &lsquo;&lsquo;Apparatus, Method and System to Dynamically Deploy Wireless Infrastructure,&rsquo;&rsquo; U.S. Patent No. 10,223,139 (March 5, 2019).</p> <p>Archival Papers:</p> <p>John Sonchack, Adam J. Aviv, and Jonathan M. Smith, &lsquo;&lsquo;Cross-domain collaboration for improved IDS rule set selection,&rsquo;&rsquo; Journal of Information Security and Applications 24-25, pp. 25-40 (2015).</p> <p>Conference &nbsp;and Workshop Papers:</p> <p>Oliver Michel, John Sonchack, Eric Keller, and Jonathan M. Smith, &lsquo;&lsquo;PIQ: Persistent Interactive Queries for Network Security Analytics,&rsquo;&rsquo; in Proceedings, ACM International Workshop on Security in Software Defined Networks and Network Function Virtualization (2019).</p> <p>John Sonchack, Oliver Michel, Adam J. Aviv, Eric Keller, and Jonathan M. Smith, &lsquo;&lsquo;Scaling Hardware Accelerated Monitoring to Concurrent and Dynamic Queries with *Flow,&rsquo;&rsquo; in Proceedings, USENIX Annual Technical Conference, Boston, MA (July 2018), pp. 823-836.</p> <p>Oliver Michel, John Sonchack, Eric Keller, and Jonathan M. Smith, &lsquo;&lsquo;Packet-Level Analytics in Software without Compromises,&rsquo;&rsquo; in 10th USENIX Workshop on Hot Topics in Cloud Computing (HotCloud &rsquo;18), Boston, MA (July 2018).</p> <p>John Sonchack, Adam J. Aviv, Eric Keller, and Jonathan M. Smith, &lsquo;&lsquo;TurboFlow: Information Rich Flow Record Generation on Commodity Switches,&rsquo;&rsquo; in Proc. ACM EuroSys &rsquo;18, Porto, PORTUGAL (April 2018), pp. 11:1-11:16. Best Student Paper</p> <p>John Sonchack, Anurag Dubey, Adam J. Aviv, Jonathan M. Smith, and Eric Keller, &lsquo;&lsquo;Timing-based reconaissance and defense in software-defined networks,&rsquo;&rsquo; in Proc. ACSAC (2016), pp. 89-100.</p> <p>John Sonchack, Adam Aviv, Eric Keller, and Jonathan M. Smith, &lsquo;&lsquo;Enabling Practical Software-defined Networking Security Applications with OFX,&rsquo;&rsquo; in Proc. NDSS, San Diego (February 2016).</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 06/02/2019<br>      Modified by: Jonathan&nbsp;Smith</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Active Security was based on the observation that programmable networks, as in the SwitchWare Active Networking elements originated at Penn, could provide substantial benefits for security. Most importantly, a new vantage point from which network security problems could be observed, diagnosed and remedied was fleshed out in this project, giving a greenfield for novel analytic tools.  Patent:  Jonathan M. Smith, Eric R. Keller, Thomas W. Rondeau, and Kyle B. Super, ??Apparatus, Method and System to Dynamically Deploy Wireless Infrastructure,?? U.S. Patent No. 10,223,139 (March 5, 2019).  Archival Papers:  John Sonchack, Adam J. Aviv, and Jonathan M. Smith, ??Cross-domain collaboration for improved IDS rule set selection,?? Journal of Information Security and Applications 24-25, pp. 25-40 (2015).  Conference  and Workshop Papers:  Oliver Michel, John Sonchack, Eric Keller, and Jonathan M. Smith, ??PIQ: Persistent Interactive Queries for Network Security Analytics,?? in Proceedings, ACM International Workshop on Security in Software Defined Networks and Network Function Virtualization (2019).  John Sonchack, Oliver Michel, Adam J. Aviv, Eric Keller, and Jonathan M. Smith, ??Scaling Hardware Accelerated Monitoring to Concurrent and Dynamic Queries with *Flow,?? in Proceedings, USENIX Annual Technical Conference, Boston, MA (July 2018), pp. 823-836.  Oliver Michel, John Sonchack, Eric Keller, and Jonathan M. Smith, ??Packet-Level Analytics in Software without Compromises,?? in 10th USENIX Workshop on Hot Topics in Cloud Computing (HotCloud ?18), Boston, MA (July 2018).  John Sonchack, Adam J. Aviv, Eric Keller, and Jonathan M. Smith, ??TurboFlow: Information Rich Flow Record Generation on Commodity Switches,?? in Proc. ACM EuroSys ?18, Porto, PORTUGAL (April 2018), pp. 11:1-11:16. Best Student Paper  John Sonchack, Anurag Dubey, Adam J. Aviv, Jonathan M. Smith, and Eric Keller, ??Timing-based reconaissance and defense in software-defined networks,?? in Proc. ACSAC (2016), pp. 89-100.  John Sonchack, Adam Aviv, Eric Keller, and Jonathan M. Smith, ??Enabling Practical Software-defined Networking Security Applications with OFX,?? in Proc. NDSS, San Diego (February 2016).          Last Modified: 06/02/2019       Submitted by: Jonathan Smith]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
