<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Time Flat Curves and Surfaces, Geometric Flows, and the Penrose Conjecture</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2014</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>214023.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>250249</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DMS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Christopher Stark</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>cstark@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924869</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Abstract&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Award: DMS 1406396, Principal Investigator: Hubert L. Bray&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project aims to continue to advance our understanding of the implications of Einstein's theory of general relativity.  This theory is at the foundation of our understanding of gravity and has applications in everyday use, such as global positioning system (GPS) technology, now present in most smart phones.  General relativity also unifies the notions of space, time, mass, and energy and provides the framework for understanding supermassive black holes and the Big Bang, the most energetic event in the history of the universe.  More specifically, this project focuses on finding a better understanding of the notion of mass in general relativity, whether it relates to a black hole or to defining the mass of an exploding supernova.  Since geometric analysis is the field of mathematics required to precisely state general relativity, this project will use many techniques from geometric analysis to study these questions.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Even more specifically, this project has two main research directions. The first is motivated by the desire to understand the geometry and mass of surfaces in spacetimes.  Jeff Jauregui, Marc Mars, and the PI have found that the Hawking mass of a surface is nondecreasing under a new geometric flow called "uniformly area expanding time flat flow."  The key idea is that the Hawking mass can overestimate the mass of a region inside a surface if the surface is not "time flat," which we define precisely.  A time flat surface is a generalization of the concept of a surface contained in a constant time slice of a static spacetime. Uniformly area expanding time flat flow, which is interesting by itself, grows the area form of the surface at a constant rate while keeping the surface, as a whole, time flat.  Existence, uniqueness, and asymptotics of this flow are very important questions to study in a variety of contexts.  The second research direction, which is related to the first, is to understand the mass of black holes as they relate to the Penrose conjecture, open since 1973.  While the PI proved the Riemannian Penrose conjecture for any number of black holes in 1999, which is the case when the hypersurface of a spacetime has zero second fundamental form, the general case pertaining to any slice of a spacetime is still open. While these questions can be posed in the language of physics, they are also important statements relating to scalar and Ricci curvature, minimal surfaces and mean curvature, isoperimetric regions, connections on bundles, submanifold geometry, geometric flows, and geometric partial differential equations.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/26/2014</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/08/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1406396</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Hubert</FirstName>
<LastName>Bray</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>L</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Hubert L Bray</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>bray@math.duke.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>9196602818</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000375410</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/26/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Duke University</Name>
<CityName>Durham</CityName>
<ZipCode>277054010</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>9196843030</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>2200 W. Main St, Suite 710</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[Erwin Square]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>North Carolina</StateName>
<StateCode>NC</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NC01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>044387793</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>DUKE UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>044387793</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Duke University]]></Name>
<CityName>Durham</CityName>
<StateCode>NC</StateCode>
<ZipCode>277080320</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[120 Science Drive]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>North Carolina</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NC04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1265</Code>
<Text>GEOMETRIC ANALYSIS</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0114</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0116</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~214023</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2016~36226</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>In 1915, Einstein came up with the most succinct deep thought in recorded history: "Matter curves spacetime." Those three words form the basis of general relativity which describes the phenomenon of gravity better than any other theory, and as accurately as can be measured. They predict black holes, the accelerating expansion of the universe, and gravitational waves - now all observed. In 1973, Sir Roger Penrose realized that general relativity also predicts certain geometric properties about black holes which, in every day terms, imply that the mass of a system must be at least the mass of the black holes contained in that system. These "geometric properties" became known as the Penrose Conjecture, a highly nontrivial statement about the geometry of black holes. Proving the Penrose Conjecture is believed to be necessary to fully understand general relativity, as a counter-example would imply a serious problem with general relativity itself.</p> <p>In 2001, the PI proved the Riemannian Penrose Conjecture for any number of black holes. In 2009, the PI proved this same result in higher dimensions with Dan Lee. In every day terms, the "Riemannian case" of the Penrose Conjecture is the case where one takes a flat slice of a spacetime, known by those in the field as a slice with zero second fundamental form.</p> <p>However, what if we take a "null slice" of a spacetime? For example, given any sphere, suppose it emits a flash of light, expanding in all directions. The set of points the light sweeps out is an example of a null hypersurface. The Penrose Conjecture, applied to any null hypersurfaces, is known as the Null Penrose Conjecture.</p> <p>I am EXTREMELY happy to report that, as a result of the funding of this project, my Ph.D. student (at the time) Henri Roesch proved a somewhat general case of the Null Penrose Conjecture. The proof yields new insights into the theory of general relativity itself. For example, Henri Roesch found a new quasi-local mass functional which tells us how much mass is inside a given region of&nbsp; a spacetime, is increasing under ANY outward flow of the surface in the null slice, and limits to the correct value at infinity. No other known quasi-local mass functional has these same outstanding properties. This kind of mass function is essential in understanding how mass behaves in general relativity. Bravo, Henri Roesch!</p> <p>The PI spent many hours discussing these ideas with Henri Roesch in weekly meetings, doing his best to use his experience working on this problem to help however he could. While this kind of mentoring and supervision is essential, Henri Roesch did every single computation himself and is the sole author of the proof of this major conjecture. The PI considers this result - having a student prove a major result - to be a double win: the conjecture is proved, and now another researcher has been trained to prove even more major results.</p> <p>The PI is also making very good  progress on "flatly foliated relativity," a simpler version of general  relativity, discovered by the PI, which may be thought of as a stepping stone between special  relativity and general relativity. The PI is still writing  these papers, though the main ideas are done. The basic idea is that, given a hard problem in general relativity, first try to prove it in flatly foliated relativity, and see if that solutions helps with the original problem. So far, so good.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 12/21/2018<br>      Modified by: Hubert&nbsp;L&nbsp;Bray</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ In 1915, Einstein came up with the most succinct deep thought in recorded history: "Matter curves spacetime." Those three words form the basis of general relativity which describes the phenomenon of gravity better than any other theory, and as accurately as can be measured. They predict black holes, the accelerating expansion of the universe, and gravitational waves - now all observed. In 1973, Sir Roger Penrose realized that general relativity also predicts certain geometric properties about black holes which, in every day terms, imply that the mass of a system must be at least the mass of the black holes contained in that system. These "geometric properties" became known as the Penrose Conjecture, a highly nontrivial statement about the geometry of black holes. Proving the Penrose Conjecture is believed to be necessary to fully understand general relativity, as a counter-example would imply a serious problem with general relativity itself.  In 2001, the PI proved the Riemannian Penrose Conjecture for any number of black holes. In 2009, the PI proved this same result in higher dimensions with Dan Lee. In every day terms, the "Riemannian case" of the Penrose Conjecture is the case where one takes a flat slice of a spacetime, known by those in the field as a slice with zero second fundamental form.  However, what if we take a "null slice" of a spacetime? For example, given any sphere, suppose it emits a flash of light, expanding in all directions. The set of points the light sweeps out is an example of a null hypersurface. The Penrose Conjecture, applied to any null hypersurfaces, is known as the Null Penrose Conjecture.  I am EXTREMELY happy to report that, as a result of the funding of this project, my Ph.D. student (at the time) Henri Roesch proved a somewhat general case of the Null Penrose Conjecture. The proof yields new insights into the theory of general relativity itself. For example, Henri Roesch found a new quasi-local mass functional which tells us how much mass is inside a given region of  a spacetime, is increasing under ANY outward flow of the surface in the null slice, and limits to the correct value at infinity. No other known quasi-local mass functional has these same outstanding properties. This kind of mass function is essential in understanding how mass behaves in general relativity. Bravo, Henri Roesch!  The PI spent many hours discussing these ideas with Henri Roesch in weekly meetings, doing his best to use his experience working on this problem to help however he could. While this kind of mentoring and supervision is essential, Henri Roesch did every single computation himself and is the sole author of the proof of this major conjecture. The PI considers this result - having a student prove a major result - to be a double win: the conjecture is proved, and now another researcher has been trained to prove even more major results.  The PI is also making very good  progress on "flatly foliated relativity," a simpler version of general  relativity, discovered by the PI, which may be thought of as a stepping stone between special  relativity and general relativity. The PI is still writing  these papers, though the main ideas are done. The basic idea is that, given a hard problem in general relativity, first try to prove it in flatly foliated relativity, and see if that solutions helps with the original problem. So far, so good.       Last Modified: 12/21/2018       Submitted by: Hubert L Bray]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
