<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Floer homology and contact and symplectic geometry</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2014</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>258397.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>258397</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DMS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Joanna Kania-Bartoszynska</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>jkaniaba@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924881</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The set of all possible configurations of a physical system generally has the structure of a symplectic manifold. When one restricts to configurations with a fixed energy, one typically obtains a contact manifold. Understanding the geometry of symplectic manifolds and contact manifolds is thus important to understanding the dynamics of physical systems. The following two geometric questions about such manifolds are of particular interest. First, one would like to understand Reeb orbits on contact manifolds, which correspond to physical behavior which repeats over time. Second, one would like to understand when one symplectic manifold can be symplectically embedded into another, in order to better understand the relations between different symplectic manifolds. Contact homology is a powerful tool, currently under development, which can be applied to both of these questions.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The project will develop the foundations, computation, and applications of various kinds of contact homology. In particular, embedded contact homology (ECH) will be extended to a functor on three-dimensional contact manifolds and four-dimensional strong symplectic cobordisms. The foundations of ECH and other kinds of contact homology will be constructed directly in terms of holomorphic curves when possible, in order to more closely relate them to geometry. ECH capacities (quantitative invariants which obstruct symplectic embeddings in four dimensions) will be computed in more examples and related to geodesic flows and Hamiltonian dynamics. Analogues of ECH capacities for other kinds of contact homology, such as cylindrical contact homology and rational symplectic field theory, will be constructed and studied. These new tools will be used to explore whether the Weinstein conjecture can be extended by increasing the lower bound on the number of Reeb orbits or proving the existence of short Reeb orbits.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/15/2014</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/15/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1406312</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Michael</FirstName>
<LastName>Hutchings</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>L</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Michael L Hutchings</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>hutching@math.berkeley.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5106424329</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000127679</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/15/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of California-Berkeley</Name>
<CityName>BERKELEY</CityName>
<ZipCode>947101749</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5106433891</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>Sponsored Projects Office</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[1608 Fourth Street, Suite 220]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>13</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CA13</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>124726725</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>REGENTS OF THE UNIVERSITY OF CALIFORNIA, THE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>071549000</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of California, Berkeley]]></Name>
<CityName>Berkeley</CityName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>947203840</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[Mathematics Department]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>13</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CA13</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1267</Code>
<Text>TOPOLOGY</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0114</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~258397</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>This project studied certain questions in symplectic geometry and Reeb dynamics. Symplectic geometry is the basic geometry underlying classical mechanics. In this framework, the state of a physical system at a given time is described by a point in a phase space, which is a space with an even number of dimensions, equipped with a symplectic structure. Over time the state of the physical system follows a trajectory in the phase space, which is determined by the synplectic geometry. Moreover, conservation of energy implies that this trajectory stays on an odd-dimensional hypersurface. In many cases of interest this hypersurface has a contact structure, and the trajectory follows the Reeb vector field associated to the contact structure. A fundamental object of study are the periodic orbits of the Reeb vector field; these represent physical behavior which repeats in time, such as planet orbiting a star.</p> <p>One major finding of this project was that in many cases where the hypersurface is three-dimensional, there are either two or infinitely many periodic orbits of the Reeb vector field. Moreover there are two periodic orbits only in very simple cases, so in most cases there are infinitely many periodic orbits.</p> <p>Another part of the project studied symplectic embeddings. These are coordinate changes which move one region in phase space to another while respecting the symplectic structure. One is interested in understanding when it is possible to move a given region inside another given region via a symplectic embedding. The project found several new obstructions to such symplectic embeddings. In particular, using embedded contact homology, a new obstruction was found in the four-dimensional case which is sharp for many examples, such as symplectically embedding a four-dimensional polydisk of certain sizes into a ball. In addition, using equivariant symplectic homology, a new family of obstructions was found for symplectic embeddings in any even dimension. This gives sharp obstructions for example to symplectic embeddings of a cube into any convex or concave toric domain.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 11/09/2018<br>      Modified by: Michael&nbsp;L&nbsp;Hutchings</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ This project studied certain questions in symplectic geometry and Reeb dynamics. Symplectic geometry is the basic geometry underlying classical mechanics. In this framework, the state of a physical system at a given time is described by a point in a phase space, which is a space with an even number of dimensions, equipped with a symplectic structure. Over time the state of the physical system follows a trajectory in the phase space, which is determined by the synplectic geometry. Moreover, conservation of energy implies that this trajectory stays on an odd-dimensional hypersurface. In many cases of interest this hypersurface has a contact structure, and the trajectory follows the Reeb vector field associated to the contact structure. A fundamental object of study are the periodic orbits of the Reeb vector field; these represent physical behavior which repeats in time, such as planet orbiting a star.  One major finding of this project was that in many cases where the hypersurface is three-dimensional, there are either two or infinitely many periodic orbits of the Reeb vector field. Moreover there are two periodic orbits only in very simple cases, so in most cases there are infinitely many periodic orbits.  Another part of the project studied symplectic embeddings. These are coordinate changes which move one region in phase space to another while respecting the symplectic structure. One is interested in understanding when it is possible to move a given region inside another given region via a symplectic embedding. The project found several new obstructions to such symplectic embeddings. In particular, using embedded contact homology, a new obstruction was found in the four-dimensional case which is sharp for many examples, such as symplectically embedding a four-dimensional polydisk of certain sizes into a ball. In addition, using equivariant symplectic homology, a new family of obstructions was found for symplectic embeddings in any even dimension. This gives sharp obstructions for example to symplectic embeddings of a cube into any convex or concave toric domain.       Last Modified: 11/09/2018       Submitted by: Michael L Hutchings]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
