<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Noncommutative and Hamiltonian geometry, symplectic resolutions, and D-modules</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2014</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>195000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>130150</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DMS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>James Matthew Douglass</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>mdouglas@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922467</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The PI defines and studies invariants of geometric spaces and quantum analogues thereof.  This area arises from the study of symmetries of geometric or physical systems and their linear actions (representation theory) and their quantization, the mathematical version of passing from classical to quantum mechanics (noncommutative geometry).  There is a rich interplay between the two, which has connections and applications to many areas of mathematics, such as combinatorics, integrable systems, real algebraic geometry, quiver varieties, and resolutions of symplectic singularities.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The PI defines new homology theories which generalize de Rham cohomology and gives new interpretations of Hochschild and cyclic homology using D-module techniques.  These ideas have applications to the representation theory of Lie groups, to the study of various algebras (Cherednik, symplectic reflection, and W-algebras), and to symplectic and Calabi-Yau resolutions.  The PI will prove that his Poisson-de Rham homology recovers the de Rham homology of every symplectic resolution in new cases, such as for determinantal varieties and hypertoric varieties.  He will recover from it important polynomials such as Kostka and Tutte polynomials.  The PI plans to pursue conjectures relating this to the orders of vanishing of holomorphic fiberwise-closed forms on the deformation of the resolution.  The main technique uses D-modules which encapsulate the Hamiltonian flow, built of canonical local systems on symplectic leaves.  He also plans to use cyclic homology to obtain representations of affine Hecke algebras via the Gauss-Manin connection on noncommutative deformations of the mirror of cotangent bundles to flag varieties.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/18/2014</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>12/18/2017</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1406553</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>David</FirstName>
<LastName>Ben-Zvi</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>D</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>David D Ben-Zvi</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>benzvi@math.utexas.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5124718151</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000183201</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>12/18/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Travis</FirstName>
<LastName>Schedler</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>J</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Travis J Schedler</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>trasched@gmail.com</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5124717189</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000079043</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/18/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate>12/18/2017</EndDate>
<RoleCode>Former Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Texas at Austin</Name>
<CityName>Austin</CityName>
<ZipCode>787595316</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5124716424</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>3925 W Braker Lane, Ste 3.340</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Texas</StateName>
<StateCode>TX</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>10</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>TX10</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>170230239</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF TEXAS AT AUSTIN</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>042000273</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Texas at Austin]]></Name>
<CityName>Austin</CityName>
<StateCode>TX</StateCode>
<ZipCode>787121202</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[2515 Speedway Stop C1200]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Texas</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>25</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>TX25</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1264</Code>
<Text>ALGEBRA,NUMBER THEORY,AND COM</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0114</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0115</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~65091</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2015~65059</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p> <div>The project was concerned with the interplay between D-modules and symplectic resolutions and their applications to deformation and singularity theory. Symplectic resolutions are exciting geometric objects that generalize the representation theory of many important algebraic objects such as semisimple Lie algebras, Cherednik algebras, quantized hypertonic and quiver varieties, etc. Their study lies at the crossroads of algebraic, symplectic, and enumerative geometry as well as representation theory and mathematical physics.</div> <div>The primary intellectual focus was twofold: 1. To develop more general D-module tools to prove finiteness theorems for Poisson homology and cohomology, as well as coinvariants under more general Lie algebras of vector fields, and to unearth links to important invariants in singularity theory such as the b-function, the Milnor number and the reduced genus. &nbsp;2. To classify symplectic resolutions, especially those appearing in 3D mirror symmetry. The intellectual merit consisted in classifying these resolutions completely in the quiver variety case and nearly completely for finite quotients, defining D-modules and prove criteria for their holonomicity which recover important invariants, and establishing some conjectures about their numerics (for example, that the reduced genus of hypersurfaces with isolated singularities is recovered by the D-module generated by the reciprocal of the polynomial), as well as their proofs in special cases (the quasi-homogeneous case in the example).</div> <div>The broader impacts of this project included mentoring three PhD students, giving several international lectures, some accessible to PhD students, and organizing two conferences, one geared towards PhD students and the other a major one for PhD students all the way up to senior researchers at the University of Chicago.</div> </p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 10/25/2018<br>      Modified by: David&nbsp;D&nbsp;Ben-Zvi</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[  The project was concerned with the interplay between D-modules and symplectic resolutions and their applications to deformation and singularity theory. Symplectic resolutions are exciting geometric objects that generalize the representation theory of many important algebraic objects such as semisimple Lie algebras, Cherednik algebras, quantized hypertonic and quiver varieties, etc. Their study lies at the crossroads of algebraic, symplectic, and enumerative geometry as well as representation theory and mathematical physics. The primary intellectual focus was twofold: 1. To develop more general D-module tools to prove finiteness theorems for Poisson homology and cohomology, as well as coinvariants under more general Lie algebras of vector fields, and to unearth links to important invariants in singularity theory such as the b-function, the Milnor number and the reduced genus.  2. To classify symplectic resolutions, especially those appearing in 3D mirror symmetry. The intellectual merit consisted in classifying these resolutions completely in the quiver variety case and nearly completely for finite quotients, defining D-modules and prove criteria for their holonomicity which recover important invariants, and establishing some conjectures about their numerics (for example, that the reduced genus of hypersurfaces with isolated singularities is recovered by the D-module generated by the reciprocal of the polynomial), as well as their proofs in special cases (the quasi-homogeneous case in the example). The broader impacts of this project included mentoring three PhD students, giving several international lectures, some accessible to PhD students, and organizing two conferences, one geared towards PhD students and the other a major one for PhD students all the way up to senior researchers at the University of Chicago.        Last Modified: 10/25/2018       Submitted by: David D Ben-Zvi]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
