<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Gravitation and Black Holes: From Magnetospheres to Firewalls</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2014</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>651404.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>801404</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03010000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>PHY</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Physics</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Pedro Marronetti</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>pmarrone@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927372</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This research is directed at developing an improved understanding in three different areas of gravitational physics: 1) puzzling issues that arise when applying quantum mechanics to black holes, 2) tests of possible deviations from standard relativity theory, 3) theory of strong magnetic fields around astrophysical black holes and in other systems. On the second topic, one project involves calculating the predicted form of gravitational waves from spherical collapsing stars and supernovae in a modified gravity theory. Another is a study of the viability of such a theory in the quantum realm, and a third is to develop alternative but similar approaches to quantum gravity. Topics in the third category include the nature of astrophysical jets, and energy extraction from black holes and stars spinning or moving in a magnetized cloud of charged particles. Also, this work studies the impact of gravity on the generation and properties of twisted magnetic field lines, and the mathematical structure of the basic equations and their simulation on computers. All of these approaches address fundamental questions regarding the structure of the universe.  The corresponding results will be disseminated through written articles, as well as seminars, conference talks, colloquia and lecture series. The PI will provide instruction and mentoring to a postdoctoral scholar, as well as graduate and undergraduate students, regarding scientific research, writing, and verbal communication. The PI will seek out opportunities to speak on this topic to audiences ranging across the spectrum from the general public to specialists in gravitational physics.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;In the quantum gravity realm, one project concerns the black hole information paradox and the possible role of the Wheeler-de Witt equation in resolving it. Specifically, this work studies the redundant encoding of information into the local degrees of freedom described by a wave function satisfying the Wheeler-de Witt equation. Another project involves the relation of black hole entropy to vacuum entanglement and Noether charge.  This research will try to determine whether the entropy contribution from non minimal coupling is balanced by a corresponding entanglement entropy change in adiabatic physical processes involving matter crossing black hole horizons. On the Lorentz violating gravity topic, this project studies whether the proposal for a UV complete, "Lifshitz" quantum gravity can pass the stability test, when all the higher derivative terms are taken into account at the non-linear level. We will also examine whether the idea of Lifshitz scaling can be applied in a spacetime with a preferred temporal threading but no preferred spatial foliation. Finally, the magnetosphere topics are will concentrate on the definition, computation and interpretation of magnetic helicity in a general relativistic setting, and in the presence of boundaries such as the surface of a neutron star or the horizon of a black hole. This should be useful in determining the role of helicity injection and conservation, and how it relates to energy minimization, in a general relativistic setting.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>05/08/2014</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/01/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1407744</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Theodore</FirstName>
<LastName>Jacobson</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>A</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Theodore A Jacobson</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>jacobson@umd.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>3014056020</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000167303</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/08/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Ira</FirstName>
<LastName>Rothstein</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Ira Rothstein</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>izr@andrew.cmu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>4122688746</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000544853</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/03/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Maryland, College Park</Name>
<CityName>College Park</CityName>
<ZipCode>207425141</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>3014056269</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>3112 LEE BLDG 7809 Regents Drive</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Maryland</StateName>
<StateCode>MD</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MD05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>790934285</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF MARYLAND, COLLEGE PARK</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>003256088</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Maryland, College Park]]></Name>
<CityName>College Park</CityName>
<StateCode>MD</StateCode>
<ZipCode>207425141</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[3112 LEE BLDG 7809 Regents Drive]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Maryland</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MD05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1244</Code>
<Text>Gravity Theory</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7483</Code>
<Text>PHYSICS OF THE UNIVERSE</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7569</Code>
<Text>CYBERINFRASTRUCTURE/SCIENCE</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0114</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0115</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0116</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~190724</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2015~303182</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2016~307498</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Intellectual Merits<br /><br />1) Jacobson found that Einstein's equation governing the curvature of spacetime in vacuum is equivalent to the statement that all small geodesic balls of a given volume have the same area, and therefore the same entropy of vacuum entanglement between the inside and the outside. Matter can be included, for non-scale free theories using a relation between energy and entanglement derived by graduate student Antony Speranza. Speranza with others also extended the general result to include corrections to the Einstein equation.<br /><br />2) Several projects were aimed at understanding the results of experiments carried out by Jeff Steinhauer, emulating a black hole and Hawking radiation in a quantum condensate of rubidium atoms. With Charles Clark, Mark Edwards, and Yi-Hsieh Wang, Jacobson found that in one of Steinhauer's experiments the observed phenomenon was not the instability originally reported, but instead resulted from a bow wave. We also discovered that variations in the number of atoms from one run to the next inadvertently generated spurious correlations that were misinterpreted in the original paper by Steinhauer. Also Jacobson and Wang discovered that the simulation method used by Steinhauer was not true to the physics, and led to an enhanced signal of a new kind of sound generation, distinct from the Hawking effect. Finally, with a Maryland experimental group Jacobson helped interpret the results of their expanding ring condensate experiment, finding evidence of redhift and other phenomena analogous to quantum field phenomena in the expanding universe.<br /><br />3) Jacobson, Speranza, and Jose Senovilla considered the area-volume relationship of a small ball in vacuum, accounting for quadratic effects in curvature. We derived a number of results that could be useful in further developing insights into the nature of ``gravitational energy density".<br /><br />4) Speranza developed the theory of gravitational dynamics in a region with boundary, focusing on the nature of the boundary degrees of freedom that are required if the dynamics is to share the symmetry of the boundaryless theory.<br /><br />5) With undergraduate/graduate student Andrew Shaw, Jacobson analysed the sourcing of axion field by the electromagnetic field of a neutron star, the gravitational binding of that field to theneutron star, and potential mechanisms by which the energy in that axion field might be converted to observable electromagnetic waves.<br /><br />6) Rothstein along with Chad Galley, showed how the dynamical renormalization group can be used find analytic solutions to binary inspirals without the need for an adiabatic approximation. Having such solutions will speed up the production of template banks with smaller systematic errors.<br /><br />7) Rothstein along with Rafael Porto, elucidated the apparent ambiguities in the fourth order Post-Newtonian approximation to the conservative equations of motion. We showed how to distinguish the infra-red and ultraviolet divergences that arise when using dimensional regularization, and how the IR divergences that arise result from double counting radiation modes. These results are crucial for ensuring control over higher order post-Newtonian calculations that are necessary to make accurate parameter extractions at LIGO.<br /><br />8) With Michael Solon and Clifford Cheung, Rothstein generalized his previous work that utilized modern scattering amplitude techniques to calculate potentials in the post-Minkowskian regime. These results have been utilized by the LIGO collaboration to improve the quality of the templates that are used to perform parameter extraction and to calculate the conservative force at third Post-Minkowskian order.<br /><br />9) With&nbsp; Stefano Foffa, Rafael Porto and Riccardo Sturani, Rothstein presented the fourth order Post-Newtonian (PN) conservative renormalized Lagrangian, making use of the above result by Porto and Rothstein. This state of the art result was shown to agree with the results of Blanchet et al. It also allows for the calculation of higher order (above 4PN) logarithms that show up in the PN expansion.<br /><br /><br />Broader Impacts<br /><br />The work promoted synergy between distant subfields of physics. For example, our work on the physics of cold atom condensates and the analogy with black holes has drawn together two otherwise quite separate research communities at UMD and the world at large. Moreover, the experiments of Steinhauer made a large spash in the international media. Jacobson was interviewed by journalists and helped explain the significance.<br /><br />We have introduced string theoretic amplitude techniques into the field of gravitational wave physics, forming a strong connection between the string theory amplitudes and GR communities. There have now been several international workshops on the subject of scattering amplitudes and gravitational wave templates.<br /><br />Our training of students in rigorous, technical scientific research contributes to creating a pool of highly skilled individuals. The research involved three females (a graduate student, an assistant professor, and a NIST employee), and a Jamaican-American (under)graduate student. Such activity helps to develop the population of successful, highly trained minority groups in scientific work, to the ultimate benefit of science and society.<br /><br /><br /></p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 01/06/2020<br>      Modified by: Theodore&nbsp;A&nbsp;Jacobson</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Intellectual Merits  1) Jacobson found that Einstein's equation governing the curvature of spacetime in vacuum is equivalent to the statement that all small geodesic balls of a given volume have the same area, and therefore the same entropy of vacuum entanglement between the inside and the outside. Matter can be included, for non-scale free theories using a relation between energy and entanglement derived by graduate student Antony Speranza. Speranza with others also extended the general result to include corrections to the Einstein equation.  2) Several projects were aimed at understanding the results of experiments carried out by Jeff Steinhauer, emulating a black hole and Hawking radiation in a quantum condensate of rubidium atoms. With Charles Clark, Mark Edwards, and Yi-Hsieh Wang, Jacobson found that in one of Steinhauer's experiments the observed phenomenon was not the instability originally reported, but instead resulted from a bow wave. We also discovered that variations in the number of atoms from one run to the next inadvertently generated spurious correlations that were misinterpreted in the original paper by Steinhauer. Also Jacobson and Wang discovered that the simulation method used by Steinhauer was not true to the physics, and led to an enhanced signal of a new kind of sound generation, distinct from the Hawking effect. Finally, with a Maryland experimental group Jacobson helped interpret the results of their expanding ring condensate experiment, finding evidence of redhift and other phenomena analogous to quantum field phenomena in the expanding universe.  3) Jacobson, Speranza, and Jose Senovilla considered the area-volume relationship of a small ball in vacuum, accounting for quadratic effects in curvature. We derived a number of results that could be useful in further developing insights into the nature of ``gravitational energy density".  4) Speranza developed the theory of gravitational dynamics in a region with boundary, focusing on the nature of the boundary degrees of freedom that are required if the dynamics is to share the symmetry of the boundaryless theory.  5) With undergraduate/graduate student Andrew Shaw, Jacobson analysed the sourcing of axion field by the electromagnetic field of a neutron star, the gravitational binding of that field to theneutron star, and potential mechanisms by which the energy in that axion field might be converted to observable electromagnetic waves.  6) Rothstein along with Chad Galley, showed how the dynamical renormalization group can be used find analytic solutions to binary inspirals without the need for an adiabatic approximation. Having such solutions will speed up the production of template banks with smaller systematic errors.  7) Rothstein along with Rafael Porto, elucidated the apparent ambiguities in the fourth order Post-Newtonian approximation to the conservative equations of motion. We showed how to distinguish the infra-red and ultraviolet divergences that arise when using dimensional regularization, and how the IR divergences that arise result from double counting radiation modes. These results are crucial for ensuring control over higher order post-Newtonian calculations that are necessary to make accurate parameter extractions at LIGO.  8) With Michael Solon and Clifford Cheung, Rothstein generalized his previous work that utilized modern scattering amplitude techniques to calculate potentials in the post-Minkowskian regime. These results have been utilized by the LIGO collaboration to improve the quality of the templates that are used to perform parameter extraction and to calculate the conservative force at third Post-Minkowskian order.  9) With  Stefano Foffa, Rafael Porto and Riccardo Sturani, Rothstein presented the fourth order Post-Newtonian (PN) conservative renormalized Lagrangian, making use of the above result by Porto and Rothstein. This state of the art result was shown to agree with the results of Blanchet et al. It also allows for the calculation of higher order (above 4PN) logarithms that show up in the PN expansion.   Broader Impacts  The work promoted synergy between distant subfields of physics. For example, our work on the physics of cold atom condensates and the analogy with black holes has drawn together two otherwise quite separate research communities at UMD and the world at large. Moreover, the experiments of Steinhauer made a large spash in the international media. Jacobson was interviewed by journalists and helped explain the significance.  We have introduced string theoretic amplitude techniques into the field of gravitational wave physics, forming a strong connection between the string theory amplitudes and GR communities. There have now been several international workshops on the subject of scattering amplitudes and gravitational wave templates.  Our training of students in rigorous, technical scientific research contributes to creating a pool of highly skilled individuals. The research involved three females (a graduate student, an assistant professor, and a NIST employee), and a Jamaican-American (under)graduate student. Such activity helps to develop the population of successful, highly trained minority groups in scientific work, to the ultimate benefit of science and society.          Last Modified: 01/06/2020       Submitted by: Theodore A Jacobson]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
