<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>DISSERTATION RESEARCH: Between-class gene flow in complex mating systems: The evolution of breeding systems in Silene vulgaris</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>06/01/2014</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>19628.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>19628</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>08010207</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>BIO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DEB</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Environmental Biology</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>George Gilchrist</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>In most plants and animals, males and females differ in size, shape, or color because natural selection drives the sexes in different directions. The evolution of this dimorphism is constrained by the mixing of genes among males and females during mating known as between-class gene flow. This work investigates the effects of between-class gene flow in a plant Silene vulgaris, in which individuals are either hermaphrodite or female. In species with such complex mating systems, the rates of between-class gene flow vary among populations, allowing their effects to be more easily detected. Using genetic markers, this work will estimate the strength of natural selection in hermaphrodites and females, as well as the patterns of gene flow among hermaphrodites and females for multiple populations. These estimates will be combined with estimates of heritability to determine if between-class gene flow limits the evolution of differences between sexes.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This work will test the importance of between-class gene flow as a factor affecting adaptation in natural systems. The understanding of this process will inform strategies for artificial selection of agriculturally important species such as cattle (Bos primigenius), in which males and females have different desired traits, and species with complex mating systems, such as maize (Zea mays). Finally, this work directly supports the training of a doctoral student as a researcher and mentor and provides opportunities for undergraduate students to engage in research in quantitative genetics and molecular ecology.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>04/08/2014</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/11/2017</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.074</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1407166</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Edmund</FirstName>
<LastName>Brodie</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>D</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME>III</PI_SUFX_NAME>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Edmund D Brodie</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>bbrodie@virginia.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>4342431068</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000434078</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/08/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Malcolm</FirstName>
<LastName>Augat</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Malcolm Augat</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>ma5ke@virginia.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>4349825897</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000633020</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/08/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Virginia Main Campus</Name>
<CityName>CHARLOTTESVILLE</CityName>
<ZipCode>229044195</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>4349244270</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>P.O.  BOX 400195</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Virginia</StateName>
<StateCode>VA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>VA05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>065391526</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>RECTOR &amp; VISITORS OF THE UNIVERSITY OF VIRGINIA</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>065391526</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Virginia Main Campus]]></Name>
<CityName>Charlottesville</CityName>
<StateCode>VA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>229044328</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[P.O. Box 400328]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Virginia</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>VA05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7377</Code>
<Text>EVOLUTIONARY ECOLOGY</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9169</Code>
<Text>BIODIVERSITY AND ECOSYSTEM DYNAMICS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9179</Code>
<Text>GRADUATE INVOLVEMENT</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>EGCH</Code>
<Text>ENVIRONMENT AND GLOBAL CHANGE</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>SMET</Code>
<Text>SCIENCE, MATH, ENG &amp; TECH EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0114</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~19628</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p class="normal">In most plants and animals, males and females differ in size, shape, or color because natural selection drives the sexes in different directions. The evolution of this dimorphism is constrained</p> <p class="normal">because genes favored in one sex can be inherited by members of the other sex. This mixing of genes between males and females is know as between-class gene flow.</p> <p class="normal">The project developed theoretical models to track the effect of between-class gene flow in complex mating systems that include uneven sex ratios, and the presence of hermaphroditic individuals. This system is common in plants such as <em>Silene vulgaris</em>, which was used as the model for empirical work in this project. Modeling illustrated that unequal sex ratios, and uneven migration of genes between mating classes can constrain the evolution of sex differences, even under simple assumptions of genetic architecture.</p> <p class="normal">Natural selection was estimated for both sexes in six populations and showed that wider but shorter petals were favored in hermaphrodites, but narrower and longer petals were favored in females. Differences between sexes in observed flower size matched this pattern. Quantitative genetic breeding designs and marker based estimates of gene flow were executed to estimate the heritability and genetic correlations for floral traits to further parameterize the models. Taken together with the theoretical modeling, these results led to the prediction that populations with more hermaphrodite skewed sex ratios should have greater dimorphism. This hypothesis was not supported. Related work on soil quality and its effect on sexual dimorphism suggested that plasticity could contribute to observed patterns of dimorphism.&nbsp;</p> <p class="normal">The project provided the support for one PhD student&rsquo;s dissertation research. This work further generated opportunities for two undergraduate REU students supported through the Mountain Lake Biological Station REU Program. An additional five undergraduate students were mentored in independent research at the home institution.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 08/07/2017<br>      Modified by: Edmund&nbsp;D&nbsp;Brodie</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[In most plants and animals, males and females differ in size, shape, or color because natural selection drives the sexes in different directions. The evolution of this dimorphism is constrained because genes favored in one sex can be inherited by members of the other sex. This mixing of genes between males and females is know as between-class gene flow. The project developed theoretical models to track the effect of between-class gene flow in complex mating systems that include uneven sex ratios, and the presence of hermaphroditic individuals. This system is common in plants such as Silene vulgaris, which was used as the model for empirical work in this project. Modeling illustrated that unequal sex ratios, and uneven migration of genes between mating classes can constrain the evolution of sex differences, even under simple assumptions of genetic architecture. Natural selection was estimated for both sexes in six populations and showed that wider but shorter petals were favored in hermaphrodites, but narrower and longer petals were favored in females. Differences between sexes in observed flower size matched this pattern. Quantitative genetic breeding designs and marker based estimates of gene flow were executed to estimate the heritability and genetic correlations for floral traits to further parameterize the models. Taken together with the theoretical modeling, these results led to the prediction that populations with more hermaphrodite skewed sex ratios should have greater dimorphism. This hypothesis was not supported. Related work on soil quality and its effect on sexual dimorphism suggested that plasticity could contribute to observed patterns of dimorphism.  The project provided the support for one PhD student?s dissertation research. This work further generated opportunities for two undergraduate REU students supported through the Mountain Lake Biological Station REU Program. An additional five undergraduate students were mentored in independent research at the home institution.          Last Modified: 08/07/2017       Submitted by: Edmund D Brodie]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
