<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Research Initiation Award - Basic Mechanism of DNA Assembly into Nano-shells</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>06/01/2014</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>199995.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>319945</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>11060000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>EHR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>HRD</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Human Resource Development</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Claudia Rankins</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Research Initiation Awards provide support for junior and mid-career faculty at Historically Black Colleges and Universities who are building new research programs or redirecting and rebuilding existing research programs. It is expected that the award helps to further the faculty member's research capability and effectiveness, improves research and teaching at her home institution, and involves undergraduate students in research experiences.  The award to Howard University has potential impact in the areas of nanomedicine and bio-detection. The research has broader societal impacts by generating a new line of self-assembled drug-delivery vehicles for transporting labile molecules into cells, and by enhancing the research experience and training of four undergraduate students for pursuing a career in the sciences or entry into graduate school.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The goal of the project is to understand the mechanism of nanoshells formation by focusing on how mannobiosylation alters the polymer physics of the linear polyethylenimine backbone and therefore its interaction with DNA, and alters the packing interaction between condensed DNA.  The three specific objectives are to 1) determine the effect of mannobiose on the interaction state of polyethylenimine in three biophysical regimes; 2) measure the self-adhesive and self-clustering interactions in mannobiose layers; and 3) measure the interactions between the intermediates of nanoshell assembly. The study uses an innovative approach that combines polymer phase maps, multi-parameter pH titrations, dynamic light scattering and atomic force spectroscopy. Preliminary data demonstrate that the approach is feasible.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>05/30/2014</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/30/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.076</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1407891</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Preethi</FirstName>
<LastName>Chandran</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>L</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Preethi L Chandran</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>preethi.chandran@howard.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2028064759</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000646963</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/30/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Howard University</Name>
<CityName>Washington</CityName>
<ZipCode>200599000</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2028064759</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>2400 Sixth Street N W</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>District of Columbia</StateName>
<StateCode>DC</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>00</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>DC00</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>056282296</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>HOWARD UNIVERSITY (INC)</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>056282296</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Howard University]]></Name>
<CityName>Washington</CityName>
<StateCode>DC</StateCode>
<ZipCode>200590001</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[2400 sixth street NW]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>District of Columbia</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>00</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>DC00</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1594</Code>
<Text>Hist Black Colleges and Univ</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9178</Code>
<Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>CL10</Code>
<Text>CLB-Career Life Balance</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0414</Code>
<Name>NSF Education &amp; Human Resource</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040106</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0415</Code>
<Name>NSF Education &amp; Human Resource</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040106</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0416</Code>
<Name>NSF Education &amp; Human Resource</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040106</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~239993</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2015~39963</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2016~39989</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>What we sought out to do:</p> <p>DNA is a negative-charged polymer, which is usually extended when in solution. Small positive-charged polymers can bind DNA and pack it into compact structures. These compact structures are used to transporting DNA into cells. One positive-charged polymer polyethylenimine (PEI) appeared to be compacting DNA into shell-like structures when it had branches of mannose. Our specific goal was to understand how the mannose bristles altered the properties of the PEI backbone and its interaction with DNA, resulting in the compaction into shells instead of filled spheres. Our broader goal was to use the phenomenon as a platform for understanding why nature chose mannose to coat the surface of cells, particularly of viruses like HIV, Ebola, SARS, Dengue, and fungus like <em>Cryptococcus neoformans</em> which causes meningitis. In other words, studying how mannose modifies the biophysics of PEI and PEI-DNA interactions can also provide insight into the survival advantages conferred by a mannose coating on a pathogen.</p> <p>What we found:</p> <ol> <li>PEI has one of the simplest structures of a polymer. Yet modest changes in pH and salt induce large changes in its charge and clustering, independently. This finding is important because PEI is extensively used for transfecting DNA into cells, our findings suggest that transfection success is intricately dependent on how the compact-DNA solutions are prepared. </li> <li>In the process of studying PEI we found that the ninhydrin assay used to estimating amine concentration actually estimates the concentration of unprotonated amines. This finding is important because ninhydrin assay is a workhorse for estimating protein concentration (from the amount of amines on the proteins) in research and industry.</li> <li>We found that attaching mannose to PEI changes the latter&rsquo;s aggregation and pH profile. This finding is important because most proteins secreted by cells have mannose sugars on them, and the sugars could be modifying the interfacial properties of the proteins. </li> <li>We found that two opposing mannose-coated surface can specifically self-latch to each other. Since mannose is found extensively on the surface of pathogens, the finding has implications for pathogen-pathogen interactions. </li> <li>We found that a relatively large layer of bound water exists around a mannose layer, slowing down the approach of particles, but 'fracturing' when particles approach at high velocity. This finding has implications for the hydration and immune-recognition of pathogens, and therefore for the latter's survivability. </li> <li>Additional findings on virus surfaces and DNA packaging are being compiled into manuscripts for dissemination. </li> </ol> <p>The broader impacts of the project were:</p> <p>1. Under-represented minority students got opportunities to apply classroom learning to solve problems at the interface of engineering and fundamental sciences, to think critically about testing methods and outcomes, and to quantify findings for effective communication. Via the research opportunities made available to five undergraduate student, skills critical for a superior STEM workforce were imparted.</p> <p>2. . A graduate student did a PhD thesis at the nexus of engineering and biochemistry, leading to the exchange of thoughts and ideas between the engineering and medical colleges at Howard University.</p> <p>3. The increased research capability enabled the PI to lead a team of undergraduate honor students to mentor middle-school students via science-engagement modules.</p> <p>5. The research enterprise at Howard University was significantly increased both by the upgrade of an atomic force microscope, and by the lectures on bioengineering facilitated by the resulting research.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 06/05/2018<br>      Modified by: Preethi&nbsp;L&nbsp;Chandran</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ What we sought out to do:  DNA is a negative-charged polymer, which is usually extended when in solution. Small positive-charged polymers can bind DNA and pack it into compact structures. These compact structures are used to transporting DNA into cells. One positive-charged polymer polyethylenimine (PEI) appeared to be compacting DNA into shell-like structures when it had branches of mannose. Our specific goal was to understand how the mannose bristles altered the properties of the PEI backbone and its interaction with DNA, resulting in the compaction into shells instead of filled spheres. Our broader goal was to use the phenomenon as a platform for understanding why nature chose mannose to coat the surface of cells, particularly of viruses like HIV, Ebola, SARS, Dengue, and fungus like Cryptococcus neoformans which causes meningitis. In other words, studying how mannose modifies the biophysics of PEI and PEI-DNA interactions can also provide insight into the survival advantages conferred by a mannose coating on a pathogen.  What we found:  PEI has one of the simplest structures of a polymer. Yet modest changes in pH and salt induce large changes in its charge and clustering, independently. This finding is important because PEI is extensively used for transfecting DNA into cells, our findings suggest that transfection success is intricately dependent on how the compact-DNA solutions are prepared.  In the process of studying PEI we found that the ninhydrin assay used to estimating amine concentration actually estimates the concentration of unprotonated amines. This finding is important because ninhydrin assay is a workhorse for estimating protein concentration (from the amount of amines on the proteins) in research and industry. We found that attaching mannose to PEI changes the latter?s aggregation and pH profile. This finding is important because most proteins secreted by cells have mannose sugars on them, and the sugars could be modifying the interfacial properties of the proteins.  We found that two opposing mannose-coated surface can specifically self-latch to each other. Since mannose is found extensively on the surface of pathogens, the finding has implications for pathogen-pathogen interactions.  We found that a relatively large layer of bound water exists around a mannose layer, slowing down the approach of particles, but 'fracturing' when particles approach at high velocity. This finding has implications for the hydration and immune-recognition of pathogens, and therefore for the latter's survivability.  Additional findings on virus surfaces and DNA packaging are being compiled into manuscripts for dissemination.    The broader impacts of the project were:  1. Under-represented minority students got opportunities to apply classroom learning to solve problems at the interface of engineering and fundamental sciences, to think critically about testing methods and outcomes, and to quantify findings for effective communication. Via the research opportunities made available to five undergraduate student, skills critical for a superior STEM workforce were imparted.  2. . A graduate student did a PhD thesis at the nexus of engineering and biochemistry, leading to the exchange of thoughts and ideas between the engineering and medical colleges at Howard University.  3. The increased research capability enabled the PI to lead a team of undergraduate honor students to mentor middle-school students via science-engagement modules.  5. The research enterprise at Howard University was significantly increased both by the upgrade of an atomic force microscope, and by the lectures on bioengineering facilitated by the resulting research.       Last Modified: 06/05/2018       Submitted by: Preethi L Chandran]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
