<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Creating a Community of Scientists, Supporting PUI Faculty and Undergraduates at the American Society for Biochemistry and Molecular Biology National Meetings</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>04/15/2014</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>03/31/2015</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>15750.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>15750</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>08070400</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>BIO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>MCB</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Molecular and Cellular Bioscience</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Kamal Shukla</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The goal of this project is for the American Society for Biochemistry and Molecular Biology&lt;br/&gt;(ASBMB) to create a culture of inclusion and a sense of community for primarily undergraduate&lt;br/&gt;institution (PUI), Minority Serving Institution (MSI), and Community College (CC) faculty&lt;br/&gt;and undergraduates at the ASBMB Annual Meeting. This will be accomplished by increasing the&lt;br/&gt;visibility of high quality, outcome-oriented undergraduate research and by offering enrichment&lt;br/&gt;events for PUI, MSI and CC faculty and undergraduates throughout the meeting.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>04/08/2014</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>04/08/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.074</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1407433</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Joseph</FirstName>
<LastName>Provost</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>J</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Joseph J Provost</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>josephprovost@sandiego.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>7013061586</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000380838</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/08/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Regina</FirstName>
<LastName>Stevens-Truss</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Regina Stevens-Truss</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>Regina.Stevens-Truss@kzoo.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2402836600</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000581666</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/08/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Weiyi</FirstName>
<LastName>Zhao</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Weiyi Zhao</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>wzhao@asbmb.org</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>3016347145</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000530380</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/08/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Margaret</FirstName>
<LastName>Carroll</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>A</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Margaret A Carroll</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>margie@mec.cuny.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>3016347145</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000651837</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/08/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>American Society for Biochemistry and Molecular Biology</Name>
<CityName>Rockville</CityName>
<ZipCode>208523310</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2402836600</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>11200 Rockville Pike</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[Suite 302]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Maryland</StateName>
<StateCode>MD</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>08</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MD08</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>040553539</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>AMERICAN SOCIETY FOR BIOCHEMISTRY AND MOLECULAR BIOLOGY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>040553539</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[American Society for Biochemistry and Molecular Biology]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>MD</StateCode>
<ZipCode>208523110</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Maryland</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>08</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MD08</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1144</Code>
<Text>Molecular Biophysics</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1144</Code>
<Text>BIOMOLECULAR SYSTEMS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7465</Code>
<Text>NANOSCALE BIO CORE</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9178</Code>
<Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0114</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~15750</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The project was part of an ongoing process by the American Society for Biochemistry and Molecular Biology (ASBMB) to build a community for undergraduate science students and to improve society access for what has been considered less-traditional research faculty. Emphasis was placed on reaching out to those students and their STEM faculty from primarily undergraduate institutions (PUI), minority serving institutions (MSI) and community colleges (CC).This was a one-year pilot project that included a significant assessment component to determine the success of planned activities to better engage undergraduates and research faculty from PUI, MSI and CC within the ASBMB community at our annual meeting, which is held in conjunction with the Experimental Biology. To achieve these goals and foster a feeling of community at the ASBMB meeting, all undergraduates and PUI, MSI and CC faculty were invited to participate in a number of meeting activities. In addition, to further strengthen the perception of undergraduate researchers and &nbsp;PUI faculty as valued scientists within the ASBMB, &nbsp;all undergraduate students and PUI, MSI or CC faculty who submitted a research abstract were identified and screened as possible platform presenters for the various sessions of the meeting. Selected abstracts were forwarded, with ASBMB endorsement, to the various session Chairs for consideration. Finally a formal assessment was performed to determine the impact of these activities on building a community of research/biomedical scientists that is more inclusive of PUI research faculty and undergraduate science students.&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>A panel led by the PI and Co-PIs reviewed over 300 abstracts submitted by undergraduates or PUI faculty and forwarded those most appropriate (with an emphasis on NSF funded research) to the session Chairs for consideration as platform presentations and the abstracts of four PUI faculty and 10 undergraduates were selected and those individuals invited. This was significant given the small number of possible at-large slots each session organizer has available. &nbsp;It was also one of the highest numbers of platform presentations given by these non-traditional research presenters, who were not scientists affiliated with research intensive institutions. This project also devised and implemented three events to enrich the experiences of the students and PUI faculty at the meeting, and to enhance their connection to the larger scientific community. An &ldquo;orientation session&rdquo; for all undergraduate students was held at the start of the meeting and was attended by over 200 student participants and 30 faculty from various PUI, MSI or CC. &nbsp;A &ldquo;network developing&rdquo; initiative incorporated teams of students to interact, and created opportunities for PUI MSI and CC faculty to network via social events sponsored by the society's Minority Affairs Committee and the Undergraduate Affiliate Network. &nbsp;Lastly a &ldquo;career speed-dating&rdquo; event was held and well attended by over 150 undergraduates who had the opportunity to ask questions and get a quick overview of 12 different STEM professionals concerning their STEM career and the path they took to get there. Collectively, this project funded valuable activities at the annual ASBMB meeting that positively impacted over 200 students and PUI STEM faculty. &nbsp;Thorough assessment of the effectiveness of these activities on the goals of the project support the continued need for the ASBMB to devise and implement strategies that build a strong and more inclusive &ldquo;Community of Scientists&rdquo;. This will enable us to retain and broaden our membership, and contribute towards the national goal of sufficient numbers of diverse and well-qualified STEM professionals in the US workforce.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 05/05/2015<br>      Modified by: Joe&nb...]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The project was part of an ongoing process by the American Society for Biochemistry and Molecular Biology (ASBMB) to build a community for undergraduate science students and to improve society access for what has been considered less-traditional research faculty. Emphasis was placed on reaching out to those students and their STEM faculty from primarily undergraduate institutions (PUI), minority serving institutions (MSI) and community colleges (CC).This was a one-year pilot project that included a significant assessment component to determine the success of planned activities to better engage undergraduates and research faculty from PUI, MSI and CC within the ASBMB community at our annual meeting, which is held in conjunction with the Experimental Biology. To achieve these goals and foster a feeling of community at the ASBMB meeting, all undergraduates and PUI, MSI and CC faculty were invited to participate in a number of meeting activities. In addition, to further strengthen the perception of undergraduate researchers and  PUI faculty as valued scientists within the ASBMB,  all undergraduate students and PUI, MSI or CC faculty who submitted a research abstract were identified and screened as possible platform presenters for the various sessions of the meeting. Selected abstracts were forwarded, with ASBMB endorsement, to the various session Chairs for consideration. Finally a formal assessment was performed to determine the impact of these activities on building a community of research/biomedical scientists that is more inclusive of PUI research faculty and undergraduate science students.      A panel led by the PI and Co-PIs reviewed over 300 abstracts submitted by undergraduates or PUI faculty and forwarded those most appropriate (with an emphasis on NSF funded research) to the session Chairs for consideration as platform presentations and the abstracts of four PUI faculty and 10 undergraduates were selected and those individuals invited. This was significant given the small number of possible at-large slots each session organizer has available.  It was also one of the highest numbers of platform presentations given by these non-traditional research presenters, who were not scientists affiliated with research intensive institutions. This project also devised and implemented three events to enrich the experiences of the students and PUI faculty at the meeting, and to enhance their connection to the larger scientific community. An "orientation session" for all undergraduate students was held at the start of the meeting and was attended by over 200 student participants and 30 faculty from various PUI, MSI or CC.  A "network developing" initiative incorporated teams of students to interact, and created opportunities for PUI MSI and CC faculty to network via social events sponsored by the society's Minority Affairs Committee and the Undergraduate Affiliate Network.  Lastly a "career speed-dating" event was held and well attended by over 150 undergraduates who had the opportunity to ask questions and get a quick overview of 12 different STEM professionals concerning their STEM career and the path they took to get there. Collectively, this project funded valuable activities at the annual ASBMB meeting that positively impacted over 200 students and PUI STEM faculty.  Thorough assessment of the effectiveness of these activities on the goals of the project support the continued need for the ASBMB to devise and implement strategies that build a strong and more inclusive "Community of Scientists". This will enable us to retain and broaden our membership, and contribute towards the national goal of sufficient numbers of diverse and well-qualified STEM professionals in the US workforce.          Last Modified: 05/05/2015       Submitted by: Joe Provost]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
