<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Development of environment-controlled enclosures for the Network of Robotic Echelle Spectrographs</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/15/2014</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2016</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>61691.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>61691</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03020000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>AST</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Astronomical Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>James Neff</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>jneff@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922475</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>&lt;br/&gt;Just a few decades ago, scientists discovered the first planets around other stars.  Since then, it has become apparent that these "exoplanets" are very common in the universe, and a large catalog of them has been compiled.  Detailed followup study is generally difficult, owing to the faintness of their light, but is vital to understanding the exoplanets and their contribution to a chain of reasoning that ultimately bears on the question of how common life itself might be elsewhere in the universe.  Very specialized instrumentation is needed to study exoplanets thoroughly once they are detected, and the shortage of that instrumentation is a significant bottleneck addressed by the construction of the Las Cumbres Observatory Global Telescope (LCOGT), a worldwide network of primarily 1-meter telescopes.  LCOGT will be equipped, through recent NSF funding, with precise spectrographs appropriate to exoplanet study.  The current proposal addresses an improvement to the instrumentation in the form of a better enclosure that will be thermally controlled to allow optimum spectrographic precision to be achieved.  The prototype to be constructed will demonstrate an important element in overall system performance.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The LCOGT project addresses a specific recommendation of the ASTRO 2010 (decadal) report calling for making increased telescope time available to radial velocity (RV) exoplanet work, even if limiting precision were not improved from then-current levels.  LCOGT will roughly double the nationwide capacity for RV studies of exoplanets, and will allow accuracy of 3m/s in exposure times of less that an hour for stars brighter than V=12.  With its multiple locations, LCOGT provides a powerful combination of quantity and quality of data acquisition.  The ultimate LCOGT spectrographs are cross-dispersed echelles with resolving power R=53,000 and almost full wavelength coverage over 380-860 nm, designed for efficiency, stability, and ease of wavelength calibration.  The new enclosure design is called an "igloo", and is carefully insulated and temperature-controlled.  An RV accuracy of 3 m/s requires temperature control to +/- 1 C.  The NRES system will enable astronomers to characterize exoplanet candidate host stars, validate transiting companions, search for multiple planetary systems, and derive masses and orbital elements for a wide range of planets.  Candidates will be supplied by ground-based transit surveys, such as HATnet, SuperWASP, and Qatar, and from NASA's TESS mission.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The LCOGT project is active in education, operating an extensive program of student observing on their telescopes.  Numerous students from high-school to university seniors are employed as interns.  Designs developed for LCOGT are open-source, and science data are made available to the community.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Funding for this project is being provided by NSF's Division of Astronomical Sciences through its Advanced Technologies and Instrumentation program.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/21/2014</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>04/13/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1407666</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Timothy</FirstName>
<LastName>Brown</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Timothy Brown</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>tbrown@lcogt.net</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>3035254509</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000615178</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/21/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>John</FirstName>
<LastName>Hygelund</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>John Hygelund</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>johnh@lcogt.net</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>8058801600</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000612728</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/21/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate>04/13/2016</EndDate>
<RoleCode>Former Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Zachary</FirstName>
<LastName>Walker</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Zachary Walker</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>zwalker@lcogt.net</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>8058801600</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000657875</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/21/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate>07/13/2015</EndDate>
<RoleCode>Former Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Robert</FirstName>
<LastName>Siverd</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Robert Siverd</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>rsiverd@lcogt.net</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>8058801608</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000713346</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/13/2016</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Las Cumbres Observatory Global Telescope Network</Name>
<CityName>Goleta</CityName>
<ZipCode>931175575</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>8058801608</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>6740 Cortona Dr Suite 102</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>24</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CA24</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>128152035</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>LAS CUMBRES OBSERVATORY GLOBAL TELESCOPE NETWORK, INC.</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Las Cumbres Observatory Global Telescope Network]]></Name>
<CityName>Goleta</CityName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>931175575</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[6740 Cortona Drive]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>24</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CA24</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1218</Code>
<Text>ADVANCED TECHNOLOGIES &amp; INSTRM</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7697</Code>
<Text>INSTRUMENTATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0114</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~61691</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Las Cumbres Observatory (LCO) operates a worldwide network of professional, robotic, computer-controlled 1-meter telescopes. The individual sites, located in Hawaii, Texas, the Canary Islands, Tibet, Chile, South Africa, and Australia, are spread out in latitude and longitude in order to provide uninterrupted access to the night-time sky for cutting-edge science. Each of the existing telescopes is equipped with multiple cameras and numerous filters to measure and study visible light.</p> <p>With funding from the NSF, LCO is building and deploying a Network of Robotic Echelle Spectrographs (NRES) to 1-meter telescopes at up to six different sites. These high-resolution spectrographs are purpose-built to characterize stars (i.e., their temperature and composition) and discover new planets in orbit around them. Once available, NRES will be an invaluable resource to the astronomical community.</p> <p>In order to operate at the necessary precision, each spectrograph must reside in an exceptionally stable environment. The NRES Igloo (this grant) is a cost-effective enclosure that successfully meets our stringent pressure and temperature stability requirements (+/- 0.01 C temperature and +/- 0.02 mbar pressure) even under harsh external conditions. Providing this stability at low cost makes it a critical component in the delivery of cost-effective, high-precision spectra.</p> <p>Each Igloo enclosure is built from a refrigerated 20-foot shipping container. These containers are sturdy, inexpensive, and very well insulated, making them ideally suited to our application. We wall-mount a standard HVAC unit which is able to maintain temperature steady to about +/- 1 degree C. To further improve our temperature control, we erect a plastic &ldquo;tent&rdquo; structure in the middle of the igloo, effectively creating a separate room within the igloo. Airflow into and out of the tent is managed by a set of four computer-controlled, variable-speed fans affixed to the outside of the tent. The combined effect of the plastic barrier and active fan control is an air temperature steady to +/- 0.1 degree C inside the tent, a 10-fold improvement over what HVAC alone could do (and significantly better than expected). &nbsp;</p> <p>Each NRES spectrograph is housed inside a thick, multi-layer chamber that provides a high degree of insulation. The tent is erected around this spectrograph chamber, thereby immersing it in air of a steady temperature. This multi-stage approach to temperature regulation produces excellent results at a significantly lower cost than any other available option.&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 12/03/2016<br>      Modified by: Robert&nbsp;Siverd</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Images (<span id="selectedPhoto0">1</span> of <span class="totalNumber"></span>)           </div> <div class="galControls" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2016/1407666/1407666_10321711_1480782243233_igloo_interior--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2016/1407666/1407666_10321711_1480782243233_igloo_interior--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Igloo Interior"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2016/1407666/1407666_10321711_1480782243233_igloo_interior--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Igloo Interior"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">This photo, taken from the open doorway of the first completed NRES Igloo, shows the interior layout. The rectangular, clear plastic structure is the thermal "tent." The spectrograph optics reside inside a heavily insulated chamber (the silver half-cylinder) which sits inside the tent.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Robert Siverd</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Robert&nbsp;Siverd</div> <div class="imageTitle">Igloo Interior</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2016/1407666/1407666_10321711_1480781915324_dome_and_igloo--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2016/1407666/1407666_10321711_1480781915324_dome_and_igloo--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Dome and Igloo"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2016/1407666/1407666_10321711_1480781915324_dome_and_igloo--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Dome and Igloo"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">This photo shows the first completed igloo (right) alongside (and connected to) the telescope and dome. Prior to deployment, each igloo and spectrograph are tested using a telescope identical to those in our worldwide network.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Robert Siverd</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Robert&nbsp;Siverd</div> <div class="imageTitle">Dome and Igloo</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2016/1407666/1407666_10321711_1480783152787_network_map--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2016/1407666/1407666_10321711_1480783152787_network_map--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Las Cumbres Observatory Network Map"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2016/1407666/1407666_10321711_1480783152787_network_map--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Las Cumbres Observatory Network Map"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Las Cumbres Observatory (LCO) operates a worldwide network of robotic telescopes. The sites are distributed in latitude and logitude to provide us continuous access to the night-time sky in both the Northern and Southern hemispheres.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Las Cumbres Observatory</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyright owner is an institution with an existing agreement allowing use by NSF</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Robert&nbsp;Siverd</div> <div class="imageTitle">Las Cumbres Observatory Network Map</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Las Cumbres Observatory (LCO) operates a worldwide network of professional, robotic, computer-controlled 1-meter telescopes. The individual sites, located in Hawaii, Texas, the Canary Islands, Tibet, Chile, South Africa, and Australia, are spread out in latitude and longitude in order to provide uninterrupted access to the night-time sky for cutting-edge science. Each of the existing telescopes is equipped with multiple cameras and numerous filters to measure and study visible light.  With funding from the NSF, LCO is building and deploying a Network of Robotic Echelle Spectrographs (NRES) to 1-meter telescopes at up to six different sites. These high-resolution spectrographs are purpose-built to characterize stars (i.e., their temperature and composition) and discover new planets in orbit around them. Once available, NRES will be an invaluable resource to the astronomical community.  In order to operate at the necessary precision, each spectrograph must reside in an exceptionally stable environment. The NRES Igloo (this grant) is a cost-effective enclosure that successfully meets our stringent pressure and temperature stability requirements (+/- 0.01 C temperature and +/- 0.02 mbar pressure) even under harsh external conditions. Providing this stability at low cost makes it a critical component in the delivery of cost-effective, high-precision spectra.  Each Igloo enclosure is built from a refrigerated 20-foot shipping container. These containers are sturdy, inexpensive, and very well insulated, making them ideally suited to our application. We wall-mount a standard HVAC unit which is able to maintain temperature steady to about +/- 1 degree C. To further improve our temperature control, we erect a plastic "tent" structure in the middle of the igloo, effectively creating a separate room within the igloo. Airflow into and out of the tent is managed by a set of four computer-controlled, variable-speed fans affixed to the outside of the tent. The combined effect of the plastic barrier and active fan control is an air temperature steady to +/- 0.1 degree C inside the tent, a 10-fold improvement over what HVAC alone could do (and significantly better than expected).    Each NRES spectrograph is housed inside a thick, multi-layer chamber that provides a high degree of insulation. The tent is erected around this spectrograph chamber, thereby immersing it in air of a steady temperature. This multi-stage approach to temperature regulation produces excellent results at a significantly lower cost than any other available option.           Last Modified: 12/03/2016       Submitted by: Robert Siverd]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
