<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>DISSERTATION RESEARCH: Functional behavioral analysis of positively selected genes in Drosophila</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>06/01/2014</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>20254.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>20254</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>08010207</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>BIO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DEB</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Environmental Biology</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>George Gilchrist</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Behavioral isolation rapidly evolves between species, yet relatively little is known about the genetic basis of pre-mating reproductive isolation, particularly the role of behavioral genes involved in courtship.  This knowledge gap is important to fill since behavioral cues are generally species-specific and thought to evolve under strong selective pressures.  Using a combination of computational, genetic, and behavioral approaches, the researchers propose to address three main objectives: 1) to identify positively selected genes in the fruit fly, Drosophila melanogaster, that are not specifically expressed in the gonads, 2) to characterize the effects of reducing gene expression in adaptive genes on mating and aggression behavior, and 3) to characterize the adaptive genes involved in behavioral interactions by tissue and molecular function.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The proposed work will extend our understanding of the genetic bases of pre-mating reproductive barriers and their role in early species divergence. Data produced from this proposal will advance the training of students in the areas of genetics, bioinformatics, computational biology, and genomic analysis. Second, this project will implement high school curricula designed to expose students to new high-throughput methods in biology, along with applied hands-on experience using modern genetic and behavioral techniques. Third, the development of a portable high-throughput behavioral lab will be used to increase awareness and engagement in STEM fields to a broader non-scientific audience.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>03/26/2014</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>03/26/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.074</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1407006</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Rob</FirstName>
<LastName>Kulathinal</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>J</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Rob J Kulathinal</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>robkulathinal@temple.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2152040620</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000563441</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>03/26/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Craig</FirstName>
<LastName>Stanley, Jr.</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>E</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Craig E Stanley, Jr.</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>craig.stanley@temple.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2152047723</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000654957</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>03/26/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Temple University</Name>
<CityName>Philadelphia</CityName>
<ZipCode>191226003</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2157077547</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1801 N. Broad Street</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Pennsylvania</StateName>
<StateCode>PA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>PA02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>057123192</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>TEMPLE UNIVERSITY-OF THE COMMONWEALTH SYSTEM OF HIGHER EDUCATION</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>057123192</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Temple University]]></Name>
<CityName>Philadelphia</CityName>
<StateCode>PA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>191226078</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[1900 N. 12th Street]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Pennsylvania</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>PA02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7378</Code>
<Text>EVOLUTIONARY GENETICS</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9169</Code>
<Text>BIODIVERSITY AND ECOSYSTEM DYNAMICS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9179</Code>
<Text>GRADUATE INVOLVEMENT</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>EGCH</Code>
<Text>ENVIRONMENT AND GLOBAL CHANGE</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>SMET</Code>
<Text>SCIENCE, MATH, ENG &amp; TECH EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0114</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~20254</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Understanding the evolutionary processes that drive population divergence, functional diversity, and speciation has been a longstanding question in biology.&nbsp; It has been proposed that sexual selection, particularly mating behavior, is a major driver.&nbsp; Our project combined comparative functional genomics approaches with high-throughput ethomics to investigate the genetics of mating behavior divergence in the model organism, <em>Drosophila melanogaster</em>. &nbsp;Using the extensive genetic and genomic resources of Drosophila, we identified highly diverged and adapted candidate genes, and developed and applied a novel phenotyping assay for male-female interactions. &nbsp;Among highly diverged loci between populations, we found an enrichment of behavioral loci involved in various aspects of courtship behavior.&nbsp;</p> <p>The first phase of our project was to establish a set of aligned orthologs across 12 sequenced species of Drosophila (spanning almost 100 million years of evolution) to provide baseline estimates of selection across each protein-coding gene.&nbsp; Since previous genome- and genus-wide estimates were based on low-quality releases of assemblies and annotations, we developed an automated pipeline to extract new assemblies and gene models, align protein-coding sequences, and estimate evolutionary divergence, dN/dS, using multiple parameters and models.&nbsp; We published (in G3) this database resource, flyDIVaS (DIVergence and Selection in Drosophila, <a href="http://www.flydivas.info">www.flydivas.info</a>), made it publically available, and provided instructions for researchers studying any phyla of annotated genomes to create similar databases.</p> <p>Behavioral isolation is thought to be among the first stages in forming new species. Since our goal was to identify adapted candidate neuro-behavioral genes involved in early species divergence, we focused on estimates of dN/dS between the experimental model, <em>D. melanogaster</em>, and its closest well-assembled species, <em>D. simulans</em>.&nbsp; To identify candidates from incipient stages of population divergence, we compared available <em>D. melanogaster</em> genomes sequenced across global populations (Drosophila Genome Nexus) including a population from Zimbabwe exhibiting behavioral isolation with its neighboring populations.&nbsp; This Zimbabwean population represents one of the few naturally occurring examples of incipient speciation, providing an excellent model to study speciation at its earliest stage. &nbsp;We identified novel candidate genes involved in sexual isolation by scanning genomic regions for highly differentiated SNPs (significant Fst) between Zimbabwean, Zambian, and North American populations.&nbsp; We functionally assayed these genes using high-throughput behavioral arenas. &nbsp;Our top candidate gene, <em>fruitless</em>, revealed significantly reduced male-female interactions when the <em>fru</em> gene is knocked down in either females or males. &nbsp;This powerful combination of high-throughput genomics and ethomics is providing us with a detailed understanding of the evolutionary processes involved in population divergence and early species formation&nbsp;</p> <p>This project precipitated several other significant discoveries and outcomes.&nbsp; Our functional analysis of neurogenic genes in Drosophila uncovered a genome-wide pattern that neurogenic genes cover a disproportional fraction of the genome in all tested eukaryotes, with important implications to evolution and medicine.&nbsp; We published our new genomic hypothesis, &ldquo;Neurogenomics and the role of a large mutational target on rapid behavioral change&rdquo;, in BMC Biology Direct.&nbsp; Our comparative genomic analysis of populations also led us to discover genomic patterns of domestication among laboratory strains of <em>D. melanogaster</em> (Genomic signatures of domestication on neurogenetic genes in&nbsp;<em>Drosophila melanogaster</em>, published in BMC Evolutionary Biology).&nbsp; Our <em>D. simulans</em> &ndash; <em>D. melanogaster</em> genome alignment generated in this project is widely used by the Drosophila community (e.g., Drosophila Nexus, FlyBase).&nbsp; Finally, we are just about to submit a manuscript that shows pervasive adaptation of testes- and sperm-related genes between <em>D. melanogaster</em> and <em>D. simulans</em>, based on the same analyses that we performed on our neurogenetic candidates.</p> <p>Intellectual Merit: &nbsp;This project advances our understanding of the genomic architecture of courtship genes and the role of pre-mating reproductive barriers in early species divergence. &nbsp;We found an enrichment of neurogenic genes among the most highly differentiated loci between two divergent natural populations of <em>D. melanogaster</em>.&nbsp; We further developed and applied a high-throughput ethomic assay to functionally test RNAi knock-downs of candidate genes on male-female interactions in a high-throughput behavioral arena.&nbsp; We found significantly reduced levels of intersexual interactions, indicating their preferred role in early behavioral isolation.</p> <p>Broader Impacts:&nbsp; This project resulted in training of students in the areas of genetics, bioinformatics, and genomic analysis including eight undergraduates from different STEM fields, a Public School District of Philadelphia high school teacher and her class, a graduated Masters student, and a graduated doctoral student, Dr. Craig Stanley.&nbsp; This grant also facilitated the development of tested and published (in GSA-PREP) high school curricula geared to expose students to new high-throughput methods in biology, i.e., integrating genomics with ethomics, along with applied hands-on experience using modern genetic and behavioral techniques.&nbsp; Finally, as a direct result of this grant, we were able to develop, publish, and maintain a publically available database, flyDIVaS (www.flydivas.info), that provides the community with divergence and selection estimates across 12 species of Drosophila.&nbsp; This interactive website is well used by the research community and provides an entryway for students to study comparative genomic patterns.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 11/28/2017<br>      Modified by: Rob&nbsp;J&nbsp;Kulathinal</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Images (<span id="selectedPhoto0">1</span> of <span class="totalNumber"></span>)           </div> <div class="galControls" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1407006/1407006_10296101_1511871626222_ScreenShot2017-11-28at7.19.09AM--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1407006/1407006_10296101_1511871626222_ScreenShot2017-11-28at7.19.09AM--rgov-800width.jpg" title="flyDIVaS, A genome- and phyla-wide database of divergence and selection in Drosophila"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1407006/1407006_10296101_1511871626222_ScreenShot2017-11-28at7.19.09AM--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="flyDIVaS, A genome- and phyla-wide database of divergence and selection in Drosophila"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">As the basis of this study, we generated, published, and maintain a much-needed publicly available and interactive database that is used by the several communities of scientists, and students.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Rob Kulathinal</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Creative Commons</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Rob&nbsp;J&nbsp;Kulathinal</div> <div class="imageTitle">flyDIVaS, A genome- and phyla-wide database of divergence and selection in Drosophila</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1407006/1407006_10296101_1511872098813_ScreenShot2017-11-28at7.27.30AM--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1407006/1407006_10296101_1511872098813_ScreenShot2017-11-28at7.27.30AM--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Genome-wide divergence in behaviorally isolated populations"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1407006/1407006_10296101_1511872098813_ScreenShot2017-11-28at7.27.30AM--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Genome-wide divergence in behaviorally isolated populations"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Circos plot of adaptive neuro-behavioral candidate genes from diverging populations of D. melanogaster.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Rob Kulathinal</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Public Domain</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Rob&nbsp;J&nbsp;Kulathinal</div> <div class="imageTitle">Genome-wide divergence in behaviorally isolated populations</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1407006/1407006_10296101_1511872371439_ScreenShot2017-11-28at7.29.07AM--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1407006/1407006_10296101_1511872371439_ScreenShot2017-11-28at7.29.07AM--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Genome scan identifies highly differentiated candidate genes"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1407006/1407006_10296101_1511872371439_ScreenShot2017-11-28at7.29.07AM--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Genome scan identifies highly differentiated candidate genes"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">A genome-wide Fst scan between Zimbabwe and other D. melanogaster populations reveals our top two candidate genes, fruitless and clueless.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Rob Kulathinal</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Rob&nbsp;J&nbsp;Kulathinal</div> <div class="imageTitle">Genome scan identifies highly differentiated candidate genes</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1407006/1407006_10296101_1511872740760_ScreenShot2017-11-28at7.33.41AM--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1407006/1407006_10296101_1511872740760_ScreenShot2017-11-28at7.33.41AM--rgov-800width.jpg" title="High throughput ethomics on KD of top candidate, fru"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1407006/1407006_10296101_1511872740760_ScreenShot2017-11-28at7.33.41AM--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="High throughput ethomics on KD of top candidate, fru"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Reduction in male-female interactions from the RNAi knock-down of our top candidate gene, fruitless.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Rob Kulathinal</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Public Domain</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Rob&nbsp;J&nbsp;Kulathinal</div> <div class="imageTitle">High throughput ethomics on KD of top candidate, fru</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1407006/1407006_10296101_1511872942121_ScreenShot2017-11-28at7.41.42AM--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1407006/1407006_10296101_1511872942121_ScreenShot2017-11-28at7.41.42AM--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Neurogenomics and the large target effect"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1407006/1407006_10296101_1511872942121_ScreenShot2017-11-28at7.41.42AM--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Neurogenomics and the large target effect"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">A new neurogenomic hypothesis was the direct result of this study.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Rob Kulathinal</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Public Domain</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Rob&nbsp;J&nbsp;Kulathinal</div> <div class="imageTitle">Neurogenomics and the large target effect</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1407006/1407006_10296101_1511873072307_ScreenShot2017-11-28at7.43.52AM--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1407006/1407006_10296101_1511873072307_ScreenShot2017-11-28at7.43.52AM--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Functional adaptive landscape in D. melanogaster"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1407006/1407006_10296101_1511873072307_ScreenShot2017-11-28at7.43.52AM--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Functional adaptive landscape in D. melanogaster"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">The comprehensive functional genomic analysis generated from this study allowed us to survey the adaptive landscape of sperm-specific genes.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Rob Kulathinal</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Public Domain</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Rob&nbsp;J&nbsp;Kulathinal</div> <div class="imageTitle">Functional adaptive landscape in D. melanogaster</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Understanding the evolutionary processes that drive population divergence, functional diversity, and speciation has been a longstanding question in biology.  It has been proposed that sexual selection, particularly mating behavior, is a major driver.  Our project combined comparative functional genomics approaches with high-throughput ethomics to investigate the genetics of mating behavior divergence in the model organism, Drosophila melanogaster.  Using the extensive genetic and genomic resources of Drosophila, we identified highly diverged and adapted candidate genes, and developed and applied a novel phenotyping assay for male-female interactions.  Among highly diverged loci between populations, we found an enrichment of behavioral loci involved in various aspects of courtship behavior.   The first phase of our project was to establish a set of aligned orthologs across 12 sequenced species of Drosophila (spanning almost 100 million years of evolution) to provide baseline estimates of selection across each protein-coding gene.  Since previous genome- and genus-wide estimates were based on low-quality releases of assemblies and annotations, we developed an automated pipeline to extract new assemblies and gene models, align protein-coding sequences, and estimate evolutionary divergence, dN/dS, using multiple parameters and models.  We published (in G3) this database resource, flyDIVaS (DIVergence and Selection in Drosophila, www.flydivas.info), made it publically available, and provided instructions for researchers studying any phyla of annotated genomes to create similar databases.  Behavioral isolation is thought to be among the first stages in forming new species. Since our goal was to identify adapted candidate neuro-behavioral genes involved in early species divergence, we focused on estimates of dN/dS between the experimental model, D. melanogaster, and its closest well-assembled species, D. simulans.  To identify candidates from incipient stages of population divergence, we compared available D. melanogaster genomes sequenced across global populations (Drosophila Genome Nexus) including a population from Zimbabwe exhibiting behavioral isolation with its neighboring populations.  This Zimbabwean population represents one of the few naturally occurring examples of incipient speciation, providing an excellent model to study speciation at its earliest stage.  We identified novel candidate genes involved in sexual isolation by scanning genomic regions for highly differentiated SNPs (significant Fst) between Zimbabwean, Zambian, and North American populations.  We functionally assayed these genes using high-throughput behavioral arenas.  Our top candidate gene, fruitless, revealed significantly reduced male-female interactions when the fru gene is knocked down in either females or males.  This powerful combination of high-throughput genomics and ethomics is providing us with a detailed understanding of the evolutionary processes involved in population divergence and early species formation   This project precipitated several other significant discoveries and outcomes.  Our functional analysis of neurogenic genes in Drosophila uncovered a genome-wide pattern that neurogenic genes cover a disproportional fraction of the genome in all tested eukaryotes, with important implications to evolution and medicine.  We published our new genomic hypothesis, "Neurogenomics and the role of a large mutational target on rapid behavioral change", in BMC Biology Direct.  Our comparative genomic analysis of populations also led us to discover genomic patterns of domestication among laboratory strains of D. melanogaster (Genomic signatures of domestication on neurogenetic genes in Drosophila melanogaster, published in BMC Evolutionary Biology).  Our D. simulans &ndash; D. melanogaster genome alignment generated in this project is widely used by the Drosophila community (e.g., Drosophila Nexus, FlyBase).  Finally, we are just about to submit a manuscript that shows pervasive adaptation of testes- and sperm-related genes between D. melanogaster and D. simulans, based on the same analyses that we performed on our neurogenetic candidates.  Intellectual Merit:  This project advances our understanding of the genomic architecture of courtship genes and the role of pre-mating reproductive barriers in early species divergence.  We found an enrichment of neurogenic genes among the most highly differentiated loci between two divergent natural populations of D. melanogaster.  We further developed and applied a high-throughput ethomic assay to functionally test RNAi knock-downs of candidate genes on male-female interactions in a high-throughput behavioral arena.  We found significantly reduced levels of intersexual interactions, indicating their preferred role in early behavioral isolation.  Broader Impacts:  This project resulted in training of students in the areas of genetics, bioinformatics, and genomic analysis including eight undergraduates from different STEM fields, a Public School District of Philadelphia high school teacher and her class, a graduated Masters student, and a graduated doctoral student, Dr. Craig Stanley.  This grant also facilitated the development of tested and published (in GSA-PREP) high school curricula geared to expose students to new high-throughput methods in biology, i.e., integrating genomics with ethomics, along with applied hands-on experience using modern genetic and behavioral techniques.  Finally, as a direct result of this grant, we were able to develop, publish, and maintain a publically available database, flyDIVaS (www.flydivas.info), that provides the community with divergence and selection estimates across 12 species of Drosophila.  This interactive website is well used by the research community and provides an entryway for students to study comparative genomic patterns.          Last Modified: 11/28/2017       Submitted by: Rob J Kulathinal]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
