<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Heavy Ion Physics in ALICE at the LHC</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/15/2014</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>90000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>90000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03010000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>PHY</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Physics</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Allena K. Opper</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>aopper@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032928958</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>A major benefit to undergraduate students pursuing careers in Science, Technology, Engineering, and Math (STEM) disciplines, is the opportunity to experience first-hand the application of technology and scientific techniques in real world settings.  This project is part of a research program that studies heavy ion collisions within A Large Ion Collider Experiment (ALICE) at the European Organization for Nuclear Research (CERN).  The primary goal is to provide students with research experiences that stimulate an interest in science and technology, exposes them to techniques used in experimental high energy physics, allows the development of global relationships and prepares them for careers in science and technology.  The project on which the students will work has a focus centered on understanding the behavior of extremely dense matter, similar to that existing a fraction of a second after the Big Bang.  This is achieved by colliding atomic nuclei at very high energies and studying the remnants of these collisions using highly sophisticated detectors.  The students involved in this project will analyze the resulting sub-atomic particles generated by these collisions, and will contribute to the design of new detectors that will enable even more sensitive experiments in the future.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;As stated earlier, the focus of ALICE at CERN is to understand the behavior of matter at very high density, similar to the matter that existed a fraction a second after the Big Bang. This state of matter, consisting of a very hot and dense medium of quarks and gluons, is often referred to as a Quark Gluon Plasma (QGP). By colliding nuclei at very high energies it is possible to create a QGP in a controlled environment that facilitates the study of its properties. Chicago State University (CSU) students will investigate the flavor characteristics, specifically strangeness, of jets resulting from high-energy proton-proton and lead-lead collisions and their use as probes in the study of QGP formation.  In addition, CSU students will be involved in a research and development program devoted to the upgrade of ALICE sub-detectors, thereby participating in the hardware development of important components in the ALICE experiment.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Collaboration with a large international laboratory such as the Large Hadron Collider at CERN allows students to work with world-class scientists and "state of the art" technology, thus preparing them for STEM careers.   Additionally, a program such as this has the potential of creating a cadre of students who become ambassadors for STEM; students who demonstrate to their peers the benefits of pursuing careers in science, engineering, math and technology. Also, students who participate in this program may serve as mentors and role models for students of high school age and younger, thereby, contributing to the creation of a pipeline of students actively preparing for careers in STEM.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/08/2014</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/08/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1407051</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Austin</FirstName>
<LastName>Harton</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Austin Harton</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>aharton61@gmail.com</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>7739952847</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000585807</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/08/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Chicago State University</Name>
<CityName>Chicago</CityName>
<ZipCode>606281598</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>7739952400</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>9501 South King Drive</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Illinois</StateName>
<StateCode>IL</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>IL01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>108109182</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>CHICAGO STATE UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>108109182</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Chicago State University]]></Name>
<CityName>Chicago</CityName>
<StateCode>IL</StateCode>
<ZipCode>606281598</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[9501 South King Drive]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Illinois</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>IL01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1233</Code>
<Text>NUCLEAR STRUCTURE &amp; REACTIONS</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7621</Code>
<Text>PHYSICS-BROADEN PARTICIPATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0114</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~90000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>This grant has provided summer research experiences abroad for undergraduate students at Chicago State University.&nbsp; The ALICE experiment, which is devoted to heavy ion physics, located at the European Center for Nuclear Research (CERN) in Geneva, Switzerland, has been the center of the program.&nbsp;&nbsp; The program consists of students performing physics analysis using data obtained by the ALICE experiment, and on participating in detector upgrades for the ALICE experiment through hardware development, computer simulations and data analysis. The program is designed such that many of the students continue the research started at CERN at CSU during the academic year.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>At CERN, our research group has taken on shared responsibilities and duties that have contributed to the success of the ALICE experiment by performing shifts, data analysis, detector maintenance, detector calibrations, technical reviews reviews. We have been involved in the design, simulation, and prototype testing of the Fast Interacting Trigger (FIT) T0-Plus detector, which is an upgrade of the existing T0 detector in ALICE. We have studied the performance of the recently installed di-jet calorimeter (DCal) in simulations, and we are involved in two physics analysis topics. Our group proposed the study of the topology of the jets associated with the J/y decay, as a means to understand the production mechanisms of the J/y prompt and jet quenching in Pb-Pb collisions. In addition, we began an investigation of the production of strange particles in jets.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>As a result of the support provided by this grant along with others, Chicago State University has been very fortunate that over the last seven summers beginning in the summer of 2010, twenty of its students have had the opportunity to work with the ALICE experiment at CERN. This research and education program provides students with the opportunity to collaborate with R1 universities and research laboratories. They participate in a state of the art research program which engages them in physics analysis and hardware projects through which they have gained valuable experience and professional relationships. A large majorityof the students have presented their work at national conferences. All have found the experience at the LHC to be tremendously rewarding and one that stimulated a strong desire to continue their pursuit of careers in STEM.&nbsp;&nbsp; A large number of the students are actively pursuing careers in STEM related fields. Since the summer of 2014, the period of this grant, our group has involved nine students in research with eight of them coming from traditionally underrepresented groups. Of the nine students: three are in physics graduate school, one is in engineering graduate school, one is in math graduate school, one is a physics undergraduate and two are engineering undergraduates.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>In summary, this grant has provided undergraduate students pursuing STEM careers the opportunity to play a role in the application and development of &ldquo;state of the art&rdquo; scientific techniques and technology.&nbsp; In addition, they have had the opportunity to contribute to a major research project having global significance.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 06/29/2017<br>      Modified by: Austin&nbsp;Harton</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ This grant has provided summer research experiences abroad for undergraduate students at Chicago State University.  The ALICE experiment, which is devoted to heavy ion physics, located at the European Center for Nuclear Research (CERN) in Geneva, Switzerland, has been the center of the program.   The program consists of students performing physics analysis using data obtained by the ALICE experiment, and on participating in detector upgrades for the ALICE experiment through hardware development, computer simulations and data analysis. The program is designed such that many of the students continue the research started at CERN at CSU during the academic year.     At CERN, our research group has taken on shared responsibilities and duties that have contributed to the success of the ALICE experiment by performing shifts, data analysis, detector maintenance, detector calibrations, technical reviews reviews. We have been involved in the design, simulation, and prototype testing of the Fast Interacting Trigger (FIT) T0-Plus detector, which is an upgrade of the existing T0 detector in ALICE. We have studied the performance of the recently installed di-jet calorimeter (DCal) in simulations, and we are involved in two physics analysis topics. Our group proposed the study of the topology of the jets associated with the J/y decay, as a means to understand the production mechanisms of the J/y prompt and jet quenching in Pb-Pb collisions. In addition, we began an investigation of the production of strange particles in jets.     As a result of the support provided by this grant along with others, Chicago State University has been very fortunate that over the last seven summers beginning in the summer of 2010, twenty of its students have had the opportunity to work with the ALICE experiment at CERN. This research and education program provides students with the opportunity to collaborate with R1 universities and research laboratories. They participate in a state of the art research program which engages them in physics analysis and hardware projects through which they have gained valuable experience and professional relationships. A large majorityof the students have presented their work at national conferences. All have found the experience at the LHC to be tremendously rewarding and one that stimulated a strong desire to continue their pursuit of careers in STEM.   A large number of the students are actively pursuing careers in STEM related fields. Since the summer of 2014, the period of this grant, our group has involved nine students in research with eight of them coming from traditionally underrepresented groups. Of the nine students: three are in physics graduate school, one is in engineering graduate school, one is in math graduate school, one is a physics undergraduate and two are engineering undergraduates.     In summary, this grant has provided undergraduate students pursuing STEM careers the opportunity to play a role in the application and development of "state of the art" scientific techniques and technology.  In addition, they have had the opportunity to contribute to a major research project having global significance.       Last Modified: 06/29/2017       Submitted by: Austin Harton]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
