<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Development of Chiral Charge Density Wave Electronic Devices</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2014</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>360000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>360000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07010000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>ECCS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Electrical, Commun &amp; Cyber Sys</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Paul Lane</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>plane@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922453</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The goal of this proposal is to gain a fundamental understanding of the properties of chiral charge density wave systems and create new electronic devices exploiting unique advantages of the chiral state of the collective charge system. Understanding the nature of chiral charge density wave and learning how to manipulate chiral charge domains will be transformative to the condensed matter physics and it will open the doors to devices based on collective electron excitations. The main advantage of using collective charge systems for electronics is lower power dissipation at high device densities. The fundamental studies will involve both macroscopic and atomic scale investigations of the chiral charge density wave states in carefully engineered two-dimensional materials.&lt;br/&gt;The program will provide students and young researchers with necessary tools to carry out modern fundamental research in the fields of materials science, condensed matter physics and electronic device engineering. Since the designed research activities are highly interdisciplinary, the students will be stimulated to take classes across disciplines, such as nanoscience, electron and scanning probe microscopy and nanofabrication. The plan is to broaden participation and appreciation of students through (a) incorporating elements of the research in existing nanoscience, nano-electronics and solid-state physics courses at both the undergraduate and graduate level; (b) train students to use state of the art fabrication and characterization tools and (c) expose the students to research enterprise and collaborative research across different organizations. This work should lead to training a PhD student and several undergraduate students. Outreach to local area high schools through senior thesis work experience and science research clubs as well as College's open houses are part of the overreaching strategy to prepare high school students to pursue science and engineering degrees.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Chirality breaks down the spatial inversion symmetry and results in unexpected new electronic properties, in particular in systems with reduced dimensionality. In many cases the electronic chirality is facilitated by the specific structure of the system in which it emerges, either on atomic scale or on mesoscopic scale. Recently, it was discovered that one of the well-studied macroscopically correlated electronic state, the charge density wave, also exhibits chiral properties. This proposal explores the opportunity to use the nanometer-size domains of opposite chirality that are separated with domain walls as basic elements for memory and logic units.&lt;br/&gt;The goal of the research is to gain a fundamental understanding of the nature of the coupling of the chiral charge density waves with external perturbations, such as light, quasi static electric and magnetic fields with the aim of actively controlling and measuring the chiral state of individual charge density wave domains. Successful manipulation and read-out of the chiral state of individual several nanometer-size domains would enable utilization of the chiral charge systems in information storage and processing. To achieve this goal the investigators will synthesize single crystals of chiral charge density wave materials, conduct local scanning probe characterization as well as bulk characterization on both single crystal and exfoliated few layer crystals of dichalcogenides. Scanning tunneling microscopy on few-layer single crystals as well as coupling the light to the scanning tunneling microscopy junction will play important role in identifying practical regimes for chiral domain manipulation. &lt;br/&gt;The use of collective chiral states in electronic devices could dramatically extend the current down-scaling limit of complementary metal-oxide semiconductors that is set by the level of power dissipation in incoherent electron based devices. The fundamental studies will involve both macroscopic and atomic scale investigations of the chiral charge density wave states in carefully engineered two-dimensional materials, thus clearly exposing the complex mesoscopic physics that couples excitonic and charge density wave correlations</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/12/2014</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/12/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1408151</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Goran</FirstName>
<LastName>Karapetrov</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Goran Karapetrov</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>goran@drexel.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2155714090</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000587741</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/12/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Drexel University</Name>
<CityName>Philadelphia</CityName>
<ZipCode>191021119</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2158956342</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1505 Race St, 10th Floor</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Pennsylvania</StateName>
<StateCode>PA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>PA03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>002604817</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>DREXEL UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>002604817</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Drexel University]]></Name>
<CityName>Philadelphia</CityName>
<StateCode>PA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>191042737</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[3141 Chestnut Street]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Pennsylvania</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>PA03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1517</Code>
<Text>EPMD-ElectrnPhoton&amp;MagnDevices</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>100E</Code>
<Text>Novel devices &amp; vacuum electronics</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0114</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~360000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>In the framework of this project the group at Drexel University optimized the synthesis of high quality single crystals of TiSe2 and CuxTiSe2 with different doping concentrations of copper intercalant. Using variable temperature electrical transport characterization of bulk single crystals the full phase diagram of charge density wave transition temperature vs copper doping was established. By careful adjustment of chemical vapor transport reaction conditions, the TiSe2 single crystals were grown with extremely low defect densities which enabled the use of the crystals for fundamental studies of this dichalcogenides by Drexel group and their collaborators across US. Establishment of charge density wave incommensuration in CuxTiSe2 arising at copper intercalation concentrations coincident with the onset of superconductivity at around x=0.05 is one of the breakthroughs that was enabled by the high quality of single crystals.</p> <p>Variable temperature optical probe ultrafast spectroscopy studies of TiSe<sub>2</sub> and Cu<sub>x</sub>TiSe<sub>2</sub> and continuous wave Raman spectroscopy were performed within the project. Several groundbreaking results were established: first, it was found that there is a threshold laser intensity at which chalcogene vacancies start forming in TiSe2. This could have widespread implication on the dichalcogenides in general as materials for electronic applications. Second, pump probe optical spectroscopy investigation showed that the charge density wave in TiSe2 can be non-thermal melted, establishing an essential process for manipulating the chiral domain state in charge density wave. With this finding the role of exciton in forming the charge density wave was confirmed. Third, the relevant coherent oscillations in the transient reflectivity spectra established the phonon modes responsible for establishing the charge density wave. Overall, this project has resulted in new understanding of the mechanism of chiral charge density wave in semimetalic dichalcogenide TiSe2 that could have practical implication on devices based on chiral charge density wave.</p> <p>Detailed research results have been disseminated to the research community and are also accessible to the general public. This grant resulted in 5 publications in peer-reviewed journals, with 2 more in preparation. Research was also presented at 5 national and international conferences.</p> <p>This grant provided the primary support for education and training of one PhD students and partial support for undergraduate students. The graduate student defended his PhD and now works in the optoelectronics defense industry. The undergraduate student that participated in this project got his BS degree and is planning to pursue a PhD as well.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 11/13/2018<br>      Modified by: Goran&nbsp;Karapetrov</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Images (<span id="selectedPhoto0">1</span> of <span class="totalNumber"></span>)           </div> <div class="galControls" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1408151/1408151_10331685_1542082751607_Figure2--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1408151/1408151_10331685_1542082751607_Figure2--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Transient reflectivity change in CuxTiSe2"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1408151/1408151_10331685_1542082751607_Figure2--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Transient reflectivity change in CuxTiSe2"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">(a-d) Transient reflectivity change in optical density DOD for (a) normal/semimetalic phase, (b) metallic phase, (c)CDW phase, (d) non-thermally melted CDW state. (e,f) Fourier transforms of coherent A1g oscillations for the CDW (3K and 0.017 mJ/cm2) and normalphases (3K and a 0.9 mJ/cm2);</div> <div class="imageCredit">D.B. Lioi, R.D. Schaller, G.P. Wiederrecht, and G. Karapetrov</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Goran&nbsp;Karapetrov</div> <div class="imageTitle">Transient reflectivity change in CuxTiSe2</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1408151/1408151_10331685_1542082394519_Figure1--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1408151/1408151_10331685_1542082394519_Figure1--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Photon-induced selenium migration in TiSe2"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1408151/1408151_10331685_1542082394519_Figure1--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Photon-induced selenium migration in TiSe2"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Raman spectra of TiSe2 single crystal at different temperatures. Each spectrum is taken at a pristine location on thefreshly cleaved surface of TiSe2 single crystal. Clear onset of the laser damagethreshold is at around 355 K</div> <div class="imageCredit">D.B. Lioi, D.J. Gosztola, G.P. Wiederrecht, and G. Karapetrov</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Goran&nbsp;Karapetrov</div> <div class="imageTitle">Photon-induced selenium migration in TiSe2</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ In the framework of this project the group at Drexel University optimized the synthesis of high quality single crystals of TiSe2 and CuxTiSe2 with different doping concentrations of copper intercalant. Using variable temperature electrical transport characterization of bulk single crystals the full phase diagram of charge density wave transition temperature vs copper doping was established. By careful adjustment of chemical vapor transport reaction conditions, the TiSe2 single crystals were grown with extremely low defect densities which enabled the use of the crystals for fundamental studies of this dichalcogenides by Drexel group and their collaborators across US. Establishment of charge density wave incommensuration in CuxTiSe2 arising at copper intercalation concentrations coincident with the onset of superconductivity at around x=0.05 is one of the breakthroughs that was enabled by the high quality of single crystals.  Variable temperature optical probe ultrafast spectroscopy studies of TiSe2 and CuxTiSe2 and continuous wave Raman spectroscopy were performed within the project. Several groundbreaking results were established: first, it was found that there is a threshold laser intensity at which chalcogene vacancies start forming in TiSe2. This could have widespread implication on the dichalcogenides in general as materials for electronic applications. Second, pump probe optical spectroscopy investigation showed that the charge density wave in TiSe2 can be non-thermal melted, establishing an essential process for manipulating the chiral domain state in charge density wave. With this finding the role of exciton in forming the charge density wave was confirmed. Third, the relevant coherent oscillations in the transient reflectivity spectra established the phonon modes responsible for establishing the charge density wave. Overall, this project has resulted in new understanding of the mechanism of chiral charge density wave in semimetalic dichalcogenide TiSe2 that could have practical implication on devices based on chiral charge density wave.  Detailed research results have been disseminated to the research community and are also accessible to the general public. This grant resulted in 5 publications in peer-reviewed journals, with 2 more in preparation. Research was also presented at 5 national and international conferences.  This grant provided the primary support for education and training of one PhD students and partial support for undergraduate students. The graduate student defended his PhD and now works in the optoelectronics defense industry. The undergraduate student that participated in this project got his BS degree and is planning to pursue a PhD as well.          Last Modified: 11/13/2018       Submitted by: Goran Karapetrov]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
