<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>The Impact of European Contact on Native American Evolutionary History</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2014</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>10/31/2016</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>211666.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>211666</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>04010000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>SBE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>SMA</Abbreviation>
<LongName>SBE Off Of Multidisciplinary Activities</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Josie S. Welkom</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>jwelkom@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927376</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The objective of this Fellowship project is to investigate the impact of European contact (EC) on Native American genomic diversity by analyzing genome-wide diversity patterns in contemporary and ancient Native Americans from the southern US. Many genetic studies have investigated the origins and early history of Native Americans, but comparatively little attention has been given to recent evolutionary history and the impact that selection, migration, and genetic drift have had on Native American genomic diversity over the last five centuries. However, since European Contact, Native Americans have experienced repeated epidemics, demographic collapse, and genetic exchange (admixture) with non-native peoples. It is critical that we test whether and how each of these events reshaped the genetic structure of indigenous populations if we are to accurately reconstruct Native American evolutionary history and account for population genetic structure in other studies. In addition, this project provides research and training opportunities for a female Hispanic postdoctoral researcher to develop the technical and process skills necessary for her to succeed in science and in academia. The project also provides research experience and mentoring for students from underrepresented groups, including some from participating Native American communities. Additionally, this project formulates a community-based participatory research model for future genetic studies, and it integrates education and research through extensive outreach to indigenous communities.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;While some research suggests that admixture and the population collapse after EC influenced Native American genetic diversity, no study has fully assessed the genetic changes that occurred after EC. Existing datasets are insufficient for this purpose because few studies have examined genome-wide variation and relatively few pre-EC samples have been analyzed. Because of these limitations, we know remarkably little about the genetic makeup of Native American populations or about the genetic impact of European Contact. This project overcomes these deficiencies and has two major research goals: (1) assess the genomic diversity in pre-EC and contemporary (post-EC) Native North Americans, and (2) evaluate the genetic impact of EC by measuring the effects of post-EC demographic collapse, selection, and admixture. This project uses newly developed microarray and next-generation sequencing technologies and implement a novel comparative approach. The PI-team analyzes 629,443 genome-wide SNPs to evaluate diversity patterns in a post-EC population. They also analyze ~370,000 of the same SNPs in ancient DNA samples from pre-EC burial populations in the same geographic region to track changes in the Native American gene pool over time. This study focuses on contemporary and ancient populations from the southern US, where EC first occurred in North America. This project is designed to produce a dataset that is unprecedented in combining genome-wide coverage with population samples spanning a wide temporal range. With this dataset, it will become possible to measure the effects of drift, selection, and admixture following EC, providing the first comprehensive test of the hypothesis that EC reshaped the genetic structure of Native American populations. This project has the potential to transform our understanding of Native American genetic diversity and evolutionary history in the southern US, and improve our ability to account for current population genetic structure in disease association studies. It can also inform our understanding of how sociocultural change influences the human genome.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/02/2014</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/02/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.075</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1408876</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Deborah</FirstName>
<LastName>Bolnick</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Deborah Bolnick</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>deborah.bolnick@uconn.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5122897455</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000406794</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/02/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Aida</FirstName>
<LastName>Miro-Herrans</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Aida Miro-Herrans</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>amiroherrans@utexas.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5124716424</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000655782</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/02/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Texas at Austin</Name>
<CityName>Austin</CityName>
<ZipCode>787595316</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5124716424</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>3925 W Braker Lane, Ste 3.340</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Texas</StateName>
<StateCode>TX</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>10</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>TX10</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>170230239</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF TEXAS AT AUSTIN</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>042000273</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Texas at Austin]]></Name>
<CityName>Austin</CityName>
<StateCode>TX</StateCode>
<ZipCode>787121532</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[101 E. 27th Street, STE 5.300]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Texas</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>25</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>TX25</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>8208</Code>
<Text>SPRF-Broadening Participation</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0114</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~211666</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><strong><span style="text-decoration: underline;">Abstract:</span></strong></p> <p>Since European contact (EC) in 1492 AD, Native Americans have experienced severe demographic collapse and community restructuring, genetic exchange (admixture) with non-native peoples, and repeated epidemics. These events may have altered genetic patterns in the Americas, but no previous study has fully assessed the genomic changes that occurred after EC. This project evaluates whether and how each of these events reshaped the genetic structure of indigenous populations in the southern United States, the region where EC first occurred.</p> <p><strong>&nbsp;</strong></p> <p><strong><span style="text-decoration: underline;">Intellectual Merit</span></strong><strong>:</strong> This project investigated the recent evolutionary history of Native Americans. Using recent methodological advances in biotechnology, bioinformatics and statistics, this project assessed the genomic diversity present in contemporary Native North Americans to evaluate the impact of EC by investigating the effects of post-EC admixture, natural selection, and community restructuring on Native American genomic diversity. Through comparisons of genome-wide DNA data from contemporary Native American and non-Native American populations, the Fellow measured the impact of admixture on Native American populations. Analyses of Native American and Siberian whole genomes showed that the proportion and sources of admixture may have varied across different regions across North America. Samples from the southern U.S. showed that Native American communities in this region have experienced low levels of admixture with non-natives, particularly when compared to populations in northwest North America. Comparisons of genomic data among Native American populations identified genes associated with immune functions that may have been selected for in communities in the southern U.S. Analyses of mitochondrial DNA among the communities in the southern U.S. suggest that relocation history had a subtle but significant effect on contemporary genetic diversity patterns, but colonial history and more recent events restructuring communities have not erased the genetic signal of earlier connections. These patterns suggest that Native American cultural practices may have helped mitigate the effects of European contact to some degree.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p><strong><span style="text-decoration: underline;">Broader Impacts:</span></strong><strong>&nbsp; </strong>This project deepens our understanding of Native American genetic diversity and evolutionary history in the southern United States, and improves our ability to account for current genetic population structure in disease association studies. It also informs our understanding of how sociocultural change influences the human genome. Importantly, this project increased the participation of underrepresented groups in science. The project provided research and training opportunities for the Fellow, a female Hispanic post-doctoral researcher, to develop theoretical and technical skills critical for her success in science and academia. It also provided research experience and mentoring for students from underrepresented groups, including some from Native American communities. This project involved Native American community members throughout the different stages of the project and addressed questions important to the research participants. The results from this project addressed research participants&rsquo; interest in community relatedness by showing that genetic signals indicate pre-European contact connectivity between communities. This project enhanced community engagement in science and promoted continued collaboration with Native Americans. The Fellow also disseminated the findings of this project in academic and non-academic settings, including to the Native Americans involved in the project.&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 01/30/2017<br>      Modified by: Aida&nbsp;Miro-Herrans</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Abstract:  Since European contact (EC) in 1492 AD, Native Americans have experienced severe demographic collapse and community restructuring, genetic exchange (admixture) with non-native peoples, and repeated epidemics. These events may have altered genetic patterns in the Americas, but no previous study has fully assessed the genomic changes that occurred after EC. This project evaluates whether and how each of these events reshaped the genetic structure of indigenous populations in the southern United States, the region where EC first occurred.     Intellectual Merit: This project investigated the recent evolutionary history of Native Americans. Using recent methodological advances in biotechnology, bioinformatics and statistics, this project assessed the genomic diversity present in contemporary Native North Americans to evaluate the impact of EC by investigating the effects of post-EC admixture, natural selection, and community restructuring on Native American genomic diversity. Through comparisons of genome-wide DNA data from contemporary Native American and non-Native American populations, the Fellow measured the impact of admixture on Native American populations. Analyses of Native American and Siberian whole genomes showed that the proportion and sources of admixture may have varied across different regions across North America. Samples from the southern U.S. showed that Native American communities in this region have experienced low levels of admixture with non-natives, particularly when compared to populations in northwest North America. Comparisons of genomic data among Native American populations identified genes associated with immune functions that may have been selected for in communities in the southern U.S. Analyses of mitochondrial DNA among the communities in the southern U.S. suggest that relocation history had a subtle but significant effect on contemporary genetic diversity patterns, but colonial history and more recent events restructuring communities have not erased the genetic signal of earlier connections. These patterns suggest that Native American cultural practices may have helped mitigate the effects of European contact to some degree.     Broader Impacts:  This project deepens our understanding of Native American genetic diversity and evolutionary history in the southern United States, and improves our ability to account for current genetic population structure in disease association studies. It also informs our understanding of how sociocultural change influences the human genome. Importantly, this project increased the participation of underrepresented groups in science. The project provided research and training opportunities for the Fellow, a female Hispanic post-doctoral researcher, to develop theoretical and technical skills critical for her success in science and academia. It also provided research experience and mentoring for students from underrepresented groups, including some from Native American communities. This project involved Native American community members throughout the different stages of the project and addressed questions important to the research participants. The results from this project addressed research participants? interest in community relatedness by showing that genetic signals indicate pre-European contact connectivity between communities. This project enhanced community engagement in science and promoted continued collaboration with Native Americans. The Fellow also disseminated the findings of this project in academic and non-academic settings, including to the Native Americans involved in the project.           Last Modified: 01/30/2017       Submitted by: Aida Miro-Herrans]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
