<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Doctoral Dissertation Research: Statistical Rating Organizations and Institutional Isomorphism</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2014</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2015</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>5569.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>5569</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>04050000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>SBE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>SES</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Divn Of Social and Economic Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Patricia White</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The proposed research examines the extent to which major corporate bond rating agencies, as gatekeepers to corporate investment capital, promote the adoption of normative practices to firms through the bond rating process.  According to new-institutional theories, when facing uncertainty, institutional notions about best practices often guide organizational behavior rather than rational calculations based on economic efficiency.  The high level of uncertainty present in the bond rating industry and the lack of accountability that comes from the few rating agencies creates an environment in which institutional notions about best practices potentially inform rating decisions.  &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The project focuses on quantitative analysis of firm ratings. I hypothesize that those firms engaging in normative behaviors (e.g. using popular forms of financial reporting, engaging in typical levels of product diversification, etc.) will be rewarded with higher credit ratings.  I utilize regression modeling to predict firm credit rating as a function of engaging in normative behaviors.  I further test whether or not engaging in the normative behaviors promoted by major bond rating agencies is in fact a good predictor of firm health or default.  This research will make contributions to the existing organizational literature in sociology.  By examining the extent to which bond rating agencies perpetuate institutionalized best practices, it tests theories of institutional isomorphism that claim industry norms often trump economically rational behavior in organizational fields. If theories of legitimacy can be used to explain some of the variance in credit ratings, we will gain a better understanding of how economic processes that appear irrational from a neoclassical economic perspective continue to exist. Also, through the content analysis of publicly available rating documents, this research directly observes a mechanism driving institutional isomorphism by analyzing the means through which rating agencies communicate appropriate behaviors to corporate bond issuers.  &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This research will contribute to broader society by examining the ways in which the existing bond rating sector, and by extension the entire securities rating sector, might be prone to systemic risk.  This research examines an understudied group of powerful social actors who influence the resources of major global corporations.  By illuminating details of the existing securities rating industry, this research will provide insight that will help to more broadly understand credit systems.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/29/2014</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/29/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.075</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1408572</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Robert</FirstName>
<LastName>Hanneman</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>A</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Robert A Hanneman</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>robert.hanneman@ucr.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>9518273638</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000340057</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/29/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Jacob</FirstName>
<LastName>Apkarian</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Jacob Apkarian</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>japka001@ucr.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>9518275535</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000654111</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/29/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of California-Riverside</Name>
<CityName>RIVERSIDE</CityName>
<ZipCode>925210217</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>9518275535</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>Research &amp; Economic Development</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[245 University Office Building]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>44</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CA44</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>627797426</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>REGENTS OF THE UNIVERSITY OF CALIFORNIA AT RIVERSIDE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>071549000</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of California-Riverside]]></Name>
<CityName>Riverside</CityName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>925210001</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[200 University Office Building]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>41</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CA41</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1331</Code>
<Text>Sociology</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9179</Code>
<Text>GRADUATE INVOLVEMENT</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>SMET</Code>
<Text>SCIENCE, MATH, ENG &amp; TECH EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0114</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~5569</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>This research studied the logic models of corporate credit rating used by major bond rating agencies.&nbsp; Though the firm financial health indicators used to assign ratings (e.g. liquidity, leverage, profitability) are significant predictors of future firm default, multilevel probit models demonstrated that other factors (shareholder return, specialization, financialization, firm size) used to generate corporate bond ratings are not empirically tied to firm default over the last decade.&nbsp; This suggests that models of credit rating might be influenced by institutional myths about credit risk factors.&nbsp; If this is the case, current models should be revised and the industry itself might need to undergo substantive changes.&nbsp;</p> <p>Major securities rating agencies are currently facing scrutiny from the media and world governments for their role in the economic crisis of 2008.&nbsp; However, the spotlight has focused on individual instances of malfeasance as the cause for concern.&nbsp; This research takes a structural approach and examines how myths about credit risk might be informing the ratings process.&nbsp; Inaccuracies in securities ratings can lead to systemic risk which is evidenced by the collapse of the mortgage backed securities (MBS) market in 2008, the dot-com bubble in the early 2000s, the Asian financial crisis of the late 1990s, and potentially other global credit events.&nbsp; While it appears that some rating agents were involved in deceptive self-interested behavior by rating certain securities lower risk than they actually were (Taibbi, 2013), many others likely followed institutional myths in the mortgage rating industry creating an abundance of inaccurately rated securities that led to the credit crisis.&nbsp; This research appears to provide evidence that there are industry level issues with the way that securities ratings are being produced and that major changes might be in order above and beyond the increase in SEC monitoring proposed by the Dodd-Frank act.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 09/19/2015<br>      Modified by: Jacob&nbsp;Apkarian</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ This research studied the logic models of corporate credit rating used by major bond rating agencies.  Though the firm financial health indicators used to assign ratings (e.g. liquidity, leverage, profitability) are significant predictors of future firm default, multilevel probit models demonstrated that other factors (shareholder return, specialization, financialization, firm size) used to generate corporate bond ratings are not empirically tied to firm default over the last decade.  This suggests that models of credit rating might be influenced by institutional myths about credit risk factors.  If this is the case, current models should be revised and the industry itself might need to undergo substantive changes.   Major securities rating agencies are currently facing scrutiny from the media and world governments for their role in the economic crisis of 2008.  However, the spotlight has focused on individual instances of malfeasance as the cause for concern.  This research takes a structural approach and examines how myths about credit risk might be informing the ratings process.  Inaccuracies in securities ratings can lead to systemic risk which is evidenced by the collapse of the mortgage backed securities (MBS) market in 2008, the dot-com bubble in the early 2000s, the Asian financial crisis of the late 1990s, and potentially other global credit events.  While it appears that some rating agents were involved in deceptive self-interested behavior by rating certain securities lower risk than they actually were (Taibbi, 2013), many others likely followed institutional myths in the mortgage rating industry creating an abundance of inaccurately rated securities that led to the credit crisis.  This research appears to provide evidence that there are industry level issues with the way that securities ratings are being produced and that major changes might be in order above and beyond the increase in SEC monitoring proposed by the Dodd-Frank act.       Last Modified: 09/19/2015       Submitted by: Jacob Apkarian]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
