<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Doctoral Dissertation Research: Market Logic in Higher Education</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/15/2014</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2015</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>11996.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>11996</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>04050000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>SBE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>SES</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Divn Of Social and Economic Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Patricia White</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>In the past decade, significant attention has been afforded to the market-based behavior of for-profit universities.  This project considers which organizations choose to pursue this logic. This study poses questions at both the organizational and individual level. First, the macro query of "How and why did particular organizations give greater attention to a market-based strategy of higher education?" is considered. Then, at the individual level, "What effects or consequences did changes in attention to market pressures have on individuals within the organizations and how did they navigate the organizational change?" This dissertation makes  significant intellectual contributions.  Higher education researchers have primarily given attention to revenue streams available to large state or elite universities with the research or philanthropic means to secure market types of funding. In contrast, this study examines the college or university that has one dominant source of revenue: student enrollments. More specifically, the project shifts the focus of the study of colleges from belief systems to behavior and highlights how the institutional logic of belief interacts with other organizational logics, such as the market, state, or professions.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;To answer these questions, this research employs a comparative case study design that examines data across eight institutions. This project relies on publicly available data such as course catalogs, alumni magazines, and IPEDS financial data, as well as employee interviews. This project focuses on important developments that continue to unfold in American education and American society - the rapid expansion of market logic. It contributes to the understanding of organizational responses to market pressures, a phenomenon that applies to almost every organization.  Given that this study focuses on the dependence of broad access schools and their reliance on tuition revenue, it will offer important insights into financing of higher education, including investment of individual resources as well as the financial aid programs.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/11/2014</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/11/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.075</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1409364</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Josipa</FirstName>
<LastName>Roksa</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Josipa Roksa</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>jroksa@virginia.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>4349246528</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000557559</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/11/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Joshua</FirstName>
<LastName>Brown</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>T</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Joshua T Brown</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>jtb8n@virginia.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>4349244270</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000653477</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/11/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Virginia Main Campus</Name>
<CityName>CHARLOTTESVILLE</CityName>
<ZipCode>229044195</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>4349244270</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>P.O.  BOX 400195</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Virginia</StateName>
<StateCode>VA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>VA05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>065391526</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>RECTOR &amp; VISITORS OF THE UNIVERSITY OF VIRGINIA</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>065391526</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Virginia Main Campus]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>VA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>229044195</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Virginia</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>VA05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1331</Code>
<Text>Sociology</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9179</Code>
<Text>GRADUATE INVOLVEMENT</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>SMET</Code>
<Text>SCIENCE, MATH, ENG &amp; TECH EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0114</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~11996</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Joshua Brown has completed the data collection for his dissertation &ldquo;The Market Logic in Higher Education&rdquo; which was supported by the National Science Foundation Doctoral Dissertation Improvement Grant.&nbsp; Brown was interested in understanding how and why do religious postsecondary institutions that primarily depend on enrollments differ in their adoption of market-based strategies.&nbsp; During the funding period, he conducted one-week site visits at eight different private postsecondary institutions in the United States, four Catholic and four Protestant.&nbsp;</p> <p>The NSF Dissertation Improvement Grant provided Brown with the necessary funding for travel and lodging to complete university site visits in eight different states. The data collection effort was successful: Brown visited each of the eight sites and conducted interviews with senior management and faculty members.&nbsp; By the conclusion of the data collection Brown had conducted a total of 151 interviews with employees at varying levels of the eight postsecondary institutions.</p> <p>The site visits and interviews Brown conducted allow for an analysis of organizations informed by cultural data unique to each organization that complement the publicly available data this project also relies on (course catalogs, alumni magazines, IRS 990 forms, and IPEDS financial data).&nbsp; To be completed in 2016, the dissertation will offer important insights to the literature on higher education and religious education.&nbsp; Moreover, it will inform public debates about funding of higher education, particularly for institutions that are heavily dependent on enrollments and thus tuition revenue.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 09/01/2015<br>      Modified by: Joshua&nbsp;T&nbsp;Brown</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Joshua Brown has completed the data collection for his dissertation "The Market Logic in Higher Education" which was supported by the National Science Foundation Doctoral Dissertation Improvement Grant.  Brown was interested in understanding how and why do religious postsecondary institutions that primarily depend on enrollments differ in their adoption of market-based strategies.  During the funding period, he conducted one-week site visits at eight different private postsecondary institutions in the United States, four Catholic and four Protestant.   The NSF Dissertation Improvement Grant provided Brown with the necessary funding for travel and lodging to complete university site visits in eight different states. The data collection effort was successful: Brown visited each of the eight sites and conducted interviews with senior management and faculty members.  By the conclusion of the data collection Brown had conducted a total of 151 interviews with employees at varying levels of the eight postsecondary institutions.  The site visits and interviews Brown conducted allow for an analysis of organizations informed by cultural data unique to each organization that complement the publicly available data this project also relies on (course catalogs, alumni magazines, IRS 990 forms, and IPEDS financial data).  To be completed in 2016, the dissertation will offer important insights to the literature on higher education and religious education.  Moreover, it will inform public debates about funding of higher education, particularly for institutions that are heavily dependent on enrollments and thus tuition revenue.       Last Modified: 09/01/2015       Submitted by: Joshua T Brown]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
