<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Nanoscale Imaging of Topological Superconductivity in Heterostructures</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2014</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>405835.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>405835</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03070000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DMR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Materials Research</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Tomasz Durakiewicz</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>tdurakie@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924892</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Non technical Abstract: &lt;br/&gt;In addition to their well-known negative electric charge, electrons carry a second property called "spin", akin to an axis of rotation which may point in any direction. An ideal topological insulator (TI) is a material whose interior is electrically insulating, but whose surface is a special metal where electron spins are prevented from backscattering, removing the primary source of unwanted heating in today's microelectronics. These surface properties make TIs promising candidates to enable two transformative future technologies: "spintronics," a very low power replacement for conventional electronics, and "quantum computing," a completely new method for rapidly solving computationally intensive problems. However, the first generation of topological materials, discovered over the last 5 years, has suffered from unwanted "leakage" of electrons through their interiors, which undermines their promising surface properties.  This award supports two parallel sets of experiments aimed at discovering perfect topological insulators and at engineering the interfaces between topological and other materials which are predicted to enable quantum computing applications. The experiments combine two advanced atomic-scale material synthesis and characterization techniques: molecular beam epitaxy and scanning tunneling microscopy. A fundamental advancement of the understanding and utility of topological insulators towards spintronics and quantum computing would be expected from this project. This award also supports the education and training of one postdoctoral fellow and one graduate student. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Technical Abstract:&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;An ideal topological insulator (TI) is a material with an insulating bulk, but a topologically protected conducting surface state on which spin-polarized electrons are prevented from backscattering. These properties make TIs promising candidates to enable two transformative future technologies: "spintronics," which may circumvent the severe power dissipation problems now limiting conventional electronics, and "topological quantum computing," which provides an alternative to the short decoherence times in the best present-day qubits. However, the highly-studied first-generation Bi2X3 topological "insulators" suffer from unwanted bulk conduction due to apparently unavoidable self-doping.  This award supports two parallel experimental approaches to circumvent these challenges. One is to use scanning tunneling microscopy (STM) to search for topological surface states on true bulk insulators, such as topological Kondo insulators. The parallel approach is to engineer topological semimetal antimony-superconductor heterostructures using a combined molecular beam epitaxy and STM system, with guidance from density functional theory calculations. The significance of this approach lies in the first achievement and study of topological p-wave superconductivity, which would have high impact on the field of unconventional superconductors more broadly and also provide a playground for the eventual search for the Majorana fermion at the heart of topological quantum computing applications. The award also supports the education and training of one postdoctoral fellow and one graduate student in advanced material synthesis and characterization techniques.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/23/2014</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/15/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1410480</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Jennifer</FirstName>
<LastName>Hoffman</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>E</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Jennifer E Hoffman</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>jhoffman@physics.harvard.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6174953734</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000120713</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/23/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Harvard University</Name>
<CityName>Cambridge</CityName>
<ZipCode>021385369</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6174955501</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1033 MASSACHUSETTS AVE</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[5th Floor]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
<StateCode>MA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MA05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>082359691</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>PRESIDENT AND FELLOWS OF HARVARD COLLEGE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>001963263</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Harvard University]]></Name>
<CityName>Cambridge</CityName>
<StateCode>MA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>021382933</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[17 Oxford Street]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MA05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1710</Code>
<Text>CONDENSED MATTER PHYSICS</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7237</Code>
<Text>NANO NON-SOLIC SCI &amp; ENG AWD</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0114</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0115</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0116</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~150000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2015~143267</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2016~112568</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The last decade has seen the discovery and initial exploration of a new family of materials with exotic properties that arise from the topology of their electron states. The key is that the bulk (interior) of the material is an insulator, whose topology requires that the surface is a conductor. Furthermore, the conducting surface electrons have a strict relationship between their momentum (direction of travel) and their spin (magnetic direction). A number of applications have been proposed for such &ldquo;topological materials&rdquo;. One promising pathway is to couple a topological material with a superconductor &ndash; a material that conducts electricity without loss at low temperatures. A topological superconductor can host a Majorana fermion, that could be useful in robust quantum computing. Another promising pathway is to couple a topological material with a magnetic material to achieve the quantum anomalous Hall (QAH) effect &ndash; electrical conductivity only at specific, discrete intervals. In theory, with the right kind of magnetism, QAH&nbsp; could enables lossless electrical conductivity up to room temperature.</p> <p>Our outcomes contribute to both pathways. Under the support of NSF grant DMR-14104800, we improved growth of topological superconducting FeTe on monolayer FeSe/SrTiO<sub>3</sub>, we performed spectroscopic studies of topological Sb<sub>2</sub>Te<sub>3</sub> doped with magnetic vanadium (V), and we explored low temperature magnetism in the topological Kondo insulator SmB<sub>6</sub>.</p> <p>Initial theoretical calculations in 2010 predicted that vanadium doping in Sb<sub>2</sub>Te<sub>3</sub> would short the insulating bulk of the topological materials, which would make it impossible to observe the QAH effect. However, the QAH effect was observed experimentally in V-doped Sb<sub>2</sub>Te<sub>3</sub> in 2013, although only at unexpectedly low temperature. Our atomic-resolution images clarified the energy of V impurity states and their interaction with the conducting surface states, and also measured the thickness of the conducting surface state to be less than 1 nm.</p> <p>We found that in the topological Kondo insulator SmB<sub>6</sub>, even nominally nonmagnetic defects, such as missing Sm atoms, can induce low temperature magnetism and scatter the topological surface states (i.e. alter the relationship between their momentum and spin). This finding opens a new way to couple topological phases with magnetic phases. By controllably introducing vacancies or other nonmagnetic impurities in SmB<sub>6</sub>, intrinsic magnetism can emerge and thus SmB<sub>6</sub> could be a robust substrate for a topological superconductor heterostructure.</p> <p>In addition, the NSF support contributed to the training of one undergraduate, five graduate students, and four postdoctoral fellows throughout the 3-year duration of the grant.&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 12/28/2017<br>      Modified by: Jennifer&nbsp;E&nbsp;Hoffman</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Images (<span id="selectedPhoto0">1</span> of <span class="totalNumber"></span>)           </div> <div class="galControls" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1410480/1410480_10337240_1514488425681_Hoffman-DMR-1410480-VSb2Te3--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1410480/1410480_10337240_1514488425681_Hoffman-DMR-1410480-VSb2Te3--rgov-800width.jpg" title="single vanadium atoms in Sb2Te3"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1410480/1410480_10337240_1514488425681_Hoffman-DMR-1410480-VSb2Te3--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="single vanadium atoms in Sb2Te3"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Figure 1: (A, B) Scanning tunneling microscope images of single vanadium atom impurities in the top layer and next-to-top layer of the topological material Sb2Te3. The images are 4 nm x 4nm. (C, D) Theoretical calculations of V atoms in Sb2Te3. The excellent match between theory and experiment suppo</div> <div class="imageCredit">Pengcheng Chen, Shiang Fang</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Jennifer&nbsp;E&nbsp;Hoffman</div> <div class="imageTitle">single vanadium atoms in Sb2Te3</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1410480/1410480_10337240_1514489156590_Hoffman-DMR-1410480-SmB6--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1410480/1410480_10337240_1514489156590_Hoffman-DMR-1410480-SmB6--rgov-800width.jpg" title="electron surface states on topological SmB6"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1410480/1410480_10337240_1514489156590_Hoffman-DMR-1410480-SmB6--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="electron surface states on topological SmB6"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Figure 2: (A) Atomically-resolved scanning tunneling microscope images of the topological Kondo insulator SmB6. The 4 layers show the waves of electrons scattering off of single-atom defects at different energies. (B) The relation between the energy and momentum of the conducting surface electrons.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Harry Pirie, Mohammad Hamidian</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Jennifer&nbsp;E&nbsp;Hoffman</div> <div class="imageTitle">electron surface states on topological SmB6</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The last decade has seen the discovery and initial exploration of a new family of materials with exotic properties that arise from the topology of their electron states. The key is that the bulk (interior) of the material is an insulator, whose topology requires that the surface is a conductor. Furthermore, the conducting surface electrons have a strict relationship between their momentum (direction of travel) and their spin (magnetic direction). A number of applications have been proposed for such "topological materials". One promising pathway is to couple a topological material with a superconductor &ndash; a material that conducts electricity without loss at low temperatures. A topological superconductor can host a Majorana fermion, that could be useful in robust quantum computing. Another promising pathway is to couple a topological material with a magnetic material to achieve the quantum anomalous Hall (QAH) effect &ndash; electrical conductivity only at specific, discrete intervals. In theory, with the right kind of magnetism, QAH  could enables lossless electrical conductivity up to room temperature.  Our outcomes contribute to both pathways. Under the support of NSF grant DMR-14104800, we improved growth of topological superconducting FeTe on monolayer FeSe/SrTiO3, we performed spectroscopic studies of topological Sb2Te3 doped with magnetic vanadium (V), and we explored low temperature magnetism in the topological Kondo insulator SmB6.  Initial theoretical calculations in 2010 predicted that vanadium doping in Sb2Te3 would short the insulating bulk of the topological materials, which would make it impossible to observe the QAH effect. However, the QAH effect was observed experimentally in V-doped Sb2Te3 in 2013, although only at unexpectedly low temperature. Our atomic-resolution images clarified the energy of V impurity states and their interaction with the conducting surface states, and also measured the thickness of the conducting surface state to be less than 1 nm.  We found that in the topological Kondo insulator SmB6, even nominally nonmagnetic defects, such as missing Sm atoms, can induce low temperature magnetism and scatter the topological surface states (i.e. alter the relationship between their momentum and spin). This finding opens a new way to couple topological phases with magnetic phases. By controllably introducing vacancies or other nonmagnetic impurities in SmB6, intrinsic magnetism can emerge and thus SmB6 could be a robust substrate for a topological superconductor heterostructure.  In addition, the NSF support contributed to the training of one undergraduate, five graduate students, and four postdoctoral fellows throughout the 3-year duration of the grant.           Last Modified: 12/28/2017       Submitted by: Jennifer E Hoffman]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
