<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Collaborative Research: Overproduction and Harvesting of Methylated Triterpenes in a Heterologous Host</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>12/01/2014</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>11/30/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>90000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>102000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03090000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CHE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Chemistry</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Robin McCarley</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>rmccarle@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927514</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>In the face of dwindling fossil fuel reserves, a high priority has been placed on the development of strategies capable of producing viable replacements for transportation fuels from renewable resources. Even with a dramatic recent increase in domestic natural gas production in the U.S., renewable fuels remain a priority for countries that lack comparable natural resources, and thus represent a potential area for growth for U.S. biotechnology. The challenges associated with accomplishing this task are extensive, and success in this endeavor ultimately depends upon the ability to generate a good yield of a target molecule in a biological source and an efficient isolation and recovery of the molecule from the source.  The focus of this proposal will be twofold: 1) the production of a fuel-like compound in a bacterial host, and 2) the design, screening, and implementation of biocompatible materials to efficiently isolate the compound from the bacteria.  As a proposal from a predominantly undergraduate institution, this collaborative approach to an immediate and relevant alternative energy source will help catalyze the development of an undergraduate research program in chemistry at the interface with biology at Dixie State University (DSU), located in the remote southwest corner of Utah. This rural community is comprised of students with diverse backgrounds who, through the proposed research plans, will engage in collaborations with established programs at complementary universities. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;With this award, the Chemistry of Life Processes Program in the Chemistry Division and NSF-EPSCoR are funding Drs. Rico Del Sesto (Dixie State University, Utah), Blaine Pfeifer (Univ. Buffalo, NY) and Andrew Koppisch (Northern Arizona Univ.) to address the issues above through multiple approaches. First, new extractants will be synthesized for the purpose of efficient sequestration of biofuel products from biological host systems. The extractants to be produced will be applicable to any host generating relevant isoprenoid compounds, but they will particularly be utilized in this proposal with a heterologous production platform. The known biosynthetic pathway for C32-botryococcene will be transplanted into E. coli. In particular, the proposed E. coli host has been engineered to support high-level production of isoprenoid compounds (reaching g/L levels of the Taxol precursor taxadiene). Furthermore, the new heterologous system will be subjected to a range of readily-available engineering and characterization strategies to optimize production of C32-botryococcene. The overall production process will therefore be complemented by a heterologous production host, and the novel introduction of extraction techniques. In addition to a clear applied goal of high level C32-botryococcene production through E. coli, the proposed plan is dedicated to fundamental knowledge of isoprenoid biosynthesis, extractant synthesis and extraction potential, and the cellular-extractant dynamic that is crucial for the success of this application. As such, the proposal features both science and engineering towards a meaningful and timely problem. The applied and basic themes of the proposal are also mirrored by the collaborative team driving this proposal and their collective expertise available to support and enable the overall production process proposed.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>11/24/2014</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/31/2018</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1410075</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Blaine</FirstName>
<LastName>Pfeifer</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Blaine Pfeifer</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>blainepf@buffalo.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>7166451198</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000418854</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>11/24/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>SUNY at Buffalo</Name>
<CityName>Buffalo</CityName>
<ZipCode>142282567</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>7166452634</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>520 Lee Entrance</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[Suite 211]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>26</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NY26</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>038633251</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>RESEARCH FOUNDATION FOR THE STATE UNIVERSITY OF NEW YORK, THE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>020657151</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[SUNY at Buffalo]]></Name>
<CityName>Buffalo</CityName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<ZipCode>142604200</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[914 Furnas Hall]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>26</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NY26</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>6883</Code>
<Text>Chemistry of Life Processes</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1982</Code>
<Text>BIOLOGICAL CHEMISTRY</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9183</Code>
<Text>GENERAL FOUNDATIONS OF BIOTECHNOLOGY</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9229</Code>
<Text>RES IN UNDERGRAD INST-RESEARCH</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0115</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0118</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2015~90000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2018~12000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>This final report will comment upon both the initial award and a follow-up supplement.&nbsp; The original award focused upon the heterologous production of terpenoid like compounds from E. coli.&nbsp; The award supported a PhD student who gained valuable experience in the design of E. coli strains and biosynthetic pathways for terpenoid biosynthesis.&nbsp; This was in conjunction with collaborators at the University of Northern Arizona and Dixie State University towards a larger vision of sustainable chemical/fuel production combined with ionic liquid processing.&nbsp; Combined, the collaborating universities supported a wide range of student groups.&nbsp; The PhD student supported at the University at Buffalo subsequently graduated and found employment within the emerging synthetic biology industrial sector (note, the award was also used to partially support two additional PhD students, one of which also graduated and obtained a position within the Asian private equity industry focused upon pharmaceutical/biotech ventures).&nbsp; The supplemental award supported a second PhD student, with a focus on interning at a local start-up company.&nbsp; While this student may still gain full time employment with this start-up venture, she has had several interviews with a separate local pharmaceutical company (with an offer anticipated in the near future), primarily because of the experience she has gained in the industrial space through this supplement.&nbsp; Hence, the award has been very effective in student training and placement.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 12/03/2018<br>      Modified by: Blaine&nbsp;Pfeifer</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ This final report will comment upon both the initial award and a follow-up supplement.  The original award focused upon the heterologous production of terpenoid like compounds from E. coli.  The award supported a PhD student who gained valuable experience in the design of E. coli strains and biosynthetic pathways for terpenoid biosynthesis.  This was in conjunction with collaborators at the University of Northern Arizona and Dixie State University towards a larger vision of sustainable chemical/fuel production combined with ionic liquid processing.  Combined, the collaborating universities supported a wide range of student groups.  The PhD student supported at the University at Buffalo subsequently graduated and found employment within the emerging synthetic biology industrial sector (note, the award was also used to partially support two additional PhD students, one of which also graduated and obtained a position within the Asian private equity industry focused upon pharmaceutical/biotech ventures).  The supplemental award supported a second PhD student, with a focus on interning at a local start-up company.  While this student may still gain full time employment with this start-up venture, she has had several interviews with a separate local pharmaceutical company (with an offer anticipated in the near future), primarily because of the experience she has gained in the industrial space through this supplement.  Hence, the award has been very effective in student training and placement.          Last Modified: 12/03/2018       Submitted by: Blaine Pfeifer]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
