<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Collaborative Research:  Observing the Epoch of Reionization with the Murchison Wide field Array</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/15/2014</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>343404.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>343404</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03020000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>AST</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Astronomical Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Richard Barvainis</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The investigators in this collaborative proposal will analyze low frequency radio data from the Murchison Widefield Array to detect the spatial power spectrum of fluctuations in the 21 cm signal caused by the first generation of stars and collapsed objects, during an era known as the Epoch of Reionization (EoR). Broader impacts of the work include training of graduate students and postdocs, and engagement of under-represented groups toward careers in science.  Community outreach will be undertaken at local urban schools and tribal centers.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The observations will have the sensitivity to measure the rise and fall of the EoR power spectrum, placing meaningful constraints on models of reionization and early star formation.  These constraints will have impact on the astrophysics community and could influence how JWST observations are interpreted, constrain the optical depth of cosmic microwave background measurements, and aid our understanding of the early universe.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/15/2014</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/15/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1410484</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Miguel</FirstName>
<LastName>Morales</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>F</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Miguel F Morales</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>mmorales@phys.washington.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2066171137</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000463122</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/15/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Washington</Name>
<CityName>Seattle</CityName>
<ZipCode>981950001</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2065434043</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>4333 Brooklyn Ave NE</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Washington</StateName>
<StateCode>WA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>WA07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>605799469</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF WASHINGTON</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>042803536</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Washington]]></Name>
<CityName>Seattle</CityName>
<StateCode>WA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>981951560</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[4333 Brooklyn Ave NE]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Washington</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>WA07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1217</Code>
<Text>EXTRAGALACTIC ASTRON &amp; COSMOLO</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1207</Code>
<Text>OBSERVATIONAL ASTRONOMY</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0114</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~343404</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The Epoch of Reionization marks when the Universe's first stars and galaxies burned away the primeval neutral hydrogen fog about 13 billion years ago, and radio measurements of this time have been identified as one of the key astrophysical goals of this decade.&nbsp;</p> <p>Work funded by this grant pioneered four major advances in the detection of the Epoch of Reionization, and led to the publication of the deepest imaging power spectrum limits in 2016.&nbsp;</p> <p>The major advances pioneered by this grant include: &nbsp;</p> <p>- Implementing the first imaging pipeline with end-to-end error propagation, leading to the publication of the deepest imaging power spectrum limits in Beardsley et al. 2016.</p> <p>- Creating a precise catalog of extra-galactic foregrounds (KATALOGGS), used as the reference calibration list for Murchison Widefield Array cosmology observations. Published in Carroll et al. 2016.</p> <p>- Understanding the limitations of sky based calibration, and the constraints this places on future instruments. This was published in Barry et al. 2016, and has set the research direction of the field and led to instrumental design changes for the MWA, HERA, and SKA.&nbsp;</p> <p>- Developing new methods for combining observations from the James Webb Space Telescope and deep radio Epoch of Reionization observations. Once thought impossible, Beardsley et al. 2015 showed how to combine these future observations to greatly increase our scientific understanding of the first galaxies.&nbsp;</p> <p>This grant has directly led to two PhD thesis with a third expected in the coming months; the training of approximately 10 community college transfer students; and a significant diversification of the field.&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 12/21/2017<br>      Modified by: Miguel&nbsp;F&nbsp;Morales</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The Epoch of Reionization marks when the Universe's first stars and galaxies burned away the primeval neutral hydrogen fog about 13 billion years ago, and radio measurements of this time have been identified as one of the key astrophysical goals of this decade.   Work funded by this grant pioneered four major advances in the detection of the Epoch of Reionization, and led to the publication of the deepest imaging power spectrum limits in 2016.   The major advances pioneered by this grant include:    - Implementing the first imaging pipeline with end-to-end error propagation, leading to the publication of the deepest imaging power spectrum limits in Beardsley et al. 2016.  - Creating a precise catalog of extra-galactic foregrounds (KATALOGGS), used as the reference calibration list for Murchison Widefield Array cosmology observations. Published in Carroll et al. 2016.  - Understanding the limitations of sky based calibration, and the constraints this places on future instruments. This was published in Barry et al. 2016, and has set the research direction of the field and led to instrumental design changes for the MWA, HERA, and SKA.   - Developing new methods for combining observations from the James Webb Space Telescope and deep radio Epoch of Reionization observations. Once thought impossible, Beardsley et al. 2015 showed how to combine these future observations to greatly increase our scientific understanding of the first galaxies.   This grant has directly led to two PhD thesis with a third expected in the coming months; the training of approximately 10 community college transfer students; and a significant diversification of the field.        Last Modified: 12/21/2017       Submitted by: Miguel F Morales]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
