<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>A Mechanistic Modeling Framework to Link Biochemical Network Signaling and Cell-Decision Processes</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/15/2014</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2020</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>1421789.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>1546858</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>08070000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>BIO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>MCB</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Molecular and Cellular Bioscience</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Richard Cyr</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>rcyr@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032928440</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Cells sense and respond to external and internal perturbations and must make decisions in response to these stimuli. The challenge to understand how cells process biochemical signals that lead to phenotypic responses is largely due to the complex multi-dimensional biochemical data able to identify the relationship between molecular interactions and phenotypes. Thus, understanding the cell-decision processes has wide applicability to address fundamental and applied problems in biology. This project will study the cellular signaling switch from proliferation to programed cell death phenotypes in mammalian cells by developing tools necessary to extract useful mechanistic insights from dynamic program-driven models that will be used to guide experiments. The project offers an interdisciplinary training opportunity for undergraduate students as well as graduate students and post-doctoral associates (including members of underrepresented groups) who will conduct interdisciplinary research by integrating physical, chemical, statistical, mathematical, and computer science methods to compose computational models of cell signaling processes. In addition, the computational tools and methods developed as part of this award will be made freely available to the research community, having the potential to be further employed in other applications, such as climate modeling, communication and economics.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Cells constantly sense and respond to external and internal perturbations that trigger intracellular biochemical reaction networks leading to cellular phenotypic outcomes. The advent of 'omics' technologies in the last decades, in combination with statistical approaches, have yielded a correlative understanding between gene interactions, protein expression, and phenotypes. However, a mechanistic understanding of biochemical interaction network dynamics and cellular commitment to a given outcome is currently lacking. This fundamental knowledge gap to associate genotype and phenotype is largely due to the management and analysis of complex biochemical signaling networks that is needed for applications such as cell reprogramming, synthetic biology applications, and microorganism bioengineering. This project will enable the development and implementation of theoretical and computational tools, based on rigorous physical, chemical, mathematical, and statistical methods, to understand how cells commit to programmed cell death (i.e. apoptosis). The challenge is to understand how proliferating cells process external cues, and shift biochemical signaling pathways from growth to death.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award is supported jointly by the Cellular Dynamics and Function Cluster in the Division of Molecular and Cellular Biosciences and by the Program in Mathematical Biology in the Division of Mathematical Sciences.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/08/2014</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/19/2018</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.074</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1411482</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Carlos</FirstName>
<LastName>Lopez</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>F</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Carlos F Lopez</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>c.lopez@Vanderbilt.Edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6159361311</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000654005</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/08/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Vanderbilt University Medical Center</Name>
<CityName>Nashville</CityName>
<ZipCode>372032408</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6153222631</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>Suite 800</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[110 21st Avenue, South]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Tennessee</StateName>
<StateCode>TN</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>TN05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>004413456</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>VANDERBILT UNIVERSITY, THE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>004413456</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Vanderbilt University Medical Center]]></Name>
<CityName>Nashville</CityName>
<StateCode>TN</StateCode>
<ZipCode>372122809</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[1400 18th Avenue South]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Tennessee</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>TN05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1114</Code>
<Text>Cellular Dynamics and Function</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7275</Code>
<Text>Cross-BIO Activities</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7334</Code>
<Text>MATHEMATICAL BIOLOGY</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7454</Code>
<Text>MSPA-INTERDISCIPLINARY</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1114</Code>
<Text>CELLULAR SYSTEMS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1228</Code>
<Text>MINORITY INVOLVEMENT -- BIO</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7465</Code>
<Text>NANOSCALE BIO CORE</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7487</Code>
<Text>BROADENING PARTICIPATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8007</Code>
<Text>BioMaPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0114</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0116</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0117</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0118</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~844260</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2016~45474</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2017~365506</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2018~291618</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>This project supported the development of a computational modeling framework to explain and predict biological processes using the language of computer programming, As part of this work we developed several tools including PySB, PyDREAM, PyDyNo, and PyVIPR to build, calibrate, analyze, and visualize complex network-driven processes in cell biology.&nbsp;</p> <p>The currency of cellular processes is biochemical reactions. Simple reactions among thousands of molecules create a complex network of interactions that yield adaptive and non-linear responses to perturbations. One of the central challenges in biology is to understand how biochemical reaction networks process signals, in the form of intrinsic or extrinsic cell perturbations, process these signals, and commit the cell to fate. From a mechanistic perspective, the challenge can be considered one where we explore individual biochemical reactions in the context of a network to explore how perturbations contribute to non-linear, complex behaviors and outcomes.&nbsp;</p> <p>In this work, we have built a modeling framework for complex biochemical reaction networks. A key innovation of our approach is that we have embeded the language of biochemical reactions as computer programs in the Python programming language. In this manner we have attained two fundamental advances: (i) we are now able to encode biochemical cellular processes as computer code, and (ii) we can now leverage deacdes of progress in computer engineering and computer science to build, calibrate, analyze, disseminate, and revise models as computer programs. The project has yielded four main programming frameworks that are interactive and address needs of modern biology. PySB, is the core programming language to build and maintain complex models of biochemical processes. The framework is highly useful for small models in pedagogic environments yet powerful for the study of large, complex biochemical processes. Once the model is built in PySB, the next challenge becomes the determination of suitable parameters to carry out simulations of the cellular process of interest. Given that data is not always available for the determination of biochemical kinetic parameters, we encoded a tool, PyDREAM, that uses Bayesian inference methods to infer model parameters. Once we have a properly calibrated network, the next challenge is the analysis of the dynamic network process. To address this need we developed PyDyNo, a tool to study the dynamic properties of network-driven processes. Finally, we developed PyVIPR, a tool to visualize network processes using a multiscale visualization schema that facilitates visualization. These tools were applied to various complex cell problems both, in my lab and in collaboration with others that resulted in multiple publications. Our tools have accelerated how biological knowledge can be extracted from complex datasets and enabled users to make testable predictions.&nbsp;</p> <p>In addition to the research advances our work has also served to introduce non-experts to numerical methods for scientific computing. In particular, we carried out multiple tutorials and hackathons for undergraduate students, graduate students, postdoctoral researchers, and other interested researchers to learn the basics of Python, to employ Pyhon programs as biological models, and to learn a novel paradigm for the study of cellular processes.&nbsp;</p> <p>In addition to the impact that our work has had in biolological research, our work has also been used in other areas including materials science research and economics.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 10/14/2020<br>      Modified by: Carlos&nbsp;F&nbsp;Lopez</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ This project supported the development of a computational modeling framework to explain and predict biological processes using the language of computer programming, As part of this work we developed several tools including PySB, PyDREAM, PyDyNo, and PyVIPR to build, calibrate, analyze, and visualize complex network-driven processes in cell biology.   The currency of cellular processes is biochemical reactions. Simple reactions among thousands of molecules create a complex network of interactions that yield adaptive and non-linear responses to perturbations. One of the central challenges in biology is to understand how biochemical reaction networks process signals, in the form of intrinsic or extrinsic cell perturbations, process these signals, and commit the cell to fate. From a mechanistic perspective, the challenge can be considered one where we explore individual biochemical reactions in the context of a network to explore how perturbations contribute to non-linear, complex behaviors and outcomes.   In this work, we have built a modeling framework for complex biochemical reaction networks. A key innovation of our approach is that we have embeded the language of biochemical reactions as computer programs in the Python programming language. In this manner we have attained two fundamental advances: (i) we are now able to encode biochemical cellular processes as computer code, and (ii) we can now leverage deacdes of progress in computer engineering and computer science to build, calibrate, analyze, disseminate, and revise models as computer programs. The project has yielded four main programming frameworks that are interactive and address needs of modern biology. PySB, is the core programming language to build and maintain complex models of biochemical processes. The framework is highly useful for small models in pedagogic environments yet powerful for the study of large, complex biochemical processes. Once the model is built in PySB, the next challenge becomes the determination of suitable parameters to carry out simulations of the cellular process of interest. Given that data is not always available for the determination of biochemical kinetic parameters, we encoded a tool, PyDREAM, that uses Bayesian inference methods to infer model parameters. Once we have a properly calibrated network, the next challenge is the analysis of the dynamic network process. To address this need we developed PyDyNo, a tool to study the dynamic properties of network-driven processes. Finally, we developed PyVIPR, a tool to visualize network processes using a multiscale visualization schema that facilitates visualization. These tools were applied to various complex cell problems both, in my lab and in collaboration with others that resulted in multiple publications. Our tools have accelerated how biological knowledge can be extracted from complex datasets and enabled users to make testable predictions.   In addition to the research advances our work has also served to introduce non-experts to numerical methods for scientific computing. In particular, we carried out multiple tutorials and hackathons for undergraduate students, graduate students, postdoctoral researchers, and other interested researchers to learn the basics of Python, to employ Pyhon programs as biological models, and to learn a novel paradigm for the study of cellular processes.   In addition to the impact that our work has had in biolological research, our work has also been used in other areas including materials science research and economics.       Last Modified: 10/14/2020       Submitted by: Carlos F Lopez]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
