<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>RNA structures regulating ribosomal protein synthesis in gram-positive bacteria</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2014</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>499235.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>499235</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>08070100</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>BIO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>MCB</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Molecular and Cellular Bioscience</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Michael Weinreich</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The objective of this project is to examine how bacteria coordinate production of ribosomes, which are crucial for their growth. Ribosomes are the biological machines responsible for making proteins, and in actively growing bacteria they constitute over 1/3 of the cell's contents.  Thus, cells devote a large proportion of their resources to the production of ribosomes. Ribosomes require approximately 60 different components that must be produced in the correct proportions. In order to use resources most efficiently, bacteria practice just-in-time production of their ribosomal parts. This research will provide insight into this process in bacterial strains with important roles in soil bioremediation, agriculture, and the food industry, leading to increased ability to engineer the growth rate and metabolism of these strains. By understanding how this biological problem is solved in different ways by different strains of bacteria, we will better understand how such coordination can evolve and what the important performance parameters may be. This research also provides significant opportunities to young scientist trainees at the graduate, undergraduate and high school levels because it may be broken into many individual projects with limited scope and specific testable hypotheses that are accessible to novice scientists. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project seeks to determine the role of RNA regulation on ribosomal protein synthesis in gram-positive bacteria. While the regulation of this process is well understood in the model gram-negative bacterium Escherichia coli, it remains virtually unexamined in gram-positive bacteria. By identifying and characterizing RNA structures that accomplish this task in the model gram-positive bacterium Bacillus subtilis, we will uncover numerous uncharacterized RNA regulatory structures that are alternative solutions to the same biological problem, and provide another picture of how this complex process occurs. This research will also contribute new fodder for growing RNA structural databases and biophysical analysis of RNA-protein interactions, and provide insight into the factors influencing how such systems may evolve. To accomplish these goals computationally predicted RNA structures associated with ribosomal proteins will be computationally curated to determine whether they are transcribed, resemble ribosomal RNA binding sites, or are associated with features that commonly have regulatory roles. The biological function of these RNAs will then be experimentally validated using both in vitro RNA-protein binding assays and in vivo genetic regulatory assays.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/17/2014</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/09/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.074</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1411970</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Michelle</FirstName>
<LastName>Meyer</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Michelle Meyer</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>m.meyer@bc.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6175520735</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000593311</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/17/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Boston College</Name>
<CityName>Chestnut Hill</CityName>
<ZipCode>024673800</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6175528000</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>140 Commonwealth Avenue</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
<StateCode>MA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MA04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>045896339</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>TRUSTEES OF BOSTON COLLEGE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>045896339</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Boston College]]></Name>
<CityName>Chestnut Hill</CityName>
<StateCode>MA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>024673800</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[140 Commonwealth Ave.]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MA04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1112</Code>
<Text>Genetic Mechanisms</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1112</Code>
<Text>GENES AND GENOME SYSTEMS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7465</Code>
<Text>NANOSCALE BIO CORE</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0114</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0115</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0116</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~159998</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2015~164799</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2016~174438</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><strong>Intellectual Merit</strong></p> <p>This award allowed us to significantly expand knowledge of how ribosomal protein regulators form and are maintained over evolutionary time.&nbsp; This work provides critical basic knowledge for the engineering of novel regulators, and understanding essential biological processes such as ribosome assembly and stoichiometry in bacteria.&nbsp; Four publications resulted from this work.</p> <p>The major goals of the award were to curate and prioritize putative regulators of ribosomal protein biosynthesis in gram-positive bacteria, and to subsequent experimentally evaluate these regulators using both genetic and <em>in vitro</em> methods.</p> <p>Toward this goal, we successfully characterized a novel regulatory RNA present in <em>Bacillus subtilis</em> that responds to the S6:S18 dimer both <em>in vitro</em> and using genetic reporter assays (Babina et al. 2015). Experiments were conducted with several other putative regulators, although many candidates are transcribed and promising genetic results were obtained for several, ultimately few demonstrated convincing direct RNA-protein interaction <em>in vitro</em>.</p> <p>&nbsp;Thus, we expanded the scope of our work to include comparison of regulatory RNAs in different species that interact with homologous ribosomal proteins. This work centered on ribosomal protein S15 and the four very distinct regulatory RNAs in different species of bacteria with which it interacts (our models were <em>Escherichia coli</em>, <em>Geobacillus kaustophilus</em>, <em>Thermus thermophilus</em> and <em>Radiobacter radiodurans</em>). In this work we demonstrated that RNA structures from diverse bacterial species are recognized differently by divergent S15 homologs, and we identified evidence for co-evolution between the S15 protein and its mRNA regulators (Slinger et al. 2015). This work is some of the first to show how RNA binding specificity of proteins may change over evolutionary time.</p> <p>These results sparked our interest to further examine the evolution of RNA regulators, in particular to characterize the sequence space that allows RNA regulation. Therefore, we conducted an <em>in vitro</em> selection for RNAs that interact with S15 from <em>G. kaustophilus</em> (using the <em>E. coli</em> mRNA structure as a template sequence). This study revealed 1) sequences that bind S15 are common in sequence space, and 2) regulation occurs as a consequence of binding relatively easily, with over 60% of tested sequences both binding and allowing regulation in a genetic assay (Slinger et al. 2016). Furthermore, high-throughput sequencing of this population and further experimental assessment of the sequences shows that S15 interacts with a very large number of sequences with high affinity, and that many of them regulate (Pei et al. 2017).</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;<strong>Broader Impacts</strong></p> <p>Three completed PhD, an MS, and five undergraduate senior theses were supported by this award. The award supported the summer research experiences of an additional four undergraduates that did not elect to complete senior theses, and an additional two PhD students are expected to complete their work in the coming years. Two of the published journal articles include undergraduate authors (Babina et al. 2015 and Slinger et al 2015). &nbsp;Several undergraduates from the PI&rsquo;s lab have entered PhD. programs at places such as Harvard and University of Chicago, many others have gone on to medical school, or work as technicians in the Boston area biotech industry.</p> <p>&nbsp;In addition, this award supported the PI&rsquo;s contribution to the Boston College Women in Science Program. During each of the award years this program brought 25 to 35 at risk girls (ages 12-15) to campus for a series of weekend workshops. The workshops included exposure to a variety of scientific disciplines and included participation in lab projects as well as a tour of an industrial chemistry lab. The Biology activities varied over the years and included DNA extraction, gel electrophoresis, microbiology culturing and microscopy, dissection of animal hearts, analysis of macromolecule content in processed foods, and simulations of vaccine efficacy during an epidemic. The PI personally supervised all of the biology experiments and coordinated the efforts of undergraduate women that act as mentors during this program.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 08/10/2018<br>      Modified by: Michelle&nbsp;Meyer</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Intellectual Merit  This award allowed us to significantly expand knowledge of how ribosomal protein regulators form and are maintained over evolutionary time.  This work provides critical basic knowledge for the engineering of novel regulators, and understanding essential biological processes such as ribosome assembly and stoichiometry in bacteria.  Four publications resulted from this work.  The major goals of the award were to curate and prioritize putative regulators of ribosomal protein biosynthesis in gram-positive bacteria, and to subsequent experimentally evaluate these regulators using both genetic and in vitro methods.  Toward this goal, we successfully characterized a novel regulatory RNA present in Bacillus subtilis that responds to the S6:S18 dimer both in vitro and using genetic reporter assays (Babina et al. 2015). Experiments were conducted with several other putative regulators, although many candidates are transcribed and promising genetic results were obtained for several, ultimately few demonstrated convincing direct RNA-protein interaction in vitro.   Thus, we expanded the scope of our work to include comparison of regulatory RNAs in different species that interact with homologous ribosomal proteins. This work centered on ribosomal protein S15 and the four very distinct regulatory RNAs in different species of bacteria with which it interacts (our models were Escherichia coli, Geobacillus kaustophilus, Thermus thermophilus and Radiobacter radiodurans). In this work we demonstrated that RNA structures from diverse bacterial species are recognized differently by divergent S15 homologs, and we identified evidence for co-evolution between the S15 protein and its mRNA regulators (Slinger et al. 2015). This work is some of the first to show how RNA binding specificity of proteins may change over evolutionary time.  These results sparked our interest to further examine the evolution of RNA regulators, in particular to characterize the sequence space that allows RNA regulation. Therefore, we conducted an in vitro selection for RNAs that interact with S15 from G. kaustophilus (using the E. coli mRNA structure as a template sequence). This study revealed 1) sequences that bind S15 are common in sequence space, and 2) regulation occurs as a consequence of binding relatively easily, with over 60% of tested sequences both binding and allowing regulation in a genetic assay (Slinger et al. 2016). Furthermore, high-throughput sequencing of this population and further experimental assessment of the sequences shows that S15 interacts with a very large number of sequences with high affinity, and that many of them regulate (Pei et al. 2017).      Broader Impacts  Three completed PhD, an MS, and five undergraduate senior theses were supported by this award. The award supported the summer research experiences of an additional four undergraduates that did not elect to complete senior theses, and an additional two PhD students are expected to complete their work in the coming years. Two of the published journal articles include undergraduate authors (Babina et al. 2015 and Slinger et al 2015).  Several undergraduates from the PI?s lab have entered PhD. programs at places such as Harvard and University of Chicago, many others have gone on to medical school, or work as technicians in the Boston area biotech industry.   In addition, this award supported the PI?s contribution to the Boston College Women in Science Program. During each of the award years this program brought 25 to 35 at risk girls (ages 12-15) to campus for a series of weekend workshops. The workshops included exposure to a variety of scientific disciplines and included participation in lab projects as well as a tour of an industrial chemistry lab. The Biology activities varied over the years and included DNA extraction, gel electrophoresis, microbiology culturing and microscopy, dissection of animal hearts, analysis of macromolecule content in processed foods, and simulations of vaccine efficacy during an epidemic. The PI personally supervised all of the biology experiments and coordinated the efforts of undergraduate women that act as mentors during this program.          Last Modified: 08/10/2018       Submitted by: Michelle Meyer]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
