<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Collaborative Research: Observing the Epoch of Reionization with the Murchison Widefield Array</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/15/2014</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>230122.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>230122</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03020000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>AST</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Astronomical Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Richard Barvainis</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The investigators in this collaborative proposal will analyze low frequency radio data from the Murchison Widefield Array to detect the spatial power spectrum of fluctuations in the 21 cm signal caused by the first generation of stars and collapsed objects, during an era known as the Epoch of Reionization (EoR). Broader impacts of the work include training of graduate students and postdocs, and engagement of under-represented groups toward careers in science.  Community outreach will be undertaken at local urban schools and tribal centers.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The observations will have the sensitivity to measure the rise and fall of the EoR power spectrum, placing meaningful constraints on models of reionization and early star formation.  These constraints will have impact on the astrophysics community and could influence how JWST observations are interpreted, constrain the optical depth of cosmic microwave background measurements, and aid our understanding of the early universe.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/15/2014</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/15/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1411622</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Jacqueline</FirstName>
<LastName>Hewitt</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>N</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Jacqueline N Hewitt</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>jhewitt@mit.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6172533071</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000244228</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/15/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Massachusetts Institute of Technology</Name>
<CityName>Cambridge</CityName>
<ZipCode>021394301</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6172531000</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>77 MASSACHUSETTS AVE</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[NE18-901]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
<StateCode>MA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MA07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>001425594</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>MASSACHUSETTS INSTITUTE OF TECHNOLOGY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>001425594</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Massachusetts Institute of Technology]]></Name>
<CityName>Cambridge</CityName>
<StateCode>MA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>021394301</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[77 Massachusetts Avenue]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>07</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MA07</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1217</Code>
<Text>EXTRAGALACTIC ASTRON &amp; COSMOLO</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1207</Code>
<Text>OBSERVATIONAL ASTRONOMY</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0114</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~230122</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>INTELLECTUAL MERIT</p> <p><br />Over the past couple of decades, astrophysicsts have succeeded incarrying out "precision cosmology;'" that is, charting the expansion of the universe since the Big Bang 13.8 billion years ago and identifying the universe's constitutents of dark energy, dark matter, and ordinary&nbsp;matter. &nbsp;This is a remarkable framework, and current efforts are focussed on filling in our knowledge within this framework. One question is: How did the structure we see today -- galaxies, stars, planets -- emerge from the primoridial soup of elementary particles? &nbsp;Detailed computer simulations give us prediction for how this should occur, and we are building instruments that are capable of mapping structure formation, providing a comparison of data to the predictions. &nbsp;This grant supported the construction, operation, and data analysis for a radio array that measures structures of hydrogen gas by detecting a radio transition of the neutral hydrogen atom. &nbsp;<br />With the funding of this grant we&nbsp;&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp; - collected data from the Murchison Widefield Array&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp; - developed techniques for calibration and analysis of the data&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;- demonstrated the sensitivity of these techniques by publishing limits on density and temperature of hydrogen at the time of first &nbsp;star formation&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;- developed techniques for determining the response of low-frequency &nbsp;radio antennas&nbsp;</p> <p>- assessed a correlation of radio emission and infrared emission in nearby astronomical objects, data necessary for future study of these tracers in the first stars</p> <p><br />BROADER IMPACT</p> <p><br />The techniques of antenna characterization, antenna calibration, and&nbsp;data analysis for radio arrays have been published and have broad applicability to future astrophysics research and other fields of&nbsp;science and engineering. &nbsp;They are currently being applied to new&nbsp;radio arrays being built for further astrophysics research, including the Hydrogen Epoch of Reionization Array. &nbsp;An example of an application outside astrophysics is the development of hand-held ultrasound medical imaging. &nbsp;The ultrasound sensors are made of thousands of programmable micro-sensors on a chip, and the&nbsp;mathematics and techniques for controlling the mixro-sensors and interpreting their&nbsp;signals are nearly identical to those developed for radio astronomy. &nbsp;Two graduate students were trained in electronics, data analysis, and&nbsp;radio array design, construction, and utlization. They continue to apply these techniques in astrophysics and in work in the private sector. &nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 04/30/2019<br>      Modified by: Jacqueline&nbsp;N&nbsp;Hewitt</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Image         </div> <div class="galControls onePhoto" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation onePhoto" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1411622/1411622_10333267_1556639368935_hera_clouds.17mar03--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1411622/1411622_10333267_1556639368935_hera_clouds.17mar03--rgov-800width.jpg" title="HERA"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1411622/1411622_10333267_1556639368935_hera_clouds.17mar03--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="HERA"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">The Hydrogen Epoch of Reionization Array (HERA) under construction in South Africa.  HERA is a second-generation instrument designed to detect hydrogen gas structures during the epoch of our universe's history when the first stars and galaxies formed.</div> <div class="imageCredit">J. Dillon</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Public Domain</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Jacqueline&nbsp;N&nbsp;Hewitt</div> <div class="imageTitle">HERA</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ INTELLECTUAL MERIT   Over the past couple of decades, astrophysicsts have succeeded incarrying out "precision cosmology;'" that is, charting the expansion of the universe since the Big Bang 13.8 billion years ago and identifying the universe's constitutents of dark energy, dark matter, and ordinary matter.  This is a remarkable framework, and current efforts are focussed on filling in our knowledge within this framework. One question is: How did the structure we see today -- galaxies, stars, planets -- emerge from the primoridial soup of elementary particles?  Detailed computer simulations give us prediction for how this should occur, and we are building instruments that are capable of mapping structure formation, providing a comparison of data to the predictions.  This grant supported the construction, operation, and data analysis for a radio array that measures structures of hydrogen gas by detecting a radio transition of the neutral hydrogen atom.   With the funding of this grant we      - collected data from the Murchison Widefield Array     - developed techniques for calibration and analysis of the data    - demonstrated the sensitivity of these techniques by publishing limits on density and temperature of hydrogen at the time of first  star formation    - developed techniques for determining the response of low-frequency  radio antennas   - assessed a correlation of radio emission and infrared emission in nearby astronomical objects, data necessary for future study of these tracers in the first stars   BROADER IMPACT   The techniques of antenna characterization, antenna calibration, and data analysis for radio arrays have been published and have broad applicability to future astrophysics research and other fields of science and engineering.  They are currently being applied to new radio arrays being built for further astrophysics research, including the Hydrogen Epoch of Reionization Array.  An example of an application outside astrophysics is the development of hand-held ultrasound medical imaging.  The ultrasound sensors are made of thousands of programmable micro-sensors on a chip, and the mathematics and techniques for controlling the mixro-sensors and interpreting their signals are nearly identical to those developed for radio astronomy.  Two graduate students were trained in electronics, data analysis, and radio array design, construction, and utlization. They continue to apply these techniques in astrophysics and in work in the private sector.               Last Modified: 04/30/2019       Submitted by: Jacqueline N Hewitt]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
