<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Investigations of Binary Star Properties and Evolutionary Processes with the CHARA Array Interferometer</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2014</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>402342.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>402342</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03020000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>AST</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Astronomical Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>James Neff</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>jneff@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922475</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Long baseline optical interferometry allows measurement (and even imaging) of structure on smaller scales than can be obtained even with the largest ground-based telescopes.  The investigators will continue to make excellent use of Georgia State's Center for High Angular Resolution Astronomy (CHARA) interferometer array on Mt. Wilson in California.  This is the only long-baseline optical interferometer run by a university, so it provides a unique opportunity for student training in this state-of-the art technology.  Results from this program will be featured in undergraduate classes at Georgia State and in the southern California public outreach efforts of the Mt. Wilson Institute.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The proposal presents a three-part investigation that will use the CHARA optical long-baseline interferometer array to determine fundamental stellar and circumstellar properties of stars in close binary systems before, during, and after they interact and exchange mass.  The high angular resolution provided by interferometry will permit them to measure the orbits of over 200 non-interacting spectroscopic binaries, which will allow direct determination of component masses and indirect determination of other physical parameters.  They will also be able to image circumstellar material in binary stars that are currently exchanging material.  Finally, they will search for the poorly-stuied donor stars in a carefully-selected sample of systems that have already undergone mass transfer.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/19/2014</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/19/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1411654</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Douglas</FirstName>
<LastName>Gies</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>R</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Douglas R Gies</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>gies@chara.gsu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>4044136021</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000376869</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/19/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Georgia State University Research Foundation, Inc.</Name>
<CityName>Atlanta</CityName>
<ZipCode>303032921</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>4044133570</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>58 Edgewood Avenue</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[PO Box 3999]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Georgia</StateName>
<StateCode>GA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>GA05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>837322494</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>GEORGIA STATE UNIVERSITY RESEARCH FOUNDATION, INC.</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Georgia State University Research Foundation, Inc.]]></Name>
<CityName>Atlanta</CityName>
<StateCode>GA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>303025060</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[G76Dahlberg Hall 30 Courtland St]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Georgia</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>GA05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1215</Code>
<Text>STELLAR ASTRONOMY &amp; ASTROPHYSC</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1207</Code>
<Text>OBSERVATIONAL ASTRONOMY</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0114</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~402342</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The stars are distant Suns that are so far away that scientists need special tools <br />to examine them in any detail.&nbsp; The ability to see small details (high angular <br />resolution) depends on the diameter of the telescope lens or mirror, but to build<br />a single telescope large enough to see even the largest stars is prohibitively <br />expensive.&nbsp; The solution is to build a network of distributed telescopes, known <br />as an optical interferometer.&nbsp; The nation's leading optical long baseline <br />interferometer is the Georgia State University Center for High Angular Resolution <br />Astronomy (CHARA) Array, a system of six telescopes at the Mount Wilson Observatory<br />in southern California.&nbsp; These telescopes have separations (baselines) ranging from<br />34 to 331 meters (see Fig. 1 for the arrangement), effectively making a telescope <br />as large as three football fields placed end-to-end.&nbsp;&nbsp; The light is combined from <br />each telescope (each with a 1 meter primary mirror; Fig. 2) by sending the beams<br />along light pipes into a central optics laboratory (Fig. 3).&nbsp; There the beams <br />come together to study the details of the visual and near infrared light of the stars. <br /><br />The CHARA Array provided the means to make several in depth studies of very distant<br />stars with masses greater than that of the Sun.&nbsp; Measurements were made of the <br />hot and massive O- and B-type stars, objects that burn quickly through their <br />nuclear fuel to explode as supernovae and create neutron stars and black hole <br />remnants.&nbsp; By combining the angular size with distant estimates from the European <br />Space Agency's Gaia Mission, the physical radii of these stars are determined <br />and compared to computer models of their interior structure and radiative flux <br />output.&nbsp; The other key measure of a star is its mass, and masses can be found by <br />tracking the orbital motion of pairs of stars forming a binary system.&nbsp; The CHARA <br />Array is ideal for mapping out the angular orbits of close pairs discovered by <br />the time variable Doppler shifts of their spectra.&nbsp; For example, observations <br />from the Array provided the first three-dimensional orbital map of the binary <br />star system sigma Orionis, leading to mass estimates with 1% accuracy and a <br />distance set with an accuracy of 0.3%. <br /><br />The other method to find orbital orientations and masses of stellar pairs is <br />to study the variable light output of eclipsing binary stars in which the flux <br />changes as each component mutually transits in front of the other star.&nbsp; The NASA <br />Kepler mission to find planets around other stars through similar planetary transits<br />created the most accurate eclipsing binary light curves ever made, and a second part<br />of this NSF-sponsored program was a spectroscopic follow up campaign to obtain <br />Doppler shift (or radial velocity) curves of the projected motions of 41 eclipsing<br />binaries in the Kepler field of view.&nbsp; This analysis led to accurate measurements of <br />stellar masses, radii, temperatures, and spin rates, so that the physical and <br />pulsational properties of these stars could be critically compared to computer <br />models that track the changes in stellar parameters as stars age. <br /><br />Pairs of massive stars in close orbits are destined to interact over time in ways<br />that dramatically transform both components.&nbsp; As the initially more massive star <br />grows in size, its outer gas layers will be pulled by the gravity of the companion<br />star until it is stripped down to its nuclear-burning core.&nbsp; The result is then <br />a pair composed of a small but very hot, mass donor star in orbit around an <br />enlarged and rapidly rotating, mass gainer star.&nbsp; Detecting such systems is <br />very difficult because the stripped-down star is lost in the glare of the much <br />brighter mass gainer.&nbsp; However, the search is more favorable in the ultraviolet <br />part of the spectrum where the hot core contributes relatively more of the starlight. <br />A systematic and large scale search for such transformed pairs was made using data<br />from the archive of the NASA International Ultraviolet Explorer satellite, and this<br />effort increased the number of known pairs from three to sixteen.&nbsp; One such system, <br />phi Persei, was detected and its orbit mapped using the CHARA Array.&nbsp; This work <br />provides us with a first glimpse of the kinds of binary star systems that will <br />eventually become pairs of orbiting neutron stars, such as the pair that spiraled <br />together and merged in an explosion and burst of gravitational waves that was <br />observed in 2017 by the Laser Interferometer Gravitational-Wave Observatory.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 11/16/2018<br>      Modified by: Douglas&nbsp;R&nbsp;Gies</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Images (<span id="selectedPhoto0">1</span> of <span class="totalNumber"></span>)           </div> <div class="galControls" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1411654/1411654_10320984_1542387172646_map--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1411654/1411654_10320984_1542387172646_map--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Overview of the CHARA Array"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1411654/1411654_10320984_1542387172646_map--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Overview of the CHARA Array"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">A sketch of the arrangement of the six telescopes of the CHARA Array interferometer at Mount Wilson Observatory.</div> <div class="imageCredit">CHARA</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Public Domain</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Douglas&nbsp;R&nbsp;Gies</div> <div class="imageTitle">Overview of the CHARA Array</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1411654/1411654_10320984_1542387455755_telescope--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1411654/1411654_10320984_1542387455755_telescope--rgov-800width.jpg" title="CHARA Array telescope"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1411654/1411654_10320984_1542387455755_telescope--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="CHARA Array telescope"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Photograph of one of the six telescopes that make up the CHARA Array at the Mount Wilson Observatory.</div> <div class="imageCredit">GSU</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Public Domain</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Douglas&nbsp;R&nbsp;Gies</div> <div class="imageTitle">CHARA Array telescope</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1411654/1411654_10320984_1542387620363_OPLE--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1411654/1411654_10320984_1542387620363_OPLE--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Optics laboratory of the CHARA Array"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1411654/1411654_10320984_1542387620363_OPLE--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Optics laboratory of the CHARA Array"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">A view of the Optical Path Length Equalization facility in the optical laboratory of the CHARA Array at Mount Wilson Observatory.</div> <div class="imageCredit">CHARA</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Public Domain</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Douglas&nbsp;R&nbsp;Gies</div> <div class="imageTitle">Optics laboratory of the CHARA Array</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The stars are distant Suns that are so far away that scientists need special tools  to examine them in any detail.  The ability to see small details (high angular  resolution) depends on the diameter of the telescope lens or mirror, but to build a single telescope large enough to see even the largest stars is prohibitively  expensive.  The solution is to build a network of distributed telescopes, known  as an optical interferometer.  The nation's leading optical long baseline  interferometer is the Georgia State University Center for High Angular Resolution  Astronomy (CHARA) Array, a system of six telescopes at the Mount Wilson Observatory in southern California.  These telescopes have separations (baselines) ranging from 34 to 331 meters (see Fig. 1 for the arrangement), effectively making a telescope  as large as three football fields placed end-to-end.   The light is combined from  each telescope (each with a 1 meter primary mirror; Fig. 2) by sending the beams along light pipes into a central optics laboratory (Fig. 3).  There the beams  come together to study the details of the visual and near infrared light of the stars.   The CHARA Array provided the means to make several in depth studies of very distant stars with masses greater than that of the Sun.  Measurements were made of the  hot and massive O- and B-type stars, objects that burn quickly through their  nuclear fuel to explode as supernovae and create neutron stars and black hole  remnants.  By combining the angular size with distant estimates from the European  Space Agency's Gaia Mission, the physical radii of these stars are determined  and compared to computer models of their interior structure and radiative flux  output.  The other key measure of a star is its mass, and masses can be found by  tracking the orbital motion of pairs of stars forming a binary system.  The CHARA  Array is ideal for mapping out the angular orbits of close pairs discovered by  the time variable Doppler shifts of their spectra.  For example, observations  from the Array provided the first three-dimensional orbital map of the binary  star system sigma Orionis, leading to mass estimates with 1% accuracy and a  distance set with an accuracy of 0.3%.   The other method to find orbital orientations and masses of stellar pairs is  to study the variable light output of eclipsing binary stars in which the flux  changes as each component mutually transits in front of the other star.  The NASA  Kepler mission to find planets around other stars through similar planetary transits created the most accurate eclipsing binary light curves ever made, and a second part of this NSF-sponsored program was a spectroscopic follow up campaign to obtain  Doppler shift (or radial velocity) curves of the projected motions of 41 eclipsing binaries in the Kepler field of view.  This analysis led to accurate measurements of  stellar masses, radii, temperatures, and spin rates, so that the physical and  pulsational properties of these stars could be critically compared to computer  models that track the changes in stellar parameters as stars age.   Pairs of massive stars in close orbits are destined to interact over time in ways that dramatically transform both components.  As the initially more massive star  grows in size, its outer gas layers will be pulled by the gravity of the companion star until it is stripped down to its nuclear-burning core.  The result is then  a pair composed of a small but very hot, mass donor star in orbit around an  enlarged and rapidly rotating, mass gainer star.  Detecting such systems is  very difficult because the stripped-down star is lost in the glare of the much  brighter mass gainer.  However, the search is more favorable in the ultraviolet  part of the spectrum where the hot core contributes relatively more of the starlight.  A systematic and large scale search for such transformed pairs was made using data from the archive of the NASA International Ultraviolet Explorer satellite, and this effort increased the number of known pairs from three to sixteen.  One such system,  phi Persei, was detected and its orbit mapped using the CHARA Array.  This work  provides us with a first glimpse of the kinds of binary star systems that will  eventually become pairs of orbiting neutron stars, such as the pair that spiraled  together and merged in an explosion and burst of gravitational waves that was  observed in 2017 by the Laser Interferometer Gravitational-Wave Observatory.          Last Modified: 11/16/2018       Submitted by: Douglas R Gies]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
