<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Collaborative Research - A Panchromatic Imaging Survey of the Galactic Bulge</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2014</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>132148.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>132148</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03020000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>AST</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Astronomical Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Glen Langston</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>glangsto@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924937</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The researchers will study our Milky Way galaxy and the great star clouds of Sagittarius, which are easily visible on a dark summer night, low on the Southern horizon, from the anywhere in the United States. Their observation plan is to precisely measure the colors of stars in the brightest part of the Milky Way, including the bulge of stars near the center of our galaxy.   Their scientific target is understanding the origin and history of formation of stars in the bulge. The investigators will use the Dark Energy Camera (currently most powerful on any telescope) on the 4m telescope at the Cerro Tololo observatory in Chile.  They will produce a sequence of color images, from infrared, optical to ultraviolet wavelengths. The broader impact of this program has several components. Foremost is providing professional astronomers and public with tools to view the multi-color images online.  The investigators will give the public access to the same data as are used by professional astronomers.  The investigators will report the results via popular journal articles, public lectures and sky viewing events. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The collaboration will use these detailed images of the bulge of our Milky Way to map the structure of its stars, deduce their age and metal content, to shed light on the structure and formation history of the bulge stars. An additional bonus will be detailed images of over 30 globular star clusters in the six filters observed by the collaboration. Over time, the space motions of stars will be measured, enabling study of the stellar orbits that support the structure of the bulge. The bulge of stars surrounding the core of our galaxy was likely formed as the result of three processes, 1) rapid, violent merging within the first billion years after the Big Bang, 2) ongoing mergers of massive stellar clusters and 3) formation from the early disk of the Milky Way, by slower dynamical processes. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The collaboration's images and derived measurements, combined with additional studies, have the potential to transform our understanding of the formation of the Galaxy.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/12/2014</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/12/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1412673</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Catherine</FirstName>
<LastName>Pilachowski</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>A</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Catherine A Pilachowski</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>cpilacho@indiana.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>8128556913</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000017330</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/12/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Scott</FirstName>
<LastName>Michael</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Scott Michael</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>scamicha@iu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>8128560197</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000630310</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/12/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Indiana University</Name>
<CityName>Bloomington</CityName>
<ZipCode>474013654</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>3172783473</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>509 E 3RD ST</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Indiana</StateName>
<StateCode>IN</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>09</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>IN09</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>006046700</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>TRUSTEES OF INDIANA UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>006046700</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Indiana University]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>IN</StateCode>
<ZipCode>474013654</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Indiana</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>09</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>IN09</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1216</Code>
<Text>GALACTIC ASTRONOMY PROGRAM</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1206</Code>
<Text>THEORETICAL &amp; COMPUTATIONAL ASTROPHYSICS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1207</Code>
<Text>OBSERVATIONAL ASTRONOMY</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0114</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~132148</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The central bulge of our Milky Way galaxy contains some of the oldest, most metal-rich stars in the Universe.&nbsp; The stellar populations of the bulge are complex, with stars forming in different epochs and under different circumstances.&nbsp; Cataloging and understanding the stellar populations within the bulge helps us unravel the formation and history of our galaxy, yet only a small fraction of the brightest stars in the bulge have been studied by astronomers.</p> <p>The Blanco DECam Bulge Survey (BDBS) has imaged some 200 square degrees of the central bulge using the Dark Energy Camera on the Blanco 4-m telescope at the Cerro Tololo Interamerican observatory in Chile.&nbsp; The observations were taken through six filters ranging in wavelength from the ultraviolet to the infrared.&nbsp; From these observations, we have used high performance computers at Indiana University to extract photometric and positional information for 250 million individual stars in the bulge, from the brightest stars down to stars fainter than the Sun, some two magnitudes below the stellar main sequence turnoff in the bulge, corresponding to stars with masses of about half that of our sun.&nbsp; Our photometric and positional measurements have been carefully calibrated to a standard photometric system, and corrections have been applied to remove the effects of interstellar extinction on our measurements, allowing us to see through the dust of interstellar space.</p> <p>The principal outcome of our work at Indiana University is the creation of the largest catalog of stars in the Galactic bulge ever produced.&nbsp; In addition, we have created online tools to access, extract, and examine key subsets of stars in the bulge to address critical questions about the origin of the bulge and its stellar populations.&nbsp; The catalog is being made available to astronomers everywhere to enable detailed studies of the Galactic bulge.</p> <p>The BDBS catalog will permit astronomers to search for substructure in the bulge at an unprecedented level, and to determine the age-metallicity relation of stars in the bulge.&nbsp; From the ultraviolet filter data we are able to examine the hot-star populations of the bulge for help us understand the ultraviolet light we see in the bulges of other spiral galaxies.&nbsp; The catalog also contains photometry and positional measurements of stars in some two dozen globular star clusters, many not yet studied in detail by astronomers.&nbsp; BDBS data allows us to determine the ages, metallicities, and complexities of these clusters, and to search for tidal streams of stars being stripped from the clusters to join the field population of stars in the bulge.</p> <p>Deep, multi-filter images of the bulge also allow us to produce color images of interesting nebulae populating the bulge, and to provide the public the opportunity to explore this star-rich environment in detail.&nbsp; In addition, the development of the software for crowded-field photometry will have application to future surveys of regions with high stellar densities.&nbsp; The user-interface tools for accessing catalogs will benefit researchers in other fields working with large datasets.</p> <p><strong>&nbsp;</strong><em>&nbsp;</em></p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 10/12/2019<br>      Modified by: Catherine&nbsp;A&nbsp;Pilachowski</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The central bulge of our Milky Way galaxy contains some of the oldest, most metal-rich stars in the Universe.  The stellar populations of the bulge are complex, with stars forming in different epochs and under different circumstances.  Cataloging and understanding the stellar populations within the bulge helps us unravel the formation and history of our galaxy, yet only a small fraction of the brightest stars in the bulge have been studied by astronomers.  The Blanco DECam Bulge Survey (BDBS) has imaged some 200 square degrees of the central bulge using the Dark Energy Camera on the Blanco 4-m telescope at the Cerro Tololo Interamerican observatory in Chile.  The observations were taken through six filters ranging in wavelength from the ultraviolet to the infrared.  From these observations, we have used high performance computers at Indiana University to extract photometric and positional information for 250 million individual stars in the bulge, from the brightest stars down to stars fainter than the Sun, some two magnitudes below the stellar main sequence turnoff in the bulge, corresponding to stars with masses of about half that of our sun.  Our photometric and positional measurements have been carefully calibrated to a standard photometric system, and corrections have been applied to remove the effects of interstellar extinction on our measurements, allowing us to see through the dust of interstellar space.  The principal outcome of our work at Indiana University is the creation of the largest catalog of stars in the Galactic bulge ever produced.  In addition, we have created online tools to access, extract, and examine key subsets of stars in the bulge to address critical questions about the origin of the bulge and its stellar populations.  The catalog is being made available to astronomers everywhere to enable detailed studies of the Galactic bulge.  The BDBS catalog will permit astronomers to search for substructure in the bulge at an unprecedented level, and to determine the age-metallicity relation of stars in the bulge.  From the ultraviolet filter data we are able to examine the hot-star populations of the bulge for help us understand the ultraviolet light we see in the bulges of other spiral galaxies.  The catalog also contains photometry and positional measurements of stars in some two dozen globular star clusters, many not yet studied in detail by astronomers.  BDBS data allows us to determine the ages, metallicities, and complexities of these clusters, and to search for tidal streams of stars being stripped from the clusters to join the field population of stars in the bulge.  Deep, multi-filter images of the bulge also allow us to produce color images of interesting nebulae populating the bulge, and to provide the public the opportunity to explore this star-rich environment in detail.  In addition, the development of the software for crowded-field photometry will have application to future surveys of regions with high stellar densities.  The user-interface tools for accessing catalogs will benefit researchers in other fields working with large datasets.              Last Modified: 10/12/2019       Submitted by: Catherine A Pilachowski]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
