<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>DNA elimination mechanisms in Tetrahymena</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2014</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>510000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>510000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>08070100</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>BIO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>MCB</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Molecular and Cellular Bioscience</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Karen Cone</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>kccone@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924967</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The genomes of many organisms contain DNA with no known function.  In some organisms, this so-called junk DNA is eliminated during development by a complex rearrangement of the genome.  However, it is not clear how the cell can tell what is junk and what is not. This research will study how the ciliate, Tetrahymena thermophila, establishes what parts of the genome should be thrown away as junk and what should be retained as functionally important.  Because junk DNA is found in the genomes of many organisms, this work could have broad scientific significance on understanding how cells deal with extraneous, non-essential DNA.  To accomplish the research, a tool for visualizing genome-related datasets will be created and made accessible for use by the broader scientific community, thereby improving the current scientific infrastructure. The project will enhance the future scientific workforce by engaging trainees from the undergraduate to post-doctoral level in hypothesis-driven research. The research efforts will be coordinated with curricular development activities of the principle investigator, and thus will facilitate best teaching practice by bringing authentic research into the university biology classroom. Students engaged in the classroom research, in turn, will gain first-hand experience in the practice of scientific discovery and add to a growing body of scientific knowledge.&lt;br/&gt;  &lt;br/&gt;This project will elucidate mechanisms that eukaryotic cells use to establish boundaries between functionally distinct regions of the genome by exploiting the model experimental organism, Tetrahymena thermophila, which eliminates much of its non-coding DNA from the somatic copy of its genome. Using a combination of genetic and biochemical approaches, the work will uncover mechanisms that Tetrahymena cells use to define the boundaries of the DNA segments that are eliminated during its development. The fact that Tetrahymena eliminates these sequences allows one to unambiguously identify those that get packaged as junk by comparing the content of the reorganized somatic genome and the intact germline genome. The project will use available Tetrahymena genome sequences to generate a genome browser that will map the retained and eliminated regions, using the intact genome as a reference. Previous research revealed that a regulatory protein called Lia3 is critical for the accurate removal of a subset of the eliminated sequences.  The genome browser will be used to compare the DNA of normal cells to DNA from cells lacking LIA3 to identify all the sequences for which elimination boundaries are inaccurately defined when this protein is absent. Preliminary experiments have revealed that the sequences controlled by Lia3 contain guanine (G)-rich sequences positioned about 50 base pairs from each boundary.  Lia3 binds these sequences when they form G-quadruplex DNA, a four-stranded DNA structure.  This represents a novel DNA binding activity, and the project will thoroughly characterize both the ability of Lia3 to bind this non-standard DNA structure and elucidate how this structure can serve to organize the genome. In addition, the Tetrahymena genome encodes three other proteins that are similar to Lia3 in sequence and gene expression, and the project will test the hypothesis that each of these proteins identifies the boundaries of a distinct subset of eliminated DNA.  Together, these approaches will characterize a previously unknown mechanism that eukaryotic cells use to define boundaries between genes and non-coding DNA and provide clear evidence that G-quadruplex structures have important regulatory roles.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>09/03/2014</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/01/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.074</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1412336</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Douglas</FirstName>
<LastName>Chalker</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>L</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Douglas L Chalker</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>dchalker@wustl.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>3149358838</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000439243</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/03/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Ting</FirstName>
<LastName>Wang</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Ting Wang</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>twang@genetics.wustl.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>3147474134</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000641324</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/03/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Washington University</Name>
<CityName>Saint Louis</CityName>
<ZipCode>631304862</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>3147474134</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>CAMPUS BOX 1054</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[1 Brookings Drive]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Missouri</StateName>
<StateCode>MO</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MO01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>068552207</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>WASHINGTON UNIVERSITY, THE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>068552207</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Washington University]]></Name>
<CityName>St. Louis, MO</CityName>
<StateCode>MO</StateCode>
<ZipCode>631304899</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[1 Brookings Drive]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Missouri</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MO01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1112</Code>
<Text>Genetic Mechanisms</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7275</Code>
<Text>Cross-BIO Activities</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1112</Code>
<Text>GENES AND GENOME SYSTEMS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7275</Code>
<Text>CROSS-EF ACTIVITIES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7465</Code>
<Text>NANOSCALE BIO CORE</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9178</Code>
<Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9179</Code>
<Text>GRADUATE INVOLVEMENT</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9251</Code>
<Text>REU SUPP-Res Exp for Ugrd Supp</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0114</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0116</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~340000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2016~170000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The genomes of eukaryotic organisms contain large numbers of transposable elements and other DNA sequences, often referred to as ?junk? DNA, which must be kept relatively inactive so as ensure the stability of genome structure and proper gene expression levels. This project investigated mechanisms used by the ciliated protozoan <em>Tetrahymena thermophila</em> to partition these parts of the genome into specialized DNA-protein structures, which, in this organism leads to the physical removal of junk DNA from their developing somatic genome. By investigating how this organism distinguishes its junk DNA from the rest of the genome, the research uncovered new ways by which eukaryotes are able to differential regulate adjacent regions with genomes that have distinct functions.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>The key results from this research, which represents the <strong>intellectual merit</strong> of the project, included the identification and characterization of proteins and DNA sequences that determine the boundaries between the parts of the genome that are eliminated during somatic genome differentiation from the rest of the genome, including genes, that must remain in the genome to keep the cells alive. Specifically, the discovery that the Lia3 protein defines the boundaries of hundreds of junk DNA segments from the rest of the genome represented the first description of a protein that controls the accuracy of the DNA elimination process. The detailed characterization of Lia3 revealed that it is a DNA binding protein that recognizes a non-canonical DNA structure called a guanine quadruplex (G4), a finding that provided one of the most convincing cases that such alternative structures can form and have key regulatory roles in cells. This is one of the few examples discoved in any organism in which a deletion of a protein that binds G4 DNA in biochemical assays is known to affect loci that contain quadruplex-forming sequences. The work also revealed an unrecognized potential for distally localized guanine-rich sequences to interact with each other and regulate genetic processes.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>The project characterized a second protein, Lia3-like 1 (Ltl1) to demonstrate that it controls the boundaries of eliminated junk DNA loci that are distinct from those regulated by Lia3. Ltl1 shares amino acid similarity with Lia3 and was likewise shown to bind DNA. Nevertheless, Ltl1 binds specific double-stranded DNA sequences, not G4 DNA, which Lia3 binds. Our finding that a family of related proteins regulate different subsets of junk DNA loci while binding different sequences/structure provides new insights into how distinct chromatin domains may be partitioned in genomes. Lia3 and its related proteins have structural similarities to DNA binding domains of proteins encoded by transposable elements. This raises the interesting possibility that these genome boundary regulators evolved by the process of transposon sequence domestication. Future exploration into this possibility will provide new understanding into the evolution of genome regulatory proteins. These results were disseminated through the publication of three research studies.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>The project also fostered collarborative research that was disseminated through publication. It promoted the completion and publication of a study that described the role of an essential RNA helicase protein in controlling chromosome fragmentation and new telomere addition that occurs during <em>Tetrahymena</em> development. In collaoration with the laboratory of Dr. Sergej Duronvich (Washington University School of Medicine), undergraduate researchers supported by the project help demonstrate that that gene transcripts that contain poly-adenosine (A) stretches, which encode poly-lysine, are hot spots for ribosome stalling and frameshifting, eliciting mRNA surveillance pathways and attenuating protein synthesis in a majority of prokaryotic and eukaryotic organisms. This worked helped define a new mechanism of post-transcriptional genetic regulation.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>In addition of fostering collaborotive research, a major <strong>broader impact</strong> outcome of the project was the training and mentoring of early career scientists, mostly undergraduate students, in the practice of science. Funds budgeted for summer research internships enable such formative experiences for several undergraduates who were recognized for their contributions through authorship on research publications. The project also intitiated the creation of a community research resource, the WashU <em>Tetrahymena</em> epigenome browser, which can be used to examine genomic patterns of epigenetic modifications, fostering genetic investigations. This resource will be continued to be developed to enable future studies. Overall, the project produced several novel research findings in genetics and genomics, contributed to the training of the biololgical research workforce, and created new research infrastructure.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 12/29/2019<br>      Modified by: Douglas&nbsp;L&nbsp;Chalker</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The genomes of eukaryotic organisms contain large numbers of transposable elements and other DNA sequences, often referred to as ?junk? DNA, which must be kept relatively inactive so as ensure the stability of genome structure and proper gene expression levels. This project investigated mechanisms used by the ciliated protozoan Tetrahymena thermophila to partition these parts of the genome into specialized DNA-protein structures, which, in this organism leads to the physical removal of junk DNA from their developing somatic genome. By investigating how this organism distinguishes its junk DNA from the rest of the genome, the research uncovered new ways by which eukaryotes are able to differential regulate adjacent regions with genomes that have distinct functions.     The key results from this research, which represents the intellectual merit of the project, included the identification and characterization of proteins and DNA sequences that determine the boundaries between the parts of the genome that are eliminated during somatic genome differentiation from the rest of the genome, including genes, that must remain in the genome to keep the cells alive. Specifically, the discovery that the Lia3 protein defines the boundaries of hundreds of junk DNA segments from the rest of the genome represented the first description of a protein that controls the accuracy of the DNA elimination process. The detailed characterization of Lia3 revealed that it is a DNA binding protein that recognizes a non-canonical DNA structure called a guanine quadruplex (G4), a finding that provided one of the most convincing cases that such alternative structures can form and have key regulatory roles in cells. This is one of the few examples discoved in any organism in which a deletion of a protein that binds G4 DNA in biochemical assays is known to affect loci that contain quadruplex-forming sequences. The work also revealed an unrecognized potential for distally localized guanine-rich sequences to interact with each other and regulate genetic processes.     The project characterized a second protein, Lia3-like 1 (Ltl1) to demonstrate that it controls the boundaries of eliminated junk DNA loci that are distinct from those regulated by Lia3. Ltl1 shares amino acid similarity with Lia3 and was likewise shown to bind DNA. Nevertheless, Ltl1 binds specific double-stranded DNA sequences, not G4 DNA, which Lia3 binds. Our finding that a family of related proteins regulate different subsets of junk DNA loci while binding different sequences/structure provides new insights into how distinct chromatin domains may be partitioned in genomes. Lia3 and its related proteins have structural similarities to DNA binding domains of proteins encoded by transposable elements. This raises the interesting possibility that these genome boundary regulators evolved by the process of transposon sequence domestication. Future exploration into this possibility will provide new understanding into the evolution of genome regulatory proteins. These results were disseminated through the publication of three research studies.     The project also fostered collarborative research that was disseminated through publication. It promoted the completion and publication of a study that described the role of an essential RNA helicase protein in controlling chromosome fragmentation and new telomere addition that occurs during Tetrahymena development. In collaoration with the laboratory of Dr. Sergej Duronvich (Washington University School of Medicine), undergraduate researchers supported by the project help demonstrate that that gene transcripts that contain poly-adenosine (A) stretches, which encode poly-lysine, are hot spots for ribosome stalling and frameshifting, eliciting mRNA surveillance pathways and attenuating protein synthesis in a majority of prokaryotic and eukaryotic organisms. This worked helped define a new mechanism of post-transcriptional genetic regulation.     In addition of fostering collaborotive research, a major broader impact outcome of the project was the training and mentoring of early career scientists, mostly undergraduate students, in the practice of science. Funds budgeted for summer research internships enable such formative experiences for several undergraduates who were recognized for their contributions through authorship on research publications. The project also intitiated the creation of a community research resource, the WashU Tetrahymena epigenome browser, which can be used to examine genomic patterns of epigenetic modifications, fostering genetic investigations. This resource will be continued to be developed to enable future studies. Overall, the project produced several novel research findings in genetics and genomics, contributed to the training of the biololgical research workforce, and created new research infrastructure.       Last Modified: 12/29/2019       Submitted by: Douglas L Chalker]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
