<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>The Role of Gas in the Evolution of Galaxies</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2014</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>500016.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>500016</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03020000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>AST</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Astronomical Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Richard Barvainis</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>One of the principal unsolved problems in modern astrophysics is the formation and evolution of galaxies. Astronomers wish to understand when galaxies &amp;#64257;rst develop, as well as how star formation evolves over the history of the universe. The ultimate goal of this proposal is to develop a physical understanding, informed by observations of galaxies in the nearby and distant universe, of some of the main processes that shape galaxies.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The Principal Investigator and collaborators will use new observations, including those with the Atacama Large Millimeter/submillimeter Array (ALMA) and the Plateau de Bure Interferometer (PdBI), to study a number of topics that are required to improve our understanding of galaxy evolution. In a multi-pronged strategy, the team will study the evolution of gas fractions and depletion time scales in main sequence galaxies during cosmic time, the mass dependence of gas fractions, the dominant feedback and quenching mechanisms in field galaxies, the physics of galaxy outflows, and the physical conditions in molecular clouds in low metallicity and starburst galaxies. This research will lead to a greatly improved understanding of galaxy evolution, with ALMA observations forming a central component of the research.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The PI will also work with the Graduate Resources Advancing Diversity with Maryland Astronomy and Physics initiative (GRAD-MAP), which is a program designed to lessen the barriers faced by minorities to enter astronomy and physics graduate school. Finally, the PI will continue the development of the Astronomy Workshop Extragalactic (AWE) website, which provides a suite of online demonstrations of astronomical concepts.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/22/2014</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/22/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1412419</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Alberto</FirstName>
<LastName>Bolatto</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Alberto Bolatto</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>bolatto@astro.umd.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>3014056269</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000506066</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/22/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Maryland, College Park</Name>
<CityName>College Park</CityName>
<ZipCode>207425141</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>3014056269</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>3112 LEE BLDG 7809 Regents Drive</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Maryland</StateName>
<StateCode>MD</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MD05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>790934285</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF MARYLAND, COLLEGE PARK</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>003256088</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Maryland, College Park]]></Name>
<CityName>College Park</CityName>
<StateCode>MD</StateCode>
<ZipCode>207425141</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[3112 LEE BLDG 7809 Regents Drive]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Maryland</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MD05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1217</Code>
<Text>EXTRAGALACTIC ASTRON &amp; COSMOLO</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1207</Code>
<Text>OBSERVATIONAL ASTRONOMY</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0114</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~500016</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Galaxies form early in the history of the universe, and grow through cosmic time by gaining mass in the form of gas and stars. In the process of doing that, galaxies also expel gas through a phenomenon known as galactic winds. The mass transferred in these winds can be the main mechanismo to shut down star formation through gas loss. The engines of this phenomenon are massive star formation itself, and growing supermassive black holes in active galactic nuclei. This project looks at the physics determining how gas becomes stars inside galaxies, and how part of this gas is expelled from the system and returned to the circum-galactic and inter-galactic medium.</p> <p><br />Some of the results from this work are measurements of fundamental quantities in nearby galaxies, such as the thermal gas pressure pressure in their disks (Herrera-Camus et al. 2017), and the amount of molecular gas in systems very poor in heavy elements and dust (Jameson et al. 2018). We have also measured the amount and structure of gas flowing out of galaxies that host massive galactic winds driven by either a starburst (Walter et al. 2017) or an growing supermassive black hole (Veilleux et al. 2017). The high spatial resolution measurements of the outflowing mlecular gas in the nearest nuclear starburst galaxy (NGC253) allow us to draw conclusions about the driving mechanisms (radiation pressure by itself is not able to explain the observations, Walter et al. 2017), gas properties (molecular line ratios show that the molecular streamers in the outflow are likely high density, Walter et al. 2017), and mass outflow rate (the carbon monoxide line ratios show that the emission is not optically thin, which caused us to revise our "minimum estimate" of the mass loss rate upward, Zschaechner et al. 2018). These measurements are crucial to guide and constrain modeling and theories of galaxy evolution through cosmic time.</p> <p><br />This project provided training for graduate students and postdocs. As part of the broader outcomes we also continued developing the Astronomy Workshop Extragalactic suite of Java apps to present and explore astronomical results. We have also continued effort in GRAD-MAP, a project to help under-represented minorities gain research experience to put them in a better place to apply to graduate school in Physics and Astronomy.&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 12/17/2018<br>      Modified by: Alberto&nbsp;Bolatto</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Galaxies form early in the history of the universe, and grow through cosmic time by gaining mass in the form of gas and stars. In the process of doing that, galaxies also expel gas through a phenomenon known as galactic winds. The mass transferred in these winds can be the main mechanismo to shut down star formation through gas loss. The engines of this phenomenon are massive star formation itself, and growing supermassive black holes in active galactic nuclei. This project looks at the physics determining how gas becomes stars inside galaxies, and how part of this gas is expelled from the system and returned to the circum-galactic and inter-galactic medium.   Some of the results from this work are measurements of fundamental quantities in nearby galaxies, such as the thermal gas pressure pressure in their disks (Herrera-Camus et al. 2017), and the amount of molecular gas in systems very poor in heavy elements and dust (Jameson et al. 2018). We have also measured the amount and structure of gas flowing out of galaxies that host massive galactic winds driven by either a starburst (Walter et al. 2017) or an growing supermassive black hole (Veilleux et al. 2017). The high spatial resolution measurements of the outflowing mlecular gas in the nearest nuclear starburst galaxy (NGC253) allow us to draw conclusions about the driving mechanisms (radiation pressure by itself is not able to explain the observations, Walter et al. 2017), gas properties (molecular line ratios show that the molecular streamers in the outflow are likely high density, Walter et al. 2017), and mass outflow rate (the carbon monoxide line ratios show that the emission is not optically thin, which caused us to revise our "minimum estimate" of the mass loss rate upward, Zschaechner et al. 2018). These measurements are crucial to guide and constrain modeling and theories of galaxy evolution through cosmic time.   This project provided training for graduate students and postdocs. As part of the broader outcomes we also continued developing the Astronomy Workshop Extragalactic suite of Java apps to present and explore astronomical results. We have also continued effort in GRAD-MAP, a project to help under-represented minorities gain research experience to put them in a better place to apply to graduate school in Physics and Astronomy.           Last Modified: 12/17/2018       Submitted by: Alberto Bolatto]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
