<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Dynamics of Large Networks</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2014</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>150277.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>150277</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DMS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Victor Roytburd</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>vroytbur@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032928584</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>A number of very important problems in science and technology lead to the analysis of large networks of interacting dynamical systems. Our ability to predict epileptic seizures, to effectively control a power grid, or to coordinate a group of robots rely on our understanding of the principles underlying collective behavior in coupled dynamical systems. Many natural and man-made networks around us feature extraordinary richness and complexity of interconnections. Mathematical modeling of such networks poses new challenges for nonlinear science and requires new approaches incorporating combinatorial and probabilistic methods into dynamical analysis of complex systems. Graph Theory holds an extraordinary potential to inspire new powerful techniques for extended dynamical systems and applications to technological, social, economic, and biological networks. In this research, the Principal Investigator (PI) combines state-of-the-art techniques of Graph Theory with analytical methods for Dynamical Systems to develop an effective set of tools for studying coupled dynamical systems and their applications in neuroscience. The results of this research will be integrated into graduate courses in Dynamical Systems and Mathematical Neuroscience. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;In this project, the PI develops a unified approach for studying dynamical networks as evolution equations on three types of spatial domains: Caley graphs, quasirandom graphs, and graph limits. For problems in each class, analytical and algebraic techniques, which mesh well with the underlying spatial structures, are identified. These techniques are used to study stability of spatial patterns in systems of coupled phase oscillators on Caley graphs, synchronization in systems of coupled chaotic maps, and differential equations on different random graphs including small-world and graphs that exhibit power law behavior, as well as those that exhibit temporally structured stable patterns in a neural network model of learning. The PI seeks systematic ways for describing the role of network connectivity in shaping the dynamics in coupled systems. This work is aimed toward development of a theory for interacting dynamical systems on regular and random graphs.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/03/2014</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/03/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1412066</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Georgi</FirstName>
<LastName>Medvedev</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Georgi Medvedev</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>medvedev@drexel.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2158956612</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000284708</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/03/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Drexel University</Name>
<CityName>Philadelphia</CityName>
<ZipCode>191021119</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2158956342</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1505 Race St, 10th Floor</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Pennsylvania</StateName>
<StateCode>PA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>PA03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>002604817</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>DREXEL UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>002604817</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Drexel University]]></Name>
<CityName>Philadelphia</CityName>
<StateCode>PA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>191042737</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[3201 Arch Street]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Pennsylvania</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>PA03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1266</Code>
<Text>APPLIED MATHEMATICS</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8396</Code>
<Text>Clean Energy Technology</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8609</Code>
<Text>Other Energy Research</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0114</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~150277</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p style="text-align: left;">&nbsp;This research is aimed at developing mathematical techniques for interacting dynamical systems on regular and random graphs. These dynamical models are used in different branches of science and engineering ranging from statistical physics, to technological, social, and biological networks. Real-world networks feature a rich variety of connectivity patterns, which can be regular, random, or combination of thereof.&nbsp; Understanding and quantifying the effects of network topology on&nbsp; dynamics presents a&nbsp; unique challenge for mathematical analysis of complex systems. <br /><br /><span>Motivated by applications, the PI and his colleagues studied mathematical models of interacting dynamical systems such as coupled oscillators and coupled nonlinear maps&nbsp; on regular and random graphs. Through studying stability of various dynamical regimes&nbsp; the PI and his colleagues sought to elucidate the link between the network structure and dynamics in interacting dynamical systems. The specific outcomes of this research are as follows. The PI and Tang analyzed synchronization and stability of twisted states in the <span>Kuramoto</span> model of coupled phase oscillators on <span>Caley</span> and random graphs. </span>In another work with Tang, the PI obtained sufficient conditions for synchronization for coupled maps&nbsp; on various graphs including small-world graphs, quasirandom graphs, and expanders. In the joint work with Wright,&nbsp; the PI derived a sufficient condition for nonlinear stability of twisted states in a nonlocal diffusion equations approximating the large networks of coupled oscillators. In this work, stability of twisted states with respect to<span> perturbations in <span>Sobolev</span> and <span>BV</span> norms was established. The work of the PI and <span>Kaliuzhnyi</span>-<span>Verbovetskyi</span>&nbsp; provides the first rigorous results for the continuum limit of the <span>Kuramoto</span> model on sparse graphs. These results are&nbsp; important, because they cover dynamical systems on power law graphs, which have been related to many real-world networks. The results of this work illuminate the role of the network connectivity on stability of coherent structures in large networks of interacting dynamical systems. In particular, this research shows how spatial</span> organization contributes to synchronization,&nbsp; an important mode of collective behavior in diverse physical, biological, and technological networks. Besides providing quantitative results characterizing evolution of&nbsp; coupled systems, this research provides new approaches to studying dynamics of large systems on regular and random graphs. <br /><br /><span>The PI gave 16 invited presentations on the results of this research, and organized two <span>minisimposia</span> at international conferences on applied dynamical systems. One Ph.D. student was trained in the course of this project.</span><span> In addition, an undergraduate and a graduate student participated in summer research projects. The results of this research were incorporated in the graduate courses on applied probability and statistics and&nbsp; mathematical <span>neuroscience</span> taught by the PI at Drexel University.</span></p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 10/29/2017<br>      Modified by: Georgi&nbsp;Medvedev</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ This research is aimed at developing mathematical techniques for interacting dynamical systems on regular and random graphs. These dynamical models are used in different branches of science and engineering ranging from statistical physics, to technological, social, and biological networks. Real-world networks feature a rich variety of connectivity patterns, which can be regular, random, or combination of thereof.  Understanding and quantifying the effects of network topology on  dynamics presents a  unique challenge for mathematical analysis of complex systems.   Motivated by applications, the PI and his colleagues studied mathematical models of interacting dynamical systems such as coupled oscillators and coupled nonlinear maps  on regular and random graphs. Through studying stability of various dynamical regimes  the PI and his colleagues sought to elucidate the link between the network structure and dynamics in interacting dynamical systems. The specific outcomes of this research are as follows. The PI and Tang analyzed synchronization and stability of twisted states in the Kuramoto model of coupled phase oscillators on Caley and random graphs. In another work with Tang, the PI obtained sufficient conditions for synchronization for coupled maps  on various graphs including small-world graphs, quasirandom graphs, and expanders. In the joint work with Wright,  the PI derived a sufficient condition for nonlinear stability of twisted states in a nonlocal diffusion equations approximating the large networks of coupled oscillators. In this work, stability of twisted states with respect to perturbations in Sobolev and BV norms was established. The work of the PI and Kaliuzhnyi-Verbovetskyi  provides the first rigorous results for the continuum limit of the Kuramoto model on sparse graphs. These results are  important, because they cover dynamical systems on power law graphs, which have been related to many real-world networks. The results of this work illuminate the role of the network connectivity on stability of coherent structures in large networks of interacting dynamical systems. In particular, this research shows how spatial organization contributes to synchronization,  an important mode of collective behavior in diverse physical, biological, and technological networks. Besides providing quantitative results characterizing evolution of  coupled systems, this research provides new approaches to studying dynamics of large systems on regular and random graphs.   The PI gave 16 invited presentations on the results of this research, and organized two minisimposia at international conferences on applied dynamical systems. One Ph.D. student was trained in the course of this project. In addition, an undergraduate and a graduate student participated in summer research projects. The results of this research were incorporated in the graduate courses on applied probability and statistics and  mathematical neuroscience taught by the PI at Drexel University.       Last Modified: 10/29/2017       Submitted by: Georgi Medvedev]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
