<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>The Astrophysical Multimessenger Observatory Network</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2014</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>384373.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>384373</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03010000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>PHY</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Physics</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Jean Allen</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>jcallen@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032928783</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Astrophysical phenomena, and particularly the most energetic, emit a range of particles from photons to neutrinos and cosmic rays.  They may also produce gravitational radiation.  These "messengers" carry details of the energetics and physical conditions in these sources.  The Astrophysical Multimessenger Observatory Network (AMON) aims to discover new particle astrophysics phenomena by merging the world's leading multimessenger observatories into a single data system for the first time.  The facilities to be linked by AMON observe high-energy neutrinos (the IceCube and ANTARES Neutrino Observatories), the strongly-interacting nuclei observed as cosmic rays (the Pierre Auger Cosmic Ray Observatory), and in future phases, the oscillations in the fabric of space-time manifested as gravitational waves (the Advanced LIGO and VIRGO gravitational-wave detectors). These are complemented by current and next-generation gamma-ray facilities, including the Swift and Fermi satellites and the HAWC gamma-ray observatory.  Over the three year award period, the PIs will construct a prototype AMON network with the scientific goal of discovering the first jointly-emitting gamma-ray and high-energy neutrino sources.  In conjunction with the AMON project, the PIs will also initiate and run "AstroTxt," an applied educational experience that will involve central Pennsylvania middle and high school students directly in real-time AMON operations. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;AMON will assemble the first terabyte-scale multimessenger database and develop tools for data exchange and real-time correlation analysis, establishing a superior level of interoperability.  This new and transparent sharing of data promises significant scientific advances:  Data from individual facilities that in isolation cannot be interpreted as the detection of an astrophysical source, may achieve a higher level of significance in a joint coincident analysis of data from multiple participating observatories.  Each candidate astrophysical signal will be packaged as an electronic AMON Alert and distributed to a network of follow-up facilities for counterpart searches and characterization.  Identification of an x-ray, optical, or radio counterpart will serve to confirm the astrophysical nature of an event and enable a broad range of detailed studies, including distance or redshift measurement, using traditional astronomical techniques.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/18/2014</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>04/05/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1412633</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Douglas</FirstName>
<LastName>Cowen</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>F</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Douglas F Cowen</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>cowen@phys.psu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>8148635943</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000236648</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/18/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Derek</FirstName>
<LastName>Fox</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Derek Fox</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>dfox@astro.psu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>8148654700</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000473647</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/18/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Miguel</FirstName>
<LastName>Mostafa</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>A</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Miguel A Mostafa</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>miguel@psu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>8148654306</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000297514</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/18/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Pennsylvania State Univ University Park</Name>
<CityName>University Park</CityName>
<ZipCode>168021503</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>8148651372</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>201 Old Main</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Pennsylvania</StateName>
<StateCode>PA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>PA05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>003403953</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>PENNSYLVANIA STATE UNIVERSITY, THE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>003403953</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Pennsylvania State Univ University Park]]></Name>
<CityName>University Park</CityName>
<StateCode>PA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>168021503</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[201 Old Main]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Pennsylvania</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>PA05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1643</Code>
<Text>Particle Astrophysics/Cosmic P</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7244</Code>
<Text>COMPUTATIONAL PHYSICS</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7433</Code>
<Text>CyberInfra Frmwrk 21st (CIF21)</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7483</Code>
<Text>PHYSICS OF THE UNIVERSE</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7569</Code>
<Text>CYBERINFRASTRUCTURE/SCIENCE</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8084</Code>
<Text>CDS&amp;E</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0114</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0115</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0116</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~122441</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2015~135103</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2016~126829</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The Astrophysical Multimessenger Observatory Network (AMON) realized and operates a data network that integrates, for the first time, the global science community&rsquo;s most ambitious observatories of high-energy astrophysical phenomena into a single comprehensive alert system with a combinedsensitivity greater than that of any single component facility. AMON links the World's leading high-energy neutrino, cosmic-ray, gamma-ray, and gravitational-wave observatories by performing real-time coincidence searches for multimessenger signals. The resulting coincidences are distributed in the form of electronic alerts for real-time follow-up observation. Individual facilities have already provided the discoveries of astrophysical neutrinos and gravitational waves. But the actual sources of these messengers cannot be identified with the current generation of observatories. The main goal of AMON is to probe the high-energy universe, and identify the astrophysical sources from the multimessenger coincident signals. This identification will yield exciting breakthroughs in our understanding of the universe and fundamental physics, including how and where ultra-high-energy particles are produced.</p> <p>AMON collates burst-compatible data from each individual facility, in real-time, to identify spatially and temporally coincident events detected by two or more observatories. These data do not generally represent a significant detection at any single observatory, but they may easily achieve a high level of significance in a joint coincident analysis using appropriately designed algorithms. For example, a single neutrino observed by the IceCube Neutrino Observatory cannot be ascribed an astrophysical origin, but if it is coincident in arrival time and direction with a gamma-ray detection, together they would represent an a priori highly unlikely occurrence that could be cleanly interpreted as the signature of an astrophysical source. In fact, AMON has recently facilitated the first identification of a deep-space source of high-energy neutrinos. IceCube detected a high-energy neutrino on September 22, 2017. The IceCube-AMON alert (distributed automatically within seconds of the neutrino detection) triggered a sequence of X-ray and ultraviolet observations with NASA&rsquo;s Neil Gehrels Swift Observatory, and led to further studies with over a dozen other observatories around the world. These observations provided strong evidence that the neutrino was generated by a flaring supermassive black hole (or &ldquo;blazar&rdquo;) known to astronomers as TXS 0506+056. Thanks to the automated trigger from AMON, Swift was observing within four hours of the neutrino detection, and was able to identify right away the flaring blazar as a possible counterpart. The high-energy neutrino detection and the source identification are the focus of two Science papers and a July 12, 2018 press conference at the National Science Foundation in Washington, D.C.&nbsp;</p> <p>AMON ultimately aims to be a nexus for all types of multimessenger astrophysics research, enabling searches of all messenger databases. This ambitious objective informed the design of our network.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 07/10/2018<br>      Modified by: Miguel&nbsp;A&nbsp;Mostafa</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The Astrophysical Multimessenger Observatory Network (AMON) realized and operates a data network that integrates, for the first time, the global science community?s most ambitious observatories of high-energy astrophysical phenomena into a single comprehensive alert system with a combinedsensitivity greater than that of any single component facility. AMON links the World's leading high-energy neutrino, cosmic-ray, gamma-ray, and gravitational-wave observatories by performing real-time coincidence searches for multimessenger signals. The resulting coincidences are distributed in the form of electronic alerts for real-time follow-up observation. Individual facilities have already provided the discoveries of astrophysical neutrinos and gravitational waves. But the actual sources of these messengers cannot be identified with the current generation of observatories. The main goal of AMON is to probe the high-energy universe, and identify the astrophysical sources from the multimessenger coincident signals. This identification will yield exciting breakthroughs in our understanding of the universe and fundamental physics, including how and where ultra-high-energy particles are produced.  AMON collates burst-compatible data from each individual facility, in real-time, to identify spatially and temporally coincident events detected by two or more observatories. These data do not generally represent a significant detection at any single observatory, but they may easily achieve a high level of significance in a joint coincident analysis using appropriately designed algorithms. For example, a single neutrino observed by the IceCube Neutrino Observatory cannot be ascribed an astrophysical origin, but if it is coincident in arrival time and direction with a gamma-ray detection, together they would represent an a priori highly unlikely occurrence that could be cleanly interpreted as the signature of an astrophysical source. In fact, AMON has recently facilitated the first identification of a deep-space source of high-energy neutrinos. IceCube detected a high-energy neutrino on September 22, 2017. The IceCube-AMON alert (distributed automatically within seconds of the neutrino detection) triggered a sequence of X-ray and ultraviolet observations with NASA?s Neil Gehrels Swift Observatory, and led to further studies with over a dozen other observatories around the world. These observations provided strong evidence that the neutrino was generated by a flaring supermassive black hole (or "blazar") known to astronomers as TXS 0506+056. Thanks to the automated trigger from AMON, Swift was observing within four hours of the neutrino detection, and was able to identify right away the flaring blazar as a possible counterpart. The high-energy neutrino detection and the source identification are the focus of two Science papers and a July 12, 2018 press conference at the National Science Foundation in Washington, D.C.   AMON ultimately aims to be a nexus for all types of multimessenger astrophysics research, enabling searches of all messenger databases. This ambitious objective informed the design of our network.       Last Modified: 07/10/2018       Submitted by: Miguel A Mostafa]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
