<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Texas Analysis and Mathematical Physics Symposium</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>06/01/2014</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2015</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>18963.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>18963</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DMS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Victor Roytburd</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>vroytbur@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032928584</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This award provides support for the 2014 Texas Analysis and Mathematical Physics Symposium that will take place at the University of Texas at Austin during  the Fall 2014 semester. The Symposium will focus on the area where probability theory, dynamical systems theory, spectral theory, and partial differential equations intersect and interact. The Symposium is a forum for regional specialists in mathematical physics and related areas of analysis to become familiar with the latest problems and present their own results; in addition it introduces young mathematicians to the current state of the subject. More information, including a list of speakers and abstracts, registration information, and an archive of the past symposium can be found at the website of the meeting: https://www.ma.utexas.edu/users/tc/TeXAMP/TeXAMP-2014/TeXAMP-2014.html&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The Texas Analysis and Mathematical Physics Symposium is a regional weekend meeting held annually, hosted in turn by Rice University, and the University of Texas at Austin. It is intended for the participation of around 50 people (including 25 non-local graduate students). The workshop brings together many senior mathematicians from Texas and neighboring states, who may not otherwise have a chance to discuss mathematics together throughout the year. Structurally the symposium consists of 8 main lectures given by nationally recognized leaders in the field, and contributed sessions for advanced graduate students and participating researchers from regional universities, to present their work. This will provide graduate students with an opportunity to obtain feedback from senior faculty from other departments. The networking activities made possible by the Symposium will prove to be a valuable experience for young researchers. The Symposium encourages and financially supports participation by students, recent Ph.D. recipients, and members of groups underrepresented in mathematics.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>04/15/2014</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>04/15/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1412627</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Thomas</FirstName>
<LastName>Chen</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Thomas Chen</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>tc@math.utexas.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5124717180</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000179148</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/15/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Texas at Austin</Name>
<CityName>Austin</CityName>
<ZipCode>787595316</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5124716424</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>3925 W Braker Lane, Ste 3.340</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Texas</StateName>
<StateCode>TX</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>10</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>TX10</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>170230239</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF TEXAS AT AUSTIN</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>042000273</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Texas at Austin]]></Name>
<CityName>Austin</CityName>
<StateCode>TX</StateCode>
<ZipCode>787595316</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[3925 W Braker Lane, Ste 3.340]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Texas</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>10</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>TX10</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1266</Code>
<Text>APPLIED MATHEMATICS</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1281</Code>
<Text>ANALYSIS PROGRAM</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7556</Code>
<Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0114</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~18963</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The Texas Analysis and Mathematical Physics Symposium (TeXAMP) is a regional weekend meeting held annually. The first two conferences were hosted by Rice University, and the University of Texas at Austin.</p> <p>It is intended for the participation of around 50 people (including 25 non-local graduate students). The workshop brings together many senior mathematicians from Texas and neighboring states, who may not otherwise have a chance to discuss mathematics together throughout the year. We take great interest in the advancement of graduate students and recent Ph.D.s.; they are a main focus of this funding proposal.</p> <h4>Project Report</h4> <p>This award provided support for the second Texas Analysis and Mathematical Physics Symposium, which took place November 21-23, 2014 on the campus of the University of Texas at Austin. This is a regional mathematics conference with focus on active research areas in Analysis and Mathematical Physics. &nbsp;</p> <div class="page" title="Page 2"> <div class="section"> <div class="layoutArea"> <div class="column"> <p><span>The invited talks were presented by the following leading experts in their areas: Francois Baccelli (UT Austin), Sourav Chatterjee (Stanford University), Serguei Denissov (University of Wisconsin), Alice Guionnet (MIT), Rowan Killip (UCLA), Dong Li (University of British Columbia), Gigliola Staffilani (MIT), Michael I. Weinstein (Columbia University). The topics covered a broad range of key advances in mathematical research.&nbsp;</span></p> <p><span>In addition, participants were given the opportunity to present contributed talks, in three sessions: In Session 1 (Analysis and Mathematical Physics), the speakers were Ngoc Do (Texas A&amp;M University), Milivoje Lukic (University of Toronto), Darren Ong (University of Oklahoma), Rajinder Mavi (University of Virginia), Tracy Weyand (Baylor University), Jon Harrison (Baylor University). In Session 2 (Analysis and PDE), the speakers were Younghun Hong (UT Austin), Dana Mendelson (MIT), Kenneth Taliaferro (UT Austin), Yannick Sire (<span>University of Aix-Marseille</span>), Maja Taskovic (UT Austin). In Session 3 (Applied Mathematics and Mathematical Physics), the speakers were Vladimir Dragovic (UT Dallas), Sergey Dyachenko (University of Arizona), Alexey Sukhinin (Southern Methodist University), Rishika Rupam (Texas A&amp;M University), Baofeng Feng (UT Pan-American), Youngxin Jiang (Hohai University).&nbsp;This list includes a large proportion of junior researchers, ranging from graduate students to junior faculty. Overall, there were 56 registered participants, with many regional universities being represented.</span></p> </div> </div> </div> </div> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 08/24/2015<br>      Modified by: Thomas&nbsp;Chen</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The Texas Analysis and Mathematical Physics Symposium (TeXAMP) is a regional weekend meeting held annually. The first two conferences were hosted by Rice University, and the University of Texas at Austin.  It is intended for the participation of around 50 people (including 25 non-local graduate students). The workshop brings together many senior mathematicians from Texas and neighboring states, who may not otherwise have a chance to discuss mathematics together throughout the year. We take great interest in the advancement of graduate students and recent Ph.D.s.; they are a main focus of this funding proposal. Project Report  This award provided support for the second Texas Analysis and Mathematical Physics Symposium, which took place November 21-23, 2014 on the campus of the University of Texas at Austin. This is a regional mathematics conference with focus on active research areas in Analysis and Mathematical Physics.        The invited talks were presented by the following leading experts in their areas: Francois Baccelli (UT Austin), Sourav Chatterjee (Stanford University), Serguei Denissov (University of Wisconsin), Alice Guionnet (MIT), Rowan Killip (UCLA), Dong Li (University of British Columbia), Gigliola Staffilani (MIT), Michael I. Weinstein (Columbia University). The topics covered a broad range of key advances in mathematical research.   In addition, participants were given the opportunity to present contributed talks, in three sessions: In Session 1 (Analysis and Mathematical Physics), the speakers were Ngoc Do (Texas A&amp;M University), Milivoje Lukic (University of Toronto), Darren Ong (University of Oklahoma), Rajinder Mavi (University of Virginia), Tracy Weyand (Baylor University), Jon Harrison (Baylor University). In Session 2 (Analysis and PDE), the speakers were Younghun Hong (UT Austin), Dana Mendelson (MIT), Kenneth Taliaferro (UT Austin), Yannick Sire (University of Aix-Marseille), Maja Taskovic (UT Austin). In Session 3 (Applied Mathematics and Mathematical Physics), the speakers were Vladimir Dragovic (UT Dallas), Sergey Dyachenko (University of Arizona), Alexey Sukhinin (Southern Methodist University), Rishika Rupam (Texas A&amp;M University), Baofeng Feng (UT Pan-American), Youngxin Jiang (Hohai University). This list includes a large proportion of junior researchers, ranging from graduate students to junior faculty. Overall, there were 56 registered participants, with many regional universities being represented.              Last Modified: 08/24/2015       Submitted by: Thomas Chen]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
