<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Stabilization of Periodic Regimes in Symmetric Systems with Memory via Time-Delayed Feedback Control</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2014</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>152587.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>152587</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DMS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Victor Roytburd</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>vroytbur@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032928584</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The symmetric character of fundamental laws of nature manifests itself in an abundance of symmetries in natural phenomena. Modeling of such phenomena by networks of interacting oscillators is common in various fields of science and technology ranging from electronics and optical communications to neurology and medicine. Controlling symmetric features of spontaneously generated oscillatory patterns in such networks constitutes a substantial challenge. The goal of this project is to develop new methods that allow simple but effective control of performance of complex symmetric networks of oscillators. The work is focused on non-invasive methods of control that allow achievement of the desired behavior with minimal forcing of the system and that can be easily adopted for practical implementations (e.g. in electronic circuits). The educational component of this project aims to allow students from the undergraduate to the post-graduate levels to actively participate in this research, working on concrete networks of oscillators with specific symmetry groups. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Stabilization of unstable systems is one of the most important problems in applied nonlinear science. Natural symmetries of real life systems lead to multiple periodic regimes and complicate the stabilization problem. The objective of this research is to develop methods for stabilization of unstable periodic regimes in symmetric systems by a combination of delayed feedback control and linear proportional control. The focus of the project will be on two types of symmetric systems with memory, namely systems with hysteresis and with delay. The method of stabilization of unstable periodic orbits (UPO) by non-invasive delayed feedback control (due to Pyragas) has been successfully tested against different types of models of chaotic systems. During the last two years, the co-PIs have been developing computerized symbolic numerical tools and supporting theoretical framework for localization and classification of UPOs in models of systems admitting large symmetry groups. The efficiency of these methods is based on development of the equivariant degree theory and its applications. This project will combine these new methods with a properly adapted version of Pyragas' control to achieve stabilization of UPOs in systems with complex symmetries. It is expected that these methods will be instrumental in navigating the system to various oscillation patterns (related to different spatio-temporal symmetries of UPOs) of practical interest. The application component of the project includes stabilization of UPOs in models of networks of electronic circuits, networks of hysteretic oscillators, and symmetrically coupled semiconductor lasers.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/22/2014</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/22/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1413223</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Wieslaw</FirstName>
<LastName>Krawcewicz</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Wieslaw Krawcewicz</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>wieslaw@utdallas.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>9728836620</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000544492</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/22/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Zalman</FirstName>
<LastName>Balanov</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Zalman Balanov</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>balanov@utdallas.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>9728836591</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000584315</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/22/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Dmitry</FirstName>
<LastName>Rachinskiy</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Dmitry Rachinskiy</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>dxr124030@utdallas.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>9728836697</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000632664</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/22/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Texas at Dallas</Name>
<CityName>Richardson</CityName>
<ZipCode>750803021</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>9728832313</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>800 W. Campbell Rd., AD15</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Texas</StateName>
<StateCode>TX</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>32</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>TX32</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>800188161</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF TEXAS AT DALLAS</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>042000273</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Texas at Dallas]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>TX</StateCode>
<ZipCode>750803021</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Texas</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>32</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>TX32</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1266</Code>
<Text>APPLIED MATHEMATICS</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8396</Code>
<Text>Clean Energy Technology</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8609</Code>
<Text>Other Energy Research</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0114</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~152587</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><strong>Overview: </strong>The control of periodic regimes (such as&nbsp;circadian rhythms, reoccurrence of epidemics, cyclic processes in engineering, molecular vibrations, etc.) is one of the most important problems in nonlinear sciences. The goal of this project was to develop new mathematical methods that allow simple but effective control of performance of complex symmetric networks of oscillators. The four year work on this project was focused on Pyragas type feedback control for non-invasive stabilization of unstable periodic orbits of symmetric systems, development of topological methods&nbsp;for analysis of symmetric patterns of periodic oscillations in systems with memory occurring when equilibrium changes its stability, and analysis of the impact of reversal symmetry on symmetric patterns of periodic regimes. All the goals of this project have been achieved, and the resulting products include:</p> <p>(i) 25 papers published in research journals and&nbsp;9 papers published in juried conference proceedings;&nbsp;</p> <p>(ii) 5 papers accepted for publication in research journals;</p> <p>(iii) 12 more papers submitted for publication in research journals;</p> <p>(iv) 5 graduate students trained by the project successfully completed their PhD degree;</p> <p>(v) an undergraduate student who participated in the project defended his Undergraduate Thesis and co-authored a paper submitted for publication;</p> <p>(vi) a K12 student who participated in the project via a Summer Research Program co-authored a paper submitted for publication.</p> <p><strong> Intellectual merit:</strong> The project developed and tested a general class of non-invasive stabilization algorithms and techniques enabling stabilization of unstable periodic orbits and relative periodic orbits (born via equivariant Hopf bifurcations) of equivariant systems using Pyragas type control. This control uses measurements of both current and past states of the system on order to stabilize the desired regime of operation. The novel control algorithms were applied to modeling of symmetric systems such as electronic circuits and coupled laser systems. The twisted equivariant degree theory has been extended and applied to&nbsp;study relative periodic solutions born via&nbsp;a local equivariant Hopf bifurcations in laser and electro-mechanical systems. Special software (based on GAP&nbsp;programing) was created to support these methods. The developed local methods are equally applicable to systems for which the standard requirements fail to be satisfied and in the settings with approximate data. Brouwer equivariant degree method was adapted to study the local bifurcation of periodic solutions in symmetric reversible systems including delays and non-local interaction. Computational challenges related to the complex nature of the gradient degree based method were overcome in the case of reversible Hamiltonian systems and the method was applied to study vibrations of symmetric molecules. The methodology developed in this project led to a series of further results in related topics.&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;</p> <p><strong>Broader impacts:</strong> The project has opened new possibilities for the implementation of equivariant tools in various applied areas, such as engineering, electronics, robotics, and photonics, and for studying symmetric interactions between physical processes. These methods, especially in the case of specific systems lacking strong smoothness properties, may have indeed a strong impact on the area of non-smooth bifurcation theory. In particular, the participants have proposed non-local (in the parameter space) sufficient conditions for the Hopf bifurcation, which are suitable for analysis of systems with incomplete information about the values of coefficients (known as interval systems in problems of adaptive control). The results on molecular vibrations have a potential for applications in molecular chemistry.&#8232;&#8232;The project had a significant educational component with 8 PhD students (among them 5 defended their PhD), an undergraduate student and a K-12 student being involved. Topic graduate courses related to the project have been offered and the corresponding material is incorporated into the graduate textbook (under development). The Graduate students (among them 2 women and 1 minority) participated in, and made presentation at, national and international conferences, workshops, summer schools and NSF EPASI Program.&nbsp; Trained in this project undergraduate and graduate students had an opportunity to&#8232;(a) learn and conduct research in several science and engineering disciplines;&#8232;(b) gain expertise in several mathematical fields unified under one umbrella: pure, applied, computational mathematics;&#8232;(c) become independent researchers with expertise in equivariant topological methodology which was involved in the project;&#8232;(d) develop competitiveness in reaching their career goals.&#8232;&#8232;The results were disseminated through publications in the top internationally recognized journals, conference presentations and invited presentations worldwide. The co-PIs organized multiple conferences, presented series of lectures at workshops and summer schools and conducted international collaboration aiming to spread the accomplishments of this project. The developed&nbsp;under this project software supporting the equivariant methods has been made available to mathematicians, applied scientists, engineers and&nbsp;educators worldwide.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 11/17/2018<br>      Modified by: Wieslaw&nbsp;Krawcewicz</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Overview: The control of periodic regimes (such as circadian rhythms, reoccurrence of epidemics, cyclic processes in engineering, molecular vibrations, etc.) is one of the most important problems in nonlinear sciences. The goal of this project was to develop new mathematical methods that allow simple but effective control of performance of complex symmetric networks of oscillators. The four year work on this project was focused on Pyragas type feedback control for non-invasive stabilization of unstable periodic orbits of symmetric systems, development of topological methods for analysis of symmetric patterns of periodic oscillations in systems with memory occurring when equilibrium changes its stability, and analysis of the impact of reversal symmetry on symmetric patterns of periodic regimes. All the goals of this project have been achieved, and the resulting products include:  (i) 25 papers published in research journals and 9 papers published in juried conference proceedings;   (ii) 5 papers accepted for publication in research journals;  (iii) 12 more papers submitted for publication in research journals;  (iv) 5 graduate students trained by the project successfully completed their PhD degree;  (v) an undergraduate student who participated in the project defended his Undergraduate Thesis and co-authored a paper submitted for publication;  (vi) a K12 student who participated in the project via a Summer Research Program co-authored a paper submitted for publication.   Intellectual merit: The project developed and tested a general class of non-invasive stabilization algorithms and techniques enabling stabilization of unstable periodic orbits and relative periodic orbits (born via equivariant Hopf bifurcations) of equivariant systems using Pyragas type control. This control uses measurements of both current and past states of the system on order to stabilize the desired regime of operation. The novel control algorithms were applied to modeling of symmetric systems such as electronic circuits and coupled laser systems. The twisted equivariant degree theory has been extended and applied to study relative periodic solutions born via a local equivariant Hopf bifurcations in laser and electro-mechanical systems. Special software (based on GAP programing) was created to support these methods. The developed local methods are equally applicable to systems for which the standard requirements fail to be satisfied and in the settings with approximate data. Brouwer equivariant degree method was adapted to study the local bifurcation of periodic solutions in symmetric reversible systems including delays and non-local interaction. Computational challenges related to the complex nature of the gradient degree based method were overcome in the case of reversible Hamiltonian systems and the method was applied to study vibrations of symmetric molecules. The methodology developed in this project led to a series of further results in related topics.     Broader impacts: The project has opened new possibilities for the implementation of equivariant tools in various applied areas, such as engineering, electronics, robotics, and photonics, and for studying symmetric interactions between physical processes. These methods, especially in the case of specific systems lacking strong smoothness properties, may have indeed a strong impact on the area of non-smooth bifurcation theory. In particular, the participants have proposed non-local (in the parameter space) sufficient conditions for the Hopf bifurcation, which are suitable for analysis of systems with incomplete information about the values of coefficients (known as interval systems in problems of adaptive control). The results on molecular vibrations have a potential for applications in molecular chemistry.&#8232;&#8232;The project had a significant educational component with 8 PhD students (among them 5 defended their PhD), an undergraduate student and a K-12 student being involved. Topic graduate courses related to the project have been offered and the corresponding material is incorporated into the graduate textbook (under development). The Graduate students (among them 2 women and 1 minority) participated in, and made presentation at, national and international conferences, workshops, summer schools and NSF EPASI Program.  Trained in this project undergraduate and graduate students had an opportunity to&#8232;(a) learn and conduct research in several science and engineering disciplines;&#8232;(b) gain expertise in several mathematical fields unified under one umbrella: pure, applied, computational mathematics;&#8232;(c) become independent researchers with expertise in equivariant topological methodology which was involved in the project;&#8232;(d) develop competitiveness in reaching their career goals.&#8232;&#8232;The results were disseminated through publications in the top internationally recognized journals, conference presentations and invited presentations worldwide. The co-PIs organized multiple conferences, presented series of lectures at workshops and summer schools and conducted international collaboration aiming to spread the accomplishments of this project. The developed under this project software supporting the equivariant methods has been made available to mathematicians, applied scientists, engineers and educators worldwide.       Last Modified: 11/17/2018       Submitted by: Wieslaw Krawcewicz]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
