<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>PFI:AIR - TT:  Blood Typing Device without Reagents: Sensing Electrodes to Replace Optics</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>05/01/2014</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>200000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>220196</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07070000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>IIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Industrial Innovation &amp; Partnersh</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Prakash Balan</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>pbalan@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032925341</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This PFI: AIR Technology Translation project focuses on translating electrokinetic lab-on-a-chip blood typing technology to fill the need for rapid blood typing at blood donor sites and in disaster relief situations.  The project will result in a proof-of-concept blood typing microdevice to simultaneously detect cell signatures without a microscope. This blood typing microdevice has the following unique features: portability, rapid ABO-Rh type identification, no reagents, simultaneous hematocrit determination, and small blood volumes. These features provide the following advantages: time- and cost-savings, increased efficiency, longer shelf life, and better reliability when compared to paper-based blood agglutination kits, the leading competitor in this market space. While most electrokinetic/microfluidic devices fit on handheld microscope slides, the supporting infrastructure to operate the device comprises a considerable cost and space footprint.  This project addresses this technology gap by developing sensing electrodes to replace the optical microscope?s role of recording red blood cell responses in the microdevice, facilitating a key step in the transition from research discovery toward a user-friendly commercial application. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This blood typing microdevice is important because trauma centers and hospitals rely extensively on blood donations provided by blood banks across the U.S to save lives. There are currently 84 million blood typings per year in the U.S., with approximately 16 million donations annually. Processing costs approach $200 per pint of blood, so the ability to pre-screen donors by blood type and selectively direct the donation process (i.e. plasma, red cells) would result in significant savings and bolster our declining blood supply. This portable technology could also be translated to remote geographical locations for disaster relief applications. In addition, the potential initial economic impact is expected to be up to $12 million per year, which will contribute to the U.S. competitiveness in healthcare including trauma, blood therapies, and surgeries.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>04/30/2014</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/30/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1414331</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Paul</FirstName>
<LastName>Bergstrom</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>L</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Paul L Bergstrom</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>paulb@mtu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>9064872058</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000381552</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/30/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Adrienne</FirstName>
<LastName>Minerick</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>R</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Adrienne R Minerick</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>minerick@mtu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>9064872796</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000418146</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/30/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Mary</FirstName>
<LastName>Raber</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>B</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Mary B Raber</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>mraber@mtu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>9064874318</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000325033</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/30/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Michigan Technological University</Name>
<CityName>Houghton</CityName>
<ZipCode>499311295</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>9064871885</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1400 Townsend Drive</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Michigan</StateName>
<StateCode>MI</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MI01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>065453268</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>MICHIGAN TECHNOLOGICAL UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>065453268</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Michigan Technological University]]></Name>
<CityName>Houghton</CityName>
<StateCode>MI</StateCode>
<ZipCode>499311295</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[1400 Townsend Drive]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Michigan</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MI01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>8019</Code>
<Text>Accelerating Innovation Rsrch</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>116E</Code>
<Text>RESEARCH EXP FOR UNDERGRADS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8019</Code>
<Text>Accelerating Innovation Rsrch</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9231</Code>
<Text>SUPPL FOR UNDERGRAD RES ASSIST</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9251</Code>
<Text>REU SUPP-Res Exp for Ugrd Supp</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0114</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0115</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0116</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~200000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2015~8196</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2016~12000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The focus of this project was to explore the feasibility of passive electrical measurements to discern biological cell location within a microfluidic device.&nbsp; This approach would replace optical microscope observation of cell location.&nbsp; &nbsp;We previously demonstrated the use of dielectrophoretic response curves to discern ABO-Rh types of red blood cells in a microfluidic chamber ~350 &mu;m in diameter. &nbsp;The passive electrical measurements were integrated into this chamber.&nbsp; &nbsp;Details are not disclosed here because the work is being commercialized by a spin-off company, MicroDevice Engineering, Inc.</p> <p>Significant results included designs and microfabrication of multiple layers of metals and dielectrics within a test region that could passively measure biological cells on the surface.&nbsp; Metals and dielectrics were selected to enable concurrent optical verification of the electrical measurements.&nbsp; Parametric studies were conducted to ascertain the spatial sensitivity of the measurements including cell position and cell concentrations.&nbsp; Interactions with concurrent electrical signals were also measured.&nbsp; Research experiences for undergraduates were also included with the parent project.&nbsp; A total of three undergraduates (two African-American female students) participated by using the microchips to complete parametric studies on the accuracy of the measurements in the presence of secondary flows, passive capillary force loading of the channels and chambers, as well as the design and testing of a LED/photodiode Arduino configuration to detect cell concentration.&nbsp;</p> <p>In summary, the key outcomes were the design, testing, and implementation of a non-optical detection method for biological cell location within a microfluidic device.&nbsp; The technique enabled monitoring of cell location in near-real-time such that response curves as a function of other microdevice operational parameters could be obtained.&nbsp; The designs from this work were utilized in the ongoing R&amp;D for a portable blood typing and hematocrit detection unit for blood donation centers.&nbsp; These centers aim to utilize the devices to advise and route volunteer donors.&nbsp;</p> <p>One patent is pending, and one manuscript is under review at this point in time. &nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 03/12/2018<br>      Modified by: Adrienne&nbsp;R&nbsp;Minerick</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Image         </div> <div class="galControls onePhoto" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation onePhoto" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1414331/1414331_10300940_1520861681550_ProjectOutcomesImages_180309--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1414331/1414331_10300940_1520861681550_ProjectOutcomesImages_180309--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Microfabricated wafer"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1414331/1414331_10300940_1520861681550_ProjectOutcomesImages_180309--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Microfabricated wafer"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">A)Microfabricated wafer illustrating multiple microdevices. This constitutes the electronic layer.  B) Microfabricated fluidic layer of the microdevices.  The two are sealed together.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Minerick group, Michigan Tech Microfabrication Facility</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyrighted</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Adrienne&nbsp;R&nbsp;Minerick</div> <div class="imageTitle">Microfabricated wafer</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The focus of this project was to explore the feasibility of passive electrical measurements to discern biological cell location within a microfluidic device.  This approach would replace optical microscope observation of cell location.   We previously demonstrated the use of dielectrophoretic response curves to discern ABO-Rh types of red blood cells in a microfluidic chamber ~350 &mu;m in diameter.  The passive electrical measurements were integrated into this chamber.   Details are not disclosed here because the work is being commercialized by a spin-off company, MicroDevice Engineering, Inc.  Significant results included designs and microfabrication of multiple layers of metals and dielectrics within a test region that could passively measure biological cells on the surface.  Metals and dielectrics were selected to enable concurrent optical verification of the electrical measurements.  Parametric studies were conducted to ascertain the spatial sensitivity of the measurements including cell position and cell concentrations.  Interactions with concurrent electrical signals were also measured.  Research experiences for undergraduates were also included with the parent project.  A total of three undergraduates (two African-American female students) participated by using the microchips to complete parametric studies on the accuracy of the measurements in the presence of secondary flows, passive capillary force loading of the channels and chambers, as well as the design and testing of a LED/photodiode Arduino configuration to detect cell concentration.   In summary, the key outcomes were the design, testing, and implementation of a non-optical detection method for biological cell location within a microfluidic device.  The technique enabled monitoring of cell location in near-real-time such that response curves as a function of other microdevice operational parameters could be obtained.  The designs from this work were utilized in the ongoing R&amp;D for a portable blood typing and hematocrit detection unit for blood donation centers.  These centers aim to utilize the devices to advise and route volunteer donors.   One patent is pending, and one manuscript is under review at this point in time.            Last Modified: 03/12/2018       Submitted by: Adrienne R Minerick]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
