<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>EAPSI: The Implications of Firm Ownership on Innovation and the Environment in the Chinese Automotive Industry</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>06/01/2014</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2015</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>5291.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>5291</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Fellowship Award</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>01090000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>O/D</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Office Of The Director</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>OISE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Office Of Internatl Science &amp;Engineering</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Anne Emig</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>aemig@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927241</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>China has the largest passenger car market in the world. Cars now consume approximately half of all crude oil used in China and also contribute to over half of all harmful pollutants in China. Although the majority of vehicle sales are captured by foreign brands, foreign automakers are not permitted to independently manufacture and sell vehicles in China. Instead they are required to create separate "joint venture" (JV) firms with local Chinese automakers. This requirement has directly affected both the success of different automakers as well as the technologies they sell. In particular, more advanced fuel-saving technologies such as hybrid and electric vehicles have not yet been developed in mass production by any automakers in China, including those with ties to foreign automakers who sell these technologies in other countries. This research will investigate the links between firm ownership, experience in China, and the development of innovative new technologies in China's automotive sector. This work will be conducted with Dr. Xunmin Ou at Tsinghua University in China, and it aims to inform both automakers and policy makers on barriers to the transfer of advanced fuel-saving technologies to China.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This research builds on previous work on learning through international joint ventures in China by including information from major Chinese automakers, including those without joint venture partnerships. This research will use a mixture of quantitative and qualitative data, including automotive statistical yearbooks and a series of in-depth interviews with automotive managers and engineers, government officials, and other potential information holders such as researchers, journalists, and consultants. Results of this study will shed insights into the potential effects of informal and formal institutions in China on technology trajectories and the environment not only in China but also globally. This NSF EAPSI award is funded in collaboration with the Chinese Ministry of Science and Technology.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>05/29/2014</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/29/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.079</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1414734</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>John</FirstName>
<LastName>Helveston</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>P</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>John P Helveston</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress/>
<PI_PHON>2029947173</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000660035</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/29/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Helveston               John           P</Name>
<CityName>Pittsburgh</CityName>
<ZipCode>152321449</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber/>
<StreetAddress/>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Pennsylvania</StateName>
<StateCode>PA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>18</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>PA18</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM/>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME/>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Helveston               John           P]]></Name>
<CityName>Pittsburgh</CityName>
<StateCode>PA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>152321449</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Pennsylvania</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>18</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>PA18</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7316</Code>
<Text>EAPSI</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>5978</Code>
<Text>EAST ASIA AND PACIFIC PROGRAM</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7316</Code>
<Text>EAPSI</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9200</Code>
<Text>US CHINA COOP IN BASIC SCIENCE</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0114</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~5291</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>This report summarizes the activities and findings completed during the PI&rsquo;s summer study during June and July of 2014 as part of the 2014 East Asia Pacific Summer Institutes (EAPSI) fellowship program administered in the U.S. by the National Science Foundation (NSF) and in China by the Ministry of Science and Technology (MOST) through the China Science and Technology Exchange Center (CSTEC). The summer research project had three primary components: 1) conducting interviews with automakers and experts, 2) collecting vehicle sales and specification data and 3) building relationships with researchers in China.</p> <p>This research focused on two main questions on the electric vehicle industry in China: 1) How does different ownership and partnership characteristics amongst automotive firms in China influence their respective abilities to develop and produce plug-in electric vehicles? 2) Given today&rsquo;s vehicle preferences in China, what would the subsidies for hybrid and plug-in electric vehicles need to be today in order to achieve the average fleet fuel economy goals set by the Chinese government for 2015 and 2020? During the EAPSI fellowship summer, the data required to address these research questions were collected. Full data analysis results are expected by the end of 2015, and the findings from these two primary research questions will be used in the final chapters of the PI&rsquo;s Ph.D. dissertation.&nbsp;</p> <p>In order to investigate the links between firm ownership, experience in China, and the development of innovative new technologies in China&rsquo;s automotive sector (research question 1), in-depth interviews were conducted with managers at different automotive firms in China as well as experts on the industry. Contacts at automotive firms and with experts were made through a snowball technique in which previous interviewees were asked to introduce other potential interviewees. While contacts originated from personal friendships or acquaintances, others were introduced to the PI through various contacts met at the host institution which also provided a convenient location for successful interviewing.</p> <p>A total of eleven interviews were completed during June and July of 2014: four with managers at automotive firms and seven with experts on the industry. One interview was conducted in Mandarin Chinese and all others were conducted in English. These interviews provided not only invaluable information about the informal decision-making structures inside Chinese automotive firms, but also a strong network with Chinese automakers, experts, and academics for conducting future interviews. While a seeminly small number, all interviewees were high-level individuals in their respective careers and provided detailed information that is otherwise unattainable to researchers. The information provided also provided the foundation for stronger hypotheses about differences between joint venture and domestic independent automotive firm decision-making processes, which will be the focus of future interviews.</p> <p>Vehicle sales data were also collected from automotive statistical yearbooks between 2007 &ndash; 2012 from the Chinese Association of Automotive Manufacturers (CAAM). These data only exists in pub- lished books in Chinese, so digitizing the data was a long process of hand-copying the data into spreadsheets and translating the information into English. Fortunately, much of these data were acquired by an investment bank that had already conducted the copying and translating, so only a small portion had to be hand-copied from books. Nonetheless, translation was a difficult and time-consuming task that took the entire summer to complete. Vehicle specifications data was ac- quired from autohome.com.cn using a web scraper built in Python. The two datasets were merged in order to build discrete choice models for fleet forecasting.</p> <p>The intervi...]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ This report summarizes the activities and findings completed during the PIÆs summer study during June and July of 2014 as part of the 2014 East Asia Pacific Summer Institutes (EAPSI) fellowship program administered in the U.S. by the National Science Foundation (NSF) and in China by the Ministry of Science and Technology (MOST) through the China Science and Technology Exchange Center (CSTEC). The summer research project had three primary components: 1) conducting interviews with automakers and experts, 2) collecting vehicle sales and specification data and 3) building relationships with researchers in China.  This research focused on two main questions on the electric vehicle industry in China: 1) How does different ownership and partnership characteristics amongst automotive firms in China influence their respective abilities to develop and produce plug-in electric vehicles? 2) Given todayÆs vehicle preferences in China, what would the subsidies for hybrid and plug-in electric vehicles need to be today in order to achieve the average fleet fuel economy goals set by the Chinese government for 2015 and 2020? During the EAPSI fellowship summer, the data required to address these research questions were collected. Full data analysis results are expected by the end of 2015, and the findings from these two primary research questions will be used in the final chapters of the PIÆs Ph.D. dissertation.   In order to investigate the links between firm ownership, experience in China, and the development of innovative new technologies in ChinaÆs automotive sector (research question 1), in-depth interviews were conducted with managers at different automotive firms in China as well as experts on the industry. Contacts at automotive firms and with experts were made through a snowball technique in which previous interviewees were asked to introduce other potential interviewees. While contacts originated from personal friendships or acquaintances, others were introduced to the PI through various contacts met at the host institution which also provided a convenient location for successful interviewing.  A total of eleven interviews were completed during June and July of 2014: four with managers at automotive firms and seven with experts on the industry. One interview was conducted in Mandarin Chinese and all others were conducted in English. These interviews provided not only invaluable information about the informal decision-making structures inside Chinese automotive firms, but also a strong network with Chinese automakers, experts, and academics for conducting future interviews. While a seeminly small number, all interviewees were high-level individuals in their respective careers and provided detailed information that is otherwise unattainable to researchers. The information provided also provided the foundation for stronger hypotheses about differences between joint venture and domestic independent automotive firm decision-making processes, which will be the focus of future interviews.  Vehicle sales data were also collected from automotive statistical yearbooks between 2007 &ndash; 2012 from the Chinese Association of Automotive Manufacturers (CAAM). These data only exists in pub- lished books in Chinese, so digitizing the data was a long process of hand-copying the data into spreadsheets and translating the information into English. Fortunately, much of these data were acquired by an investment bank that had already conducted the copying and translating, so only a small portion had to be hand-copied from books. Nonetheless, translation was a difficult and time-consuming task that took the entire summer to complete. Vehicle specifications data was ac- quired from autohome.com.cn using a web scraper built in Python. The two datasets were merged in order to build discrete choice models for fleet forecasting.  The interview data collect during this project will contribute in a substantive way to new theory about how automotive firms make te...]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
