<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>EAPSI: Characterizing energy storage in supercapacitors using atomically thin carbon sheets (Graphene)</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>06/01/2014</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2015</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>5070.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>5070</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Fellowship Award</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>01090000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>O/D</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Office Of The Director</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>OISE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Office Of Internatl Science &amp;Engineering</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Anne Emig</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>aemig@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927241</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Current challenges in energy storage technology require more than batteries and capacitors. These devices suffer from several deficiencies when applications require simultaneously handling large amounts of energy and doing so quickly. Supercapacitors are a potential solution due to their strong performance in both power and energy comparisons. The flexibility of supercapacitors to handle moderate amounts of energy faster than batteries makes them ideal for use in a variety of applications. Recent studies show graphene, a single layer of carbon in a honeycomb arrangement, performs particularly well as the electrode material for supercapacitors. This project will seek to explore the behavior of graphene and map the behavior from single to multilayer. This research will be conducted at the National Synchrotron Research Laboratory, in collaboration with Dr. Li Song and will only be made possible through the finely-tuned graphene growth capabilities exhibited there.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Carbon materials are commonly used as the electrode material for the construction of supercapacitors, and graphene stands out as a strong candidate given its 2D structure and vast specific surface area. However, graphene synthesis is complicated due to the Van der Waals interactions between the 2D layers, causing layers to agglomerate into a bulk material. The behavior as the system moves from the nanoscale to the macroscale changes significantly. Often methods are used to shear these layers apart mechanically, chemically, or through liquid-phase exfoliations. These "top down' processes are often limited in product quality or quantity. Samples will be characterized with Tunneling Electron Microscopy and X-Ray Photoelectron Microscopy. This study will allow for the accurate mapping of the behavior of devices using Cyclic Voltammetry, Galvanostatic Charge-discharge, and Electrochemical Impedance Spectroscopy. This NSF EAPSI award is funded in collaboration with the Chinese Ministry of Science and Technology.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>05/29/2014</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/29/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.079</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1414819</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Jacob</FirstName>
<LastName>Huffstutler</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>D</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Jacob D Huffstutler</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress/>
<PI_PHON>6185594970</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000660301</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/29/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Huffstutler             Jacob          D</Name>
<CityName>Carbondale</CityName>
<ZipCode>629027503</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber/>
<StreetAddress/>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Illinois</StateName>
<StateCode>IL</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>12</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>IL12</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM/>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME/>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Huffstutler             Jacob          D]]></Name>
<CityName>Carbondale</CityName>
<StateCode>IL</StateCode>
<ZipCode>629027503</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Illinois</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>12</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>IL12</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7316</Code>
<Text>EAPSI</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>5978</Code>
<Text>EAST ASIA AND PACIFIC PROGRAM</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7316</Code>
<Text>EAPSI</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9200</Code>
<Text>US CHINA COOP IN BASIC SCIENCE</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0114</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~5070</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><span style="white-space: pre;"> </span>Graphene (two-dimensional sheet carbon) electrodes were prepared in specific thicknesses (stacking by number of layers) for use in a relatively new energy storage technology, supercapacitors. Supercapacitors bridge the gap between conventional capacitors, which store very small amounts of energy, but distribute it very quickly, and batteries, which hold large amounts of energy, but distribute it very slowly. Supercapacitors rest in the middle, exhibiting relatively good performance in both aspects of speed and storage. Supercapacitor device performance can be manipulated in a variety of ways. In the course of this project, the effect of the layering thickness of the prepared graphene sheets on the performance of the device was investigated.</p> <p><span style="white-space: pre;"> </span>The layering thickness of the grown carbon sheets was investigated with a series of high-powered scientific tools in order to confirm that the samples grown over the course of the project were of an appropriate thickness for use. The effects of the layering thickness of the carbon sheets on device performance was investigated using a variety of experimental techniques.</p> <p><span style="white-space: pre;"> </span>At the time of submission, little was known about the effects of layering thickness upon device performance. This project explored relatively unknown territory using the highly advanced procedures available at the host institution: the University of Science and Technology of China.</p> <p><span style="white-space: pre;"> </span>It is hoped that these advances and those of others will further push supercapacitors towards greater efficiency and performance. These advances will allow for supercapacitors to fulfill energy storage gaps left by their limited counterparts, conventional capacitors and batteries, further improving existing alternative energy production techniques.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 02/24/2015<br>      Modified by: Jacob&nbsp;D&nbsp;Huffstutler</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[  Graphene (two-dimensional sheet carbon) electrodes were prepared in specific thicknesses (stacking by number of layers) for use in a relatively new energy storage technology, supercapacitors. Supercapacitors bridge the gap between conventional capacitors, which store very small amounts of energy, but distribute it very quickly, and batteries, which hold large amounts of energy, but distribute it very slowly. Supercapacitors rest in the middle, exhibiting relatively good performance in both aspects of speed and storage. Supercapacitor device performance can be manipulated in a variety of ways. In the course of this project, the effect of the layering thickness of the prepared graphene sheets on the performance of the device was investigated.   The layering thickness of the grown carbon sheets was investigated with a series of high-powered scientific tools in order to confirm that the samples grown over the course of the project were of an appropriate thickness for use. The effects of the layering thickness of the carbon sheets on device performance was investigated using a variety of experimental techniques.   At the time of submission, little was known about the effects of layering thickness upon device performance. This project explored relatively unknown territory using the highly advanced procedures available at the host institution: the University of Science and Technology of China.   It is hoped that these advances and those of others will further push supercapacitors towards greater efficiency and performance. These advances will allow for supercapacitors to fulfill energy storage gaps left by their limited counterparts, conventional capacitors and batteries, further improving existing alternative energy production techniques.       Last Modified: 02/24/2015       Submitted by: Jacob D Huffstutler]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
