<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Collisionless Shocks in the Large Plasma Device</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/15/2014</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>390000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>390000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03010000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>PHY</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Physics</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Vyacheslav (Slava) Lukin</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>vlukin@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927382</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This project will study magnetized, collisionless shock waves.  Collisionless shocks are ubiquitous in space and astrophysical environments.  Magnetized shocks are produced for example by supernova explosions, by the outflow of hot gases from certain types of stars by the solar wind upstream of planetary magnetospheres, or solar flares.  Astrophysical collisionless shocks will be mimicked in the laboratory using high-powered lasers. This will allow their properties to be studied in a detail not currently possible by observing them in space. Collisionless shocks in space affect the particle and field distribution throughout the universe and are believed to be the primary source of cosmic rays. The proposed experiments could open the possibility of studying astrophysics in the laboratory and advance the understanding of space and astrophysical processes such as coronal mass ejections, supernovae or the origin of cosmic rays. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The magnetized collisionless shocks launched in the Large Plasma Device (LAPD) at UCLA will be fully characterized. In these experiments, an energetic laser pulse of several hundred joules rapidly ablates a solid target embedded in a large (17 m x 0.5 m), and magnetized ambient plasma. Collisionless coupling between the debris ions and ambient plasma accelerates the ambient ions to super-Alfvenic velocities and a self-sustained shock can separate from the laser-plasma piston and propagate through the ambient plasma over large distances. The shock will be characterized by measuring the jump of density, magnetic field, temperature and flow across the ramp in a variety of shock geometries. These experiments could potentially launch quasi-parallel (i.e. Alfvenic) shocks and find evidence of particle acceleration in a controlled laboratory setting for the very first time. The experiments will be compared to two-dimensional and three-dimensional computer simulations performed with an existing multi-dimensional hybrid code.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/17/2014</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/09/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1414591</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Christoph</FirstName>
<LastName>Niemann</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Christoph Niemann</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>cniemann@ucla.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>3108254950</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000487416</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/17/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of California-Los Angeles</Name>
<CityName>LOS ANGELES</CityName>
<ZipCode>900951406</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>3107940102</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>10889 Wilshire Boulevard</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[Suite 700]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>33</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CA33</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>092530369</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF CALIFORNIA, LOS ANGELES</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>071549000</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of California Los Angeles]]></Name>
<CityName>Los Angeles</CityName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>900952000</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[1040 Veteran Ave]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>33</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CA33</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1242</Code>
<Text>PLASMA PHYSICS</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1062</Code>
<Text>BASIC PLASMA SCIENCE &amp; ENGINEERING</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0114</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0115</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0116</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~130000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2015~130000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2016~130000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Collisionless shocks are prevalent in many space and astrophysical settings and affect the particle and field distribution throughout the cosmos. Examples include supernova remnants, coronal mass ejections, or bow shocks upstream of planets and comets. In these rarified environments, particle collisions are rare, and an exploding plasma interacts with the surrounding medium via collisionless, collective, electromagnetic effects (plasma waves and turbulence).</p> <p>We have investigated the formation of quasi-perpendicular collisionless shocks by a laser driven magnetic piston in a large magnetized laboratory plasma produced by the Large Plasma Device (LAPD). A high-power laser beam was focused onto a solid target inside the LAPD plasma to create a dense plasma that explodes at high speed (several 100 km/s) into the surrounding plasma. The interaction of the exploding plasma and the ambient plasma mimics an astrophysical explosion in space and can be used to study the micro-physics of collisionless shocks.</p> <p>The experiments investigated under which conditions shocks form, their structure, and their effect on the surrunding medium. Specifically, we have observed how the ambient plasma is accelerated perpendicular to the shock direction by a collisionless coupling mechanisms called Larmor coupling. This important mechanism to couple momentum and energy between different plasmas in space had been theoretically postuded but had never been observed in a controlled laboratory setting.</p> <p>Intellectual merit: understanding the formation and evolution of collisionless shocks and the origin of cosmic rays represents a grand challange in the plasma cosmos and the laboratory, and data are scarce.</p> <p>Broader impact: the work helped to bridge a gap between the basic plasma phyiscs community and the high-energy density plasma community. Students and postdocs were exposed to both fields and have been tained on a unique hands-on experimental facility.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 11/07/2018<br>      Modified by: Christoph&nbsp;Niemann</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Collisionless shocks are prevalent in many space and astrophysical settings and affect the particle and field distribution throughout the cosmos. Examples include supernova remnants, coronal mass ejections, or bow shocks upstream of planets and comets. In these rarified environments, particle collisions are rare, and an exploding plasma interacts with the surrounding medium via collisionless, collective, electromagnetic effects (plasma waves and turbulence).  We have investigated the formation of quasi-perpendicular collisionless shocks by a laser driven magnetic piston in a large magnetized laboratory plasma produced by the Large Plasma Device (LAPD). A high-power laser beam was focused onto a solid target inside the LAPD plasma to create a dense plasma that explodes at high speed (several 100 km/s) into the surrounding plasma. The interaction of the exploding plasma and the ambient plasma mimics an astrophysical explosion in space and can be used to study the micro-physics of collisionless shocks.  The experiments investigated under which conditions shocks form, their structure, and their effect on the surrunding medium. Specifically, we have observed how the ambient plasma is accelerated perpendicular to the shock direction by a collisionless coupling mechanisms called Larmor coupling. This important mechanism to couple momentum and energy between different plasmas in space had been theoretically postuded but had never been observed in a controlled laboratory setting.  Intellectual merit: understanding the formation and evolution of collisionless shocks and the origin of cosmic rays represents a grand challange in the plasma cosmos and the laboratory, and data are scarce.  Broader impact: the work helped to bridge a gap between the basic plasma phyiscs community and the high-energy density plasma community. Students and postdocs were exposed to both fields and have been tained on a unique hands-on experimental facility.       Last Modified: 11/07/2018       Submitted by: Christoph Niemann]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
