<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>EAPSI: Spatial estimation of early radioactive fallout from the Hiroshima atomic bomb</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>06/01/2014</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2015</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>5300.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>5300</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Fellowship Award</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>01090000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>O/D</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Office Of The Director</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>OISE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Office Of Internatl Science &amp;Engineering</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Anne Emig</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>aemig@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927241</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>In 1945, a uranium atomic bomb was dropped on Hiroshima, Japan. Victims of the atomic bomb experienced direct doses of radiation from the blast, but radioactive particles were also suspended into the atmosphere and deposited farther from the bomb's epicenter. These distal exposures are known as radioactive fallout and exposure is of concern to victims of the atomic bomb and their families. Researchers are studying health effects of radiation because it is possible that persons more distal from the atomic blast center received significant doses of radiation from fallout. Some measurements of fallout were taken by different research organizations during the days following the bombings but they were sparse and have not been utilized widely due to differences in measurement techniques. This project will join data from early surveys to estimate levels of early fallout from the atomic bomb, and produce a singular map of fallout. This project will be conducted at the Radiation Effects Research Foundation in collaboration with Dr. Harry Cullings, an expert in atomic bomb dosimetry.&lt;br/&gt; &lt;br/&gt;Using geospatial statistical methods, hierarchical models, and substantive physics knowledge, this study will model early radiation exposure in the Koi-Takasu area. Combining early surveys while considering survey timing in relation to radioactive decay of the fallout, the precision of each survey's measurements, and possible differences in calibration among surveys will allow spatial modeling of time-specific and integrated gamma-ray exposure rates. Early radiation exposure is important to characterize in order to better inform dosimetry research and other studies with biological endpoints, particularly the Life Span Study, which informs radiation protection standards worldwide. This NSF EAPSI award is funded in collaboration with the Japan Society for the Promotion of Science.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>05/29/2014</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/29/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.079</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1414730</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Kaitlin</FirstName>
<LastName>Kelly-Reif</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>E</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Kaitlin E Kelly-Reif</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress/>
<PI_PHON>9168123317</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000658050</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/29/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Kelly-Reif              Kaitlin        E</Name>
<CityName>Carrboro</CityName>
<ZipCode>275104327</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber/>
<StreetAddress/>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>North Carolina</StateName>
<StateCode>NC</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NC04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM/>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME/>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of North Carolina Chapel Hill]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>NC</StateCode>
<ZipCode>275997400</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>North Carolina</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NC04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7316</Code>
<Text>EAPSI</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>5921</Code>
<Text>JAPAN</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>5978</Code>
<Text>EAST ASIA AND PACIFIC PROGRAM</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7316</Code>
<Text>EAPSI</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0114</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~5300</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>When the atomic bomb was dropped on Hiroshima, victims experienced direct doses of radiation from the blast, but radioactive particles were also suspended into the atmosphere and deposited farther from the bomb&rsquo;s epicenter. These distal exposures, known as radioactive fallout, are of concern to victims of the atomic bomb and their families, and researchers studying health effects of radiation. Some measurements of fallout were taken by different research organizations during the days following the bombings but have not been utilized due to differences in measurement techniques and sparse measurements. Early radiation exposure is important to characterize in order to better inform dosimetry research and other studies with biological endpoints, particularly the Life Span Study, which informs radiation protection standards worldwide.</p> <p>Using geospatial statistical methods, hierarchical models, and substantive physics knowledge, this study modeled early radiation exposure in the northwest Koi-Takasu area. Preliminary results suggest excess levels of radionuclides may be present in the northwest. However, researchers are still working on calibrating different measurements from early surveys, and incorporating statistical models to account for the small number of measurements taken in this area.</p> <p>The graduate student who received this award developed professional relationships with her foreign counterpart, the Radiation Effects Research Foundation (RERF), and continues to collaborate with RERF researchers on questions of radioactive fallout.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 08/28/2015<br>      Modified by: Kaitlin&nbsp;E&nbsp;Kelly-Reif</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ When the atomic bomb was dropped on Hiroshima, victims experienced direct doses of radiation from the blast, but radioactive particles were also suspended into the atmosphere and deposited farther from the bombÆs epicenter. These distal exposures, known as radioactive fallout, are of concern to victims of the atomic bomb and their families, and researchers studying health effects of radiation. Some measurements of fallout were taken by different research organizations during the days following the bombings but have not been utilized due to differences in measurement techniques and sparse measurements. Early radiation exposure is important to characterize in order to better inform dosimetry research and other studies with biological endpoints, particularly the Life Span Study, which informs radiation protection standards worldwide.  Using geospatial statistical methods, hierarchical models, and substantive physics knowledge, this study modeled early radiation exposure in the northwest Koi-Takasu area. Preliminary results suggest excess levels of radionuclides may be present in the northwest. However, researchers are still working on calibrating different measurements from early surveys, and incorporating statistical models to account for the small number of measurements taken in this area.  The graduate student who received this award developed professional relationships with her foreign counterpart, the Radiation Effects Research Foundation (RERF), and continues to collaborate with RERF researchers on questions of radioactive fallout.          Last Modified: 08/28/2015       Submitted by: Kaitlin E Kelly-Reif]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
