<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Tenth International Nanotechnology Conference on Communication and Cooperation</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>04/01/2014</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>03/31/2015</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>31950.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>31950</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>05010000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>CSE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CCF</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division of Computing and Communication Foundations</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Sankar Basu</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>sabasu@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927843</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Support is provided for student travel and partial support for a limited number of faculty speakers at "Tenth International Nanotechnology Conference on Communication and Cooperation (INC10)" to be held on May 13-16, 2014 at the NIST campus in Gaithersburg, Maryland. The INC10 meeting brings together some of the world's most renowned and technologically advanced researchers to exchange information and ideas on nanotechnology, nano-optics and nano-electronics.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Electronics, a two-trillion-dollar enterprise, has been the major enabler of the computer, communication and consumer industries throughout the 20th century, and has propelled the growth of the global economy for last several decades. Most of the building blocks of these industries will reach fundamental limits by the end of the next decade. It is of fundamental importance that these limits are overcome in the next 10 years, possibly through the use of devices enabled by nanotechnology. The meeting (INC10) will provide an important forum for discussion and dissemination of relevant information to young scientists and researchers.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>04/01/2014</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>04/01/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.070</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1414272</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Kosmas</FirstName>
<LastName>Galatsis</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Kosmas Galatsis</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>kos@seas.ucla.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>3107940102</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000486345</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/01/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of California-Los Angeles</Name>
<CityName>LOS ANGELES</CityName>
<ZipCode>900951406</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>3107940102</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>10889 Wilshire Boulevard</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[Suite 700]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>33</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CA33</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>092530369</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF CALIFORNIA, LOS ANGELES</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>071549000</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of California-Los Angeles]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>900951594</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>33</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CA33</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7681</Code>
<Text>ENG NNI Special Studies</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7798</Code>
<Text>Software &amp; Hardware Foundation</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7945</Code>
<Text>DES AUTO FOR MICRO &amp; NANO SYST</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0114</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~31950</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The NSF travel grant enabled 21 faculty/students &amp; nonprofit representatives from the US to attend the Tenth International Nanotechnology Conference on Communication and Cooperation, May 13-15, 2014 which took place at the NIST Campus in Gaithersburg, Maryland. Details of the conference can be found at <a href="http://www.inc10.org/">http://www.inc10.org/</a>. This conference was sponsored by SRC-SIA, NSF, IMEC, JEITA-JSI, and several US, European and Asian companies. It featured invited speakers and poster presenters from industry, academia, and government who presented advances in beyond-CMOS nanoelectronics, nanoenergy, nanophotonics and issues related to nanosocietal implications. The INC10 conference attracted some of the world&rsquo;s most reknowned and technologically advanced thinkers who presented the latest concepts in beyond-CMOS nanoelectronics, nanoenergy, nanophotonics and issues related to nanosocietal implications. Within four days, 161 participants from 8 different countries had lively discussions about the opportunities and challenges of Nanotechnology with a special focus on Nanoelectronics and its applications. Topics like the expected applications areas of the upcoming material Graphene, the vlaue of nano applications in biology and medicine to further improve our personal health, and the perspectives on nano photonics integration as well as on Nanoelectroncis for energy efficiency represent only some of the issues addressed. In addition, this arena provided a unique opportunity where academics and industry leaders could interact on issues in nanotechnology.&nbsp; At a high level, the spirits of the meeting targeted regional groups co-operation to implement strategic and beneficial cooperative programs to progress mandkinds&rsquo; development through nanotechnology and its associated intellectual merits.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 11/18/2014<br>      Modified by: Kosmas&nbsp;Galatsis</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The NSF travel grant enabled 21 faculty/students &amp; nonprofit representatives from the US to attend the Tenth International Nanotechnology Conference on Communication and Cooperation, May 13-15, 2014 which took place at the NIST Campus in Gaithersburg, Maryland. Details of the conference can be found at http://www.inc10.org/. This conference was sponsored by SRC-SIA, NSF, IMEC, JEITA-JSI, and several US, European and Asian companies. It featured invited speakers and poster presenters from industry, academia, and government who presented advances in beyond-CMOS nanoelectronics, nanoenergy, nanophotonics and issues related to nanosocietal implications. The INC10 conference attracted some of the worldÆs most reknowned and technologically advanced thinkers who presented the latest concepts in beyond-CMOS nanoelectronics, nanoenergy, nanophotonics and issues related to nanosocietal implications. Within four days, 161 participants from 8 different countries had lively discussions about the opportunities and challenges of Nanotechnology with a special focus on Nanoelectronics and its applications. Topics like the expected applications areas of the upcoming material Graphene, the vlaue of nano applications in biology and medicine to further improve our personal health, and the perspectives on nano photonics integration as well as on Nanoelectroncis for energy efficiency represent only some of the issues addressed. In addition, this arena provided a unique opportunity where academics and industry leaders could interact on issues in nanotechnology.  At a high level, the spirits of the meeting targeted regional groups co-operation to implement strategic and beneficial cooperative programs to progress mandkindsÆ development through nanotechnology and its associated intellectual merits.       Last Modified: 11/18/2014       Submitted by: Kosmas Galatsis]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
