<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>EAPSI: Investigating novel perspectives on internal migration control and urban citizenship in China</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>06/01/2014</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2015</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>5070.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>5070</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Fellowship Award</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>01090000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>O/D</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Office Of The Director</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>OISE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Office Of Internatl Science &amp;Engineering</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Anne Emig</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>aemig@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927241</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Internal migration is one of the most important political and social issues in China today. The nearly 200 million individuals who make up China's so-called "floating population" of migrant laborers are not only a powerful social force, but are also a fundamental economic building block for Chinese urban development. At the same time, official state policy - the hukou system - regulates where individuals are allowed to legally live and work. In collaboration with Dr. Li Zhang, a scholar of internal migration at Fudan University in Shanghai, this project will investigate how the hukou system is able to regulate and manage the massive flows of migrant labor that are in the process of remaking China's urban centers as well as its countryside. Because of the importance of U.S.-China relations as well as our own country's experience of large flows of labor migration, this project has the potential to inform both scholarship and policy with regards to labor control and development. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;In order to better understand this phenomenon, this project will generate new empirical data through qualitative survey methods, examining the perceptions of migrants, non-migrants, and migration authorities in Shanghai. This data will then be analyzed through theoretical frameworks that have been developed to understand international migration. Because of the many similarities between the hukou system and international migration controls (heritability, place-based assignations of belonging, and restriction of some rights and privileges to migrants), analysis of the hukou system through this framework promises to reveal interesting points of convergence that will inform further theorizations of urban citizenship strategies, migration within China, and international migration as a whole. This NSF EAPSI award is funded in collaboration with the Chinese Ministry of Science and Technology.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/10/2014</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/10/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.079</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1414810</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Leif</FirstName>
<LastName>Johnson</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>A</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Leif A Johnson</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress/>
<PI_PHON>8595362117</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000658604</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/10/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Johnson                 Leif</Name>
<CityName>Lexington</CityName>
<ZipCode>405081931</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber/>
<StreetAddress/>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Kentucky</StateName>
<StateCode>KY</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>06</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>KY06</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM/>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME/>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Johnson                 Leif]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>KY</StateCode>
<ZipCode>405081931</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Kentucky</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>06</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>KY06</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7316</Code>
<Text>EAPSI</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EPSCoR Co-Funding</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>5978</Code>
<Text>EAST ASIA AND PACIFIC PROGRAM</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7316</Code>
<Text>EAPSI</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9200</Code>
<Text>US CHINA COOP IN BASIC SCIENCE</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0114</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~5070</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><span style="color: #000000;"><span style="font-family: Times-Roman, serif;"><span>Internal migration is one of the most important political and social issues in China today. The nearly 200 million individuals who make up China's so-called &ldquo;floating population&rdquo; of migrant laborers are not only a powerful social force, but are also a fundamental economic building block for Chinese urban development. At the same time, official state policy - the hukou system - regulates where individuals are allowed to legally live and work. In collaboration with Dr. Li Zhang, a scholar of internal migration at Fudan University in Shanghai, I performed a series of interviews that investigated how the hukou system is able to regulate and manage the massive flows of migrant labor that are in the process of remaking China&rsquo;s urban centers as well as its countryside. Through the eight weeks of the EAPSI program, as well as an additional three months of research funded by the University of Kentucky and a research assistantship at Fudan University, my research developed the basis for comparative analyses of China's internal migration controls and the border controls implemented internationally. </span></span></span></p> <p><span style="color: #000000;"><span style="font-family: Times-Roman, serif;"><span>The tangible outcomes of this project include data produced from a series of </span></span></span><span style="color: #000000;"><span style="font-family: Times-Roman, serif;"><span><span>8 interviews and one focus group were conducted with migrants and local residents in Shanghai (15 total participants), as well as 6 interviews and one focus group (11 total participants) conducted in a rural community near outlying Wuhu City, Anhui province. A pair of papers based on these data are currently in preparation for publication. By taking comparisons between China's internal migration governance regime and international border laws seriously, these papers will advance ongoing conversations in human geography and border studies. In addition to these outputs, the international collaboration I began with Li Zhang at Fudan University has the possibility of increasing international understanding around issues of migration, and leading to continued investigation of the parallels that can be drawn between China's hukou system and international bordering.&nbsp;</span></span></span></span></p> <p class="western">&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 03/06/2015<br>      Modified by: Leif&nbsp;Johnson</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Internal migration is one of the most important political and social issues in China today. The nearly 200 million individuals who make up China's so-called "floating population" of migrant laborers are not only a powerful social force, but are also a fundamental economic building block for Chinese urban development. At the same time, official state policy - the hukou system - regulates where individuals are allowed to legally live and work. In collaboration with Dr. Li Zhang, a scholar of internal migration at Fudan University in Shanghai, I performed a series of interviews that investigated how the hukou system is able to regulate and manage the massive flows of migrant labor that are in the process of remaking ChinaÆs urban centers as well as its countryside. Through the eight weeks of the EAPSI program, as well as an additional three months of research funded by the University of Kentucky and a research assistantship at Fudan University, my research developed the basis for comparative analyses of China's internal migration controls and the border controls implemented internationally.   The tangible outcomes of this project include data produced from a series of 8 interviews and one focus group were conducted with migrants and local residents in Shanghai (15 total participants), as well as 6 interviews and one focus group (11 total participants) conducted in a rural community near outlying Wuhu City, Anhui province. A pair of papers based on these data are currently in preparation for publication. By taking comparisons between China's internal migration governance regime and international border laws seriously, these papers will advance ongoing conversations in human geography and border studies. In addition to these outputs, the international collaboration I began with Li Zhang at Fudan University has the possibility of increasing international understanding around issues of migration, and leading to continued investigation of the parallels that can be drawn between China's hukou system and international bordering.          Last Modified: 03/06/2015       Submitted by: Leif Johnson]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
