<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>EAPSI:Studying the Interplay between Localization and Categorical Algebra via Algebraic Topology</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>06/01/2014</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2015</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>5070.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>5070</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Fellowship Award</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>01090000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>O/D</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Office Of The Director</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>OISE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Office Of Internatl Science &amp;Engineering</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Anne Emig</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>aemig@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927241</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Localization is a fundamental tool in mathematics which allows one to zoom in on the pertinent information in a problem. In the context of category theory?a mathematical theory which studies objects and their relationships?localization is a way to view two different objects as equivalent. As humans we do this all the time. For example, if two different driving routes take the same amount of time we might view them as equivalent. It is often advantageous to study objects which have additional algebraic structure, e.g. objects with a multiplication. The research in this proposal studies the interplay between localization and algebraic structure using tools from homotopy theory, which views two objects as equivalent if one can be deformed into the other. Homotopy Theory is a subfield of algebraic topology, a fundamental area of mathematics which blends algebra and topology and uses tools from each to study the other. The applications of this work will strengthen the developing bond between homotopy theory and category theory, will allow tools from each area to be applied in the other, and will lead to a better understanding of both fields. The generality of this approach allows for applications in many different fields of mathematics, physics, and computer science.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The setting of monoidal model categories guarantees the efficacy of the localization procedure described above. In this setting there is a further localization known as Bousfield localization, and algebraic structure is encoded via vehicles for universal algebra known as operads. The Principal Investigator?s recent work allows operad-algebras to be studied after Bousfield localization has been applied to the underlying category. Recent work of Michael Batanin?with whom this research will be jointly conducted at Macquarie University?allows for Bousfield localization to be applied to the category of operad-algebras. The project will attempt to link up these two approaches, to relate their outputs, to pool the two proof strategies, and to reduce the conditions required so that this work will apply to a wider class of model categories. This NSF EAPSI award is funded in collaboration with the Australian Academy of Science.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/03/2014</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/03/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.079</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1414942</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>David</FirstName>
<LastName>White</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>David White</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress/>
<PI_PHON>7734691605</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000660374</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/03/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>White                   David</Name>
<CityName>Middletown</CityName>
<ZipCode>064573315</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber/>
<StreetAddress/>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Connecticut</StateName>
<StateCode>CT</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CT03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM/>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME/>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[White                   David]]></Name>
<CityName>Middletown</CityName>
<StateCode>CT</StateCode>
<ZipCode>064573315</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Connecticut</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>03</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CT03</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7316</Code>
<Text>EAPSI</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>5912</Code>
<Text>AUSTRALIA</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>5978</Code>
<Text>EAST ASIA AND PACIFIC PROGRAM</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7316</Code>
<Text>EAPSI</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0114</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~5070</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Localization is a fundamental tool in mathematics which allows one to zoom in on the pertinent information in a problem. Category theory provides the most general setting for doing mathematics; each individual subfield of mathematics is a single category, so the study of category theory is in some sense the study of all mathematics. A category consists of a collection of objects and the relationships (morphisms) between them. In this setting, localization consists of declaring that two objects are equivalent by inverting a morphism so that it becomes an isomorphism. Studying localization on categories leads naturally to the notion of a model category, wherein a prescribed class of morphisms is to be inverted. If one wishes to invert a morphism not in this prescribed class, then the machinery of Bousfield localization must be used.</p> <p>Algebra is a powerful computational tool which may be encoded in the setting of model categories via objects called operads. My research studies the interplay between a Bousfield localization L and the algebraic structure as encoded by an operad P. In my Ph.D. thesis I provided conditions so that L is forced to preserve P-algebra structure. Under these conditions, one can study algebraic objects after applying localization, denoted P-alg(L(M)). In the summer of 2014 I visited Michael Batanin at Macquarie University in Sydney, Australia. He has recently provided conditions under which the general machinery of localization may be applied to categories of algebraic objects, i.e. the output is L&rsquo;(P-alg(M)). We proved that if L is localization with respect to a set of maps C and if L&rsquo; is localization with respect to the free P-algebra homomorphisms on C then these two model structures P-alg(L(M)) and L&rsquo;(P-alg(M)) coincide if they exist.</p> <p>My thesis and Batanin&rsquo;s paper with Clemens Berger provide conditions for this existence, and relate it to the question of preservation of operad-algebra structure under localization. In order to weaken these conditions (so that the results will hold in more general settings), I proved that they both exist as semi-model categories (a slightly more general setting) under almost no conditions at all. This involved generalizing left Bousfield localization to the setting of semi-model categories (where the left properness assumption is not required).</p> <p>We next proved that full model structures on categories of operad-algebras can be obtained in many situations where previously only semi-model structures were known previously, e.g. for so-called Sigma-cofibrant operads over model categories satisfying the monoid axiom. This resolves a difficulty which has been present in the research literature for the past fifteen years. Additionally, these model structures can be made left proper if the underlying model category is strongly h-monoidal. Jointly with Mark Weber, we began the process of studying non-cofibrant colored operads by realizing them as polynomial monads valued in the category of categories, and applying the method which worked to put a model structure on commutative monoids to this setting.</p> <p>Lastly, we proved that in the presence of the commutative monoid axiom from my thesis, the category of non-reduced symmetric operads is a left proper model category. We checked that the commutative monoid axiom holds for simplicial presheaves, diagram categories (including an application to commutative ideals of ring spectra), and Rezk&rsquo;s categories of n-fold complete Segal spaces. This leads to a short proof of the Baez-Dolan Stabilisation Hypothesis regarding truncations and n-Operads.</p> <p>I provide applications of this work within homotopy theory and computer science, and Michael Batanin provides applications in categorical algebra. By pooling our proof strategies we have produced a very powerful machine for putting model structures on operad-algebras even in th...]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Localization is a fundamental tool in mathematics which allows one to zoom in on the pertinent information in a problem. Category theory provides the most general setting for doing mathematics; each individual subfield of mathematics is a single category, so the study of category theory is in some sense the study of all mathematics. A category consists of a collection of objects and the relationships (morphisms) between them. In this setting, localization consists of declaring that two objects are equivalent by inverting a morphism so that it becomes an isomorphism. Studying localization on categories leads naturally to the notion of a model category, wherein a prescribed class of morphisms is to be inverted. If one wishes to invert a morphism not in this prescribed class, then the machinery of Bousfield localization must be used.  Algebra is a powerful computational tool which may be encoded in the setting of model categories via objects called operads. My research studies the interplay between a Bousfield localization L and the algebraic structure as encoded by an operad P. In my Ph.D. thesis I provided conditions so that L is forced to preserve P-algebra structure. Under these conditions, one can study algebraic objects after applying localization, denoted P-alg(L(M)). In the summer of 2014 I visited Michael Batanin at Macquarie University in Sydney, Australia. He has recently provided conditions under which the general machinery of localization may be applied to categories of algebraic objects, i.e. the output is LÆ(P-alg(M)). We proved that if L is localization with respect to a set of maps C and if LÆ is localization with respect to the free P-algebra homomorphisms on C then these two model structures P-alg(L(M)) and LÆ(P-alg(M)) coincide if they exist.  My thesis and BataninÆs paper with Clemens Berger provide conditions for this existence, and relate it to the question of preservation of operad-algebra structure under localization. In order to weaken these conditions (so that the results will hold in more general settings), I proved that they both exist as semi-model categories (a slightly more general setting) under almost no conditions at all. This involved generalizing left Bousfield localization to the setting of semi-model categories (where the left properness assumption is not required).  We next proved that full model structures on categories of operad-algebras can be obtained in many situations where previously only semi-model structures were known previously, e.g. for so-called Sigma-cofibrant operads over model categories satisfying the monoid axiom. This resolves a difficulty which has been present in the research literature for the past fifteen years. Additionally, these model structures can be made left proper if the underlying model category is strongly h-monoidal. Jointly with Mark Weber, we began the process of studying non-cofibrant colored operads by realizing them as polynomial monads valued in the category of categories, and applying the method which worked to put a model structure on commutative monoids to this setting.  Lastly, we proved that in the presence of the commutative monoid axiom from my thesis, the category of non-reduced symmetric operads is a left proper model category. We checked that the commutative monoid axiom holds for simplicial presheaves, diagram categories (including an application to commutative ideals of ring spectra), and RezkÆs categories of n-fold complete Segal spaces. This leads to a short proof of the Baez-Dolan Stabilisation Hypothesis regarding truncations and n-Operads.  I provide applications of this work within homotopy theory and computer science, and Michael Batanin provides applications in categorical algebra. By pooling our proof strategies we have produced a very powerful machine for putting model structures on operad-algebras even in the absence of strong hypotheses on the model categories or on the opeards. We have strengthened the developing bond between...]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
