<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>SBIR Phase I:  Geometric System for Music Composition</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2014</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2015</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>150000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>179999</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07070000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>IIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Industrial Innovation &amp; Partnersh</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Glenn H. Larsen</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This SBIR project's broader and commercial impact of this project is a benefit to society, because it will help more people learn and experience music in a new and fun way.  This project will share concepts from upper division and graduate mathematics graphically with the general public.  By helping people through the learning curve for music writing, it opens up commercial potential for new economic interactions?allowing users to sell each other content they create.  The marketplace for online music applications has grown by a factor of 10 in the last 2 years.  As an example, one major music application now has 250 million users, up from 10 million users 2 years ago.  This project provides an opportunity to compete in this space.  This project can impact society by helping transform the internet from a market of advertisers to a more desirable market of content producers, and simultaneously advance the state of the art in distributed computing.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This SBIR project addresses the following problem: to write music, students must learn to understand music notation.  Music notation is based on a centuries old system which obfuscates the mathematical structures present in music, and complicates the learning process.  This project advances the knowledge of the student and/or composer using 3 dimensional views and color systems to construct a higher dimensional spatial representation of music.  This representation removes obfuscations, and enables user interfaces for intuitive musical expression, helping the student learn faster.  The research objectives for are to complete the user interface design to enable artistic expression through the tool, to identify software architecture features for optimal system performance, to design and partition a domain and data model to enable user to user commerce across the cloud and social network, and to define appropriate interface points to external systems for full functionality.  Research will consist of mathematical modeling by the principal investigator, combined with graphic design for user interfaces by a senior investigator.  These results will refine and integrate with existing and new interfaces for the system, in a prototyping process.  The results of the research should include a completed system specification and/or system prototype.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>05/27/2014</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>12/23/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1415813</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Mark</FirstName>
<LastName>Strachan</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>D</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Mark D Strachan</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>mark@codesource-software.com</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>3106639273</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000659226</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/27/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>CodeSource Software Corp</Name>
<CityName>Thousand Oaks</CityName>
<ZipCode>913601327</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>3106639273</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>2702 San Miguel Circle</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>26</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CA26</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>621934889</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>CODESOURCE SOFTWARE CORP</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[CodeSource Software Corp]]></Name>
<CityName>Thousand Oaks</CityName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>913601327</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[2702 San Miguel circle]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>26</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CA26</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>5371</Code>
<Text>SBIR Phase I</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>110E</Code>
<Text>EDUCATION RESEARCH</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>163E</Code>
<Text>SBIR Phase IB</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1654</Code>
<Text>HUMAN COMPUTER INTERFACE</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>5371</Code>
<Text>SMALL BUSINESS PHASE I</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8031</Code>
<Text>Education Products</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8039</Code>
<Text>Information, Communication &amp; Computing</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0114</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0115</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~150000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2015~29999</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>This NSF SBIR funded project has been a research effort for Music Shaper-the Geometric System for Music Composition.&nbsp; Music Shaper provides a complete geometric encoding of western music theory, in cloud-based multi-touch software, with social networking integration.&nbsp; Music Shaper lets aspiring artists sculpt music visually, in a language of shape, touch and color.&nbsp; Music Shaper is a platform for musical expression, collaboration, and content sharing, which helps students climb the music theory and song writing learning curves quickly, so they can express musical ideas with intention.<br /><br />This project addresses the following problem--to write music, students must learn to understand music notation. Music notation is based on a centuries old system which obfuscates mathematical structures present in music, and complicates the learning process.&nbsp; Music Shaper advances the knowledge of the student and or/composer, using 2D &amp; 3D views &amp; color systems to construct a higher dimensional spatial representation of music.&nbsp; This representation removes obfuscations, &amp; enables user interfaces to provide intuitive musical expression, helping the student learn faster. <br /><br />The work with Music Shaper has defined a new way to navigate the space of harmony, combined with a new and intuitive way to describe rhythm.&nbsp; In addition to this, the work relating color models to intervals and chords, leverages the subjective controls made available in modern color models.&nbsp; Together, these features allow an aspiring artist to set an emotional context for their writing using coloration.&nbsp; They can then build and release tension, in rhythm with complementary colors.&nbsp; These colors are described by the intuitive color mapping, within the mathematical confines of the geometry, describing music theory rules.&nbsp; Complex musical structures are presented visually, as opposed to presentation embedded as abstract ideas within strings of obfuscated classical music notation.&nbsp; <br /><br />The investigators for this project believe this form of communication can help students jump up the learning curve for music theory and song writing, and help aspiring artists express musical ideas intentionally, rather than hunting and picking.&nbsp; This could open up opportunities for students to express themselves musically, and for new musical ideas to find their way into the world, through users of our system.&nbsp; We believe this invention has the potential to change how music is taught to students.&nbsp; Additionally, the project may open up possibilities for students who otherwise have difficulty communicating--i.e. autistic children.&nbsp; The system may provide them a new opportunity to express themselves.<br /><br />Music Shaper can benefit society because it will help more people experience and write music in a new &amp; fun way. It will share concepts from upper division &amp; graduate mathematics, graphically, with the general public. By helping people through the learning curve for music writing, it opens up commercial potential for new economic interactions--allowing users to sell each other content they create.&nbsp; Music Shaper presents a new way to write music, and a new way to teach it, where previously invisible structures are presented clearly and visually.&nbsp; Metadata describing the nature of the customers&rsquo; musical compositions shall be available as a resource for research into user behavior and interests, which could reveal interesting insights about music and the creative process.&nbsp; Music Shaper can impact society by helping transform the internet from a market of advertisers to a more desirable market of content producers, and simultaneously advance the state of the art in distributed computing.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 07/10/2015<br>      Modified by: Mark&nbsp;D&nbsp;Strachan</p> </div> <div...]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ This NSF SBIR funded project has been a research effort for Music Shaper-the Geometric System for Music Composition.  Music Shaper provides a complete geometric encoding of western music theory, in cloud-based multi-touch software, with social networking integration.  Music Shaper lets aspiring artists sculpt music visually, in a language of shape, touch and color.  Music Shaper is a platform for musical expression, collaboration, and content sharing, which helps students climb the music theory and song writing learning curves quickly, so they can express musical ideas with intention.  This project addresses the following problem--to write music, students must learn to understand music notation. Music notation is based on a centuries old system which obfuscates mathematical structures present in music, and complicates the learning process.  Music Shaper advances the knowledge of the student and or/composer, using 2D &amp; 3D views &amp; color systems to construct a higher dimensional spatial representation of music.  This representation removes obfuscations, &amp; enables user interfaces to provide intuitive musical expression, helping the student learn faster.   The work with Music Shaper has defined a new way to navigate the space of harmony, combined with a new and intuitive way to describe rhythm.  In addition to this, the work relating color models to intervals and chords, leverages the subjective controls made available in modern color models.  Together, these features allow an aspiring artist to set an emotional context for their writing using coloration.  They can then build and release tension, in rhythm with complementary colors.  These colors are described by the intuitive color mapping, within the mathematical confines of the geometry, describing music theory rules.  Complex musical structures are presented visually, as opposed to presentation embedded as abstract ideas within strings of obfuscated classical music notation.    The investigators for this project believe this form of communication can help students jump up the learning curve for music theory and song writing, and help aspiring artists express musical ideas intentionally, rather than hunting and picking.  This could open up opportunities for students to express themselves musically, and for new musical ideas to find their way into the world, through users of our system.  We believe this invention has the potential to change how music is taught to students.  Additionally, the project may open up possibilities for students who otherwise have difficulty communicating--i.e. autistic children.  The system may provide them a new opportunity to express themselves.  Music Shaper can benefit society because it will help more people experience and write music in a new &amp; fun way. It will share concepts from upper division &amp; graduate mathematics, graphically, with the general public. By helping people through the learning curve for music writing, it opens up commercial potential for new economic interactions--allowing users to sell each other content they create.  Music Shaper presents a new way to write music, and a new way to teach it, where previously invisible structures are presented clearly and visually.  Metadata describing the nature of the customersÆ musical compositions shall be available as a resource for research into user behavior and interests, which could reveal interesting insights about music and the creative process.  Music Shaper can impact society by helping transform the internet from a market of advertisers to a more desirable market of content producers, and simultaneously advance the state of the art in distributed computing.       Last Modified: 07/10/2015       Submitted by: Mark D Strachan]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
