<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Collaborative Research:   Ocean Acidification and Coral Reefs: Scale Dependence and Adaptive Capacity</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>01/01/2015</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>1892911.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>1892911</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>06040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>GEO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>OCE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Ocean Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Daniel J. Thornhill</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>dthornhi@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032928143</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Title:  Collaborative Research: Ocean Acidification and Coral Reefs - Scale Dependence and Adaptive Capacity&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project focuses on the most serious threat to marine ecosystems, Ocean Acidification (OA), and addresses the problem in the most diverse and beautiful ecosystem on the planet, coral reefs.  The research utilizes Moorea, French Polynesia as a model system, and builds from the NSF investment in the Moorea Coral Reef Long Term Ecological Research Site (LTER) to exploit physical and biological monitoring of coral reefs as a context for a program of studies focused on the ways in which OA will affect corals, calcified algae, and coral reef ecosystems.  The project builds on a four-year NSF award with research in five new directions: (1) experiments of year-long duration, (2) studies of coral reefs to 20-m depth, (3) experiments in which carbon dioxide will be administered to plots of coral reef underwater, (4) measurements of the capacity of coral reef organisms to change through evolutionary and induced responses to improve their resistance to OA, and (5) application of emerging theories to couple studies of individual organisms to studies of whole coral reefs.  Broader impacts will accrue through a better understanding of the ways in which OA will affect coral reefs that are the poster child for demonstrating climate change effects in the marine environment, and which provide income, food, and coastal protection to millions of people living in coastal areas, including in the United States.  Additionally, the research will have broad-reaching and cascading effects at multiple levels associated with public awareness of climate change effects, and the preparation of an American workforce focused on Science, Technology, Engineering and Mathematics (STEM) careers.  These effects will be realized by basing the research in a 4-year, Hispanic-serving campus California State University Northridge (CSUN) where undergraduates will have strong involvement in the project through classroom instruction and Research Experience for Undergraduates (REU) opportunities, and postdoctoral, graduate, and technical staff opportunities will be supported.  An ongoing program of high school involvement will be extended to include K-12 educators in Moorea, and integration of lesson plans between local schools and CSUN.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project focuses on the effects of Ocean Acidification on tropical coral reefs and builds on a program of research results from an existing 4-year award, and closely interfaces with the technical, hardware, and information infrastructure provided through the Moorea Coral Reef (MCR) LTER.  The MCR-LTER, provides an unparalleled opportunity to partner with a study of OA effects on a coral reef with a location that arguably is better instrumented and studied in more ecological detail than any other coral reef in the world.  Therefore, the results can be both contextualized by a high degree of ecological and physical relevance, and readily integrated into emerging theory seeking to predict the structure and function of coral reefs in warmer and more acidic future oceans.  The existing award has involved a program of study in Moorea that has focused mostly on short-term organismic and ecological responses of corals and calcified algae, experiments conducted in mesocosms and flumes, and measurements of reef-scale calcification.  This new award involves three new technical advances: for the first time, experiments will be conducted of year-long duration in replicate outdoor flumes; CO2 treatments will be administered to fully intact reef ecosystems in situ using replicated underwater flumes; and replicated common garden cultivation techniques will be used to explore within-species genetic variation in the response to OA conditions.  Together, these tools will be used to support research on corals and calcified algae in three thematic areas: (1) tests for long-term (1 year) effects of OA on growth, performance, and fitness, (2) tests for depth-dependent effects of OA on reef communities at 20-m depth where light regimes are attenuated compared to shallow water, and (3) tests for beneficial responses to OA through intrinsic, within-species genetic variability and phenotypic plasticity.  Some of the key experiments in these thematic areas will be designed to exploit integral projection models (IPMs) to couple organism with community responses, and to support the use of the metabolic theory of ecology (MTE) to address scale-dependence of OA effects on coral reef organisms and the function of the communities they build.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/06/2014</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/06/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.050</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1415268</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Robert</FirstName>
<LastName>Carpenter</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>C</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Robert C Carpenter</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>robert.carpenter@csun.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>8186773256</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000324812</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/06/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Peter</FirstName>
<LastName>Edmunds</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>J</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Peter J Edmunds</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>peter.edmunds@csun.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>8186772502</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000478133</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/06/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>The University Corporation, Northridge</Name>
<CityName>Northridge</CityName>
<ZipCode>913308309</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>8186771403</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>18111 Nordhoff Street</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>30</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CA30</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>055752331</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY CORPORATION, THE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>055752331</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[California State University-Northridge]]></Name>
<CityName>Northridge</CityName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>913308303</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[Department of Biology]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>30</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CA30</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>8001</Code>
<Text>CRI-Ocean Acidification</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1382</Code>
<Text>OCEAN ACIDIFICATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9117</Code>
<Text>MARINE BIOTECHNOLOGY</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9169</Code>
<Text>BIODIVERSITY AND ECOSYSTEM DYNAMICS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9229</Code>
<Text>RES IN UNDERGRAD INST-RESEARCH</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0114</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~1892911</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p class="normal"><strong>Overview</strong></p> <p class="normal">This project was designed to expand on an initial effort funded by NSF to explore the effects of ocean acidification on coral reefs. Having developed a foundational understanding of the organism-level effects of ocean acidification on corals and algae, in the present award we expanded understanding of ocean acidification on coral reefs through experiments with corals and algae grown in common gardens and with whole reef communities grown in the lab and on the reef. Growth in the common gardens revealed variation in the genetic capacity to respond to ocean acidification, and the experiments with reef communities addressed the complex response of diverse communities. Our analyses were conducted over temporal scales from weeks to a year, on both shallow back reef and deep fore reef deep habitats, and utilized autonomous experiments on undisturbed reef communities. At the conclusion of this award, our results reveal transformative discoveries related to a better understanding of the function of coral reefs in a more acidic future, the work has created an international experienced STEM workforce, and the scientific discoveries have been integrated with the curriculum of local schools.</p> <p class="normal"><strong>Intellectual merit</strong></p> <p class="normal">Our research has answered important questions through experimentation with individual corals and algae as well as the reef communities they build in multiple habitats. At each scale of investigation, we have advanced conceptual understanding and technical skills to complete experiments extending from the laboratory to underwater on undisturbed reef communities. The underwater experiments employ a Free Ocean Carbon Enrichment (FOCE) approach to create a new standard for measurement of metabolism of reef communities under conditions employing a high degree of realism.</p> <p class="normal">Our research with corals and algae from shallow reefs suggests these organisms will not find refuges from ocean acidification by exploiting shaded microhabitats, but spatial refuges might be found in locations with high flow speeds and natural daily cycles in the concentration of seawater carbon dioxide. Coral and algae show variation in their sensitivity of calcification to ocean acidification among genotypes within each species, thereby revealing the potential for evolution to favor organisms with the capacity to resist future conditions. To enhance the ecological relevance of our experiments, our research expanded to large, outdoor flumes of seawater in which coral communities could be kept for many months and be exposed to ocean acidification conditions. These experiments revealed the subtle effects of ocean acidification on reef communities, notably by favoring the dissolution of the rock and sediments upon which the living reef community is located. Over at least years, the live cover of corals and algae on reefs may show only small effects of ocean acidification, and they may persist until the underlying framework weakens and crumbles. Nevertheless, the rate at which limestone is deposited by reef organisms will decline under acidic seawater conditions, with the effects of these reductions hidden by variation in ways by which the carbonate is deposited to produce new skeletons. Corals and algae may increase in length at similar rates under future conditions, but this extension might be achieved by compromising skeletal strength. The veracity of these predictions are consistent with the results of our FOCE experiments, which underscores the threats posed to coral reefs by ocean acidification. In one glimmer of hope, our FOCE experiments suggests that reef communities can attenuate their sensitivity to ocean acidification at night, thereby suggesting that mechanisms may be present to reduce the susceptibility of net calcification to ocean acidification.&nbsp;</p> <p class="normal"><strong>Broader impacts</strong></p> <p class="normal">This research addressed the response of a beautiful and functionally important ecosystem to critical aspects of physical and chemical world that are changing in the 21<sup>st</sup> Century. By studying coral reefs and their response to ocean acidification, our work focuses on an ecosystem faced with functional extinction with dire consequences for humans that rely on them for income, protein, and coastal protection. Our results provide the most accurate and rigorous analyses of the ways in which reefs will respond to ocean acidification, thereby informing pro-active ecosystem management and societal decisions. The data from our analyses are freely available to inform these decisions.</p> <p class="normal">The research advances supported with this award have been accomplished by placing skilled teams of US researchers in a remote tropical location in the South Pacific. These teams have engaged diverse participants at multiple stages of career developed to work together to solve problems and advance science. These efforts have trained undergraduates, graduates, postdoctoral researchers, and technicians as globally-experienced members of the scientific workforce that can promote US leadership in science, technology, engineering, and math (STEM). To broaden the impacts of our work, we have integrated with high schools in California to advance scientific understanding and promote STEM careers through exciting discoveries and positive role models. In French Polynesia, this theme has been extended to local stakeholders and Village Elders, thus integrating our research with civic leadership decisions.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 01/08/2020<br>      Modified by: Robert&nbsp;C&nbsp;Carpenter</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Images (<span id="selectedPhoto0">1</span> of <span class="totalNumber"></span>)           </div> <div class="galControls" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1415268/1415268_10308203_1577815065103_Fig.2--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1415268/1415268_10308203_1577815065103_Fig.2--rgov-800width.jpg" title="FOCE flumes underwater in Moorea"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1415268/1415268_10308203_1577815065103_Fig.2--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="FOCE flumes underwater in Moorea"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Four, FOCE flumes deployed on the back reef of Moorea in 2019. These are supported with power and data from floating support platform, and typically are operated with two maintained at ambient conditions, and two at a future prediction of acidic seawater conditions.</div> <div class="imageCredit">P Edmunds</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Creative Commons</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Peter&nbsp;J&nbsp;Edmunds</div> <div class="imageTitle">FOCE flumes underwater in Moorea</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1415268/1415268_10308203_1577814992845_Fig.1--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1415268/1415268_10308203_1577814992845_Fig.1--rgov-800width.jpg" title="FOCE technology deployed in Moorea"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1415268/1415268_10308203_1577814992845_Fig.1--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="FOCE technology deployed in Moorea"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">FOCE technology deployed in the back reef of the north shore of Moorea, showing the floating white surface platform and the in-water flume bolted over an undisturbed area of reef at 3-m depth. Within the flume, seawater carbon dioxide conditions can be increased for months at a time.</div> <div class="imageCredit">P Edmunds</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Creative Commons</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Peter&nbsp;J&nbsp;Edmunds</div> <div class="imageTitle">FOCE technology deployed in Moorea</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1415268/1415268_10308203_1577815393255_Fig.3--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1415268/1415268_10308203_1577815393255_Fig.3--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Assembled back reef communities in flumes"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2019/1415268/1415268_10308203_1577815393255_Fig.3--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Assembled back reef communities in flumes"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Four, back reef communities assembled from organisms collected from the reefs of Moorea and incubated under controlled conditions simulating present and future scenarios for up to a year.</div> <div class="imageCredit">C. Lantz</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Creative Commons</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Peter&nbsp;J&nbsp;Edmunds</div> <div class="imageTitle">Assembled back reef communities in flumes</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[Overview This project was designed to expand on an initial effort funded by NSF to explore the effects of ocean acidification on coral reefs. Having developed a foundational understanding of the organism-level effects of ocean acidification on corals and algae, in the present award we expanded understanding of ocean acidification on coral reefs through experiments with corals and algae grown in common gardens and with whole reef communities grown in the lab and on the reef. Growth in the common gardens revealed variation in the genetic capacity to respond to ocean acidification, and the experiments with reef communities addressed the complex response of diverse communities. Our analyses were conducted over temporal scales from weeks to a year, on both shallow back reef and deep fore reef deep habitats, and utilized autonomous experiments on undisturbed reef communities. At the conclusion of this award, our results reveal transformative discoveries related to a better understanding of the function of coral reefs in a more acidic future, the work has created an international experienced STEM workforce, and the scientific discoveries have been integrated with the curriculum of local schools. Intellectual merit Our research has answered important questions through experimentation with individual corals and algae as well as the reef communities they build in multiple habitats. At each scale of investigation, we have advanced conceptual understanding and technical skills to complete experiments extending from the laboratory to underwater on undisturbed reef communities. The underwater experiments employ a Free Ocean Carbon Enrichment (FOCE) approach to create a new standard for measurement of metabolism of reef communities under conditions employing a high degree of realism. Our research with corals and algae from shallow reefs suggests these organisms will not find refuges from ocean acidification by exploiting shaded microhabitats, but spatial refuges might be found in locations with high flow speeds and natural daily cycles in the concentration of seawater carbon dioxide. Coral and algae show variation in their sensitivity of calcification to ocean acidification among genotypes within each species, thereby revealing the potential for evolution to favor organisms with the capacity to resist future conditions. To enhance the ecological relevance of our experiments, our research expanded to large, outdoor flumes of seawater in which coral communities could be kept for many months and be exposed to ocean acidification conditions. These experiments revealed the subtle effects of ocean acidification on reef communities, notably by favoring the dissolution of the rock and sediments upon which the living reef community is located. Over at least years, the live cover of corals and algae on reefs may show only small effects of ocean acidification, and they may persist until the underlying framework weakens and crumbles. Nevertheless, the rate at which limestone is deposited by reef organisms will decline under acidic seawater conditions, with the effects of these reductions hidden by variation in ways by which the carbonate is deposited to produce new skeletons. Corals and algae may increase in length at similar rates under future conditions, but this extension might be achieved by compromising skeletal strength. The veracity of these predictions are consistent with the results of our FOCE experiments, which underscores the threats posed to coral reefs by ocean acidification. In one glimmer of hope, our FOCE experiments suggests that reef communities can attenuate their sensitivity to ocean acidification at night, thereby suggesting that mechanisms may be present to reduce the susceptibility of net calcification to ocean acidification.  Broader impacts This research addressed the response of a beautiful and functionally important ecosystem to critical aspects of physical and chemical world that are changing in the 21st Century. By studying coral reefs and their response to ocean acidification, our work focuses on an ecosystem faced with functional extinction with dire consequences for humans that rely on them for income, protein, and coastal protection. Our results provide the most accurate and rigorous analyses of the ways in which reefs will respond to ocean acidification, thereby informing pro-active ecosystem management and societal decisions. The data from our analyses are freely available to inform these decisions. The research advances supported with this award have been accomplished by placing skilled teams of US researchers in a remote tropical location in the South Pacific. These teams have engaged diverse participants at multiple stages of career developed to work together to solve problems and advance science. These efforts have trained undergraduates, graduates, postdoctoral researchers, and technicians as globally-experienced members of the scientific workforce that can promote US leadership in science, technology, engineering, and math (STEM). To broaden the impacts of our work, we have integrated with high schools in California to advance scientific understanding and promote STEM careers through exciting discoveries and positive role models. In French Polynesia, this theme has been extended to local stakeholders and Village Elders, thus integrating our research with civic leadership decisions.          Last Modified: 01/08/2020       Submitted by: Robert C Carpenter]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
