<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>SEES Fellowship: Integrating Computational Toxicology and Green Chemistry to design inherently safer functional replacements for harmful industrial chemicals</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2014</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>504512.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>504512</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03090000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CHE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Chemistry</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Anne-Marie Schmoltner</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>aschmolt@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924716</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The project is supported under the NSF Science, Engineering and Education for Sustainability Fellows (SEES Fellows) program, with the goal of helping to enable discoveries needed to inform actions that lead to environmental, energy and societal sustainability while creating the necessary workforce to address these challenges. Sustainability science is an emerging field that addresses the challenges of meeting human needs without harm to the environment, and without sacrificing the ability of future generations to meet their needs. A strong scientific workforce requires individuals educated and trained in interdisciplinary research and thinking, especially in the area of sustainability science. With the SEES Fellowship support, this project will enable a promising early career researcher to establish himself in an independent research career related to sustainability. This project focuses on sustainable materials, with a multidisciplinary approach combining chemistry and toxicology. This integrated approach to sustainable chemical development will provide the Fellow with tools and experiences to make fundamentally better molecules and materials. This approach enables new classes of safer chemicals to be characterized and preferentially adopted early during the design process. The products of this research will be disseminated to students through the Berkeley Center for Green Chemistry (BCGC) Greener Solutions Program and to relevant industry partners through the BCGC Consortium Program and the UC Berkeley Industry Research Alliances.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Greater than 95% of synthetic chemicals and materials are petroleum-based, the vast majority of which are built around a relatively small subset of roughly 140 petroleum-derived feedstock chemicals. The environmental and health costs of using non-renewable and often toxic petrochemical feedstocks and their derivatives are high. Renewable chemicals with desired functions that also lack the disadvantages of conventional petrochemical-based chemicals are urgently needed. Biological molecules are an attractive pool of feedstock molecules. Due to their structural and chemical diversity relative to petroleum feedstock molecules, there may be molecules that are functionally equivalent to toxic petroleum molecules yet have fewer negative attributes than their conventional counterparts. This fellowship builds on existing partnerships between professors Chris Vulpe and Dale Johnson in the Molecular Toxicology graduate program at UC Berkeley and the Chemists working with the Berkeley Center for Green Chemistry. In addition to bridging chemistry and toxicology, the molecules and approaches identified in this work will be evaluated by Rui Resendes at the GreenCentre Canada, to assess their commercial viability.  By combining state of the art computational tools with basic statistical analysis it will be possible to rapidly screen large data sets and uncover new classes of biological molecules that share essential functional properties with the current generation of industrial chemicals. As promising candidate molecules are identified, they will be screened against relevant human and environmental health hazards. The work combines chemistry and toxicology to discover and characterize chemicals that are fundamentally safer and perform a range of industrial functions.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This research develosp tools that identify and transition inherently more sustainable chemistries into the market. The results of this research will be leveraged by interactions with the Berkeley Center for Green Chemistry (BCGC) which interacts with stakeholders across chemically intensive supply chains. The current market lacks clear tools for identifying chemical hazards early during the design process leading to regrettable substitutes. This fellowship will develop ties between academia and external entrepreneurs who have experience taking green technologies to scale in the market place. This partnership will promote early stage techno-economic&lt;br/&gt;evaluation of innovations and translate basic science to influence industrial chemical selection. The range of professional development and industry interactions will ensure that the technologies and insights gained as a part of this fellowship are translated into the broader stakeholder community.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/08/2014</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/08/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1415417</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Martin</FirstName>
<LastName>Mulvihill</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>J</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Martin J Mulvihill</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>marty_m@berkeley.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5106428109</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000593185</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/08/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of California-Berkeley</Name>
<CityName>BERKELEY</CityName>
<ZipCode>947101749</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5106433891</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>Sponsored Projects Office</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[1608 Fourth Street, Suite 220]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>13</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CA13</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>124726725</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>REGENTS OF THE UNIVERSITY OF CALIFORNIA, THE</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>071549000</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of California-Berkeley]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>947201460</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>13</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CA13</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>8055</Code>
<Text>SEES Fellows</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8232</Code>
<Text>SEES Fellows</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0114</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~504512</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The goal of this project was to advance the design of inherently safer chemistry. We developed new tools to help scientists and product designers find and choose safer, biobased chemicals to use in consumer products. There has been a growing consumer awareness concerning the presence of potentially harmful chemicals in consumer products and packaging. This has created a demand for chemical alternatives that perform important functions like making plastic flexible and preserving foods and products without causing harm to human or environmental health.</p> <p>Biobased chemicals are a particularly attractive target for safer alternatives. In order to ensure that chemical alternatives are safer for human health and the environment, we developed screening tools for to ensure that alternatives are both high performing and safer than the currently used petroleum based chemicals. During this grant period we focused our efforts on plasticizers and preservatives, which have both been targeted for chemical alternatives development.&nbsp; Through the course of our research we identified and tested alternatives for phthalates, preservatives, and isocyanates in insulation foam. The results of these studies were published in peer reviewed journals and they were shared with relevant companies and government organizations looking for safer chemicals.</p> <p>We identified two new classes of safer plasticizers that could be used to eliminate the use of phthalates in a number of consumer and building products. Our initial results indicated that these alternatives were more effective than the current petroleum based plasticizers. These results were shared with local biobased chemical companies including Solyzme and Amyris, so that they could evaluate larger scale biological production of these chemicals.</p> <p>We conducted an alternatives assessment of insulation products with a focus on finding a high performing alternative to isocyanates in polyurethane foams. These results were shared with General coatings a California based manufacture of foam insulation as well as the California Department of Toxic Substance Control who is currently considering regulation of isocyanates. Our work has the potential to find safer and more cost effective alternatives that would enable increases in building efficiency and the creation of more local manufacturing and installation jobs.</p> <p>Finally, we identified and tested a range of safer preservatives for their antimicrobial effectiveness and human and environmental hazard, and compare them to conventional preservatives. By considering chemical safety as a key performance criterion, our approach facilitated the direct evaluation of the tradeoffs inherent in selecting preservatives.&nbsp; We also proposed our solution to the GC3 Challenge: Developing New Preservatives for Personal Care &amp; Household Products which means that our approach will be considered by large companies for inclusion in their formulated products.</p> <p>The funding provided for this work has catalyzed the discovery and evaluation of safer chemistry across a number of product categories. While it will take a while for these new chemistries to be widely adopted they each have the potential to vastly improve environmental and human health and thereby create far reaching economic benefits.&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 09/26/2017<br>      Modified by: Martin&nbsp;J&nbsp;Mulvihill</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Image         </div> <div class="galControls onePhoto" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation onePhoto" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1415417/1415417_10316788_1506474225432_OverviewGraphic--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1415417/1415417_10316788_1506474225432_OverviewGraphic--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Screening protocol"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2017/1415417/1415417_10316788_1506474225432_OverviewGraphic--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Screening protocol"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">We used a multi-component screening process to evaluate the design of safer biobased chemicals.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Heather Buckley</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Creative Commons</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Martin&nbsp;J&nbsp;Mulvihill</div> <div class="imageTitle">Screening protocol</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The goal of this project was to advance the design of inherently safer chemistry. We developed new tools to help scientists and product designers find and choose safer, biobased chemicals to use in consumer products. There has been a growing consumer awareness concerning the presence of potentially harmful chemicals in consumer products and packaging. This has created a demand for chemical alternatives that perform important functions like making plastic flexible and preserving foods and products without causing harm to human or environmental health.  Biobased chemicals are a particularly attractive target for safer alternatives. In order to ensure that chemical alternatives are safer for human health and the environment, we developed screening tools for to ensure that alternatives are both high performing and safer than the currently used petroleum based chemicals. During this grant period we focused our efforts on plasticizers and preservatives, which have both been targeted for chemical alternatives development.  Through the course of our research we identified and tested alternatives for phthalates, preservatives, and isocyanates in insulation foam. The results of these studies were published in peer reviewed journals and they were shared with relevant companies and government organizations looking for safer chemicals.  We identified two new classes of safer plasticizers that could be used to eliminate the use of phthalates in a number of consumer and building products. Our initial results indicated that these alternatives were more effective than the current petroleum based plasticizers. These results were shared with local biobased chemical companies including Solyzme and Amyris, so that they could evaluate larger scale biological production of these chemicals.  We conducted an alternatives assessment of insulation products with a focus on finding a high performing alternative to isocyanates in polyurethane foams. These results were shared with General coatings a California based manufacture of foam insulation as well as the California Department of Toxic Substance Control who is currently considering regulation of isocyanates. Our work has the potential to find safer and more cost effective alternatives that would enable increases in building efficiency and the creation of more local manufacturing and installation jobs.  Finally, we identified and tested a range of safer preservatives for their antimicrobial effectiveness and human and environmental hazard, and compare them to conventional preservatives. By considering chemical safety as a key performance criterion, our approach facilitated the direct evaluation of the tradeoffs inherent in selecting preservatives.  We also proposed our solution to the GC3 Challenge: Developing New Preservatives for Personal Care &amp; Household Products which means that our approach will be considered by large companies for inclusion in their formulated products.  The funding provided for this work has catalyzed the discovery and evaluation of safer chemistry across a number of product categories. While it will take a while for these new chemistries to be widely adopted they each have the potential to vastly improve environmental and human health and thereby create far reaching economic benefits.           Last Modified: 09/26/2017       Submitted by: Martin J Mulvihill]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
