<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>EAPSI: Measuring the hearing and echolocation characteristics of a Risso's dolphin</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>06/01/2014</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2015</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>5070.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>5070</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Fellowship Award</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>01090000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>O/D</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Office Of The Director</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>OISE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Office Of Internatl Science &amp;Engineering</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Anne Emig</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>aemig@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927241</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>All toothed whales and dolphins possess highly developed hearing and biosonar systems that cannot be replicated even with modern technology. These exceptional capabilities are the result of extremely specialized anatomical structures in the head. A better understanding of these systems in toothed whales may lead to improved technological advancements for signal processing, sonar techniques, medical imaging devices, and cochlear implants. One species of dolphin, the Risso's dolphin, has evolved a unique vertical crease on its forehead which is absent in other dolphin species. Although the function of this crease is unknown, its location on the head indicates it likely plays an important role in the hearing or echolocation systems. Detailed study of these systems requires the cooperation of a trained captive subject animal. In collaboration with Dr. Jack Wei-Cheng Yang at National Chiayi University in Taiwan, this project will investigate the function of the melon crease by measuring the hearing capabilities and echolocation sounds of a trained captive Risso's dolphin at Farglory Ocean Park in Hualien, Taiwan, one of only three captive individuals of this species in the world. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Proposed experiments for this project will 1) measure the hearing sensitivities of the animal to acoustic stimuli presented at different points on the animal's head, and 2) measure acoustic characteristics of the echolocation beam in the near and far sound field.  Hearing measurements will be conducted using non-invasive Auditory Brainstem Response (ABR) methodology, which measures nerve impulses from the brainstem in response to the reception of sound. Echolocation beam patterns in the near and far field will be recorded using a variable array of synchronized hydrophones. The proposed study would represent the first description of the hearing pathways and echolocation beam patterns in the Risso's dolphin and the first step toward studying the functional morphology of the melon cleft. This NSF EAPSI award is funded in collaboration with the National Science Council of Taiwan.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/15/2014</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/15/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.079</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1415110</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Adam</FirstName>
<LastName>Smith</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>B</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Adam B Smith</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress/>
<PI_PHON>6057703381</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000660290</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/15/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Smith                   Adam           B</Name>
<CityName>Honolulu</CityName>
<ZipCode>968163907</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber/>
<StreetAddress/>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Hawaii</StateName>
<StateCode>HI</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>HI01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM/>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME/>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Hawaii Institute of Marine Biology]]></Name>
<CityName>Kaneohe</CityName>
<StateCode>HI</StateCode>
<ZipCode>967443617</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Hawaii</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>HI02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7316</Code>
<Text>EAPSI</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>5924</Code>
<Text>TAIWAN</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>5978</Code>
<Text>EAST ASIA AND PACIFIC PROGRAM</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7316</Code>
<Text>EAPSI</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0114</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~5070</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>In collaboration with Dr. Wei-Cheng Yang at National Chiayi University, and Dr. I-Fan Jen at Farglory Ocean Park in Taiwan, this 2014 EAPSI Taiwan fellowship afforded me the amazing opportunity to travel to Taiwan to conduct research on the hearing and biosonar systems of a little studied species of captive marine mammal, the Risso's dolphin. All toothed whales and dolphins possess highly developed hearing and biosonar systems. These exceptional capabilities are the result of extremely specialized anatomical structures in the head. The Risso's dolphin has evolved a unique vertical crease on its forehead which is absent in other dolphin species. Although the function of this crease is unknown, its location on the head indicates it likely plays an important role in the hearing or echolocation systems. A better understanding and ability to compare these systems between species may reveal ecological factors that influenced the development of these adaptations. Furthermore, it may lead to improved technological advancements for signal processing, sonar techniques and medical imaging devices.</p> <p>As part of this EAPSI fellowship, experiments were conducted that measured hearing sensitivities of the animal to acoustic stimuli presented at different points on the animal's head, as well as the acoustic characteristics of the echolocation signal beam in the far sound field. Over 3000 echolocation signals were recorded, along with hearing measurements at 11 points around the animal's head using non-invasive Auditory Brainstem Response (ABR) methodology, which records nerve impulses from the brainstem in response to the reception of sound. The results of these experiments are being presented at professional scientific conferences and will be submitted for publication in peer review journals.</p> <p>In addition to the research goals, the completion of this East Asia and Pacific Summer Institutes Fellowship has resulted in the formation of a long term research collaboration between the participating institutions that will extend long past the duration of this fellowship project. Research faculty and staff at National Chiayi University were successfully trained on how to complete future bioacoustic research project with captive animals in Taiwan, while multiple undergraduate students in Taiwan were exposed for the first time to the field of marine mammal bioacoustic research. Furthermore, training staff at Farglory Ocean Park were taught how to successfully train animals in their care for complicated behaviors that will enable more in-depth research questions to be answered with subsequent projects.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 02/28/2015<br>      Modified by: Adam&nbsp;B&nbsp;Smith</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ In collaboration with Dr. Wei-Cheng Yang at National Chiayi University, and Dr. I-Fan Jen at Farglory Ocean Park in Taiwan, this 2014 EAPSI Taiwan fellowship afforded me the amazing opportunity to travel to Taiwan to conduct research on the hearing and biosonar systems of a little studied species of captive marine mammal, the Risso's dolphin. All toothed whales and dolphins possess highly developed hearing and biosonar systems. These exceptional capabilities are the result of extremely specialized anatomical structures in the head. The Risso's dolphin has evolved a unique vertical crease on its forehead which is absent in other dolphin species. Although the function of this crease is unknown, its location on the head indicates it likely plays an important role in the hearing or echolocation systems. A better understanding and ability to compare these systems between species may reveal ecological factors that influenced the development of these adaptations. Furthermore, it may lead to improved technological advancements for signal processing, sonar techniques and medical imaging devices.  As part of this EAPSI fellowship, experiments were conducted that measured hearing sensitivities of the animal to acoustic stimuli presented at different points on the animal's head, as well as the acoustic characteristics of the echolocation signal beam in the far sound field. Over 3000 echolocation signals were recorded, along with hearing measurements at 11 points around the animal's head using non-invasive Auditory Brainstem Response (ABR) methodology, which records nerve impulses from the brainstem in response to the reception of sound. The results of these experiments are being presented at professional scientific conferences and will be submitted for publication in peer review journals.  In addition to the research goals, the completion of this East Asia and Pacific Summer Institutes Fellowship has resulted in the formation of a long term research collaboration between the participating institutions that will extend long past the duration of this fellowship project. Research faculty and staff at National Chiayi University were successfully trained on how to complete future bioacoustic research project with captive animals in Taiwan, while multiple undergraduate students in Taiwan were exposed for the first time to the field of marine mammal bioacoustic research. Furthermore, training staff at Farglory Ocean Park were taught how to successfully train animals in their care for complicated behaviors that will enable more in-depth research questions to be answered with subsequent projects.       Last Modified: 02/28/2015       Submitted by: Adam B Smith]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
