<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Cornell Program for Student-Centered Accelerator Science</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2014</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>9972786.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>10597786</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03010000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>PHY</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Physics</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Vyacheslav (Slava) Lukin</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>vlukin@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927382</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This award addresses the fundamental physics and technology of modern accelerators through a program aimed at investigating and understanding the phenomena driving the behavior of compact, high power beams.  This includes studies of bright sources and RF superconductivity. In addition, the extensive instrumentation and flexibility of the Cornell Electron Storage Ring (CESR) will provide a framework to carry a program of accelerator science studies.  A better understanding of the physics and behavior of particle beams and related technology paves the way for new accelerators that are ever more powerful probes of materials, biological systems, molecules, atoms, nuclei and the most fundamental particles in nature. Research accelerators may be used to develop new drugs, to design lighter and stronger jet engine components, or better battery technology. Accelerators are tools of discovery that may inspire young scientists to explore our universe. Future accelerators may also enable the manufacture of smaller computer chips, more effective border security, and a safer food supply.  This program will also train future accelerator scientists. The participating graduate and postdoctoral students will have the opportunity to operate state of the art particle accelerators, and to advance the understanding of accelerated beams and beam technology. The operational experience will prepare them for leadership roles in accelerator science and future accelerators. The public will also gain deeper understanding of accelerator-based research through guided tours of the Cornell facilities.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Superconducting RF (SRF) is by far the most energy efficient means of accelerating a beam of charged particles. The Cornell SRF research will focus on the physics of microwave superconductivity. The physics that limits the performance and efficiency of SRF cavities will be studied in order to improve the technology and advance the capabilities of future accelerators. The combination of state of the art SRF expertise and technology with Cornell's world's brightest electron source provides an experimental program focused on very high power beams.  The high energy storage ring CESR is the vehicle for systematic study of the phenomena that emerge and ultimately limit particle density in very compact beams, thereby contributing to studies of fourth generation synchrotron light x-ray sources and electron positron colliders, building on past work that has led to the design of damping rings for linear and circular colliders. The particle source ultimately determines the quality of the accelerated beam and the power it can deliver. As part of this award, new electron source materials will be developed with a thorough understanding of material properties that is supported by theoretical considerations as well as direct measurements.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/30/2014</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/07/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1416318</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Donald</FirstName>
<LastName>Hartill</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>L</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Donald L Hartill</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>dlh13@cornell.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6072558787</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000432322</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/30/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>David</FirstName>
<LastName>Rubin</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>David Rubin</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>dlr10@cornell.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON/>
<NSF_ID>000202762</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/30/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Georg</FirstName>
<LastName>Hoffstaetter</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>H</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Georg H Hoffstaetter</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>gh77@cornell.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6072555197</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000322135</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/30/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Matthias</FirstName>
<LastName>Liepe</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>U</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Matthias U Liepe</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>MUL2@cornell.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6072548937</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000077214</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/30/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Ivan</FirstName>
<LastName>Bazarov</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>V</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Ivan V Bazarov</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>ib38@cornell.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6072542781</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000082546</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/30/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Cornell University</Name>
<CityName>Ithaca</CityName>
<ZipCode>148502820</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6072555014</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>373 Pine Tree Road</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>23</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NY23</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>872612445</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>CORNELL UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>002254837</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Cornell University]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<ZipCode>148502820</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>23</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NY23</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7243</Code>
<Text>Accelerator Science</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0114</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0115</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0116</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~3497786</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2015~4125000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2016~2975000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The three major thrusts of the project were; to study emittance limits in the Cornell Electron Storage Ring, to develop techniques to enhance the efficiency in RF superconducting accelerators, and to develop and characterize a cryogenically cooled photoemission source.</p> <p><strong>Emittance Limits in Storage Rings</strong></p> <p>Beam instrumentation was developed and installed in the Cornell Electron-positron Storage Ring to measure the position, and size of individual bunches of electrons and positrons as they circulate,&nbsp;at a sampling rate of upwards of 250 MHz. The instrumentation enabled bunch-by-bunch and turn-by-turn measurements of trains of as many as 40 closely spaced bunches. The instrumentation was used to characterize phenomena that limit beam emittance (brightness), especially as a result of the electron cloud. Software was created to analyze the extensive experimental data. The measurements informed numerical models that can be used to predict electron cloud effects, including electron density, associated tune shifts and emittance growth.</p> <p>Our measurements indicated that electron cloud contributes to horizontal as well as vertical tune shifts and emittance growth, and provided the first direct observation of the contribution of the pinch effect to equilibrium beam size. The availability of control measurements with electron beams was invaluable in reducing systematic uncertainties.</p> <p>The new instrumentation and our experimental findings and modeling codes, will be important to the design and performance of high energy positron, proton and heavy ion accelerators, and low emittance sources of synchrotron x-rays.</p> <p><strong>RF superconductivity</strong></p> <p>High performance superconducting RF (SRF) is a key technology that will enable new, powerful accelerators for a wide range of sciences, providing evermore powerful probes of materials, biological systems, molecules, atoms, nuclei and the most fundamental particles in nature. Next-generation SRF accelerating cavities also&nbsp;have the potential of wide societal impact by enabling new, energy-efficient particle accelerators for energy generation, nuclear waste transmutation, for medical applications, and for national security.&nbsp;</p> <p>The SRF work funded by this project has led to SRF cavities with much higher energy efficiency by developing optimized low-temperature impurity doping protocols of superconductors and optimized SRF cavity cool-down procedures. For example, this work has been critical in the development of the high-efficiency SRF cavities for the Linac Coherent Light Source-II (LCLS-II) currently under construction at SLAC.Research supported by this project also showed that metastable RF fields above the lower critical field limit of a superconductor can be reached, thus demonstrating the feasibility of next-generation SRF cavities using new, higher temperature superconductors. This project has led to improved understanding of the fundamental physics of superconductors under extreme field conditions, and near fundamental limits.</p> <p><strong>Photoemission sources</strong></p> <p><strong>&nbsp;</strong>This award supported detailed beam dynamics simulations, design, construction and successful commissioning of a novel cryogenically cooled photoemission high-voltage gun. This device is capable of producing highest brightness electron beams, which can find myriad uses; from making molecular movies, to enabling high energy particle colliders for exploration of the fundamental forces of nature.</p> <p>To better understand the behavior of photocathodes in accelerators, a previously developed simulation code has been extended to cryogenically cooled systems to predict photoemission properties such as spectral sensitivity,&nbsp;&nbsp;response time, and transverse momentum spread from a cesium antimonide photocathode. These simulations have been compared to experimental data and give favorable projections of main photoemission characteristics when cooled down all the way to single digit Kelvin temperatures.&nbsp;</p> <p>Systematic measurements of ultralow transverse energy spreads from photocathodes have been carried out utilizing devices developed to resolve lowest-to-date photoelectron transverse energy. We have also developed new photocathodes for use in accelerators that have an extended photoemission response, which simplifies the requirements, complexity and cost of the associated laser systems.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p><strong>Training</strong></p> <p><strong></strong>The work for all three project thrusts was carried out by graduate and undergraduate students, and postdoctoral associates, with technical support from laboratory staff, and under the direction of the PI and co-PIs.&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 01/04/2019<br>      Modified by: David&nbsp;Rubin</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The three major thrusts of the project were; to study emittance limits in the Cornell Electron Storage Ring, to develop techniques to enhance the efficiency in RF superconducting accelerators, and to develop and characterize a cryogenically cooled photoemission source.  Emittance Limits in Storage Rings  Beam instrumentation was developed and installed in the Cornell Electron-positron Storage Ring to measure the position, and size of individual bunches of electrons and positrons as they circulate, at a sampling rate of upwards of 250 MHz. The instrumentation enabled bunch-by-bunch and turn-by-turn measurements of trains of as many as 40 closely spaced bunches. The instrumentation was used to characterize phenomena that limit beam emittance (brightness), especially as a result of the electron cloud. Software was created to analyze the extensive experimental data. The measurements informed numerical models that can be used to predict electron cloud effects, including electron density, associated tune shifts and emittance growth.  Our measurements indicated that electron cloud contributes to horizontal as well as vertical tune shifts and emittance growth, and provided the first direct observation of the contribution of the pinch effect to equilibrium beam size. The availability of control measurements with electron beams was invaluable in reducing systematic uncertainties.  The new instrumentation and our experimental findings and modeling codes, will be important to the design and performance of high energy positron, proton and heavy ion accelerators, and low emittance sources of synchrotron x-rays.  RF superconductivity  High performance superconducting RF (SRF) is a key technology that will enable new, powerful accelerators for a wide range of sciences, providing evermore powerful probes of materials, biological systems, molecules, atoms, nuclei and the most fundamental particles in nature. Next-generation SRF accelerating cavities also have the potential of wide societal impact by enabling new, energy-efficient particle accelerators for energy generation, nuclear waste transmutation, for medical applications, and for national security.   The SRF work funded by this project has led to SRF cavities with much higher energy efficiency by developing optimized low-temperature impurity doping protocols of superconductors and optimized SRF cavity cool-down procedures. For example, this work has been critical in the development of the high-efficiency SRF cavities for the Linac Coherent Light Source-II (LCLS-II) currently under construction at SLAC.Research supported by this project also showed that metastable RF fields above the lower critical field limit of a superconductor can be reached, thus demonstrating the feasibility of next-generation SRF cavities using new, higher temperature superconductors. This project has led to improved understanding of the fundamental physics of superconductors under extreme field conditions, and near fundamental limits.  Photoemission sources   This award supported detailed beam dynamics simulations, design, construction and successful commissioning of a novel cryogenically cooled photoemission high-voltage gun. This device is capable of producing highest brightness electron beams, which can find myriad uses; from making molecular movies, to enabling high energy particle colliders for exploration of the fundamental forces of nature.  To better understand the behavior of photocathodes in accelerators, a previously developed simulation code has been extended to cryogenically cooled systems to predict photoemission properties such as spectral sensitivity,  response time, and transverse momentum spread from a cesium antimonide photocathode. These simulations have been compared to experimental data and give favorable projections of main photoemission characteristics when cooled down all the way to single digit Kelvin temperatures.   Systematic measurements of ultralow transverse energy spreads from photocathodes have been carried out utilizing devices developed to resolve lowest-to-date photoelectron transverse energy. We have also developed new photocathodes for use in accelerators that have an extended photoemission response, which simplifies the requirements, complexity and cost of the associated laser systems.     Training  The work for all three project thrusts was carried out by graduate and undergraduate students, and postdoctoral associates, with technical support from laboratory staff, and under the direction of the PI and co-PIs.        Last Modified: 01/04/2019       Submitted by: David Rubin]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
