<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>SBIR Phase I:  Bandages for Wound Healing</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2014</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2015</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>150000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>150000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07070000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>IIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Industrial Innovation &amp; Partnersh</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Rajesh Mehta</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>rmehta@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032922174</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The broader impact/commercial potential of this project is in enabling the development of inexpensive miniature pumps that can be integrated with bandages in order to apply negative pressure therapy to wounds.  Negative pressure wound therapy (NPWT) is the most commonly prescribed therapy for wounds that do not heal by themselves (i.e. chronic wounds), or to make wounds heal faster.  However, a limitation is that the application of NPWT is constrained by the price of the pump, as a result of which, wounds fester in individuals, before therapy can be prescribed.  It is noted that inexpensive and miniature pumps capable of applying therapeutic levels of negative pressure are not currently available.  This project enables the development of these inexpensive pumps.  The commercial potential of the project is in the possibility of widespread use of bandages that incorporate pumps capable of applying negative pressure to all wounds.  These pumps, which can apply high as well as low pressure, in a small form factor, can be used in a multitude of other applications as well.    &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This Small Business Innovation Research (SBIR) Phase I project involves the manufacture of miniature, low-weight, energy-efficient, and inexpensive pumps that are integrated onto bandages.  We will test the efficacy of bandages that incorporate the current generation of pumps in generating therapeutic magnitudes of negative pressure.  It is noted that electronics is the primary driver of component costs in the current generation of pumps.  Therefore, we propose to micro-manufacture components of the electronics that will be used to operate the pumps.  Micro-manufacturing the electronics can generate tremendous cost-savings that will enable an order of magnitude reduction in the cost of pumps, enabling them to be integrated onto all bandages.  Micro-manufacturing will also enable miniaturization, and lowering of weight of the pumps.  Finally, the developed pumps will enable new applications as they are able to generate significantly high pressures as well as low pressures while occupying a very small volume.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>05/21/2014</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/21/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1416359</AwardID>
<Institution>
<Name>Bionic Concepts</Name>
<CityName>West Hartford</CityName>
<ZipCode>061191254</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>8167281251</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>52 Robin Rd, B2</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Connecticut</StateName>
<StateCode>CT</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>01</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CT01</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>829141139</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>BIONIC CONCEPTS</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Bionic Concepts Inc.]]></Name>
<CityName>Mechanicville</CityName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
<ZipCode>121183659</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[11 Foxhound Circle]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>20</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NY20</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>5371</Code>
<Text>SBIR Phase I</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>028E</Code>
<Text>BIOMECHANICS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>5371</Code>
<Text>SMALL BUSINESS PHASE I</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8029</Code>
<Text>Manufacturing</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8034</Code>
<Text>Hardware Components</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0114</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~150000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>This Small Business Innovation Research Phase I project developed a miniature and low cost bandage for negative pressure wound therapy. Chronic wounds are a debilitating problem, affect 6.5 million individuals and costing $25 billion annually in the US alone.&nbsp;NPWT has been shown to be extremely effective at healing these wounds, with annual sales of $2 billion. However, NPWT is only available via a prescription, and typically only prescribed after wounds become chronic. This means that patients are usually hospitalized before receiving treatment. By making our bandage lower cost and smaller, it will make it more accessible to patients and will be more likely to be prescribed as a first resort rather than a last resort. Early treatment of all wounds by application of our NPWT bandage before some of these wounds become serious and chronic would significantly reduce costs associated with hospital/nurse visits, and physician/nursing care. This would reduce the amount of time spent by patients in hospitals because of chronic wounds, and therefore reduce suffer and medical expenses. In addition, there are over 71.5 million surgical procedures performed in the US (40 million inpatient, 31.5 million out-patient), where it is important to speed-up healing. Shorter healing times can reduce the probability of exposure to anti-biotic resistant bacteria, which are becoming more prevalent. Use of our NPWT bandage on these wounds will speed up healing and lower costs for patients and tax payers alike.</p> <p>The NPWT bandage developed by this Phase I award is substantially cheaper and smaller than any current negative pressure wound therapy device available on the market today, and our bandage has similar performance in terms of flow rate, vacuum, and battery life. Substantial work during this Phase I award went into designing a manufacturing process that is fast, low cost, and repeatable. And a lot of effort went into making the pump energy efficient, especially when operating at high flow rates. These efforts were done in addition to the effort proposed because it was determined that these were critical to make our pump the best available on the market.</p> <p>Flow rates of our pumps were increased from 50ml/min to up to 600ml/min during Phase I. This was a significant improvement which was necessary to evacuate the area under the bandage in a reasonable amount of time. In speaking with physicians and nurses, who are the primary users of NPWT devices, we learned that a high flowrate is required so that they know there are no leaks present in a freshly used bandage. The maximum flowrate of pumping viscous liquid was determined, and it was significantly lower than that of air (27ml/min versus 600ml/min). This was because the resonant frequency of the pump was much lower when pumping a high density liquid when compared to a gas. However, higher flowrates are only necessary immediately after a bandage is applied, so it can be determined there are no leaks. Afterward, when exudate is being emitted by the wound, higher flowrates are not required. Being able to pump exudate is something no other NPWT device can do currently. This makes our pump well suited for over the counter use, as we will not need an exudate separator and reservoir, thus reducing the size of our bandage.</p> <p>Physicians we spoke to said a common problem is that leaks occur, or bandages are removed (sometimes by the patient) and then insufficient therapy is administered. Therefore, we developed a means to measure and record vacuum levels. A Bluetooth module was incorporated into a circuit to control the pump and measure vacuum levels. And a smartphone app was written to control the pump and record vacuum level data to a file. This is a first for any NPWT device, and makes our product very competitive.</p> <p>In conclusion; NPWT is a very effective therapy for treating chronic and non-healing wounds. However, NPWT is prohibitively expensive and can only be prescribed and administered in a clinical setting. Making a NPWT bandage that is smaller, cheaper, and more available to patients would greatly reduce medical expenses associated with chronic wounds, and would reduce patient suffering because wounds would be treated earlier. Therefore, we have developed a small, low-cost, and energy NPWT bandage. Pump inside the bandage has performance features that meet or exceed those of currently available NPWT pumps. The pump and bandage use low cost manufacturing techniques.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 08/12/2015<br>      Modified by: Robert&nbsp;Nesbitt</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ This Small Business Innovation Research Phase I project developed a miniature and low cost bandage for negative pressure wound therapy. Chronic wounds are a debilitating problem, affect 6.5 million individuals and costing $25 billion annually in the US alone. NPWT has been shown to be extremely effective at healing these wounds, with annual sales of $2 billion. However, NPWT is only available via a prescription, and typically only prescribed after wounds become chronic. This means that patients are usually hospitalized before receiving treatment. By making our bandage lower cost and smaller, it will make it more accessible to patients and will be more likely to be prescribed as a first resort rather than a last resort. Early treatment of all wounds by application of our NPWT bandage before some of these wounds become serious and chronic would significantly reduce costs associated with hospital/nurse visits, and physician/nursing care. This would reduce the amount of time spent by patients in hospitals because of chronic wounds, and therefore reduce suffer and medical expenses. In addition, there are over 71.5 million surgical procedures performed in the US (40 million inpatient, 31.5 million out-patient), where it is important to speed-up healing. Shorter healing times can reduce the probability of exposure to anti-biotic resistant bacteria, which are becoming more prevalent. Use of our NPWT bandage on these wounds will speed up healing and lower costs for patients and tax payers alike.  The NPWT bandage developed by this Phase I award is substantially cheaper and smaller than any current negative pressure wound therapy device available on the market today, and our bandage has similar performance in terms of flow rate, vacuum, and battery life. Substantial work during this Phase I award went into designing a manufacturing process that is fast, low cost, and repeatable. And a lot of effort went into making the pump energy efficient, especially when operating at high flow rates. These efforts were done in addition to the effort proposed because it was determined that these were critical to make our pump the best available on the market.  Flow rates of our pumps were increased from 50ml/min to up to 600ml/min during Phase I. This was a significant improvement which was necessary to evacuate the area under the bandage in a reasonable amount of time. In speaking with physicians and nurses, who are the primary users of NPWT devices, we learned that a high flowrate is required so that they know there are no leaks present in a freshly used bandage. The maximum flowrate of pumping viscous liquid was determined, and it was significantly lower than that of air (27ml/min versus 600ml/min). This was because the resonant frequency of the pump was much lower when pumping a high density liquid when compared to a gas. However, higher flowrates are only necessary immediately after a bandage is applied, so it can be determined there are no leaks. Afterward, when exudate is being emitted by the wound, higher flowrates are not required. Being able to pump exudate is something no other NPWT device can do currently. This makes our pump well suited for over the counter use, as we will not need an exudate separator and reservoir, thus reducing the size of our bandage.  Physicians we spoke to said a common problem is that leaks occur, or bandages are removed (sometimes by the patient) and then insufficient therapy is administered. Therefore, we developed a means to measure and record vacuum levels. A Bluetooth module was incorporated into a circuit to control the pump and measure vacuum levels. And a smartphone app was written to control the pump and record vacuum level data to a file. This is a first for any NPWT device, and makes our product very competitive.  In conclusion; NPWT is a very effective therapy for treating chronic and non-healing wounds. However, NPWT is prohibitively expensive and can only be prescribed and administered in a clinical setting. Making a NPWT bandage that is smaller, cheaper, and more available to patients would greatly reduce medical expenses associated with chronic wounds, and would reduce patient suffering because wounds would be treated earlier. Therefore, we have developed a small, low-cost, and energy NPWT bandage. Pump inside the bandage has performance features that meet or exceed those of currently available NPWT pumps. The pump and bandage use low cost manufacturing techniques.          Last Modified: 08/12/2015       Submitted by: Robert Nesbitt]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
