<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>STTR Phase I:  High Quality Carbon Nanotubes for Radio Frequency Applications</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2014</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2015</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>225000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>269999</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07070000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>ENG</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>IIP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Div Of Industrial Innovation &amp; Partnersh</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Steven Konsek</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>skonsek@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927021</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The broader impacts/commercial potential of this Small Business Technology Transfer (STTR) Phase I can be found across the semiconductor industry with a very large first market in wireless communications.  Due to their extraordinary properties, more specifically, the linearity of these devices, the technologies can find applications in low noise amplifiers, mixers, and power amplifiers in wireless systems by replacing the transistors used in these parts. Such a wireless market is estimated to be ten(s) billion dollars by 2020 driven by mobile data. The high performance of the devices will also lead to radically change of the current cost-performance paradigm allowing for billions of dollars of savings in base stations for current service levels and likely accelerating the displacement of wireline networks. As the technology matures, it will displace most if not all moderate bandgap materials used in today's technology.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This Small Business Technology Transfer (STTR) Phase I project will develop electronic devices for radio frequency (RF) application using carbon nanotubes (CNTs). The demanding for high speed wireless communication requires electronic devices with high linearity.  RF devices made of silicon and compound semiconductors, such as gallium arsenide, have to sacrifice power efficiency in order to reach certain linearity specification. CNT is a one dimensional material with diameter in nanometer range. It has far superior properties ranging from mobility to current carrying capability to thermal stability.  Calculations show CNT amplifiers will be inherently linear with noise suppressed to the lowest possible quantum limit. These properties allow for electronic devices that will performance better than the existing technologies with high speed, low noise, and most importantly, high linearity.  With improved linearity, higher data rate and higher power efficiency (longer battery time of the mobile device) can be achieved.  As importantly, the cost for making such devices will be dramatically lower because of the simple method for material synthesis and device fabrication and the material's properties allow for older, cheaper fabrication processes to be retained.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>05/12/2014</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/04/2015</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.041</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1417276</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Jie</FirstName>
<LastName>Liu</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Jie Liu</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>jliu@chem.duke.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>9196601549</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000122291</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/12/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Dawei</FirstName>
<LastName>Wang</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Dawei Wang</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>dawei.wang@carbontekinc.com</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>9496337183</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000660529</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>05/12/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Carbon Technology, Inc.</Name>
<CityName>San Clemente</CityName>
<ZipCode>926725481</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>9492332093</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>232 Trafalgar Lane</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>49</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CA49</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>079437491</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>CARBON TECHNOLOGY, INC.</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Duke University]]></Name>
<CityName>Durham</CityName>
<StateCode>NC</StateCode>
<ZipCode>277054010</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[2200 W. Main St.]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>North Carolina</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>04</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NC04</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1505</Code>
<Text>STTR Phase I</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>097E</Code>
<Text>High Freq Devices &amp; Circuits</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1505</Code>
<Text>STTR PHASE I</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>163E</Code>
<Text>SBIR Phase IB</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8035</Code>
<Text>Hardware Devices</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0114</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0115</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~225000</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2015~44999</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>A Carbon Nanotube (CNT) is essentially a rolled up sheet of a single or a few graphite layers. Semiconducting CNTs have great potential for high performance RF applications due to their intrinsic linear behavior. Today, linearity is the underlying limitation in increasing the data transport densities of wireless networks.&nbsp;&nbsp;The intrinsic linearity of CNTs offers the potential for significant improvements in performance without sacrificing power thus radically improving the data rate achievable, while improving spectrum efficiency.&nbsp;However, a key problem is growing high performance semiconducting tubes suitable for RF applications in a wafer scale process which is compatible with existing semiconductor processing flows.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>Carbon Technology Inc. (CTI) is developing a CVD (Chemical Vapor Deposition) based process for creating wafer scale populations of in-situ high performance carbon nanotubes suitable for use in highly linear CNT FET devices (CFETs) and has pioneered a novel method to create these CNTs. In our Phase 1 work we developed a recipe that has been shown to grow populations of tubes with the very tight diameter distribution and high ratio of Semiconducting to Metallic (S/M) tubes mandated for RF applications. Moreover this approach is fully compatible with conventional semiconductor process flows requiring no special manufacturing equipment. The results indicate that high quality CNTs can be obtained through a CVD synthesis method, an important step forward in creating the high quality CNT materials required for high performance CFETs.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>Looking forward, CFETs based architectures can reshape the world of analog RF electronics, enabling the higher data rates and improved capacity demanded by next generation wireless systems due to their intrinsic linearity and associated low out of band interference. Wafer scale CVD grown CNTs are a key step in exploiting the revolutionary properties of CNT transistors, and a first step on the road to a future of Carbon based electronics.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 02/22/2016<br>      Modified by: Dawei&nbsp;Wang</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ A Carbon Nanotube (CNT) is essentially a rolled up sheet of a single or a few graphite layers. Semiconducting CNTs have great potential for high performance RF applications due to their intrinsic linear behavior. Today, linearity is the underlying limitation in increasing the data transport densities of wireless networks.  The intrinsic linearity of CNTs offers the potential for significant improvements in performance without sacrificing power thus radically improving the data rate achievable, while improving spectrum efficiency. However, a key problem is growing high performance semiconducting tubes suitable for RF applications in a wafer scale process which is compatible with existing semiconductor processing flows.     Carbon Technology Inc. (CTI) is developing a CVD (Chemical Vapor Deposition) based process for creating wafer scale populations of in-situ high performance carbon nanotubes suitable for use in highly linear CNT FET devices (CFETs) and has pioneered a novel method to create these CNTs. In our Phase 1 work we developed a recipe that has been shown to grow populations of tubes with the very tight diameter distribution and high ratio of Semiconducting to Metallic (S/M) tubes mandated for RF applications. Moreover this approach is fully compatible with conventional semiconductor process flows requiring no special manufacturing equipment. The results indicate that high quality CNTs can be obtained through a CVD synthesis method, an important step forward in creating the high quality CNT materials required for high performance CFETs.     Looking forward, CFETs based architectures can reshape the world of analog RF electronics, enabling the higher data rates and improved capacity demanded by next generation wireless systems due to their intrinsic linearity and associated low out of band interference. Wafer scale CVD grown CNTs are a key step in exploiting the revolutionary properties of CNT transistors, and a first step on the road to a future of Carbon based electronics.          Last Modified: 02/22/2016       Submitted by: Dawei Wang]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
