<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Collaborative Research: The Climate lab: An innovative partnership between climate research and middle-school practice</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/15/2014</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>264242.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>302198</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>11090000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>EHR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DRL</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Research On Learning</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Toni Dancstep</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>tdancste@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927922</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This project will develop and test an education partnership model focusing on climate change (The Climate Lab) that features inquiry-oriented and place-based learning.  Curriculum development will begin with a prototype program pioneered by the Manomet Center for Conservation Sciences, and a design-based implementation research (DBIR) approach will be used to develop a curriculum that is aligned with key elements of the Next Generation Science Standards (NGSS).  The project partnership includes scientists at three research centers, education researchers, and middle school teachers.  The completed curriculum will provide opportunities for middle school students and teachers to compare their locally collected data with historic data to create unique and powerful learning opportunities.  The collaboration between scientists and schools introduces middle school students to local, community citizen science endeavors with multiple stakeholders.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The project is innovative in linking direct exploration of current, local conditions with archived data to examine long-term changes in natural phenomena that cannot be directly perceived.  Components of the model being developed will include: a) a standards-aligned curriculum; b) field and lab activities that engage students in collecting and analyzing data on local biotic and abiotic indicators of climate change; c) integration with a current climate science research program; d) support materials for teachers and scientists (print and electronic) and a digital teacher professional development program; and e) a project Website.  During development of these curricular components, barriers to implementation of this learning strategy will be identified and studied.  The findings of this project have the potential to broadly impact middle school science education practices by introducing a curricular model that links direct data collection with analysis of archived data to study long-term environmental changes that are not directly perceived.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/05/2014</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>12/10/2018</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.076</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1417202</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Gillian</FirstName>
<LastName>Puttick</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>M</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Gillian M Puttick</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>gilly_puttick@terc.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6178739600</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000101084</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/05/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Brian</FirstName>
<LastName>Drayton</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>E</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Brian E Drayton</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>brian_drayton@terc.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6175470430</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000087508</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>08/05/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>TERC Inc</Name>
<CityName>Cambridge</CityName>
<ZipCode>021401339</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6178739600</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>2067 Massachusetts Avenue</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
<StateCode>MA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MA05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>071719801</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>TERC, INC.</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[TERC Inc]]></Name>
<CityName>Cambridge</CityName>
<StateCode>MA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>021401364</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[2067 Massachusetts Ave]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MA05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7645</Code>
<Text>Discovery Research K-12</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9177</Code>
<Text>ELEMENTARY/SECONDARY EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>SMET</Code>
<Text>SCIENCE, MATH, ENG &amp; TECH EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0414</Code>
<Name>NSF Education &amp; Human Resource</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040106</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0416</Code>
<Name>NSF Education &amp; Human Resource</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040106</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0418</Code>
<Name>NSF Education &amp; Human Resource</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040106</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~264242</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2016~26428</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2018~11528</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The purpose of this exploratory grant was to research and develop a transferrable educational model building from a relationship between scientists and middle-school teachers and students. Our model used scientists and data from a migratory bird research station as training tools and inspiration for teachers to guide their students in developing their own long-term research studies on environmental indicators within walking distance of their schools. Collaborators TERC (Cambridge, MA) and Manomet Inc. (Plymouth, MA) worked together to create a suite of middle school curricula and supplemental materials that adhere to the Next Generation Science Standards. These curricula focused on teaching students the fundamentals of long-term research and taught key concepts regarding climate science, environmental indicators and environmental monitoring. Student lessons culminated in data collection on environmental indicators (spring leaf emergence) at green spaces near their school grounds. Throughout the three years of this project we developed a core of dedicated middle school teachers in Eastern Massachusetts and Southern Maine that have their students collecting and contributing data to a long-term climate change study. We have also trained over 25 teachers and administrators and taught over 1500 middle school students the valuable lesson that sound science can be conducted by anybody.&nbsp;</p> <p><strong><span style="text-decoration: underline;">Resource development</span></strong></p> <p>A key component of our research was to determine what materials best facilitated student learning, teacher buy-in and consistent participation. Accordingly, we created numerous products and resources for educators and their students to try.&nbsp;</p> <p>Paramount to our goal of resource availability, we created an online repository for relevant teacher resources and curriculum materials. This web page is nested under Manomet?s website at:</p> <p><a href="https://www.manomet.org/project/climate-lab/">https://www.manomet.org/project/climate-lab/</a></p> <p>Over the course of our three years, TERC developed two sets of curricula to address teacher time limits and flexibility issues. To further assist teachers with project and curriculum planning, we created the Climate Lab Project Selector, an online tool to help educators customize their students? level of involvement based upon time constraints.&nbsp;</p> <p><a href="https://external-wiki.terc.edu/display/BAC/Project+Selector">https://external-wiki.terc.edu/display/BAC/Project+Selector</a></p> <p>We hosted several teacher training webinars as part or our efforts to explore methods for scaling up regionally and supervising remotely. Recordings of these webinars along with instructional videos were made available to participants via the Climate Lab YouTube channel.&nbsp;&nbsp;</p> <p><a href="https://www.youtube.com/channel/UCG_1pyyGVXrNlOPZ_onZfbg">https://www.youtube.com/channel/UCG_1pyyGVXrNlOPZ_onZfbg</a></p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p><strong><span style="text-decoration: underline;">Lessons learned/ intellectual merit</span></strong></p> <p>Our exploratory study was successful in that we have learned many valuable lessons. For instance, attempts to engage teachers and their students remotely were far less successful than in-person professional development workshops and direct supervision in the field. Student engagement and data quality also improved dramatically in the presence of direct scientist supervision.</p> <p>We monitored student learning through pre and post testing. We found that our curricula were effective in teaching some key scientific concepts. Assimilation of these materials takes time, but we saw data collection become spring tradition at three of our partner schools. Where data collection has been consistent, some interesting scientific insights have emerged. Our work informs the field of science education, particularly in an age of collaboration between research institutions and schools.&nbsp;</p> <p><strong><span style="text-decoration: underline;">Broader impacts</span></strong></p> <ul> <li>Our&nbsp;partners included racially and socioeconomically diverse schools in Boston and Wareham, MA as well as a charter school in downeast Maine.&nbsp;</li> <li>Our protocols were developed such that schools do not require expansive green spaces nearby to collect relevant data.</li> <li>Our program addressed the availability of relevant, STEM appropriate materials with the goal of universal availability to&nbsp;<span style="text-decoration: underline;">all</span>schools.</li> <li>The Bird Observatory at Manomet has an international friendship relationship with Jerusalem Bird Observatory in Israel, which has launched similar techniques and presentations in an urban nature park located on the Eastern Mediterranean bird migration flyway.&nbsp;</li> <li>Lessons students learn from Climate Lab inform their future decisions and interactions with the environment, their families and communities.&nbsp;</li> <li>The collaboration among TERC, Manomet, and schools opened the door for research on boundary crossing, the dynamics of scientist-educator partnerships, and the process of curriculum design</li> <li>The Climate Lab project design, implementation, and findings have been widely disseminated in scientific and educational conferences and publications.</li> </ul> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 11/13/2019<br>      Modified by: Brian&nbsp;E&nbsp;Drayton</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The purpose of this exploratory grant was to research and develop a transferrable educational model building from a relationship between scientists and middle-school teachers and students. Our model used scientists and data from a migratory bird research station as training tools and inspiration for teachers to guide their students in developing their own long-term research studies on environmental indicators within walking distance of their schools. Collaborators TERC (Cambridge, MA) and Manomet Inc. (Plymouth, MA) worked together to create a suite of middle school curricula and supplemental materials that adhere to the Next Generation Science Standards. These curricula focused on teaching students the fundamentals of long-term research and taught key concepts regarding climate science, environmental indicators and environmental monitoring. Student lessons culminated in data collection on environmental indicators (spring leaf emergence) at green spaces near their school grounds. Throughout the three years of this project we developed a core of dedicated middle school teachers in Eastern Massachusetts and Southern Maine that have their students collecting and contributing data to a long-term climate change study. We have also trained over 25 teachers and administrators and taught over 1500 middle school students the valuable lesson that sound science can be conducted by anybody.   Resource development  A key component of our research was to determine what materials best facilitated student learning, teacher buy-in and consistent participation. Accordingly, we created numerous products and resources for educators and their students to try.   Paramount to our goal of resource availability, we created an online repository for relevant teacher resources and curriculum materials. This web page is nested under Manomet?s website at:  https://www.manomet.org/project/climate-lab/  Over the course of our three years, TERC developed two sets of curricula to address teacher time limits and flexibility issues. To further assist teachers with project and curriculum planning, we created the Climate Lab Project Selector, an online tool to help educators customize their students? level of involvement based upon time constraints.   https://external-wiki.terc.edu/display/BAC/Project+Selector  We hosted several teacher training webinars as part or our efforts to explore methods for scaling up regionally and supervising remotely. Recordings of these webinars along with instructional videos were made available to participants via the Climate Lab YouTube channel.    https://www.youtube.com/channel/UCG_1pyyGVXrNlOPZ_onZfbg     Lessons learned/ intellectual merit  Our exploratory study was successful in that we have learned many valuable lessons. For instance, attempts to engage teachers and their students remotely were far less successful than in-person professional development workshops and direct supervision in the field. Student engagement and data quality also improved dramatically in the presence of direct scientist supervision.  We monitored student learning through pre and post testing. We found that our curricula were effective in teaching some key scientific concepts. Assimilation of these materials takes time, but we saw data collection become spring tradition at three of our partner schools. Where data collection has been consistent, some interesting scientific insights have emerged. Our work informs the field of science education, particularly in an age of collaboration between research institutions and schools.   Broader impacts  Our partners included racially and socioeconomically diverse schools in Boston and Wareham, MA as well as a charter school in downeast Maine.  Our protocols were developed such that schools do not require expansive green spaces nearby to collect relevant data. Our program addressed the availability of relevant, STEM appropriate materials with the goal of universal availability to allschools. The Bird Observatory at Manomet has an international friendship relationship with Jerusalem Bird Observatory in Israel, which has launched similar techniques and presentations in an urban nature park located on the Eastern Mediterranean bird migration flyway.  Lessons students learn from Climate Lab inform their future decisions and interactions with the environment, their families and communities.  The collaboration among TERC, Manomet, and schools opened the door for research on boundary crossing, the dynamics of scientist-educator partnerships, and the process of curriculum design The Climate Lab project design, implementation, and findings have been widely disseminated in scientific and educational conferences and publications.                 Last Modified: 11/13/2019       Submitted by: Brian E Drayton]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
