<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Developing a Model of Solar Energy Performance</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>12/15/2014</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>11/30/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>197128.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>197128</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>11060000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>EHR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>HRD</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Human Resource Development</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Lura Chase</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>lchase@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032925173</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>A goal of the Tribal Colleges and Universities Program (TCUP) is to increase the science, technology, engineering and mathematics (STEM) instructional and research capacities of specific institutions of higher education that serve the Nation's indigenous students. Expanding the research efforts of faculty at these institutions expands the opportunities of their students to pursue challenging, rewarding careers in STEM fields, provides for research studies in areas that may be culturally significant, and encourages a community and generational appreciation for science and mathematics education. This project aligns directly with that goal, using a design that will facilitate progression and advancement of American Indian students by providing training in experimental field research, data collection and analysis, general STEM-based concepts, technical report writing, and presentation skills.  It can prepare students for careers in the competitive and growing field of sustainable energy production.  Moreover, the results from this research may advance knowledge and understanding within the field of solar energy performance and reliability. It can have practical applications for both manufacturers and consumers.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The overarching goal of the potentially transformative research is to explore climatic factors that affect solar module performance and reliability, and develop a framework for the performance, failure and reliability assessment of solar energy systems. This project will be implemented in collaboration with Argonne National Laboratory (ANL), which has recently installed a state-of-the-art solar energy comparative research facility, the first of its kind in the Midwest.  The objectives of this research include (1) Develop a framework to model the efficiency and reliability of solar energy systems, to estimate the system performance at any given point in time, for new and in particular, used solar energy systems. (2) Develop a method to denoise and convert actual raw continuous PV system and weather data (e.g. incoming solar irradiation, temperature, generated DC electricity, inverter converted AC electricity) into useful performance metrics. (3) Verify the accuracy of the solar energy system performance model through comparison to real-time solar energy system performance data.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>12/04/2014</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>12/04/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.076</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1417582</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Lisa</FirstName>
<LastName>Bosman</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Lisa Bosman</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>lbosman@purdue.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>7158518683</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000637746</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>12/04/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>College of the Menominee Nation</Name>
<CityName>Keshena</CityName>
<ZipCode>541351179</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>7157995600</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>P O Box 1179</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[N172 Sth 47-55]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Wisconsin</StateName>
<StateCode>WI</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>08</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>WI08</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>965801608</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>COLLEGE OF MENOMINEE NATIONS</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM/>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[College of the Menominee Nation]]></Name>
<CityName/>
<StateCode>WI</StateCode>
<ZipCode>541351179</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Wisconsin</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>08</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>WI08</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1744</Code>
<Text>Tribal College &amp; Univers Prog</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0415</Code>
<Name>NSF Education &amp; Human Resource</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040106</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2015~197128</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>This project is titled, &ldquo;Developing a Model of Solar Energy Performance.&rdquo; From an intellectual merit perspective, the results from this research are important in advancing knowledge and understanding within the field of solar energy performance and reliability. Practically speaking, this research is important for providing manufacturers and&nbsp;installers&nbsp;predictive capabilities for determining warranty offers, and is just as important for consumers to make educated choices about solar module return on investment for residential and commercial energy. Here, the focus was on developing a framework to model the efficiency and reliability of solar energy systems, and to estimate the system performance at any given point in time, for new and in particular, used solar energy systems.&nbsp;From a broader impacts perspective, the research and undergraduate experience advanced discovery and understanding of STEM research, while promoting teaching, training, and learning of STEM principles for Native American students. Here, the focus was not only on the TCU college student educational experience, but also, on disseminating the knowledge to a variety of K-12 audiences.</p> <p>Key project outcomes are as follows:</p> <p>1. Student Research Experiences: (a) 32 CMN student research assistant experiences were provided to participate in solar energy research, (b) 10 students participated in solar energy training through the Midwest Renewable Energy Association (MREA) and Solar Energy International (SEI), (c) each year, 2 students presented research at the Emerging Researcher's Network (ERN) Conference; 3 students presented research at the American Indian Higher Education Consortium (AIHEC) national conference; 3 students presented research at the&nbsp;Society for&nbsp;Advancement of&nbsp;Chicanos/Hispanics and&nbsp;Native&nbsp;Americans in&nbsp;Science (SACNAS), (d) 5 renewable energy books + 8 engineering books were developed by students, including supporting hands-on experiments and engaging projects</p> <p>2. Renewable Energy After School Program: (a) 56 CMN student mentor experiences were provided to conduct solar energy workshops to K-5 students, (b) 7 CMN faculty and staff participated in project activities, (c) 5 grade school solar energy multiple week workshops (part of the YMCA after school program) were conducted, impacting over 270 at-risk elementary school students, (d) 2 different age-specific renewable energy curriculum (+ kits) were developed and deployed</p> <p>3. Other K-12 Solar Energy Education: (a) 25 high school students from the Menominee Youth Empowerment Program (YEP) attended a solar energy present showcasing opportunities to get involved at CMN, (b) 20 YMCA trainers and 40 K-12 school teachers participated in Renewable Energy "Train-the-Trainer" workshops</p> <p>4. Knowledge Dissemination</p> <ol> <li>Bosman, L.,&nbsp;Chelberg, K., &amp;&nbsp;Fernhaber&nbsp;S.      (2017).&nbsp;Introduction to      Engineering: A constructivist-based approach to encourage engagement and      promote accessibility.&nbsp;<em></em><em>Global Journal of Engineering Education</em>&nbsp;</li> <li>Bosman,      L. (2017). PVSysCo: Solar Energy System Comparison and Evaluation.&nbsp;<em>Journal      of Environmental Science and Pollution Research</em></li> <li>Bosman,      L., Chelberg, K., &amp; Winn, R. (2017). How does service learning      increase and sustain interest in engineering education for      underrepresented pre-engineering college students?&nbsp;<em>Journal of STEM      Education: Innovations and Research</em></li> <li>Bosman,      L. &amp; Darling, S. (2016). Difficulties and Recommendations for More      Accurately Predicting the Performance of Solar Energy Systems during the      Snow Season.&nbsp;<em>IEEE - Renewable Energy Research and Applications</em></li> <li>Winn,      R., Bosman, L., &amp; Chelberg, K. (2016). Our HEROs: Engaging and      Inspiring Native Engineers.&nbsp;<em>Journal of American Indian Higher      Education</em></li> <li>Bosman,      L., Winn, R., &amp; Chelberg, K. (2016). STEM Recruitment and Retention:      Student Success at the College of Menominee Nation.&nbsp;<em>Tribal College      Journal</em></li> <li>Otieno, W. &amp; Bosman, L.      (2014). Solar PV Selection Decision Tool: The case of U.S.A. Midwest      Region.&nbsp;<em>Journal&nbsp;of Civil Engineering and Environmental      Technology</em></li> </ol><br> <p>            Last Modified: 12/11/2017<br>      Modified by: Lisa&nbsp;Bosman</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ This project is titled, "Developing a Model of Solar Energy Performance." From an intellectual merit perspective, the results from this research are important in advancing knowledge and understanding within the field of solar energy performance and reliability. Practically speaking, this research is important for providing manufacturers and installers predictive capabilities for determining warranty offers, and is just as important for consumers to make educated choices about solar module return on investment for residential and commercial energy. Here, the focus was on developing a framework to model the efficiency and reliability of solar energy systems, and to estimate the system performance at any given point in time, for new and in particular, used solar energy systems. From a broader impacts perspective, the research and undergraduate experience advanced discovery and understanding of STEM research, while promoting teaching, training, and learning of STEM principles for Native American students. Here, the focus was not only on the TCU college student educational experience, but also, on disseminating the knowledge to a variety of K-12 audiences.  Key project outcomes are as follows:  1. Student Research Experiences: (a) 32 CMN student research assistant experiences were provided to participate in solar energy research, (b) 10 students participated in solar energy training through the Midwest Renewable Energy Association (MREA) and Solar Energy International (SEI), (c) each year, 2 students presented research at the Emerging Researcher's Network (ERN) Conference; 3 students presented research at the American Indian Higher Education Consortium (AIHEC) national conference; 3 students presented research at the Society for Advancement of Chicanos/Hispanics and Native Americans in Science (SACNAS), (d) 5 renewable energy books + 8 engineering books were developed by students, including supporting hands-on experiments and engaging projects  2. Renewable Energy After School Program: (a) 56 CMN student mentor experiences were provided to conduct solar energy workshops to K-5 students, (b) 7 CMN faculty and staff participated in project activities, (c) 5 grade school solar energy multiple week workshops (part of the YMCA after school program) were conducted, impacting over 270 at-risk elementary school students, (d) 2 different age-specific renewable energy curriculum (+ kits) were developed and deployed  3. Other K-12 Solar Energy Education: (a) 25 high school students from the Menominee Youth Empowerment Program (YEP) attended a solar energy present showcasing opportunities to get involved at CMN, (b) 20 YMCA trainers and 40 K-12 school teachers participated in Renewable Energy "Train-the-Trainer" workshops  4. Knowledge Dissemination  Bosman, L., Chelberg, K., &amp; Fernhaber S.      (2017). Introduction to      Engineering: A constructivist-based approach to encourage engagement and      promote accessibility. Global Journal of Engineering Education  Bosman,      L. (2017). PVSysCo: Solar Energy System Comparison and Evaluation. Journal      of Environmental Science and Pollution Research Bosman,      L., Chelberg, K., &amp; Winn, R. (2017). How does service learning      increase and sustain interest in engineering education for      underrepresented pre-engineering college students? Journal of STEM      Education: Innovations and Research Bosman,      L. &amp; Darling, S. (2016). Difficulties and Recommendations for More      Accurately Predicting the Performance of Solar Energy Systems during the      Snow Season. IEEE - Renewable Energy Research and Applications Winn,      R., Bosman, L., &amp; Chelberg, K. (2016). Our HEROs: Engaging and      Inspiring Native Engineers. Journal of American Indian Higher      Education Bosman,      L., Winn, R., &amp; Chelberg, K. (2016). STEM Recruitment and Retention:      Student Success at the College of Menominee Nation. Tribal College      Journal Otieno, W. &amp; Bosman, L.      (2014). Solar PV Selection Decision Tool: The case of U.S.A. Midwest      Region. Journal of Civil Engineering and Environmental      Technology        Last Modified: 12/11/2017       Submitted by: Lisa Bosman]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
