<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Collaborative Research: Understanding Arctic Marine Biogeochemical Response to Climate Change for Seasonal to Decadal Prediction Using Regional and Global Climate System Models</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>10/01/2014</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>09/30/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>437764.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>437764</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>06090100</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>GEO</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>OPP</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Office of Polar Programs (OPP)</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Gregory Anderson</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>greander@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924693</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The Arctic Ocean is experiencing rapid and dramatic environmental changes related to global warming.  These changes affect the arctic marine carbon cycle as part of complex and coupled system interactions between the ocean, atmosphere, cryosphere and land surfaces, with important feedbacks to the global Earth System, including altering the concentration of atmospheric greenhouse gases. Previous and ongoing studies have laid the foundations for improving the understanding of arctic carbon sinks and sources using observational studies, regional ice-ocean modeling, and recent global carbon cycle simulations.  However, there remain large uncertainties in the understanding of variability and change in the arctic marine carbon budget that are difficult to reconcile with existing tools.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project will use the Regional Arctic System Model, comprised of marine biogeochemistry components in the eddy-resolving ocean and sea ice models to advance understanding and prediction of the arctic biogeochemical system, including shelf-basin and vertical nutrient exchange, the subsurface chlorophyll maximum, ice edge and under ice blooms and their role in ecosystem response to climate change.  It builds on the recent and ongoing research by the team of investigators, including the development and evaluation of the marine biogeochemistry components for global sea ice/ocean models and the high resolution Regional Arctic System Model.  The model simulates mass and energy exchange between sea ice, ocean, atmosphere and land on decadal timescales, with regionally constrained variability using observationally based atmospheric and oceanic datasets at lateral boundaries.  The research will: (i) evaluate and refine the established ocean marine biogeochemistry model, and (ii) add a newly developed sea ice algal biogeochemistry component within the existing model infrastructure. These model enhancements will help better quantify variability, complexity, and change in arctic marine primary production.  The overarching goal of this study is to achieve a comprehensive understanding of interactions between physical system components and the arctic marine carbon cycle, and to advance arctic system prediction at seasonal to centennial time scales with quantified uncertainty.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/23/2014</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/23/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.078</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1417925</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Clara</FirstName>
<LastName>Deal</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>J</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Clara J Deal</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>cmdeal@alaska.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>9074747875</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000473258</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/23/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Meibing</FirstName>
<LastName>Jin</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Meibing Jin</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>mjin@iarc.uaf.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>9074742442</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000473073</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/23/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Alaska Fairbanks Campus</Name>
<CityName>Fairbanks</CityName>
<ZipCode>997757880</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>9074747301</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>West Ridge Research Bldg 008</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[2145 N. Tanana Loop]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Alaska</StateName>
<StateCode>AK</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>00</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>AK00</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>615245164</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF ALASKA FAIRBANKS</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>048679567</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Alaska Fairbanks Campus]]></Name>
<CityName>Fairbanks</CityName>
<StateCode>AK</StateCode>
<ZipCode>997757340</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[930 Koyukuk Drive]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Alaska</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>00</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>AK00</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>5219</Code>
<Text>ARCSS-Arctic System Science</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1079</Code>
<Text>ARCTIC RESEARCH</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>5219</Code>
<Text>ARCTIC SYSTEM SCIENCE PROGRAM</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>02XX</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~437764</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>To improve our understanding of the Arctic marine ecosystem variations in response to climate changes, this project developed the high-resolution Regional Arctic System Model (RASM) with an addition capacity of coupled sea ice and marine biogeochemistry (mBGC). During the course of the project, we published ten journal papers, and one still under review. Our main outcomes are: 1) built up the coupled ice-ocean mBGC codes into the RASM; 2) evaluated the model extensively in the subarctic and Arctic Oceans with multidecadal observational data. The global coarse resolution model and high resolution regional model converge to similar mean status of observed physical ecosystem environments in general, but high resolution model can better represent areas with sharp topographic gradient, and shelf-basin exchanges, thus get reduced model errors compared with observations; 3) compared with other arctic ecosystem models with different model domains, resolutions and parameters to better understand model behaviors. Our models performed reasonably well in simulation of spatial distribution of annual cycle of ocean stratification, nutrients, chlorophyll and primary production etc. compared to other models; 4) investigate arctic marine ecosystem changes in response to climate changes. Under a warming arctic with declining sea ice cover, the total primary production within the Arctic Circle is increasing according to our model, in agreement with several other models and remote sensing results. 5) released the RASM version 1 to general public and conducted education and outreach through various presentations at scientific conferences and to non-professional audiences.</p> <p><strong>&nbsp;</strong><em>&nbsp;</em></p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 01/31/2020<br>      Modified by: Meibing&nbsp;Jin</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ To improve our understanding of the Arctic marine ecosystem variations in response to climate changes, this project developed the high-resolution Regional Arctic System Model (RASM) with an addition capacity of coupled sea ice and marine biogeochemistry (mBGC). During the course of the project, we published ten journal papers, and one still under review. Our main outcomes are: 1) built up the coupled ice-ocean mBGC codes into the RASM; 2) evaluated the model extensively in the subarctic and Arctic Oceans with multidecadal observational data. The global coarse resolution model and high resolution regional model converge to similar mean status of observed physical ecosystem environments in general, but high resolution model can better represent areas with sharp topographic gradient, and shelf-basin exchanges, thus get reduced model errors compared with observations; 3) compared with other arctic ecosystem models with different model domains, resolutions and parameters to better understand model behaviors. Our models performed reasonably well in simulation of spatial distribution of annual cycle of ocean stratification, nutrients, chlorophyll and primary production etc. compared to other models; 4) investigate arctic marine ecosystem changes in response to climate changes. Under a warming arctic with declining sea ice cover, the total primary production within the Arctic Circle is increasing according to our model, in agreement with several other models and remote sensing results. 5) released the RASM version 1 to general public and conducted education and outreach through various presentations at scientific conferences and to non-professional audiences.              Last Modified: 01/31/2020       Submitted by: Meibing Jin]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
