<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Advances in Interdisciplinary Statistics and Combinatorics, October 10-12, 2014</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>06/01/2014</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2015</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>10000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>10000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DMS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Gabor Szekely</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>gszekely@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032928869</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This award supports the participation of junior researchers in the  international conference "Advances in Interdisciplinary Statistics and Combinatorics," held at The University of North Carolina at Greensboro on October 10-12, 2014.  The conference brings together statisticians and researchers from other disciplines to discuss the use of statistical techniques in research programs in a variety of disciplines including anthropology, biology, computer science, economics, education, education research methodology, environmental science, information systems, medicine, psychology, and public health. A major emphasis is on training young researchers through two workshops, one on Big Data and Machine Learning, and the other on Mathematical Biology and Game Theory. In addition to these two workshops, the conference includes a variety of sessions on topics that highlight the use of statistical methods in other disciplines.  &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The main goal of the workshop on Mathematical Biology and Game Theory is to introduce undergraduates and graduate students to the mathematical modeling that is an essential part of any research in applied mathematics, mathematical biology in particular. The workshop focuses on game theoretical models that are used for situations where several entities interact (directly or indirectly) with one another and where each entity acts in its own interest (potentially in conflict with the interests of others).  The workshop on Big Data and Machine Learning, designed for graduate students, will provide a forum for researchers from academia and industry to exchange information and develop new research directions in areas of big data and machine learning focusing on scalability, reliability, and security. These workshops will help to advance the next generation of researchers on some of the most important contemporary topics in statistical science.  The meeting also offers an opportunity to students from underrepresented groups to be part of a high profile conference to broaden their vision of research in mathematical sciences and advance their career goals. More details are available at the conference website http://www.uncg.edu/mat/aisc/2014/index.html</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>04/21/2014</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>04/21/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1417056</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Shan</FirstName>
<LastName>Suthaharan</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Shan Suthaharan</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>ssuthaharan@uncg.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>3362561122</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000347998</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/21/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Sat</FirstName>
<LastName>Gupta</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Sat Gupta</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>sngupta@uncg.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>3365544608</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000416416</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/21/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Jan</FirstName>
<LastName>Rychtar</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Jan Rychtar</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>rychtarj@vcu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>8048281301</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000494502</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>04/21/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of North Carolina Greensboro</Name>
<CityName>Greensboro</CityName>
<ZipCode>274125013</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>3363345878</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1111 Spring Garden Street</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[2702 Moore Hum. & Research Admin]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>North Carolina</StateName>
<StateCode>NC</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>13</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>NC13</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>616152567</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>UNIVERSITY OF NORTH CAROLINA AT GREENSBORO</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>142363428</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of North Carolina Greensboro]]></Name>
<CityName>Greensboro</CityName>
<StateCode>NC</StateCode>
<ZipCode>274026170</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[1111 Spring Garden Street]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>North Carolina</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>06</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>NC06</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1269</Code>
<Text>STATISTICS</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7556</Code>
<Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0114</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~10000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The proposed conference (AISC - 2014) took place, as scheduled, during October 10 - 12, 2014, at UNC Greensboro. The conference featured 161 talks including 30 talks by students and 22 by very senior plenary speakers. The plenary speakers included C. S. Cheng and Lexin Li (Berkeley); David Dunson, Jerry Reiter and Mike West (Duke); Richard Smith (SAMSI and UNC Chapel Hill); Marie Davidian, Anastasios Tsiatis and Alun Lloyd (NC State); John Stufken (Arizona State); Dan Zelterman (Yale); Alan Karr (RTI); Ben Kedem (Maryland); Sudipto Guha (U Penn); Ming Yuan (Wisconsin - Madison); Ejaz Ahmed (Brock Uiversity); Mike Broom (City University London); Vlastimil K?ivan (University of South Bohemia, Czech Republic); Mike Mesterton-Gibbons (Florida State); Ross Cressman (Wilfrid Laurier University, Canada); Benjamin Allen (Emanuel College);  and Dmitri Zaykin (National Institute of Environmental Health Sciences). <strong><strong><strong><strong><strong><strong>&nbsp;</strong></strong></strong></strong></strong></strong></p> <p>Two workshops were arranged, largely&nbsp; for young researchers -<strong><strong><strong><strong><strong><strong></strong></strong></strong></strong></strong></strong> one on Big Data/Machine Learning and the other on Mathematical Biology/Game Theory. There were more than 200 participants with many coming from abroad. The conference supported 26 young researchers including 10 women.</p> <p>Four of the young researchers were recognized for outstanding presentations. These were Nicole Dalzell (Duke), Gina - Maria Pomann (N C State), Geeta Kalucha (University of Delhi) and David Sykes (UNC Greensboro).</p> <p>Four of the senior NC Statisticians were honord with the NC- ASA Chapter Distinguished Service awards. These were Mike West (Duke), Richard Smith (SAMSI and UNC Chapel Hill), Anastasios Tsiatis (N C State), and Sat Gupta (UNC Greensboro).</p> <p>Selected papers from the conference will appear in the <em>Journal of Statistical Theory and Practice</em>.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 07/02/2015<br>      Modified by: Sat&nbsp;Gupta</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The proposed conference (AISC - 2014) took place, as scheduled, during October 10 - 12, 2014, at UNC Greensboro. The conference featured 161 talks including 30 talks by students and 22 by very senior plenary speakers. The plenary speakers included C. S. Cheng and Lexin Li (Berkeley); David Dunson, Jerry Reiter and Mike West (Duke); Richard Smith (SAMSI and UNC Chapel Hill); Marie Davidian, Anastasios Tsiatis and Alun Lloyd (NC State); John Stufken (Arizona State); Dan Zelterman (Yale); Alan Karr (RTI); Ben Kedem (Maryland); Sudipto Guha (U Penn); Ming Yuan (Wisconsin - Madison); Ejaz Ahmed (Brock Uiversity); Mike Broom (City University London); Vlastimil K?ivan (University of South Bohemia, Czech Republic); Mike Mesterton-Gibbons (Florida State); Ross Cressman (Wilfrid Laurier University, Canada); Benjamin Allen (Emanuel College);  and Dmitri Zaykin (National Institute of Environmental Health Sciences).    Two workshops were arranged, largely  for young researchers - one on Big Data/Machine Learning and the other on Mathematical Biology/Game Theory. There were more than 200 participants with many coming from abroad. The conference supported 26 young researchers including 10 women.  Four of the young researchers were recognized for outstanding presentations. These were Nicole Dalzell (Duke), Gina - Maria Pomann (N C State), Geeta Kalucha (University of Delhi) and David Sykes (UNC Greensboro).  Four of the senior NC Statisticians were honord with the NC- ASA Chapter Distinguished Service awards. These were Mike West (Duke), Richard Smith (SAMSI and UNC Chapel Hill), Anastasios Tsiatis (N C State), and Sat Gupta (UNC Greensboro).  Selected papers from the conference will appear in the Journal of Statistical Theory and Practice.          Last Modified: 07/02/2015       Submitted by: Sat Gupta]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
