<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Preparing Urban Middle Grades Mathematics Teachers to Teach Argumentation Throughout the School Year</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>06/15/2014</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>2999737.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>2999737</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>11090000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>EHR</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DRL</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Research On Learning</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Karen King</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI/>
<PO_PHON/>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The project is an important study that builds prior research to bring a comprehensive implementation of reform mathematics instruction focused on mathematical argumentation to an urban school district. The objective of this full research and development project is to develop resources, models, and tools (RMTs) that help inservice middle grades mathematics teachers support mathematical argumentation throughout the school year. Mathematical argumentation, the construction and critique of mathematical conjectures and justifications, is a fundamental disciplinary practice in mathematics that students often never master. Building on a proof of concept of the project's approach in short curriculum units from two prior NSF-funded studies, this project expands the model to help teachers support mathematical argumentation all year. A coherent, portable, yearlong professional development program on mathematical argumentation has the potential to increase access to mathematical argumentation for students nationwide and, in particular, to address the needs of teachers and students in urban areas. Demonstrating this program in the nation's capital likely attracts broad interest and produces important knowledge about how to implement mathematical practices in urban settings. Increasing mathematical argumentation in schools has the potential for dramatic contributions to students' achievement and participation in 21st century workplaces.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Mathematical argumentation is rich discussion in which students take on mathematical authority and co-construct conjectures and justifications. For many teachers, supporting such discourse is challenging; many are most comfortable with Initiate-Respond-Evaluate types of practices and/or have insufficient content understanding. The professional development trains teachers to be disciplined improvisers -- professionals with a toolkit of tools, knowledge, and practices to be deployed creatively and responsively as mathematical argumentation unfolds. This discipline includes establishing classroom norms and planning lessons for argumentation. The model's theory of action has four design principles: provide the toolkit, use simulations of the classroom to practice improvising, support learning of key content, and provide job-embedded, technology-enabled supports for using new practices all year. Three yearlong studies will address design, feasibility, and promise. In Study 1 the team co-designs the RMTs with District of Columbia Public Schools staff. Study 2 is a feasibility study to examine program implementation, identify barriers and facilitators, and inform improvements. Study 3 is a quasi-experimental pilot to test the promise for achieving intended outcomes: expanding teachers' content knowledge and support of mathematical argumentation, and increasing students' mathematical argumentation in the classroom and spoken argumentation proficiency. The studies will result in a yearlong professional development program with documentation of the theory of action, design decisions, pilot data, and instrument technical qualities.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/07/2014</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/12/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.076</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1417895</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Jennifer</FirstName>
<LastName>Knudsen</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Jennifer Knudsen</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>jennifer_knudsen@terc.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>4156522230</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000428221</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/07/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Nicole</FirstName>
<LastName>Shechtman</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>B</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Nicole B Shechtman</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>nicole.shechtman@sri.com</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6508595692</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000222448</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/07/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Teresa</FirstName>
<LastName>Lara-Meloy</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Teresa Lara-Meloy</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>teresa_lara-meloy@terc.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6508739819</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000588636</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/07/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Harriette</FirstName>
<LastName>Stevens</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT>S</PI_MID_INIT>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Harriette S Stevens</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>hstevens@berkeley.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>4157523240</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000656356</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/07/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>SRI International</Name>
<CityName>Menlo Park</CityName>
<ZipCode>940253493</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>7032478529</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>333 RAVENSWOOD AVE</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>18</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>CA18</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>009232752</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>SRI INTERNATIONAL</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>009232752</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[SRI International]]></Name>
<CityName>Menlo Park</CityName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>940253493</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[333 Ravenswood Ave]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>18</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>CA18</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7645</Code>
<Text>Discovery Research K-12</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0414</Code>
<Name>NSF Education &amp; Human Resource</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040106</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0415</Code>
<Name>NSF Education &amp; Human Resource</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040106</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0416</Code>
<Name>NSF Education &amp; Human Resource</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040106</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~656164</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2015~1771325</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2016~572248</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The project, Preparing Urban Middle Grades Mathematics Teachers to Teach Argumentation Throughout the School Year, was the third phase in a series of research and design projects known collectively as Bridging Professional Development (PD) for Mathematical Argumentation in the Middle Grades. In collaboration with a large urban district, SRI researchers and developers created a two-year sequence of PD that supported teachers in establishing the practice of mathematical argumentation in their classrooms.</p> <p>The intellectual merit of the project included features of the design as well as products of the research. While a fair amount of literature on argumentation in the middle grades existed, and served as a foundation for Bridging, Bridging included "ordinary" teachers who may have been teaching argumentation for the first time. The PD program founded the use of innovative warm up "games" based on improvisational theater games?to aid teachers in establishing productive norms for rich discourse. The main findings of the program are detailed case studies focusing on the role of lesson planning and curriculum resources, both critical parts of the PD, in teachers' work in engaging students in the mathematical practice of argumentation while still addressing content standards to which they were accountable. Additional papers and presentations include expositions on the design process for this PD: how PD can be conceived of as "approximations of practice" that start with a mathematics learning experience and grow ever closer to real classroom activity; and the design dilemmas faced and dealt with in creating a program introducing a very new practice for most teachers.</p> <p>The broader impacts of the project include a well received, practical book for teachers and teacher leaders, published by Corwin, <em>Mathematical Argumentation in Middle School: The What, Why, and How. </em>Teachers and teacher leaders from throughout the country now have access to the PD and curriculum materials designed all Bridging projects, through the bridgingmath.org website. &nbsp;Specially designed for urban districts with strict pacing guides and other institutional constraints, Bridging is a resource for engaging historically marginalized students in an empowering practice. Observed use of the book has spread the teaching methods advocated by the project and supported by research in the field of mathematical argumentation.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 04/09/2019<br>      Modified by: Jennifer&nbsp;Knudsen</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The project, Preparing Urban Middle Grades Mathematics Teachers to Teach Argumentation Throughout the School Year, was the third phase in a series of research and design projects known collectively as Bridging Professional Development (PD) for Mathematical Argumentation in the Middle Grades. In collaboration with a large urban district, SRI researchers and developers created a two-year sequence of PD that supported teachers in establishing the practice of mathematical argumentation in their classrooms.  The intellectual merit of the project included features of the design as well as products of the research. While a fair amount of literature on argumentation in the middle grades existed, and served as a foundation for Bridging, Bridging included "ordinary" teachers who may have been teaching argumentation for the first time. The PD program founded the use of innovative warm up "games" based on improvisational theater games?to aid teachers in establishing productive norms for rich discourse. The main findings of the program are detailed case studies focusing on the role of lesson planning and curriculum resources, both critical parts of the PD, in teachers' work in engaging students in the mathematical practice of argumentation while still addressing content standards to which they were accountable. Additional papers and presentations include expositions on the design process for this PD: how PD can be conceived of as "approximations of practice" that start with a mathematics learning experience and grow ever closer to real classroom activity; and the design dilemmas faced and dealt with in creating a program introducing a very new practice for most teachers.  The broader impacts of the project include a well received, practical book for teachers and teacher leaders, published by Corwin, Mathematical Argumentation in Middle School: The What, Why, and How. Teachers and teacher leaders from throughout the country now have access to the PD and curriculum materials designed all Bridging projects, through the bridgingmath.org website.  Specially designed for urban districts with strict pacing guides and other institutional constraints, Bridging is a resource for engaging historically marginalized students in an empowering practice. Observed use of the book has spread the teaching methods advocated by the project and supported by research in the field of mathematical argumentation.          Last Modified: 04/09/2019       Submitted by: Jennifer Knudsen]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
