<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Numerical Analysis and Methods for Simulating Moving Interfaces and Controlling Shape</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2014</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>153520.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>153520</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DMS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Leland Jameson</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>ljameson@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924883</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Understanding physical laws and developing mathematical models to make predictions enables advancement of modern technology and industrial processes.  Moreover, optimization of these processes allows for better and more efficient designs.  The direct impacts to society are in general cost savings, more robust infrastructure, and better quality of life. The goal of this research project (see  technical description) is to target a specific set of physical/industrial processes that involve moving  boundaries or interfaces (e.g. the surface of a melting ice-cube in water is an interface between the solid  "ice" phase and the liquid "water" phase). Examples include growing solid phases in a desired shape from a liquid melt (controlled crystal  growth), modeling liquid crystals (display technology), micro-fluidics that control small droplets of liquid  by electric fields (useful in the bio-medical field), and self-assembly of particles and polymer chains on  deformable membrane surfaces (design of materials).  The research will enable better design, optimization, and control of these systems.  In addition, the project will create new methods for creating computer models of complex shapes that efficiently capture moving boundaries.  This is known as grid generation, which is a basic tool used in  many areas, from computer graphics (for creating life-like animations) all the way to commercial  product design (engineering design of structures such as bridges).  Grid generation is still an expensive task in terms of man-hours and money.  Any computational tools developed by this research will be made available to the public through online resources.  Furthermore, undergraduate and graduate students will benefit from a special course developed by the PI on computational free boundary problems.  Lastly, the PI is guiding middle school students in science fair projects motivated by this research.   &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The proposed research will develop numerical analysis tools and methods for simulating moving interface and multi-physics problems and for optimal control of free boundaries.  We will take  advantage of variational/finite element methods, stability/energy estimates, shape differentiation, and  automatic meshing technology in the following projects: (A) develop and analyze new discrete  formulations of the Stefan problem (phase change/solidification) in 2-D and 3-D and explore well posedness questions of the time-dependent  interface motion (in a finite element method (FEM) setting); (B) develop a new FEM for liquid crystals  with provable stability/convergence properties and explore dynamics and equilibrium configurations; (C)  develop PDE-based optimal control techniques and numerics for directing and controlling shape; (D)  develop stable and accurate numerical methods (FEM) for simulating geometric objects that obey the no  self-penetration condition; and (E) create new mesh generation methods to handle 3-D problems in a  robust and automatic way with attention given to parallel implementation issues.  This project will advance the fundamental theory of free boundary problems by investigating well-posedness of time dependent domain-deforming problems and optimal control of shape.  It will further the development of methods for multi-physics problems with coupling to non-linear interfacial physics, such as anisotropic surface tension.  It will create novel numerical analysis and efficient methods for simulating dynamic curves and surfaces that respect *no self-penetration*, i.e. that enforce the excluded volume  constraint.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/31/2014</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/31/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1418994</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Shawn</FirstName>
<LastName>Walker</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Shawn Walker</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>walker@math.lsu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>2255781603</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000560409</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/31/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Louisiana State University</Name>
<CityName>Baton Rouge</CityName>
<ZipCode>708032701</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2255782760</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>202 Himes Hall</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Louisiana</StateName>
<StateCode>LA</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>06</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>LA06</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>075050765</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>LOUISIANA STATE UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>940050792</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Louisiana State University & Agricultural and Mechanical College]]></Name>
<CityName>Baton Rouge</CityName>
<StateCode>LA</StateCode>
<ZipCode>708032701</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[202 Himes Hall]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Louisiana</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>06</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>LA06</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1271</Code>
<Text>COMPUTATIONAL MATHEMATICS</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8396</Code>
<Text>Clean Energy Technology</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8609</Code>
<Text>Other Energy Research</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9263</Code>
<Text>COMPUTATIONAL SCIENCE &amp; ENGING</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0114</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~153520</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>Understanding physical laws and developing mathematical models to make predictions enables advancement of modern technology and industrial processes.&nbsp; Moreover, optimization of these processes allows for better and more efficient designs.&nbsp; The direct impacts to society are in general cost savings, more robust infrastructure, and better quality of life. The goal of this research project is to target a specific set of physical/industrial processes that involve moving boundaries or interfaces (e.g. the surface of a melting ice-cube in water is an interface between the solid "ice" phase and the liquid "water" phase). Examples include growing solid phases in a desired shape from a liquid melt (controlled crystal growth), modeling liquid crystals for material design, micro-fluidics that control small droplets of liquid by electric fields (useful in the bio-medical field), and self-assembly of particles and polymer chains on deformable membrane surfaces (design of materials).&nbsp; The research will enable better design, optimization, and control of these systems.<br /><br />INTELLECTUAL MERIT:<br /><br />In particular, the research developed tools to (1) model/simulate melting and solidification; (2) model/simulate the adsorption of polymers onto surfaces using tools of shape optimization; (3) control the shape of liquid droplets on substrates by affecting surface tension; (4) simulate liquid crystals interacting with colloidal particles and electric effects; (5) model/simulate the shape of immersed droplets of liquid crystals.<br /><br />BROADER IMPACT:<br /><br />Better numerical algorithms allow for more complicated problems to be tackled by simulation, thus enabling the modeling and development of new materials.&nbsp; The work in modeling liquid crystals could eventually open up new methods for simulating and controlling liquid crystal systems to create novel, unimagined, liquid crystal devices and materials.&nbsp; In particular, the simulation tools for liquid crystals interacting with colloids (and electric fields) should prove useful for technological innovation in the liquid crystal community.&nbsp; The work on controlling droplet shape can (potentially) enable new ways of micro-fluid processing.<br /><br />The PI continues to develop a sophisticated finite element (simulation) toolbox that is available to anyone through online resources.&nbsp; Furthermore, undergraduate and graduate students benefited from a special course developed by the PI on computational free boundary problems.&nbsp; Moreover, the PI has contributed to the local Baton Rouge community by being a judge in local science fair competitions, and also on guiding middle-school students in their science fair projects at minority serving schools.</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 08/06/2018<br>      Modified by: Shawn&nbsp;Walker</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"> <div class="each-gallery"> <div class="galContent" id="gallery0"> <div class="photoCount" id="photoCount0">          Images (<span id="selectedPhoto0">1</span> of <span class="totalNumber"></span>)           </div> <div class="galControls" id="controls0"></div> <div class="galSlideshow" id="slideshow0"></div> <div class="galEmbox" id="embox"> <div class="image-title"></div> </div> </div> <div class="galNavigation" id="navigation0"> <ul class="thumbs" id="thumbs0"> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1418994/1418994_10326114_1533582413702_Stefan_Problem_Image_2015--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1418994/1418994_10326114_1533582413702_Stefan_Problem_Image_2015--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Image of Stefan simulation"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1418994/1418994_10326114_1533582413702_Stefan_Problem_Image_2015--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Image of Stefan simulation"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Simulation of a solid region freezing into a liquid phase.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Shawn W. Walker</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyright owner is an institution with an existing agreement allowing use by NSF</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Shawn&nbsp;Walker</div> <div class="imageTitle">Image of Stefan simulation</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1418994/1418994_10326114_1533582479999_Droplet_Footprint_Control_Image_2015--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1418994/1418994_10326114_1533582479999_Droplet_Footprint_Control_Image_2015--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Image of Droplet Footprint Control"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1418994/1418994_10326114_1533582479999_Droplet_Footprint_Control_Image_2015--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Image of Droplet Footprint Control"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Shape optimization of a droplet toward a 4-leaf clover footprint shape on flat substrate.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Shawn W. Walker</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyright owner is an institution with an existing agreement allowing use by NSF</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Shawn&nbsp;Walker</div> <div class="imageTitle">Image of Droplet Footprint Control</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1418994/1418994_10326114_1533582579991_Stefan_Remesh--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1418994/1418994_10326114_1533582579991_Stefan_Remesh--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Remeshing in the Stefan problem"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1418994/1418994_10326114_1533582579991_Stefan_Remesh--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Remeshing in the Stefan problem"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Snapshot of mesh (in the Stefan problem) immediately before and after a re-mesh happens.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Shawn W. Walker</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyright owner is an institution with an existing agreement allowing use by NSF</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Shawn&nbsp;Walker</div> <div class="imageTitle">Remeshing in the Stefan problem</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1418994/1418994_10326114_1533582654426_Tennis_Ball--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1418994/1418994_10326114_1533582654426_Tennis_Ball--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Image of self-avoiding curves"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1418994/1418994_10326114_1533582654426_Tennis_Ball--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Image of self-avoiding curves"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Optimal shape of a self-avoiding elastic curve that is bound to a sphere.Final shape for a closed curve adsorbed onto a sphere. The surface is plotted in the lower right hand figure only. Note the symmetric "tennis-ball" pattern.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Shawn W. Walker</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyright owner is an institution with an existing agreement allowing use by NSF</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Shawn&nbsp;Walker</div> <div class="imageTitle">Image of self-avoiding curves</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1418994/1418994_10326114_1533582747086_Liquid_Crystal_Droplet_Normal_Anchoring--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1418994/1418994_10326114_1533582747086_Liquid_Crystal_Droplet_Normal_Anchoring--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Image of liquid crystal droplet with normal anchoring"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1418994/1418994_10326114_1533582747086_Liquid_Crystal_Droplet_Normal_Anchoring--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Image of liquid crystal droplet with normal anchoring"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Optimal shape exhibits corners because of anchoring conditions.  Droplet interface and liquid crystal director field are shown.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Shawn W. Walker</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyright owner is an institution with an existing agreement allowing use by NSF</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Shawn&nbsp;Walker</div> <div class="imageTitle">Image of liquid crystal droplet with normal anchoring</div> </div> </li> <li> <a href="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1418994/1418994_10326114_1533582835496_Liquid_Crystal_Droplet_Planar_Anchoring--rgov-214x142.jpg" original="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1418994/1418994_10326114_1533582835496_Liquid_Crystal_Droplet_Planar_Anchoring--rgov-800width.jpg" title="Image of liquid crystal droplet with planar anchoring"><img src="/por/images/Reports/POR/2018/1418994/1418994_10326114_1533582835496_Liquid_Crystal_Droplet_Planar_Anchoring--rgov-66x44.jpg" alt="Image of liquid crystal droplet with planar anchoring"></a> <div class="imageCaptionContainer"> <div class="imageCaption">Optimal shape exhibits corners because of anchoring conditions.  Droplet interface and liquid crystal director field are shown.</div> <div class="imageCredit">Shawn W. Walker</div> <div class="imagePermisssions">Copyright owner is an institution with an existing agreement allowing use by NSF</div> <div class="imageSubmitted">Shawn&nbsp;Walker</div> <div class="imageTitle">Image of liquid crystal droplet with planar anchoring</div> </div> </li> </ul> </div> </div> </div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Understanding physical laws and developing mathematical models to make predictions enables advancement of modern technology and industrial processes.  Moreover, optimization of these processes allows for better and more efficient designs.  The direct impacts to society are in general cost savings, more robust infrastructure, and better quality of life. The goal of this research project is to target a specific set of physical/industrial processes that involve moving boundaries or interfaces (e.g. the surface of a melting ice-cube in water is an interface between the solid "ice" phase and the liquid "water" phase). Examples include growing solid phases in a desired shape from a liquid melt (controlled crystal growth), modeling liquid crystals for material design, micro-fluidics that control small droplets of liquid by electric fields (useful in the bio-medical field), and self-assembly of particles and polymer chains on deformable membrane surfaces (design of materials).  The research will enable better design, optimization, and control of these systems.  INTELLECTUAL MERIT:  In particular, the research developed tools to (1) model/simulate melting and solidification; (2) model/simulate the adsorption of polymers onto surfaces using tools of shape optimization; (3) control the shape of liquid droplets on substrates by affecting surface tension; (4) simulate liquid crystals interacting with colloidal particles and electric effects; (5) model/simulate the shape of immersed droplets of liquid crystals.  BROADER IMPACT:  Better numerical algorithms allow for more complicated problems to be tackled by simulation, thus enabling the modeling and development of new materials.  The work in modeling liquid crystals could eventually open up new methods for simulating and controlling liquid crystal systems to create novel, unimagined, liquid crystal devices and materials.  In particular, the simulation tools for liquid crystals interacting with colloids (and electric fields) should prove useful for technological innovation in the liquid crystal community.  The work on controlling droplet shape can (potentially) enable new ways of micro-fluid processing.  The PI continues to develop a sophisticated finite element (simulation) toolbox that is available to anyone through online resources.  Furthermore, undergraduate and graduate students benefited from a special course developed by the PI on computational free boundary problems.  Moreover, the PI has contributed to the local Baton Rouge community by being a judge in local science fair competitions, and also on guiding middle-school students in their science fair projects at minority serving schools.       Last Modified: 08/06/2018       Submitted by: Shawn Walker]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
