<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Novel Paradigms in Geometric Modeling of Large and High-Dimensional Data Sets</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/15/2014</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>250000.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>250000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DMS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Christopher Stark</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>cstark@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924869</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The principal investigator and his collaborators aim to develop effective data modeling paradigms that are sufficiently simple for statistical inference. Current scientific investigations, as well as industrial applications, produce and rely on massive, high-dimensional and possibly corrupted data sets. A major focus of applied mathematicians and statisticians in this area has been on quantitative geometric data modeling. In order to effectively analyze large data and obtain meaningful statistical inference, the underlying geometric models need to be sufficiently simple. The proposal suggests mathematical paradigms for such effective geometric models. It plans to develop rigorous mathematical theory for these paradigms combined with carefully designed numerical strategies addressing specific and important applications. Despite the recent progress in this area, there are many open directions, several of which this research project addresses.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;More specifically, the proposal focuses on several important directions of geometric data modeling. One direction aims to address modern issues in single robust subspace modeling with respect to new paradigms of learning and computation that have hardly been addressed so far in this setting. Another direction will explore important issues in modeling data by multiple subspaces or manifolds with new paradigms and perspectives. The proposal will also emphasize specific paradigms of low-rank and sparse modeling, which are induced by important applications, such as approximate nearest subspace for object recognition, improved feature tracking, structure from motion in computer vision, and sparse modeling in the atmospheric sciences.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/11/2014</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/11/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1418386</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Gilad</FirstName>
<LastName>Lerman</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Gilad Lerman</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>lerman@umn.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>6122054207</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000227711</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/11/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Minnesota-Twin Cities</Name>
<CityName>Minneapolis</CityName>
<ZipCode>554552070</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6126245599</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>200 OAK ST SE</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Minnesota</StateName>
<StateCode>MN</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MN05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>555917996</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>REGENTS OF THE UNIVERSITY OF MINNESOTA</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>117178941</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Minnesota-School of Mathematics]]></Name>
<CityName>Minneapolis</CityName>
<StateCode>MN</StateCode>
<ZipCode>554552070</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[206 Church St.  SE 127 Vincent]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Minnesota</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>05</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MN05</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1271</Code>
<Text>COMPUTATIONAL MATHEMATICS</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>8069</Code>
<Text>CDS&amp;E-MSS</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7433</Code>
<Text>CyberInfra Frmwrk 21st (CIF21)</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8084</Code>
<Text>CDS&amp;E</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8396</Code>
<Text>Clean Energy Technology</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8609</Code>
<Text>Other Energy Research</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9263</Code>
<Text>COMPUTATIONAL SCIENCE &amp; ENGING</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0114</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~250000</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>The project aimed at developing methods with guarantees for effective data modeling. &nbsp;The primary focus revolved around the simple and common model of a low-dimensional subspace. The main challenge, though, is that it is hard to fit such a subspace to corrupted datasets. A classical statistical method for fitting a subspace is principal component analysis. However, principal component analysis is notoriously sensitive to corrupted data. Methods of fitting a subspace to corrupted data are generally referred to as robust, in the sense that they do not subscribe to the clean assumptions required by many classical statistical procedures. While the problem of robustly fitting a subspace to data has a long history and some classical solutions, modern problems, such as the development of computationally efficient and highly accurate robust subspace fitting procedures for large and possibly high-dimensional datasets, did not have satisfying solutions when the project began.</p> <p>The project provided careful mathematical foundations for the problem of fitting a subspace to corrupted data. It also produced a survey paper on the topic, which included relationships to other interesting and important problems and discussion of future directions. The main focus of the project was the development of non-convex methods for robust subspace fitting. Such methods seem to yield computationally efficient and highly accurate algorithms. This claim was established in theory and practice under some conditions on the data. More specifically, the landscape of a robust non-convex energy has been characterized, at least around its global minimum, and properties of two non-convex algorithms for finding the minimum were established. Such properties include rate of convergence, accuracy and robustness to corruption.</p> <p>To deal with truly large sample sizes, the project explored subspace modeling on distributed networks, where the data is distributed across nodes and the communication is limited by the network structure. Strategies were developed and adapted to this setting.</p> <p>Another effective data model is the so-called union of manifolds. A strategy for recovering such a model was developed by fitting subspaces at different neighborhoods of the dataset. Theoretical guarantees for this strategy were established. They showed, in particular, that the proposed method can recover the different manifolds given special datasets sampled from a union of manifolds model even if the manifolds intersect each other.</p> <p>Non-convex landscapes were also studied in different discrete scenarios. Robustness was further studied in the related problem of recovering camera locations from corrupted pairwise directions. This problem is part of the well-known pipeline of structure-from-motion in computer vision. Subspaces and other models were also applied to feature tracking in computer vision, especially when utilizing information from gyroscopes.</p> <p>The project has also involved educational activities. In addition to mentoring undergraduate and graduate students and initiating university-wide activities in data science, such as a multidisciplinary seminar, the PI has been serving as the director of the Minnesota Center for Industrial Mathematics (MCIM). In this capacity, the PI has helped to prepare students for leadership positions in industry. In particular, he organized an industrial problems seminar, where he invited speakers from industry to discuss their research problems and perspectives.&nbsp; These speakers have shared their experience of transition from an academic environment to leadership in industry with students and faculty and have often kept long-term relationships with the students and the department. He has also organized industrial internships for undergraduate and graduate students. Resources on internships and permanent positions for students have been maintained and are publicly available.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 10/04/2018<br>      Modified by: Gilad&nbsp;Lerman</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ The project aimed at developing methods with guarantees for effective data modeling.  The primary focus revolved around the simple and common model of a low-dimensional subspace. The main challenge, though, is that it is hard to fit such a subspace to corrupted datasets. A classical statistical method for fitting a subspace is principal component analysis. However, principal component analysis is notoriously sensitive to corrupted data. Methods of fitting a subspace to corrupted data are generally referred to as robust, in the sense that they do not subscribe to the clean assumptions required by many classical statistical procedures. While the problem of robustly fitting a subspace to data has a long history and some classical solutions, modern problems, such as the development of computationally efficient and highly accurate robust subspace fitting procedures for large and possibly high-dimensional datasets, did not have satisfying solutions when the project began.  The project provided careful mathematical foundations for the problem of fitting a subspace to corrupted data. It also produced a survey paper on the topic, which included relationships to other interesting and important problems and discussion of future directions. The main focus of the project was the development of non-convex methods for robust subspace fitting. Such methods seem to yield computationally efficient and highly accurate algorithms. This claim was established in theory and practice under some conditions on the data. More specifically, the landscape of a robust non-convex energy has been characterized, at least around its global minimum, and properties of two non-convex algorithms for finding the minimum were established. Such properties include rate of convergence, accuracy and robustness to corruption.  To deal with truly large sample sizes, the project explored subspace modeling on distributed networks, where the data is distributed across nodes and the communication is limited by the network structure. Strategies were developed and adapted to this setting.  Another effective data model is the so-called union of manifolds. A strategy for recovering such a model was developed by fitting subspaces at different neighborhoods of the dataset. Theoretical guarantees for this strategy were established. They showed, in particular, that the proposed method can recover the different manifolds given special datasets sampled from a union of manifolds model even if the manifolds intersect each other.  Non-convex landscapes were also studied in different discrete scenarios. Robustness was further studied in the related problem of recovering camera locations from corrupted pairwise directions. This problem is part of the well-known pipeline of structure-from-motion in computer vision. Subspaces and other models were also applied to feature tracking in computer vision, especially when utilizing information from gyroscopes.  The project has also involved educational activities. In addition to mentoring undergraduate and graduate students and initiating university-wide activities in data science, such as a multidisciplinary seminar, the PI has been serving as the director of the Minnesota Center for Industrial Mathematics (MCIM). In this capacity, the PI has helped to prepare students for leadership positions in industry. In particular, he organized an industrial problems seminar, where he invited speakers from industry to discuss their research problems and perspectives.  These speakers have shared their experience of transition from an academic environment to leadership in industry with students and faculty and have often kept long-term relationships with the students and the department. He has also organized industrial internships for undergraduate and graduate students. Resources on internships and permanent positions for students have been maintained and are publicly available.          Last Modified: 10/04/2018       Submitted by: Gilad Lerman]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
