<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Fast high-order methods for electrohydrodynamics of vesicle suspensions</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/15/2014</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>216637.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>216637</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DMS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Leland Jameson</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>ljameson@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924883</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The objective of this project is to develop novel computational tools for simulating the electrohydrodynamics (EHD) of vesicle suspensions.  Vesicles enclose a viscous fluid and they share the same structural component of a biological cell, the bilipid membrane.  Hence, their EHD has been a paradigm for understanding how general biological cells behave under an electric field. The dynamics of this system is characterized by a competition between viscous, elastic, and electric stresses on the individual membranes and the nonlocal hydrodynamic interactions. A number of technological applications call for better understanding of EHD including targeted drug delivery, gene transfection and lab-on-a-chip design. The proposed work will enable researchers to learn how the physics at micro-scale (e.g., single particle deformation) alters the macro-scale behavior of dense suspensions (e.g., electrorheology). In addition, this project will undertake educational, mentoring, and outreach activities that are expected to have a broad impact.   &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The mathematical model for multiple-vesicle EHD consists of the incompressible Stokes equation for the fluid surrounding the membranes combined with a far-field boundary condition and a kinematic condition at the fluid-vesicle interfaces. The classical Taylor- Melcher leaky-dielectric framework models the electric response of individual vesicles and the Helfrich energy combined with local inextensibility models their elastic response.  The proposed numerical methods will be based on boundary integral equation formulations, which avoid volume discretizations. Fast, high-order methods will be developed for solving the coupled boundary integral equations for the vesicle positions and their trans-membrane electric potentials. Computational challenges faced by the vesicle EHD are shared by other particulate flows such as drop, bubble and capsule flows. Therefore, the methods proposed here could more generally be applied to several other problems of practical importance. This award by the Computational Mathematics Program of the Division of Mathematical Sciences is co-funded by the Particulate and Multiphase Processes program in the CBET Division of the ENG Directorate.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/03/2014</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/03/2014</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1418964</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Shravan</FirstName>
<LastName>Veerapaneni</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Shravan Veerapaneni</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>shravan@umich.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>7349369963</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000585612</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>07/03/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Regents of the University of Michigan - Ann Arbor</Name>
<CityName>Ann Arbor</CityName>
<ZipCode>481091274</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>7347636438</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>3003 South State St. Room 1062</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Michigan</StateName>
<StateCode>MI</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>12</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MI12</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>073133571</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>REGENTS OF THE UNIVERSITY OF MICHIGAN</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>073133571</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[University of Michigan Ann Arbor]]></Name>
<CityName>Ann Arbor</CityName>
<StateCode>MI</StateCode>
<ZipCode>481091271</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Michigan</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>12</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MI12</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1271</Code>
<Text>COMPUTATIONAL MATHEMATICS</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1415</Code>
<Text>PMP-Particul&amp;MultiphaseProcess</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7454</Code>
<Text>MSPA-INTERDISCIPLINARY</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>055E</Code>
<Text>Particle science and technology</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8007</Code>
<Text>BioMaPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9263</Code>
<Text>COMPUTATIONAL SCIENCE &amp; ENGING</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0114</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~216637</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>This project advanced the state-of-the-art algorithms for simulating the electrohydrodynamics (EHD) of vesicle suspensions. A new boundary integral equation formulation was derived that describes the coupled electro- and hydro-dynamics of a vesicle suspended in a viscous fluid and subjected to external flow and electric fields in three dimensions. A numerical method was developed to solve the coupled governing equations for the vesicle position and its transmembrane electric potential; it is spectrally accurate in space and first-order in time. The method uses a semi-implicit time-stepping scheme to overcome the numerical stiffness associated with the governing equations.</p> <p>Using the algorithms developed in this project, several new results in biophysics were established. The EHD of vesicle suspensions is characterized by studying their pairwise interactions in applied DC electric fields in two dimensions. In the dilute limit, the rheology of the suspension is shown to vary nonlinearly with the electric conductivity ratio of the interior and exterior fluids. The prolate-oblate-prolate transition and other transitionary dynamics observed in experiments and previously confirmed via numerical simulations is further investigated here for smaller reduced areas. When two vesicles are initially un-aligned with the external electric field, three different responses are reported when the key parameters are varied:&nbsp; <em>Chain formation</em>, wherein, they self-assemble to form a chain that is aligned along the field direction; <em>Circulatory motion</em>, wherein, they rotate about each other; <em>Oscillatory motion</em>, wherein, they form a chain but oscillate about each other.</p> <p>&nbsp;</p> <p>&nbsp;</p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 09/01/2017<br>      Modified by: Shravan&nbsp;Veerapaneni</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ This project advanced the state-of-the-art algorithms for simulating the electrohydrodynamics (EHD) of vesicle suspensions. A new boundary integral equation formulation was derived that describes the coupled electro- and hydro-dynamics of a vesicle suspended in a viscous fluid and subjected to external flow and electric fields in three dimensions. A numerical method was developed to solve the coupled governing equations for the vesicle position and its transmembrane electric potential; it is spectrally accurate in space and first-order in time. The method uses a semi-implicit time-stepping scheme to overcome the numerical stiffness associated with the governing equations.  Using the algorithms developed in this project, several new results in biophysics were established. The EHD of vesicle suspensions is characterized by studying their pairwise interactions in applied DC electric fields in two dimensions. In the dilute limit, the rheology of the suspension is shown to vary nonlinearly with the electric conductivity ratio of the interior and exterior fluids. The prolate-oblate-prolate transition and other transitionary dynamics observed in experiments and previously confirmed via numerical simulations is further investigated here for smaller reduced areas. When two vesicles are initially un-aligned with the external electric field, three different responses are reported when the key parameters are varied:  Chain formation, wherein, they self-assemble to form a chain that is aligned along the field direction; Circulatory motion, wherein, they rotate about each other; Oscillatory motion, wherein, they form a chain but oscillate about each other.             Last Modified: 09/01/2017       Submitted by: Shravan Veerapaneni]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
