<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Weak Galerkin Modeling of Wave Scattering and Propagation in Dispersive Media</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2014</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2015</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>79743.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>26049</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DMS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Leland Jameson</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>ljameson@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924883</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The propagation and scattering of electromagnetic waves in dispersive and inhomogeneous media are of essential importance in microwave, THz (tera-hertz) and light-wave technologies. The effects of dispersive dielectrics, such as biological tissues, rocks, soil, snow, ice, plasma, optical fibers, and radar-absorbing materials, must be taken into account in the design of electromagnetic devices. The understanding of these effects leads to new devices with unique characteristics.  Due to geometric complexity, interface discontinuities, solution singularity and time-varying nature of the solution, the development of efficient and accurate numerical methods for solving dispersive media problems remains a challenging issue in computational mathematics. &lt;br/&gt;   &lt;br/&gt;The goal of this proposal is to develop a new efficient and accurate numerical method for modeling, analysis, and simulation of electromagnetic wave problems in dispersive and inhomogeneous media.  In this project, the investigator will construct stable and reliable formulations based on the weak-Galerkin finite element method for handling the complex geometry, interface discontinuity and low regularity solution, and then extend the analysis to time dependent problems.  New mathematical schemes will be developed based on dispersive media models and complicated coupling of field components at the dielectric interface. The proposed approaches will be applied to a number of realistic problems, including microwave breast imaging, ground penetrating radar and double negative metamaterial.  Advanced computational tools developed in this project, including those for constructing efficient numerical formulation, handling complex geometries and interface discontinuities will lead to a major advance in mathematical modeling and computation of wave scattering and propagation in dispersive media.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>09/04/2014</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>12/04/2015</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1418973</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Lin</FirstName>
<LastName>Mu</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Lin Mu</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>linmu@uga.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>5174888175</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000636238</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>09/04/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Michigan State University</Name>
<CityName>East Lansing</CityName>
<ZipCode>488242600</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5173555040</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>Office of Sponsored Programs</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2><![CDATA[426 Administration Bldg, Rm2]]></StreetAddress2>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Michigan</StateName>
<StateCode>MI</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>08</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>MI08</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>193247145</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>MICHIGAN STATE UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>053343976</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Michigan State University]]></Name>
<CityName>East Lansing</CityName>
<StateCode>MI</StateCode>
<ZipCode>494541000</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Michigan</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>MI02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1271</Code>
<Text>COMPUTATIONAL MATHEMATICS</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9263</Code>
<Text>COMPUTATIONAL SCIENCE &amp; ENGING</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0114</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~26049</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p>A new weak Galerkin finite element methods have been developed for analyzing the interface problems in the dispersive media and other related partial differential equations. These interface problems have a wide range of applications in engineering and biology.</p> <p>Weak Galerkin finite element method was first introduced by Wang and Ye. The advantage of weak Galerkin algorithm includes handling geometric complexities, boundary conditions, conservation laws, and flexibility in constructing higher order accuracy schemes.&nbsp;</p> <p>In this project, the new weak Galerkin method has been used to solve elliptic interface problems, Stokes equations, Brinkman problems, and multiscale problems.&nbsp;</p> <div class="page" title="Page 3"> <div class="layoutArea"> <div class="column"> <p>Six manuscripts have been submitted to journal for publication. Lin focus on the simulation, modeling, development of high-order numerical schemes, and also numerical analysis for the developed algorithms. &nbsp;The algorithm was developed into a software package and made availabe online for academic and research purposes. Lin has seven invited presentations during the grant period. The work in the project was present in conferences and workshops. The shared work improved more collaboration during the grant.&nbsp;</p> <p>The developed numerical schemes can be applied for engineering community due to their simplicity and to the local conservation properties. The work in this project is an important contribution to scientists and engineers in the related fields.</p> </div> </div> </div><br> <p>            Last Modified: 12/10/2015<br>      Modified by: Lin&nbsp;Mu</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ A new weak Galerkin finite element methods have been developed for analyzing the interface problems in the dispersive media and other related partial differential equations. These interface problems have a wide range of applications in engineering and biology.  Weak Galerkin finite element method was first introduced by Wang and Ye. The advantage of weak Galerkin algorithm includes handling geometric complexities, boundary conditions, conservation laws, and flexibility in constructing higher order accuracy schemes.   In this project, the new weak Galerkin method has been used to solve elliptic interface problems, Stokes equations, Brinkman problems, and multiscale problems.      Six manuscripts have been submitted to journal for publication. Lin focus on the simulation, modeling, development of high-order numerical schemes, and also numerical analysis for the developed algorithms.  The algorithm was developed into a software package and made availabe online for academic and research purposes. Lin has seven invited presentations during the grant period. The work in the project was present in conferences and workshops. The shared work improved more collaboration during the grant.   The developed numerical schemes can be applied for engineering community due to their simplicity and to the local conservation properties. The work in this project is an important contribution to scientists and engineers in the related fields.          Last Modified: 12/10/2015       Submitted by: Lin Mu]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
