<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Collaborative Research: Topological Methods for Parsing Shapes and Networks and Modeling Variation in Structure and Function</AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2014</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>312886.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>312886</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>DMS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Christopher Stark</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>cstark@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032924869</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Critical to advancing data-enabled science is our ability to probe, conceptualize, interpret, and visualize information residing in complex datasets in order to transform data into knowledge.  This project develops computational methods and tools for investigation and visualization of structural variation in networks and 3D shapes, as well as inference of functional outcomes of such variation. These problems arise in areas of strategic interest such as health and medicine, where it is important to understand patterns of morphological variation in biological shapes and structural changes in biological networks, and their roles in behavior, health and disease. To emphasize this important interdisciplinary facet, the project is supported by several case studies that investigate: (i) mechanisms underlying the development of facial shape; (ii) interactions between brain shape, skull morphology, and behavior; (iii) organization of microbial communities in the digestive tract; and (iv) connections between social networks and microbiome networks.  We envision many long-term ramifications of the project. Potential applications include analyses of dynamical social networks, exploratory discovery of associations between biological networks and phenotypic traits or diseases, quantitative studies of evolution, development, and inheritance of morphological traits, and challenges such as indexing and organizing databases of networks or 3D shapes for efficient data management, search, and retrieval. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The project integrates techniques from topological data analysis, integral geometry, spectral geometry, and statistics to develop computational methods and tools for modeling and visualizing structural variation in diverse collections of shapes and networks, and exploring associations between variation in structure and function. The project addresses theoretical foundations, computational methods, implementation of tools for statistical analysis and visualization, and validation of methodology. A shape or network is represented by a Borel probability measure on a Hilbert space whose elements represent Euler characteristic curves that encode rich geometric and topological properties. Dimension reduction and discretization of the probability measure lead to representations that allow organization of complex datasets into compact dictionaries that facilitate data analytics, processing, visualization, and search. This enables integration of the new methods with an array of existing techniques of multivariate statistical analysis to address such problems as development of regression-based models over networks.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/29/2014</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/10/2016</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>0</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>1418007</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Washington</FirstName>
<LastName>Mio</LastName>
<PI_MID_INIT/>
<PI_SUFX_NAME/>
<PI_FULL_NAME>Washington Mio</PI_FULL_NAME>
<EmailAddress>mio@math.fsu.edu</EmailAddress>
<PI_PHON>9046445596</PI_PHON>
<NSF_ID>000160391</NSF_ID>
<StartDate>06/29/2014</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Florida State University</Name>
<CityName>TALLAHASSEE</CityName>
<ZipCode>323064166</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>8506445260</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>874 Traditions Way, 3rd Floor</StreetAddress>
<StreetAddress2/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Florida</StateName>
<StateCode>FL</StateCode>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>FL02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_ORG>
<ORG_DUNS_NUM>790877419</ORG_DUNS_NUM>
<ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>FLORIDA STATE UNIVERSITY</ORG_LGL_BUS_NAME>
<ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>159621697</ORG_PRNT_DUNS_NUM>
</Institution>
<Performance_Institution>
<Name><![CDATA[Florida State University]]></Name>
<CityName>Tallahassee</CityName>
<StateCode>FL</StateCode>
<ZipCode>323064510</ZipCode>
<StreetAddress><![CDATA[1017 Academic Way]]></StreetAddress>
<CountryCode>US</CountryCode>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Florida</StateName>
<CountryFlag>1</CountryFlag>
<CONGRESSDISTRICT>02</CONGRESSDISTRICT>
<CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>FL02</CONGRESS_DISTRICT_PERF>
</Performance_Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>8069</Code>
<Text>CDS&amp;E-MSS</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7433</Code>
<Text>CyberInfra Frmwrk 21st (CIF21)</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8084</Code>
<Text>CDS&amp;E</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9263</Code>
<Text>COMPUTATIONAL SCIENCE &amp; ENGING</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0114</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0115</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<Appropriation>
<Code>0116</Code>
<Name>NSF RESEARCH &amp; RELATED ACTIVIT</Name>
<APP_SYMB_ID>040100</APP_SYMB_ID>
</Appropriation>
<FUND_OBLG>2014~97468</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2015~96622</FUND_OBLG>
<FUND_OBLG>2016~118796</FUND_OBLG>
<POR>
<DRECONTENT><![CDATA[<div class="porColContainerWBG"> <div class="porContentCol"><p><span>Big data can be big in size, but also in complexity. Of great interest to multiple domains of science and application are datasets comprising objects such as shapes, images, and networks. However, quantifying, interpreting and visualizing information residing in such datasets to transform data into actionable knowledge present many challenges. Putting numbers to data that capture their richness to enable effective analysis and inference was a key objective of this project. How can we map associations and causal relations between genetic variation and phenotypic outcomes? How do changes in the human microbiome relate to health and disease? What can phenotypic plasticity tell us about living organisms? These are some examples of questions of fundamental interest that motivated the research carried out in this project.</span></p> <p><span>The project developed methods of data analysis grounded on geometry and topology that advance our ability to analyze functional, structural and network data, addressing both theory and computation. The methods were used to: (i) study associations between variation in the genetic makeup and the morphology of leaves and roots of tomato plants; (ii) investigate phenotypic plasticity in Gingko biloba leaves; (iii) analyze changes in the gut microbiome due to Clostridium difficile infection and treatment with fecal microbiota transplantation.</span></p> <p><span>Other project activities included: (i) dissemination of research findings through publications and presentations at conferences and workshops; (ii) education and training of graduate and undergraduate students, including those from underrepresented groups in mathematics; (iii) participation in outreach activities for K-12 students.</span></p><br> <p>            Last Modified: 12/11/2018<br>      Modified by: Washington&nbsp;Mio</p> </div> <div class="porSideCol"></div> </div>]]></DRECONTENT>
<POR_COPY_TXT><![CDATA[ Big data can be big in size, but also in complexity. Of great interest to multiple domains of science and application are datasets comprising objects such as shapes, images, and networks. However, quantifying, interpreting and visualizing information residing in such datasets to transform data into actionable knowledge present many challenges. Putting numbers to data that capture their richness to enable effective analysis and inference was a key objective of this project. How can we map associations and causal relations between genetic variation and phenotypic outcomes? How do changes in the human microbiome relate to health and disease? What can phenotypic plasticity tell us about living organisms? These are some examples of questions of fundamental interest that motivated the research carried out in this project.  The project developed methods of data analysis grounded on geometry and topology that advance our ability to analyze functional, structural and network data, addressing both theory and computation. The methods were used to: (i) study associations between variation in the genetic makeup and the morphology of leaves and roots of tomato plants; (ii) investigate phenotypic plasticity in Gingko biloba leaves; (iii) analyze changes in the gut microbiome due to Clostridium difficile infection and treatment with fecal microbiota transplantation.  Other project activities included: (i) dissemination of research findings through publications and presentations at conferences and workshops; (ii) education and training of graduate and undergraduate students, including those from underrepresented groups in mathematics; (iii) participation in outreach activities for K-12 students.       Last Modified: 12/11/2018       Submitted by: Washington Mio]]></POR_COPY_TXT>
</POR>
</Award>
</rootTag>
